<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Road to Joy Is Long but Cheap</title>
    <meta content="04FRUG$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D61431F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="2785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Road to Joy Is Long but Cheap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SPANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spano, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frugal Traveler column by Susan Spano on inexpensive monthlong trip to India; map; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A BREATH from the snows blows away 20 years from the life of a man.'' This is how the old Buddhist lama in Rudyard Kipling's novel ''Kim'' describes his yearning for the mountains of northern India -- a sentiment shared by the English who summered in the Himalayan foothills, and by me.</p>
        <p>So when I started planning a monthlong trip to India in October, it seemed inconceivable that I shouldn't go to the mountains. After all, these are the Himalayas -- the highest and one of the the most sacred chains of peaks on earth. Home to Tibetan Buddhism, the gods of the ancient Hindu Vedas and the holy River Ganges, the Himalayas stretch 1,400 miles across the northern border of India, from Jammu and Kashmir in the west to Arunchal Pradesh in the east.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A BREATH from the snows blows away 20 years from the life of a man.'' This is how the old Buddhist lama in Rudyard Kipling's novel ''Kim'' describes his yearning for the mountains of northern India -- a sentiment shared by the English who summered in the Himalayan foothills, and by me.</p>
        <p>So when I started planning a monthlong trip to India in October, it seemed inconceivable that I shouldn't go to the mountains. After all, these are the Himalayas -- the highest and one of the the most sacred chains of peaks on earth. Home to Tibetan Buddhism, the gods of the ancient Hindu Vedas and the holy River Ganges, the Himalayas stretch 1,400 miles across the northern border of India, from Jammu and Kashmir in the west to Arunchal Pradesh in the east.</p>
        <p>Soon my living room in New York was scattered with lushly illustrated catalogues from American and English trekking companies offering once-in-a-lifetime trips. Among them was Wilderness Travel's rigorous 27-day Beyond Dhaulagiri trek to the seventh-highest peak in the world (for $3,045 to $3,245, including gear, food, guides, domestic air fare and a single supplement).</p>
        <p>But even if I could have come up with the money, there were other problems. India is a big country and I didn't want to devote all my time there to a trek. Then, too, I suspected that I could get a short walking trip in the mountain regions of Himachal Pradesh or Uttar Pradesh for a lot less by working directly with an Indian trekking company.  Faxes to firms in New Delhi brought interesting options, like a 13-day group trip in the lower Himalayas of Himachal Pradesh for $2,331 (including a single supplement) organized by Shikhar Travels. Later, I visited with Shikhar's managing director, Capt.  Swadesh Kumar, in New Delhi. He told me that people who book tours there receive 25 percent discounts.</p>
        <p>High Points of India worked up a special eight-day itinerary that would have taken me by train from Delhi to Pathankot, in the northern Punjab; by car to McLeod Ganj, above the Kangra Valley of Himachal Pradesh, and then on an overnight trek to an alpine meadow called Triund at the threshold of the lower Himalayas, for $858 (including hotels, equipment, porterage and a guide).</p>
        <p>But in ''Trekking in the Indian Himalaya,'' a Lonely Planet guide, I read that there are agents in McLeod Ganj who will arrange walking trips for as little as $4.30 a day (at 35 rupees to $1), and that the scenic little town is a good place for day hikes into the foothills. So I decided to go to McLeod Ganj on my own and see what developed.</p>
        <p>McLeod Ganj, which sits on a ridge in the Shivalik Hills, between the resplendent Kangra Valley and the high peaks of the Dhauladhar Range, was named for Sir Donald Friell McLeod, a British lieutenant governor of the Punjab. It is also known as Upper Dharmsala. There, the British established a cantonment for a battalion of Gurkha mercenaries from Nepal around 1850 and a hill station for summering colonials.</p>
        <p>But while more-popular retreats like Shimla and Darjeeling thrived, McLeod Ganj slumbered. When a devastating earthquake struck in 1905, many residents moved down the ridge to Lower Dharmsala.</p>
        <p>Today this unlikely village, reached by a winding six-mile road from Lower Dharmsala, has become one of the spiritual hot spots of the world. It is the home of the 14th Dalai Lama, who settled there in 1960 after escaping from Chinese-occupied Tibet in 1959. With him came 52 monks from Namgyal Monastery in Lhasa, and some 5,000 industrious refugees who strung prayer flags between the branches of deodar cedars, built a new Namgyal Monastery and administrative center for the Tibetan government-in-exile and gradually prospered with the support of sympathetic Westerners.</p>
        <p>For a while Dharmsala chiefly attracted backpacking hippies from Europe and the Americas, drawn by the beliefs of the Tibetan Buddhists, bhang peddlars who haunt the back lanes of McLeod Ganj and incredibly low prices for meals and hotel rooms. A few of the young travelers never returned home (their lives perhaps claimed by illness, drugs or accident) -- as attested to by posters placed on walls around the village by distraught parents.</p>
        <p>But since the Dalai Lama received the Nobel Peace Prize in 1989 and Hollywood started making films like ''Little Buddha'' (1994) and ''Kundun'' and ''Seven Years in Tibet'' (1997), even more eyes have turned toward Dharmsala -- resulting in an influx of tourists carrying prayer beads and plastic bottles of mineral water. Now, if you take  the train to the closest railhead at Pathankot, many of your fellow travelers are bound to be young Westerners hoping to study meditation, yoga or Tibetan medicine while taking a break from the intense exoticism of India in mellow McLeod Ganj.</p>
        <p>I took the Jammu Mail, from cavernous Old Delhi Station ($20 for the best berth on the train, in a second-class air-conditioned sleeper), scheduled to reach Pathankot early the next morning. When the porter deposited me in my compartment, a young German smiled and said, ''You must be Susan.''</p>
        <p>Briefly I wondered if he was psychic, but then he introduced me to one of the surprises of Indian rail travel: computerized lists of the occupants of each car posted by the entrance.</p>
        <p>The doorless compartment had four well-worn bunks with individual lights, a window and fixtures to secure luggage with padlocks. The friendly young man was named Andreas, and the two other occupants, Marta and Mathias, were also German. They spoke English, so we had a nice time discussing cures for the sore throats we'd all contracted in New Delhi, and how we'd get from Pathankot to McLeod Ganj -- a 50-mile trip along a road renowned for precipitous drops and frightful switchbacks that takes four hours by bus for $1.40 or two and a half hours by cab for about $23.</p>
        <p>An attendant passed out sheets, blankets and small, hard pillows, but I didn't sleep much. The bathrooms at the rear grew filthier by the hour -- and there were many because a derailment delayed the Jammu Mail by about eight hours. My stash of cookies and bottled water was running out.</p>
        <p>ACCORDING to ''The Way to Freedom'' by the Dalai Lama, the first Noble Truth of Buddhism is ''the truth of suffering, that our happiness is constantly passing away.'' By the time we finally reached Pathankot, I was willing to accept this wholeheartedly.  But then we had tea and thalis (samplers with small dishes of rice, curry and vegetables) at the station restaurant for 60 cents a person, and hired a van to take us to McLeod Ganj. Marta, whose tough bargaining skills filled me with awe, got the price down from $23 to $17, and a talkative young Australian named Tamara joined us, bringing the cost of the ride to $3.40 each. (On my return trip, I took the bus -- a long, bumpy and crowded ride.)</p>
        <p>Dark was falling as we set out, following the gorge of the Chakki River, and the sky was overcast. But when we rounded a bend and the Dhauladhars reared up in a massive wall, marbled with snow, I said, ''Holy cow!'' and everybody laughed.  One of the ranges that roll away from the Great Himalayas, the Dhauladhars crest at 18,000-foot Mount Kailash and include many high peaks that have never been conquered by climbers.</p>
        <p>When we finally reached the muddy main square in McLeod Ganj, which is as raw as any Western  mining camp, my companions trudged off to find budget rooms (for $4.60 to $8.60) in one of the dozens of small hotels with names like Dreamland, Shangrila and Om, run by Tibetan refugees. But I was traveling first class and had a reservation for a $15.70 share-bath single at Chonor House, where Richard Gere stays when he comes to McLeod Ganj to study with the Dalai Lama. The 11-room inn sits in a nest of trees, on a hill at the east end of town. It is run by the Norbulingka Institute, a Japanese organization that has a temple and school in the valley near Lower Dharmsala devoted to preserving the art and culture of the displaced Tibetan Buddhists.</p>
        <p>Although Chonor House is hardly luxurious, it is pleasingly decorated with Tibetan accents, like the hand-embroidered spread on the single bed in my room (which also had carpeting, a desk, chair, cupboard,  space heater and a balcony overlooking Namgyal Temple). There are thangka scroll paintings in the lobby and folk murals on the walls of the basement restaurant, where the food is hearty and good. My favorite at dinner was chicken and mushroom stir-fry over rice ($1.60), and at breakfast oat porridge with orange juice ($1.30).</p>
        <p>Though the weather remained mostly chilly and gray during my four days in McLeod Ganj, my Delhi throat evaporated and my cheeks pinkened. On my first morning, I wandered along the rocky path that leads up a steep hill toward town, but stopped short when I heard a violent shaking in the treetops -- caused by branch-hopping langurs, a kind of shy, black-faced Asian monkey. Then it was on to the yellow Namgyal Monastery complex, where I joined worshippers in a circumambulation of the temple, spun prayer wheels and spotted a monk in sunglasses, sunning himself on a chaise longue.</p>
        <p>The Dalai Lama was away. But I saw his guarded residence near the temple and walked about a mile down a rutted lane to the concrete government complex, which includes the parliament-in-exile, secretariats and the Library of Tibetan Works and Archives, with 70,000 precious books and manuscripts. There I met up with Andreas and Tamara for a free class on Buddhism offered several times a week. It started with chanting in Tibetan, and ended with a lecture delivered by a lama who told us that we have the chance for lasting happiness in this life, and that it would be sad to let it slip away.</p>
        <p>We also toured the little museum there (15 cents) and lunched on benches beneath a tree at the nearby Nechung Cafe, where a big bowl of steaming tofu and vegetable noodles seemed a steal at 43 cents. Later meals around McLeod Ganj (like a plate of Tibetan dumplings called momos in the tiny Yak Restaurant and pancakes in the Cafe Shambala on Main Street) rarely cost more than 85 cents.</p>
        <p>That afternoon we climbed up to the Tushita Meditation Center, a rustic enclave with a temple, dormitories and a dining hall on the path to the village of Dharamkot. There we discovered that an 11-day Introduction to Meditation course was scheduled to begin in two days (for $83, including room and board). Despite the very basic, unheated accommodations and the fact that students must not speak or leave the grounds, Andreas signed up on the spot. When I last saw him, he was headed up the path to the center, wrapped in a woolen shawl.</p>
        <p>On other days I hiked about a mile to the village of Bhagsu, which has a Hindu temple and a waterfall, to the Victorian Church of St. John in the Wilderness, just below McLeod Ganj, and to Lower Dharmsala, a crowded, jangling town with a good museum that specializes in miniature paintings from the Kangra Valley.</p>
        <p>At nearby Yeti Trekking, the owner, A. J. Thapa, told me he could arrange high-mountain trips for $34 a day. But not this year -- with early snows and the 14,000-foot Indrahar Pass already closed.</p>
        <p>I did make it to Triund, though -- a 10-mile round trip beginning on a path near the town dump, where rhesus monkeys scramble in towering piles of spent water bottles. I'd been warned that single women shouldn't climb into the foothills alone and had noticed an article in a local newspaper about a recent crime wave in the Kangra district, with robberies, rapes and killings on the rise. So I went with Tam and an earnest young American college student named Lucy, who'd come to McLeod Ganj to research a paper on Tibetan Buddhism. Meanwhile, she complained, her roommates were spending their time drinking beer, finding Indian boyfriends and watching movies in video parlors.</p>
        <p>FOR once, the morning was clear and there was no one else around. The path wound up past Tushita, Dharamkot and a little stone Shiva temple on Galu Devi ridge. But on the way I grew tired and fell behind my companions. Pausing to rest, I heard people approaching on the path in front of me -- Lucy and Tam, I expected. But it was a gang of young Indian men, who stopped talking when they saw me. I knew I could be in trouble, but kept walking as if everything was fine. Quickly they surrounded me, at first just asking if I'd pose for a picture. When I declined, one touched my arm, followed by another. A third put his hand on my backside. I shook them off and ran. When I looked back they seemed to be debating whether to follow. Fortunately, they didn't.  Half an hour later, I reached Triund, breathless and tense.</p>
        <p>Lucy and Tam had been treated the same way. Still, we all relaxed gradually, and gazed up at the mountains where snow clouds were swirling and hundreds of miles to the north Tibet lay.</p>
        <p>I could not make sense of McLeod Ganj, with its soulfulness, dangers and cultural collisions. But for the moment I was content just to be looking at the Himalayas.</p>
        <p>The bottom line, high in the mountains</p>
        <p>In McLeod Ganj, I spent $18 a day on accommodations at Chonor House; my other daily expenses were about $8.</p>
        <p>Chonor House in McLeod Ganj, (91-1892) 21468, fax (91-1892) 21006, has a restaurant and 11 rooms with and without private baths for $14 to $36, at 35 rupees to $1.</p>
        <p>To reach New Delhi From New York in early October, I took Royal Jordanian Airlines, (212) 949-0050, which flies via Amsterdam and Amman. I bought the round-trip ticket for $1,000 from The Travel Center, 373 Fifth Avenue, Second Floor, New York, N.Y. 10016; (212) 545-7474, fax (212) 545-7698.</p>
        <p>Getting Around</p>
        <p>Overnight buses make the trip from New Delhi to Dharmsala for about $10. But most people find the train to Chandigarh or Pathankot more comfortable. Some have first-class, air-conditioned sleepers, with locks on compartment doors.</p>
        <p>The Jammu Mail costs $20 for a second-class air-conditioned sleeper from New Delhi to Pathankot. On the way back, I took the Jammu-Delhi Express from a station near Pathankot called Chakki Bank, for $35 in a first-class air-conditioned sleeper.</p>
        <p>Information</p>
        <p>The India Government Tourist Office is at 1270 Avenue of the Americas, Suite 1808, New York, N.Y. 10020; (212) 586-4901, fax (212) 582-3274. In New Delhi, the tourist office for Himachal Pradesh is in the Chandralok Building, 36 Janpath; (91-11) 332-5320, fax (91-11) 373-1072.</p>
        <p>The Consulate General of India, 3 East 64th Street, New York, N.Y. 10021; (212) 774-0600, fax (212) 570-9581, provides mandatory visas. The basic tourist visa, valid for up to six months, is $50, in person or by mail.</p>
        <p>Local Tours</p>
        <p>For help with travel arrangements in McLeod Ganj, try Ways Tours and Travel, Temple Road; (91-1892) 21910, fax (91-1892) 21775.</p>
        <p>The Regional Mountaineering Center in McLeod Ganj is at Kangra District, Himachal Pradesh, 176219, (91-1892) 21787; Yeti Trekking, (91-1892) 21032, fax (91-1892) 21578, has the same address. High Points of India has an office at 1 Portofino Court, San Carlos, Calif. 94070, (800) 624-3330, fax (415) 591-7120, and in New Delhi at 39 Paschim Marg, Vasant Viihar, New Delhi 110057; (91-11) 614-1224, fax 614-4767; Shikhar Travels is at 209 Competent House, F-14, Middle Circle, Connaught Place; (91-11) 331-2444, fax (91-11) 332-3660. Wilderness Travel is at 1102 Ninth Street, Berkeley, Calif. 94710; (800) 368-2794, fax (510) 558-2489.</p>
        <p>SUSAN SPANO</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
