<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN BRIEF</title>
    <meta content="4BRIEFS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Westchester County Airport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (Ny)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harrison (Ny)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattanville College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delfino, Joseph M (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gretsas, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graessle, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunphy, Edward P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'rourke, Andrew P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schulman, S J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD61231F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN BRIEF</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA GREENE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greene, Donna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Joseph M Delfino of White Plains, NY, retains all but three of city's top appointees of predecessor S J Schulman; names George Gretsas executive assistant; nominates Michael J Graessle as Planning Commissioner and Edward P Dunphy as Corporation Counsel; Westchester County Board of Legislators overrides most of budget vetoes of former County Executive Andrew P O'Rourke; General Electric receives permission to build hangar at Westchester County Airport, where it has rented space for almost four decades; Yonkers, NY, issues report finding it has been successful in controlling development and building affordable housing; Town Board in Harrison, NY, approves plan by New York Rangers to use planned sports center at Manhattanville College as practice facility (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Appointees Retained</p>
        <p>The new Mayor of White Plains, Joseph M. Delfino, a Republican replacing a Democrat, is retaining most of the city's top personnel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Appointees Retained</p>
        <p>The new Mayor of White Plains, Joseph M. Delfino, a Republican replacing a Democrat, is retaining most of the city's top personnel.</p>
        <p>In keeping all but three of the top appointees of S. J. Schulman, the former Mayor, Mr. Delfino said, ''We have some very talented people working for our city, and I am proud to have them as part of my administration.'' His action contrasts with that of the new Westchester County Executive, Andrew J. Spano, a Democrat, who has replaced many of the top appointees of the former longtime County Executive, Andrew J. O'Rourke, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Mayor Delfino did make three key appointments: he named George Gretsas, the former program coordinator for the Board of Legislators, as his executive assistant, a position that does not require confirmation by the Common Council. Mr. Gretsas, who replaces Kevin Fish, will earn $105,000.</p>
        <p>The new Mayor nominated Michael J. Graessle, Village Manager of Port Chester, to be Commissioner of Planning -- a department Mr. Graessle worked for for 12 years until 1993. Mr. Graessle, who will be paid $100,000, replaces Joseph R. Potenza. Mayor Delfino's nominee to be Corporation Counsel is his former campaign manager, Edward P. Dunphy, a senior associate with the law firm of Donovan Parry Carbin McDermott &amp; Radzik. Mr. Dunphy, who has been active in many White Plains government and civic groups, replaces John G. Callahan in the job, which pays $104,000. Both Mr. Graessle and Mr. Dunphy must be confirmed by the Common Council.</p>
        <p>Board Overrides Vetoes</p>
        <p>In the last battle of last year between the legislative branch and the executive branch, the Board of Legislators overrode most of the budget vetoes of the then County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke.</p>
        <p>As a consequence, proposals of at various times had been 8 percent, 5.5 percent and 6.5 percent increase in the average county tax rate finally become an average increase of 5.6 percent. The actual amount of increase homeowners will pay will vary municipality to municipality depending on assessing practices.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Rourke, a Republican who left office Thursday, had made 28 line-item vetoes to the budget adopted by the Board of Legislators, including 6 that dealt with $3.21 million in revenues that the Board added to Mr. O'Rourke's original budget. Mr. O'Rourke called the Board's projections ''flawed,'' claiming they were overly optimistic and would create fiscal problems.</p>
        <p>Five of those six vetoes were overridden by the Board, by the necessary two-thirds, or 12, votes, thereby restoring $2.2 million in revenue to the budget. The Board also overrode all of Mr. O'Rourke's other vetoes, which were of a technical nature.</p>
        <p>County taxes account for about 20 percent of property owners' bills. The rest is levied by school districts, local governments and special districts.</p>
        <p>New Airport Hangar</p>
        <p>Over objections of some environmentalists, General Electric received permission to build a hangar at the Westchester County Airport, where it has rented space for almost four decades.</p>
        <p>By a vote of 16-1, the Board of Legislators authorized construction of a 100,000-square-foot hangar off Route 120 in Harrison. Voting against the proposal was Paul J. Noto, a Republican from Mamaroneck.</p>
        <p>Because this site is near Rye Lake, part of the Kensico Reservoir System, environmentalists had opposed it, saying the hangar could have a significant environmental impact on the area's water and should not be approved without completion of a formal environmental impact statement.</p>
        <p>Legislators who supported the hangar said G.E. had modified its original plan to make sure that the environment was protected. For example, the company had agreed to increase the wetlands at the site, replace trees and shrubs it would remove and allow a committee of environmentalists to provide oversight.</p>
        <p>Under terms of the legislation, G.E. will pay the county $6.7 million over 30 years and pay about $325,000 in yearly property taxes to the county, the town of Harrison and the Harrison School District.</p>
        <p>Progress on Housing</p>
        <p>The city of Yonkers says 1997 was a resounding success in its effort to control its own destiny and develop affordable housing in compliance with court orders.</p>
        <p>According to a recent report issued by Mayor John D. Spencer, ''The city is on target in meeting its annual goals.'' The report was accompanied by a map, which suggested that the city has been relatively successful in distributing housing units throughout the city.</p>
        <p>''The distribution of units shows that no neighborhood is receiving the brunt of the court order, and the undeniable facts show that those who claim the city is loading up the housing in only a few neighborhoods are not telling the truth,'' the Mayor said.</p>
        <p>The report said that since last July the city's Affordable Housing Department had completed sales of 31 affordable housing units in 15 neighborhoods (defined by census tracts). An additional 17 units were being completed. Of the 31 finished units,  16 were in the northeast section of the city, 11 in the southeast section and 4 in the more affluent northeast section of the city.</p>
        <p>Yonkers has been embroiled in a Federal desegregation lawsuit for about 17 years, begun by the city's chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. In an effort to regain control of its own destiny, the city entered into an agreement with the court to build 100 units of affordable housing each year for the next five years.</p>
        <p>Rangers at Purchase</p>
        <p>The New York Rangers will be making Purchase their home away from their home at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Under a plan approved recently by the Harrison Town Board, the professional hockey team will use a Sports Center to be constructed at Manhattanville College, in the Purchase section of the town, as its practice site. This is not far from Purchase College, where the New York Knicks practice, and it continues the tradition of the Rangers' using Westchester for practice. For the last 10 years, the Rangers have used the ice rink at Playland, but now are leaving that site for Purchase. As at Playland, some Rangers' practice sessions at Manhattanville will be open to the public.</p>
        <p>The new sports center will be built at a cost of about $15 million, part of which will be paid by the Rangers, and the center could be ready by next fall. It will have two regulation-size hockey rinks for use by the Rangers, college students and at certain times local public school teams. The center is expected to accommodate other sports as well.</p>
        <p>DONNA GREENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
