<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing From Seeds, With the Faith of Thoreau</title>
    <meta content="04CUT.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Cass</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDC1F31F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing From Seeds, With the Faith of Thoreau</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cass Peterson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Cass</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuttins column on difficulty of growing flowers from seed, and patience required (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SEED represents a promise, a contract between gardener and nature. The general provisions are that if a gardener places the seed in soil, warms it, waters it and provides it with light, it will sprout and eventually manifest itself as a plant, maybe even the one pictured in the seed catalogue.</p>
        <p>To accept this contract requires a certain amount of faith. Henry David Thoreau had that kind of faith. ''Convince me that you have a seed there,'' he wrote, ''and I am prepared to expect wonders.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SEED represents a promise, a contract between gardener and nature. The general provisions are that if a gardener places the seed in soil, warms it, waters it and provides it with light, it will sprout and eventually manifest itself as a plant, maybe even the one pictured in the seed catalogue.</p>
        <p>To accept this contract requires a certain amount of faith. Henry David Thoreau had that kind of faith. ''Convince me that you have a seed there,'' he wrote, ''and I am prepared to expect wonders.''</p>
        <p>Thoreau, however, grew beans and corn -- the seeds of which are so eager to fulfill their promise that they will sprout in a wet paper towel. Clearly, he never had his faith tested by lisianthus, helleborus or tuberous begonia.</p>
        <p>Despite the term, ''seed catalogues'' are generally thin on information about seeds. Nowhere in the description of that gorgeous double-flowered begonia is it mentioned that there are roughly two million begonia seeds in an ounce or that a packet of 350 seeds contains what looks like a tiny pinch of fine dust.</p>
        <p>Nor does the term ''irregular germination'' adequately convey the message that if one plants 35 seeds of Anemone pulsatilla, two seedlings will emerge after three months and one of those will promptly expire.</p>
        <p>There are some plants that even professionals are loath to grow from seed, like rosemary and lavender, which have notoriously low germination rates. For every 100 rosemary seeds planted, possibly a dozen will sprout. That's why rosemary and lavender are almost always grown from cuttings.</p>
        <p>As much as faith, it takes patience to grow from seed. A geranium will take five to six months to go from seed to bloom; a lily might take five to six years. You'll get blooming plants much faster with cuttings from a geranium or offsets from a lily bulb.</p>
        <p>Still, it's hard to resist the temptations arrayed in the catalogues. It's even harder to deny the urge to be doing some kind of gardening during the dark, cold months.</p>
        <p>Here are a few tips to ease the frustration.</p>
        <p>BEWARE MINUSCULE SEEDS -- Some seeds are vanishingly small. An ounce of petunia, lobelia, lisianthus or portulaca seeds, for example, consists of between a quarter-million and a half-million seeds. No matter how carefully you sow the seed, you are bound to end up with crowded clumps of seedlings, which will choke each other out. If possible, buy pelleted seed, which has been coated with a claylike substance that enlarges the seed and makes it easier to handle. If you can't get pelleted seed, sow as thinly as possible, and don't sneeze while you're seeding.</p>
        <p>BEWARE THE NEONATAL UNIT -- Some plants are highly susceptible to damp-off and other fungal diseases in the seedling stage, even though they may be disease-resistant when mature. Begonias, browallia and vinca belong in the seed grower's ''challenging'' class.</p>
        <p>LET THERE BE LIGHT -- A surprising number of seeds, including those of ageratum, alyssum, coleus, impatiens and lobelia, need to be exposed to the light. Sprinkle them on the surface of the soil in a seedling flat, and don't cover them. As a rule of thumb, I don't cover any very small seeds. Watering the flat will wash a tiny bit of soil over the seed, and that will be enough. Conversely, some seeds, including those of Oriental poppies, globe amaranth and pansies, germinate better in the dark. Cover the flat with a sheet of newspaper, and peek under it every day. As soon as the first sprout appears, take the cover off.</p>
        <p>STRATIFY THY PERENNIALS -- Seeds of many perennial plants arrive from the seed company in a dormant state and have to be tricked into germinating -- not tough if you know the subterfuge called stratifying, but impossible if you don't. Stratifying is fooling the seed into thinking it has been through winter. Often it's enough to simply put the seed packet into the refrigerator or freezer for a couple of weeks before sowing. (I do this routinely for all hardy perennials, as well as for cool-weather perennials grown as annuals, like snapdragons and pansies.)</p>
        <p>If no seedlings appear within a month after sowing the chilled seed, put the entire moistened flat back into the refrigerator for a couple of weeks. A second, moist chilling is usually enough to awaken the seed.</p>
        <p>SCARIFY THY TOUGH NUTS -- Some seeds are encased in hard seed coats, nature's way of protecting the seed over the winter. Large seeds, like nasturtiums and sweet peas, can be scratched with a nail file or sandpaper to break the skin. This is called scarifying. Smaller seeds should be put into hot (not boiling) water and allowed to sit overnight to soften the skin.</p>
        <p>BE PATIENT -- If seeds of an annual plant have not sprouted in three weeks, begin to worry. Give it another week, or maybe two, and then reseed. If the seeds are of a perennial, however, be resigned. Germination times of one to three months are common, and some species, like helleborus, may take 18 months.</p>
        <p>Oh, for the faith of Thoreau.</p>
        <p>THIS WEEK  Tropical Delights for Winter</p>
        <p>As holiday blooms fade, try pots of tender bulbs that will flower in winter on windowsills. An easy one for bright light is the Amazon lily (Eucharis x grandiflora, commonly listed in mail-order bulb catalogues as Eucharis amazonica). It bears fragrant white flowers above glossy leaves and has the advantage of requiring nighttime temperatures of more than 60 degrees.</p>
        <p>The need to see something grow can be inexpensively satisfied by planting tropical produce. Plant firm, fresh ginger root in rich, evenly moist soil (besides the rhizome, the delicate lemon-scented leaves that emerge are used in cooking). Remove dry outer leaves of lemon grass, root them in water and pot. Tips on how to grow almost any edible plant are available in The Pits, the newsletter of the Rare Pit and Plant Council, 17 Circuit Avenue, Scituate, Mass. 02066 ($12.50 a year).</p>
        <p>PATRICIA JONAS</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
