<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holdsclaw's Defense Makes a Difference in Unlikely Rout</title>
    <meta content="04HUSK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Connecticut</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DF1430F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holdsclaw's Defense Makes a Difference in Unlikely Rout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>KNOXVILLE, Tenn., Jan. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tennessee defeats Connecticut, 84-69, in women's basketball; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whenever the Tennessee and Connecticut women's basketball teams have shared the same court, the games -- from the tip-off to the final buzzer -- have been thrilling, usually because of what was at stake.</p>
        <p>With the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament a couple of months away, the importance of today's game was somewhat diminished. But there was excitement nonetheless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whenever the Tennessee and Connecticut women's basketball teams have shared the same court, the games -- from the tip-off to the final buzzer -- have been thrilling, usually because of what was at stake.</p>
        <p>With the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament a couple of months away, the importance of today's game was somewhat diminished. But there was excitement nonetheless.</p>
        <p>The Lady Volunteers had their No. 1 ranking on the line against the No. 3 Huskies, and both teams looked to their all-Americans -- Chamique Holdsclaw of Tennessee and Nykesha Sales of UConn. But only Holdsclaw answered the challenge.</p>
        <p>The senior forward led an intense halfcourt press, scored a game-high 25 points and held Sales to 12 points as the Lady Vols defeated the Huskies, 84-69, before 24,597 at Thompson-Boling Arena, the largest crowd ever to watch a women's game here.</p>
        <p>''I felt our defensive pressure and our rebounding today was key for us,'' Lady Vols Coach Pat Summitt said. ''I challenged Chamique Holdsclaw to step up her defense. She's known as a mostly an offensive player, but I think her defense made the  difference in the game.''</p>
        <p>The Lady Vols got some help from a couple of freshmen, Semeka Randall, who scored 23 points and Tamika Catchings, who scored 17.</p>
        <p>UConn was led by Svetlana Abrosimova, a freshman forward from St. Petersburg, Russia, who scored 14 points. Amy Duran added 13, and Paige Sauer had 12.</p>
        <p>''This is by far my best game defensively,'' said Holdsclaw, who had a game-high six steals. ''We took them out of their game with our defense.''</p>
        <p>That included Sales, a senior forward who came into the game averaging 20 points.</p>
        <p>''She applied good pressure,'' Sales said of Holdsclaw. ''Whenever I caught the ball, a lot of Tennessee players were swarming near me.''</p>
        <p>The Huskies had trailed by 42-28 at halftime, settled down and nearly caught Tennessee, at 49-48, with 2 minutes 34 seconds to play in the third quarter. Abrosimova led the Huskies' comeback, scoring 6 points in the period.</p>
        <p>But Holdsclaw's 14 points in the second half helped hold the Huskies off. She scored twice in the final minute of the third quarter as the Lady Vols extended their lead to 56-48.</p>
        <p>The Huskies got within 62-54 with 6:25 left to play on a layup by Abrosimova, but they could not inch nearer.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes these games take on an eerie appearance,'' UConn Coach Geno Auriemma said. ''If you win this game, everything is right. If you lose, it's like you will not win another game. It's hard for the players to lose when so much is attached to this game.</p>
        <p>''There is very little you can do because of the tremendous pressure Tennessee puts on you. We did a pretty decent job, minus the turnovers and rebounds.''</p>
        <p>Tennessee outrebounded UConn by 41-28, and the Huskies made 27 turnovers.</p>
        <p>''Whenever Tennessee beats Connecticut, it's significant,'' Summitt said. ''I thought Connecticut made a good run at us.''</p>
        <p>Tennessee dominated the first half as Catchings scored 11 points and Holdsclaw 10. The Lady Vols scored the first 10 points, but the Huskies, behind the strong inside play of the 6-foot-5-inch Sauer, rebounded and cut the Tennessee lead to 14-13 with 2:54 left in the first quarter. The game was played in 10-minute quarters instead of 20-minute halves to allow for television breaks.</p>
        <p>After a slow start by Holdsclaw, the junior forward from Astoria, Queens, took over the game. Sales started the game with a couple of air balls. She scored 4 points in the first half; much of the credit for that goes to Holdsclaw's defense.</p>
        <p>As she has previously this season, Summitt showed confidence in her underclassmen, putting four freshmen -- Catchings, Randall, Kristen Clement and Teresa Geter -- on the floor for much of the second quarter. It was a glimpse of Tennessee's future, which seems to be very promising, given how well the four are playing.</p>
        <p>But if they did not seem intimidated by Connecticut, the freshmen had plenty of reminders that they were playing in one of the game's great rivalries.</p>
        <p>''I'm used to playing in my old high school gym in front of 50 people,'' Randall said. ''But 24,000? I can't even explain it.''  COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
