<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Friends Say Ferraro Will Seek D'Amato's Seat</title>
    <meta content="04FERR$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferraro, Geraldine A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDF1430F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Friends Say Ferraro Will Seek D'Amato's Seat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Repr Geraldine A Ferraro reportedly decides to seek Democratic nomination for US Senate seat from New York held by Alfonse M D'Amato; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Geraldine A. Ferraro has told friends she will seek the Democratic nomination to challenge Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato this year, and she asked her advisers to assemble today in New York City to plan for an official announcement tomorrow, her supporters said.</p>
        <p>The decision by Ms. Ferraro, the former United States Representative from Queens, was made as she returned from a vacation with her family on the Caribbean Island of St. Croix, and it sets the stage for another return to politics by the first woman ever nominated to run for Vice President. The decision clears the way for her to take a second shot at winning a prize -- her party's nomination to run against Mr. D'Amato -- that eluded her by a single percentage point during a memorably brutal four-way primary in 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Geraldine A. Ferraro has told friends she will seek the Democratic nomination to challenge Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato this year, and she asked her advisers to assemble today in New York City to plan for an official announcement tomorrow, her supporters said.</p>
        <p>The decision by Ms. Ferraro, the former United States Representative from Queens, was made as she returned from a vacation with her family on the Caribbean Island of St. Croix, and it sets the stage for another return to politics by the first woman ever nominated to run for Vice President. The decision clears the way for her to take a second shot at winning a prize -- her party's nomination to run against Mr. D'Amato -- that eluded her by a single percentage point during a memorably brutal four-way primary in 1992.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be meeting tomorrow and we'll have an announcement on Monday,'' said David Eichenbaum, the former communications director of the Democratic National Committee, who is expected to be Ms. Ferraro's campaign manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eichenbaum declined to comment further, and Ms. Ferraro did not return telephone messages left at her home yesterday. But other friends of Ms. Ferraro's said that she and her campaign advisers intend to spend today putting the final touches on the details of her announcement speech, which she will deliver in Manhattan tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro, who is a commentator for CNN, is poised to enter what is already one of the nation's most competitive and closely watched political contests of 1998. Mr. D'Amato is seeking a fourth term, and many Democrats are convinced, based on a series of polls, that he is as vulnerable to defeat as he has been at any point in his career.</p>
        <p>Two New York City Democrats have already said they are seeking the nomination: Mark J. Green, the city's Public Advocate, and United States Representative Charles E. Schumer of Brooklyn. But many Democrats said that even with her comparatively late entry into the race, Ms. Ferraro would instantly be perceived as the front-runner.</p>
        <p>There are two reasons for that assessment: the first is that she is far better known than either Mr. Green or Mr. Schumer. Ms. Ferraro has been a national celebrity since Walter F. Mondale asked her to be his running-mate against President Reagan and Vice President George W. Bush in 1984. Although the memory of that failed campaign has faded, she has managed to keep her face in the public view with her seat on the CNN program ''Crossfire'' -- to the annoyance of Mr. D'Amato.</p>
        <p>The second reason is her sex: As things stand now, Ms. Ferraro would be the only woman in a three-way primary. Recent New York political history has shown that sex is not the decisive factor that some Democratic politicians wish it were; Ruth W. Messinger lost the mayoral race decisively among both women and men to Rudolph W. Giuliani in November. But this year's race will be run in the shadow of the 1992 Senate primary, a contest that many women viewed as a setback for women trying to attain high office in American politics.</p>
        <p>That primary was remarkable for the ferocity of attacks leveled at Ms. Ferraro's ethics and personal business dealings by another prominent New York Democrat, Elizabeth Holtzman, the City Comptroller. Attorney General Robert Abrams, who also attacked Ms. Ferraro's ethics, though not as intensely, won the nomination before going on to lose to Mr. D'Amato.</p>
        <p>This year's Senate election will provide Ms. Ferraro with what will almost certainly be her last opportunity to revive her political career. She is now 62 years old, and she has lost the two highest-profile campaigns of her career.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro returned last night from a vacation in St. Croix, in the Virgin Islands, where she had said she and her family would make a final decision about her political future. She asked her political aides to assemble in New York today to plan the campaign. Her advisers yesterday declined to discuss Ms. Ferraro's campaign, pending her own announcement. Her decision was described by her friends as all but final.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro's likely Democratic opponents were not surprised by the news, which she has strongly hinted at for nearly six months. ''My reaction is, 'Welcome back and welcome in,' '' Mr. Green said yesterday evening. ''I look forward to a clean contest that compares what she and I have accomplished over the years for consumers, for children and families.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer said Ms. Ferraro's decision was evidence of Mr. D'Amato's vulnerability. ''I always assumed this was going to happen,'' he said. ''I always thought there'd be a fight for the Democratic nomination. But I believe my record makes me the person best able to win the Democratic primary and beat Al D'Amato.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro's entry into the race seems certain to cause a flurry of excitement within the Democratic Party, which has been going through a particularly dark period in this state since the 1992 primary. The party lost the mayoral race last year, and it faces a gubernatorial race against George E. Pataki this year that many Democrats think is equally problematic.</p>
        <p>For all of Ms. Ferraro's stature, Mr. D'Amato's vulnerability, and the likely symbolism of her candidacy, however, there have already been signs this year that the Senate contest will not be easy.</p>
        <p>Elected officials and those with the Democratic Party have already begun lining up with Mr. Green and Mr. Schumer, despite Ms. Ferraro's request that they hold off. That suggests that Ms. Ferraro may not have the pull that she had hoped with the Democratic establishment in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro might also be hampered by the fact that she has been essentially out of government for 14 years. Her lack of a record has already been raised, if implicitly, by Mr. Schumer and Mr. Green, both of whom have made clear that they would make their own records in government a central part of their campaign appeals. They have made a deliberate if unstated effort to remind voters how long Ms. Ferraro has been out of government.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferraro faces financial hurdles as well. Mr. Schumer has raised more than $8 million. Ms. Ferraro, by contrast, has not done any fund-raising in the past six months, out of concern that politicking might prompt CNN to remove her from her position as a commentator. But Ms. Ferraro has argued that her own network of supporters, particularly among feminist groups, would provide her with a quick source of money.</p>
        <p>Finally, Ms. Ferraro may remain vulnerable to the kind of attacks that contributed to her loss in 1992, when Ms. Holtzman and Mr. Abrams criticized the business matters of Ms. Ferraro and her husband, John A. Zacarro, presenting the family as having shady dealings and ties to organized crime. By the end of the campaign, Ms. Ferraro made a highly unusual two-minute television statement, in which she said: ''My opponents have tried to turn me into an evil figure from the shadows. In the end, I know of no other way to respond than to look you in the eye and swear to you that I have never been involved with organized crime.''</p>
        <p>There was tremendous backlash within the Democratic Party over that primary, and aides to Mr. Schumer and Mr. Green said the candidates probably will not go down that road. Ms. Ferraro's friends said they believed that those attacks, and the newspaper coverage of the allegations, had succeeded in inoculating her from being hurt by such charges this time around.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
