<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Your Money; Saving Too Much For Retirement</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIVIDUAL RETIREMENT ACCOUNTS (IRA)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSEN, JAN M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Individual Retirement Accounts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Individual Retirement Accounts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91E3FF930A15756C0A964958260" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Your Money; Saving Too Much For Retirement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jan M. Rosen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSEN, JAN M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unlike the majority of Americans who need to save more for retirement, some people -- notably upper-income professionals and business owners -- may be putting away too much in tax-deferred retirement savings plans.</p>
        <p>Sam Radin, a lawyer and president of the National Madison Group Inc. in New York, said, "Tax-qualified wealth can be illusory." Once a person's assets in an individual retirement account, Keogh or similar plan reach $1 million, he recommends doing an individual analysis to determine how much is likely to be there at retirement age and whether the owner and his or her estate are likely to be liable for penalties, as well as income and estate taxes. There is no one limit for everyone; it must be calculated under complex requirements of the 1987 tax law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unlike the majority of Americans who need to save more for retirement, some people -- notably upper-income professionals and business owners -- may be putting away too much in tax-deferred retirement savings plans.</p>
        <p>Sam Radin, a lawyer and president of the National Madison Group Inc. in New York, said, "Tax-qualified wealth can be illusory." Once a person's assets in an individual retirement account, Keogh or similar plan reach $1 million, he recommends doing an individual analysis to determine how much is likely to be there at retirement age and whether the owner and his or her estate are likely to be liable for penalties, as well as income and estate taxes. There is no one limit for everyone; it must be calculated under complex requirements of the 1987 tax law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radin told of one client, a 53-year-old professional man who intended to retire at 65. He wanted a comfortable retirement for himself and his wife and a good estate for his children and grandchildren, so he was putting as much into his group's retirement plan as he could each year, $30,000, and now has more than $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>The plan is earning 9 percent a year, and at that rate, his account balance would be almost $3.5 million when he is 65. That amount is enough that should he die that year, his heirs -- other than his wife -- would owe a 15 percent tax on excess accumulation, or $263,000; a 55 percent estate tax, or $1.75 million, and Federal and state income taxes of more than $575,000. The family would get only a quarter of the money that was in the plan, or $860,000.</p>
        <p>Another trap for people with what are known as overfunded plans is the excess-distribution penalty, a 15 percent excise tax on annual withdrawals above roughly $150,000. Mr. Radin's client would be likely to face that should he keep putting money into the plan and not take distributions until retirement time.</p>
        <p>The client already has enough in the plan for his own retirement needs, Mr. Radin said. Therefore, the client intends to start early withdrawals in two years, taking money out in an annuitized form based on life expectancy to avoid the 10 percent penalty imposed on withdrawals before age 59 1/2.</p>
        <p>He can put the money withdrawn, plus the money he would have put into the retirement fund -- $18,000 a year on an after-tax basis -- into trust for his children and escape the estate tax and the excess-accumulation penalty. There are several investment options for the money in trust, Mr. Radin said, but the client plans to buy life insurance, which will pay almost $3 million to his heirs.</p>
        <p>The need for such planning came about as a result of the tax laws of the 1980's. Most people are well aware of how those laws have affected their current tax situations, but many are not aware of the effect on retirement plans, simply assuming that pensions are exempt from estate taxes as they once were.</p>
        <p>Also, the assets in many retirement plans surged during the bull market of the last decade, another reason to analyze one's holdings and the likely tax consequences.</p>
        <p>"There's nothing I can do about income taxes at life or death," Mr. Radin said, "but there is something I can do about the 15 percent excise tax and the estate tax," mainly by using trusts tailored for personal financial goals.</p>
        <p>Many people, of course, may analyze their retirement savings and decide steady as you go.</p>
        <p>Milton Pickman, senior tax partner with Anchin Block &amp; Anchin, a New York accounting firm, said that generally it was advisable to leave money in a tax-qualified plan as long as possible. That is because the advantages of putting money into a plan on a pretax basis and having it compound tax free over the years more than offset the taxes that will be due when money is taken out.</p>
        <p>This is nearly always the case for middle-income people, and often it works that way for upper-income people, as well, he said, even if a 15 percent excise tax has to be paid, as well as current income tax. But, he stressed, it is important to do individual calculations for each client.</p>
        <p>Calculations are done using computer programs that take account of such variables as projected return on investment, expected future income and estate tax rates and projected income needs. Because any of these numbers can change, the calculations need to be reviewed annually.</p>
        <p>"One thing that works for a charitably minded person is to" bequeath the balance in an I.R.A. or similar plan to a charity, he said, because charities are exempt from estate and income taxes.</p>
        <p>Typically the money would go first to a surviving spouse since no estate taxes would be due, then the widow or widower would leave it to charity. This would enable a couple to have the account balance available as long as they needed it.</p>
        <p>If the couple intend to leave property to both their children and a charity, Mr. Pickman said, it is better to give the charity the money from the I.R.A. and the children other assets, because, unlike the charity, the children would have to pay income tax on any money from the I.R.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
