<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Cowboys, Mood Swings Are Just Another Part of Their Seesaw Season</title>
    <meta content="23cowboys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1806831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1DF133EF930A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Cowboys, Mood Swings Are Just Another Part of Their Seesaw Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>IRVING, Tex., Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cowboys were glummer than a stranded holiday traveler, and Coach Bill Parcells's deadened delivery during his postgame address after Dallas's loss to the Giants last month embodied the team's desolation.</p>
        <p>''I'm ashamed to put a team out there that played like that,'' Parcells said after the 36-22 defeat, and his pathos was so pronounced that nobody doubted his sincerity. In the days that followed, as the 3-3 Cowboys tried to regroup, Parcells was portrayed in more than one article as a man on the verge of a third retirement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cowboys were glummer than a stranded holiday traveler, and Coach Bill Parcells's deadened delivery during his postgame address after Dallas's loss to the Giants last month embodied the team's desolation.</p>
        <p>''I'm ashamed to put a team out there that played like that,'' Parcells said after the 36-22 defeat, and his pathos was so pronounced that nobody doubted his sincerity. In the days that followed, as the 3-3 Cowboys tried to regroup, Parcells was portrayed in more than one article as a man on the verge of a third retirement.</p>
        <p>Six days after the debacle against the Giants, the Cowboys traveled to North Carolina and beat the Panthers, 35-14, in a game that ended with a giddy Parcells kissing some of his players.</p>
        <p>From enervated one week to exuberant the next, the mood swings in the N.F.L. can be manic in their extremes. Every week, teams pour all their energy and effort into a single game, the regular season a four-month grind that is reduced to 16 breakaways from the pack.</p>
        <p>The cycling of emotions is what happens when people's reputations and careers can be derailed by a tipped ball or a bad call, a field goal or a freakish injury. The Cowboys' seesaw season, in which they have gone from National Football Conference championship contenders to underachievers and back in four short weeks, is the story writ large of the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>After replacing the benched Drew Bledsoe in the second half of the Giants' game, quarterback Tony Romo made his N.F.L. starting debut in the Cowboys' game at Charlotte. The 26-year-old Romo, who is as even-tempered as Parcells is emotional, rallied the Cowboys from a 14-point deficit against the Panthers on the strength of a 25-point fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The day after the victory against Carolina, Parcells sounded less like a man on the verge of retirement than a golfer who birdies the 18th hole after making a mess of the first 17.</p>
        <p>He said he would take the abuse ''I took in this business twice a day for about two years to feel just like I did last night once.''</p>
        <p>The dark clouds were back the next week after a 22-19 loss to Washington in which Terrell Owens dropped a pass that probably would have gone for a 74-yard touchdown. Mike Vanderjagt's potential game-winning 35-yard field goal with seconds left was blocked and a face-mask penalty by the Cowboys' Kyle Kosier on the ensuing return made possible the Redskins' winning kick with no time left.</p>
        <p>''It is trying on me,'' Parcells said, referring to his team's mistake-prone play. ''It is, there's no doubt. But that's the way the game is.''</p>
        <p>The Cowboys' next game was at Arizona, and Romo, again, was outstanding. He threw for 308 yards, completed all 10 passes he attempted in the second half and was not sacked in the Cowboys' 27-10 victory. The result, Cowboys defensive tackle Jason Ferguson said afterward, ''is something we needed, like some therapy.''</p>
        <p>Romo, who was signed by the Cowboys as an undrafted free agent in 2003, has had the same effect on his teammates as an antidepressant.</p>
        <p>''When you see positive play on the part of anybody,'' Parcells said, ''it has the tendency to inspire a lot of people. Any player that can inspire other players can usually inspire me.''</p>
        <p>Last weekend against the undefeated Indianapolis Colts, the Cowboys played inspired on both sides of the ball. After the Cowboys defeated the Colts, 21-14, Romo returned Parcells's praise.</p>
        <p>''Bill is unbelievable,'' Romo said. ''He had a plan for today.'' He added, ''You guys should never question how good he is.''</p>
        <p>Nobody has talked this week of how tired the 65-year-old Parcells looks or has dared suggest that the game has passed him by. His Cowboys again have the look of an N.F.C. title contender, while the injury-ravaged Giants (6-4) are looking vulnerable and the New Orleans Saints (6-4) have lost two in a row and the Philadelphia Eagles (5-5) have lost quarterback Donovan McNabb for the season.</p>
        <p>A victory Thursday at Texas Stadium against the Tampa Bay Buccaneers, who are winless on the road this season, would improve the Cowboys' record to 7-4 as they head into their rematch next week with the Giants. A loss would no doubt ruin everything.</p>
        <p>''When you lose, all of the sudden it's the end of the world around here,'' Romo said. ''We don't want the world to end any time soon, so we'll just try and keep winning.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
