<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kelly and Bills Bury Jets</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="189088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUFFALO BILLS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DA123DF93BA25753C1A96E948260" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kelly and Bills Bury Jets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly, it seems like winter again for the Jets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly, it seems like winter again for the Jets.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, it seems like winter again for the Jets.</p>
        <p>The injury jinx returned, but even more damaging tonight was the presence of the Buffalo Bills, their defense grinding the Jets into the turf, their offense led by Jim Kelly's powerful aerials.</p>
        <p>The Bills, the American Conference East's top team at 6-1, sent the Jets into third place with a 37-14 rout.</p>
        <p>The game was punctuated by a bizarre series of fights in the stands, where some fans even set a bonfire, and where they chanted, ''Joe Must Go!''</p>
        <p>''I can't think of one excuse I can give you,'' said Coach Joe Walton after the game, the Jets' worst performance since their season's opener. Second Straight Loss</p>
        <p>It was the Jets' second straight loss, and their third straight game without a victory following their surprising three-game winning streak. And inevitably, it suggested later-season collapses of recent years.</p>
        <p>This loss produced more injuries on a club that this season had seemed able to avoid its injury jinx. Going into the game, not one regular had missed more than one start this fall.</p>
        <p>Instead, the left side of the offensive line will be out for a month, at least. Before the game the left tackle, Dave Cadigan, was placed on injured reserve because of a sprained foot. In the game, Ted Banker, the left guard, sprained a foot that will keep him out for four games, too.</p>
        <p>Small wonder that marauding Bills' defenders, especially Bruce Smith, trampled over the line to sack Ken O'Brien five times. Smith produced two and a half sacks, twice going over Cadigan's replacement, Jeff Criswell, once with a spin move on which he was untouched.</p>
        <p>Faced with this constant pressure, O'Brien was doubly in jeopardy: He couldn't dump the ball off to his favorite short-range target, Mickey Shuler. The tight end, who was on the sidelines suffering from a pinched neck nerve, never got into the game. Gordon Out With Thigh Bruise</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Kelly punctured the weakened Jets' defense at will. It performed without Alex Gordon, the key left outside linebacker, who has helped bring back the pass rush in tandem with Mark Gastineau. But Gordon did not even suit up, bothered with a thigh bruise.</p>
        <p>Kelly was dumped only once, when it hardly mattered. The Bills scored points the first four times they had the ball to generate a 24-0 lead. Kelly produced 302 yards and threw for three scores. He completed 16 of 27 passes and was picked off once.</p>
        <p>Role players also were injured for the Jets. Terry Williams, the defensive back on ''dime'' passing situations, sprained a knee and is out four to five weeks. And Nuu Faaola, a special teams' tackler, suffered a bruised neck, but left the locker room under his own power after being placed in a neck brace on the field. pick up only ad f.s. jets That was late in the game, after other damage had been inflicted on his teammates. Kelly's first-half performance, which included a pair of touchdown tosses to Andre Reed, set up a second half in which the Bills simply ran. They didn't throw a pass in the final quarter, and controlled the ball for almost 23 minutes of the half.</p>
        <p>Reed was to snare 7 receptions for 132 yards. His first score completed a 65-yard pass play after he had slipped between Bobby Humphery and Rich Miano. That followed an opening drive that ended with a Scott Norwood 30-yard field goal.</p>
        <p>Just after Reed's score, Kelly was looking for Robb Riddick over the middle. The pass was deflected near midfield by Carl Howard - and right into Flip Johnson's hands. He dashed home alone to complete a 66-yard play.</p>
        <p>Seconds into the second period, Riddick dived over from the 1-yard line to produce a 24-point gap.</p>
        <p>The Jets responded with a 76-yard drive on which they picked up 26 yards on an O'Brien-to-Al-Toon pass that was set up after Freeman McNeil faked a run, and tossed the ball back to O'Brien. Johnny Hector completed the march with a 1-yard dive.</p>
        <p>But Reed was all alone in the end zone and spotted by Kelly on a 16-yard play late in the half. Norwood sandwiched second-half field goals around Erik McMillan's 40-yard interception return of a Kelly pass, the Bills' only turnover.</p>
        <p>O'Brien generated scant yardage, completing only four passes to a wide receiver, all to Toon. They produced only 49 yards. Over all, the quarterback completed 18 of 30 passes for 191 yards and was picked off once.</p>
        <p>The Jets' running game totaled only 45 yards on 13 carries, with Freeman McNeil having only 23 yards on 7 attempts.  Rare Appearance</p>
        <p>This was the Bills' first Monday night appearance since 1984, and their first victory since 1981. The Bills had not been on a Monday night telecast since 1984 and had not won on that night since 1981. The Jets had been 7-0 at home on Mondays.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
