<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Series of Scandals Have Japanese Debating if Country Has Grown Corrupt</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="468000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DF123CF93AA2575BC0A967958260" item-length="1372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Series of Scandals Have Japanese Debating if Country Has Grown Corrupt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Aug. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first trickle of scandal came last winter, with reports of a major bank arranging illegal loans for a convicted stock manipulator. Then some respected corporations were reported to have used purchases of European paintings to launder money and evade taxes.</p>
        <p>A torrent of additional disclosures has come in recent months. Now the Japanese are awash in scandals involving major institutions and politicians, about a dozen arrests and billions of dollars in questionable payments and transactions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first trickle of scandal came last winter, with reports of a major bank arranging illegal loans for a convicted stock manipulator. Then some respected corporations were reported to have used purchases of European paintings to launder money and evade taxes.</p>
        <p>A torrent of additional disclosures has come in recent months. Now the Japanese are awash in scandals involving major institutions and politicians, about a dozen arrests and billions of dollars in questionable payments and transactions.</p>
        <p>Those include about $5 billion in allegedly fraudulent loans by banks, $1 billion in improper compensation to certain companies by brokerage firms and hundreds of millions of dollars in stock manipulation carried out by organized-crime figures and others.</p>
        <p>The disclosures have led to the resignation of top officers of at least five big financial companies, and the resignation of Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto is widely expected later this month.  'An Insider's Game'</p>
        <p>Taken together, the Japanese scandals are bigger than the improprieties attributed to the Bank of Credit and Commerce International, and they have set off a debate over whether the booming 1980's transformed Japan from an honest society into a dishonest one.</p>
        <p>"Is Japan basically corrupt?" asked Makoto Sataka, whose articles and columns on corporate behavior appear in several magazines. "I think most people don't like the way things are going, but they accept that in Japan, capitalism is an insider's game."</p>
        <p>The backdrop of the scandals is an economic boom greater and longer than any other in Japan's postwar history, accompanied by soaring real estate and stock market prices that leveled off and in some cases collapsed in the last year.</p>
        <p>The air being let out of what Japanese call the "bubble economy" inevitably led to business failures, bad debts and disclosures of questionable business practices, from stock manipulation to dealings with mobsters to tax evasion on a mammoth scale.  Disillusion Sets In</p>
        <p>"We have to realize that all our vices have been concealed for a long time now," said Takao Akabane, an adviser at the Government's Economic Planning Agency. "As long as everything was going up, everything seemed O.K. We shouldn't be shocked by what's happened. It was inevitable."</p>
        <p>But in some quarters, disillusion has set in. Young Japanese used to lust after jobs at banks and brokerage houses, but no longer.</p>
        <p>"Students are beginning to realize that there is a bad side to that industry," said Katsu Tanaka, head of job counseling at Sophia University in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Some Japanese worry that the boom has created two separate societies.</p>
        <p>"We have politicians and businessmen who manipulate the economy," said Hiroyoshi Ishikawa, professor of social psychology at Seijo University in Tokyo. "The ordinary people have not benefited."  Some Customers Don't Object</p>
        <p>But on the other hand, there is a widespread belief in Japan that the excesses of the recent scandals are merely exaggerated forms of what had been standard business practices and that those should not be discredited just because of the recent problems.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the problems at Nomura Securities, for instance, are the illegal compensations for losses in the stock market paid by the world's biggest brokerage to its best corporate customers, with its small individual and foreign customers left out in the cold.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu and a host of Government officials have criticized those practices as an affront to Japan's 10 million individual stockholders and an embarrassment giving new fodder to foreign critics who accuse Japan of corporate cronyism.</p>
        <p>But at the Ginza office of Nomura Securities, every single customer one recent lunchtime expressed a lack of concern over the disclosures. Wasn't it right, they said, that brokers took care of their best customers?</p>
        <p>"I haven't lost my faith," said a woman staring at a flashing board of stock market prices. "These kinds of practices may really be what made Japan rich. And the fact that Japan is rich may also have benefited the whole world -- the Americans, too."  A Common Element</p>
        <p>The details of all the scandals in Japan today are bewildering, but a common element has been the involvement of people close to some of Japan's leading politicians. The role played by politicians points up the close connection between the Japanese political and financial worlds and the fact that favors are legal and almost always a part of the relationship. And many analysts inside and outside Japan agree that despite the postwar Westernizing trend, it is relationships, much more than laws and regulations, that are the glue holding Japanese society together.</p>
        <p>By tradition, gift-giving is a major ingredient of doing business. According to the National Tax Agency, Japanese businesses spent $35 billion on legal gifts and entertainment expenses last year alone, a nearly 10 percent increase over the previous year.</p>
        <p>Favors are sometimes demanded explicitly, as when the governing Liberal Democratic Party raised hundreds of millions of dollars in campaign funds last year, warning the automobile, electronics and appliance industries that taxes on their products could be increased if they did not cooperate.</p>
        <p>Though it is illegal, the trading of insider stock information is seen as a recent extreme outgrowth of this honored tradition. But it appears to be widespread, and rarely prosecuted; a top officer at a big brokerage firm said in an interview that politicians were routinely given free stock tips.</p>
        <p>Many people were also not surprised when it was disclosed this month that the secretary of Mr. Hashimoto was an intermediary in a questionable loan. Intermediaries are often a part of business deals, and politicians are often in a position to play such a role.  Politicians Profit</p>
        <p>"I don't think Japan is any more corrupt than any other mature society," said Kazuo Nukazawa, managing director of Keidanren, the biggest industry trade association in Japan. "I don't see any money going into the Finance Minister's pocket, or the pocket of his secretary."</p>
        <p>The construction, securities and banking industries have also been major sources of financing for the governing party, and the Japanese press has long reported that individual party politicians have raised money from the stock market.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, many Japanese are also not surprised to see the names of politicians as beneficiaries in the recent scandal. In fact, many people say it is inevitable that more disclosures will bring names of more politicians to the surface.</p>
        <p>"In Japan, deals are discreetly negotiated, intermediaries always get a share, the wheels are always greased a little and big people get more than little people," said the president of a major industrial corporation. "But these things have to be contained within certain limits."</p>
        <p>The executive said those practices had at least insured that politicians committed to democracy could succeed in a country with no democratic traditions.</p>
        <p>"I've always felt that these scandals are a price you have to pay to get democracy moving in this country," he said. "It was the one way to bring power and authority to the political establishment."  The 'Outlaws' Take Part</p>
        <p>Japanese seem to accept such practices as long as the gains go to political organizations' operating budgets and do not end up in the pockets of the politicians themselves. The so-called Recruit scandal of 1989, which led to charges of bribery against 12 politicians, civil servants and businessmen and toppled the Government of Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita, featured bureaucrats and politicians using the money for big houses or other luxuries.</p>
        <p>Another aspect of the boom of the last few years has been the drawing in of unsavory types not previously involved in conventional business deals, like organized-crime figures.</p>
        <p>"In the last five years, we've had all this active land price speculation, which inevitably drew quite a number of outlaws into the picture," said Akio Mikuni, president of Mikuni &amp; Company, a securities rating company. "With all these pseudo takeovers, some illegal practitioners could be expected."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
