<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sheep Inc.: As a Herd Grows, So Do a Restaurant and Inn</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="831443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHEEP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OLD CHATHAM (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">OLD CHATHAM SHEEPHERDING COMPANY INN (OLD CHATHAM, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARK, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARK, NANCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLY, MELISSA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE THOMASCAMPBELL 'TOM' CLARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EED71339F932A15751C0A960958260" item-length="1433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sheep Inc.: As a Herd Grows, So Do a Restaurant and Inn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE THOMASCAMPBELL 'TOM' CLARK;</byline>
      <dateline>OLD CHATHAM, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOM CLARK, who lives in Rye, N.Y., and has an investment company in Greenwich, Conn., has long been interested in raising sheep. "I grew up near Poughkeepsie, my grandfather had 25 acres, and I took care of three sheep," he said.</p>
        <p>Now, he has more than 800 sheep. And by summer, he and his wife, Nancy, expect to have nearly 2,000 head at the Old Chatham Sheepherding Company, their  farm in Old Chatham, in the Hudson Valley, about a two-and-a-half-hour drive north of Manhattan. It is already the largest dairy sheep farm in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOM CLARK, who lives in Rye, N.Y., and has an investment company in Greenwich, Conn., has long been interested in raising sheep. "I grew up near Poughkeepsie, my grandfather had 25 acres, and I took care of three sheep," he said.</p>
        <p>Now, he has more than 800 sheep. And by summer, he and his wife, Nancy, expect to have nearly 2,000 head at the Old Chatham Sheepherding Company, their  farm in Old Chatham, in the Hudson Valley, about a two-and-a-half-hour drive north of Manhattan. It is already the largest dairy sheep farm in the country.</p>
        <p>The Clarks, both in their mid-50's, also own the Old Chatham Sheepherding Company Inn, a gracious, antique-filled, eight-room country inn and restaurant that opened on the farm last fall.</p>
        <p>In the coming months, a bakery, several acres of vegetable gardens, a smokehouse and a shop will be added to the burgeoning 500-acre enterprise, and cheese-making equipment will be installed in the Shaker-style barn. Two more guest rooms are under construction. As the size of the herd increases, fresh lamb, already on the menu, will be available to other restaurants and perhaps at retail. (The female lambs will become milk producers; many of the male lambs will become meat.)</p>
        <p>"This project has an energy all its own," Mr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>It has led to the ultimate synthesis of chef and farmer. Many chefs cultivate their own little organic gardens, but Melissa Kelly, the chef whom the Clarks hired for the restaurant, is almost giddy at the prospect of the resources she will have.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kelly, a graduate of the Culinary Institute of America, worked for many years with her mentor, Larry Forgione, the chef and an owner of An American Place in Manhattan. She learned the importance of supporting small local farms from Mr. Forgione, one of the country's first chefs to exploit home-grown American ingredients. She also became familiar with the Hudson Valley's agricultural bounty during a two-year stint as the chef of the Beekman Arms in Rhinebeck, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Now, right out the back door of her kitchen is a rapidly expanding farm project supported by ambitious proprietors with deep pockets, who were a little  surprised that a 30-year-old chef with some big-city job offers was so eager to  work for them.</p>
        <p>"This is a working farm," Ms. Kelly said. "Why wouldn't I want to work here?" She is already providing guests at the 45-seat restaurant with delicious ice creams made with sheep's milk and dishes made with sheep's milk cheese. The milk is rich and sweet, balanced with the merest hint of salt.</p>
        <p>"If you tell people you serve sheep-milk ice cream, they think you're crazy," she said. "Until they taste it." Rum raisin, ginger, chocolate and vanilla are a few of the flavors.</p>
        <p>Her food emphasizes farm-fresh ingredients in well-flavored contemporary dishes done with stylish Mediterranean and Asian touches. A recent menu paired a rack of lamb from the herd with homemade lamb sausage on a bed of rape and garlic mashed potatoes. Sunday brunch might include an omelet wrapped around roasted potatoes and fresh sheep's milk cheese or a country-bread sandwich of grilled eggplant and roast lamb.</p>
        <p>Sheep's milk is used in much of the baking. But most of the milk is sold to Hollow Road Farms in nearby Stuyvesant, N.Y., one of the country's first producers of sheep's milk cheese. For now, most of the sheep's milk cheeses and  yogurt on the inn's menu are from Hollow Road.</p>
        <p>The Clarks originally planned to have just a sheep farm. But the property, which they bought in 1993, included a roomy Georgian-style house, built in 1790. The Clarks decided not to live in it, because they were happy with their weekend house nearby. They sought advice from Cornell University's School of Hotel Administration. Their project became an assignment for several graduate students, who recommended they turn the house into an inn.</p>
        <p>More than $1 million later, the inn opened, luxuriously outfitted and appointed. Mrs. Clark, who still works as an interior decorator, filled the house mostly with 18th- and 19th-century antiques, including four-poster beds and country armoires.</p>
        <p>Wool from the sheep fills the bed pads and quilts. With the inn's hand-painted sheep logo, sheep-shaped doorstops and assorted sheep and lamb items on the menu, the ovine theme is ever-present. There is even an appropriate quaff at the bar: a single malt Scotch called Sheep Dip.</p>
        <p>The Old Chatham Sheepherding Company Inn is at 99 Shaker Museum Road, Old Chatham, N.Y.; (518) 794-9774. Room rates range from $185 to $325 and include continental breakfast. Dinner is served Monday through Saturday, from 5:30 to 10 P.M., and Sunday, 5 to 9 P.M. Main courses are $14 to $23. Sunday brunch is from 10 A.M to 2 P.M., with dishes from $5 to $10.</p>
        <p>A Lamb Dish, From the Bounty of a Farm</p>
        <p>Melissa Kelly's Rubbed Rack of Lamb Total time: 45 minutes, plus marinating</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons sea salt or to taste 2 teaspoons dried oregano 1 teaspoon dried rosemary 1 tablespoon caraway seeds 1 teaspoon cumin seeds 1/2 teaspoon ground turmeric 2 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil 1 tablespoon roasted garlic (about 2 large roasted cloves, mashed; 1/2 tablespoon garlic paste may be substituted) 2 tablespoons prepared harissa (North African hot sauce, sold at fancy-food shops or shops that sell Middle Eastern foods) or tomato paste seasoned with ground red pepper 2 racks of lamb, frenched.</p>
        <p>1. Combine the salt, oregano, rosemary, caraway, cumin and turmeric in a mortar, spice grinder or blender, and process until fairly well ground. Transfer to a small dish, and work in 1 1/2 tablespoons of the olive oil, plus the garlic and the harissa or tomato paste mixture. Rub the lamb with the mixture, and set aside to marinate at room temperature, at least 3 hours.</p>
        <p>2. Preheat oven to 450 degrees.</p>
        <p>3. Shortly before serving, heat a heavy ovenproof saute pan on top of the stove and brush with remaining olive oil. Add the lamb, and sear for a couple of minutes on each side. Turn the lamb so it sits bone side up, and place the pan with the lamb in the oven for about 15 minutes, or until a meat thermometer registers 125 degrees for medium-rare. Carve each rack into four double chops.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 580 calories, 35 grams fat, 195 milligrams cholesterol, 985 milligrams sodium, 60 grams protein, 4 grams carbohydrate.</p>
        <p>Melissa Kelly's Chocolate Hazelnut Torte</p>
        <p>Total time: 1 hour, 15 minutes</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon unsalted butter 6 ounces hazelnuts, toasted, skinned and chopped 6 ounces bittersweet chocolate, chopped fine Zest of 1 lemon Zest of 1 orange 6 large eggs, separated 1/2 cup granulated sugar Ice cream.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Line the bottom of an 8-inch round cake pan with parchment paper, and lightly butter it.</p>
        <p>2. Combine hazelnuts, chocolate, lemon zest and orange zest in a food processor. Pulse until finely ground.</p>
        <p>3. Combine egg yolks and 1/4 cup sugar in an electric mixer. Whisk on high speed for about 3 minutes, until light and creamy. Turn speed to low, and mix in the ground hazelnut-chocolate mixture.</p>
        <p>4. Place egg whites in a clean bowl, and whip at medium speed until frothy. Increase to high speed, and whip until softly peaked. Continue to whip, gradually adding remaining sugar, until stiff.</p>
        <p>5. Fold a third of the beaten egg whites into the batter, and when they are almost completely incorporated, fold in the rest.</p>
        <p>6. Spread in prepared pan, and bake for about 35 minutes, until a cake tester comes out clean. Cool briefly on a rack. The cake will drop somewhat as it cools. Remove the cake from the pan, and invert it. Peel off the paper. Serve while still warm, with ice cream.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 510 calories, 35 grams fat, 205 milligrams cholesterol, 90 milligrams sodium, 11 grams protein, 45 grams carbohydrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
