<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Fishkill, a New Team Steps Up to the Plate; Minor-League Club Excites Baseball Fans in the Economically Ailing Hudson Valley</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="666721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINOR LEAGUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FISHKILL (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HUDSON VALLEY RENEGADES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ERIE SAILORS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISMAN, SKIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBERG, JACQUES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DA1E39F936A35751C0A962958260" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Fishkill, a New Team Steps Up to the Plate; Minor-League Club Excites Baseball Fans in the Economically Ailing Hudson Valley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINBERG, JACQUES</byline>
      <dateline>FISHKILL, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It may be buried under 16 inches of snow and studded with evergreen, pine and birch trees, but when Skip Weisman drives past the 20-acre field wedged between Route 9D and Interstate 84, he sees baseball.</p>
        <p>"The lights are on and a game is going on," Mr. Weisman says, conjuring the daydream he has each night as he heads home from work. "The scoreboard's lit up. There's a packed house. There's green grass. There's brown dirt."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It may be buried under 16 inches of snow and studded with evergreen, pine and birch trees, but when Skip Weisman drives past the 20-acre field wedged between Route 9D and Interstate 84, he sees baseball.</p>
        <p>"The lights are on and a game is going on," Mr. Weisman says, conjuring the daydream he has each night as he heads home from work. "The scoreboard's lit up. There's a packed house. There's green grass. There's brown dirt."</p>
        <p>Mr. Weisman is not the only one with such visions these days. Ever since his minor-league baseball franchise, the Erie Sailors, announced in late November that it was leaving Pennsylvania for this Dutchess County town, the economically ailing Hudson Valley has found itself cheered by a refreshing case of baseball fever. The Renegades</p>
        <p>When Mr. Weisman, the team's general manager and part owner, asked residents of the area to suggest a name for the franchise, more than 5,000 entries streamed in. Late Friday, the team announced that it would call itself the Hudson Valley Renegades.</p>
        <p>Already, more than 400 individuals, families and businesses have bought season tickets to the team's 38 home games, at $225 a seat. The Class A team, affiliated with the Texas Rangers, is expected to open its 76-game season in mid-June in a 4,000-seat ball park now under construction. The season ends Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>The appeal of the national pastime in one of its purest incarnations, free of million-dollar salaries and matching egos, has fueled much of the excitement. So has talk that the team could contribute upward of $1 million a year to the slumping local economy, what with the souvenir caps and T-shirts it would sell, and the services, like printing and hotel rooms, that it would purchase.</p>
        <p>But this is also the heart of I.B.M. country, and people here say that baseball is just the ticket to lift their spirits after the computer manufacturer's retrenchment, which saw thousands of Hudson Valley residents lose their jobs last year at the company's three nearby factories.</p>
        <p>"I don't know about anyone else, but I'm planning my summer vacation around the season," said Marsha Rozales Gordon, the president of the Greater Southern Dutchess Chamber of Commerce, which is raising private donations to pay for part of the $4.95 million stadium. "Someone invited me to a wedding on June 24 and my first thought was, 'I hope there's not a game that night.' "</p>
        <p>Jaime Giannetta, a 28-year-old lawyer from Wappingers Falls, about 10 miles north of here, said she bought two season tickets, one for herself and the other to be shared with her father and assorted friends.</p>
        <p>"I think the feeling is that we've got something else to do in the Hudson Valley, something that's ours," said Ms. Giannetta, who works for the Legal Aid Society in Putnam County. "I guess it's the way people in the Bronx feel, like they have the Yankees. It's such a morale boost."</p>
        <p>Until Friday the hottest game in town -- other than wondering how the team will fare against such New York-Penn League opponents as the Pittsfield (Mass). Mets and the Burlington (Vt.) Expos -- had been guessing what the team would be called.</p>
        <p>After scanning the reams of entries to the "Name the Team" contest, Mr. Weisman put all speculation to rest and announced that the team had settled on the name Renegades, bypassing three other top submissions: the Hudson Valley Vipers, the Hudson Valley Venom and the Hudson Valley Hawks. One idea that was rejected out of hand was the Jailbirds, an allusion to the nearby Fishkill Correctional Facility.</p>
        <p>"The nickname Renegade conveys a strong sense of the unconventional," Mr. Weisman said in a statement, "the team that will hit and run or steal third when it is least expected, and take the opponent out of its own game plan."</p>
        <p>He added, "It flows nicely with the geographic name of the Hudson Valley."</p>
        <p>The woman who suggested the winning name, Yvette Cruz, 31, of Gardiner, N.Y., will receive two free box seats for the season and be the guest of honor on opening day, Mr. Weisman said.</p>
        <p>The Renegades will join two other new teams in the New York region, the Trenton Thunder, an affiliate of the Detroit Tigers, and the New Haven Ravens, a farm club of the Colorado Rockies. Both will be in the AA Eastern League, a step up from the Hudson Valley team's league. Financing Is Questioned</p>
        <p>The key to bringing the team to Fishkill, after the owners were unable to reach agreement with Erie officials on a lease for a proposed new stadium, was a 27-8 vote by the Dutchess County Board of Legislators last month to lend $2.5 million to the private company that will build the ball park here.</p>
        <p>But that deal has not set well with everyone, particularly Woody Klose, a County Legislator who voted against it. Mr. Klose said he was concerned that the company formed to build the park, the Dutchess County Entertainment Corporation, planned to pay back much of the loan with private contributions and a grant of more than $2 million from the State Urban Development Corporation that it has not yet been awarded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klose said he doubted that the stadium builders would be able to reach their goal of collecting more than $1 million in donations from corporations and individuals to house a team three notches below the major leagues.</p>
        <p>"It is one step above college ball," Mr. Klose said. "You're not going to see Dwight Gooden. You're not going to see Mickey Mantle. You're not going to see Joe DiMaggio."</p>
        <p>Supporters of the team brand Mr. Klose a killjoy. They say they are eager to get a front-row glimpse of the baseball stars of tomorrow, some of whom may be in the major leagues within three years.</p>
        <p>The Texas Rangers will determine the roster of team players about four days before opening day, Mr. Weisman said. The players, who will be paid $850 a month, will be drawn from other Ranger farm teams and from a draft of college players.</p>
        <p>Local officials say they are confident that the team's spending, on everything from automobiles to apartments for players to hotel rooms for visiting umpires, will help the economy.</p>
        <p>"I went to my local physical therapist and he asked me if they are interested in a team doctor," said Jack Dexter, 62, a one-time prospect of the Cleveland Indians who is president of the Dutchess County Old-Timers' Baseball Association, a hall of fame. "My local optometrist was saying that if a player strikes out 18 times in a row, maybe his eyes are bad and he can help out." 'Solid and Optimistic'</p>
        <p>But the team's most important contribution, its fans say, may be helping the Hudson Valley redefine itself as something more than I.B.M.'s backyard, particularly when the relationship between the computer giant and its neighbors has frayed.</p>
        <p>"Nothing is more solid and optimistic than, what do they call it, the boys of summer," said Roger Akeley, the Dutchess County Commissioner of Planning and Development.</p>
        <p>Captivated by that optimism, Matt Schlossberg, who runs a magazine distributorship in Poughkeepsie, was first in line to buy season tickets when sales began earlier this year. He bought four: for himself; his wife, Marcia; his 15-year-old son, Josh, and his 12-year-old daughter, Rachel.</p>
        <p>"You've got your own team in the area now, something you can root for," he said. "Without getting corny about the whole thing, I just enjoy being around baseball."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
