<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.A.A.C.P. Says Hughes Is Violating Diversity Rules</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="626276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIRING AND PROMOTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HUGHES AIRCRAFT CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ASSN FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF COLORED PEOPLE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAW, VANCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMS, CALVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DA143CF937A3575BC0A965958260" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.A.A.C.P. Says Hughes Is Violating Diversity Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMS, CALVIN</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People is accusing the Hughes Aircraft Company of violating Federal guidelines that require Government contractors to diversify their work forces and managements.</p>
        <p>Officials of the civil rights group said they would present evidence at a news conference in Washington on Wednesday that Hughes, which employs 55,000 people, has only two black vice presidents and that blacks are grossly underrepresented in its work force.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People is accusing the Hughes Aircraft Company of violating Federal guidelines that require Government contractors to diversify their work forces and managements.</p>
        <p>Officials of the civil rights group said they would present evidence at a news conference in Washington on Wednesday that Hughes, which employs 55,000 people, has only two black vice presidents and that blacks are grossly underrepresented in its work force.</p>
        <p>The move by the N.A.A.C.P. reflects its new strategy of scrutinizing industries that do business with the Federal Government to assure that they comply with affirmative action requirements.</p>
        <p>In the case of Hughes, the N.A.A.C.P. said today that of the 1,000 people employed at the Hughes Network Systems facility in Germantown, Md., only 16 are black. The N.A.A.C.P. said that it had received numerous calls from black Hughes employees who contend that they have been discriminated against on the job.</p>
        <p>A former manager of employment, who is black, has filed a lawsuit against Hughes Network Systems, contending that he was unfairly dismissed after he complained that a recruiter had made racist remarks.</p>
        <p>Most striking, however, are the accusations by the former manager, Vance Shaw, that a Hughes vice president kicked him, with great force, in his buttocks in May 1992.</p>
        <p>"It was the most humiliating, demeaning, demasculinizing embarrassment of my life," Mr. Shaw said in a telephone interview. "The blow caused me to stagger in pain. Clearly it was racist."</p>
        <p>Responding to the charges, Hughes Aircraft, a unit of the General Motors Corporation, said that 9.1 percent of its employees are black and that 30.7 percent over all are members of minority groups. The company, based in the Los Angeles area, also said three of its 51 vice presidents are black.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Hughes said that Mr. Shaw was "accidentally kicked in jestful play" when being asked to leave a conference room that had been reserved for use by other executives. The Hughes executive who kicked Mr. Shaw was formally reprimanded by the company and apologized to Mr. Shaw, the spokesman added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shaw was dismissed because of poor performance reviews and for making derogatory remarks about the company to potential employees, the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The N.A.A.C.P.'s rebuke of Hughes underscores a new willingness by the group to denounce companies that it believes have discriminated against blacks. The N.A.A.C.P. recently announced an agreement with the Flagstar Companies, the parent of the Denny's restaurant chain, to foster black management and ownership of restaurants after accusations that black customers at Denny's were refused service.  A Hot Line for Employees</p>
        <p>W. Gregory Wims, president of the Montgomery County, Md., branch of the N.A.A.C.P. and a member of the group's Federal task force, said that starting Wednesday, it was setting up a hot line for current and former Hughes employees to voice their concerns. He added that if enough complaints were gathered, the group would consider filing a class-action suit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wims said Hughes also had a weak record in awarding subcontracts to concerns owned by blacks or other minority groups.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department's Office of Federal Contract Compliance said today that it had no evidence that Hughes Aircraft or any of its subsidiaries were in violation of Federal requirements for work force diversity.</p>
        <p>Annie A. Blackwell, director of the office's policy division, said that while it had on several occasions reviewed Hughes's hiring and promotion practices, all the cases had been closed either because there were no grounds to pursue them or because the company had agreed to make changes that would lead to greater work force diversity. She declined to discuss specific cases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
