<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.A.A. Suspends a Plan to Reroute Newark Flights</title>
    <meta content="31ROUT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newark International Airport (NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Guardia Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFD61331F932A05751C1A961958260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.A.A. Suspends a Plan to Reroute Newark Flights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Dec. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Aviation Administration agrees to suspend experiment to reroute some planes leaving Newark International Airport; decision is hailed by New Jersey groups concerned about experiment, which was intended to reduce noise in areas around Carteret, Scotch Plains and parts of Woodbridge and Rahway by shifting departure routes closer to South Plainfield; agency says it will also conduct a more thorough review of aircraft routes for all three airports in New Jersey-New York region that would be more sensitive to communities beneath flight paths (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey groups won a minor skirmish today in a 10-year-long battle with the Federal Aviation Administration over airplane noise when the agency agreed to suspend an experiment to reroute some planes leaving Newark International Airport.</p>
        <p>Resident groups, lawmakers and the Governor's office hailed the decision, saying they hoped it meant that the Aviation Administration would make noise complaints more of a priority. They also said they were encouraged that the agency would conduct a more thorough review of aircraft routes for all three airports in the New Jersey-New York region that would be more sensitive to communities beneath the flight paths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey groups won a minor skirmish today in a 10-year-long battle with the Federal Aviation Administration over airplane noise when the agency agreed to suspend an experiment to reroute some planes leaving Newark International Airport.</p>
        <p>Resident groups, lawmakers and the Governor's office hailed the decision, saying they hoped it meant that the Aviation Administration would make noise complaints more of a priority. They also said they were encouraged that the agency would conduct a more thorough review of aircraft routes for all three airports in the New Jersey-New York region that would be more sensitive to communities beneath the flight paths.</p>
        <p>Agency officials said that they did indeed plan an intensive review of the routes affecting Newark, Kennedy International and La Guardia airports, beginning in February, but that the review had been planned well before today's decision to scrap the Newark experiment. The experiment, which had been scheduled to start on Thursday, was intended to reduce noise in areas around Carteret, Scotch Plains and parts of Woodbridge and Rahway by shifting the departure routes closer to South Plainfield.</p>
        <p>Referring to the broader review of the region's air routes, Frank Hatfield, the manager of air space for the agency's New York regional office, said: ''It is an initiative that the F.A.A. has been planning for a number of years. For a number of years we have realized that you must review the system to make efficient use of new systems such as global positioning satellites.''</p>
        <p>In looking at the area's air routes, he said, the agency would take a ''white paper approach'' -- meaning that officials would start from scratch and consider a host of options.</p>
        <p>The review comes as the region's airspace has become the most congested in the world, according to a spokesman for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which operates Newark, La Guardia and Kennedy airports. Projections suggest that there will be more than 1.169 million takeoffs and landings at the three airports by the end of 1997, an increase of nearly 20,000 over last year, said the spokesman, Bill Cahill. Newark accounted for more than half of that increase.</p>
        <p>The experiment proposed for Newark would have rerouted about 25 percent of the airport's daily flights. The plan would have shifted flights from the current route, in which planes climb slowly to the southwest along the Arthur Kill to Carteret before turning west, to a more sharply westward turn well to the north, near Linden, which would have enabled them to gain altitude more quickly.</p>
        <p>The proposed change, say critics like Michael Schatzki, amounted to ''tinkering that moves the noise from one set of New Jersey towns to another set of New Jersey towns.''  Mr. Schatzki is director of New Jersey Citizens for Environmental Research, one of a number of groups that are part of the New Jersey Coalition Against Aircraft Noise.</p>
        <p>''We are looking,'' Mr. Schatzki said, ''for some real relief from the noise and want to stop playing this game of moving the noise around. We consider it a positive development that they have postponed this experiment and hope it is a sign that they will change the way they plan.''</p>
        <p>He said that safety and efficiency considerations rather than noise concerns have long dominated the F.A.A.'s planning process. That view was partly echoed by the coalition's technical consultant, Glenn Bales, a former F.A.A. airspace manager who was at the center of creating the routing system for the region that has been in place since 1987.</p>
        <p>Both he and Mr. Hatfield, who succeeded him as the region's airspace manager, said their main concerns in planning the routes were safety considerations, like creating separation between planes in the most efficient way and using a host of land-based navigational aids for pilots.</p>
        <p>It was a defensible approach, Mr. Hatfield said, because the agency's mission was to develop a safe and secure air travel system, not to abate noise. Noise and whether the air routes affected communities beneath them came much later as a concern.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Mr. Bales, working for the New Jersey groups, devised an alternative routing system that took most of the Newark departures out over New York Bay and the Atlantic Ocean, where planes could rise to 16,000 feet before turning west, south and north over land. It eliminates much of the noise problem, he said, but officials of the aviation agency feared that such a change would affect flight patterns along the Eastern Seaboard and elsewhere, and airlines feared additional fuel costs and flight delays.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hatfield said the routes devised by Mr. Bales would be considered along with other alternatives.</p>
        <p>The decision by the agency to suspend the experiment came after meetings with residents' groups over the last two days organized by Senator Robert G. Torricelli, Representatives Robert D. Franks and Rodney P. Frelinghuysen and Gov. Christine Todd Whitman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hatfield said the Aviation Administration still believed that the experimental routes would reduce noise because they pass over industrial areas, not residential ones. He said the agency had agreed to suspend the plan so community groups could evaluate it further.</p>
        <p>As part of that evaluation, the agency agreed for the first time to turn over to Mr. Bales data on the number of flights, their altitudes and speeds as they pass over central New Jersey. Such data are critical in modeling alternatives that reduce noise while maintaining safety, Mr. Schatzki said .</p>
        <p>The agency's impending review of the region's routes has also drawn attention in Queens, the site of the area's two other major airports. Daniel Andrews, a spokesman for the Queens Borough President, Claire Shulman, said borough officials had been unaware of the planned study, but he said Ms. Shulman would look into it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrews warned that certain changes to Newark Airport's routes could affect air routes into La Guardia and Kennedy. ''A global approach is welcome,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
