<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Profiting From Tax-Proof Companies</title>
    <meta content="05TAXX$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeney, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA153AF936A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Profiting From Tax-Proof Companies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SWEENEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sweeney, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investing in United States-traded stocks of companies that benefit from various tax advantages discussed; many such companies do much of their business from tax havens; table (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE'S a pleasantly rebellious thought for this tax season: After you pay the I.R.S., invest in some companies that don't have to.</p>
        <p>Just ask Harry Rosenbluth, a portfolio manager and partner at Boston Partners Asset Management in Greenbrae, Calif., about such investments. His $15 billion fund owns hefty chunks of several insurers, including Exel Insurance, Terra Nova, Partners Reinsurance and Ace Ltd. These enterprises are innovative, well managed and have not been faced with payouts for heavy losses in several years. But those facts only partly explain why they had average returns of 63.9 percent for the 12 months ended March 31, compared with 45.5 percent for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE'S a pleasantly rebellious thought for this tax season: After you pay the I.R.S., invest in some companies that don't have to.</p>
        <p>Just ask Harry Rosenbluth, a portfolio manager and partner at Boston Partners Asset Management in Greenbrae, Calif., about such investments. His $15 billion fund owns hefty chunks of several insurers, including Exel Insurance, Terra Nova, Partners Reinsurance and Ace Ltd. These enterprises are innovative, well managed and have not been faced with payouts for heavy losses in several years. But those facts only partly explain why they had average returns of 63.9 percent for the 12 months ended March 31, compared with 45.5 percent for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>Another reason is that these companies are based in Bermuda, which imposes no income taxes. ''There is a real advantage to the investor,'' Mr. Rosenbluth said of the stocks, all of which trade in the United States. Freedom from taxes, he said, ''permits the compounding of earnings much faster.''</p>
        <p>Consider Exel, the 14th-largest insurer in the North American property and casualty market. The company, which provides liability insurance for corporations, paid only $5 million in income taxes worldwide last year on $677 million in pretax income, while many of its competitors in the United States paid an average tax rate of 40 percent. (Most accounting experts use that admittedly imprecise number as an average American corporate tax rate, adding state and local taxes of about 5 percent to the 35 percent Federal rate.)</p>
        <p>Gavin R. Arton, senior vice president of Exel, said this tax freedom means more than just extra income. ''If we get into a competitive situation,'' he said, ''we can lower our pricing structure by 40 percent.''</p>
        <p>Exel and other companies that pay little or no income tax get an advantage in their investments, too. They can keep all the earnings they get, say, on a 7 percent taxable bond, while their competitors must either pay tax on those earnings or opt for the lower dividends they would receive from a tax-exempt investment.</p>
        <p>Bermuda-based insurers are not the only companies traded in the United States that benefit from these various tax advantages. Cruise, construction, engineering and oil-exploration companies do so, too. And although the strategy is most practical and lucrative for companies, like these, with much non-American business, many other corporations use this tactic to at least some extent. For example, multinationals from a variety of industries have regional headquarters in countries like Ireland or Luxembourg in order to minimize their European taxes.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the advantages can be great. The Carnival Corporation, a cruise company with headquarters in Miami, is incorporated in Panama, which imposes no income tax on businesses. In fiscal 1997, Carnival had pretax income of about $672 million, yet it managed to pay just a bit more than $6 million in taxes. (Those taxes were due on work the company did in the United States; even if incorporated in a no-tax nation, an enterprise must often pay tax on business it conducts in other countries.) Carnival's bill amounts to a tax rate of less than 1 percent -- a far cry from the $269 million tax bill that a 40 percent rate would bring.</p>
        <p>For other companies, the tax rate is higher, but the savings are still huge. Consider  Schlumberger Ltd., the largest oilfield-services company and one of several in the field that employ tax havens.</p>
        <p>Incorporated in the Netherlands Antilles, Schlumberger racked up about $1.67 billion in pretax income last year yet paid just $373 million in taxes. ''Schlumberger pays taxes in the low 20 percent range while its competitors, like Halliburton and Baker Hughes, pay taxes in the mid-30 percent range,'' said Jeffrey Freedman, an oilfield-services analyst at Prudential Securities. ''So it clearly has an advantage in attaining earnings per share. And you have to say that the lower tax rate pushes up the stock price.''</p>
        <p>Of course, this tax benefit is only one reason that Schlumberger's stock trades at 28.9 times its earnings per share, one of the loftiest ratios in the oilfield-services industry. ''Schlumberger has the most technically sophisticated product lines, such as its formation-evaluation technology, which is among the most profitable in the industry,''  Mr. Freedman said. ''That is why it has been dominant.''</p>
        <p>The tax advantage is blunted in fields like the cruise industry, where most or many enterprises get similar breaks. While Carnival paid less than 1 percent in taxes, for example, one of its main rivals did even better. Royal Caribbean Cruises, which is incorporated in tax-free Liberia, paid no  taxes last year on profits of $175 million.</p>
        <p>NEVERTHELESS, many analysts agree with Mr. Freedman that tax advantages, while not the most important factor in stock evaluation, can enhance a company's attractiveness. Thomas Driscoll, a research analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, played down the advantage of low taxes for Triton Energy, an oil-exploration company that is based in Dallas but incorporated in the Cayman Islands. But when Triton's Thailand operations begin to produce oil, ''the tax savings will be huge,'' Mr. Driscoll acknowledged, adding, ''I suspect that the buy rating I have on the stock would not be as aggressive if they had to pay taxes at the U.S. rate.''</p>
        <p>Of course, some people see red when they look at tax-haven companies. ''This is ridiculous,'' fumed Marc Perkins, chairman of Perkins Capital Advisers in Delray Beach, Fla., speaking about the tax status of Carnival, for which Micky Arison serves as chairman. ''I don't like people like Micky Arison dipping in my pocket. He already has better basketball seats than I do, since he owns the Miami Heat.'' Even so, Mr. Perkins does not blame Mr. Arison. ''It's the guys in Washington who are letting him get away with this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At least while you labor over Form 1040, Carnival may seem pretty smart.</p>
        <p>INVESTING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
