<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES THIS WEEK</title>
    <meta content="CRTC04$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7D7173BF936A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES THIS WEEK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Howard Thompson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR literary adaptations lend luster to the lineup of films on television this week.</p>
        <p>Nunnally Johnson's MAN IN THE GRAY FLANNEL SUIT (1956), from Sloan Wilson's best-selling novel, crisply depicts a Manhattan executive worn down by commuting and office intrigue and confused by a wartime affair that has resurfaced. The fine cast is headed by Gregory Peck, Jennifer Jones, Fredric March, Lee J. Cobb, Ann Harding and Marisa Pavan. The story moves so surely and skillfully that it provides as much insight as entertainment -- Saturday at 9 P.M. on Channels 13 and 49.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR literary adaptations lend luster to the lineup of films on television this week.</p>
        <p>Nunnally Johnson's MAN IN THE GRAY FLANNEL SUIT (1956), from Sloan Wilson's best-selling novel, crisply depicts a Manhattan executive worn down by commuting and office intrigue and confused by a wartime affair that has resurfaced. The fine cast is headed by Gregory Peck, Jennifer Jones, Fredric March, Lee J. Cobb, Ann Harding and Marisa Pavan. The story moves so surely and skillfully that it provides as much insight as entertainment -- Saturday at 9 P.M. on Channels 13 and 49.</p>
        <p>The quietly chilling SPIRAL STAIRCASE (1946) is an excellent thriller adapted from Ethel Lina White's story of a mute servant (Dorothy McGuire) stalked by a village maniac. Ethel Barrymore, George Brent and Kent Smith round out the able cast, under Robert Siodmak's tingling direction. One huge close-up of a watchful eye will go through you like a knife -- Tuesday at 4:30 P.M. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Adapted from a play by Somerset Maugham, THE LETTER (1940) has superb components, from William Wyler's atmospheric opening to a superlative, restrained performance by Bette Davis as a Singapore planter's adulterous wife on trial for murder. Herbert Marshall is well cast as an embittered cuckold. James Stephenson and Gale Sondergaard shine in key roles. The stunning black-and-white photography is matched by Max Steiner's striking musical score. This is gorgeously adult, dramatic film fare for television -- Sunday at 10 P.M. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Watching the great Greta Garbo contemplate suicide to end her misery as an outcast wife in old Moscow is a sight to behold in this version of Leo Tolstoy's classic ANNA KARENINA (1935). Directed by Clarence Brown, this gripping drama also spotlights Fredric March as her soldier-lover, Basil Rathbone as her icy husband and young Freddie Bartholomew as her son. The solid supporting cast includes Maureen O'Sullivan, Constance Collier and Mae Robson -- Monday/Early Tuesday at 1:15 A.M. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Howard Thompson</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
