<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taming the Wild Adolescent</title>
    <meta content="05ENDPAPT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="98" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewin, Tamar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D6133BF936A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taming the Wild Adolescent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tamar Lewin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewin, Tamar</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tamer Lewin article on dealing with adolescents; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When my kids were little, I would leave work each night thinking about the lyrical moment -- in Hollywood they'd shoot it in slow motion -- when I'd open the door and yell hello, and the kids' faces would light up, and they would run into my arms.</p>
        <p>Everyone knows how much little kids want and need their moms: experts from Freud to Penelope Leach have ham- mered home the central role mothers play in their children's development. There's the formal blessing for maternity leave. And there are those little arms pulling you back when you leave and reaching out when you come home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When my kids were little, I would leave work each night thinking about the lyrical moment -- in Hollywood they'd shoot it in slow motion -- when I'd open the door and yell hello, and the kids' faces would light up, and they would run into my arms.</p>
        <p>Everyone knows how much little kids want and need their moms: experts from Freud to Penelope Leach have ham- mered home the central role mothers play in their children's development. There's the formal blessing for maternity leave. And there are those little arms pulling you back when you leave and reaching out when you come home.</p>
        <p>But I never felt it was much of a stretch to have a job and babies, mostly because I was pretty sure that whoever was making Play-Doh pizzas with the kids while I was at work was warm and loving and fun, and that those relationships were valuable. I never felt the kids were being cheated. And I never felt out of touch with them: we had hours of before-bed songs and early-morning cuddles and silly hanging out.</p>
        <p>But then the kids got older. And older kids are different. They don't run to you when you walk in the door. You're lucky if they look up from what they're doing. They've got friends and homework and the new Chumbawamba CD, and talking with Mom is not real high on the agenda.</p>
        <p>So it's much, much harder to know what's up with them. Walk into your big kids' rooms, and they're not apt to want to hang out with you -- or tell you their innermost feelings -- just because it's a convenient time for you. They're apt to clam up. And if you push it, they'll probably tell you to butt out of their lives. Which you may be tempted to do. Especially when you notice that the child who mostly impersonates a bored lump when you're around becomes the charmer you used to know when other kids appear.</p>
        <p>But as a mother of older kids advised, ''The main thing I've learned is that just at the moment that you start to think you can leave them alone and go off on that trip, that's the moment you can't.'' Kids need you a lot in those prickly years when they are struggling to sort out what's cool, what's you, what's their friends and what's really them. They hear what you say, kind of. They watch what you do, for sure. And they need to know you're watching out for them.</p>
        <p>True, teen-agers need to push off into their own independent lives. But they need someone to push against. And for that, even the most fabulous baby sitter isn't good enough. No matter how well the Play-Doh years handed off, you can't delegate the parenting of an older kid.</p>
        <p>While a 2-year-old is a 2-year-old, there's no telling who a 12-year-old will be at any given moment. The child who just seceded from all family connections, declaring complete independence -- the ''Get off my back, it's my life, and I'll manage it myself'' speech -- will turn around, stricken, and ask, ''Aren't you going to make my sandwich?''</p>
        <p>But if adolescents' development is filled with conflicting impulses, so is their parents': the first time I ran into my son on Broadway, my shocked impulse was to grab him and take him home. But by the time he was in grabbing range, I realized that he was comfortable out there on his own and old enough so that passers-by would think, ''What a great-looking kid,'' and not, ''Where is that child's mother?''</p>
        <p>I still regress into mom-of-a-little-kid sometimes. I reach down to tie a shoe. Or get surprised when they pack their own bathing suits. (Or ask, ''Did you dance with a lot of people tonight?'' And am told, ''Do you really need to know?'')</p>
        <p>It's hard to get used to their independence. Especially since you can't help but be aware of the perils they face, how little you can protect them -- and how they keep their problems so much of a mystery. The saying goes, ''Little children, little problems; big children, big problems.'' And the mother who was on the case for her toddler's hitting problem might not even spot her teen-ager's drinking problem.</p>
        <p>I've seen women who sailed through the early years, juggling careers and little kids with zest, stopped short when adolescence hit and a child seemed to be slowly drifting out to sea, losing the hang of school or friends. One mother who worked like a fiend and never considered taking more than four weeks' maternity leave faltered when her daughter declared herself stupid, stopped doing her homework and started hanging out with the worst possible people. The mom walked around in a cloud of misery for almost a year and finally wangled six months off to help her daughter back on track. It worked.</p>
        <p>With big kids, the little daily crises don't get solved, or even reported, in the phone-call checking-in after school. But they may, just possibly, if you happen to be there when the kid walks in looking like a thundercloud. It's like taming a wild animal: you have to go slowly, speak softly and avoid sudden questions.</p>
        <p>There's a whole literature out there, a growing and passionate one, of new moms agonizing over balancing work and kids, dithering about how important it is to be there for the first play date with Amanda or the shot at the doctor's. But whether you're on the scene full time or part time, you're the one setting things up with Amanda's mom and choosing the pediatrician.</p>
        <p>The real dither comes later, when the choices are your child's, not yours, and there isn't much time left to help them learn to make good ones.</p>
        <p>So you open the door and yell hello and wish you knew the best way to find them now that they don't come running.  Tamar Lewin is a national correspondent for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tamar Lewin is a national correspondent for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
