<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="05QNA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DC103BF936A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE MacNEILLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Visiting Diana's Burial Site</p>
        <p>Q. Is there still time to get tickets to Althorp Park, the family home of Diana, Princess of Wales? -- Martha Trindem, Albany</p>
        <p>A. If you act quickly, you may be able to buy tickets to the estate, which will be open from July 1, the late Princess's birthday, until Aug.  30, the day before the first anniversary of her death at age 36 in an automobile accident in Paris. Admission has been limited to 2,500 people a day; as of late March, about 8,000 tickets were left. A spokeswoman for the Althorp estate estimated that tickets would be sold out by the end of May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Visiting Diana's Burial Site</p>
        <p>Q. Is there still time to get tickets to Althorp Park, the family home of Diana, Princess of Wales? -- Martha Trindem, Albany</p>
        <p>A. If you act quickly, you may be able to buy tickets to the estate, which will be open from July 1, the late Princess's birthday, until Aug.  30, the day before the first anniversary of her death at age 36 in an automobile accident in Paris. Admission has been limited to 2,500 people a day; as of late March, about 8,000 tickets were left. A spokeswoman for the Althorp estate estimated that tickets would be sold out by the end of May.</p>
        <p>The 8,500-acre Althorp Park, on the outskirts of the tiny village of Great Brington, 70 miles north of London, was the Spencers' ancestral home where Diana spent many of her teenage years. Visitors will be able to tour several of the 122 rooms in the 16th-century Althorp House,  which has on view works by Van Dyck, Gainsborough and Sir Joshua Reynolds. They can also roam through the landscaped garden leading to the Arboretum, where a collection of rare trees has been planted, some by Diana and her sons. Visitors will not have access to the island where the Princess is buried but can  view the memorial across the small ornamental lake known as Round Oval.</p>
        <p>A restored 18th-century temple at the lake's edge will be dedicated to Diana's memory, and that is where visitors can place floral tributes.</p>
        <p>Work has also begun on a museum, which will be housed within the estate's 12,000-square-foot stone stable block. It is expected to be completed by July. The Spencer family tiara, worn by the Princess on many state occasions, will be on display, as will be childhood film footage taken by Diana's father, the late Lord Spencer. Details of most of the other exhibits have yet to be released, though it is expected that Diana's wedding dress will be on view. A cafe that can accommodate 300 people and a shop will be included in the building.</p>
        <p>Applications for tickets can be made by calling (44-1604) 592020. Admission is about $16.50 (calculated at the rate of 58 pence to $1) for adults, $13 for those 65 and older and $8.50 for children.</p>
        <p>Details of a joint rail and coach service from London will be issued with tickets.</p>
        <p>Yucatan's Wild Coast</p>
        <p>Q. My wife and I would like to visit the Boca Paila peninsula in Mexico next winter. Can you suggest some moderately priced places to stay on or near the peninsula that are not fishing camps? -- Samuel L. Calder, Cincinnati</p>
        <p>A. The 22-mile long Boca Paila peninsula, just south of Tulum on Mexico's Caribbean coast, is one of the least developed stretches of coast on the entire Yucatan Peninsula. Part of the 1.3 million-acre Sian Ka'an Biosphere, Boca Paila is known for remote beaches, thick jungles, isolated coves, wildlife -- including jaguars, crocodiles and hundreds of species of birds -- and fishing (the waters here are the richest source of lobsters in Mexico).</p>
        <p>Most of the tourists who come here are, indeed, interested in fishing, and as you infer, there are a number of camps -- many of them quite expensive -- that are used by tour companies from the United States and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>There are also other accommodations -- quite modest in comparison to those in Cancun, Cozumel and other resorts to the north. Many of them can only be booked by mail, which can be a lengthy process -- sometimes it can take a month or more for a letter to reach this area.</p>
        <p>In the tiny seaside Maya village of Punta Allen, 35 miles south of Tulum, at the tip of the Boca Paila peninsula, several local entrepreneurs have opened small seasonal hotels and restuarants. At The Cuzan Guest House, which has a dozen or so cabanas with mosquito-netted beds and communal bathrooms, rates do not exceed $50 during the October to April high season. For reservations: write to Cuzan Guest House, Punta Allen, Postal 24, Felipe Carrillo Puerto, Quintana Roo, Mexico, 77200.</p>
        <p>Between Tulum and the northern border of Boca Paila there are a series of small hotels and guest houses. El Paraiso, which is off Highway 307 (just beyond the Tulum turnoff, take the road marked ''Punta Allen''), has 10 clean cabanas for about $40 a night, each with private bath, hot water and two double beds. Write El Paraiso, Postal 61, Tulum, telephone (52-987) 1-21-42.</p>
        <p>Three Gorges Tours</p>
        <p>Q. Can you provide names of tour companies with fall itineraries in China that include major sites, plus a Yangtze River cruise? Given the construction of the dam, we would like to see the Three Gorges before it is too late. -- Lynda S. Henderson, Memphis</p>
        <p>A. Many companies are feverishly pitching tours that include the Three Gorges area, for, if all goes according to plan, the ambitious and highly controversial Three Gorges Dam project will be completed by 2009. Four years before that, however, a 400-mile-long reservoir will submerge much of the stunning scenery and archeological riches of the Three Gorges. The dam, which will provide power to rural Chinese provinces and facilitate flood management and shipping, is the largest hydroelectric project in the world, forcing the relocation of more than a million people.</p>
        <p>Among the companies offering tours is Overseas Adventure Travel, which has a 17-day tour of Imperial China, Tibet and the Yangtze. Beijing's Forbidden City, the Summer Palace, Xian, Lhasa, Chengdu and a three-day cruise down the Yangtze in a 287-foot river vessel, are among the highlights of the itinerary. Departures are Aug. 20 and 27, Oct. 22 and 29 and Nov. 5 and 12. Fares start at $4,190, and include air fare from Los Angeles, local transportation, accommodations and most meals. Information: (800) 955-1925 or (800) 873-6528.</p>
        <p>IST Cultural Tours, based in New York, has an 18-day tour departing Sept. 26 and Oct. 24, that includes visits to Beijing, Zhengzhou, Xian, Dengfeng and Shanghai. A four-day cruise along the Yangtze goes through the five-mile long Qutang  Gorge with its 4,000-foot limestone peaks, the Wu Gorge and the Xiling Gorge, made up of seven smaller gorges; offshore excursions include a visit to the 2,000-year-old Zhangua Temple. Fares are $4,995, including  air fare from the United States, accommodations, domestic flights and most meals. Information: (212) 563-1202 or (800) 833-2111, or fax (212) 594-6953.</p>
        <p>SUZANNE MacNEILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
