<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Seeks Normalcy In Troubled Times; A Disrupted Premiere Week Dawns With Comedy and Familiarity Favored</title>
    <meta content="24SEAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/24/arts/television/24SEAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1327778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D9173AF937A1575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Seeks Normalcy In Troubled Times; A Disrupted Premiere Week Dawns With Comedy and Familiarity Favored</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Disrupted Premiere Week Dawns With Comedy and Familiarity Favored</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Opening of television season, disrupted by terrorist attacks, is set to begin quietly, amid uncertainty about how and whether to try to amuse and entertain wounded nation; unlikely reversal of tastes may be taking place that could revive situation comedies and test appeal of reality shows; viewers are expected to seek out shows they have known longest and liked best; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The television season finally arrives tonight, tiptoeing in as carefully as it can, still not sure if it is appropriate to try to amuse and entertain a wounded country.</p>
        <p>The attacks on New York and Washington have clearly made the question of what kind of television show is going to work seem both inconsequential and harder than ever to answer. Still, starting tonight, the networks will go back to trying to figure it all out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The television season finally arrives, still not sure if it is appropriate to try to amuse and entertain a wounded country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The television season finally arrives tonight, tiptoeing in as carefully as it can, still not sure if it is appropriate to try to amuse and entertain a wounded country.</p>
        <p>The attacks on New York and Washington have clearly made the question of what kind of television show is going to work seem both inconsequential and harder than ever to answer. Still, starting tonight, the networks will go back to trying to figure it all out.</p>
        <p>A few signs suggest that an unlikely reversal of tastes may be taking place, with situation comedies, thought to be fading if not already passé, reviving, and reality shows, the phenomenon of the past two years, suddenly facing a test of how enduring they are. As for the heavy-hitting dramas that have held up the late hours of weekday nights, they may have to tread more gently.</p>
        <p>The best guess in many places is that, at least initially, most viewers will seek out the shows they have known longest and liked best.</p>
        <p>But less than two weeks after millions watched events they never wanted to see, no one knows what anyone wants to watch on television.</p>
        <p>''I frankly have no idea what to expect,'' said Leslie Moonves, the president of CBS Television. ''To be honest with you, I've been finding it very hard to concentrate.''</p>
        <p>In a normal year ''premiere week'' is accompanied by the roar of entertainment engines, ready to be unleashed all at once like the start of the Indy 500. This season the roar has been turned down to a dim hum, the promotion and the planning that filled the summer almost completely tossed away. If viewers once had a sense of what new shows were coming this season and which ones intrigued them -- ''Scrubs'' on NBC? ''Undeclared'' on Fox? ''Bob Patterson'' on ABC? -- they are likely to have lost it by now.</p>
        <p>And, as one senior entertainment executive put it, ''It's awfully hard to plan when nobody knows when the other shoe will drop.'' A retaliatory strike by the United States would surely mean a return to nonstop news coverage and further disruption of prime-time shows.</p>
        <p>Yet amid the confusion network executives say they have spotted indications that the public is ready to greet a new season with a combination of relief and real enthusiasm. ''I do think people are craving to see some entertainment,'' Mr. Moonves said.</p>
        <p>They certainly seem to have gradually gravitated away from the grim news that started on the morning of Sept. 11. David F. Poltrack, the executive vice president for research at CBS, noted that about 77 million viewers watched the four broadcast networks and the all-news cable channels that first Tuesday night. The number fell to 55 million on Wednesday and 53 million Thursday. On Friday it dropped to 39 million.</p>
        <p>The movie box office jumped on the Saturday night after the attacks, as did the figures for Blockbuster video rentals. Network entertainment executives interpreted all of these as signs that viewers were looking for escape.</p>
        <p>Further evidence came in the ratings for entertainment shows last week, mostly still repeats. While news programming continued to attract viewers, the numbers for entertainment reruns began to look significant. On Thursday a repeat of last season's finale of ''Friends'' performed spectacularly well, pulling in more than 17 million viewers.</p>
        <p>That result was consistent with two predictions many television executives were making about what might draw this week: comedy and familiarity.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty clear that comedies have a chance to do really well,'' said Jeff Zucker, president of NBC Entertainment. Lloyd Braun, the co-chairman for entertainment at ABC, cited his network's family comedy ''My Wife and Kids'' as something that fits the national mood: ''It's family and funny.''</p>
        <p>Established hits ought to do best because ''people are looking for a comfort level,'' Mr. Moonves said. ''That's why they turned to Dan Rather and Tom Brokaw and Peter Jennings.'' Sandy Grushow, chairman of Fox Entertainment, said, ''My gut is that people will go to the familiar.''</p>
        <p>Thus comedy shows that are emphasizing their longtime connection to viewers may be in the best position. NBC's ''Frasier,'' for example, has a one-hour premiere episode tomorrow night that brings back a whole roster of characters long associated with the show, including Bebe Neuwirth's Lilith and Shelley Long's Diane, a character that goes back almost 20 years now, to ''Cheers.''</p>
        <p>Familiarity will also be a feature of a show on ABC at the same time, ''Spin City,'' with Michael J. Fox making a return guest appearance.</p>
        <p>But most executives predicted that many of the new shows would struggle simply because of the awareness of what they are and when they are on has diminished.</p>
        <p>''All the tracking studies we do about intent-to-view were obviously suspended,'' Mr. Poltrack said. ''And we've lost all that promotional momentum. A lot of the listings are all wrong because they were set up to start last week. It's going to be totally confusing.''</p>
        <p>The Fox network was affected more than others because it controls the television rights to post-season baseball, and the major leagues postponed almost a week's worth of games. The World Series might end in November. ''It's going to be a challenge,'' Mr. Grushow said.</p>
        <p>What intrigues many executives is what may happen to the entire trend of reality television, which only weeks ago was threatening to take over much of television. Some have questioned whether the genre might be in trouble. This argument goes, How can pseudo-reality match up to the stark reality of recent weeks? ''I think you can make a case that the reality genre's success had a lot to do with the slow erosion of the newsmagazine,'' said Michael Davies, the executive producer of ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire.''</p>
        <p>The most intense scrutiny will surely surround the biggest reality hit, ''Survivor,'' when it returns to CBS in three weeks. Some have suggested that the title might sound jarring to people after hours of watching a fruitless search for real survivors at the Pentagon and the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>One senior executive from a competing network said: ''They have to be worried at CBS if the show can be as impactful as it has been. There may be people not interested in watching that kind of interpersonal pettiness anymore.''</p>
        <p>But CBS's expectation is just the opposite: as perhaps the most popular show on television the past two years, ''Survivor'' may be welcomed back. ''People love that show,'' Mr. Moonves said. ''It's escapist. That's what people want right now.''</p>
        <p>Early indications are that the reality shows are holding up. CBS got strong results for the last two episodes of ''Big Brother 2'' last week, even though they were rescheduled so many times that fans may have had no idea when they were on. And a new CBS entry, ''The Amazing Race,'' while it fell off from its opening night Sept. 5, still had the biggest audience among younger viewers of any show last Wednesday.</p>
        <p>But future reality series may have more problems. The biggest doubts surround ''The Runner'' on ABC, a show that at one time held the promise of becoming an overwhelming phenomenon on the order of ''Survivor.'' The premise -- one individual moving incognito around the country, performing tasks for money while being tracked by the whole nation -- has resonances that some may find troubling. It involves techniques like falsifying ID's and hiding in plain sight, skills that may now be associated with terrorists.</p>
        <p>The show is not scheduled to arrive until January, but it is so complicated to execute that ABC must test it in the next few weeks. Mr. Davies, who is producing it for ABC, acknowledged the concerns. ''Is January too early to try it?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Other questions surround drama shows. Three networks have shows that touch on secret agents tracking evildoers. The CBS series ''The Agency'' is overtly about the C.I.A. Its pilot episode centered on a terrorist plot to blow up Harrods in London. CBS has postponed that episode indefinitely and will substitute another when the show begins on Thursday night. ABC plans no changes for ''Alias,'' trusting that its premise -- a college-age female secret agent -- is fantasy oriented and so will not be taken too seriously.</p>
        <p>Fox has the most anticipated new show of the season in ''24,'' a story told in 24 episodes, each representing one hour of real time. It stars Kiefer Sutherland as an agent out to stop a political assassination. The big problem: the most dramatic scene of the pilot depicts a plane exploding from a terrorist bomb.</p>
        <p>''That scene is very easy to excise, and frankly, it will be excised,'' Mr. Grushow said. He noted that the show would not start until mid-November and said he was confident the plot line was different enough from real events to be safely broadcast.</p>
        <p>The show with a unique problem is NBC's ''West Wing,'' which offers up the fictional adventures of a president that cannot hope to match the real stuff going on in the White House. NBC executives initially professed confidence that their most-honored series would continue to captivate viewers.</p>
        <p>But on Friday, at the behest of the show's creator, Aaron Sorkin, NBC flinched and pulled the season premiere of ''The West Wing,'' scheduled for Wednesday. Mr. Sorkin found the problem of writing the show while avoiding any mention of what had happened in real life to be impossible. He will now incorporate some issues raised by the terrorist incidents into a special episode, a development that risks violating the show's separation between fiction and reality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker had said earlier, ''The biggest mistake we could make is to hold ourselves hostage and overthink everything.'' But thoughts of what happened in New York and Washington may prove too powerful for even Hollywood to find ways to forget completely.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
