<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plan Without A Goal In Kosovo</title>
    <meta content="28RIEF$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1049941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yugoslavia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rieff, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3D61539F93BA1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plan Without A Goal In Kosovo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Rieff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rieff, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by author David Rieff says humanitarian justification for military intervention by NATO to halt attacks by Serb security forces against Albanian nationalists in Kosovo province is unsustainable since conditions there pale by comparison to those elsewhere; says it is not clear that Clinton Administration is prepared to overthrow Pres Slobodan Milosevic or impose settlement in Kosovo, hence air strikes, far from defusing crisis, can only aggravate it terribly; says while Milosevic is to blame for crisis in Kosovo and for persecution of ethnic Albanian minority, no one in Washington or in Western Europe seems to have clear idea of what new status of Kosovo, which is part of Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, should be (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time since Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia began a brutal crackdown against the ethnic Albanians of Kosovo, there is a real chance that NATO may intervene militarily. After the United Nations Security Council passed a resolution last week demanding that Mr. Milosevic withdraw his forces, NATO commanders prepared plans for air strikes. The question is, What earthly purpose would such an action serve, however momentarily satisfying it might be?</p>
        <p>Supporters of military strikes appear to believe that there is no difference between Kosovo today and Bosnia from 1992 to 1995. This is simply false. Bosnia was an internationally recognized state with a legitimate government. Intervention there broke no principle of international law, nor did it pose serious questions about what, once the fighting was over, an independent Bosnia might look like.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time since Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia began a brutal crackdown against the ethnic Albanians of Kosovo, there is a real chance that NATO may intervene militarily. After the United Nations Security Council passed a resolution last week demanding that Mr. Milosevic withdraw his forces, NATO commanders prepared plans for air strikes. The question is, What earthly purpose would such an action serve, however momentarily satisfying it might be?</p>
        <p>Supporters of military strikes appear to believe that there is no difference between Kosovo today and Bosnia from 1992 to 1995. This is simply false. Bosnia was an internationally recognized state with a legitimate government. Intervention there broke no principle of international law, nor did it pose serious questions about what, once the fighting was over, an independent Bosnia might look like.</p>
        <p>The situation in Kosovo is entirely different. Legally, it is a province of Serbia, part of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia. And while Mr. Milosevic is almost wholly to blame for the crisis in Kosovo and for the persecution of its ethnic Albanian majority, no one in Washington or in Western Europe seems to have a clear idea of what the new status of Kosovo should be.</p>
        <p>The Security Council resolution merely calls for negotiations. But to what end, and with what result? Do the NATO powers intend their air strikes to alter the military balance so that the Kosovo Albanians can wrest their independence from Yugoslavia? Are the attacks meant to force Mr. Milosevic to grant Kosovo autonomy?</p>
        <p>Or do the strikes have the sole purpose of alleviating the humanitarian nightmare of what to do with more than 200,000 refugees?</p>
        <p>This last explanation, which is the one most often mentioned by Clinton Administration officials, aid workers and human rights activists, is actually the least persuasive of all. There is a war in Kosovo, and with it has come terrible human suffering.</p>
        <p>But as the excellent reports by the United States Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance bear out, events there pale in comparison with, say, what is taking place in southern Sudan, where many refugees are literally starving to death. And there are hundreds of thousands of refugees in Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>Unless one believes that the lives of Europeans are intrinsically more valuable than those of Africans, the humanitarian justification for military intervention is unsustainable.</p>
        <p>True, there may be political reasons for intervention. Like Saddam Hussein, President Milosevic is a genuinely evil force in the world, and his ouster would in all likelihood improve the chances for peace in the Balkans substantially. And simply preventing continued Serb attacks on the Kosovo Albanians would go some way toward preventing the crisis in the southern Balkans from spiraling out of control.</p>
        <p>The peace in Bosnia is fragile, and at any time the situation in either Macedonia or in Albania could deteriorate dramatically. The war Mr. Milosevic is waging in Kosovo can only make things worse.</p>
        <p>But it is not clear that the Clinton Administration is prepared to overthrow Mr. Milosevic or impose a settlement in Kosovo. If that is the case, a few air strikes, far from helping defuse the crisis, can only aggravate it terribly.</p>
        <p>Statesmen are supposed to propose solutions that have some chance of enduring, not make statements they have no will to back up -- as the United States has done until the last few weeks -- or undertake military operations whose goals are so ill-defined.</p>
        <p>For all the talk of humanitarian intervention, what the Administration is now considering is making war on President Milosevic's Serbia. As Clausewitz said more than 150 years ago, no leader should start a war ''without being first clear in his mind what he intends to achieve by that war and how he plans to conduct it.'' At the moment, neither question has been satisfactorily answered in Washington.</p>
        <p>David Rieff is the author of ''Slaugh-  terhouse: Bosnia and the Failure of the West.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Rieff is the author of ''Slaugh-
&lt;br&gt;terhouse: Bosnia and the Failure of the West.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
