<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hillary Clinton, Smile in Place, Hits Fund-Raisers</title>
    <meta content="Y28HIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE FIRST LADY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DD1039F93BA1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hillary Clinton, Smile in Place, Hits Fund-Raisers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton stages three-day, five-state fund raising tour for Democratic candidates for Congress; campaigns with smile, assuring old friends and political allies that she is just fine; speeches include praise of President and criticism of Congress; says country is much better off because of husband's leadership; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is she a national role model as First Lady? The President's top crisis manager determined to rescue his legacy? Or a traumatized victim deserving of America's embrace?</p>
        <p>In a three-day, five-state fund-raising tour on behalf of Democratic candidates for Congress, Hillary Rodham Clinton was analyzed and lionized, criticized and beatified on each of these points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is she a national role model as First Lady? The President's top crisis manager determined to rescue his legacy? Or a traumatized victim deserving of America's embrace?</p>
        <p>In a three-day, five-state fund-raising tour on behalf of Democratic candidates for Congress, Hillary Rodham Clinton was analyzed and lionized, criticized and beatified on each of these points.</p>
        <p>Through it all, she stayed the course, smiling opaquely and assuring old friends and political allies that she was ''Just fine!'' as she thickly larded her speeches with praise of the President and criticism of Congress.</p>
        <p>Her steadfast fans could not stop themselves from gushing.</p>
        <p>''She's kind of like our American Princess Di,'' said Lawrence Johnson, 30, a clerk at Seattle's Westin Hotel who saw Mrs. Clinton as she swept in for an evening of fund-raising on Thursday. ''They ought to leave her husband alone. And she should be our next President!''</p>
        <p>With elections just a few weeks away and concerns that the President's sex scandal may inhibit Democrats from voting, Mrs. Clinton is getting many standing ovations as she asks audiences to empty their pockets and get out the vote.</p>
        <p>And if there was any doubt that Mrs. Clinton was withholding support from her husband as she sorted out her own feelings, she dispelled it in her sweep through New York, Colorado, Washington, Oregon and California.</p>
        <p>At times she seemed to be campaigning even more for Mr. Clinton than she was for the candidates, tirelessly promoting him as the President who turned around the economy, reduced crime, furthered educational change and balanced the budget for the first time since Neil Armstrong walked on the moon.</p>
        <p>''By any objective measure, by any fair assessment, our country is so much better off because of my husband's leadership,'' she told a crowd of several hundred at a fund-raising dinner for four Congressional candidates in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Most of the candidates said little about the President, and in some cases they appeared relieved that she, not he, was around.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mrs. Clinton sits at the innermost circle of the President's crisis-management team, drafting hardball responses to the Lewinsky scandal and the Paula Jones sexual misconduct suit -- and to the Republicans who have attacked the President because of them. Mrs. Clinton's loyalists believe that she is a First Lady with a future, no matter how the Clinton Presidency weathers the impeachment debate, no matter whether the White House strategy, to which she has contributed so much, prevails.</p>
        <p>''The attraction of Mrs. Clinton is that she focuses on the issues rather than the distractions swirling around Washington, D.C.,'' said Jay Inslee, who is running for Congress in Washington State. ''The President is a distraction.''</p>
        <p>Despite the best efforts of Democratic candidates to change the subject from Mr. Clinton's woes to issues like child care, education, Social Security and the environment, the President's troubles kept intruding, often in unexpected ways.</p>
        <p>At a re-election fund-raiser for Senator Barbara Boxer in the grand ballroom of the San Francisco Hilton Hotel on Friday night, the actress, Frances Fisher, of ''Titanic'' fame read excerpts from Mrs. Clinton's best seller, ''It Takes a Village,'' telling the $250-a-plate audience of 1,100 supporters how children are ''a moral touchstone amidst the complexity and contentiousness of modern life.''</p>
        <p>But on the sidewalk outside the hotel, 8-year-old Carolyn Ahr carried a poster that she had drawn with a sad face and the words, ''The President lies and should be fired.''</p>
        <p>''Mrs. Clinton is a setback for American women,'' said Catherine Ahr, 37, a homemaker, and Carolyn's mother. ''I've never protested in my life -- and I even went to Berkeley. But this time was different. What kind of moral message does this whole thing send to our children?''</p>
        <p>In none of her child-related events did Mrs. Clinton answer that question. None of the candidates did either.</p>
        <p>At Portland State University in Oregon, Mrs. Clinton appeared in front of a big poster that read, ''Kids First'' with David Wu, a Yale-educated lawyer and candidate for Congress whose main pitch is education and who praised his guest as ''our nation's foremost children's advocate.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether there was a conflict between Mrs. Clinton's focus on children's needs and the difficulty parents are having in explaining her husband's behavior to their children, Mr. Wu said, ''I will have to think about that.''</p>
        <p>So much was said in code and fraught with double meaning on Mrs. Clinton's campaign tour that it was often hard to sort out what the real message was supposed to be.</p>
        <p>At the fund-raising dinner in Seattle, Mrs. Clinton mocked what she called ''the other Washington.''</p>
        <p>''I think that's the way to look at it,'' she said. ''It's like a parallel universe and sort of exists out there somewhere in outer space.''</p>
        <p>But she also said that the American people do not get enough political news, and throughout her trip described politics as a noble calling, exhorting her audiences to ''persuade people that politics matters.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the First Lady, Mrs. Boxer, whose daughter is married to Mrs. Clinton's brother, said flat out in her speech at the fund-raiser in San Francisco, ''The President has problems.''</p>
        <p>But she never said what they were. And she blamed the ''extraordinary atmosphere we are living in'' for making it impossible to get the media to focus on serious issues.</p>
        <p>But it was not just the media that were focusing on sex. There was also Art Torres, the chairman of the California Democratic Party, introducing Mrs. Boxer and explaining how her Republican opponent in 1992, Bruce Herschensohn, was ''the family values guy on every day except Friday nights.''</p>
        <p>''And then we found out,'' Mr. Torres continued, ''he did other things in his spare time.''</p>
        <p>The audience groaned. Some people even cursed their chairman. (In 1992 the Democrats turned up evidence that Mr. Herschensohn had frequented a nude bar in Hollywood called The Seventh Veil and bought girlie magazines.)</p>
        <p>''He didn't have to do that!'' a woman said, referring to Mr. Torres's remarks. ''This is not the time to bring this up.''</p>
        <p>As in San Francisco, there were competing demonstrators in Denver, where Mrs. Clinton campaigned on Thursday for Dottie Lamm, Colorado's former first lady who is running against Ben Nighthorse Campbell for the Senate, and Gail Schoettler, Lieutenant Governor and a candidate for governor.</p>
        <p>As Mrs. Clinton shook hands with children in front of Fort Logan Elementary School outside Denver, Ilona Smith, 41, a mental health worker, shouted, ''Hang in there, Hillary,'' as protesters down the block chanted, ''Jail Slick Willy.'' A handmade sign read, ''Lyin' King and the Queen of Denial.'' Another read, ''It Takes a Village to Raise an Idiot.''</p>
        <p>''It's a really inappropriate forum for what these people are doing,'' Ms. Smith said. ''It's rude, it's ill-mannered, it's embarrassing to Colorado. It's Hillary that's here, not Bill.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton spoke to safe, friendly audiences. She has avoided situations in which journalists could question her.</p>
        <p>She was tireless in raising money and stingy with the chitchat.</p>
        <p>In Seattle, a picture with her cost $2,500. She took a quick hello-and-thank-you approach. ''I told her we support her and the Democratic agenda,'' said Arun Bhagat, a consulting engineer. ''She thanked us for coming. Everyone was very tactful.''</p>
        <p>At a $200-a-head private reception for 200 in Denver, ''a lot of people were doing the two-handed shake, saying thank you for what you're doing for Gail and Dottie,'' said Laurie Zeller, 38. ''Nobody made reference to the current crisis.''</p>
        <p>Support is what Mrs. Clinton needs these days, said Brian Baird, a clinical psychologist who lost a Congressional race in Washington State in 1996 and is running again. ''There was something different in the applause tonight,'' Mr. Baird said of the fund-raiser in Seattle. ''There was a sort of effort to send some love Hillary's way. We want to help her during this trying time, in a healing way, to give her a respite from all this stuff.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baird, who teaches psychology and treats cancer patients and other patients, said that he thought Mrs. Clinton was ''doing well.'' But then, he added, '' 'Well' is a relative word.''</p>
        <p>THE TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE FIRST LADY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
