<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Jazz; Making the Repertory Of the Hallowed Past Into Something New</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JAZZ</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CARNEGIE HALL JAZZ BAND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATROUS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FADDIS, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDD163EF930A15753C1A965958260" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Jazz; Making the Repertory Of the Hallowed Past Into Something New</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER WATROUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WATROUS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the most part, the repertory movement in jazz has stayed within fairly limiting boundaries, reproducing as idiomatically as possible the arrangements and styles of bands of the past. That has suddenly changed. On Thursday night, the Carnegie Hall Jazz Band, led by the trumpeter Jon Faddis through a group of tunes associated with Benny Goodman, gave notice that arrangements are no longer sacrosanct. Where other repertory groups might change the emphasis in an interpretation, or open up solo space beyond the constraints of the original three-minute recording of a piece, the Carnegie Hall band radically rewrote the material.</p>
        <p>The historical and creative liberty the band took comes not a moment too soon. It happened during the second half of the show, when the band began to play some Goodman tunes newly arranged by its pianist, Jim McNeely. It started with "Air Mail Special," then moved into "Stompin' at the Savoy" and "King Porter Stomp." Each of these pieces featured odd touches, and some nice, sly dissonances that seemed to cram too many notes into too small a space; "King Porter Stomp" had two clarinets harmonizing on the melody.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the most part, the repertory movement in jazz has stayed within fairly limiting boundaries, reproducing as idiomatically as possible the arrangements and styles of bands of the past. That has suddenly changed. On Thursday night, the Carnegie Hall Jazz Band, led by the trumpeter Jon Faddis through a group of tunes associated with Benny Goodman, gave notice that arrangements are no longer sacrosanct. Where other repertory groups might change the emphasis in an interpretation, or open up solo space beyond the constraints of the original three-minute recording of a piece, the Carnegie Hall band radically rewrote the material.</p>
        <p>The historical and creative liberty the band took comes not a moment too soon. It happened during the second half of the show, when the band began to play some Goodman tunes newly arranged by its pianist, Jim McNeely. It started with "Air Mail Special," then moved into "Stompin' at the Savoy" and "King Porter Stomp." Each of these pieces featured odd touches, and some nice, sly dissonances that seemed to cram too many notes into too small a space; "King Porter Stomp" had two clarinets harmonizing on the melody.</p>
        <p>But none of this truly gave a warning of what would happen when the soprano saxophonist Dave Liebman came out to perform "Let's Dance," and then "Sing, Sing, Sing." Mr. McNeely has completely rewritten these pieces, using Gil Evans as a guide. Big, airy brass chords floated above the rhythm section. The melodies were submerged under the gauzy textures of the arrangement. And occasionally Mr. McNeely quoted a voice that might have been from the original arrangement, hard, dense harmony that contrasted with the modernism he provided.</p>
        <p>"Sing, Sing, Sing" was his masterpiece. Before intermission, the band had played the tune with Mr. Goodman's original arrangement. In Mr. McNeely's interpretation, what was once a bravura showpiece for the drummer Gene Krupa, with sharp riffs borrowed from the big-band canon, turned into a piece constructed of smudged, pensive chords. Where the original embodied a dance-hall exuberance, this was almost sullen in parts. And where the original was fairly concise, Mr. McNeely's version was sprawling, evolving into a free duet for Mr. Liebman and the band's drummer, Victor Lewis, then into an improvised call-and-response section between Mr. Liebman's screaming saxophone and the band. It was exhilarating; the repertory movement all of a sudden had new potential.</p>
        <p>The show opened with a series of small-group and big-band performances. Mr. Goodman's clarinet parts were handled by three clarinetists who brought entirely separate approaches to the instrument. Bill Easley pulled off talkative, high-speed improvisations. Walt Levinsky, all measured grace, used a gorgeous, thick tone. And Michael White, though regularly playing out of tune, had a sure rhythmic sense and a real precision with ideas. The vibraphonist Milt Jackson, on hand ostensibly to play Lionel Hampton's role in the Goodman story, instead handed in several flawless improvisations.</p>
        <p>The band, tight and precise, swung hard. But its most important accomplishment of the evening was to start an essential process: the reworking of original source material, with no sense of restraint.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
