<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hevesi, on Attack, Accuses Badillo of Smears and Lying About Giuliani Aid</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPTROLLERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEBATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, ALAN G (ASSEMBLYMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BADILLO, HERMAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE153DF930A15753C1A965958260" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hevesi, on Attack, Accuses Badillo of Smears and Lying About Giuliani Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIREYA NAVARRO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to turn the tables in the race for New York City Comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi yesterday went on the attack against Herman Badillo in a new radio commercial and in their first one-on-one debate.</p>
        <p>For days, Mr. Badillo has been running ads that accuse Mr. Hevesi of taking campaign contributions from school-bus contractors that do business with the city and from school custodians "while city schools are crumbling." But in an hourlong radio debate taped yesterday for broadcast tomorrow at 8 P.M. on WCBS-AM, it was Mr. Hevesi who went on the offensive, accusing Mr. Badillo of obfuscation in talking about Mr. Hevesi and making false claims about who is paying for Mr. Badillo's ads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trying to turn the tables in the race for New York City Comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi yesterday went on the attack against Herman Badillo in a new radio commercial and in their first one-on-one debate.</p>
        <p>For days, Mr. Badillo has been running ads that accuse Mr. Hevesi of taking campaign contributions from school-bus contractors that do business with the city and from school custodians "while city schools are crumbling." But in an hourlong radio debate taped yesterday for broadcast tomorrow at 8 P.M. on WCBS-AM, it was Mr. Hevesi who went on the offensive, accusing Mr. Badillo of obfuscation in talking about Mr. Hevesi and making false claims about who is paying for Mr. Badillo's ads.</p>
        <p>Specifically, Mr. Hevesi, a Democratic Assemblyman who is ahead in recent polls, accused Mr. Badillo of falsely claiming that his campaign is paying for advertising that was actually financed with $50,000 from the coffers of his running mate, Rudolph W. Giuliani. The Badillo campaign contends that such use of the funds meet the city's campaign-finance-board rules as long as they are paid back to the Giuliani campaign by Election Day. Mr. Giuliani and Mr. Badillo are running on the Republican-Liberal lines.</p>
        <p>Campaign finance reports released yesterday showed Mr. Badillo running extremely low on money and owing more than $50,000 to the Giuliani campaign for advertising. Commercial Claims 'Smear'</p>
        <p>On Monday, the last day of the filing period, Mr. Badillo had only $31,961 on hand in the bank and listed outstanding campaign debts of $109,000, the records show.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Hevesi also started broadcasting a new radio commercial that accuses Mr. Badillo of "smearing" him. Saying that Mr. Badillo once called former Mayor Abraham D. Beame "a malicious little man," Mayor Edward I. Koch "cowardly" and Mayor Dinkins a "sleaze," Mr. Hevesi portrays himself as the latest victim of a candidate who "has made a career of attacking people."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi's campaign manager, Hank Morris, said the ad is in response to Mr. Badillo's previous attacks.</p>
        <p>"Alan Hevesi is not a punching bag," Mr. Morris said. "It takes two people to have a positive campaign."</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the first time the two candidates appeared in a debate since they ran in the Sept. 14 Democratic primary against Elizabeth Holtzman, the incumbent. Mr. Badillo, who like Mr. Giuliani refuses to participate in debates that include other minor-party candidates, skipped a debate last week in which Mr. Hevesi sparred with Barbara S. Bollaert of the Right to Life Party and Howard Lim Jr. of the Conservative Party.</p>
        <p>Polls have consistently shown Mr. Hevesi ahead. He was the top vote-getter in the primary and won the nomination in a runoff with Ms. Holtzman. A New York 1 News poll released yesterday showed him ahead of Mr. Badillo, 46 to 34 percent, with 11 percent undecided. Badillo Plays Down Polls</p>
        <p>In an interview before the debate, Mr. Badillo, a former United States Representative, Deputy Mayor and Bronx Borough President, played down the polls, saying that in an overwhelmingly Democratic city, Mr. Hevesi should be leading by a much wider margin.</p>
        <p>"It's bad news for Mr. Hevesi because of the percentage of undecided." he said. "That means they're thinking about voting for me."</p>
        <p>During yesterday's debate, Mr. Badillo did not bring up any of the accusations he has made in his ads, stressing instead his experience in government and other qualifications for the job. The Comptroller, the city's chief fiscal monitor, makes recommendations on city spending, manages city pension funds and has the power to audit city agencies.</p>
        <p>The two candidates went over ground they had covered in their three primary debates with Ms. Holtzman, both saying they would increase the number of audits the office performs and invest pension money in a way that would create more jobs and housing. They disagreed on the issue of bond sales; Mr. Hevesi wants to use a competitive bid system for the city's bond underwriting business, while Mr. Badillo favors negotiated bond sales.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
