<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utility: A Tupperware Party for Sophisticates</title>
    <meta content="13TUPPERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="118" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tupperware (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolotin, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cousins, Morison S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DC143AF930A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utility: A Tupperware Party for Sophisticates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Susan Bolotin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bolotin, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Bolotin article on lively, colorful new generation of Tupperware; photos; Morison S Cousins, vice president of design since 1990, explains softer, more gracious containers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Tupperware lady from Bethpage, N.Y., was giving instructions to 10 people gathered in my living room. ''Say your name,'' Tina Marie Engel said. ''Then pick a word that describes yourself using the first letter of your name.''</p>
        <p>''My name is John. I'm judgmental.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Tupperware lady from Bethpage, N.Y., was giving instructions to 10 people gathered in my living room. ''Say your name,'' Tina Marie Engel said. ''Then pick a word that describes yourself using the first letter of your name.''</p>
        <p>''My name is John. I'm judgmental.''</p>
        <p>''I'm Hallie. I'm generally hysterical.''</p>
        <p>''I'm Jessica, and. . .can I use judgmental also? No? All right, then, I'll be Jewish.''</p>
        <p>This was not your average Tupperware party. Let me start with the guest list: three painters (one a professor); an artist's agent; a curator; an up-market weaver; an artist who four years ago did a project in which he used retro Tupperware pieces as molds for translucent beeswax forms; an actor (my husband, but nonetheless a man of impeccable taste); a food writer; and a single mom whose ex-husband had insisted she dress their first child in nothing but black-and-white baby clothes.</p>
        <p>I had asked these people into my home not to buy (though they did), nor to help me rack up commissions, but to assess the design of a product they all remembered but no longer knew. What had been frosted and pastel, brown and orange, is now deep yellow, blue, white. What had been familiar, utilitarian, sensible, even tacky, is surprising, contemporary, quirky -- in a word, designed. The very language of Tupperware has changed. My designer pals weren't at a Tupperware ''party'' but at a ''demonstration.'' And that exhilarating moment when one lifts the lid of a Tupperware container and lets out the pfft of air is no longer a burp. These days, it's a whisper.</p>
        <p>Morison S. Cousins is a big part of the change. When he became Tupperware's vice president of design in the United States in 1990, the products were, he says, ''functional, durable, very sensible.'' A year later, the company introduced his version of the One Touch Reminder canisters, a set of rounded containers with understated seals -- murmurs of color across the horizons of the canisters' tops. ''A hard look, he says, had become much more gracious.''</p>
        <p>Soft. Pleasant to hold. Easy. The words Cousins applies to the innovations he has wrought at Tupperware echo in his sweet manner on the phone. And he, like his work, has an effect on me. Perhaps it's his healthy ego that invigorates. Cousins likes that his designs end up in museums; he likes working for a company that thinks that sort of aspiration will lift its products above the competition. But it's his optimism that's most affecting -- his belief that the public, while caring not a whit about museum prizes, has good taste. Every piece of Tupperware he makes beautiful gives expression to that belief. And a lot of what he makes is very beautiful.</p>
        <p>Before my party, George Stoll, the artist who'd once worked with Tupperware, had explained to me why the old forms held poignancy for him. ''They were like a field of flowers. I wanted to make people stop and pay attention.'' But he had seen pictures of the new designs and wanted to like them too. He did. As the group began examining the mountains of plastic Tina Marie had laid out, George got things rolling: ''The purple Winnie the Pooh plate has real integrity -- it couldn't be produced in any other material but plastic.''</p>
        <p>The weaver disagreed: ''I like the deep blue precisely because it looks the least like plastic.''</p>
        <p>''But what's the story with that cranberry stuff?'' one of the painters wanted to know. ''The blue-and-green steamer, with that white cover and the Mickey Mouse ear handles, is very Italian, very Michael Graves. Where's the consciousness that creates both these objects?</p>
        <p>This was a tough crowd. They liked what Tupperware calls its Impressions line, a collection of undulating shapes in translucent blues and greens. But they suffered physical revulsion over a casserole that comes only in a color called Dijon. They were confounded by the decision to offer a nifty hand blender (very childlike and dangerous at the same time,'' another painter observed) only in mint green, and a handsome knife set only with dark-blue-and-white handles. ''Why don't they just make it all in white?'' they wailed, sounding, well, exactly like who they are.</p>
        <p>My party was heating up. The crowd had its favorites: measuring spoons with flat bottoms; measuring cups with rounded handles; an ice-cream scoop that means business; a garlic press; salt and pepper shakers from the Impressions line, which everyone found fun (like a 1957 DeSoto,'' the cranberry hater said) yet practical. Though only three of them own microwaves, they were drawn to Tupperware's best-selling Rock 'N Serve containers (clear bottoms, cinnamon tops, yellow vents), which are intended for winging leftovers directly from freezer to microwave. Their attraction to a product most of them couldn't use was curious but understandable. Designers admire good design -- even if they find it derivative, as they occasionally did here (Umbra, Graves, Alessi, Good Grips) -- but they love design that is both good and clever. Meaning? The piece works: neither form nor function takes precedence.</p>
        <p>So while my group admired Cousins's multi-award-winning double colander -- a T.W.A. terminal of a strainer, with a spheric bottom and Saarinen-esque top -- they didn't love it. They didn't need it for pasta draining and thought they wouldn't use it for salad drying (wouldn't water fly all over the kitchen?) or straining liquids from a pot (why not use the lid?).</p>
        <p>On the other hand, they remembered with affection Tupperware's retro lettuce crisper. O.K., it was a wee bit ugly, but that perfect removable spike that so perfectly impaled the iceberg that so perfectly fit in the crisper whose color so perfectly evoked the color of the lettuce! We were in agreement. It was. . .perfect. But how to balance their nostalgia for the old pieces with their admiration for the new -- or in some cases with their complete disbelief? People balked at Tina Marie's description of the Tupper Wave Stack Cooker, a three-tiered gizmo that allows you to cook a three-course meal in your microwave in less than 30 minutes. The food writer, much too polite to say anything, stared open-mouthed as Tina Marie (who was No. 6 in Tupperware sales in the United States this past year) described dipping chicken cutlets in salad dressing and then tossing in a package of frozen vegetables. But my guests revolted when Tina Marie brought out Modular Mates, stackable storage units that are ''the building blocks of Tupperware.'' The idea is that everything in your pantry should be decanted into an appropriately sized, ''virtually airtight'' container.</p>
        <p>''I can't tell you how compelling I find this,'' my professor of painting said. ''I look at this and think, this will improve me. But the modular system deindividualizes products and produces a singular skin for existence, something I have spent my whole life avoiding. I mean, I didn't get a nose job.'' The crowd went wild.</p>
        <p>''I love my McCann's oatmeal carton,'' one said. And what's as beautiful as a baking soda tin? another asked, nearly reducing the gang to tears. ''The question is,'' the professor concluded, ''do you want to see the detritus of your life or not?''</p>
        <p>Detritus -- and how you store it -- is what Tupperware comes down to. No matter that Lawrie Platt Hall, my public relations guide through the Land of Tupper, called to ''correct'' a comment made by Gerry Crompton, vice president of worldwide marketing, who had told me Tupperware's main competitor in the United States is Rubbermaid. Whoops! ''Our competitors are Williams-Sonoma and Crate and Barrel,'' Hall said. I wouldn't buy it, and neither would my designers. For them, the real meaning of Tupperware lies not in upscale housewares but in food storage. Really good-looking food storage.</p>
        <p>A few weeks after my party, I was doing Halloween candy triage, wondering where to put the junk. My eyes landed on the Stack Cooker. Not just one bowl, but three. Each with its own lid. Sure, the thing was in the dread cranberry color, but who cared? It worked.</p>
        <p>Frutiger -- Designed for the classifieds, the clean lines of Adrian Frutiger's 1976 face are now used for everything from airport signs to small print.</p>
        <p>Susan Bolotin is an editor and writer who lives in New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Susan Bolotin is an editor and writer who lives in New York.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
