<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good Nazi</title>
    <meta content="13WUDUNNT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nanking (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wudunn, Sheryl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rabe, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Man of Nanking, The: The Diaries of John Rabe (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D7103BF930A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good Nazi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sheryl WuDunn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wudunn, Sheryl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sheryl WuDunn reviews book The Good Man of Nanking: The Diaries of John Rabe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Good Man  of Nanking  The Diaries of John Rabe.  By John Rabe.</p>
        <p>Edited by Erwin Wickert.  Illustrated. 294 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Good Man  of Nanking  The Diaries of John Rabe.  By John Rabe.</p>
        <p>Edited by Erwin Wickert.  Illustrated. 294 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $26.</p>
        <p>Sixty-one years ago, Japanese soldiers captured the ancient Chinese capital of Nan-king, torturing, raping and killing vast numbers of people in one of the bloodiest massacres in modern history. Yet there is a stunning difference of opinion on exactly what took place. Some Japanese have tried to say -- perhaps wishfully -- that the massacre never happened, while many Chinese regard it as a symbol of Japanese brutality and one of the ugliest landmarks of an ugly century.</p>
        <p>Thus, there is a deep and divided body of literature on the Rape of Nanking, as the incident has become known, but most of that literature is, by necessity, dependent on secondary sources. That is why ''The Good Man of Nanking'' soars above most of the rest. Essentially the diaries of one man, John Rabe, a German businessman for the Siemens China Company, the work is at once riveting, inspiring, terrifying and tragically sad. It is also, in an odd way, refreshing. For Rabe is modest, unpolemical. He is, by turns, naive and cynical, generous and materialistic, outraged and calm. His account is compassionate and, at times, humorous, with an understated horror that seethes through the straightforward delivery.</p>
        <p>Rabe not only witnessed the slaughter as the Japanese captured Nanking (now known as Nanjing) in December 1937, he also saved the lives of many people. By invoking the name of Hitler, he gained tacit approval from the Japanese to set up a special safety zone that ended up sheltering a couple of hundred thousand Chinese from the rampaging Japanese soldiers. The zone lasted about four months.</p>
        <p>A Nazi who originally supported Hitler, Rabe chose not to flee Nanjing with most of the other foreigners as the Japanese approached. He remarked in his diary: ''I don't love being shelled . . . but I simply cannot bring myself to save my skin just yet.''</p>
        <p>So Rabe stayed behind in Nanjing to set up a small shelter, which quickly expanded into a vast safety zone. He had his tussles with the Chinese, particularly the Chinese troops, who kept sneaking into his shelter, even digging trenches to secure safety behind its walls. The Chinese military's presence, of course, made the shelter a prime target for the Japanese, so Rabe wanted them out.</p>
        <p>They did not leave, even as the Japanese began bombing their way into the city. Mean-while, everyone else was pleading to be let into the shelter. ''I can't listen to their wailing any longer, so I open both gates and let everyone in who wants in,'' he writes.</p>
        <p>This was just the beginning of the chaos, though. Rabe's initial hopes that the Japanese would capture the city peacefully -- their planes dropped pamphlets saying that all civilians would be ''treated humanely in all respects'' -- soon gave way to frustration, then horror and despair. ''We come across corpses every 100 to 200 yards,'' he writes on Dec. 13, 1937, the day after the Japanese took control. ''The bodies of civilians that I examined had bullet holes in their backs. These people had presumably been fleeing and were shot from behind.''</p>
        <p>Japanese soldiers looted, smashed, burned people and buildings -- whatever was in their way, whatever was their fancy, Rabe says. They entered his safety zone to pillage, rape and murder. Just behind Rabe's garden wall, a woman was raped and then wounded in the neck with a bayonet. Nurses at the nearby hospital were also violated.</p>
        <p>''Last night up to 1,000 women and girls are said to have been raped, about 100 girls at Ginling Girls College alone,'' Rabe reports on Dec. 17. ''You hear of nothing but rape. If husbands or brothers intervene, they're shot. What you hear and see on all sides is the brutality and bestiality of the Japanese soldiery.''</p>
        <p>Then the Japanese began burning down the city and the people in it. When army officers demanded Chinese workers, a trusting Rabe suggested where they could be found. Days later, he discovered that 43 of the 54 workers the Japanese had rounded up were led to the riverbank and machine-gunned, ''ostensibly because they were the employees of an enterprise managed by the Chinese Government.''</p>
        <p>Rabe mentions one day when he was cleaning the safety zone: ''We find many bodies in the ponds, civilians who have been shot (30 in just one pond), most of them with their hands bound, some with stones tied to their necks.'' At another time, he complains that 50 corpses lay unburied. At still another, he reports that a German colleague saw 300 corpses in a dry ditch near one of the city gates.</p>
        <p>Rabe records all sorts of atrocities: a woman is found dead with a golf ball inside her vagina, another bayoneted there. ''You can't breathe for sheer revulsion when you keep finding the bodies of women with bamboo poles thrust up their vaginas,'' he writes. ''Even old women over 70 are constantly being raped.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Rabe hears from a Japanese Foreign Ministry official that Tokyo has asked for order to be restored. But he cannot get approval even to bury the dead, and he points to ''the danger to which we are all exposed as long as perhaps a thousand corpses are lying about the city unburied.'' He continues: ''These corpses have been partially eaten by dogs. At the same time, however, dog meat is being sold by the Chinese in the streets.''</p>
        <p>As Nanjing starved, the crops outside the city walls lay rotting because no one was allowed to go out to harvest them. Rabe surmises that the Japanese wanted the Chinese to starve to death. He compares the soldiers to the ''hordes of Genghis Khan'' and laments: ''One might well believe the Japanese Army is made up of ex-convicts. Normal people do not behave this way.''</p>
        <p>One of the most intriguing aspects of these diaries is that while Rabe recounts tortures, rapes and mass murders by the Japanese, he appears not to have seen many of the atrocities that are commonly described by the Chinese themselves. There are no accounts of live burials, mass disembowelments, deaths by freezing or death by being eaten alive by dogs.</p>
        <p>Japanese soldiers would naturally have tried to avoid torturing Chinese in front of foreign witnesses, but Rabe was also getting reports of atrocities from his Chinese assistants. It is unlikely that the book's editor, Erwin Wickert, who had known Rabe and obtained the diaries from his granddaughter, would have left such stories out. So it is probable that Rabe, who did not speak Chinese, simply did not see these particular atrocities, or did not dare to record them for some reason. It is also possible that these crimes were committed in extreme secrecy. Or perhaps they did not occur at all.</p>
        <p>Even now, an emotional debate rages over how many people actually lost their lives at the hands of the Japanese. Some Chinese estimates go as high as 200,000 to 300,000, a number that was recently popularized by Iris Chang in her book, ''The Rape of Nanking.'' In his diary, Rabe says that out of an initial population of 1.2 million people, about 800,000 fled before Nanjing was captured. He writes that about 250,000 ended up in his safety zone, and though many were killed there, most survived. That would leave about 150,000 people unaccounted for by Rabe.</p>
        <p>Basing his numbers on reports from one of the humanitarian groups involved in burying the dead, Rabe estimates that a total of 50,000 to 60,000 people were actually killed, and those are the numbers that he used when he returned to Germany and lectured on his experiences in China. (When he tried to send a report of the atrocities to Hitler, he was arrested and interrogated by the Gestapo; upon his release, he stopped speaking publicly about Nanjing.)</p>
        <p>Rabe recorded the deaths he saw in his diaries, but he did not keep a tally of the dead. That is unfortunate. However, he certainly had enough on his hands.</p>
        <p>Sheryl WuDunn is a Tokyo-based correspondent for The New York Times who, with her husband, Nicholas D. Kristof, is the author of ''China Wakes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sheryl WuDunn is a Tokyo-based correspondent for The New York Times who, with her husband, Nicholas D. Kristof, is the author of ''China Wakes.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
