<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Secret Surveillance Cameras Growing in City, Report Says</title>
    <meta content="13CAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="61" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Civil Liberties Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDC163DF930A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Secret Surveillance Cameras Growing in City, Report Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Civil Liberties Union reports that millions of people who live or work in Manhattan, or just visit, are being secretly videotaped everyday on public streets, sidewalks and parks by a proliferating array of surveillance cameras; urges city and state officials to hold hearings and adopt regulations intended to prevent the abuse of public surveillance; estimates that 2,000 of the 2,380 cameras it counted in borough are operated by private entities and the remainder by government agencies; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Millions of people who live or work in Manhattan, or just visit, are being secretly videotaped every day on public streets, sidewalks and parks by a proliferating array of surveillance cameras, according to a new study by the New York Civil Liberties Union.</p>
        <p>A block-by-block survey by volunteers found 2,380 surveillance cameras trained on public spaces, and the group says its total is undoubtedly conservative.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Millions of people who live or work in Manhattan, or just visit, are being secretly videotaped every day on public streets, sidewalks and parks by a proliferating array of surveillance cameras, according to a new study by the New York Civil Liberties Union.</p>
        <p>A block-by-block survey by volunteers found 2,380 surveillance cameras trained on public spaces, and the group says its total is undoubtedly conservative.</p>
        <p>''Someone is watching where you're going and what you're doing,'' the group's executive director, Norman Siegel, said.</p>
        <p>The group is proposing that city and state officials hold hearings and adopt regulations intended to prevent the abuse of public surveillance. These measures include posting signs telling people that they are under surveillance, requiring camera owners to register their equipment and setting a time limit on how long tapes can be retained.</p>
        <p>Although it is not certain who owns the cameras, the survey estimated that 2,000 are operated by private entities and the remainder by government agencies.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has endorsed the use of video surveillance to enhance public safety. His Police Commissioner, Howard Safir, said yesterday that such cameras had proven to be ''incredibly effective,'' cutting crime by 30 percent to 50 percent in public housing projects.</p>
        <p>''You have no right to privacy in a public place,'' Commissioner Safir added, and ''no court order is required'' to use cameras.</p>
        <p>Critics say that while cameras may have legitimate uses as crime-fighting tools, the unfettered spread of surveillance threatens private freedom. That is especially true in New York, they say, where diversity and tolerance have been a magnet for unorthodox people seeking the big city's cloak of anonymity.</p>
        <p>''We're a hub for freedom of thought, action and life style,'' Mr. Siegel said. ''There's a right to be anonymous and not be observed by government.''</p>
        <p>Most of the cameras are on Wall Street and in midtown, the survey found, and the biggest concentration -- 70 -- is in three blocks around Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>At the civil liberties group's headquarters in Manhattan yesterday, workers pressed colored pushpins, each representing a camera, into a 10-foot-long map of Manhattan. ''We should be driving the technology, not the technology driving us,'' Mr. Siegel said. ''The cameras are already here, but without any public debate or rules, and it raises a slew of questions.'' The group plans to extend its survey to the other four boroughs.</p>
        <p>But Commissioner Safir scoffed at the civil liberties group's concerns, saying, ''Norman Siegel, as usual, is on the wrong side.''</p>
        <p>Most surveillance cameras are in fixed positions, attached to places like building entrances, rooftops and lampposts, the report said. But nearly 400 are rotating cameras concealed at the bottom of globes that look like light fixtures.</p>
        <p>The most sophisticated ones have remote controls that can focus and zoom in on windows and backyards.</p>
        <p>In the survey, cameras installed on courthouses and other public buildings were assumed to be government cameras, while those on private property were assumed to be privately owned. The survey takers said they might have missed additional concealed cameras.</p>
        <p>Some cameras are operated by television stations for news gathering, mostly traffic and weather reports. Mr. Siegel said such uses of cameras involve First Amendment rights of the news media.</p>
        <p>Some opposition to surveillance has emerged. Earlier this year, after the police installed cameras in Washington Square Park in Greenwich Village, about 200 protesters rallied against the surveillance. Gay and lesbian leaders have said surveillance of popular cruising spots like the West Side piers could inhibit couples from holding hands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
