<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stage Set for Competition For Long Island Cable TV</title>
    <meta content="06cable" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/06/nyregion/06cable.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1752406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hempstead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cablevision Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cablevision Systems Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D91030F935A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stage Set for Competition For Long Island Cable TV</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stage Set for Competition for Long Island Cable TV</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hempstead, NY, officials grant cable television franchise to Verizon Communications; decision sets up Verizon battle with Cablevision, which has long had monopoly on Long Island; Hempstead decision reflects growing nationwide trend to encourage competition in telecommunications industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across the nation, telephone and cable television companies are starting to invade each other's traditional turf. Their latest battleground, and one of the biggest anywhere, is now on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Hempstead Town officials have granted Verizon Communications a franchise to provide cable television through its fiber-optic telephone lines, setting the stage for head-to-head competition with the longtime local monopoly, Cablevision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Hempstead, Verizon Communications now may provide cable television through telephone lines and compete with Cablevision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across the nation, telephone and cable television companies are starting to invade each other's traditional turf. Their latest battleground, and one of the biggest anywhere, is now on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Hempstead Town officials have granted Verizon Communications a franchise to provide cable television through its fiber-optic telephone lines, setting the stage for head-to-head competition with the longtime local monopoly, Cablevision.</p>
        <p>Both companies also provide telephone and Internet connections and offer packages that include television. Cablevision's introductory rate is about $90 a month for all three services.</p>
        <p>Hempstead's 750,000 residents -- more than Boston, Washington or Miami -- make it by far the biggest jurisdiction in the New York region to promote such competition.</p>
        <p>The deal needs the approval of the state's Public Service Commission, but it has already allowed such competition in Massapequa Park and Nyack. Other battlefronts are also opening up, a result of technological advances and deregulation that is forcing the telecommunications industry to reinvent itself. Advocates of the new rivalry say that competition will give customers more choice, keep prices down and improve service.</p>
        <p>Some proponents are pushing Congress to authorize such competition nationally; a bill to that effect passed a House subcommittee on Wednesday. And the battle is also being waged in other states and communities. In New Jersey, for instance, the telephone industry is lobbying the Legislature to permit statewide competition for cable television. The long-entrenched cable industry, including Cablevision and Comcast, is resisting there.</p>
        <p>''What's happening there in New York is an early curve of what's going to be happening around the country in the next few years,'' said Jeff Kagan, a telecommunications analyst and consultant in Atlanta. ''This is a new wave of competition. Basically the telephone and cable television companies are both rushing to offer the same bundle of services: television, phone, Internet and wireless. The sooner they do, the sooner prices will come down for all the customers.''</p>
        <p>In a preliminary skirmish with Cablevision, Verizon recently won permission to offer cable television in the small Long Island village of Massapequa Park. ''I've heard nothing but positives about it,'' said the local Nassau County legislator, Peter Schmitt. ''Competition is good. I think it's wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Cablevision, based in Nassau, is not taking the challenge lightly, especially in its own backyard. It is the nation's fifth-largest cable company, with three million customers concentrated in the New York region. Defending against Verizon's intrusion, Cablevision and its allies campaigned against the Hempstead franchise in television commercials, mass mailings and telephone calls.</p>
        <p>But after a nearly four-hour public hearing on Tuesday, Hempstead's Town Board voted unanimously to approve Verizon's proposal, which requires the company to pay the town a 5 percent fee on its sales. Cablevision also pays a fee.</p>
        <p>''This issue, bar none, has elicited the most public interest I've ever encountered,'' said Hempstead's supervisor, Kathleen Murray. ''Over the years, many residents expressed frustration that cable television was the subject of a monopoly. The public wants cable TV choice, they deserve it and they should get it.''</p>
        <p>Giving Verizon access to the market was not a judgment against Cablevision or a criticism of that company, Supervisor Murray said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Cablevision, James Maiella, said that ''we will continue to deliver excellent products to our customers and will vigorously compete'' with Verizon. Cablevision stresses its Long Island roots and its public service like News 12, its 24-hour local news channel. Verizon's plan does not include a local news channel.</p>
        <p>Hempstead is not the end of Verizon's ambitions on Long Island. Having installed $180 million worth of fiber-optic cable in Nassau, the company says it plans to extend its competition all across Long Island, which has nearly three million people.</p>
        <p>''What it means to the customer is they will have a choice in their video entertainment,'' said a Verizon senior vice president, Monica Azare. ''And what it means for Verizon is another step in the future of the company.''</p>
        <p>For decades Cablevision's virtual monopoly here, and its repeated price increases, have drawn complaints from some customers. Critics say the company ranks just below school taxes and electricity bills as an irritant. Until now, the only alternative for residents has been television satellite dish service.</p>
        <p>Cablevision's dominance expanded when it introduced broadband service for Internet computer connections. That service proved popular and now has 1.7 million customers. Two years ago, the company also began offering low-cost telephone service, cutting into Verizon's customer base. That fast-growing business now has 731,000 subscribers.</p>
        <p>The Hempstead cable television franchise covers the unincorporated parts of the town, with a population of about 500,000. The remaining 250,000 residents live in villages that have their own franchise powers, but town officials expect the villages to follow the town's lead.</p>
        <p>Assuming approval by the Public Service Commission, the company said it hoped to begin connecting customers by September. The plan calls for extending the service throughout the unincorporated parts of town within five years.</p>
        <p>Technology could bring still further changes to the industry. The Long Island Power Authority has approved a small experiment in providing broadband service using its wires, enabling connections at any electrical outlet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
