<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welfare Rolls Falling Again, Amid Worries About Poverty</title>
    <meta content="06welfare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/06/nyregion/06welfare.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1752457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Workfare and Employment of Welfare Recipients</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1D81030F935A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welfare Rolls Falling Again, Amid Worries About Poverty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Welfare Rolls Falling Again, Amid Worries About Poverty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Number of New York City residents receiving welfare fell to 402,281 in March 2006, lowest number since December 1964 and decline of nearly two-thirds from peak of nearly 1.2 million in March 1995; drop comes nearly 10 years after federal overhaul that imposed 5-year limit on assistance, established work requirement and gave states discretion in setting welfare policy; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The number of New York City residents receiving public assistance fell to 402,281 last month, the lowest number since December 1964, at the start of President Lyndon B. Johnson's war on poverty, and a decline of nearly two-thirds from its peak of nearly 1.2 million in March 1995, officials announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>After falling sharply during the mayoralty of Rudolph W. Giuliani, when more than 600,000 people left the rolls, the city's caseload began to creep upward in September 2002, during Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's first year in office and on the tail of a national recession. The modest increases continued until October 2004, when the caseload figure again started to decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city's caseload dropped to the lowest level since December 1964, but income inequality remains a concern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The number of New York City residents receiving public assistance fell to 402,281 last month, the lowest number since December 1964, at the start of President Lyndon B. Johnson's war on poverty, and a decline of nearly two-thirds from its peak of nearly 1.2 million in March 1995, officials announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>After falling sharply during the mayoralty of Rudolph W. Giuliani, when more than 600,000 people left the rolls, the city's caseload began to creep upward in September 2002, during Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's first year in office and on the tail of a national recession. The modest increases continued until October 2004, when the caseload figure again started to decline.</p>
        <p>The recent drop in the number of welfare recipients in the city comes months before the 10th anniversary of the federal welfare overhaul that imposed a five-year limit on assistance, established work requirements and gave states discretion in setting welfare policy. Nationally, the caseload has fallen by more than half since the federal law was signed in August 1996.</p>
        <p>The decline in the caseload is occurring amid concerns about income inequality, which has risen more sharply in the city than in the nation as a whole, and new signs that poor families are having a harder time meeting housing and food costs. Last month, Mr. Bloomberg appointed a 32-member Commission for Economic Opportunity to come up with public and private solutions to poverty in the city.</p>
        <p>''When I came into office, we were going into an economic slump, and most people thought that the welfare rolls would go up,'' Mr. Bloomberg said yesterday. ''The truth of the matter is, they have gone down.''</p>
        <p>But welfare recipients who do find work are often in low-paying jobs with limited opportunities for advancement. Of those who have left welfare for work in the city, 88 percent have kept their jobs after three months and 75 percent after six months.</p>
        <p>Isabel V. Sawhill, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, a research organization in Washington, said the broad decline in welfare caseloads in the last decade could be attributed to three factors: an unusually strong economy in the late 1990's; the federal overhaul that encouraged recipients to find work and financially penalized those who did not; and policies that expanded access to food stamps, child-care subsidies and the earned-income tax credit.</p>
        <p>The city's caseload decline since 2004 is surprising because the national caseload decline has slowed significantly, said Gordon L. Berlin, president of MDRC, formerly the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation, a group in New York and Oakland, Calif., that evaluates social programs.</p>
        <p>''The economy has begun to pick up,'' Mr. Berlin said, ''and that's certainly part of the story in New York.''</p>
        <p>Welfare has been a less prominent issue under Mr. Bloomberg than under Mr. Giuliani, even though the city has maintained the welfare policies started in the mid-1990's. Mr. Giuliani imposed tough eligibility-verification reviews that removed many recipients from the rolls. He also converted welfare offices into job-search centers and required recipients to join the city's Work Experience Program, which placed them in jobs like raking leaves or answering phones. Welfare caseworkers are now called ''job opportunity specialists.''</p>
        <p>''Giuliani gloried in opposing the activist groups and challenging the welfare culture,'' said Lawrence M. Mead III, a professor of politics at New York University. ''The Bloomberg administration continued the Giuliani policies, although without the contentious rhetoric. The change under Bloomberg has been more atmospheric than substantive.''</p>
        <p>In February 2005, the city's Human Resources Administration began WeCare, which provides medical and psychological assessment and care for recipients who have been unable to find work.</p>
        <p>Verna Eggleston, the commissioner of the agency, said it had ''abandoned the 'one-size-fits-all' social service program model'' in favor of an ''individualized model.''</p>
        <p>WeCare has enrolled about 15,000 adults and is expected to serve 40,000 eventually, said Patricia M. Smith, who has worked for the welfare agency since 1974 and is now its first deputy commissioner.</p>
        <p>''We've recognized the shift in the demographics and characteristics of the caseload since the early days of welfare reform,'' she said, adding that many current recipients have ''multiple barriers to employment.''</p>
        <p>The mayor acknowledged the same problem. ''I don't think it's realistic to think that everybody can go to work,'' he said, ''but we are going in the right direction.''</p>
        <p>Gail B. Nayowith, executive director of the Citizens' Committee for Children of New York and a member of the mayor's commission, said the focus needed to shift to economic security from welfare reform. ''Parents are working full time and still poor,'' she said. ''There has to be a greater effort on making work pay.''</p>
        <p>City Councilman Bill de Blasio, a Brooklyn Democrat who is chairman of the Council's General Welfare Committee, said the decline in the caseload was ''very good news'' but added that ''people who've exhausted their benefits have not necessarily found steady income.'' In 2004, 20.3 percent of residents and 17.4 percent of families in New York City lived below the poverty line.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Blasio and advocates for the poor have estimated that there are hundreds of thousands of residents who are eligible for food stamps or for government earned-income tax credits but have not enrolled. Ms. Smith said the welfare agency was allowing people for the first time to apply for benefits through nonprofit groups and that enrollment in another program, Medicaid, had significantly risen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
