<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coast to Coast, Workers Say Fickle Economy Is a Riddle</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="610451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER 
BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDWESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUCKER, FLOYD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIZER, VIVIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DA163DF931A15756C0A965958260" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coast to Coast, Workers Say Fickle Economy Is a Riddle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., May 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sun poked through the clouds, vanished, then gave way to rain as Floyd Rucker and Vivian Kizer stepped inside a gleaming downtown shopping mall here, where they did more looking than buying. They have talked about buying a new house and having a baby. But the nation's economy, fickle as the spring sky in Missouri, has put their plans on hold.</p>
        <p>"I think about the low interest rates, and figure maybe it's time to buy something," said Mr. Rucker, a 29-year-old veterinarian's assistant. "But then I think about a friend of mine. He's got a new baby, a big house payment, two car payments. And he just got laid off. He doesn't know what he's going to do."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sun poked through the clouds, vanished, then gave way to rain as Floyd Rucker and Vivian Kizer stepped inside a gleaming downtown shopping mall here, where they did more looking than buying. They have talked about buying a new house and having a baby. But the nation's economy, fickle as the spring sky in Missouri, has put their plans on hold.</p>
        <p>"I think about the low interest rates, and figure maybe it's time to buy something," said Mr. Rucker, a 29-year-old veterinarian's assistant. "But then I think about a friend of mine. He's got a new baby, a big house payment, two car payments. And he just got laid off. He doesn't know what he's going to do."</p>
        <p>"I don't plan on losing my job," he said, "but neither did he." Many Remain Uncertain</p>
        <p>Although the nation's recession has long since been declared over, and some parts of the country have shown signs of a recovery, many Americans say they remain uncertain about the economy, fearful about their jobs and wary of making large purchases.</p>
        <p>Like the principal of a school in Rancho Cucamonga, Calif., where more and more unemployed fathers are showing up to volunteer their time, or a commercial real estate broker in Philadelphia who is facing a glut of empty office space, many workers across the country say they are not convinced that life will get easier any time soon.</p>
        <p>The wariness of Mr. Rucker and Ms. Kizer, 28, a preschool teacher, who might otherwise now be buying house furnishings and baby clothes, illustrates the chicken-or-egg conundrum of the nation's sluggish economy: consumers wait for economic recovery, which waits for consumers. Working Hard to Stay Even</p>
        <p>"A lot of things I always took for granted -- having a big family, owning a house -- it just doesn't seem realistic anymore," said Mr. Rucker, who recently saw his annual 5 percent raise cut to 3 percent because of a slack in business. "It seems like you've got to break your back just to stay even."</p>
        <p>Here in the middle of America, which saw neither the extreme boom of the 1980's nor the sharp real estate slump of the early 1990's and where the recovery has been noticeable, people tend to take the long view of things, and most are not sanguine.</p>
        <p>Anxious as they are for an economic recovery, Midwesterners say they believe the days of real job security have gone forever. Everybody Is Wondering</p>
        <p>"All businesses are reorganizing, trying to get more efficient," said Mike Hutchinson, 36, the manager of a copy-machine store in Des Moines. "And everybody is kind of wondering, Where am I going to fit in?"</p>
        <p>Like other regions in the United States, the Midwest has been hardest hit by layoffs in automobile and defense-related companies.</p>
        <p>Diana Alvarez, 46, whose annual household income is nearly $80,000, said she cannot relax for more than two weeks at a time. Her husband, Dennis, works for Boeing in Wichita, Kan., and the company is laying off 6,000 people this year. The pink slips are delivered with the paychecks.</p>
        <p>"Every two weeks on payday, my husband opens it up to see if there's anything pink inside," said Ms. Alvarez, a nurse. "So far he's come home every time to say, 'No pink slip today.' But we can't be sure about next payday. So you just live day to day."</p>
        <p>With two children in college and elderly parents who need financial help, Ms. Alvarez said she shudders to think about the future if her husband loses his job. "I don't know how we'll survive," she said.</p>
        <p>But retailers in the Crown City mall here in Kansas City say business has picked up in the last four or five months.</p>
        <p>"When more people are buying flowers," said Del Draper, a florist who has been working overtime, "you know people are feeling better."</p>
        <p>Unemployment is relatively low in Kansas City -- about 5.5 percent -- but the statistics do not say much about the kinds of jobs available.</p>
        <p>David Gardine, a 40-year-old clerk in a housewares store here, said he could survive on his $7-an-hour wage as long as he stayed healthy. Like millions of working-class Americans, he has no health insurance. "You just lay low and try to take care of yourself," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
