<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharpton Trial Papers Stolen From Maddox's Car</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBEZZLEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL YOUTH MOVEMENT (ORGN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL YOUTH MOVEMENT (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MADDOX, ALTON H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHARPTON, AL (REV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC1038F93AA15756C0A966958260" item-length="370" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharpton Trial Papers Stolen From Maddox's Car</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Two briefcases stuffed with evidence from the fraud trial of the Rev. Al Sharpton were stolen from the car of Alton H. Maddox Jr., Mr. Sharpton's lawyer, in midtown over the weekend, Mr. Maddox and the police said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Two briefcases stuffed with evidence from the fraud trial of the Rev. Al Sharpton were stolen from the car of Alton H. Maddox Jr., Mr. Sharpton's lawyer, in midtown over the weekend, Mr. Maddox and the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Two briefcases stuffed with evidence from the fraud trial of the Rev. Al Sharpton were stolen from the car of Alton H. Maddox Jr., Mr. Sharpton's lawyer, in midtown over the weekend, Mr. Maddox and the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox said most of the documents were copies of evidence introduced by the prosecution and were not crucial to Mr. Sharpton's defense. He added that although the theft would ''slow down'' his preparations, he would not ask the judge for a delay.</p>
        <p>Lock on Door Picked</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton has been on trial since March 19 in State Supreme Court in Manhattan on charges that he used the National Youth Movement, which he founded in Brooklyn 20 years ago, to steal $250,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox said the two briefcases were stolen from the trunk of his 1987 Toyota Camry while it was parked on 40th Street between the Avenue of the Americas and Broadway, near the entrance of KISS-FM, sometime between 8:50 and 10:10 A.M. Sunday.</p>
        <p>He said someone had picked the lock on a passenger's door, had taken a radar detector from the glove compartment and then aparently had opened the trunk by pulling a lever near the driver's seat. Mr. Maddox was a guest on a KISS-FM talk show, ''Open Line,'' at the time.</p>
        <p>A police spokesman, Officer Hugh Barry, said an officer in the Midtown South Precinct had filled out a complaint report after interviewing Mr. Maddox. He said the police did not intend to investigate the theft because there were no witnesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox said it appeared that thieves may have singled out his car. Several other cars belonging to employees of the station were parked in front and behind his car but were not burglarized, he said.</p>
        <p>The theft may be linked, Mr. Maddox said, to an incident two weeks ago in which vandals put glue in the locks at his office. He said he had also received harassing mail from anonymous writers.</p>
        <p>On May 7, Mr. Maddox was suspended from the practice of law for not cooperating with a grievance committee hearing a complaint against him by the State Attorney General, Robert Abrams. The complaint arose from Mr. Maddox's involvement with Tawana Brawley, a black Dutchess County teen-ager who said she had been sexually attacked by up to six white men.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
