<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Simpson Defense Team Attacks New Grand Jury Investigation</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="708420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, O J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, NICOLE BROWN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, RONALD LYLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDB1039F935A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Simpson Defense Team Attacks New Grand Jury Investigation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Los Angeles County grand jury that was convened to investigate the circumstances of O. J. Simpson's flight from the police two months ago is under attack from his defense team, which accuses prosecutors of using the grand jurors to engage in a fishing expedition involving the broader murder case against him.</p>
        <p>In a departure from the custom of maintaining secrecy on grand jury proceedings, the current inquiry was made public on Wednesday by District Attorney Gil Garcetti.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Los Angeles County grand jury that was convened to investigate the circumstances of O. J. Simpson's flight from the police two months ago is under attack from his defense team, which accuses prosecutors of using the grand jurors to engage in a fishing expedition involving the broader murder case against him.</p>
        <p>In a departure from the custom of maintaining secrecy on grand jury proceedings, the current inquiry was made public on Wednesday by District Attorney Gil Garcetti.</p>
        <p>The Simpson defense team responded today, accusing the District Attorney of using the grand jury in an effort to examine defense witnesses, lawyers and experts for evidence that could be used against Mr. Simpson when he is tried on charges of murdering his former wife, Nicole Brown Simpson, and a friend of hers, Ronald L. Goldman.</p>
        <p>The defense leveled its accusation in an emergency motion filed with Judge Lance A. Ito of Los Angeles County Superior Court, who is presiding in the murder case. The motion, which is expected to be heard on Friday, asks the judge for any of a number of remedies, including disciplinary sanctions against the District Attorney's office and suppression of any evidence obtained by the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcetti's office declined to comment on the motion, saying it would respond only in court.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, in disclosing the grand jury's investigation, Mr. Garcetti said the jurors were questioning a number of people who were with Mr. Simpson in the hours before he disappeared with his longtime friend Al Cowlings on June 17 rather than surrendering on the murder charges at midday, as his lawyer had arranged.</p>
        <p>The District Attorney's office has so far declined to charge Mr. Cowlings with aiding and abetting a fugitive, and Mr. Garcetti said Wednesday that the grand jury was being used solely for investigative purposes, not to indict Mr. Cowlings. Mr. Garcetti also said that any information gathered by the grand jury could be used in the murder case against Mr. Simpson.</p>
        <p>"Anything we learn there can be used in any other criminal proceeding," the District Attorney said. "If there is other evidence that comes out that assists us in another case, you are not going to turn your back to that evidence."</p>
        <p>In their emergency motion today, Mr. Simpson's lawyers, led by Robert L. Shapiro, took strong exception.  "The grand jury is not empowered to conduct roving investigations or assist the District Attorney in conducting his own roving investigations," the defense said in its court papers.  "The grand jury's investigative power is limited to determining whether a public offense should be charged by indictment."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
