<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Grill Where Colors and Music Ring Out</title>
    <meta content="11WEDINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1488106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sammy's Grill and Bar (Somers, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5D9123FF932A25756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Grill Where Colors and Music Ring Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M.H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Sammy's Grill and Bar in Somers, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DINERS inclined to think of Sammy's Grill and Bar as a predictable hamburger and ribs place might think again.</p>
        <p>Certainly the witty décor should rattle expectations; the new owners may well have put all their decorating capital into paint: the captain's chairs vibrate with bold hues, as do the tables, gleaming as though lacquered. Pendant wagon-wheel chandeliers, their hurricane shades awash with color, cast their stained-glass light on figures painted on the walls and on the stuffed, life-size figures perched on the high rafters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DINERS inclined to think of Sammy's Grill and Bar as a predictable hamburger and ribs place might think again.</p>
        <p>Certainly the witty décor should rattle expectations; the new owners may well have put all their decorating capital into paint: the captain's chairs vibrate with bold hues, as do the tables, gleaming as though lacquered. Pendant wagon-wheel chandeliers, their hurricane shades awash with color, cast their stained-glass light on figures painted on the walls and on the stuffed, life-size figures perched on the high rafters.</p>
        <p>The draw at Sammy's, for many, might be the late-night music, the range of generous offerings -- dishes here will suit all ages -- and the view, particularly in this warm season. Small patio and picture windows at the back of the restaurant look out onto a pretty pond and its geese. After dark, on Friday and Saturday nights, there's live music in the lounge.</p>
        <p>Some appetizers like the heap of fresh-tasting nachos with salsa, guacamole and Cheddar cheese could easily be consumed at the bar. Fat, inventive quesadillas were large enough to serve as entrees. A soft spinach tortilla wrapped chunks of lobster, avocado and Manchego cheese in a harmonious combination of flavors and textures. Quesadilla with chicken proved almost as good.</p>
        <p>Crab cakes and tempura shrimp, both resting on greens, were fine though standard issue, as was Sammy's chili with the usual shreds of beef, Cheddar cheese, onions and sour cream. A huge portobello cap, crusted in an armor of crushed nuts that made the dish chokingly dry, was a total miss.</p>
        <p>Sammy's dishes echo both American-regional and foreign kitchens. Items like quesadillas, chili, coconut shrimp, wasabi salmon, southern fried chicken and Asian short ribs, to name a few, fill out the menu. A tasty Thai stir fry of firm shrimp, shredded vegetables and fragrant peanut sauce was dished over icy cold noodles, a pity, since the dish was otherwise delightful. Noodles, as a bed for juicy seared salmon with mild wasabi, came appropriately hot in this fine dish.</p>
        <p>An order of barbecue ribs brought a full rack, so large it hung over the platter and so tender that the hickory-smoked meat almost fell off the bone. Coconut-crusted shrimp with couscous and fruity salsa were better than overly grilled shrimp with risotto.</p>
        <p>The long list of sandwiches was well worth consideration. A mere lick of horseradish added kick to lobster salad heaped into a tender roasted roll. A soft bun was filled with pulled barbecue pork with a few shavings of onion. But high hopes for the featured Sammy's Big Daddy Burger were dashed: ordered medium rare, the meat arrived overcooked, tough and dry.</p>
        <p>A very short list of standard wines was fairly priced. The selection of beers was more interesting. Most were bottled from microbrewers like Saranac and Blackened Voodoo.</p>
        <p>Desserts were acceptable without being inspirational. Key lime pie with a lovely buttery crust needed more of the lime's tart, citric zing. But rich brownie ran with good, moderately sweet chocolate sauce. Sorbets and ice cream will please the cautious.</p>
        <p>Sammy's Grill and Bar  289 Route 100, Somers.  (914)276-0600</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Long, narrow dining room and separate bar and lounge awash with bold colors -- purple, acid green, orange -- in an unpretentious old roadhouse. High ceilings, bare floors and tabletops amplify noise. Small back patio overlooks a pretty pond. Good service. Live music begins at 10 on most Friday and Saturday nights.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Lobster and avocado quesadilla, chicken quesadilla, nachos, Thai shrimp lo mein, barbecue ribs, wasabi salmon, coconut shrimp, brownie. The menu is still being fine-tuned; some dishes may no longer be available.  PRICES -- Lunch and dinner, $9 to $27, with some appetizers generous enough to serve as entrees. Brunch, $7 to $16.  CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.  HOURS -- Sundays through Thursdays, 11:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 11:30 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 11 p.m., bar is open late. Brunch, Sundays, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.  RESERVATIONS -- Advisable for large parties or for specific tables.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.  THE RATINGS -- Excellent. Very good. Good. Satisfactory. Poor.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
