<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justices to Hear President's Appeal on Line Item Veto Ruling</title>
    <meta content="Y28SCOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="998557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD1F3EF93BA15751C0A96E958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justices to Hear President's Appeal on Line Item Veto Ruling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court says it will try once again to decide constitutionality of Line Item Veto Act, setting April 27 to hear Clinton Administration's appeal from recent ruling that struck down law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court announced today that it would try once again to decide the constitutionality of the Line Item Veto Act, setting April 27 to hear the Clinton Administration's appeal from a recent ruling that struck down the 1996 law.</p>
        <p>The accelerated schedule means the Justices will be able to issue a decision by the time the current term ends early this summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court announced today that it would try once again to decide the constitutionality of the Line Item Veto Act, setting April 27 to hear the Clinton Administration's appeal from a recent ruling that struck down the 1996 law.</p>
        <p>The accelerated schedule means the Justices will be able to issue a decision by the time the current term ends early this summer.</p>
        <p>At stake is an intensely disputed measure by which Congress, for the first time in the nation's history, gave the President the power to cancel individual tax and spending items in legislation already signed into law.</p>
        <p>Since the law took effect in January 1997, President Clinton has vetoed 82 items from 11 laws; two of those vetoes, involving a tax benefit for New York City hospitals and a capital gains tax break for agricultural stock sales, are at issue in the case now before the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>In a ruling two weeks ago, Judge Thomas F. Hogan of the Federal District Court here declared the line item veto unconstitutional as violating both the constitutional separation of powers and the Constitution's precise procedural requirements for enacting legislation.</p>
        <p>In its last term the Supreme Court reviewed an earlier District Court decision that had also declared the line item veto unconstitutional. But the Justices did not rule on the merits of the issue, instead ordering that the case be dismissed on the ground that the five members of Congress who had filed the lawsuit had not suffered any ''personal, concrete injury'' and so lacked standing to bring the case.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs in the new case are in a stronger position, but it is still possible that the Court will find that they lack standing as well, a position the Administration is vigorously arguing in its appeal, Clinton v. City of New York, No. 97-1374. Most legal scholars believe that if the Court does address the merits, the result is likely to be a ruling that the Line Item Veto Act is unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Doubts about the measure's constitutionality led Congress to place the act on an unusually fast track for Supreme Court review, with direct appeal to the Court from a ruling by a single Federal District judge without the usual intermediate step of review by one of the United States Courts of Appeals.</p>
        <p>The Line Item Veto Act relieves the President of the obligation to accept or reject bills in their entirety. Instead, for spending and tax legislation, the President may cancel particular items within five days of signing a bill into law. Congress can then disapprove the cancellation by passing a special disapproval bill. That bill is itself subject to a Presidential veto, which can be overridden in the normal manner by a two-thirds vote of each house.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Congress went through this process for the first time, overriding Mr. Clinton's veto of a bill restoring $287 million worth of military construction items that he canceled last year from a $9.2 billion military construction bill.</p>
        <p>In its defense of the Line Item Veto Act, the Administration maintains that the President's cancellation authority is only ''conditional,'' subject to final and conclusive Congressional action.</p>
        <p>In his Feb. 12 opinion striking down the act, Judge Hogan rejected this analysis, declaring that the law amounted to an ''unauthorized surrender to the President of an inherently legislative function, namely, the authority to permanently shape laws and package legislation.''</p>
        <p>Judge Hogan said the President is not supposed to be a ''co-designer'' of laws, picking and choosing among various provisions, but rather is supposed to ''take care that the laws be faithfully executed'' in their entirety once he has signed them.</p>
        <p>The case the Supreme Court will review is a consolidation of two separate challenges to Mr. Clinton's exercise of the line item veto.</p>
        <p>One lawsuit was brought by New York City, its Health and Hospitals Corporation, a group of hospitals in the city, and two unions of hospital employees.</p>
        <p>They challenged the President's veto of a provision in the Balanced Budget Act of 1997 that would have relieved New York State of the obligation to reimburse the Federal Government for some $2.6 billion in Medicaid payments. State law, in turn, holds the city and the hospitals responsible for a share of the reimbursement.</p>
        <p>The initial question for the Justices, on the issue of standing, is whether the city and the hospitals are the proper plaintiffs when it is actually the state that has the financial obligation to the Government.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs in the second lawsuit are a group of potato growers in Idaho. The group argues that the President's veto of a capital gains provision will raise the cost of buying processing plant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
