<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Puts Victorious Spin on Summit</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D61731F937A35754C0A964958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Puts Victorious Spin on Summit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With President Bush due to leave this weekend for the economic summit meeting in Munich, the White House has begun a campaign to turn it into a pep rally for economic growth to demonstrate Mr. Bush's determination to do something about the sagging American economy.</p>
        <p>Especially after the sharp jump in the nation's jobless rate announced Thursday, which was a blow to Mr. Bush's re-election hopes, the White House is eager to declare Munich a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With President Bush due to leave this weekend for the economic summit meeting in Munich, the White House has begun a campaign to turn it into a pep rally for economic growth to demonstrate Mr. Bush's determination to do something about the sagging American economy.</p>
        <p>Especially after the sharp jump in the nation's jobless rate announced Thursday, which was a blow to Mr. Bush's re-election hopes, the White House is eager to declare Munich a victory.</p>
        <p>In effect, the White House is telling the people back home that the meetings were a diplomatic triumph, even before the leaders of the United States, Britain, Canada, France, Germany, Italy and Japan gather on Monday.</p>
        <p>At the same time, with President Bush slumping badly in public opinion polls, some American officials say the leaders at the summit meeting are deliberately pursuing a modest agenda that seeks to prevent any potentially embarrassing blow-ups among the leaders.</p>
        <p>In briefings and statements this week before the summit, Administration officials have asserted that they have been trying for 18 months to persuade Japan and Germany to put more emphasis on economic growth. The officials said Tokyo and Bonn had finally agreed to measures that will promote growth. 'Modest Expectations'</p>
        <p>As evidence that the strategy has been successful, the Administration is citing a commitment by Japan's Government to spend an extra $45 billion next year on public works and other projects to spur its flagging growth. It is also citing measures by the German Government to hold down its budget deficit in the hope that this will enable the Central Bank to lower interest rates.</p>
        <p>The Japanese and Germans insist that they are not taking these actions at Washington's bidding, but to restore health to their sagging economies.</p>
        <p>While not taking credit for Tokyo's and Bonn's new policies, the Administration is publicizing them as if they were part of President Bush's economic growth package.</p>
        <p>"These actions demonstrate forcefully the high priority which the summit places on strong global economic growth," Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady said in a news briefing this week.</p>
        <p>Many officials say they doubt the United States will push hard to resolve the long dispute over farm subsidies that has blocked completion of talks to liberalize world trade. Many foreign policy experts say a breakthrough in the trade talks, which would be a boon for developing nations, is needed far more than a lofty-sounding communique to send a growth message to the world.</p>
        <p>"The Administration is downplaying the summit and is trying to keep expectations quite modest," said Robert D. Hormats, a former assistant secretary of state for economic affairs who is vice chairman of Goldman Sachs International. "There is good reason because the prospect of anything big coming out of Munich is not great." No More Mr. No</p>
        <p>Some analysts say that after President Bush's last two embarrassing trips abroad -- the trade-promotion trip to Tokyo and his trip to the Earth Summit in Rio, where he was called Mr. No -- the last thing he needs on this trip, which will also take him to Poland, is a bruising fiasco over trade or any other subject.</p>
        <p>It has been suggested that the leader attending the Munich summit who enjoys the most popularity at home is not a Group of Seven member but President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia. The Western leaders will meet with Mr. Yeltsin to discuss Moscow's progress on reforms and its need for aid, but some officials say that they doubt Mr. Yeltsin will go home with anything beyond the $24 billion package that the Group of Seven leaders promised him last April.</p>
        <p>To show their concern for Russia, Bush Administration officials hope the International Monetary Fund will approve a $1 billion aid package for Russia before the summit. Not wanting to be embarrassed by any snags, however, American officials say that it will not be a tragedy if an agreement is not signed until after the summit if that is necessary to get Russia to commit to a good reform package.</p>
        <p>Secretary Brady has signaled the leaders' desire to give Mr. Yeltsin a special gift, saying they want the industrial nations to take the rare move of restructuring Russia's debt burden even before Moscow signs a comprehensive reform agreement with the monetary fund.</p>
        <p>President Bush told foreign journalists on Thursday that the Munich meeting was important because, by encouraging world growth, it could help increase American exports. He noted that 70 percent of American economic growth over the past five years has come from exports.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
