<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Will Try to Sway Arabs in Talks With Israel</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DE1F31F937A35754C0A964958260" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Will Try to Sway Arabs in Talks With Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Israel appears to be on the verge of getting a Government that is serious about peace talks with the Arabs, American officials say that Washington's top priority in the negotiations will be to insure that the Palestinians and other Arab parties put forward more realistic compromise proposals.</p>
        <p>"The Arabs did their share to get this peace process started," a senior Administration official said the other day on the condition of anonymity. "But the fact is they have been sitting around for the last year and a half watching the spectacle of the Bush Administration fighting with Israel. It was a great show, but it's over and now their moment of truth is coming."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that Israel appears to be on the verge of getting a Government that is serious about peace talks with the Arabs, American officials say that Washington's top priority in the negotiations will be to insure that the Palestinians and other Arab parties put forward more realistic compromise proposals.</p>
        <p>"The Arabs did their share to get this peace process started," a senior Administration official said the other day on the condition of anonymity. "But the fact is they have been sitting around for the last year and a half watching the spectacle of the Bush Administration fighting with Israel. It was a great show, but it's over and now their moment of truth is coming."</p>
        <p>Now, the official said, once Prime Minister-designate Yitzhak Rabin puts together a government, the Arabs will have an Israeli partner "ready, at least theoretically, to trade territory for peace and impose a de facto settlements freeze, and in order to sustain that the Arabs will have to put up or shut up."</p>
        <p>"Right now I think that is something that makes them very nervous," the official added.</p>
        <p>Indeed, American officials say the Palestinians and Syrians have both been expressing concern that Washington appears to be getting ready to urge them to compromise. 2 Visions of Autonomy</p>
        <p>When the Arab-Israeli negotiations last broke off in April, American officials say, the Likud Government of Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir was clearly dragging its feet; its only concrete proposal to the Palestinians was that they take control of an aspect of their lives that they already control: administration of hospitals in the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Palestinians had offered their own autonomy proposal, and it was tantamount to a call for an independent Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>As American officials liked to point out, the terms of the Madrid peace conference called on Israel and the Palestinians to negotiate "interim self-government arrangements" for the Palestinians. But the Likud Government put forward only interim arrangements and ignored self-government, while the Palestinians put forward a plan for self-government and ignored the requirement for a transition phase.</p>
        <p>Now, though, Mr. Rabin says he wants self-rule for the 1.7 million Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza Strip within a year. He also says that he will allow the Palestinians to hold their own elections and that he will not build new Jewish settlements except in limited strategic zones in the Jordan Valley, around Jerusalem and on the Golan Heights. A Test for Arabs</p>
        <p>Because of this shift, American officials believe for the first time that real progress is possible -- provided that the Palestinians back off from their maximal opening demands.</p>
        <p>"In my mind, frankly, the most important thing is to make sure that the Arabs are serious when they come to the table," another senior Administration official said. "Up to now they have not had an Israeli government that really tested their willingness to negotiate a quick solution. Now you have Israelis who will be talking credibly and seriously about proposals that should be taken seriously by the Arabs, and it is critical that they be ready to engage."</p>
        <p>That message has already been passed through diplomatic channels to the Palestinians and all other Arab negotiating partners, American officials said. What distinguishes Mr. Rabin from Mr. Shamir, American officials have told the Arabs, is not that Mr. Rabin is a radical dove who will be ready to give away the store. The difference, they say, is that Mr. Rabin is ready to test with a degree of seriousness and resolve the proposition that the Arabs really are ready for a different relationship with Israel. Mr. Shamir refused to do that.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Shamir would not accept even an American suggestion that he tell Syria: "What if we were ready to withdraw from all or part of the Golan Heights? What would you give in return?"</p>
        <p>American officials say they will not begin formal talks with Mr. Rabin until he puts together a government, probably within the next few weeks. Several options are being considered; Mr. Rabin could visit President Bush in August, or Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d could travel to Jerusalem and the various Arab capitals.</p>
        <p>American officials say they believe their relationship with Mr. Rabin will be quite different from the one they had with Mr. Shamir. The Likud leader did not trust the Bush Administration and insisted that Washington not get involved in the Middle East talks -- except when Israel wanted it involved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabin's philosophy is that Israel and the United States should try to agree as much as possible on an acceptable compromise formula, and then Israel should enlist the United States to help sell it to the Arabs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker's aides greeted the prospect of progress in the Middle East talks with great enthusiasm, and not just because of what it portended for the negotiations. These officials also hope that it will give Mr. Baker an excuse to stay at the State Department rather than moving to the White House so he can run the troubled Bush re-election campaign. That shift has been widely expected.</p>
        <p>Administration officials are also waiting for the new Israeli Government to be formed before they revisit the issue of Israel's request for $10 billion in loan guarantees to help absorb Jews from the former Soviet Union. That request has been on hold since March, when Prime Minister Shamir refused to meet Mr. Bush's condition that Israel freeze all new settlement building before Washington authorized the guarantees. Accommodation Is Expected</p>
        <p>Again, Administration officials say they will take a very different approach with Mr. Rabin. Mr. Bush had insisted on ironclad promises from Mr. Shamir that he freeze all settlement activity, in part because he believed that the Israeli leader had repeatedly deceived him on this question, American officials said.</p>
        <p>In particular, they point to the Administration's giving Israel $400 million in guarantees two years ago on the condition that Israel not build settlements in certain areas and that it provide Washington with certain information on settlement building. None of those promises were fulfilled.</p>
        <p>"The Shamir Government's attitude was that if there was a loophole they would use it," one of the senior Administration officials said. "There was a consistent pattern of deception. With Rabin, the whole context will be different. Bush is not going to change his mind about wanting a freeze on settlements, but we now have an Israeli Government saying it wants to change priorities, it doesn't want to go on building settlements everywhere, so we don't have to worry about them saying one thing and doing another."</p>
        <p>Therefore, the official said, "the discussions with Rabin on this issue will have a very different character," and therefore a way will be found to work things out. Ideally, the official said, Mr. Rabin and Mr. Bush will reach an understanding in August and the legislation will be introduced in the Senate in September.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
