<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Seattle's Economy Slows, Many Like the Change of Pace</title>
    <meta content="29SEAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/29/national/29SEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Fremont</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Indiana</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Queen Anne</location>
        <org class="online_producer">The Boeing Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Amazon.com Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">RealNetworks Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Internet companies</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Adobe Systems Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Raban, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbeck, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D7173FF93AA15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Seattle's Economy Slows, Many Like the Change of Pace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, March 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many residents of Seattle, Wash, say they would welcome slowdown in city's booming economy; Boeing Co is leaving, and stocks of many Seattle Internet companies are in steep decline; city has had earthquake and drought; 19-straight-year economic expansion has brought crippling traffic jams, soaring real-estate prices and angst about changing character of what had been famously livable place; there is sense now that city needs to slow down, and also that city has damaged its blue-collar roots; in many ways, debate about Seattle's changing character is not new; several years ago movement called Lesser Seattle Inc arose against 'greaterism' that some felt civic boosters were foisting on city; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Boeing Company offered some stunning news to its hometown last week, many here took it as the latest bit in a string of misfortune stretching back to the turmoil in the streets when Seattle was the host to world trade talks.</p>
        <p>Microsoft is fighting an antitrust battle. The go-go dot-com economy is sagging, with the stock of Amazon  .com, RealNetworks and other Seattle Internet companies in steep decline. There has been an earthquake and a drought. And now Boeing, the biggest employer in the region, plans to move its headquarters somewhere else.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the Boeing Company offered some stunning news to its hometown last week, many here took it as the latest bit in a string of misfortune stretching back to the turmoil in the streets when Seattle was the host to world trade talks.</p>
        <p>Microsoft is fighting an antitrust battle. The go-go dot-com economy is sagging, with the stock of Amazon  .com, RealNetworks and other Seattle Internet companies in steep decline. There has been an earthquake and a drought. And now Boeing, the biggest employer in the region, plans to move its headquarters somewhere else.</p>
        <p>But ask people on the street about Boeing and a surprising theme emerges. Here, where a 19-straight-year economic expansion has brought crippling traffic jams, soaring real-estate prices and angst about the changing character of what had been a famously livable place, many residents feel that a slowdown in the economy would not  be so terrible.</p>
        <p>''Part of my reaction was, Yes! Go! Get out of here!'' declared Joel Monteith, 38, a business systems analyst at Adobe Systems Inc., the graphics software maker. ''That'll be a thousand less cars on the road.''</p>
        <p>Maria Zazycki, a dance-company manager who worries about getting squeezed out of her Capitol Hill apartment, had a similar response.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, the first thing I thought of was, lower rents,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Census figures show that the Puget Sound region grew by more than half a million people in the last decade, to 3.3 million, and a million more are expected in the next 25 years or so. While people here are not actively hoping for a recession, there is a sense that Seattle needs to slow down. There is also a sense that the city has damaged its blue-collar roots.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's a place that's comfortable anymore for the average working-class person, and that's a shame,'' said Caro Torgessen, a 44-year-old fisherwoman whose boat is based at the Port of Seattle's Fishermen's Terminal. ''You don't feel like it's O.K. to walk around here anymore if you're a person with grease under your fingers.''</p>
        <p>Fishermen's Terminal, which the local author Jonathan Raban calls the city's ''last bastion of old-fashioned work, with its nets, crab pots, paintbrushes and carpentering,'' is  convulsed by a debate: Should the port open the terminal to yachts and pleasure boaters? The idea strikes many who work on the docks and in the boats as blasphemy.</p>
        <p>Some Seattleites who have felt the ravages of the Internet economy seem to feel ambivalent about the city's downturn. ''The place changed; it's like it got greedier,'' said Anne Buckley, who was recently laid off as a design director when her employer, onhealth.com, was acquired by another company.</p>
        <p>Now, Ms. Buckley's stock options are, in industry lingo, underwater, or worthless. That is worrisome, especially since she has a 6 1/2-month-old daughter, Maureen, to care for. Yet Ms. Buckley, who was grocery shopping the other day in the Fremont neighborhood, said she saw a silver lining in the downturn.</p>
        <p>''It gives the Seattle area some breathing room,'' she said. ''It's got to figure out a way to grow a little more intelligently.''</p>
        <p>Boeing, by far the biggest employer in the region, says it plans to move only about 1,000 of about 80,000 jobs here out of the area, with its mammoth commercial aircraft unit staying put.</p>
        <p>But if, as some civic leaders fear, the company shifts more operations away, the results could be felt everywhere from the local market to hospitals to cultural and philanthropic circles. Nearly 18 percent of the recent $82.5 million campaign for the United Way of King County came from Boeing and its employees.</p>
        <p>One attraction of Seattle is its spectacular proximity to nature; as former Mayor Norm Rice once put it, this was a place where schoolchildren could ''feel their linkages to water and weather, to sense the unfathomable power of salmon returning to spawn after years at sea, to have mountains and the forests as anchors in their souls.''</p>
        <p>But now there is a constant fret  about how that connection has been eroded.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot less nature and a lot more junk,'' said Al Kropotkin, a blues musician and Seattle native who lives in the Capitol Hill neighborhood. ''There are ugly buildings popping up all over town like mushrooms after a spring rain.''</p>
        <p>In many ways, the debate about Seattle's changing character is not  new. This is where a movement called Lesser Seattle Inc. arose several years ago against the ''greaterism'' that some felt the civic boosters were foisting on the city. At  times, residents have voted to halt freeway construction or cap the number and height of skyscrapers.</p>
        <p>Then there is this lament, echoed  in various ways today: ''I remembered Seattle as a town sitting on hills beside a matchless harborage,'' said one observer of the place known as the Emerald City. But ''it is no longer so,'' he said. ''This Seattle had no relation to the one I remembered. The traffic rushed with murderous intensity.''</p>
        <p>That was John Steinbeck, writing in ''Travels with Charley'' in 1961.</p>
        <p>Moreover, only in the last few years did the city exceed its peak population of 1960. (It has 563,374 people, the 2000 census says.) It is  the region that has grown more.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Seattle felt ''like this little corner on the map that no one really knew much about,'' said Linda Bloomer, who works in the banquet department of a hotel and who moved here from Indiana 13 years ago. While the city once struck her back then as affordable, she says housing prices are now outrageous. A house near her apartment in the Queen Anne neighborhood sold for $125,000 when she moved here; it was recently divided into three units selling for $450,000 apiece.</p>
        <p>There are plenty of good things  about the way Seattle has changed,  said Sigrid Asmus, a freelance editor who moved from New York 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Culturally, there's a lot more going on,'' Ms. Asmus said. ''In many ways it's a more interesting place.''</p>
        <p>Asked if she approved of the city's  transformation, she paused and said, ''I'd say, 70 percent approve and 30 percent violently opposed.''</p>
        <p>That answer reflected an ambivalence apparent in the reaction to raucous street demonstrations in late 1999 during the World Trade Organization meeting, an event that city boosters had hoped would show off Seattle as a trade-friendly city.</p>
        <p>''There was some guilty pleasure in the whole thing,'' said Walt Crowley, who directs historylink.org, a Web site packed with Seattle history. ''The feeling was 'Yeah, we're a union town, we care about the environment, we're a little bit suspicious of all this globalism stuff.' So now  we're an eponym for anti-globalization. And we shouldn't be too terribly shocked when Boeing says, 'Well, we've got to get out of Dodge.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
