<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Premier's Effort to Oust Serbian Leader Is Blocked</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUDETIC, CHUCK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PANIC, MILAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILOSEVIC, SLOBODAN (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA1F3EF937A35751C1A964958260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Premier's Effort to Oust Serbian Leader Is Blocked</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SUDETIC,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SUDETIC, CHUCK</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia, Dec. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Election officials here today thwarted an attempt by Yugoslavia's Serbian-American Prime Minister, Milan Panic, to oust Serbia's nationalist President, Slobodan Milosevic, in elections set for Dec. 20 by invalidating Mr. Panic's candidacy for the Serbian presidency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic announced Tuesday that he would face off against Mr. Milosevic, but then the Serbian election commission's chairman, Caslav Ignjatovic, said Mr. Panic's candidacy was rejected because he failed to meet a one-year residency requirement enacted just a month ago by the republic's parliament, which Mr. Milosevic's supporters control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Election officials here today thwarted an attempt by Yugoslavia's Serbian-American Prime Minister, Milan Panic, to oust Serbia's nationalist President, Slobodan Milosevic, in elections set for Dec. 20 by invalidating Mr. Panic's candidacy for the Serbian presidency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic announced Tuesday that he would face off against Mr. Milosevic, but then the Serbian election commission's chairman, Caslav Ignjatovic, said Mr. Panic's candidacy was rejected because he failed to meet a one-year residency requirement enacted just a month ago by the republic's parliament, which Mr. Milosevic's supporters control.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the commission came as fighting continued in war-torn Bosnia and Herzegovina. 'A Slap to Democracy'</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic criticized the commission today, saying he had maintained an apartment in Belgrade and headed a local pharmaceutical firm for more than a year.</p>
        <p>"Today it's clear that the people ruling Serbia fear free, honest elections," Mr. Panic said in a statement issued tonight. "The decision that I cannot be a candidate for Serbia's president is completely absurd."</p>
        <p>"I was born in Belgrade," he said. "I grew up in Belgrade. I lived here 25 years."</p>
        <p>"I will not accept such a slap to democracy," he said. "This is insane."</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic, 62 years old, fled Communist Yugoslavia 36 years ago and made millions of dollars marketing pharmaceuticals in California. He returned to Belgrade in July after the President Dobrica Cosic asked him to head the Government of what is left of Yugoslavia, made up of only Serbia and Montenegro.</p>
        <p>Once considered a pawn of Mr. Milosevic, Mr. Panic has become the Serbian President's only serious rival.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ignjatovic, at a news conference here this afternoon, denied accusations that the commission had succumbed to political pressure.</p>
        <p>"We established the facts without any political pressure and applied the law," said Mr. Ignjatovic, who also presides over the Supreme Court, to which Mr. Panic may appeal the commission's decision within 48 hours.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats immediately condemned the election commission's decision, and the leaders of several small opposition parties warned that they might boycott the election.</p>
        <p>"The real reason for this decision is the Socialist Party of Serbia's fear of Milan Panic's candidacy," said the president of the Democratic Party's executive committee, Zoran Djindjic.</p>
        <p>"It is impossible to believe that a person nominated by the ruling party to become the federal prime minister now lacks the basis upon which to run as president of one of the federation's units," he said. "By taking this decision, the republican election commission has called into question the very existence of the federation and the fairness of the elections and undermined the international standing of our country."</p>
        <p>The United Nations peacekeeping force in the former Yugoslavia halted air flights related to peacekeeping operations for 48 hours today after bullets struck a plane carrying the Sarajevo commander of the multinational force just after it took off from the Bosnian capital this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Six bullets shot by unidentified gunmen pierced the tail of the Soviet-built Antonov 12 airplane carrying Major Gen. Philippe Morillon of France at about 4 P.M., said a United Nations spokeswoman, Shannon Boyd. No injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Police Fire Into Crowd</p>
        <p>PRISTINA, Yugoslavia, Dec. 3 (AP) -- Serbian police officers today fired on a crowd at an outdoor market in the capital of Kosovo province, killing at least one person and wounding another, news reports said.</p>
        <p>Kosovo appears likely to be the next site of major ethnic violence in the Balkans. More than 90 percent of Kosovo residents are ethnic Albanians, but their rights are suppressed, and the province is ruled by Serbia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
