<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Designing Minds To the Millstone</title>
    <meta content="04TEDD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/04/garden/04TEDD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1563620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TED Conference</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wurman, Richard Saul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Patricia Leigh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D9123FF937A35750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Designing Minds To the Millstone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Designing Minds to the Millstone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LEIGH BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Patricia Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>MONTEREY, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Annual TED conference in Monterey, Calif, brings together 'thought leaders' from worlds of technology, entertainment and design; photo; 19-year-old conclave was founded by information designer Richard Saul Wurman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Question: What makes 800 of the country's smartest, most wildly successful architects, designers, inventors, chief executives, psychologists, ichthyologists, cosmologists, economists, digital artists and other members of the creative, academic and financial elite happy?</p>
        <p>Answer: Ruminating about ''The Pursuit of Happiness'' at the TED conference, the annual $4,000-a-pop three-and-a-half-day hedonistic be-in for the brain that brings together ''thought leaders'' from the worlds of technology, entertainment and design. Perhaps only at TED, as the 19-year-old conclave is known, would sexy Silicon Valley billionaires like Sergey Brin and Larry Page, the founders of Google, commune with nerdy M.I.T. professors who will attempt to explain string theory while hailing a taxicab.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The TED conference brings together "thought leaders" from the worlds of technology, entertainment and design.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Question: What makes 800 of the country's smartest, most wildly successful architects, designers, inventors, chief executives, psychologists, ichthyologists, cosmologists, economists, digital artists and other members of the creative, academic and financial elite happy?</p>
        <p>Answer: Ruminating about ''The Pursuit of Happiness'' at the TED conference, the annual $4,000-a-pop three-and-a-half-day hedonistic be-in for the brain that brings together ''thought leaders'' from the worlds of technology, entertainment and design. Perhaps only at TED, as the 19-year-old conclave is known, would sexy Silicon Valley billionaires like Sergey Brin and Larry Page, the founders of Google, commune with nerdy M.I.T. professors who will attempt to explain string theory while hailing a taxicab.</p>
        <p>To the TEDsters assembled here, happiness is to some extent a product of design. It is hearing about a prototype of a flying car (being developed by the inventor Paul Moller -- he's serious), or the chance to view a Johnny-Depp-look-alike robot head with video camera eyes and tiny electronic sensors embedded in its skin. The robot responds to human voices with realistic facial expressions and is made from ''frubber,'' a high-tech polymer, the brainchild of David Hanson, a 34-year-old doctoral candidate at the University of Texas at Dallas. Founded by the information designer Richard Saul Wurman, the conference has historically been a male-heavy, somewhat geeky inside-baseball kind of event, a launch-pad-by-the-sea for the Next Big Thing, from the unveiling of the Macintosh computer and Sony compact disc to the hatching of the M.I.T. Media Laboratory.</p>
        <p>These days, however, the TEDsters are increasingly looking outward. Dean Kamen, perhaps best known as the inventor of the Segway Human Transporter, the gyroscopic electronic scooter, is working on the distribution of a portable water purifier to help fend off disease in developing countries. William McDonough, who began his career as an architect, is now also a global sustainable design adviser who develops breakthrough toxin- and carcinogen-free textiles and is consulting with Chinese officials on urban design and new sustainable housing for 400 million people over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Known for ''transformative experiences,'' in the words of Chris Anderson, the 47-year-old publishing magnate whose nonprofit organization, the Sapling Foundation, bought the conference in 2000, TED has long been a brain safari with plasma televisions in which people like the Amazon.com founder Jeff Bezos, the America Online founder Stephen M. Case and the ''Simpsons'' creator Matt Groening sip Starbucks while milling about curvilinear algorithmic steel columns designed by an ''architect-morphologist'' trying to decode ''the architectural genome.''</p>
        <p>The conference is known for moments of mind-bending cognitive dissonance. One moment, you are listening to Felix Dennis, the British publisher of Maxim magazine, recite his own Elizabethan-style poems by candlelight, complete with ''thys'' and ''thines'' and ''lady fairs.'' The next minute you are hearing an economist from the University of Chicago dissect the financial health of street gangs, comparing their corporate hierarchies to McDonald's. Reports from the front of scientific happiness research by Harvard neuropsychologists and others conclude that meditation is good and that the things we think will make us happy -- or sad -- do not radically change our happiness quotient.</p>
        <p>To promote happiness, a high-tech program by Macromedia was designed to help attendees find conferencegoers who shared their interests -- a sort of intellectual dating service presented in a color-coded graphic of blue and red pins that looked suspiciously like television primary coverage. (This forlorn participant, a technophobe, came up with only two not quite kindred souls.)</p>
        <p>Things like this happen at TED. Nevertheless, its historically self-referential culture seems to be shifting somewhat. As if to underscore a new other-directed definition of happiness, Mr. Anderson, who has funneled the roughly $1 million proceeds from the conference -- formerly a profit-seeking venture -- into various worthy causes, announced the creation of the Ted Prize, ''an award program like nothing else out there,'' in which three ''remarkable people'' will be granted three wishes, presumably to be fulfilled by zillionaire, clout-heavy and intellectually supercharged TEDsters. As a backup, each winner will also be awarded $100,000. The plan is for the winners, who will be communally nominated and announced later this year, to unveil their wishes at next year's conference, where they will be anointed as ''the most perfect TEDsters we can find,'' Mr. Anderson said. They will also be given a three-year pass to TED (worth $12,000).</p>
        <p>''We are going to proactively seek them out,'' he added, saying a wish might include the use of a supercomputer to solve a problem.</p>
        <p>Eve Ensler, creator of ''The Vagina Monologues,'' noted a ratio of men to women at TED heavily weighted to people not involved in such discourses (she was one of seven female speakers of 45 at the conference). But Ms. Ensler, who has been spending much of her time on activism around the world to stop violence against women, was buoyed by the notion of the wishes. ''I'd love to see these kinds of thinkers put their minds to violence against women,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Martin Seligman, a professor and director of the Positive Psychology Network at the University of Pennsylvania, saw cause for optimism, even in this era of disgraced chief executives and former dot-com princes. ''When 15th-century Florence asked what it should do with its material abundance, it decided to invest in genius and beauty,'' he said. ''That kind of thing only comes once a century. For technology entertainment and design, this is the Florentine moment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
