<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baseball;   Roger Clemens: He's Just the Same, And He's Better</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="381493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOSTON RED SOX</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLEMENS, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D8143CF930A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baseball;   Roger Clemens: He's Just the Same, And He's Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some things never change: the boyish looks, the quiet manner, the imposing way he stands on the mound, leaning forward and peering toward home and somehow seeming in control of every moment. In many ways, Roger Clemens is the same now as he has always been, except, perhaps, that he is better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some things never change: the boyish looks, the quiet manner, the imposing way he stands on the mound, leaning forward and peering toward home and somehow seeming in control of every moment. In many ways, Roger Clemens is the same now as he has always been, except, perhaps, that he is better.</p>
        <p>But that was then; this is now. Clemens, who turned 28 years old Aug. 4, has evolved in both style and substance as a pitcher. Some people notice it. Others don't.</p>
        <p>''He's changed since I came over here,'' said one of his teammates, Mike Boddicker, who joined the Red Sox from the Baltimore Orioles in mid-1988. ''He's a smart pitcher. He's not a thrower.''</p>
        <p>Clemens won his 20th game of the season last Thursday night against the Indians in Cleveland. This is the third time in five seasons he has reached that total, and he has done so with a flourish: a 1.95 earned run average, four shutouts in his last eight starts, an eight-game winning streak and, in August, a 6-0 record and an earned run average of 1.09. He has allowed just 48 base runners in 49Y innings and hasn't given up a home run since the break for the All-Star Game.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who will next pitch tomorrow against Dave Stewart and the Oakland Athletics, could become just the second American League pitcher to finish a season with an earned run average under 2.00 since the dawn of the designated hitter in 1973. The other was the Yankees' Ron Guidry, who went 25-3 with a 1.74 e.r.a. in 1978. Clemens could also join Steve Carlton, Sandy Koufax, Jim Palmer and Tom Seaver as the only pitchers to win three Cy Young awards.</p>
        <p>Although his style may have changed in subtle ways, batters no doubt see the same Clemens they have always seen. Opponents are batting .228 against him this season, .189 with men on base, .174 with runners in scoring position, .158 with two or more men on and .135 with a runner on third. Different?  ''I don't really see any difference,'' said Wade Boggs, Boston's third baseman. ''There has been some change as far as maturity goes. He was a raw talent as a kid, but he's matured now. Basically, though, he's the same.'' This is one way that he's the same: ''Roger is the kind of guy who, if he loses to you in dominoes, he'll stay up until 2 in the morning trying to beat you so he can go to sleep,'' said Marty Barrett, the Boston second baseman. ''That's the way he is.''</p>
        <p>Clemens's intense nature has never left him. After he beat the Toronto Blue Jays, 1-0, for his 19th victory in a critical meeting between the two teams last week, he sounded as if the game was still circulating through his system.</p>
        <p>''I thrive on situations like this,'' he told reporters after the game. ''I was a little sluggish, and it was the kind of day when you throw hard even when you don't really like it. I had to rely on emotion and adrenaline.''</p>
        <p>Clemens restricts his chats with the press to the days he pitches and is firm in this rule. So it is left for those who know him to discuss the changes they have seen in him.</p>
        <p>Seaver, now a Yankee television broadcaster, pitched for Boston in 1986. Seaver said he had not seen Clemens pitch this season but had studied his record well.</p>
        <p>''When I look at the numbers and see how he 'struggled' last year, then ended up winning his last few decisions when he could've packed it in, that says something,'' Seaver said. ''He's a different pitcher now in the sense that he's still learning and progressing. He continues to be a better pitcher. He's still overpowering, but there's more knowledge to draw on. He has two wells to choose from.''</p>
        <p>Clemens began throwing a forkball two years ago, and this has made him even harder for batters to hit.</p>
        <p>''I think he's more dominant now because of the forkball,'' said Tom Brunansky, who joined the Red Sox from the St. Louis Cardinals this season. ''It makes the batter a little more hesitant. You see it coming, and then the bottom just falls out of it.''</p>
        <p>With more pitches to choose from, Clemens has perhaps become less reliant on his fastball. He'll finish the season with 200 strikeouts again, his fifth consecutive season of 200 or more, but he has struck out 10 or more batters in a game only 3 times this season.</p>
        <p>Still, his strikeout rate remains a marker by which others judge him and a symbol of his power. When he strikes out 10 or more, his record is 33-2 with six no-decisions.</p>
        <p>''When I was in Baltimore,'' Boddicker said, ''he had unbelievable stuff. He'd make some pitches that would make you wonder what he was throwing, or make you feel he was just toying with guys. He doesn't have the 95-mile-an-hour stuff, but he's learned he can get by with less. He spots the ball better, and he knows when to bounce a breaking ball or throw a forkball in the dirt.''</p>
        <p>Boddicker said Clemens's minor ailments - a bad back, shoulder trouble - had caused him to make adjustments that he might not otherwise have made.</p>
        <p>''Injuries can force you to change,'' Boddicker said. ''He's learned to pitch through stuff.''</p>
        <p>Having more help has also benefited Clemens. The Red Sox are on their way to the American League East title because of their pitching, which has been surprising if nothing else. Clemens may have 20 victories, but Boddicker has 14, Greg Harris has 12 and, going into yesterday's game with the Yankees, Dana Kiecker and Tom Bolton had combined for 13. Clemens doesn't have to do everything alone.</p>
        <p>''In '86, he stopped so many losing streaks that we just expected it,'' said the Boston outfielder Mike Greenwell. ''There was a lot of weight on his shoulders. We still expect him to win, but we expect everybody else in the rotation to win, too.</p>
        <p>''Roger is still the same person. He's what we call a gamer. He's a battler, and he expects to win every ball game. He bears down more when we're down by a run or two.''</p>
        <p>Clemens has won just once in four playoff and two World Series starts, but, Greenwell said, ''He'll be better in the playoffs than he was before.''</p>
        <p>''He's been there,'' Greenwell continued. ''By the time we got to the playoffs in the past, he was run down because all the weight had been on his shoulders. But it's not there now, and that's a plus for us.''</p>
        <p>Clemens may also have demanded less from his body earlier in the season so that he could hold some power in reserve for later. In August, he threw three complete games. In, July, two. In June, none.</p>
        <p>He is the game's most dominant pitcher. He has a 115-50 career record, has not lost a start since July 20 and has an earned run average of 0.80 during his current victory streak. He hasn't permitted more than two earned runs in a game in more than two months.</p>
        <p>And his role as Boston's single most important player seems to suit him now more than ever.</p>
        <p>''I don't think Roger in '86 was comfortable about being the No. 1 guy, not from a maturity standpoint,'' Seaver said. ''I get the feeling he's very comfortable now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
