<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>National Semiconductor Settles On a New Chief</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="848162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL SEMICONDUCTOR CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LSI LOGIC CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALLA, BRIAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AMELIO, GILBERT F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE1439F937A35756C0A960958260" item-length="344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>National Semiconductor Settles On a New Chief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA CLARA, Calif., May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Semiconductor Corporation said today that it had named Brian L.  Halla chairman, chief executive and president, succeeding Gilbert F. Amelio, who left in February to head Apple Computer Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halla, 49, will lead National Semiconductor's office of the president, which also includes Ellen Hancock, Richard Beyer and Kirk Pond. Those three executives had been leading the company since Mr. Amelio's departure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Semiconductor Corporation said today that it had named Brian L.  Halla chairman, chief executive and president, succeeding Gilbert F. Amelio, who left in February to head Apple Computer Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halla, 49, will lead National Semiconductor's office of the president, which also includes Ellen Hancock, Richard Beyer and Kirk Pond. Those three executives had been leading the company since Mr. Amelio's departure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halla had been executive vice president of the LSI Logic Corporation.</p>
        <p>The appointment comes just a week after National Semiconductor warned that fiscal fourth-quarter earnings would be disappointing because of falling sales of its electronic components.</p>
        <p>National Semiconductor had been expected to earn 40 cents a share in the fourth quarter ending May 26, based on the average estimate of 15 analysts surveyed by Zacks Investment Research.</p>
        <p>Late last month, National Semiconductor said earnings might be "substantially below" those forecasts. It blamed slowing orders from computer makers, which are working their way through bloated inventories of components.</p>
        <p>The chip maker, based in Santa Clara, Calif., said it expected to see a return to growth after the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Revenue in the fourth quarter could be much lower as well, the company said.  In the quarter a year ago, National Semiconductor earned $81.2 million, or 62 cents a share, on sales of $669.8 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halla's appointment was announced after the stock market closed. Earlier, National Semiconductor's shares ended trading up 25 cents, at $16.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>National Semiconductor posted losses totaling nearly $200 million from 1989 to 1991, and Mr. Amelio is credited with turning the company around. He revamped the company into seven management units that report to the president's office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amelio, 52, was named chairman and chief executive at Apple on Feb. 2, replacing Michael Spindler. Mr. Amelio had been a director of Apple since 1994.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
