<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viacom Registers Strong Results Despite a 61% Plunge in Profit</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="848161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">VIACOM INC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DE1439F937A35756C0A960958260" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viacom Registers Strong Results Despite a 61% Plunge in Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Viacom Inc. reported a strong performance yesterday for its first quarter, helped in large part by an alliance with the Kirch Group of Germany.</p>
        <p>While earnings fell 61 percent, they and the operating cash for the quarter were much better than many analysts had expected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Viacom Inc. reported a strong performance yesterday for its first quarter, helped in large part by an alliance with the Kirch Group of Germany.</p>
        <p>While earnings fell 61 percent, they and the operating cash for the quarter were much better than many analysts had expected.</p>
        <p>Viacom, the parent of Paramount Pictures and Blockbuster Video, earned $27.8 million, or 3 cents a share, down from $71.2 million, or 15 cents a share, in the comparable quarter a year earlier. Revenue rose 3.8 percent, to $2.8 billion from $2.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Wall Street had forecast a loss of 3 cents a share, based on the average estimate of 12 analysts surveyed by Zacks Investment Research.</p>
        <p>Underlying the earnings surprise was the company's cash flow, which was higher than expected. Operating cash flow -- earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization -- is often considered a better measure of a media company's performance. Cash flow is especially important to a company like Viacom, which is still carrying substantial debt from a number of large acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Cash flow for the quarter was $494 million, down from $516 million a year earlier, but the 1995 quarter included a gain of $88 million from an accounting  change, Jessica Reif, an analyst with Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, said in a report.</p>
        <p>Viacom said almost one-fifth of its cash flow, or $100 million, stemmed from  a five-year agreement signed last month to provide television and film programs to the Kirch Group. The agreement, which was retroactive to the beginning of the year, is valued at $1.7 billion over 10 years, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Paramount Pictures and the entertainment group had cash flow of $163.4 million, far more than the $125 million that analysts expected after the poor performance of "Sabrina," starring Harrison Ford, and other films. Cash flow was bolstered by the strong box-office results of "Eye for An Eye," starring Sally Fields, among other films, the company said. The company said selling the video  rights to Mel Gibson's "Braveheart" also helped results.</p>
        <p>A year earlier, cash flow of $189.8 million included a $68 million gain from  an accounting change and the results from "Forrest Gump," starring Tom Hanks.</p>
        <p>Viacom's Spelling Entertainment television production company, which has been put up for sale, had a loss of $3 million, compared with profits of $38 million  a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Cash flow at the networks and broadcasting segment rose 18 percent, to $148.3 million from $125.6 million, because of strong revenue from the company's cable  television channels. Viacom's cable networks -- including MTV, Nickelodeon and Showtime -- reported a 20 percent increase in cash flow to $94 million.</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
