<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martínez Will Pass on the All-Star Game</title>
    <meta content="08shea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/08/sports/baseball/08shea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martinez, Pedro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DF1630F93BA35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martínez Will Pass on the All-Star Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Martínez, Mets' Season Trumps the All-Star Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CURTIS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pedro Martínez, who has had a standout first half of the season with the Mets, said on Thursday that he would forfeit his spot on the National League team for the All-Star Game next week.</p>
        <p>Martínez is scheduled to start Sunday for the Mets in Pittsburgh, the last game before the break, and he said he would not want to pitch again just two days later. Although he usually throws in a side session two days after he pitches in a game, he said he does not throw with full effort, something he would require of himself in an All-Star Game. His decision now leaves him available to pitch on a regular amount of rest next Friday in a crucial series against the Braves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WASHINGTON, July 7 - Pedro Martínez, who has had a standout first half of the season with the Mets, said on Thursday that he would forfeit his spot on the National League team for the All-Star Game next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pedro Martínez, who has had a standout first half of the season with the Mets, said on Thursday that he would forfeit his spot on the National League team for the All-Star Game next week.</p>
        <p>Martínez is scheduled to start Sunday for the Mets in Pittsburgh, the last game before the break, and he said he would not want to pitch again just two days later. Although he usually throws in a side session two days after he pitches in a game, he said he does not throw with full effort, something he would require of himself in an All-Star Game. His decision now leaves him available to pitch on a regular amount of rest next Friday in a crucial series against the Braves.</p>
        <p>Martínez also cited the extra significance now attached to the All-Star Game, with the winning league earning home-field advantage in the World Series. ''If I couldn't pitch,'' he said, ''it makes no sense for me to occupy my place.</p>
        <p>''It's not in the best interest of myself or the organization for me to watch everyone else compete and sit down in the bullpen,'' he added. ''I would like for somebody else to compete.''</p>
        <p>After Martínez made his decision, National League Manager Tony La Russa picked Phillies closer Billy Wagner and shortstop Jimmy Rollins to replace Martínez and the Dodgers' Cesar Izturis, who is on the disabled list. Izturis has been hampered by a sore right hamstring for nearly a month.</p>
        <p>Martínez, who is 9-3 with a 2.80 earned run average in 17 starts this season, earned his seventh All-Star selection last month. He has attended four of the games and pitched in three.</p>
        <p>He dressed but asked American League Manager Mike Hargrove not to pitch him during the 1998 contest, and he missed the 2000 game while on the disabled list. In 2002, Martínez skipped the game for personal reasons, went home to the Dominican Republic, and returned late to the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>Martínez was also playing for the Red Sox when he started the 1999 All-Star Game at Fenway Park. He has not allowed a run in four innings of All-Star pitching, and he tied a record for the American League with five strikeouts in his two innings of work in the 1999 game.</p>
        <p>Mets General Manager Omar Minaya said that Martínez met with him and the team's chief operating officer, Jeff Wilpon, before announcing his decision. Martínez said he wasn't sure about how he would spend the time off from baseball. Regardless, Minaya said the team supported its star's decision.</p>
        <p>''When it's all said and done, it's about his health,'' Minaya said. ''And it's about him being ready for the second half.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
