<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Gets Out of Jam, Then Gets Some Help</title>
    <meta content="03YANK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Royals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DF1430F930A35756C0A961958260" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Gets Out of Jam, Then Gets Some Help</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Kansas City Royals, 9-1, Kauffman Stadium, Kansas City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Cone hustled from the pitcher's mound to the dugout after a precarious seventh inning tonight, exhaling and sweating with each quick step. Cone wanted a safe seat because he had narrowly avoided ruining a productive night. He was still clinging to a 2-1 lead, so he was happy.</p>
        <p>Five minutes later, Cone felt safer and happier when Bernie Williams pummeled Jim Pittsley's fat pitch for a two-run homer in the eighth inning that gave the Yankees a much-needed cushion. Forty-five minutes later, Cone was much safer and much happier after a five-run ninth helped vault the Yankees to a deceptive 9-1 victory over the Royals at Kauffman Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Cone hustled from the pitcher's mound to the dugout after a precarious seventh inning tonight, exhaling and sweating with each quick step. Cone wanted a safe seat because he had narrowly avoided ruining a productive night. He was still clinging to a 2-1 lead, so he was happy.</p>
        <p>Five minutes later, Cone felt safer and happier when Bernie Williams pummeled Jim Pittsley's fat pitch for a two-run homer in the eighth inning that gave the Yankees a much-needed cushion. Forty-five minutes later, Cone was much safer and much happier after a five-run ninth helped vault the Yankees to a deceptive 9-1 victory over the Royals at Kauffman Stadium.</p>
        <p>Even though Williams and Tino Martinez had two-run homers as the Yankees (15-13) earned their 10th victory in 13 games and inched two games over the .500 mark for the first time, the most riveting moment occurred with Cone in the seventh.</p>
        <p>The ninth-inning outburst, in which the Yankees scored four unearned runs, simply made it easier for Mariano Rivera to garner his easiest save of the season. But this was Cone's night to look awful one moment, awesome the next and admirable over all.</p>
        <p>''That's his heart,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''Any other pitcher, you wouldn't take him into the seventh inning. He got himself into trouble. He was going to get himself out of trouble. That's why he's great.''</p>
        <p>On a misty night, Cone threw 121 pitches and stranded base runners. His most important sequence came in the seventh after a walk, a single and a bunt placed Royals on second and third with one out. Suddenly his 2-1 lead looked puny. Still, Cone struck out David Howard on a 2-2 slider and induced Jay Bell to line out to shortstop. Cone exhaled on his way to the dugout. It was still a game then and that is why his effort was so critical.</p>
        <p>''I was able to make some big pitches when I was in trouble,'' Cone said. ''I got myself in trouble. Again, I felt lucky to get out of there with a one-run lead.''</p>
        <p>Despite allowing only one run on five hits in seven innings, Cone felt fortunate to win his third straight start. He struck out six but walked five. He leads the American League with 55 strikeouts in 47 innings, but the right-hander has also walked 32.</p>
        <p>''I'm on a pace to strike out 300 and walk 200,'' Cone joked. ''This has got to stop. I got to get better. This can't continue.''</p>
        <p>Can Williams and Martinez continue to stay so hot? Williams doubled to lead off the fourth, which was the first hit off Pittsley, and Martinez followed with his team-best 10th homer to give him a major league high of 36 runs batted in. In addition to his two-run homer, Williams stole a base and threw out Jeff King at home. He was also involved in a crunching collision at the plate with Tim Spehr in which he was tagged out.</p>
        <p>''I was fortunate to do the things I should do,'' Williams said.</p>
        <p>Cone, the man of the night, was more expressive about the center fielder.</p>
        <p>''Every year, he seems to do something that surprises you,'' Cone said. ''He's one of the best in the game right now. He's gotten more and more confident with every at-bat and every hit. He's a very, very dangerous player right now.'</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees have described DARRYL STRAWBERRY's injury as inflammation behind the left kneecap, but Manager JOE TORRE said Strawberry told him the injury involves cartilage. ''I talked to Darryl and he said it's cartilage-related,'' Torre explained. ''We're going to rest it to see if that takes care of it. I don't know the next step if it doesn't get better.'' The next step could be surgery, since Strawberry's left knee, which was drained April 11, has not responded to treatment. . . . DWIGHT GOODEN is progressing from a hernia operation on April 14 and is expected to start for the Yankees against Class AAA Columbus in an exhibition game on May 12. . . . The Royals' Bip Roberts was ejected in the fifth after he was called out on strikes. He then fired his bat and helmet toward Umpire TIM MCCLELLAND and probably earned a significant fine. . . . The first pitch was delayed 32 minutes by rain.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
