<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Soldier Convicted in Race-Based Killings</title>
    <meta content="03TRIA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fort Bragg (Nc)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Carolina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fayetteville (Nc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Malcolm Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burmeister, James N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burden, Jackie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D61630F930A35756C0A961958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Soldier Convicted in Race-Based Killings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, N.C., May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North Carolina jury convicts second former soldier, 22-year-old Malcolm Wright Jr, in murder of black couple in 1995; death penalty hearing to follow; Wright photo; James N Burmeister was sentenced to life in prison in February for racial killing of Jackie Burden and Michael James (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A jury today convicted a second white former Army paratrooper on murder and conspiracy charges in the killings of a black couple in North Carolina in 1995.</p>
        <p>The former soldier, Malcolm Wright Jr., 22, of Lexington, Ky., was found guilty on two counts of first-degree murder and one count of conspiracy to commit first-degree murder in the deaths of Jackie Burden, 27, and Michael James, 36, who were shot to death on Dec. 7, 1995, in Fayetteville, an Army town near Fort Bragg. The jury, 11 whites and 1 black, will now hear evidence on whether to impose the death penalty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A jury today convicted a second white former Army paratrooper on murder and conspiracy charges in the killings of a black couple in North Carolina in 1995.</p>
        <p>The former soldier, Malcolm Wright Jr., 22, of Lexington, Ky., was found guilty on two counts of first-degree murder and one count of conspiracy to commit first-degree murder in the deaths of Jackie Burden, 27, and Michael James, 36, who were shot to death on Dec. 7, 1995, in Fayetteville, an Army town near Fort Bragg. The jury, 11 whites and 1 black, will now hear evidence on whether to impose the death penalty.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 27, a jury in Fayetteville convicted another white former Army private, James N. Burmeister 2d, on two counts of first-degree murder and conspiracy in the same deaths. Mr. Burmeister, 21, of Thompson, Pa., is serving two consecutive life sentences at the Central Prison in Raleigh after a jury deadlocked on March 6 on the question of execution. The vote was 11 to 1 in favor of executing him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright's trial was moved here, to New Hanover County Superior Court, 100 miles from the crime scene, because of pretrial publicity stemming from Mr. Burmeister's conviction.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors said that the killings of Ms. Burden and Mr. James had been racially motivated and that Mr. Burmeister and Mr. Wright were neo-Nazi skinheads who had chosen their victims randomly. Both men  were once members of the elite 82d Airborne Division at Fort Bragg; the Army discharged them last summer.</p>
        <p>The killings led Army Secretary Togo D. West Jr. to initiate a worldwide inquiry into extremist activity in the ranks. Defense Department policy bars members of the armed forces from actively participating in groups that espouse racism or white supremacy, but it does not ban membership in such organizations.</p>
        <p>The inquiry found little evidence of overt racism, but it led to discharges for 22 soldiers, including those charged in the Fayetteville killings, who were found to have participated actively in extremist activity.</p>
        <p>Karon Knox, Mr. James's sister, expressed relief at the verdict. ''It's been a long year for us,'' she said, standing on the courthouse steps. ''But it's the beginning of the end. We're just so thankful to the judicial system, to the prosecutors and the judge and the jurors.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Knox added, ''I have faith in our judicial system again.''</p>
        <p>The jury deliberated in Mr. Wright's case for less than a day.  The main prosecution witness was the same as at Mr. Burmeister's trial: Randy Lee Meadows Jr., another white former paratrooper at Fort Bragg who was also charged in the case and who pleaded guilty to conspiracy and accessory charges. Mr. Meadows, 23, of Mulkeytown, Ill., will be sentenced in the fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meadows testified that he had driven Mr. Burmeister and Mr. Wright to the area where Mr. James and Ms. Burden were first spotted. He said he had heard six gunshots just minutes after his friends had left the car. After the three were arrested, Mr. Meadows testified, Mr. Burmeister told him that he had shot Ms. Burden and Mr. James, joking that he had done a community service and ''they put me in jail for it.''</p>
        <p>The prosecution argued that Mr. Burmeister had fired the shots because he wanted a spider-web tattoo, a sign in certain skinhead groups that its wearer had killed a black person. Mr. Wright has such a tattoo.</p>
        <p>The prosecution told the jurors that they should find Mr. Wright guilty because ''if you run with the pack, you're responsible for the kill.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright's lawyer, Jonathan Broun, had argued that Mr. Wright ''did not shoot anybody and did not want anyone to die'' and that Mr. Burmeister had acted alone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
