<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leading Suffolk Democrat Pleads Guilty in Bribery Case</title>
    <meta content="07SUFF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/07/nyregion/07suffolk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1579818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Steve (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baranello, Stephen J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prospect, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DE173CF934A35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leading Suffolk Democrat Pleads Guilty in Bribery Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Leading Suffolk Democrat Pleads Guilty in Bribery Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen J Baranello, top campaign adviser to County Exec Steve Levy of Suffolk County, NY, pleads guilty to two felony charges in bribery and bid-rigging case and agrees to testify against co-defendant Wayne Prospect and to supply information to continuing grand jury investigation into corruption (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Long Island politician who served as a top campaign adviser to the new Suffolk County executive pleaded guilty yesterday to two felony charges in a bribery and bid-rigging case.</p>
        <p>The politician, Stephen J. Baranello, 44, of Medford, became the first Democratic casualty in a string of corruption prosecutions that had until recently focused on Republicans in the town of Brookhaven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Long Island politician who served as a top campaign adviser to the new Suffolk County executive pleaded guilty yesterday to two felony charges in a bribery and bid-rigging case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Long Island politician who served as a top campaign adviser to the new Suffolk County executive pleaded guilty yesterday to two felony charges in a bribery and bid-rigging case.</p>
        <p>The politician, Stephen J. Baranello, 44, of Medford, became the first Democratic casualty in a string of corruption prosecutions that had until recently focused on Republicans in the town of Brookhaven.</p>
        <p>During Steve Levy's campaign for county executive last year, Mr. Baranello conferred with him virtually every day. Mr. Levy, who campaigned as an anticorruption reformer, was elected as Suffolk's first Democratic county executive since the 1980's. The crimes that Mr. Baranello admitted to yesterday started before Mr. Levy took office, and there is no suggestion that he had any connection to them.</p>
        <p>After being charged two weeks ago, Mr. Baranello resigned as a member of the Suffolk County Democratic Party's executive committee and as the executive director of the Brookhaven Town Democratic Committee. This week, he also quit his $105,000-a-year job as director of internal communications at the Suffolk off-track betting agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baranello inherited a legendary name in local politics. His father, Dominic, was the party's county chairman for more than 30 years and also served as the party's statewide chairman.</p>
        <p>In an appearance yesterday in Suffolk County Court in Riverhead before Acting Justice Michael F. Mullen of State Supreme Court, Stephen Baranello admitted to two counts involving bribery and conspiracy. Three related counts are being dropped.</p>
        <p>In a deal with the county district attorney's office, Mr. Baranello has agreed to testify against a co-defendant, Wayne Prospect, and to supply information to a continuing grand jury investigation into corruption. As part of the agreement, Mr. Baranello submitted a sealed statement about matters beyond his own case. The details were not released.</p>
        <p>In his guilty plea, Mr. Baranello acknowledged that he and Mr. Prospect, a former Democratic county legislator from Huntington, accepted a $10,000 bribe and promised in return to give inside bidding information on a county contract for a public works project. He said that they also expected to share thousands of dollars in future payments. In fact, the man who paid the bribe was an undercover investigator.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baranello, who faces three to nine years in prison, declined to comment outside the courtroom.</p>
        <p>''It was an airtight case against both of them,'' said Mr. Baranello's lawyer, Floyd Sarisohn. ''They had such specifics. They even had a video camera watching them at a diner, and the table they were sitting at was wired. How much better of a case can you get?''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Prospect, who is now a Conservative, said that he would be exonerated.</p>
        <p>Commenting on the plea, Mr. Levy said in an interview, ''There were so many emotions, from shock to anger, disappointment and even concern for the family.'' He expressed faith that ''the people understand that my appointees had nothing to do with this.''</p>
        <p>But the Suffolk Republican Party chairwoman, Patricia Acampora, criticized Mr. Levy. ''The whole thing is very troublesome, after an election in which he ran on an anticorruption campaign and now we have his leading adviser, the first person he talked to in the morning and the last one at night, pleading guilty to all these charges,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A political consultant who works mostly for Republicans, Michael D. Dawidziak, said: ''No question, it's an embarrassment anytime one of your top advisers gets caught in wrongdoing.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dawidziak said of Mr. Levy, ''I have not heard even a snippet of a suggestion that he was involved in any way.'' The potential for lasting political damage from scandals depends on how officials respond to them, he said. ''It looks like Levy has been aboveboard and honest in handling it.''</p>
        <p>The Suffolk Democratic Party chairman, Richard H. Schaffer, said that Mr. Baranello ''owes an apology'' to everyone for betraying the public trust. He also praised the district attorney, Thomas Spota, a Republican turned Democrat, for what he said was evenhanded prosecution of crimes on both sides of the political fence.</p>
        <p>Several Republican Party and government officials have been convicted in the last year or are facing trial on corruption charges.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
