<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dream Finish and a Climb to the Top for Stewart in Indianapolis</title>
    <meta content="08nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/08/sports/othersports/08nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Jimmie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DB173EF93BA3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dream Finish and a Climb to the Top for Stewart in Indianapolis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dream Finish and a Climb to the Top for Stewart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Aug. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The traditionalist in Tony Stewart seethed when his beloved Indianapolis Motor Speedway sold the naming rights to Nascar's lone Nextel Cup race here each season. Maybe the Allstate 400 will never inspire the same passion as the old Brickyard 400.</p>
        <p>But a victory here is no less sweet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Stewart's Allstate 400 victory propelled him into first place in the Nascar Nextel Cup standings as Jimmie Johnson faltered with a late-race wreck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The traditionalist in Tony Stewart seethed when his beloved Indianapolis Motor Speedway sold the naming rights to Nascar's lone Nextel Cup race here each season. Maybe the Allstate 400 will never inspire the same passion as the old Brickyard 400.</p>
        <p>But a victory here is no less sweet.</p>
        <p>Stewart, an Indiana native who said he would trade his 2002 Cup championship for just one victory at his home track, finally has the trophy he coveted most in his stock-car career. Stewart passed a game Kasey Kahne on a restart with 11 laps to go and slowly pulled away.</p>
        <p>''This is one of those days that I don't want it to end,'' Stewart said. ''I don't want to see the sunset. This is probably, definitely, the greatest day of my life at this point professionally, personally. I couldn't ask for more.''</p>
        <p>It was his fourth victory in the past six Nextel Cup races and propelled him into first place in the standings; the leader heading into the race, Jimmie Johnson, was in a late-race wreck and finished 38th. Johnson was taken to Methodist Hospital in Indianapolis for evaluation and was later released.</p>
        <p>Stewart established himself as the driver to beat in the 10-race playoff for the championship, which starts Sept. 18 at New Hampshire, and Dale Earnhardt Jr. ended just about any hope that he would join Stewart in the Chase for the Nextel Cup. The 2005 season has been a long, slow and often miserable ride for Earnhardt, and he might have reached a new low point Sunday.</p>
        <p>He crashed on a restart on Lap 61 and finished 43rd, last in the field, dropping to 16th in the points race. Only the top 10 drivers and those within 400 points of the lead qualify for the playoff chase. Earnhardt is 191 points behind 10th-place Carl Edwards and 627 behind Stewart.</p>
        <p>''That's life,'' Earnhardt said. ''You've got to deal with it, good and bad. We'll be all right. I mean, if we make the chase, we make it. If we don't, we don't.''</p>
        <p>Stewart has no such worries. He virtually guaranteed his berth with a seventh consecutive finish in the top 10 going back to a second-place showing at Michigan in June. During the stretch, which includes consecutive victories in Sonoma, Calif., and Daytona, as well as a victory at New Hampshire, he has moved from the tenuous 10th spot.</p>
        <p>Nothing compares to winning here, though, he said. Stewart grew up about 50 miles south of the Brickyard, in Columbus, Ind., and has always revered the track. He failed in his annual attempts at the Indianapolis 500 during his Indy Racing League days in the 1990's. Since joining Nascar in 1999, his best finish here had been fifth.</p>
        <p>Stewart cares so much about the race that he was incensed when the name was changed this year. ''I'm not saddened,'' Stewart said earlier in the week. ''I'm furious by it, to be honest. It would be like saying the McDonald's 500 instead of the Daytona 500.''</p>
        <p>None of that mattered once the race began. Stewart, who started 22nd, moved into the top five by the midway point. He was one of a handful of contenders in the race's second half, along with the pole winner, Elliott Sadler, and Brian Vickers and Kahne. Kahne was the only serious threat in the end. He passed Stewart with 27 laps to go and appeared to pull away, but Johnson's wreck forced a late caution flag and set up the final stretch. Stewart could not make a decision on whether to go to pit road for fresh tires.</p>
        <p>''You're going to have to call it, bud,'' Stewart said to his crew chief, Greg Zipadelli, adding that he was too ''nervous to call it.''</p>
        <p>It was Zipadelli's decision to remain on the racetrack in second place behind Kahne. On the restart, Stewart quickly moved inside of Kahne for the pass through Turns 1 and 2. Kahne could not challenge Stewart as he eased away.</p>
        <p>When Stewart crossed the finish line, his team ran to the racetrack and climbed the fence at the start-finish line as thousands of fans cheered. The team was mimicking Stewart, who had climbed the fence at Daytona and New Hampshire after victories.</p>
        <p>After a reverse victory lap, Stewart, with the help of a ladder, also climbed the fence and was joined by his team. ''I'm sleeping with that trophy tonight,'' said Stewart, who had tears in his eyes as he saw his father cheer him on from the family suite by Turn 2.</p>
        <p>Among those who pulled alongside Stewart to offer congratulations were Jeff Gordon and Mark Martin. Gordon finished eighth to move into 14th place, 87 points behind Edwards.</p>
        <p>Martin was seventh in the race and is now sixth in the points battle. Martin will surely challenge Stewart in the chase, but, for a day, he bowed to Stewart's growing legend.</p>
        <p>''Tony is today's ultimate racer,'' Martin said. ''He's the ultimate racer of this era.''</p>
        <p>But not yet the ultimate champion. Stewart has one more goal to reach.</p>
        <p>''Still, the Indy 500's on my mind,'' Stewart said. ''I guess it's made it easier finally winning the Brickyard. But there's so much history in my life and with people that are around me. I've never said never yet.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
