<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Thin Man' Is Escapism, From an Unlikely Source</title>
    <meta content="08mon4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/08/opinion/08mon4.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Adam</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Thin Man, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hammett, Dashiell</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DD173EF93BA3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Thin Man' Is Escapism, From an Unlikely Source</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Thin Man' Is Escapism, From an Unlikely Source</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial Observer by Adam Cohen speculates on why 'Thin Man' movies from 1940's recently released in boxed set are on list of best-selling DVD's</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of the media stars of the summer are a charming husband-and-wife team who made their last film appearance in 1947. Nick and Nora Charles, Dashiell Hammett's wealthy Depression-era detectives, are the hero and heroine of six ''Thin Man'' movies, which were released this month in a boxed set that quickly jumped to No. 1 on Amazon.com's list of best-selling DVD's.</p>
        <p>If it's surprising that 21st-century Americans find Nick and Nora so appealing, it's no more so than that Hammett, a dedicated socialist with a very dark worldview, created them in the first place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaving the world's grittiness behind to wallow in a life of luxury is a fantasy that is particularly prevalent right now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two of the media stars of the summer are a charming husband-and-wife team who made their last film appearance in 1947. Nick and Nora Charles, Dashiell Hammett's wealthy Depression-era detectives, are the hero and heroine of six ''Thin Man'' movies, which were released this month in a boxed set that quickly jumped to No. 1 on Amazon.com's list of best-selling DVD's.</p>
        <p>If it's surprising that 21st-century Americans find Nick and Nora so appealing, it's no more so than that Hammett, a dedicated socialist with a very dark worldview, created them in the first place.</p>
        <p>Hammett was an ex-Pinkerton detective who became a writer of pulp crime stories with unsentimental, sometimes unsympathetic, heroes. His Continental Op, an operative for the fictional Continental Detective Agency, was a sullen loner who was just a few moral notches above the criminals he was tracking down. ''It is a long step from Holmes pondering the significance of a flake of cigar ash,'' one critic has said, ''to Hammett's Op, who, on one occasion, stuffs a length of copper wire into his pocket because it's just the right length to go around somebody's neck.''</p>
        <p>Hammett's first full-length novel, ''Red Harvest,'' is a searing story set in a corrupt mining town called Personville and pronounced ''Poisonville'' by the locals. ''Poisonville is right,'' the Continental Op, who ends up engaging in a few bad acts himself, says bitterly. ''It's poisoned me.'' Dorothy Parker once called another Hammett detective, Sam Spade in ''The Maltese Falcon,'' ''so hard-boiled, you could roll him on the White House lawn.''</p>
        <p>But then the stock market crashed, and Hammett created Nick Charles, a happily married, semi-retired private eye who lives off his wife's money and cheerfully drinks his way through Manhattan high society.</p>
        <p>''The Thin Man'' announces itself right away as a very different kind of novel. It begins with Nick waiting for Nora to finish her Christmas shopping. When she does, she reports that Asta, the couple's spirited terrier, has ''had a swell afternoon -- knocked over a table of toys at Lord &amp; Taylor's, [and] scared a fat woman silly by licking her leg in Saks's.'' Nick and Nora's lives revolve around their elegant apartment, swank parties and posh supper clubs.</p>
        <p>''The Thin Man'' was made into a classic movie, starring William Powell and Myrna Loy, which in turn produced five sequels. Despite their often uninspired, even convoluted, plots, the movies' witty dialogue, engaging acting and sophisticated ambience made them immensely popular. Their great charm lies in Nick and Nora's strikingly modern marriage of equals, and the genteel, carefree world they inhabit.</p>
        <p>Even if it is first-rate escapist entertainment, Hammett purists consider ''The Thin Man'' his weakest novel. It was certainly a moral compromise for a man who identified strongly with the downtrodden and would eventually be jailed during the McCarthy era.</p>
        <p>He had exposed the rough working of capitalism in ''Red Harvest'' in early 1929, when the economy was still giddy. He could not have helped but be troubled by how much worse things were in 1934, when the unemployment rate was more than 20 percent. Yet that was the time when he was creating his most upbeat, upscale characters.</p>
        <p>There are at least two competing explanations for the new direction Hammett took in ''The Thin Man.'' One is that he was inspired by Lillian Hellman, the playwright with whom he was to have a lifelong, often tortured relationship.</p>
        <p>Hellman said that Hammett told her she was the model for Nora -- although he also told her, she said, that she was ''the silly girl in the book and the villainess.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps a better explanation is that Hammett knew that in hard times, when people opened a popular magazine or a novel, they wanted to read about penthouses, not breadlines. If they would pay to do so, Hammett was more than willing to oblige.</p>
        <p>That may be the reason Nick and Nora are popular again. Leaving the world's grittiness behind to wallow in a life of luxury is a fantasy that is particularly prevalent right now. On a new television show on VH1, ''Kept,'' young men are competing to be the kept man of a wealthy woman. On another, NBC's ''I Want to Be a Hilton,'' young people are vying to be part of a family of rich celebrities.</p>
        <p>We are not in a Great Depression. But with the economy feeling precarious, the war in Iraq going badly and the headlines filled with London subway bombers and North Korean nuclear weapons, it is comforting for many people to imagine that a rich person might want to take care of them -- or that they are rich themselves, with little more to worry about than how to get over a martini-induced hangover.</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
