<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="10Voge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/10/arts/design/10Voge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1745474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Inside Art"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Institute of Contemporary Art (Boston)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Gallery of Art (Washington, DC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Art Museum</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Laboratory of Art and Ideas at Belmar (Lakewood, Colo)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodner, Ian (1903-90)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libeskind, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Institute of Contemporary Art</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Gallery</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Denver Art Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D71231F933A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Building, New Mission for Institute in Boston</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carol Vogel Inside Art column; Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston is getting ready for opening in September of its new $51 million home, first new art museum built in Boston in nearly 100 years; National Gallery of Art in Washington receives 74 works from collection of Ian Woodner; Denver Art Museum is completing its addition, designed by Daniel Libeskind and scheduled to open this fall; Laboratory of Art and Ideas at Belmar in Lakewood, Colorado, is set to open in fall 2006; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Building, New Mission For Institute in Boston</p>
        <p>The Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston is getting ready for the opening in September of its new $51 million home, the first new art museum to be built in Boston in nearly 100 years. Designed by Diller Scofidio &amp; Renfro, the 65,000-square-foot building on the waterfront will have three times the exhibition space of the institute's current building on Boylston Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As of September, the Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston will move to the waterfront and become a collecting institution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Building, New Mission For Institute in Boston</p>
        <p>The Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston is getting ready for the opening in September of its new $51 million home, the first new art museum to be built in Boston in nearly 100 years. Designed by Diller Scofidio &amp; Renfro, the 65,000-square-foot building on the waterfront will have three times the exhibition space of the institute's current building on Boylston Street.</p>
        <p>The physical metamorphosis isn't the only big change. The institute will no longer function as a kunsthalle (an art space without holdings of its own). Instead, it will become a collecting institution.</p>
        <p>''This is an issue the trustees have been revisiting since the I.C.A. was started in 1936,'' said Jill Medvedow, its director.</p>
        <p>The decision to build a permanent collection determined the new museum's design. It will not only have space for a collection, but for the first time it will also be able to present more than one exhibition at a time. Educational offerings will increase significantly, too; the new building includes a two-story education center.</p>
        <p>In deciding what direction a permanent collection will take, Ms. Medvedow said, the museum plans to focus on artists with whom it has connections. ''We want to create a collection that captures the most significant moments in our exhibition history,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One of the first museums to show artists like Oskar Kokoschka and Andy Warhol, the institute will continue to exhibit, as well as collect, works by emerging artists.</p>
        <p>Barbara Lee, a Boston philanthropist and board member, has already donated several works by artists the institute has shown. They include two by the British sculptor Cornelia Parker that were in a 2000 exhibition: ''Hanging Fire (Suspected Arson),'' 1999, a three-dimensional image of catastrophe, and ''Wedding Ring Drawing (Circumference of a Living Room),'' 1996. Ms. Lee also gave a photograph by Nan Goldin and an installation piece by the Beirut-born artist Mona Hatoum.</p>
        <p>Gifts to National Gallery</p>
        <p>Ian Woodner, the real estate developer who spent four decades before his death in 1990 building a world-class collection of 1,000 old master, 19th- and 20th-century drawings, is well known to scholars and collectors. Over the years his collection has been shown in museums around the world, including the Metropolitan Museum in New York, the Prado in Madrid, the Albertina in Vienna and the Haus der Kunst in Munich. In 1995-96 the National Gallery of Art in Washington, where Woodner was a member of the Trustees' Council, showed 114 of his holdings in ''The Touch of the Artist: Master Drawings From the Woodner Collections.''</p>
        <p>The gallery and Woodner had been discussing the future of his collection since the 1970's. In 1991 his two daughters, Dian and Andrea Woodner, along with the Ian Woodner Family Foundation, sold the gallery a Cellini drawing and a page from an album by Vasari containing 10 drawings by Botticelli and Filippino Lippi. That year they put 145 works on long-term loan to the gallery, intending to donate them. Since then, they have given 44 drawings, including works by Dürer, Raphael and Van Dyck.</p>
        <p>Now the gallery has received 74 more works from those in its care. This group, given by Andrea, brings the total number of gifts from the Woodner collection to 118.</p>
        <p>Spanning five centuries, the group begins with a rare page from a 14th-century book by an unknown Austrian artist and ends with a sketch of a costume design by the 19th-century Symbolist Gustave Moreau.</p>
        <p>Among the highlights is a group of Renaissance drawings by Italian, German, French and Netherlandish artists. One is a pen study of two angels by Fra Bartolommeo, which Woodner bought in the landmark 1978 sale of art from the collection of Baron Robert von Hirsch, a German-born Swiss leather magnate, at Sotheby's in London.</p>
        <p>''It captures that early moment in the Renaissance where there is both a sense of delicacy and purity,'' said Andrew Robison, senior curator of prints and drawings at the National Gallery.</p>
        <p>A later image, also rare, is ''Portrait of a Noble Woman,'' by the 16th-century French artist François Quesnel. The bust-length portrait, which shows a lady in a beautifully detailed ruff, is an example of that distinctive French style of drawing thought by scholars to be influenced by the portraits of Hans Holbein the Younger.</p>
        <p>Some 35 works from the gift will be at the National Gallery in ''Master Drawings From the Woodner Collection,'' April 30 through Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>Denver Ascendant</p>
        <p>There's a lot going on in the Denver art world right now. The Denver Art Museum is completing its addition, designed by Daniel Libeskind and scheduled to open this fall. An 18,500-square-foot site just west of the museum has been selected for a new museum devoted to Clyfford Still, the American Abstract Expressionist painter, who died in 1980.</p>
        <p>In Lakewood, a western suburb of Denver, another new institution is about to add to the cultural mix, the Laboratory of Art and Ideas at Belmar. It bills itself as part museum, part think tank and part public forum. Known just as the Lab, it is to open in the fall in an 11,500-square-foot building designed by Belzberg Architects of Santa Monica, Calif.</p>
        <p>The idea came from Continuum Partners, local developers who are providing the space and operating funds, and Adam Lerner, a former curator at the Denver Art Museum who is the Lab's executive director.</p>
        <p>''It's an alternative art space, but it will also have an educational program,'' Mr. Lerner said. Among the projects in the works is the United States premiere of a new film installation, ''Fantôme Afrique,'' by the British artist Isaac Julien. The Lab will also present lectures, performances and symposiums.</p>
        <p>Inside Art</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
