<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melinda Sanders, Stephen Obermeier</title>
    <meta content="18SAND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/18/fashion/weddings/18SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1551943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDERS, DR. MELINDA ELLEN (DR. MELINDA ELLEN OBERMEIER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OBERMEIER, DR. STEPHEN JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DF1E30F93BA25752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="395" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melinda Sanders, Stephen Obermeier</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Melinda Sanders, Stephen Obermeier</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Melinda Ellen Sanders, a surgical pathologist, was married yesterday to Dr. Stephen James Obermeier, an anesthesiologist. The Rev. Dr. Nancy McCurley performed the ceremony at Hillsboro Presbyterian Church in Nashville.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, specializes in breast pathology at Vanderbilt University Medical Center and is an assistant professor of pathology at Vanderbilt Medical School, both in Nashville. She graduated from Duke and from Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Melinda Ellen Sanders was married Saturday to Dr. Stephen James Obermeier at Hillsboro Presbyterian Church in Nashville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Melinda Ellen Sanders, a surgical pathologist, was married yesterday to Dr. Stephen James Obermeier, an anesthesiologist. The Rev. Dr. Nancy McCurley performed the ceremony at Hillsboro Presbyterian Church in Nashville.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, specializes in breast pathology at Vanderbilt University Medical Center and is an assistant professor of pathology at Vanderbilt Medical School, both in Nashville. She graduated from Duke and from Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The bride is the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Jack L. Sanders of Buffalo. Her father retired as a partner in Smith, Pederson &amp; Smith, a law firm in Orchard Park, N.Y. Her mother, Jean Sheila Sanders, is the vice president of the board of the Theodore Roosevelt Inaugural National Historic Site in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 50, is a partner in Nashville Anesthesia Services, a group practice. He received his medical degree from the University of Texas at San Antonio and is a candidate for a master's degree in liberal arts and sciences at Vanderbilt. His previous marriage ended in divorce.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is a son of the late Margaret A. Obermeier and the late Col. Bernard D. Obermeier, who lived in San Antonio. Colonel Obermeier, a dentist, directed the Army dental services clinic at Fort Hood, Tex.</p>
        <p>The bride and bridegroom met in August 2002 while waiting for coffee at a Nashville cafe.</p>
        <p>''Her beeper went off while we were in line, and to make conversation, I asked if she was a doctor,'' Dr. Obermeier recalled.</p>
        <p>He let her talk about her specialty for a while before telling her that he is also a physician. That grabbed Dr. Sanders's attention.</p>
        <p>''For me as a woman, it is difficult dating someone not a doctor,'' she said. ''They don't understand the dedication and passion for what you do.''</p>
        <p>They drank their coffees together and then decided to stay at the cafe for lunch, too. Afterward, he drove her back to the hospital. On the way, they arranged a dinner date.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
