<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daunting Math for Those Tax Breaks</title>
    <meta content="01TAXX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="INVESTING IT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DB113AF932A35755C0A961958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daunting Math for Those Tax Breaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some of tax breaks proposed by Pres Clinton, and their possible fates in Congress, discussed (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER that $500-a-child tax credit that both the Republicans and President Clinton have been promising you? Don't go spending it just yet.</p>
        <p>The child tax credit is just one element of the tax-cutting package that Congress is about to take up. And as lawmakers begin drafting the legislation, they are facing some unforgiving arithmetic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER that $500-a-child tax credit that both the Republicans and President Clinton have been promising you? Don't go spending it just yet.</p>
        <p>The child tax credit is just one element of the tax-cutting package that Congress is about to take up. And as lawmakers begin drafting the legislation, they are facing some unforgiving arithmetic.</p>
        <p>Republicans have proposed tax cuts valued at more than $200 billion over five years, with the child credit alone accounting for more than $100 billion. The White House has won a vague commitment from the Republicans to include another $35 billion in tax breaks for college expenses.</p>
        <p>But the balanced-budget deal agreed to by both parties allows for a maximum of $135 billion in tax cuts the next five years -- $100 billion less than it would take for both sides to make good on their promises. And Congress will probably have only about $125 billion to allocate because Republicans are loath to raise other taxes to pay for the cuts.</p>
        <p>''Every time I go through this, I come up with not enough money,'' said Clint Stretch, head of tax legislative affairs at Deloitte &amp; Touche.</p>
        <p>That means scaling back Washington's wish list. Here are some possible paths these trims might take:</p>
        <p>CHILD CREDIT Both the Administration and Republicans support a tax credit of up to $500 a child. But because the White House proposal is considerably less expensive than the Republican version, it could be the model for whatever is enacted.</p>
        <p>The Republican plan, which would cost $109 billion over five years, would provide a $500-a-child credit for all children under age 18. It would be available to joint filers with incomes up to $110,000 and to single filers up to $75,000.</p>
        <p>The White House plan, which would cost $46 billion over five years, sets a cutoff age of 13. It makes the credit $300 a child for the first three years, rising to $500 in 2000. And it would phase out the credit, starting at an income of $60,000 and continuing until the credit disappeared at incomes of $75,000 or higher.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE EXPENSES Mr. Clinton's college plan would create a $1,500 tax credit for tuition and fees for the first two years of college. It would also allow for a per-family deduction -- $5,000 a year, increasing to $10,000 a year in 1999 -- for college education or job training. The credit and the deduction could not be taken in the same year, however, and they would be phased out for joint filers with incomes between $80,000 and $100,000, and for single filers with incomes between $50,000 and $70,000.</p>
        <p>The Republican leadership reluctantly agreed to earmark $35 billion for this program. But the measures have little support from either party in their current form, and the betting on Capitol Hill is that much of the $35 billion will be allocated elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The Republicans have also been exploring whether they could combine their proposals to expand individual retirement accounts with a savings vehicle for college expenses that would satisfy Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>ESTATE TAXES A coalition of small-business owners and farmers is pushing for reduction or even elimination of the Federal estate tax.</p>
        <p>But there is almost no prospect of outright repeal, and even small-business lobbyists acknowledge that the best they might get is a doubling, to $1.2 million, of the value of an estate that is exempted from Federal taxation. Republicans and some Democrats would like to include a provision raising the exemption for family-owned businesses and farms to $10 million, but it is unclear whether there is enough money or political support to push it through.</p>
        <p>I.R.A.'s The White House and the Republican leadership both support expanding I.R.A.'s, but the Republican plan is probably too expensive.</p>
        <p>Under current law, contributions to an I.R.A. for people whose employers offer a pension plan are fully tax deductible for single taxpayers with incomes up to $25,000. (For couples, full deductibility is phased out starting at $40,000.) The Republican plan would eliminate the income limit over four years, allow penalty-free withdrawals for certain uses, including the costs of higher education, and make it easier for nonworking spouses to make deductible I.R.A. contributions. The Republican plan would cost $31.2 billion over five years.</p>
        <p>The Administration plan would double the income limits over the next three years. It would also readjust the income limits and the $2,000 limit on deductible contributions each year to account for inflation, and would allow penalty-free withdrawals for certain expenses. The Administration's plan would cost only $5.5 billion over five years.</p>
        <p>CAPITAL GAINS Senate Republicans proposed earlier this year to cut the top rate on capital gains for individuals to 19.8 percent from 28 percent and to allow gains to be indexed for inflation starting this year. Their proposals, which would cost $33 billion over five years, will almost certainly have to be scaled back.</p>
        <p>Analysts said Congressional tax writers could trim the cost of the Republican plan by more than $7 billion by dropping a proposed reduction in the corporate capital gains rate. But they said Republicans would probably have to go further and drop their plans for indexing gains to inflation, while phasing in the reduced top rate for individuals or not bringing it down as far as 19.8 percent.</p>
        <p>INVESTING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
