<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stanley Cup Spiffed Up For Summer</title>
    <meta content="01VECS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DF163DF932A35755C0A961958260" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stanley Cup Spiffed Up For Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey, in Sports of The Times, comments on Stanley Cup, describing it as best sporting trophy that Canadian and American cultures have produced; notes that 'amazing thing' about Stanley Cup, in an age of insurance and litigation and high-tech security, is that it is still given to every winning player for one day in summer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLEANSED of the beer and the Champagne, the fingerprints and the tears, the nicks and the dents, the Stanley Cup is poised for its annual bacchanal.</p>
        <p>For these few days, the Stanley Cup, along with all the other exotic National Hockey League trophies, is on public display in the refurbished 30th Street Station, and fans brandish giant-size replicas of the cup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLEANSED of the beer and the Champagne, the fingerprints and the tears, the nicks and the dents, the Stanley Cup is poised for its annual bacchanal.</p>
        <p>For these few days, the Stanley Cup, along with all the other exotic National Hockey League trophies, is on public display in the refurbished 30th Street Station, and fans brandish giant-size replicas of the cup.</p>
        <p>Last night the Detroit Red Wings opened the Stanley Cup finals with a 4-2 victory over the Flyers. One set of these brutes -- with their playoff beards, their new scars -- will soon be bringing the cup home.</p>
        <p>It is, simply put, the best sporting trophy that Canadian and American cultures have produced -- 35 pounds and nearly three feet of Victorian stateliness, pursued for itself.</p>
        <p>The amazing thing about the Stanley Cup, in this age of insurance and litigation and high-tech security, is that it is still given to every winning player for one day in the summer.</p>
        <p>Five officials at the Hockey Hall of Fame in Toronto take turns escorting the cup. On Friday night, Philip Pritchard and Craig Campbell, as sturdy and reliable as any Mounties, drove the van here, with the cup ensconced in its form-fitting, hard-foam casing inside an inconspicuous-looking trunk.</p>
        <p>When they took it out for the eager television crews, they used rubber gloves. And, yes, there is plenty of security.</p>
        <p>Hockey fans already know the lore of the Stanley Cup -- how Lord Stanley of Preston, the Governor General of Canada, had a cup created by silversmiths in Sheffield, England, in 1893; the sore loser who threatened to heave it into the Lake of the Woods in 1907; the Montreal Canadiens who left it by the side of the road after changing a tire in 1924; how Clark Gillies of the 1980 Islanders allowed his dog to eat from it (''He's a nice dog,'' Gillies explained), and how Mark Messier lugged the cup to strip joints after winning it five times in Edmonton and then with the Rangers in 1994.</p>
        <p>''The Rangers' victory changed things,'' Pritchard said. ''It was on the Letterman show, it was at Yankee Stadium. Now there is a regular schedule of where the cup is going.''</p>
        <p>Last year the cup traveled 100,000 air miles -- and another mile or two by motorboat. That was Pritchard's best memory of the Colorado Avalanche's victory.</p>
        <p>''Chris Simon took it home to his little town of Wawa in northern Ontario,'' he said. ''There are only a few thousand people there, and they had a nice parade down the main street. He took it to his old hockey school, and showed it to the kids.</p>
        <p>''Chris was very respectful of the cup,'' Pritchard continued, then alluded to a Canadian television network. ''He's part Indian, and there was a camera crew from TSN doing a story on Indians in hockey, and he said he wanted to celebrate by going fishing with the cup with his girlfriend and his grandfather, so we got in a boat with an outboard motor and we went out with the camera crew, and we fished, although nobody caught anything. Chris was so proud to take the cup out on Lake Wawa.''</p>
        <p>Simon was later traded to Washington, but for the next 64 years his name will be seen on the cup. There are five rings connected, with room for 13 teams each. The older rings are retired to the Hall in Toronto.</p>
        <p>The cup has its imperfections, including frequent misspellings by the engravers -- New York Ilanders, Toronto Maple Leaes, Bqstqn Bruins, and four different versions of the first name of Jacques Plante, the Canadiens' goalie who won it five straight years.</p>
        <p>There are three female owners on it. And the father of Peter Pocklington, the Edmonton owner, had his name crossed out when N.H.L. officials ruled he had absolutely nothing to do with the Oilers. You can still see the XXXXXXX for 1984.</p>
        <p>Last year, the cup went to a European player's home for the first time, to Ornskoldsvik, Sweden, with Peter Forsberg. If the Red Wings should win this year, one of their five Russians might ask to bring it home.</p>
        <p>Vodka in the Stanley Cup? Probably wouldn't be the first time.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
