<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irabu? Mets Prefer Jones, Thank You All the Same</title>
    <meta content="01ANDE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Diego Padres</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Bobby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irabu, Hideki</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D61F3AF932A35755C0A961958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irabu? Mets Prefer Jones, Thank You All the Same</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson, in Sports of The Times, comments on New York Mets' star pitcher Bobby Jones; recalls that when New York Mets sought Japanese pitcher Hideki Irabu, San Diego Padres asked that Jones be included in any deal for rights to Irabu, and that Mets declined (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN all the commotion over the Yankees' having introduced Hideki Irabu, it's time to remember that the Mets wanted him, too. But when the Padres asked that Bobby Jones be included in any deal for the rights to the Japanese right-hander, the Mets declined.</p>
        <p>That was two months ago, long before Jones, with a 9-2 record, emerged as the National League's best pitcher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN all the commotion over the Yankees' having introduced Hideki Irabu, it's time to remember that the Mets wanted him, too. But when the Padres asked that Bobby Jones be included in any deal for the rights to the Japanese right-hander, the Mets declined.</p>
        <p>That was two months ago, long before Jones, with a 9-2 record, emerged as the National League's best pitcher.</p>
        <p>''This is a guy who had a winning record for three years on Mets teams that hadn't won,'' Bobby Valentine, the Mets' manager, said, referring to Jones's 36-29 record before this season. ''So I thought, 'If we start winning, he should be even better.' ''</p>
        <p>And as the Mets have ascended above .500 -- they were 30-23 after last night's 10-3 victory over the Phillies -- Jones has ascended with them.</p>
        <p>''If you put Bobby and Irabu in a tryout camp, stuff-wise, there's no comparison,'' said Valentine, who managed Irabu two years ago in Japan with the Chiba Lotte Marines. ''Irabu has the fastball. The radar gun over there measures in kilometers; 144 kilometers is 90 m.p.h. In 28 games for me, he never threw one under 144.</p>
        <p>''Irabu should be a good pitcher for the Yankees, but the fastball is only for the gun. You don't need it for the hitters.</p>
        <p>''You know the saying that a team that can run and play defense shouldn't go into a slump? That's similar to how Bobby Jones pitches.</p>
        <p>''It's not like Bobby has to throw 95, because he can't. It's not like he needs his split-fingered fastball, because he doesn't throw a split-finger. He can throw 90, 91, but he's usually around 87, 88. But he gets his strikeouts, and he gets his outs with his fastball.''</p>
        <p>Since the Mets refused to include him in an Irabu deal, Jones has allowed just 62 hits in 81 1/3 innings while assembling a 2.32 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''It's a good feeling knowing other teams are interested in you,'' Jones said, ''especially back before I got off to a good start this season. But it's a great feeling when you find out that the organization that brought you up and is paying you doesn't want to trade you.''</p>
        <p>Indirectly, Jones has two of the Mets' most famous names in his background -- Seaver and Strawberry.</p>
        <p>Before his all-America pitching career at Fresno State, Jones was graduated from Fresno High School, which was Tom Seaver's alma mater before he went to Southern Cal and then to the Mets.</p>
        <p>''Tom Seaver was the famous athlete in Fresno, the one for me, as a pitcher, to follow,'' Jones said. ''In the gym there, they had big banners and his name was up there on one.''</p>
        <p>When the Mets played the Hall of Fame game in Cooperstown the day after Seaver's induction in 1992, their starter was Jones, borrowed from Binghamton.</p>
        <p>''I met him before the game,'' Jones recalled. ''I remember he asked me if I was going to finish college. I hope to. I'm about a year short of graduating with a major in criminology.''</p>
        <p>Jones was there because the Mets were awarded a compensation choice in the 1991 draft after Darryl Strawberry deserted them to sign with the Dodgers. The Mets used it to select Jones.</p>
        <p>But perhaps the most important Mets name in Jones's career is Apodaca -- the pitching coach Bob Apodaca, whose record as a Mets right-hander two decades ago was an uncompelling 16-25.</p>
        <p>''Dac has me pitching from the left side of the rubber, which has helped my breaking pitches on the outside,'' Jones said. ''And he's got me throwing more changeups to right-hand hitters.''</p>
        <p>But Apodaca, who was Jones's pitching coach at the Norfolk farm team in 1993, assesses another attribute.</p>
        <p>''His confidence in himself,'' Apodaca said. ''That year the Braves' farm team at Richmond had a tremendous Triple A club -- Ryan Klesko, Javy Lopez, Chipper Jones, Tony Tarasco. But he looked forward to pitching against that team. He's the same way now.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't flaunt his confidence. He doesn't talk about himself. But he has no fear. When he was matched against Pedro Martinez in Montreal the other night, I could tell he liked that. Martinez was 8-0; everybody was talking about Martinez.''</p>
        <p>Jones, who pitched a 7-0 four-hitter in Montreal, will be matched against Martinez again Tuesday night at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''He's got the insides to pitch inside,'' Apodaca said. ''He knows how to pitch. When to change speeds. When to add on. When to go in. When to go away. He's his own pitching coach. If his pitches are elevated or their trajectory is flat, he knows how to fix it because he's had to be a pitcher all his life.''</p>
        <p>And now that life includes the Mets' preferring him to Hideki Irabu.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
