<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jazz Climbs the Mountain, And Takes a City Along With It</title>
    <meta content="01JAZZ$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="N.B.A. FINALS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. FINALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Utah Jazz</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friend, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Utah Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DF163DF932A35755C0A961958260" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jazz Climbs the Mountain, And Takes a City Along With It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM FRIEND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friend, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Utah Jazz as Salt Lake City prepares to host NBA championship series for first time, after Jazz wins Western Conference; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Well, this isn't the city that never sleeps.</p>
        <p>As a matter of fact, the basketball team's power forward spent his off day taking a long nap after riding one of his three Harley Davidsons up a remote mountain. And just wait until Dennis Rodman hears that last call is 11 P.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Well, this isn't the city that never sleeps.</p>
        <p>As a matter of fact, the basketball team's power forward spent his off day taking a long nap after riding one of his three Harley Davidsons up a remote mountain. And just wait until Dennis Rodman hears that last call is 11 P.M.</p>
        <p>The National Basketball Association is going where it has never gone before -- to Utah -- for the league finals beginning Sunday, and that should end any rumor of a conspiracy.</p>
        <p>This community has believed for some time that Commissioner David Stern prefers big-market teams, and that he has sicced his referees on the Jazz in crucial playoff games. But the league is sending NBC into town next weekend, isn't it?</p>
        <p>The truth is, the Jazz has been on the brink of a trophy since it drafted the softball player out of Gonzaga (John Stockton) and the fisherman out of Louisiana Tech (Karl Malone), and the league is glad the franchise did not move to Las Vegas, Nev., Minnesota or Anaheim, Calif., or merge with Denver to become the Rocky Mountain Nuggets.</p>
        <p>The league is also glad the team did not change its name to the Utah Saints, that it removed an etching of the Louisiana Superdome from its uniforms and that most of the team's employees sign on for life.</p>
        <p>''Even the secretaries stay,'' said Frank Layden, the Jazz president and former coach. ''The ushers are 108 years old, for Pete's sake. No one ever leaves.''</p>
        <p>The team runs the oldest play in the book, the pick-and-roll, and nobody can stop it, even though opponents know it is coming 9 out of every 10 times. The coach, Jerry Sloan, smokes a pack of cigarettes a day, does not fine his players and tells them that when he played, no one got a free layup.</p>
        <p>The players superstitiously eat soft pretzels before every game and tell their peers that Salt Lake City is not so horrible. Malone cannot pull up to a red light on his Harley without hearing, ''Isn't that him?''</p>
        <p>Which is why the power forward just bought new personalized license plates that say, ''It Is.''</p>
        <p>The fans spend game-day afternoons drawing signs or thinking up slogans, and are the ''most hated in the league,'' according to Houston's Eddie Johnson.</p>
        <p>''You're supposed to be a pro,'' Layden said of the players who complain. ''If you can't take the heckling, get out of the kitchen.''</p>
        <p>The fans were so convinced that Hakeem Olajuwon walks with the basketball that all 18,000 of them made the traveling signal in unison during Game 5 of the Western Conference finals last week.</p>
        <p>They also sang what many Houstonians thought was a racially insensitive parody directed at Olajuwon: ''Walk Like a Nigerian.''</p>
        <p>Fans outside Utah will get to see all of this for themselves when the Chicago Bulls hit town Friday for Game 3 of this championship series, but it goes to show that franchises come in all shapes and sizes.</p>
        <p>The Jazz originated in New Orleans, but the cavernous Superdome echoed in emptiness almost every night, and the owner, Sam Battistone, bolted for Salt Lake City in 1979, only to be slapped with a lawsuit. The Hyatt Corporation, which managed the Superdome, was trying to lure a baseball team, and the Jazz's estrangement from the city did not impress baseball's brass. So an injunction was filed, which is why the Jazz did not change its nickname or remove the drawing of the Superdome from its warm-ups when it arrived in Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>''Larry O'Brien, the commissioner, asked what that design was on the back of our uniforms, and I said, 'The Superdome,' '' Layden said. ''He said, 'What?' But we couldn't change our name if we wanted to because we might have had to go back.''</p>
        <p>The franchise's only asset was Pistol Pete Maravich, and his knees were shot, so New Orleans abandoned its legal effort.</p>
        <p>The Jazz was free at last, unstitched its Superdome logo and held a name-change contest, with the winner receiving season tickets for life.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' Layden said, ''we didn't think our life was very long, so what did it matter? I really thought it was a stopover. I mean, the A.B.A. Utah Stars won a title and folded two years later. I didn't think the community was big enough or that the building was adequate and that we'd be gone in three years to Anaheim.''</p>
        <p>Only 100 people responded to the contest, a foreboding sign, and Battistone was not enamored of the Utah Saints, or the Utah Salt Shakers or the Salt Lake Sea Gulls. But one participant had a novel idea -- keep the Utah Jazz -- and Battistone agreed.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' Battistone told employees, ''people remember us as a laughingstock, but I think we'll get good some day, and I want them to remember where we've come from.''</p>
        <p>One problem: Salt Lake City had no jazz clubs. ''Yeah, we don't have clubs or bars like in New York,'' Layden said, ''but there is an appreciation for jazz music here.''</p>
        <p>Like the fan in the front row who totes his saxophone to games and keeps having it confiscated because he plays it during enemy free throws.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Battistone was eventually right about the team's 180-degree turn, although he experimented by playing 10 home games in Las Vegas and nearly merged in 1982 with the Denver Nuggets. Adrian Dantley, Darrell Griffith and Rickey Green soon gave them credibility on the court, and a young marketing executive named Dave Checketts did the same off the court.</p>
        <p>Later, a businessman, Larry Miller, saved the franchise from moving to Minnesota in 1987, and built an arena with money he had earned peddling Toyotas.</p>
        <p>By that time, the franchise had drafted Malone and Stockton, who were running their version of the Green Bay Packer power sweep.</p>
        <p>Almost every opponent knew the pick-and-roll was coming, but the Jazz proved that a set offense beats a freelance offense almost every time.</p>
        <p>''It's almost impossible to stop,'' Houston's Johnson said. ''Because Stockton can shoot the 15-footer and because Malone's the best post-up player in the game. And if you leave Jeff Hornacek, he'll hit the 3, and so can Bryon Russell now. So, you can't leave anybody.''</p>
        <p>And, fittingly, a Malone pick set Stockton free for the game-winning bomb Thursday night that put the Jazz in the finals against Chicago. The city of Salt Lake pulled a rare all-nighter, as 15,000 people greeted the team at the airport at 2:30 A.M. Friday, way past their bedtimes.</p>
        <p>''You know what,'' Malone said, ''I didn't see one yawn.''</p>
        <p>N.B.A. FINALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
