<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unlike the Rangers, the Devils Act Like Winners</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="834754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDE1F39F935A35750C0A960958260" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unlike the Rangers, the Devils Act Like Winners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Stanley Cup playoffs six weeks away, the Devils and the Rangers seem like two planes at an airport rising and descending on parallel runways. Monday's 2-2 tie at Madison Square Garden was reflected on the faces of the opposing coaches and revealed much about their attitudes.</p>
        <p>The Devils, cup champions of 1995, felt as if they had won. They are 4-0-1 in their last five games and 14-6-5 since Jan. 1. In three games with the Rangers,  they have one victory and two ties. True, the Devils are tied with two other teams for the last three playoff rungs in the eight-team Eastern Conference bracket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Stanley Cup playoffs six weeks away, the Devils and the Rangers seem like two planes at an airport rising and descending on parallel runways. Monday's 2-2 tie at Madison Square Garden was reflected on the faces of the opposing coaches and revealed much about their attitudes.</p>
        <p>The Devils, cup champions of 1995, felt as if they had won. They are 4-0-1 in their last five games and 14-6-5 since Jan. 1. In three games with the Rangers,  they have one victory and two ties. True, the Devils are tied with two other teams for the last three playoff rungs in the eight-team Eastern Conference bracket.</p>
        <p>But they have added Phil Housley, an attacking defenseman who improves their power play. With two centers injured, Steve Sullivan was called up from the minor leagues and has three goals in four games. They seem to be peaking at the  right time. Behind the bench, near the end of Monday's game, Jacques Lemaire could barely keep the smile off his face.</p>
        <p>The Rangers, champions of 1994, acted as if they had lost. They are 0-2-2 in  their last four games, 1-4-2 in their last seven and 5-6-3 since Feb. 1. Their coach, Colin Campbell, was irked.</p>
        <p>He griped about stupid penalties, a seasonlong problem. Although Campbell hasn't been lashing out at players as much as he did in his rookie season, he complained about a lack of scoring by key forwards.</p>
        <p>"It's easy to finger Ray Ferraro and Luc Robitaille," Campbell said.</p>
        <p>His team still holds first place in the East, but the coach, for the first time since the erratic 1995 season, seems flustered. Some of his players, including Brian Leetch and Mark Messier, took the long view, explaining things in calm, analytical ways.</p>
        <p>"You don't go into these funks right away," Leetch said. "It happens over a period of time. And you don't come out of it right away either."</p>
        <p>Messier, playing despite an injured right shoulder, said: "Slowly, but surely, we'll get back on track."</p>
        <p>Robitaille, with an uneasy smile on his face, bobbed and weaved, verbally, as skeptical critiques, phrased as questions, were fired at him like so many slap shots. "Keep working hard and have fun instead of pressing," he said. He was speaking to reporters, talking about himself, but he might as well have been addressing his coach.</p>
        <p>Asked if everyone was looking at him now, Robitaille forced a tense laugh and said he "will now" think so because "you keep asking me."</p>
        <p>"I don't think my teammates are looking at me," he said. "Maybe a lot of people are talking about it." Asked if he ever doubted himself, Robitaille said: "No. Because I know."</p>
        <p>Lemaire, who played for eight cup champions in Montreal and coached one in New Jersey, is taciturn on sensitive subjects. In conversations with reporters,  Lemaire controls the agenda and rarely gets led in dangerous directions.</p>
        <p>Campbell never played for a cup winner, but assisted Mike Keenan's 1994 champions. He is loquacious, witty, insightful and blunt. It's not his nature to duck questions or smother specifics with broad generalities.</p>
        <p>The downside of this is that players often sense and react to the coach's mood. Critiques can become self-fulfilling prophecies. Remember Petr Nedved, last season's "perimeter player" who wouldn't "pay the price?"</p>
        <p>He has scored 34 goals for Pittsburgh, more than all but two Rangers. Are Robitaille and Ferraro about to become this season's scapegoats? Or will it be Aleksei Kovalev again, or even the once sacrosanct Adam Graves?</p>
        <p>Certainly Campbell's roster could use some reinforcements before the March 20 trade deadline. The obvious source is the Los Angeles Kings, conducting a close-out sale of veterans in the post-Wayne Gretzky era.</p>
        <p>With Mike Richter's health no sure thing, the Rangers might be interested in  Kelly Hrudey as Glenn Healy's backup. With Pat Verbeek out for at least four weeks with a separated shoulder, Jari Kurri could fill in at right wing. And with size and toughness so important against bigger, Eastern teams, why not bid  for Marty McSorley?</p>
        <p>But they shuffled the roster extensively last summer, when Campbell insisted  on it. The payroll rose to a league-high $31 million. Last week, they improved their size and grit by getting Sergio Momesso and Bill Berg from Toronto.</p>
        <p>Injuries and slumps are part of a season. Teams that survive them often do so because a strong, confident coach finds the right buttons to push with just the  right touch.</p>
        <p>He's the one in the cockpit when the aircraft enters a spin. Campbell's boss, Neil Smith, has been his friend and strongest supporter. The final 17 games, and the playoffs that follow, will tell much about Smith's judgment and Campbell's grasp of the controls.</p>
        <p>ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
