<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Star Wars' Makes Even More Sense Now</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="374667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">COOPER, HENRY F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DB113CF93AA3575BC0A966958260" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Star Wars' Makes Even More Sense Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Less Pie in the Star Wars Sky'' (editorial, July 31), you falsely charge that President Bush is ''imprudent'' in seeking a 1993 decision to proceed toward deployment because there could not be adequate Strategic Defense Initiative testing before then. Whether there will be ''adequate'' testing depends not upon the state of technology, but upon Congress's providing adequate funding and permitting me the flexibility to direct a program of ''adequate'' testing.</p>
        <p>Second, your assessment that testing to date is of ''no current relevance'' is also unfounded. S.D.I. testing has been of subcomponent technologies like navigation systems, signal processing, computing, propulsion, guidance, sensors, and laser and particle-beam generators. These tremendous strides will contribute to an initial strategic defense system and vastly improve parallel technologies in the civil arena.</p>
        <p>Third, your contention that ''many planned tests would violate the Antiballistic Missile Treaty is patently false. Every experiment is reviewed rigorously to insure compliance with all United States international legal obligations, including the ABM treaty. The Pentagon has no plans to test Brilliant Pebbles or any other S.D.I. system in such a way as to violate the treaty.</p>
        <p>Fourth, your assertion that the Antiballistic Missile Treaty is the ''ultimate guarantee'' of United States security is false. For example, only deployed defenses would protect the United States and its allies against even a single ballistic missile actually launched from the Soviet Union or anywhere else, whether intentional or by accident. Fifth, you present a poorly researched, fundamentally flawed report by the General Accounting Office as proof that President Bush ''won't have adequate information by 1993'' to make an informed deployment decision. The G.A.O. did not solicit Defense Department views before releasing the report to Representative John Conyers, an S.D.I. critic. If Congress permits, S.D.I. will test by 1993 a wide range of applicable system concepts and technologies. That technical data will form the basis for a Presidential decision.</p>
        <p>In sum, I agree with President Bush when he stated this year, ''In the 1990's, strategic defense makes much more sense than ever before.'' It is unfortunate that you are so caught up in ''old thinking'' that you are unable to comprehend the prescience of this statement by the President.</p>
        <p>HENRY F. COOPER</p>
        <p>Director, Strategic Defense Initiative</p>
        <p>Washington, Aug. 1, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
