<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Overcome Olajuwon's Efforts</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="198501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSTON ROCKETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDAPER, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Houston Rockets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D7123AF935A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Overcome Olajuwon's Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM GOLDAPER, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDAPER, SAM</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Nov. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Akeem Olajuwon won his statisical battle against Patrick Ewing tonight but the Knicks, by pressing, running and hitting the 3-point shot with uncanny accuracy, defeated the Houston Rockets, 126-121, the Summit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Akeem Olajuwon won his statisical battle against Patrick Ewing tonight but the Knicks, by pressing, running and hitting the 3-point shot with uncanny accuracy, defeated the Houston Rockets, 126-121, the Summit.</p>
        <p>Akeem Olajuwon won his statisical battle against Patrick Ewing tonight but the Knicks, by pressing, running and hitting the 3-point shot with uncanny accuracy, defeated the Houston Rockets, 126-121, the Summit.</p>
        <p>With their fifth straight victory, the third in a row on the road, the Knicks brought their record to 5-2, their best start since the 1980-81 season when Red Holzman was their coach. The winning streak is their longest since the 1983-84 season when they won six in a row.</p>
        <p>A year ago, in Rick Pitino's rookie coaching season, the Knicks, who are in first place in the Atlantic Division, got off to a 1-6 start and their second road success did not come until Feb. 24 in Los Angeles against the Clippers. They uon only nine road games all season.</p>
        <p>In the fifth pro meeting between the National Baskeball Association's premier centers, Olajuwon, his play limited to 33 minutes by foul trouble, finished with 28 points, but only 2 in the final 16 minutes, made 13 of his 19 shots. He also had 16 rebounds. Ewing, who also wound up with five fouls, has 14 points, 7 rebounds and 2 blockhots. 'He Had the Better Game'</p>
        <p>''He was the better player tonight,'' said Ewing, who shot 5 for 14 from the field. ''He had the better game. But this is not a one-man game. Basketball is a team sport an that's why we won. I think the big difference in this team rignt now is Charles Oakley. Since he came from Chicago, he's made every one of us play better. He's passing the ball and playing great defense.''</p>
        <p>Oakley had 10 points and 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Although the Knicks led for almost the entire game and enjoyed an advantage as high as 12 points, the game was finally won with 1 minute 15 seconds remaining on a 12-foot bank shot by Gerald Wilkins that put New York ahead to stay, 122-121. Thirty-one seconds earlier, Wilkins, who finished with a season-high 30 points, erased a Rocket 1-point lead, which Houston earned on an Allan Leavell 20-foot jumper.</p>
        <p>The victory could have come easier at the end, except that the Knicks missed six of eight free throws. Pitino blamed that on fatigue.</p>
        <p>''One of the things we has to do was to use three presses the entire night,'' said Pitino. ''We did a tremendous job of pressing. We got tied and missing the free throws was a case if being tired. We had to press all night to beat them.''</p>
        <p>Eric (Sleepy) Floyd, in the Knick dressing room to visit Ewing, his former Georgetown teammate, was asked by Mike Saunders, the Knick trainer, if he had ever seen as tough a defense as the Knicks put on tonight. The Rockets' playmaker smilingly said, ''Yeh, at Georgetown.''</p>
        <p>Olajuwon confined his talk after the game to the Knicks' defense, rather than his play against Ewing.</p>
        <p>''Their press really worked us over,'' he said. ''It just made us turn the ball over a few times too many. It's just awesome. They make things happen with it.''</p>
        <p>The Rockets committed 28 turnovers, three real bad ones in the closing minute with the game on the line.</p>
        <p>''To me it was a lack of concentration,'' said Don Chaney, the new Rockets' coach, alluding to the turnovers. ''We didn't hit the open man and we didn't handle their pressure. We worked harder than we had to. We scrambled too much and fatigue set in.''</p>
        <p>''Causing fatigue is an intregal part of our game plan,'' said Wilkins, who constantly drove the middle for 14 baskets in 18 attempts. ''You saw it all tonight, the fatigue, the running, the pressing and the 3-point shot. It's all part of our game. This is what these Knicks are all about.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks took 13 more tonight and made 7, three by Trent Tucker, who brought his total to 13 in 21 attempts, the best in league.</p>
        <p>The loss, which ended the Rockets' four-game winning streak, dropped their record to 4-3.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
