<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Sometimes a Great Notion in a Prospectus Is Only That.</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HILLSIDE BEDDING INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EICHENWALD, KURT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D71E3EF930A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Sometimes a Great Notion in a Prospectus Is Only That.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kurt Eichenwald</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EICHENWALD, KURT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW things spook investors more than a company that goes insolvent. After all, earnings are the centerpiece of the stock investment game, and if a public company cannot even meet its financial obligations, investors run for the hills.</p>
        <p>But with the gambling mentality of investors in 1993, a private company that is insolvent and is looking to pull itself out of the hole with public investment capital often looks just dandy. So it was with Hillside Bedding Inc., a retail mattress company based in the Bronx, that went public in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW things spook investors more than a company that goes insolvent. After all, earnings are the centerpiece of the stock investment game, and if a public company cannot even meet its financial obligations, investors run for the hills.</p>
        <p>But with the gambling mentality of investors in 1993, a private company that is insolvent and is looking to pull itself out of the hole with public investment capital often looks just dandy. So it was with Hillside Bedding Inc., a retail mattress company based in the Bronx, that went public in February.</p>
        <p>Hillside admitted in its prospectus that it repeatedly was unable to pay its financial obligations and that it was insolvent at the time of the offering. But, the prospectus said, the offering would change all that as the company used the money to settle old debts and start a huge expansion of its stores.</p>
        <p>The expansion strategy won over the marketplace. At the offering, investors plunked down $17.20 for each unit that consisted of one share of common stock, one share of preferred stock and two warrants. The common stock began trading in the $8 range.</p>
        <p>How are investors doing with their bet on the expansion strategy? The common share price has dropped sharply, but that could hardly be attributed to expansion: Hillside abandoned the strategy not long after it came public. And the company has not yet come around to letting its investors know.</p>
        <p>In its prospectus, the company, which operates in metropolitan New York, listed some 20 stores it has in the region. A check of those stores showed that 12 -- or 60 percent of those in operation some six months ago -- are no longer open. Investment bankers who work with the company confirm that 12 stores have closed although they add that Hillside has also opened a few stores.</p>
        <p>That could only be disappointing news for investors who were looking for the results of that expansion. Already, investors have seen their holdings shrink. Hillside stock, which reached a high last month of $10 a share, has been falling in recent weeks, closing yesterday at $3.875, down 25 cents in Nasdaq trading. That collapse has largely been the result of disappointment about the cancellation, by mutual agreement, of a foreign stock offering announced in May.</p>
        <p>How can a company that was supposed to be growing actually be shrinking? Morton Swirsky, Hillside's chief financial officer, was said to be out of the office yesterday, and other executives did not return a telephone message.</p>
        <p>But the company's investment bankers said Hillside simply decided to switch strategies -- something the company apparently planned to do all along, regardless of what the prospectus said.</p>
        <p>"One thing Hillside didn't disclose in its prospectus, and I don't think it had to disclose, was its intention to operate differently in the New York market," said Keith Gil, a senior partner with Duke &amp; Company, the investment banking firm that brought Hillside public. "Just opening more stores is not the answer."</p>
        <p>That will surely come as a shock to anyone who has read the prospectus. "The company believes that its failure to operate profitably in the periods referred to above has been due, in part, to its inability to achieve economies of scale based on the number of company-owned stores in operation during those periods," the prospectus states in reference to the times the company failed to pay its bills. In other words, Hillside was going broke because it did not have enough stores.</p>
        <p>These days, the company is talking about a joint venture with a competitor, Dial-a-Mattress. And it is rethinking its strategy in other ways that it has yet to announce.</p>
        <p>"They feel and I feel that in the future they will be doing certain things that make it clear why they are closing stores," Mr. Gil said. "When that happens, people will know about it."</p>
        <p>Let's hope that the strategy is something in which the investors actually want to invest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
