<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Notebook; Despite Rain, Denver Is a Mile High for the Pope</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DENVER (COLO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPE (JOHN PAUL II)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Denver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD61431F930A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Notebook; Despite Rain, Denver Is a Mile High for the Pope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Aug. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was rain, thunder and lightning, even a double rainbow in the evening sky.</p>
        <p>But the skies could do nothing to compare with the exhilaration that filled Mile High Stadium upon the arrival of Pope John Paul II. For hours, young Catholics attending the World Youth Day events here this week had been streaming into the stadium, where they swayed, sang, clapped and danced to throbbing music from nations around the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was rain, thunder and lightning, even a double rainbow in the evening sky.</p>
        <p>But the skies could do nothing to compare with the exhilaration that filled Mile High Stadium upon the arrival of Pope John Paul II. For hours, young Catholics attending the World Youth Day events here this week had been streaming into the stadium, where they swayed, sang, clapped and danced to throbbing music from nations around the world.</p>
        <p>The tension erupted into ear-splitting cheers for each step of the Pope's arrival: the helicopters setting down outside the stadium, the slow progress of the Popemobile inside and the opening of Pope John Paul's greeting: "I greet you all in the name of Jesus Christ. He is the way, the truth -- and the life!"</p>
        <p>Separate sections of the stadium broke into flurries of shouts and flag-waving as the Pope named individual countries with young representatives at the event and offered greetings in different languages.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Clifford, a 20-year-old junior at South Dakota State University who lives in Martin, S.D., struggled to explain her excitement. "You know how teen-agers go ga-ga over rock stars," she said. "Well, he's the rock star of our church."</p>
        <p>There was religious seriousness amid the celebration. "Of course we are here to listen to one another, I to you and you to the Pope," the Pope told his audience. "But above all we are in Denver to hear the one true Word of Life." He asked the young people to give up their Friday midday meal and contribute its cost to an African hospital serving AIDS patients.  Hymns on Wheels</p>
        <p>As she boarded the 16th Street bus this morning, Monica Lonardo could tell it was no ordinary rush hour in Denver.</p>
        <p>"People were singing hymns," said the 22-year-old jewelry saleswoman. "On the bus! At 8:30 in the morning!"</p>
        <p>Songs echoed through downtown Denver in dozens of languages today, even during the rain, as 160,000 Roman Catholics from 70 countries celebrated the arrival of Pope John Paul II for World Youth Day. "Some people are so happy they cry," said Birgitte Nyavist, a 15-year-old German girl, who wore a floppy cowboy hat and a pair of new blue jeans.</p>
        <p>To earn money for the trip here, Miss Nyavist said she tended her grandparents garden and cleaned their house for months. Other visitors said they held bake sales and went door to door for donations.</p>
        <p>After the Americans, who are represented by 120,000 people here, the largest contingent is from Italy, with 12,000, followed by Spain and Canada, with about 7,000 each, and Mexico with 6,000. There are three participants here from Angola, and two from Ethiopia.</p>
        <p>Many of the young Catholics wore T-shirts that read "I Got a Mile High With the Pope" and foam-rubber headgear cut in the likeness of a papal miter. And they shouted and waved and gave thumbs-up signs to other groups.</p>
        <p>"Where are you from?" shouted a boy in one group. "We're from North Dakota."</p>
        <p>"Italy," came the answer.</p>
        <p>And there followed a round of applause for both Rome and Fargo.</p>
        <p>Many of the foreign visitors arrived in the United States a week or so before the Pope's appearance. Nicole Widman, an 18-year-old from Lucerne, Switzerland, ticked off the big events on her trip across the West. "Hollywood studios, Grand Canyon, Rocky Mountains," she said, "and the Pope, of course." Nothing to Sweep Up</p>
        <p>It has been called the "Catholic Woodstock," but it bears more resemblance to a well-mannered field trip.</p>
        <p>The police have had virtually no disturbances to quell, despite the huge crowds.</p>
        <p>Dean Dominguez, a janitor who usually spends the noon hour sweeping the sidewalk and collecting the garbage near his office building, instead was leaning on a broom, marveling at the tidiness of the visitors.</p>
        <p>"These people are so neat and clean it's unbelievable," said Mr. Dominguez, who figured that littering must be considered a serious sin. "There's nothing to sweep up. They see a scrap, they pick it up. I've never seen anything like it." They Must Be Fasting</p>
        <p>To hear the disappointed restaurant managers tell it, the young Catholics came to Denver with the Ten Commandments and a $10 bill -- and they're determined not to break either one.</p>
        <p>"Business is off drastically," said Chris Myers, the owner of the Crocodile Cafe, which is usually packed at lunchtime, but today had plenty of empty tables. "All the Denver people got scared away by the hype and figured, 'We better get out of Dodge.'</p>
        <p>"Meanwhile, we've got all these kids in town with no money. And the few 'papal people,' as we call them, come in and order the cheapest thing on the menu, and water. Of course, they're more into praying than boozing."</p>
        <p>The World Youth Day gathering was expected to pump nearly $150 million into the local economy. Instead, stores and restaurants were sending workers home.</p>
        <p>Tourism officials said it was all worth it, however, especially given the publicity to Denver from the 3,000 journalists here.</p>
        <p>"People who have never thought much about Denver are watching their televisions and seeing the sun over the Rocky Mountains," said Rich Grant, a spokesman for the Convention and Visitors Bureau. "We couldn't buy this kind of attention."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
