<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isles Surprise the Bruins and Zero In on a Playoff Spot</title>
    <meta content="05ISLE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/05/sports/hockey/05ISLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Bruins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Boston Bruins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Bruins</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6D9163DF936A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isles Surprise the Bruins and Zero In on a Playoff Spot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isles Surprise Bruins in Drive to Playoffs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders defeat Boston Bruins in overtime, 2-1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders tried an interesting new approach tonight. They tried to beat one of the top teams in the National Hockey League by skating backward for most of the game. And, in yet another Islanders stunner, it worked.</p>
        <p>They have Oleg Kvasha, who has the wingspan of a biplane. He swerved around defensemen Hal Gill and Sean O'Donnell, then poked a one-hand shot past goaltender Byron Dafoe with 1 minute 31 seconds left in overtime to give the Islanders a hard-to-fathom 2-1 victory over the Boston Bruins at the Fleet Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oleg Kvasha's one-hand shot past Byron Dafoe with one minute left in overtime gave the Islanders a hard-to-fathom win over the Bruins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Islanders tried an interesting new approach tonight. They tried to beat one of the top teams in the National Hockey League by skating backward for most of the game. And, in yet another Islanders stunner, it worked.</p>
        <p>They have Oleg Kvasha, who has the wingspan of a biplane. He swerved around defensemen Hal Gill and Sean O'Donnell, then poked a one-hand shot past goaltender Byron Dafoe with 1 minute 31 seconds left in overtime to give the Islanders a hard-to-fathom 2-1 victory over the Boston Bruins at the Fleet Center.</p>
        <p>''It's not something I want to get into on a regular basis,'' Islanders Coach Peter Laviolette said of his team's unusual style, which included lots of trapping.</p>
        <p>Kvasha, the once-underachieving left wing who has five goals in his last six games, said his game-winning shot was more like a simple redirection of the puck. He said that he got lucky.</p>
        <p>Then he was asked why he has been so lucky recently. ''I can't answer that question,'' Kvasha said. ''I'm just trying to put the puck into the net.''</p>
        <p>Boston outshot the Islanders, 40-16, but the backup goaltender Garth Snow, playing in only his second game since March 7, was brilliant, stopping every shot except a diving rebound chance by Glen Murray with 2:16 left in the third period that tied the score.</p>
        <p>The Islanders (38-27-8-4) can earn their first playoff berth in eight years as early as Friday. Washington, the ninth-place team in the Eastern Conference, plays host Friday to Ottawa, and if the Senators win, the Capitals would be able to finish with no more than 87 points. The Islanders have 88.</p>
        <p>''We'll be happy,'' Islanders defenseman Adrian Aucoin said of clinching a playoff berth, ''but we have a lot of hockey left.''</p>
        <p>Another stunner: The Islanders, 6-2-1-0 since March 19, also still have a chance to win the Atlantic Division. Philadelphia lost to Montreal tonight, 3-1, so the Flyers' advantage over the Islanders has shrunk to 4 points. The two teams, which have five games left, are to meet in the regular-season finale April 14 at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>''It's crazy now, the parity in this league,''' Snow said. ''I've never seen anything like it.''</p>
        <p>Snow, who has not played much in the past month because Chris Osgood has been superb, seemed to spark the Islanders with his aggressive, confident play.</p>
        <p>He also had some help from Laviolette and his coaching staff. The Islanders had played a tough 1-1 tie Wednesday at Buffalo, and Laviolette knew that the Bruins, who had not played since Tuesday, would be ravenous to get 2 points of their own. Boston (44-22-5-8), the top team in the Eastern Conference, leads Philadelphia by 5 points.</p>
        <p>So the Islanders sat back. They tied a season low with only two shots in the first period, but Snow made several good saves. As Aucoin explained, his teammates knew he could take care of the long shots. So they concentrated on tying up the Bruins when they worked the puck deep.</p>
        <p>''It worked out well, because they didn't know what to do,'' Aucoin said.</p>
        <p>One team objective was to get to the end of the first period in a scoreless tie. ''We needed to weather the storm in the first period, and we did,'' Snow said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders also wanted to get to the end of the second period with a scoreless tie. But Islanders right wing Mariusz Czerkawski, who entered the game with only three goals in his last 26 games, took a backhand pass from Brad Isbister and beat Dafoe high with just 56 seconds left in the period. It was only the ninth shot of the game for the Islanders.</p>
        <p>''The pass was just perfect,'' Czerkawski said. Then, referring to Dafoe, he added, ''We were talking about that before the game, about how he might go down on shots.''</p>
        <p>Until Murray scored his 36th goal as he was slammed to the ice by Kenny Jonsson, Snow's closest call was a soft shot by Bill Guerin that Snow mishandled. The puck hit the post and bounced right back to Snow. But he also snapped a rebound shot by Jozef Stumpel out of the air early in the second period.</p>
        <p>''It's the first time we've played this system,'' center Claude Lapointe said. ''We've practiced it before a few times, so we had a good idea what to do. And Snowy played great. That's what he's there for -- to make the big saves.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
