<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AOL Official And Lawyer For Microsoft Spar in Court</title>
    <meta content="Y05SOFT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/05/technology/05SOFT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harmon, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borthwick, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kollar-Kotelly, Colleen (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pepperman, Richard C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">America Online</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5D71F3AF936A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AOL Official And Lawyer For Microsoft Spar in Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AOL Official and Lawyer for Microsoft Spar in Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY HARMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harmon, Amy</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>America Online vice president John Borthwick tells Federal Judge Colleen Kollar-Kotelly that Microsoft Corp is using its Windows operating system to 'tilt' users toward its own versions of technology that both companies see as gateway to lucrative new business called Web services; spars with Microsoft lawyer Richard C Pepperman, who displays internal AOL documents acknowledging that Microsoft's .Net technology was open to all developers and designed to run on any platform, not just Windows (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An executive of America Online told a federal judge today that Microsoft was using its Windows operating system to ''tilt'' users toward its own versions of technology that both companies see as the gateway to a lucrative new business called Web services.</p>
        <p>John Borthwick, the vice president for advanced services of America Online, sparred with Microsoft's lawyer, Richard C. Pepperman, who displayed internal AOL documents acknowledging that Microsoft's .Net technology was open to all developers and designed to run on any platform, not just Windows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An AOL executive told a judge that Microsoft was using its Windows operating system to "tilt" users toward its own versions of a new business called Web services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An executive of America Online told a federal judge today that Microsoft was using its Windows operating system to ''tilt'' users toward its own versions of technology that both companies see as the gateway to a lucrative new business called Web services.</p>
        <p>John Borthwick, the vice president for advanced services of America Online, sparred with Microsoft's lawyer, Richard C. Pepperman, who displayed internal AOL documents acknowledging that Microsoft's .Net technology was open to all developers and designed to run on any platform, not just Windows.</p>
        <p>''.Net today is a relatively open platform,'' Mr. Borthwick conceded. ''The concern is that over time the platform will become more closed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Borthwick testified on behalf of nine states that are pursuing curbs on Microsoft's business practices across a range of new technologies after a federal appeals court ruled last June that the software maker repeatedly violated antitrust laws.</p>
        <p>Microsoft contends that a less-restrictive settlement that it reached with the Justice Department and nine other states is enough to restore competition in the computer operating system market, where its Windows platform holds a monopoly. The court said Microsoft illegally maintained that monopoly by sabotaging the Netscape Navigator browser and the Java programming language, which posed a threat to Windows.</p>
        <p>After three weeks of hearings, Judge Colleen Kollar-Kotelly of the Federal District Court in Washington has still given no indication of how she views the dissenting states' argument that an effective remedy must encompass nascent technologies that may eventually challenge Windows.</p>
        <p>The states' argument is ''a stretch,'' said Robert E. Litan, director of economic studies at the Brookings Institution and a former Justice Department official. But he added that such contortions might be necessary to apply antitrust laws in the fast-changing technology industry.</p>
        <p>With Microsoft's .Net technology, for instance, there is hardly any market to dominate yet. The idea is that applications of all kinds will increasingly reside on the Internet rather than on personal computers. Instead of buying software, people will pay for services available to them from a range of devices.</p>
        <p>Unless Microsoft is required to continue to disclose information about .Net and allow competing providers of Web services to promote themselves on the Windows desktop screen, Mr. Borthwick contended, the company would provide Windows users an advantage over users of other operating systems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borthwick said Microsoft's newest operating system, Windows XP, continually prompts users to sign up for the company's ''Passport'' online identification system, which Microsoft hopes will serve as the access key to all the Web services an individual might sign up for.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pepperman was pointed out that AOL has a competing technology called Magic Carpet, to be released later this year. He suggested that AOL was primarily concerned with cornering the crucial consumer access point to Web services for itself.</p>
        <p>AOL has negotiated an exclusive arrangement with Amazon.com, perhaps the most significant e-commerce site, Mr. Pepperman noted. He said AOL refused to discuss how Magic Carpet and .Net could work together after Microsoft declined to allow AOL to promote Magic Carpet on the opening Windows screen.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
