<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FAMILY FARE</title>
    <meta content="05FAMI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/05/arts/05FAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Family Fare"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">South Street Seaport Museum (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Homesick Sailor Puppet Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Packet (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leifer, Howie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Araboolies of Liberty Street, The (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D71E3AF936A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FAMILY FARE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Don't Bully the Araboolies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laurel Graeber Family Fare column discusses performance of new children's opera, The Araboolies of Liberty Street, at Manhattan School of Music, National Academy of Design's pilot Sounds of Canvas: Visual Notes in Painting program and South Street Seaport Museum presentation of Howie Leifer's Homesick Sailor Puppet Theater and New York Packet puppet show; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don't Bully The Araboolies</p>
        <p>Before the Araboolies arrived, life was colorless -- literally and figuratively.</p>
        <p>The members of this unusual family are the heroes of ''The Araboolies of Liberty Street,'' a new children's opera about marching to a different drummer (as well as to different piano music). Based on a children's book of the same title by Sam Swope, the opera concerns the transformation of Liberty Street, which is not a place of freedom. It is dominated by a couple appropriately called the Pinches, who hate children, laughter and anything unconventional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don't Bully The Araboolies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Don't Bully The Araboolies</p>
        <p>Before the Araboolies arrived, life was colorless -- literally and figuratively.</p>
        <p>The members of this unusual family are the heroes of ''The Araboolies of Liberty Street,'' a new children's opera about marching to a different drummer (as well as to different piano music). Based on a children's book of the same title by Sam Swope, the opera concerns the transformation of Liberty Street, which is not a place of freedom. It is dominated by a couple appropriately called the Pinches, who hate children, laughter and anything unconventional.</p>
        <p>''All the houses on the street are white and perfect, and the lawns are all green,'' said Gordon Ostrowski, who will direct a performance of the opera this afternoon at the Manhattan School of Music. ''And the Araboolies are big splashes of color.''</p>
        <p>That description is more than a metaphor. The Araboolies' faces and hair are in bright rainbow hues. And since this is opera, when the Araboolies move in, they introduce a world of sound as well as color.</p>
        <p>''When they say hello, there's a beautiful wind-chime effect,'' Mr. Ostrowski said. ''And the horn on their bus is a wind instrument with a funny sound.'' General Pinch, on the other hand, is represented mainly by snare drums.</p>
        <p>Composed by Ronald Perera, with a libretto by Constance Congdon, the opera features a chorus of students, ages 10 to 12, who portray the village children. When the Pinches resolve to use their ''weirdo-eliminating tractor beam'' to get rid of the freewheeling Araboolies, the children fight back by dressing and acting like their new neighbors. ''They invite the kids in the audience to be Araboolies, too,'' Mr. Ostrowski said.</p>
        <p>The 50-minute performance, with music direction by LeAnn Overton, will be preceded by a Discover Opera program. Written by adult students at the Manhattan School, it concerns an amazing boy, Parry Hotter, who has a treble clef on his forehead. While studying at the Songwarts School, he becomes enmeshed in a mystery involving stolen voices. Although the piece is a comic parody, the school hopes to make a serious point: opera really can be magic.</p>
        <p>''Parry Hotter,'' today at 5 p.m., and ''The Araboolies of Liberty Street,'' 6 p.m., at the Hubbard Recital Hall, Manhattan School of Music, 122nd Street and Broadway, Morningside Heights. Free. Reservations required: (212) 749-2802, extension 4428.</p>
        <p>An Ear for Art</p>
        <p>Most children think of a museum's art as something to look at. But tomorrow the National Academy of Design will have them listen to it, too.</p>
        <p>''The Sounds of Canvas: Visual Notes in Painting,'' a pilot program, will lead visitors ages 6 to 12 on a tour of selected works in ''Modernism and Abstraction: Treasures From the American Smithsonian Art Museum.'' Children will be encouraged to think of how the paintings in the show might sound if they were music, and to use their mouths, hands and bodies to translate the brushstrokes into rhythms.</p>
        <p>''What I'm trying to do is to create a tone poem,'' said Alison Crockett, a musician and recording artist who will lead the workshop. ''What classical composers used to do, particularly in the 1800's, was to create sounds to represent a visual idea. Berlioz did that. Duke Ellington used to do it, too. But we won't have instruments, so we'll have to use our bodies.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Crockett plans to select the most accessible works, focusing on how abstract art uses color and form to evoke emotions. Concentrating on feelings like anger, joy, anxiety and calm, she will guide the children in creating works of sound and movement that generate the same moods.</p>
        <p>''When you're angry, you might do something fast and loud: accelerando and crescendo into forte,'' Ms. Crockett said. ''But they don't have to remember those terms. I'm not so concerned that they retain information, but that they see that art and music can correspond.''</p>
        <p>''The Sounds of Canvas: Visual Notes in Paintings,'' tomorrow at 2:30 p.m. at the National Academy of Design, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street. Admission: $10; member families, $8. Reservations advised: (212) 369-4880, extension 225.</p>
        <p>On Waves of Song</p>
        <p>Families are invited to spend two hours at sea on Sunday afternoon. But there's no need to worry about the weather; this voyage will not be by ship but by song.</p>
        <p>As part of its monthly concert series, the South Street Seaport Museum will present Howie Leifer's Homesick Sailor Puppet Theater and the New York Packet, the seaport's own folk group. Everyone will sing, including the puppets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leifer will even become a puppet himself with a device known as a humanette, in which his head and hands become those of the puppet. Thus dressed, he will play ''The Wreck of the Nancy Lee,'' a 19th-century music hall tune, on a ukulele.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leifer will also include a shadow-puppet tale about ''a sailor and a mermaid and the girl he left behind,'' he said. Fishermen get their due with a vignette in which a luckless soul, a Czech-style marionette, snags only a shoe. But like many things from the deep, his catch is more than it seems.</p>
        <p>The New York Packet will perform before and after Mr. Leifer. ''Most of the songs have choruses that are very easy to sing,'' he said. Visitors with enough wind in their sails are welcome to join in.</p>
        <p>Family concert, Sunday at 3 p.m. at the South Street Seaport Museum, Whitman Gallery, 209 Water Street, at Fulton Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 748-8600. Free; $4 suggested donation.</p>
        <p>Family Fare</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
