<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saluting Liberty With Festivities And Introspection</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="159053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDEPENDENCE DAY (US) (JULY 4)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D81438F936A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saluting Liberty With Festivities And Introspection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It was, in a way, like two Fourths of July: the garrulous, sociable one that drew people out to thundering parades, booming musket salutes, fiddle-wailing hoedowns and picnics on small-town greens. And there was the other one that drew folks inward, to thoughts of home and of loved ones and to front-porch recollections of summers past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It was, in a way, like two Fourths of July: the garrulous, sociable one that drew people out to thundering parades, booming musket salutes, fiddle-wailing hoedowns and picnics on small-town greens. And there was the other one that drew folks inward, to thoughts of home and of loved ones and to front-porch recollections of summers past.</p>
        <p>It was, in a way, like two Fourths of July: the garrulous, sociable one that drew people out to thundering parades, booming musket salutes, fiddle-wailing hoedowns and picnics on small-town greens. And there was the other one that drew folks inward, to thoughts of home and of loved ones and to front-porch recollections of summers past.</p>
        <p>For those who wanted it, there was plenty of action. Philadelphians unfurled a 600-foot American flag outside Independence Hall. Bostonians turned out at the burial place of John Adams and John Hancock to watch militiamen fire salutes. In San Francisco, soldiers solemnly raised a flag over Pershing Square.</p>
        <p>And in cities and towns across the country, brass bands thumped down Main Street playing ''The Stars and Stripes Forever,'' and children waved flags from parents' shoulders. There were lofty speeches here and there about America, some recited the Declaration of Independence and a few spoke of freedom in a nation that seems to stumble often.</p>
        <p>For others less moved, it was a day of escape to parks, beaches and country retreats, far from programmed entertainment and extravagant production. The sounds were pastoral: the clang of horseshoes, the sea breeze snapping at pennants, a bird twittering on a branch.</p>
        <p>From the Appalachians to the Rockies, it was a near-perfect day for celebration. The sun sailed gracefully across a sky that might have been a pale sea flecked with whitecaps. And in the evening, as the light and the music faded, the skies became a black velvet backdrop for fireworks - great bursting cascades of red, white, blue and gold.</p>
        <p>And when it was all over, some found it possible to put aside the day's flag-waving, hot-dog-and-mustard hoopla, even to forget for a moment that American warships were on patrol somewhere, and to sit out under the stars and listen to soft music, perhaps from a radio, and to feel that it had been not a bad old Fourth of July, at that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
