<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trenton Chalks Up End of Budget Stalemate to a Poker-Faced Corzine</title>
    <meta content="07corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/07/nyregion/07corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060708T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D61330F934A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trenton Chalks Up End of Budget Stalemate to a Poker-Faced Corzine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trenton Chalks Up End of Budget Stalemate to a Poker-Faced Corzine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Gov Jon S Corzine uses successful strategy in getting Legislature to agree to his increase in sales tax from 6 to 7 percent; forcing Legislature to meet on three consecutive mornings to repeat his message with confidence finally ends budget crisis; compromise will use $550 million of sales tax revenue for property tax relief next year and possibly beyond; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An outsider, they called him when he was elected governor last year. A wealthy dilettante who was supposed to be aloof, even arrogant. A political novice who would never survive the merciless and mysterious trenches of Trenton.</p>
        <p>But when Gov. Jon S. Corzine announced on Thursday that New Jersey had finally resolved its budget crisis, many people in and out of Trenton used another word to describe him: underestimated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, July 6  An outsider, they called him when he was elected governor last year. A wealthy dilettante who was supposed to be aloof, even arrogant. A political novice who would never survive the merciless and mysterious trenches of Trenton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An outsider, they called him when he was elected governor last year. A wealthy dilettante who was supposed to be aloof, even arrogant. A political novice who would never survive the merciless and mysterious trenches of Trenton.</p>
        <p>But when Gov. Jon S. Corzine announced on Thursday that New Jersey had finally resolved its budget crisis, many people in and out of Trenton used another word to describe him: underestimated.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Assembly Democrats had warned that Mr. Corzine's proposal to raise the sales tax to 7 percent from 6 percent would never pass their chamber. As recently as Tuesday, in fact, Assembly Speaker Joseph J. Roberts Jr. declared that the proposal was ''dead.'' But Mr. Corzine never wavered from his demand that the tax had to be increased to resolve the state's perennial budget shortfalls. In the end, he showed Trenton the kind of poker face and resourcefulness that propelled him to the top of Wall Street.</p>
        <p>He did not get it done by bullying people into submission, or doing the kind of political horse-trading that is normal in Trenton, according to legislators and aides. Instead, he calmly kept repeating his message to anyone who would listen, displaying rock-solid confidence that the numbers in his budget would win people over.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it was no accident that he demanded that the Legislature meet on three consecutive mornings to hear what was essentially the same message, an hour that would be considered late for bankers but early for politicians. And he was prepared, aides say, to do what would have been the political equivalent of the movie ''Groundhog Day'': asking them to meet every day, until he had gotten his way.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of people underestimated his resolve, and his determination to do the right thing, to do things in a very different way than they had been before,'' said State Senator Barbara Buono, a Democrat from Middlesex County. ''The way budget negotiations were conducted represented a quantum leap in the way things were done before, so you had to expect opposition.''</p>
        <p>Still, the agreement was not a complete victory for Mr. Corzine, who had to yield on something dear to Mr. Roberts, and at a princely sum: At least $550 million of the sales tax revenue will go toward property tax relief next year and possibly in the years beyond that.</p>
        <p>With New Jersey facing a deficit of at least $2 billion next year -- and even larger ones in future years because of rising pension and debt service costs -- the compromise could hobble Mr. Corzine's ability to fix the state's perpetually troubled finances. Still, the agreement was widely viewed in Trenton as a political triumph for Mr. Corzine. Those who knew Mr. Corzine from his days as co-chairman of Goldman Sachs say that they were not surprised by his actions.</p>
        <p>Whenever there was a major deal or crisis at the firm, Mr. Corzine, a trader by training, was known to stake out a position, based largely on the data he had received, and stick to it. So when he decided to push the Goldman Sachs partners to take the company public in the late 1990's, he was ''indefatigable'' in trying to win skeptics over, according to ''Goldman Sachs: The Culture of Success,'' written by Lisa J. Endlich and published in 1999.</p>
        <p>''He would go out on a limb, prodding, persuading, using his enormous stores of charisma and loyalty to bring the partnership to the action,'' Ms. Endlich wrote.</p>
        <p>This time, he engendered opposition from the Legislature, including from many Democrats who saw his budget plan as a replay of the sales tax increase that Gov. Jim Florio pushed through in Trenton in 1990 -- to disastrous electoral consequences. Then Mr. Corzine rankled legislators by not doing enough to woo them after delivering his budget.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged in a recent radio interview that he should have done more, saying he made a ''rookie'' mistake.</p>
        <p>Yet through it all, he did not waver from his position, displaying a demeanor that Republicans and Democrats have said remained calm and confident throughout the battle.</p>
        <p>What may have caught some legislators and lobbyists off guard was his refusal to engage in Trenton-style politics.</p>
        <p>''He was dealing with a bunch of people in the Legislature who didn't know him on Wall Street, and he came into office as an extremely rich guy who bought himself a seat in the U.S. Senate, and they said, 'Here's a guy we can deal with,' '' said Carl Golden, who was a spokesman for two Republican governors, Thomas H. Kean and Christie Whitman.</p>
        <p>''A lot of those people in the Legislature are accustomed to the ways things are done: 'For the next judicial appointment in Middlesex County, how about considering my family attorney?' '' Mr. Golden said. ''But he made it very clear to everybody up front that he wasn't going to play that way. And then the bucket of cold reality hit them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine plodded ahead in a manner reminiscent of a friend of his, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg in New York City -- though a 1 percent increase in the sales tax was not nearly as hard to achieve, perhaps, as Mr. Bloomberg's successful push to raise property taxes by 18 percent in his first year.</p>
        <p>''Bloomberg always said, 'Do the right thing, don't worry about polls,' and I'm sure Jon is the same way,'' said Andrew M. Alper, who worked with both men, first as a partner at Goldman Sachs, then as president of the New York City Economic Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alper added about Mr. Corzine: ''He identified a problem in New Jersey's budget. He saw a way to fix it. He clearly had the patience and the fortitude to stick to that position. And it took a lot of courage.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 8, 2006, Saturday  An article yesterday about the persistence of Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey, a trait that legislators and aides say led to his success in resolving the state's budget stalemate, misstated the percentage by which the state sales tax will increase when it is raised to 7 percent from 6. It is 16.7 percent, not 1 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 8, 2006, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the persistence of Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey, a trait that legislators and aides say led to his success in resolving the state's budget stalemate, misstated the percentage by which the state sales tax will increase when it is raised to 7 percent from 6. It is 16.7 percent, not 1 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
