<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning Over A Ship Adrift</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="496476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, BARBARA HACKMAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81E38F934A15751C1A967958260" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning Over A Ship Adrift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's choice for Commerce Secretary, Barbara H. Franklin, will inherit an agency diminished by its loss of primacy over international trade and somewhat weakened by the management style of its current leader, Robert A. Mosbacher.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mosbacher, who will leave next month to head the President's re-election campaign, has played a limited role in interagency debates on business-related issues like tax and health policy and international trade. Unlike his combative predecessor, Malcolm Baldrige, he has spent much of his tenure jetting around the world on trade missions with the nation's corporate elite, seeking to open new markets for American exports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's choice for Commerce Secretary, Barbara H. Franklin, will inherit an agency diminished by its loss of primacy over international trade and somewhat weakened by the management style of its current leader, Robert A. Mosbacher.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mosbacher, who will leave next month to head the President's re-election campaign, has played a limited role in interagency debates on business-related issues like tax and health policy and international trade. Unlike his combative predecessor, Malcolm Baldrige, he has spent much of his tenure jetting around the world on trade missions with the nation's corporate elite, seeking to open new markets for American exports.</p>
        <p>And even though he is a close friend of President Bush, Mr. Mosbacher has not always chosen to use the relationship to push his own views or his agency's cause. Losing Policy Debates</p>
        <p>The result, say Mr. Mosbacher's critics -- who include Administration officials and Washington trade experts, some of whom consider themselves friends and allies of the Commerce Secretary -- has been an agency adrift.</p>
        <p>A small crew of veteran administrators continues to work long hours on technical issues like weather forecasting, the census and economic indicators, while the department loses policy debates to other Government agencies and watches from the sidelines while others determine the nation's health and tax policies.</p>
        <p>And with the recent departure of several senior officials and the possible departure of several others, even the department's technical competence has been questioned.</p>
        <p>"The department needs to be much more broad-gauged and not just a Chamber of Commerce," said a top Administration official, who, like other critics, insisted on anonymity.  "There's a lot more to the Commerce Department than export promotion."  Defending the Secretary</p>
        <p>But other Administration officials and some corporate executives strongly disagree. They point out that Mr. Mosbacher has worked well with businesses, and defend his emphasis on exports in light of the growing concern about the nation's economic competitiveness.</p>
        <p>He has promoted American exports with some success, including forcing Japan to amend its regulations on large retail stores, which allowed Toys "R" Us to open its first discount outlet there last week.</p>
        <p>"The biggest thing he did as I saw it was that he is someone American businessmen trust," said Donald B. Marron, the chairman and chief executive of Paine Webber Inc. "He understands the issues; he's a good listener; he doesn't give people a lot of baloney."</p>
        <p>Roger B. Porter, the assistant to the President for economic and domestic policy and a former Harvard University professor who has studied the nation's trade policy, said the department had not lost influence during Mr. Mosbacher's tenure.</p>
        <p>"Bob Mosbacher has as close a personal relationship with the President as any Commerce Secretary has had in the post-World War II period," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter, who served in the Ford and Reagan Administrations, said the officials and industry lobbyists who played down Mr. Mosbacher's role were exaggerating the influence of his predecessors and missing the extent to which Congress had strengthened the Office of the United States Trade Representative at the expense of the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>Legislation in 1974 and 1988 clearly designated the trade representative as the top trade negotiator, while the end of the cold war has left the Commerce Department's export control division with less to do, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mosbacher dismisses criticisms of his aloofness from policy matters as the complaints of "low-level nerds" in the Federal Government. The collegial nature of decision-making in the Bush Administration has obscured the extent of his involvement, Mr. Mosbacher said in an interview on Monday in his walnut-paneled, two-story office with a view of the Washington Monument. A Measure of Persuasion</p>
        <p>Commerce Secretaries have traditionally championed the interests of business within the Administration. Mr. Mosbacher pointed to his success in persuading the White House that corporate leaders should accompany President Bush to Japan next month. And Mr. Mosbacher was the first Cabinet secretary to warn that banks' increasingly cautious lending policies were making it hard for companies to borrow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mosbacher waged a personal and ultimately successful crusade earlier this year to persuade the Japanese to stop importing the shells of endangered sea turtles, a goal that had eluded American officials and environmentalists for a decade.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department is also playing the lead negotiating role on American trade in automobiles and auto parts with Japan, the biggest bilateral commercial issue. Illustration of Limits</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Mosbacher's sometimes limited influence as a Cabinet secretary was illustrated again last Friday, when he scheduled a news briefing at the White House to discuss his successful effort to send top corporate executives with the President on his trip to Asia next month.</p>
        <p>Samuel K. Skinner, the new White House chief of staff, appeared at the briefing and took the podium first, praising the decision to take the executives on the trip and then listing the President's key economic policy advisers as the Treasury Secretary, Nicholas F. Brady; the budget director, Richard Darman, and the chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers, Michael Boskin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner conspicuously did not mention either Mr. Mosbacher, who was standing nearby, or the Commerce Department, which has traditionally played a role in economic policy-making.</p>
        <p>The incident highlighted the erosion of the Commerce Department's vast bureaucratic turf. The trade representative, Carla A. Hills, now dominates trade policy. The Departments of State and Defense increasingly share the Commerce Department's role in deciding export control issues. And White House officials, especially the chiefs of staff, John H. Sununu and now Mr. Skinner, dominate domestic economic policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
