<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fed Action Is Limited By Dollar</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="554971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTEREST (MONEY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D8113AF934A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fed Action Is Limited By Dollar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In cutting a key interest rate on Friday, the Federal Reserve was seeking to walk a tightrope, trying to nudge the nation's economy gently forward without pushing the dollar off a cliff.</p>
        <p>The dollar has slipped to record lows against the German mark in recent weeks, principally because short-term interest rates are so much lower in the United States than in Germany. And some analysts fear that the Fed's quarter-point reduction in the Federal funds rate -- the rate at which banks make overnight loans to each other -- could accelerate the dollar's decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In cutting a key interest rate on Friday, the Federal Reserve was seeking to walk a tightrope, trying to nudge the nation's economy gently forward without pushing the dollar off a cliff.</p>
        <p>The dollar has slipped to record lows against the German mark in recent weeks, principally because short-term interest rates are so much lower in the United States than in Germany. And some analysts fear that the Fed's quarter-point reduction in the Federal funds rate -- the rate at which banks make overnight loans to each other -- could accelerate the dollar's decline.</p>
        <p>While the latest interest rate cut was sought by the Bush Administration, especially by Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady, the reduction runs the risk of hurting President Bush if it sends the dollar to new lows and spreads turmoil in the stock and bond markets. Mr. Brady favors a weak dollar to help increase exports of American products, though it can help spur inflation by raising the price of imports. Not Generating Jobs</p>
        <p>Still, many economists say that in reducing the Federal funds rate to 3 percent from 3.25 percent, the Fed did what it had to do to lift the long-languishing economy. The Fed pumped money into the banking system on Friday to lower the Federal funds rate just hours after the Labor Department released a dismal employment report, showing that American business lost 167,000 jobs in August.</p>
        <p>"The economy is still not generating enough jobs, and the Fed had little choice but to show that it is in an easing mode," said Scott E. Pardee, a former Federal Reserve economist who is now chairman of Yamaichi International America. "But to the extent the dollar continues to decline or goes into free fall, that could become a serious political issue for the Bush Administration."</p>
        <p>In an appearance today on the ABC program "This Week with David Brinkley," Richard G. Darman, the White House budget director, predicted the dollar would not fall much further and said the Bundesbank, the German central bank, was largely to blame for the dollar's weakness.</p>
        <p>"I wouldn't expect a flight from the dollar," he said, adding that investors would not pull out of the dollar because the United States still has the world's leading economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darman said the Bundesbank was weakening the dollar by keeping German interest rates high.</p>
        <p>Economists said that the interest rate cut on Friday appeared to be the first instance in which the dollar's weakness had constrained the central bank's flexibility since Alan Greenspan became chairman in August 1987.</p>
        <p>David M. Jones, chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Company, a New York securities firm, said that were it not for the dollar's dive, the Fed might have cut rates as boldly on Friday as it did on July 2, when the Labor Department issued another disastrous jobs report. On that day, the Fed made cuts of a half of a percentage point in the Federal funds rate and the discount rate -- the rate it charges on direct loans to banks. The discount rate is currently at 3 percent.</p>
        <p>"Were it not for the threat of a dollar crisis, the Fed might have been more aggressive today," Mr. Jones said on Friday. "The dollar has become an effective limit on how much further the Fed could ease."</p>
        <p>Among foreign exchange traders, there has been talk in recent weeks that if the dollar went into a free fall, the Fed might be forced to raise rates, which would buttress the dollar by helping attract investment dollars into the United States. But a rate increase is one of the last things President Bush wants, since it could further slow economic growth, and the nearly stalled economy could well prove his downfall.</p>
        <p>The dollar fell sharply against the German mark on Friday, but remained above record lows. It closed at 1.4015 marks on Friday, down from 1.4135 late on Thursday. Help From Italy and Britain</p>
        <p>The dismaying jobs report and rate cut hurt the dollar, but analysts said its slide was slowed by economic maneuvering in Europe that was aimed at keeping the mark from soaring against other currencies. Italy raised its interest rates to buoy the sagging lira, while Britain arranged to borrow $14.5 billion worth of marks from Germany to prop up the pound.</p>
        <p>The flight from dollars toward marks has strengthened the German currency against not only the dollar, but also the lira and pound, which are in danger of sinking below the floor set by the European Monetary System, an arrangement of linked exchange rates.</p>
        <p>Analysts suggested that the Fed chose to lower the Federal funds rate instead of the more visible discount rate to reduce the chances of creating turmoil in the currency markets.</p>
        <p>The jobs report on Friday was one of several recent reports indicating new softness in the economy. The various data have led more and more analysts to talk about the possibility of a triple dip -- that is, a third dip toward recession. The reports include a drop in factory orders, a drop in consumer confidence and weak department store sales.</p>
        <p>Economists said that the Federal Reserve's quarter-point easing would have only a slight stimulative effect and that the effect would probably not be felt for at least four months.</p>
        <p>"The Federal funds rate has been cut almost 700 basis points over the past few years, and these cuts have done surprisingly little to stimulate the economy," said Norman Robertson, chief economist for the Mellon Bank in Pittsburgh. "So I fear that the new rate cut won't do any good at all." A basis point is a hundredth of a percentage point.</p>
        <p>"I suspect it might have been made to defuse political pressure," Mr. Robertson added, "to avoid the accusation that the Fed was ignoring the plight of the economy." Some Question Impact</p>
        <p>After the recovery that began in early 1991 stumbled late last year, Administration officials and many economists blamed the Fed for not cutting rates faster, saying it was not being attentive enough to the economy's problems.</p>
        <p>Just as some economists said the rate cut on Friday might be too small to help the economy much, some said it was so small that it might not hurt the dollar much. Several economists asked what difference a quarter-point rate cut would make when the spread is already almost 7 percent between short-term American and German rates.</p>
        <p>With the Fed's ability to cut rates hamstrung by the dollar's weakness, many economists say there will be increasing pressure within the Administration and Congress to embrace fiscal stimulus -- like increased spending on public works -- notwithstanding the nation's $350 billion budget deficit.</p>
        <p>In the view of many Fed watchers, the Fed may be tempted to lower rates further in the next few weeks, but they said the central bank probably first wanted to see whether the dollar steadies or sinks further.</p>
        <p>Many American officials hope Germany's central bank will soon lower rates to stop the dollar's fall, steady the markets and lift Europe's economy. While some economists predict that the Bundesbank will lower rates in the next few months because Germany's economy is slumping, others say the German central bank is intent on keeping rates high for a long time to make sure inflation returns to less than 3 percent.</p>
        <p>"I think the combination of the falling U.S. interest rates, political uncertainty and an economy that is going nowhere will keep downward pressure on the dollar," Mr. Robertson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
