<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Between The Letters Of the Law</title>
    <meta content="08NYC.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/08/nyregion/08NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1502960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprizzo, John E (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Locurto, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steiner, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walters, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sprizzo, John E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D7143DF93BA35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Between The Letters Of the Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Between the Letters of the Law</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman column deplores Judge John E Sprizzo's ruling that Giuliani administration violated First Amendment rights of two firefighters and a police officer who were dismissed for riding on racist float in Labor Day parade in Queens in 1998 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN late 1984, Judge John E. Sprizzo of Federal District Court in Manhattan refused to extradite a member of the Irish Republican Army who had been found guilty of murdering a British soldier.</p>
        <p>Two days before his 1981 conviction by a British court in Northern Ireland, the I.R.A. man, Joseph Doherty, escaped from a prison in Belfast and made his way to New York. There, he was later arrested. Britain wanted him back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The track record of John E. Sprizzo of Federal District Court in Manhattan shows that a judge's opinion is not always the last word.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN late 1984, Judge John E. Sprizzo of Federal District Court in Manhattan refused to extradite a member of the Irish Republican Army who had been found guilty of murdering a British soldier.</p>
        <p>Two days before his 1981 conviction by a British court in Northern Ireland, the I.R.A. man, Joseph Doherty, escaped from a prison in Belfast and made his way to New York. There, he was later arrested. Britain wanted him back.</p>
        <p>No way, Judge Sprizzo ruled. Killing the soldier was not the same as, say, blowing up a department store and taking civilian lives. This was a political act, he said, and as such it was not covered by the extradition treaty that then existed between the United States and Britain.</p>
        <p>It might be interesting to see if the judge would in principle feel the same about, oh, a Palestinian loyal to Hamas who had killed an Israeli soldier in an occupied part of the Gaza Strip. Or an Iraqi who had shot an American soldier to resist the military occupation of his country. More than likely, though, we will never have a chance to find out.</p>
        <p>In fairness, Judge Sprizzo was not the first judge to refuse to extradite accused I.R.A. terrorists. But his decision struck a nerve with the Reagan administration, which had appointed Judge Sprizzo to the bench and was trying to rally support for a struggle against international terrorism. (Sound familiar?) A senior Justice Department official called the court ruling ''outrageous.'' A few years later, with overwhelming Senate support, the extradition treaty was amended.</p>
        <p>Flip to early 1997. Judge Sprizzo refused to punish two anti-abortion protesters who had repeatedly blocked access to a clinic in Dobbs Ferry, N.Y., because he felt they were true believers.</p>
        <p>It is a federal crime to obstruct entry to abortion clinics. The law allows for no exceptions, not even for two Roman Catholic clergymen who believe to their very souls that abortion is evil. Judge Sprizzo himself had ordered the men, a retired bishop and a Franciscan friar, to obey the law. But they chose instead to block the clinic's driveway yet again. And so federal prosecutors asked the judge to find them in criminal contempt.</p>
        <p>No way, Judge Sprizzo said once more. These men, he said, were motivated by ''conscious-driven religious belief.''</p>
        <p>At least one editorial writer deemed the opinion a ''bizarre'' justification for law-breaking. Here, too, it might be interesting to see if the judge would apply the same principle to, say, someone who had killed an adulterous couple in the ''conscious-driven religious belief'' that the Bible had compelled him to act. It does indeed. Check Leviticus 20:10.</p>
        <p>TURN now to mid-2003. Judge Sprizzo ruled that the Giuliani administration had violated the First Amendment rights of two firefighters and a police officer who were dismissed for riding on a racist parade float in Broad Channel, Queens. They had a right to free speech, the judge said. As a result, he suggested, he may well have to order that they get their jobs back.</p>
        <p>These were the geniuses who on Labor Day 1998 wore blackface and Afro wigs, and threw fried chicken and watermelon to people watching the parade. One of them dangled from the back of the float, mocking the way a black man in Texas, James Byrd Jr., was famously dragged to his death.</p>
        <p>So now, certainly in the case of the former police officer, Joseph Locurto, the city may have to put a gun back in the hands of a man who proved himself, by his own behavior, to possess monumentally poor judgment. Bear in mind that police officers are almost always armed; they are never considered to be fully off-duty. ''Cops are expected to act in a manner consistent with their responsibilities at all times,'' said Jonathan Pines, a lawyer who is handling the case for the city.</p>
        <p>Former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani is the latest person to put a Sprizzo ruling and ''bizarre'' in the same sentence. Think of the city's liability, he said, should someone with Mr. Locurto's record find himself in a racially charged incident.</p>
        <p>Besides, Mr. Giuliani said, ''how do you expect the citizens of the city to have confidence in a Police Department that doesn't remove a police officer who, whatever he says his motives are, engages in making fun of a racial killing?'' The same holds for the Fire Department, he said.</p>
        <p>The city plans to appeal the ruling. For what it's worth, the I.R.A.'s Mr. Doherty was eventually deported. It took roughly a decade for that to happen, but happen it did.</p>
        <p>A judge's opinion is not always the last word.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
