<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Material Made Ethereal</title>
    <meta content="04SMIT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/04/arts/design/04SMIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1428916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Gallery of Art (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Gallery of Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DB1F38F937A35753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Material Made Ethereal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Material Made Ethereal by New Galleries</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews sculptures, predominantly European from 1400 to 1900, on view in newly renovated, redesigned and expanded galleries of West Building at National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER four years of construction, the National Gallery of Art here has unveiled a stunning suite of renovated, redesigned and expanded sculpture galleries on the ground floor of its original West Building. Presenting some 800 objects spanning nine centuries in 22 beautifully proportioned and detailed rooms that total 24,000 square feet, these galleries are a sculpture lover's idea of heaven. That they are devoted predominantly to European sculpture from 1400 to 1900 is quite unusual, at least in this country.</p>
        <p>Sculpture is the bulkiest art, one reason it tends to get short shrift in many American museums. This is especially true for European sculpture after about 1400, when painting began to rule the roost of Western art. Our big museums routinely devote strings of galleries to Egyptian, African, Asian, Greek and Roman sculpture. But they rarely give any extended space to postmedieval European sculpture. The separation of sculpture from architecture, the growing use of canvas, the decline of royal patronage and the secularization of art all contributed to painting's dominance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After four years of construction, the National Gallery of Art in Washington has unveiled a stunning suite of renovated, redesigned and expanded sculpture galleries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER four years of construction, the National Gallery of Art here has unveiled a stunning suite of renovated, redesigned and expanded sculpture galleries on the ground floor of its original West Building. Presenting some 800 objects spanning nine centuries in 22 beautifully proportioned and detailed rooms that total 24,000 square feet, these galleries are a sculpture lover's idea of heaven. That they are devoted predominantly to European sculpture from 1400 to 1900 is quite unusual, at least in this country.</p>
        <p>Sculpture is the bulkiest art, one reason it tends to get short shrift in many American museums. This is especially true for European sculpture after about 1400, when painting began to rule the roost of Western art. Our big museums routinely devote strings of galleries to Egyptian, African, Asian, Greek and Roman sculpture. But they rarely give any extended space to postmedieval European sculpture. The separation of sculpture from architecture, the growing use of canvas, the decline of royal patronage and the secularization of art all contributed to painting's dominance.</p>
        <p>There is also the experience factor. Great paintings are fictions, transporting fabrications that give access to a nonexistent space and a purely visual experience, and this applies even to the starkest Modernist works. Painting is also polymorphous; it can conjure up a seemingly unlimited array of forms and images. And it is no small matter that these works are relatively transportable.</p>
        <p>Sculpture, by contrast, is too, too solid flesh. It intrudes into our space; its subject matter is limited primarily to humans and animals. It has weight, dimension and a birth process, if you will, that is labor-intensive and costly. It requires not only artistic vision and skill, but highly specific craft, mechanical engineering and technical knowledge as well.</p>
        <p>Yet if you concentrate on surfaces, forms and the mechanics of sculpture, it often manages to overcome the gravitational pull of physical reality and familiarity to achieve its own kind of levitation. Concentration is the key, or more precisely, concentration on concentrations of sculpture, and that is just what the National Gallery's new sculpture displays offer.</p>
        <p>This institution has always collected sculpture and had quite a bit of it on view. It has, for example, the world's greatest collection of Renaissance bronze plaquettes, and it has recently completed the world's largest collection of Degas wax models and bronzes, which can now be shown in its entirety for the first time.</p>
        <p>But the sculpture has always been overshadowed by the gallery's world-class painting collection and its excellent, in-depth account of the history of Western painting from the early Renaissance to Post-Impressionism. Not surprisingly, this account occupies prime real estate: the grand, skylighted spaces that run the length and width of the enormous upper floor of the West Building.</p>
        <p>The new sculpture galleries have been built in the space where the old sculpture galleries once stood. But they have been transformed from rather dark, cluttered, unfrequented areas into real estate that is prime in its own right. The rooms are lovely, alternately stately and intimate, and flooded with natural light. While the period re-creation may not be to everyone's liking, the design here, orchestrated by Mark Leithauser, feels solid and is completely appropriate to John Russell Pope's Georgian architecture. (Details like the molding and floorboards have been matched with those of other rooms in the building.) This puts the new galleries head and shoulders above similar re-creations in museums around the country.</p>
        <p>The earlier twists and turns of the old galleries have been ironed out, previously walled-up windows have been uncovered, and about 5,000 square feet have been added. Some of this came from former offices just inside the Constitution Avenue entrance, some from the elimination of confusing nooks and crannies; the rest is from stripping some rooms down to their original walls and excising bulky window casings and radiators. In one of the two largest galleries, this wrangling added about two feet to the width, which is nothing to sniff at.</p>
        <p>With a couple of exceptions, the works proceed in a chronological arrangement, which in the new design is accessible from either end. From the Sixth Street entrance, you can start with the late 19th century and work backward from the glories of the Degas and Rodin holdings, which dominate the first two big galleries. The contrast of these two very different sensibilities is mesmerizing.</p>
        <p>Rodin is all exhibitionistic flamboyance, the master sculptor, whether working in marble, plaster or terra cotta. The display here includes the plaster model for his ''Age of Bronze,'' which was considered so realistic that he was accused of taking a cast from a real person. Degas can be urbane, understated elegance, as in his famous ''Little Dancer, Aged 14,'' who looks up at us as if she had just executed some bit of balletic intricacy perfectly and knows it. There are two examples of the sculpture, facing each other in tutus at the center of the gallery: a wax original and a plaster cast. These, in turn, are flanked by two slightly smaller nude versions -- a bronze and its wax study -- that reveal a young girl's flat chest and pot belly.</p>
        <p>Or Degas can be blunt, observant, psychologically acute and wildly experimental, as with the wax models of dancers, bathers and horses that were found in his studio at his death. There are 44 waxes here, their unerringly accurate forms cobbled together from brusquely modeled clumps of varying combinations of beeswax, paraffin, plastilene, suet and lard, sometimes tinted deep shades of red or green. It is easy to grasp their radicalism: the way they disturb sculpture's centuries-old balance between dumb matter and human form, preceding the sculpture of Matisse and Picasso as surely as Cézanne preceded their paintings.</p>
        <p>But if strict chronological sequence is your preference, and you want a clearer idea of the tradition that Degas overturned, start from the other end, through a doorway near the gallery's Seventh Street entrance. First comes a smattering of late-medieval works: furniture, tapestry and some outstanding pieces of metalwork. Arranged in a small jewel-box gallery, these include a 13th-century bronze aquamanile -- a ceremonial, usually figurative pitcher -- in the form of a horseman, and the chalice of the Abbot Suger of Saint-Denis, a fluted sardonyx cup from from Ptolemaic Egypt that the abbot had mounted in jewel-studded gold.</p>
        <p>From this point you plunge into the gallery's extraordinary holdings in Renaissance portrait medals and plaquettes, which deliver an undiluted sense of the epoch's fascination with classical themes, not to mention its exploration of one-point perspective, human anatomy, biblical narrative and the development of increasingly realistic profile portraits. Beginning with examples by Pisanello and Donatello, the medals and plaquettes proceed from the mid-1400's to the early 1600's, encapsulating the genius of the Italian Renaissance while portraying many of its leading lights (Alberti, Michelangelo). Western painting and sculpture were then on equal terms, and these tiny bronze dimensional images functioned as the artistic equivalent of a swing vote, reflecting and stimulating developments in both mediums.</p>
        <p>A third entrance, near the middle, will take you directly to the main idiosyncrasy of these galleries: the Widener Galleries of Chinese Porcelains, specifically the ornately colored floral patterns of famille verte vases and the rich solid tones of oxblood and peach-blossom vases primarily from the Qing and Kangxi dynasties.</p>
        <p>This entrance also leads to a gallery of works by Bayre, Géricault and Daumier, who is represented by a full set of his bronze caricature busts. It puts you within striking distance of another area of riches, the large gallery devoted to late-Renaissance and Baroque bronzes, mostly small figures. At the moment this gallery is occupied by the world's leading private collection of such bronzes, which belongs to Robert H. Smith, president of the gallery's board. In February they will be replaced by bronzes from the gallery's collection. Either way, they continue the rich tradition that begins with the medals and plaquettes. The Smith pieces, centering on the family and circle of the great Mannerist sculptor Giovanni Bologna, include the sleek animal bronzes of Antonio Susini and a marvelous progression of Hercules figures.</p>
        <p>As you may have surmised by now, the National Gallery's sculpture collection lacks the nearly unbroken narrative that unfolds in the painting galleries upstairs. Instead, it skims along the surface in some areas and elsewhere dives into wells of historic achievement where you could spend a lifetime looking and learning. And don't forget that there are more than 80 sculptures still in place in and around the painting galleries upstairs, including the mysterious madonnas and saints of Mino da Fiesole, a room of della Robbia terra cottas and sculptures by Carpeaux and Clodion in the big vaulted halls that flank the central rotunda.</p>
        <p>The National Gallery's new sculpture galleries add to sculpture's already substantial presence in museums along the Mall. Just outside the West Building's Seventh Street entrance is the gallery's sculpture garden. Directly across the Mall is the Hirshhorn Museum's sculpture garden and, inside, a double ring of galleries devoted entirely to sculpture, most of it from the late 19th and 20th centuries. Nearby are the National Museum of African Art and the Freer and Sackler Galleries of Asian Art, with their caches of non-Western sculpture.</p>
        <p>So these majestic new halls bring a double shift in the balance of visual power. Inside the National Gallery, it is now possible to lose yourself in sculpture as well as in painting. And this shift also reverberates beyond the museum's walls, adding a new concentration of sculpture to those already here.</p>
        <p>The National Gallery of Art's new sculpture galleries are in the West Building, at Sixth Street and Constitution Avenue NW, Washington, (202) 737-4215. The Robert H. Smith Collection of Renaissance bronzes, part of the initial installation, is on view through Feb. 17.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
