<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Overrun Enclave, New Evidence of Mass Killings</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="783323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SREBRENICA (BOSNIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRISTIAN SCIENCE MONITOR</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROHDE, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D81238F93AA2575BC0A963958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Overrun Enclave, New Evidence of Mass Killings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An American reporter who ventured into Bosnian Serb territory around a former Muslim enclave this week has found evidence to support the Clinton Administration's allegations that hundreds of Bosnian Muslim prisoners may have been massacred and buried in mass graves after the fall of the "safe area" in July.</p>
        <p>The reporter, David Rohde of The Christian Science Monitor, saw a building littered with feces and blood near a soccer stadium where hundreds of prisoners were held. In a nearby field, part of a human leg protruded from an area of freshly dug earth. He was told by Bosnian Serb soldiers that all Bosnian Muslims from the enclave, Srebrenica, are being hunted down and summarily executed if they are captured. The Bosnian Serb leadership had denied the charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An American reporter who ventured into Bosnian Serb territory around a former Muslim enclave this week has found evidence to support the Clinton Administration's allegations that hundreds of Bosnian Muslim prisoners may have been massacred and buried in mass graves after the fall of the "safe area" in July.</p>
        <p>The reporter, David Rohde of The Christian Science Monitor, saw a building littered with feces and blood near a soccer stadium where hundreds of prisoners were held. In a nearby field, part of a human leg protruded from an area of freshly dug earth. He was told by Bosnian Serb soldiers that all Bosnian Muslims from the enclave, Srebrenica, are being hunted down and summarily executed if they are captured. The Bosnian Serb leadership had denied the charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rohde's report was published in The Christian Science Monitor yesterday.</p>
        <p>Nowhere in his travels around Srebrenica, which fell to Bosnian Serbs on July 11, or Zepa, another United Nations "safe area" that was overrun two weeks later, did Mr. Rohde hear of any groups of Bosnian Muslim prisoners still being held. The United Nations estimates that between 4,000 and 6,000 Muslims are missing, but neither United Nations officials nor representatives of the International Committee of the Red Cross have been allowed into the area around the possible graves to check reports of massacres or to look for the missing people.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 10, Madeleine K. Albright, the United States' delegate to the United Nations, showed the Security Council American spy photographs taken around Srebrenica during the days after the town's fall to the Bosnian Serbs. Pictures made by satellite around July 13-14 showed people crowded into a soccer field at Nova Kasaba, near Srebrenica.</p>
        <p>Several days later, spy plane photography recorded an empty stadium but mounds of freshly dug earth in the nearby field. The United States also had testimony from a refugee in his 60's who had escaped after being left for dead. He said that he was among about 600 people corralled in the soccer field, and that men and boys in groups of 20 or 25 had been taken away from there and shot.</p>
        <p>Ms. Albright told the Council that 2,000 to 2,700 people may have been killed there and hastily buried.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rohde, who is based in Zagreb, Croatia, as the Monitor's eastern European correspondent, went to both the soccer stadium and the nearby field. He described what he saw in an abandoned building at the soccer ground.</p>
        <p>"Dozens of piles of feces line the floor of the three-room, one-story building, and in two places it appeared that someone or something had been repeatedly rubbed through the waste," he wrote. "Several dozen bullet holes pocked the interior walls, and what appeared to be dried blood stains dotted the floor and one wall." Mr. Rohde wrote that what he saw was consistent with published reports of accounts from refugees from the region.</p>
        <p>At the vacant field where American spy planes photographed mounds of newly disturbed earth, Mr. Rohde wrote, "three areas of fresh digging were clearly visible," the largest measuring about 300 feet by 300 feet.</p>
        <p>"On the edge of the smallest of the three alleged mass graves, what appeared to be a human femur and tibia surrounded by bits of fabric jutted from rich brown dirt." Faded photographs of a young man were scattered on the ground near another excavation.</p>
        <p>"Approximately a quarter-mile from the three sites, Muslim prayer beads, clothing and still legible receipts and election ballots from Srebrenica were found," he wrote. The reporter also wrote that he saw truck and bulldozer tracks leading to the mass graves and two empty ammunition boxes and a few shell casings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
