<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Into the Vortex to Save the Earth</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="783403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MORTAL KOMBAT (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D9113EF93AA2575BC0A963958260" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Into the Vortex to Save the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Mortal Kombat," the flashy movie version of the popular video game, reverses the customary cinematic role of using special effects to enhance the drama. Its eerie photographic distortions and computer-animated transformations of rocks and statues into fire-breathing monsters are the drama. The actors and the story are mere appendages of the action and pyrotechnics. The movie's extensive martial arts sequences, in which combatants bounce off each other doing triple handsprings, suggest a slightly more earthbound version of the aerial ballets in Hong Kong action-adventure films.</p>
        <p>In the movie, which opened yesterday, three plucky young warriors -- Liu Kang (Robin Shou), Johnny Cage (Linden Ashby) and Sonya Blade (Bridgette Wilson) -- team up to keep the earth from falling into the hands of Shang Tsung (Cary-Hiroyki Tagawa), an evil sorcerer who rules a hellish alternate reality called Outworld. Shang Tsung's power is from the collected souls of the warriors he has defeated, whom he summons into his body when fighting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Mortal Kombat," the flashy movie version of the popular video game, reverses the customary cinematic role of using special effects to enhance the drama. Its eerie photographic distortions and computer-animated transformations of rocks and statues into fire-breathing monsters are the drama. The actors and the story are mere appendages of the action and pyrotechnics. The movie's extensive martial arts sequences, in which combatants bounce off each other doing triple handsprings, suggest a slightly more earthbound version of the aerial ballets in Hong Kong action-adventure films.</p>
        <p>In the movie, which opened yesterday, three plucky young warriors -- Liu Kang (Robin Shou), Johnny Cage (Linden Ashby) and Sonya Blade (Bridgette Wilson) -- team up to keep the earth from falling into the hands of Shang Tsung (Cary-Hiroyki Tagawa), an evil sorcerer who rules a hellish alternate reality called Outworld. Shang Tsung's power is from the collected souls of the warriors he has defeated, whom he summons into his body when fighting.</p>
        <p>The showdown, which takes place on a craggy Asian island, suggests a supernatural, martial arts-oriented version of the Olympics. Coaching the young heroes is Lord Rayden, an earthly god of thunder and lightning, played by Christopher Lambert, who looks downright silly in shoulder-length silver hair and wearing his trademark smirk. When he's in a huff, Lord Rayden can generate lightning on the tips of his fingers and in his eyes, but he is powerless to do anything really significant.</p>
        <p>"Mortal Kombat" might be described as mythological junk food. Although there is talk of the three kombatants' having to face their deepest fears to prevail, the action is so frenetic and the dialogue so minimal that the allegory is weightless.</p>
        <p>Among the monsters they encounter, the most traditional is Shang Tsung's right-hand man, a roaring four-armed goon named Goro who suggests a depilated King Kong with two extra limbs. The most intriguing is a glassy-eyed follower whose right hand shoots out a hissing reptile that can extend itself for miles. Exotic creatures like these make watching "Mortal Kombat" feel like being in a high-tech fun house.</p>
        <p>"Mortal Kombat" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It includes one or two profanities and horror-movie effects that are more squishy than gory.  MORTAL KOMBAT  Directed by Paul Anderson; written by Kevin Droney, based on the video game; director of photography, John R. Leonetti; edited by Martin Hunter; music by George S. Clinton; production designer, Jonathan Carlson; produced by Lawrence Kasanoff; released by New Line Cinema. Running time: 95 minutes. This film is rated PG-13. WITH: Christopher Lambert (Lord Rayden), Linden Ashby (Johnny Cage), Cary-Hiroyuki Tagawa (Shang Tsung), Robin Shou (Liu Kang), Bridgette Wilson (Sonya Blade), Talisa Soto (Kitana) and Trevor Goddard (Kano)</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
