<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; New York savings bank mergers may not see many windfalls.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANSELL, SAUL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5D6163FF93BA35754C0A962958260" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; New York savings bank mergers may not see many windfalls.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Saul Hansell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANSELL, SAUL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE announcement on Wednesday that Dime Bancorp and Anchor Bancorp plan to merge into the largest savings bank on the East Coast confirmed that banks in the New York area are now in a certifiable merger boom.</p>
        <p>But the sharp drop in Dime's stock price is a warning that this takeover frenzy may not create easy riches for investors. Dime's shares, which reached a high of $10.75 last Friday, were down to $9.25 by Wednesday and lost 12.5 cents, to $9.125, yesterday. Anchor shares fell slightly, to $15.50 on Wednesday, but rose to $15.75 yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE announcement on Wednesday that Dime Bancorp and Anchor Bancorp plan to merge into the largest savings bank on the East Coast confirmed that banks in the New York area are now in a certifiable merger boom.</p>
        <p>But the sharp drop in Dime's stock price is a warning that this takeover frenzy may not create easy riches for investors. Dime's shares, which reached a high of $10.75 last Friday, were down to $9.25 by Wednesday and lost 12.5 cents, to $9.125, yesterday. Anchor shares fell slightly, to $15.50 on Wednesday, but rose to $15.75 yesterday.</p>
        <p>Analysts and investment bankers say that other stocks of banks in the New York area may already be trading at higher prices than even an imminent takeover warrants.</p>
        <p>"It seems, of late, it doesn't pay to speculate." said Jerome I. Baron, an analyst with Josephthal, Lyon &amp; Ross. "Speculators have been hurt."</p>
        <p>There are dozens of small banks and savings banks in the region that are recovering from real estate and other problems that crippled them in the last few years. Every industry expert predicts that the small banks will be swallowed by the medium-sized banks, which in turn will be consumed by the big banks.</p>
        <p>In the case of Dime, investors were especially disappointed that the merger with Anchor was what is termed a merger of equals, in which the banks combine at roughly equal values.</p>
        <p>Over the last month, Dime's stock, which had traded between $8 and $9 for most of the year, had been bid up on speculation that it would be taken over at a large premium.</p>
        <p>Typically, big banks are buying smaller savings banks for about 1.7 times their book value. As Dime's book value is $8.68 a share, such a takeover would imply a price of $14.75.</p>
        <p>As it is, the companies are being pooled in an arrangement that exchanges each share of Anchor for 1.77 shares of Dime, which will be the name of the combined company. When the chairmen of the banks first set the terms of the deal a month ago, shareholders of neither bank were to receive any premium. Since Dime's shares have risen sharply since then, at last Friday's prices, Anchor shareholders appear to receive a slight benefit, although much of that difference has been erased by the drop in Dime's price. Still, any investor who had bought Anchor in hopes of cashing out in a quick takeover is disappointed.</p>
        <p>Even in a classic bank takeover, investors have not always gotten the premiums they had been hoping for. For example, the Hamilton Bancorp of Brooklyn, agreed to be acquired by the New York Bancorp on July 1 for $34.60 in stock. While that price represents 1.62 times Hamilton's book value, investors had bid up Hamilton's stock to $35.25 the day before the deal was announced. (Since Hamilton said it had hired a merger adviser, the deal was by no means a surprise to the market.)</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Adar Equities, a Hamilton shareholder, sued that company to block the merger on the ground that the price was too low -- although no higher bidders had expressed interest.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that other New York banks that are seen as targets may already be at or close to their potential takeover prices. For example, the stock of Fidelity New York FSB, in Garden City, L.I., has jumped 50 percent this year, to $24.25 yesterday, on takeover speculation. While Thomas F. Theurkauf, an analyst with Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods, a New York brokerage firm that specializes in banks, estimates that the bank could be bought between $28 and $30, "there is not a tremendous amount of upside left," he said.</p>
        <p>For investors set on gambling on takeovers, several analysts are recommending the North Side Savings Bank, of Floral Park, Queens, which is selling for about its book value despite a 33 percent run-up in price this year.</p>
        <p>And for a longer-term view, most analysts are bullish on the Anchor-Dime combination. If the merger goes smoothly and the combined bank can use increased market share to bolster revenue with lower costs, it could well be bought for a substantial premium several years from now.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
