<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A REBUFF FOR U.S.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PANAMA REFUSES TO TAKE HAITIANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GUANTANAMO BAY NAVAL BASE (CUBA)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PANAMA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GRENADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTIGUA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DOMINICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GUYANA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SURINAME</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORDON, MICHAEL R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, WILLIAM H 3D (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENDARA, GUILLERMO (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Suriname</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Dominica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Grenada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guyana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Suriname</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Grenada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Dominica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Antigua and Barbuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D8163FF93BA35754C0A962958260" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A REBUFF FOR U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORDON, MICHAEL R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after the Administration announced that Panama would serve as a "safe haven" for 10,000 Haitian refugees, Panama withdrew from the plan, leaving Washington struggling to cope with a new flood of boat people.</p>
        <p>The decision, announced by the Panamanian President, Guillermo Endara, led to a round of finger-pointing between Panama and Washington and overshadowed President Clinton's arrival in Italy for an economic summit meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days after the Administration announced that Panama would serve as a "safe haven" for 10,000 Haitian refugees, Panama withdrew from the plan, leaving Washington struggling to cope with a new flood of boat people.</p>
        <p>The decision, announced by the Panamanian President, Guillermo Endara, led to a round of finger-pointing between Panama and Washington and overshadowed President Clinton's arrival in Italy for an economic summit meeting.</p>
        <p>Surprised by the decision, Administration officials tried to put the best face on the setback. William H. Gray 3d, the special envoy on Haiti, said Washington would not pursue talks with Panama, but he insisted the United States would find other sites.</p>
        <p>"We will continue forward with our policy," Mr. Gray told reporters. "Panama was an important part of it, but we are in the process of building a network to provide a response to the surge of refugees caused by the deterioration of human rights in Haiti."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray also announced that Grenada, like Antigua and Dominica, had agreed "in principle" to provide safe havens. Other officials said Washington was considering trying to establish camps in Guyana, Suriname and maybe even West Africa.</p>
        <p>"Obviously we're disappointed," the White House press secretary, Dee Dee Myers, said in Naples, where President Clinton arrived today for a summit meeting of the Group of Seven industrial democracies.</p>
        <p>American officials said Panama rejected the plan after President Endara realized he had misjudged the domestic opposition. But the collapse of the plan is likely to fuel criticism that President Clinton's foreign policy is confused. And it puts additional pressure on the White House to consider military force to oust Haiti's military leadership.</p>
        <p>Even before the Panamanian announcement, the Administration was struggling to cope with the Haitians who have continued to put to sea. The Coast Guard announced that it had picked up 892 Haitians today by noon, and 1,731 on Wednesday. That brought the total since mid-June to more than 16,000.</p>
        <p>To help stem the flood, the Administration announced on Tuesday that Haitians picked up at sea would no longer be resettled in the United States. And today, the Pentagon announced that it would expand its processing center at Guantanamo to handle 20,000 Haitians at a time.</p>
        <p>"We are very aware of what the math is on this," said Dennis Boxx, the Pentagon spokesman. "We have people in Guantanamo Bay working 24 hours a day doing everything humanly possible to expand the capability of that camp."</p>
        <p>Expanding the capacity at Guantanamo to 20,000, from 12,500 currently, will severely tax the military's ability to provide shelter, water, electricity and sanitation, military officials said. More than 10,000 Haitians are there already; more than 400 have decided to return to Haiti, an Administration source said today.</p>
        <p>"It would be monumental," George H. Walls Jr., a retired Marine brigadier general who commanded a refugee operation at Guantanamo from November 1991 to March 1992, said in a telephone interview. During that operation, the number of refugees topped 11,000.  Tents on the Golf Course</p>
        <p>To make room for 20,000 refugees, the military will have to pitch tents on the base's golf course and football field, military engineers concluded in a study two years ago.</p>
        <p>The base's desalting plant can produce three million gallons of drinking water a day, but the military would have to truck it to the Haitians or lay thousands of feet of pipe. The military could also bring in machines to convert sea water or brackish water into drinking water, General Walls added.</p>
        <p>The sudden collapse of the Administration's negotiations with Panama prompted a round of recriminations.</p>
        <p>The outlines of the plan were worked out last weekend by United States officials who went to Panama. To try to complete the understanding, Rand Beers, from the National Security Council, went to Panama early this week.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday night, Administration officials confidently described the remaining issues as largely technical. But this morning it became clear that the differences reflected broad unhappiness in Panama.</p>
        <p>President Endara was sworn in on an American military base in Panama during the 1989 United States invasion of Panama. And the perception that he was doing Washington's bidding appeared to be especially sensitive for the President, who leaves office on Sept. 1. Ernesto Perez Balladares, Mr. Endara's political opponent, won the presidency in early May in the first elections in Panama in more than 25 years. Debating Who Blinked</p>
        <p>In his remarks to reporters in Panama City, Mr. Endara complained that the Administration had continually changed the terms of the arrangement and had taken Panama's cooperation for granted.</p>
        <p>At first, Washington proposed that the refugees would be kept on an offshore island. Then, bowing to the wishes of the Panamanian political opposition, the United States said they would be kept on American bases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Endara also said the plan to put the Haitians on bases in Panama violated the Panama Canal Treaty.</p>
        <p>But one Administration official said it was President Endara who reneged after he realized he had miscalculated the degree of opposition.</p>
        <p>Other changes in the refugee plan were announced today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray acknowledged that Washington had relaxed its standard for determining which Haitians would be eligible for placement in a safe haven. On Tuesday Mr. Gray told reporters that only those with "a real and credible fear with regard to political persecution" would be sent to the camps. The others would be sent back to Haiti.</p>
        <p>But officials said today that there would not be rigorous screening of Haitians picked up sea, and they would not be asked to prove they would face persecution if they returned.</p>
        <p>Criminal and human rights violators would not be eligible to go to a safe haven. Looking Closely at Force</p>
        <p>Though Administration officials insisted they can cope, the flood of refugees adds to the pressure on Washington to consider military action to topple the military leaders who ousted President Jean-Bertrand Aristide in September 1991. Human rights abuses by the military, combined with economic sanctions imposed on Haiti, have driven tens of thousands to flee the country.</p>
        <p>Stepping up preparations for a possible invasion, more than a thousand commandos recently rehearsed a plan to seize airfields and ports in Haiti, Pentagon officials said on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Asked about the possibility of military action, Mr. Gray said today: "I think the prospect of intervention grows as the coup leadership refuses to recognize that the world community has clearly called upon them to step down and allow democracy to be restored, and for the people of Haiti to move from under the boot of repression. However the world community, along with the United States, is committed to attempting every effort to resolve this crisis through diplomacy and financial restrictions."</p>
        <p>PANAMA REFUSES TO TAKE HAITIANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
