<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; Sex Icon Once, Oddity Now</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VALENTINO, RUDOLPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D81139F93BA35752C1A967958260" item-length="1501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; Sex Icon Once, Oddity Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE wore a turban and tons of eyeshadow in "The Sheik," played a Spanish bullfighter in "Blood and Sand" and was a tango-dancing fool dressed as an Argentine gaucho in "The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse." But when Rudolph Valentino put on a powdered wig to play an 18th-century French nobleman in "Monsieur Beaucaire," his fans rejected the film as a foppish turn in the Latin lover's steamy career. "Something has happened to the Valentino of 'The Sheik' and 'Blood and Sand,' " the movie magazine Photoplay complained in 1924. "He doesn't look a bit dangerous to women." Back in the 1920's, a girl really had to watch out for those Argentine gauchos.</p>
        <p>Valentino is the best proof that one generation's sex symbol is another's campy curiosity. Though he was one of silent film's greatest superstars, today he would be more comfortable in a Mel Brooks parody than as People magazine's sexiest man alive. When he wasn't dancing or dueling, he acted by posing in elaborate costumes and popping open his eyes to show emotion. Love, hate, surprise, any emotion at all. Even considering that exaggerated gestures were standard in silent films, Valentino lacked subtlety.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE wore a turban and tons of eyeshadow in "The Sheik," played a Spanish bullfighter in "Blood and Sand" and was a tango-dancing fool dressed as an Argentine gaucho in "The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse." But when Rudolph Valentino put on a powdered wig to play an 18th-century French nobleman in "Monsieur Beaucaire," his fans rejected the film as a foppish turn in the Latin lover's steamy career. "Something has happened to the Valentino of 'The Sheik' and 'Blood and Sand,' " the movie magazine Photoplay complained in 1924. "He doesn't look a bit dangerous to women." Back in the 1920's, a girl really had to watch out for those Argentine gauchos.</p>
        <p>Valentino is the best proof that one generation's sex symbol is another's campy curiosity. Though he was one of silent film's greatest superstars, today he would be more comfortable in a Mel Brooks parody than as People magazine's sexiest man alive. When he wasn't dancing or dueling, he acted by posing in elaborate costumes and popping open his eyes to show emotion. Love, hate, surprise, any emotion at all. Even considering that exaggerated gestures were standard in silent films, Valentino lacked subtlety.</p>
        <p>But his image -- exotic, artificial, with a splash of machismo and a whiff of androgyny -- spoke to the forbidden desires of the era. His short career lasted from 1921 until his death at the age of 31 in 1926. It was a hedonistic time in Hollywood, but the actors' and film makers' licentiousness arrived on screen cloaked in conventional morality, bringing what seemed like daring sexual fantasies to Middle America. Valentino's greatest role, as icon and cultural phenomenon, is the focus of "The Valentino Cult," a series that begins tomorrow and runs through Nov. 24 at the American Museum of the Moving Image in Astoria, Queens. Among the 12 films in the series, Valentino stars in only 4. Most feature a peculiar circle of Valentino's colleagues, all of them women. There are two films starring his one-time lover Pola Negri, three starring Alla Nazimova, the flamboyant Russian actress who encouraged his career, and several featuring stunning set designs by Natacha Rambova, Valentino's second wife. It's easier to distinguish Nazimova from Rambova once you know that Rambova, Mrs. Valentino, was originally named Winifred Shaughnessy and born in Salt Lake City. Like her husband, whose career she heavily influenced, Rambova knew that in the movie landscape of the 20's, an exotic image was everything.</p>
        <p>By concentrating on less familiar films, the series creates serious omissions. Three of the movies most closely tied to the Valentino image are not included: "The Sheik" (1921), "Blood and Sand" (1922) and "Son of the Sheik" (1926). It is impossible to get a complete sense of Valentino's career or importance without them. But there are some fascinating rewards here, including the film that made Valentino a star.</p>
        <p>He had arrived at Ellis Island from Italy in 1913, still named Rodolfo Gu glielmi. He became a paid tango partner in New York dance halls and eventually made his way to Hollywood and bit parts as villains and gigolos. His career took off when he danced that tango in "Four Horsemen" in 1921.</p>
        <p>Valentino plays Julio Desnoyers, a reluctant hero in World War I. But first, he gets to be a libertine. The son of an Argentine mother and French emigre father, Julio leaves his gaucho costume behind when the family moves from Argentina to Paris.</p>
        <p>There, Valentino wears a tuxedo and slicked-back hair. Half-naked women pose for him in his artist's studio, he becomes an instructor at the Tango Palace, and falls in love with a beautiful young woman married to an old man. After these glamorous scenes, Julio must, of course, put on a uniform and die a hero's death. He returns as a ghost to shake his finger at the young woman and encourage her to stay true to her husband.</p>
        <p>Silly as it sounds, "Four Horsemen" is one of the few Valentino films that has more to offer than Valentino. It was directed by Rex Ingram and written by June Mathis, two of the most successful silent-film makers, and for its time it was an extravagant, powerful accomplishment. There are effective battle scenes and symbolic images of the four horsemen from the Book of Revelation that create a sense of helplessness in the face of war. Even the title cards give attention to detail, with decorative drawings in the corners -- liquor bottles for the libertine days or cannons for war.</p>
        <p>As Julio, Valentino seemed to be everything women wanted: an exotic-looking playboy and a moralistic hero rolled into one. It was an image he carried for the rest of his career.</p>
        <p>In 1921 alone, three more Valentino films were released: "The Sheik"; "The Conquering Power," a flat adaptation of Balzac's "Eugenie Grandet," with Valentino as an impoverished hero, and "Camille," updated to the 1920's.</p>
        <p>In "Camille," Valentino co-starred with Alla Nazimova, and there he met Nastacha Rambova, who created the film's Art Nouveau sets. At the time, Valentino was trying to escape from a messy marriage of convenience to Jean Acker, a lesbian actress who was more successful than he and might have helped his career. They had married on a whim, and she had slammed the door in his face on their wedding night. As bad as Valentino's acting was, sometimes his judgment was worse.</p>
        <p>"Camille" was the kind of literary film that the artistic Rambova thought Valentino should be making; she thought "The Sheik" was junk. It was Rambova who encouraged the disastrous "Monsieur Beaucaire." Her influence became so overwhelming -- and her advice so uncommercial -- that she was finally barred from the sets of Valentino's films. She then proved that love is not always the conquering power, and divorced him.</p>
        <p>But one of the most spectacular films in "The Valentino Cult" belongs to her. "Salome" (1922) stars Alla Nazimova in a version of Oscar Wilde's play that is part dance, part theater, part time capsule. The true star is Rambova's set design, adapted from Aubrey Beardsley's illustrations for the play. She created glittering black, white and silver backdrops, a stylized cage for John the Baptist's jail, painted tights for the servants and elaborately foolish headdresses. Nazimova, the star, insisted on short-skirted costumes and a simpering acting style that makes her more flapper than femme fatale, and her dance of the seven veils has more veils than movement. Still, this period piece is weirdly intense, and it shows the artistic ambitions and pretensions of Valentino's circle.</p>
        <p>In 1926, Valentino was in New York on a tour to promote "The Son of the Sheik" when he died. The thousands of women who screamed and fainted and streamed through Frank E. Campbell's Funeral Chapel for three days ignored the unglamorous circumstances of his death: their dashing hero had died of complications from a gastric ulcer. If he had lived, it's hard to imagine he would have aged very gracefully. But his curious legend has been preserved. When the Films in the Series Are On</p>
        <p>"The Valentino Cult" film series runs tomorrow through Nov. 24 at the American Museum of the Moving Image, 35th Avenue and 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. With the exception of the first and last films of the series, all pictures are silent, with piano accompaniment by Donald Sosin. All films are free with museum admission of $5 ($4 for the elderly, $2.50 for children and students). Museum hours are noon to 4 P.M., Mondays through Fridays; noon to 6 P.M., Saturdays and Sundays. Information: (718) 784-0077. Here is a schedule of screenings. Tomorrow</p>
        <p>"VALENTINO" (1951), directed by Lewis Allen; with Anthony Dexter, Richard Carlson, Eleanor Parker and Patricia Medina. 2 P.M.  "THE FOUR HORSEMEN OF THE APOCALYPSE" (1921), directed by Rex Ingram; with Rudolph Valentino and Alice Terry. 4 P.M.  Sunday</p>
        <p>"LOMBARDI, LTD." (1919), directed by Jack Conway; with Bert Lytell and Alice Lake. 2 P.M.  "THE CONQUERING POWER" (1921), directed by Rex Ingram; with Rudolph Valentino and Alice Terry. 4 P.M.  Nov. 16</p>
        <p>"STRONGER THAN DEATH" (1920), directed by Herbert Blanche; with Alla Nazimova and Charles Bryant. 2 P.M.  "CAMILLE" (1921), directed by Ray Smallwood; with Alla Nazimova and Rudolph Valentino. 4 P.M.  Nov. 17</p>
        <p>"SALOME" (1922), directed by Charles Bryant; with Alla Nazimova, Mitchell Lewis and Nigel de Brulier. 2 P.M.  "MARE NOSTRUM" (1926), directed by Rex Ingram; with Alice Terry and Antonio Moreno. 4 P.M.  Nov. 23</p>
        <p>"SAPPHO" (1921), directed by Dimitri Buchowetski; with Pola Negri and Alfred Abel. 2 P.M.  "HOTEL IMPERIAL" (1927), directed by Mauritz Stiller; with Pola Negri and James Hall. 4 P.M.  Nov. 24</p>
        <p>"MONSIEUR BEAUCAIRE" (1924), directed by Sidney Olcott; with Rudolph Valentino, Bebe Daniels and Lois Wilson. 2 P.M.  "VALENTINO" (1977), directed by Ken Russell; with Rudolf Nureyev, Leslie Caron and Michelle Phillips. 4 P.M.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
