<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangel's Voice: Stronger Than Ever; Dean of Delegation Furious Over Cuts</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RANGEL, CHARLES B (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED91430F935A25756C0A963958260" item-length="1689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangel's Voice: Stronger Than Ever; Dean of Delegation Furious Over Cuts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even at a recent memorial service for an old friend, held in a Harlem church just down the block from the house where he was born, Representative Charles B. Rangel used his turn at the pulpit to preach against "the silence of good people" while, as he sees it, the world is falling apart.</p>
        <p>"Black folks are being hurt as we never have before," Mr. Rangel told the crowd gathered to remember a community leader, Arnold P. Johnson, and a few people said amen to that. "And I say there are so many white folks affected who don't even know it!" he went on, his voice cresting. "The same thing happened in Germany, where people thought this was happening to somebody else. But they will find out they're on the list, too."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even at a recent memorial service for an old friend, held in a Harlem church just down the block from the house where he was born, Representative Charles B. Rangel used his turn at the pulpit to preach against "the silence of good people" while, as he sees it, the world is falling apart.</p>
        <p>"Black folks are being hurt as we never have before," Mr. Rangel told the crowd gathered to remember a community leader, Arnold P. Johnson, and a few people said amen to that. "And I say there are so many white folks affected who don't even know it!" he went on, his voice cresting. "The same thing happened in Germany, where people thought this was happening to somebody else. But they will find out they're on the list, too."</p>
        <p>Though outrage is an overused word on Capitol Hill, Mr. Rangel gives every indication of actually being mad as hell. It isn't only the Republican Contract With America that sets him off, though he says it is contrary to everything he believes in. He is also furious at many fellow Democrats, whom he describes as complacent during an all-out assault on the poor.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly likens what he calls the current apathy to the attitude in Nazi Germany that led to the Holocaust. He assails everyone from President Clinton to John Cardinal O'Connor, admonishing that they should speak out more forcefully. He also says he fears that the country is on the brink of violent revolution.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, he sounds surprisingly like a conservative talk-show host, until he gets to the part about his proposed solution, which is almost always education. He says Hispanic and black teen-agers are alone among God's creatures in having no sense of self-preservation and he calls drug dealers so dumb they have to eat in Burger Kings because they can't read a menu.</p>
        <p>And in this, his 25th year in Congress, the dean of the New York delegation, who will be 65 next month, is now the No. 2 Democrat on a powerful House committee, Ways and Means, and seems to have abandoned even the modicum of restraint traditionally maintained by those in his position.</p>
        <p>"I'm starting a new approach," he said. "I'm going to become a terrorist, too" -- an oratorical bomb-thrower with a doomsday message and the unhappy conviction that he is mostly going it alone these days.</p>
        <p>His role as spokesman for the have-nots is not new, but Mr. Rangel, who normally uses wit to make a point, has turned up the volume considerably.</p>
        <p>"I've seen, since the fall election, a different Charlie Rangel," said Barbara B. Kennelly, a Connecticut Democrat on the Ways and Means Committee. "Now he's determined to let his life experience be known."</p>
        <p>At the Democrats' recent retreat in Piney Point, Md., the House minority leader, Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, said of Mr. Rangel: "We were all focused on what to do about economic problems and the angry middle class, and he quickly brought everybody back to earth by reminding us that some people have stopped even trying to get into the middle class because there's no hope. People listened."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rangel dismissed the retreat "as just so much chitchat."</p>
        <p>After three decades in public life, the portly, gravel-voiced Mr. Rangel, who is very much the Old World-style gentleman yet sprinkles his sentences with mild profanity, still takes politics personally. And he is acutely embarrassed, he said, to see the New Deal falling apart while he is on the job.</p>
        <p>After a constituent greeted him outside his office and praised his recent performance in a television debate, he shook his head and said: "They think I'm winning. I can't tell them what I've told you. I can't say it all stopped on my watch."</p>
        <p>A particular sore point is both the substance and the language of the welfare debate, in which people on aid have been likened to wolves and alligators. "I don't know what the hell people felt in Germany when they would say the Jews were responsible for every goddamn problem that Europe and Germany had, but there were a whole lot of people who agreed with them," he said. "And more than those that agreed was the goddamn silence of the moral leaders."</p>
        <p>In referring to the Holocaust, he said, he did not intend to compare that singular horror to anything happening in Congress today. But he does intend, he said, to be as outrageous as necessary to pierce the silence.</p>
        <p>A Roman Catholic himself, he is particularly critical of leaders in his own church, including Cardinal O'Connor, who along with Catholic bishops has criticized the proposed welfare overhaul and said it could encourage abortions. But that is not enough for Mr. Rangel.</p>
        <p>"We are talking about feeding the hungry!" he said, loosening his tie and moving into an impassioned monologue in his New York office, on 125th Street, where the view from his window includes one of the nation's first public housing projects. The Cardinal, he said, "sent somebody to say he saw me on C-Span and how proud he was of how I was dealing with the question of welfare and he was preparing to make a political statement.</p>
        <p>"I said, 'You turn right back and tell him I don't need any political statement. Tell him to put his vestments on and get on the Capitol steps and read Matthew,' " he said, referring to the Gospel reading in which Jesus says heaven belongs to those who feed the hungry, take in the strangers and visit the sick and those in prison. "What the hell do you need a political statement for when it's in the New Testament?"</p>
        <p>His own experience, he said, illustrates the need for a more aggressive approach.</p>
        <p>Born in Harlem in 1930, Charles Bernard Rangel barely knew the father who he says physically abused his mother, never held a job and left the family when Charles was 6.</p>
        <p>His mother, Blanche Rangel, cleaned houses, worked as a home attendant and cut the threads off shoulder pads coming off a factory assembly line. When he was 8, he too went to work, in a neighborhood drug store, delivering prescriptions and pouring castor oil into small bottles from 5-gallon cans.</p>
        <p>He always worked, but by the time he was in high school he was often truant and occasionally driven home by the police. At 16, he quit school to sell shoes, and drifted, he said, until he served in the Army during the Korean War, when he rescued 40 men from behind enemy lines and was decorated with the Purple Heart and the Bronze Star.</p>
        <p>And after he returned home to banner headlines in The New York Amsterdam News, he went back to school and became a lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel's rocky start, overcome with the government's help, has made him a broken record on the subject of funds for education and programs for those he calls "second chancers" like himself.</p>
        <p>Yet he is no softy in speaking about personal responsibility. "I've always talked about the problem of irresponsible women having babies that will turn into urban terrorists," he said. "Sure, that's just what the Republicans picked up on and I don't deny that. But it's an indictment of the educational system."</p>
        <p>And he describes drug dealers in the harshest terms: "These young entrepreneurs are so stupid that they can't even count their money with a money counter. They have no idea what to do with the money, I mean after they get their mother a big television set and they buy some stupid Jeep with a boom system in it and they get every girl there is to like some gold teeth and some chains. If you told them, 'Why don't you go to Europe?' it's, 'Which way is Europe?' "</p>
        <p>His own role model, when he was a child who could have easily got into trouble, was his mother's father, a courthouse elevator operator who always wore his uniform and badge home and knew all the judges and big-shot lawyers.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Rangel's most emotional memories is returning home alone and sad after his New York University graduation, which he had very much wanted his grandfather to attend, and finding him in the kitchen, all dressed up and drunk. He had gone to the graduation, it turned out, but had been unable to find his grandson in the crowd, so he went home.</p>
        <p>When his grandfather wanted to continue working at his Civil Service job past the mandatory retirement age of 70, the young Mr. Rangel stopped by the local political club to ask for help in the matter. Soon after that he got involved in politics himself, mostly, he said, because he had seen how puny the competition was.</p>
        <p>In Congress, the fight against drug abuse has been his great passion; he has vehemently opposed those who favor legalization, and defended Nancy Reagan when others disparaged her 'Just Say No' campaign.</p>
        <p>But the Congressman's wife, Alma Carter Rangel, a former social worker whom he says he loved at first sight, which was nearly 40 years ago on the dance floor of Harlem's Savoy Ballroom, said without hesitation that his chief motivation in life is ambition.</p>
        <p>Some of those ambitions have lately been dashed, at least temporarily, during an exceptionally difficult period for Mr. Rangel, both personally and politically. After the last election, he lost his chairmanship of a key Ways and Means subcommittee.</p>
        <p>Then, in March, Mr. Rangel's mother, with whom he had spoken several times a day every day, died at age 90. And now, he said, he often goes around feeling like he has forgotten to do something, then remembers that he would ordinarily have been checking in with her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel declined to speculate on his political future except to say that he does not look forward to retirement. He has no hobbies, he said, can't relax past the third day of any vacation and has been warned by his wife that he is going to wind up friendless in his old age because he tends to neglect personal relationships in favor of work.</p>
        <p>"I feel alone a lot, so that's what has been a source of complaint on my part," Mrs. Rangel said. "But then again, he loves what he does."</p>
        <p>And for now, her husband said, a big part of his job is annoying his fellow lawmakers.</p>
        <p>When asked the standard question about his current role, he laughed and said: "To be a thorn in the side of people who say they're Democrats" but sound increasingly like Republicans. "If you're going down the tube, if you're going to lose, lose fighting."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
