<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plea to Invest in What's Good</title>
    <meta content="16TEACHER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/16/business/16teacher.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1543628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tiaa-Cref</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">College Retirement Equities Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allison, Herbert M Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">College Retirement Equities Fund</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Union Theological Seminary</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFD8113CF935A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plea to Invest in What's Good</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Plea to Invest in Whats Good</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investors raise questions about TIAA-CREF chief executive Herbert M Allison Jr's executive pay at annual meeting of College Retirement Equities Fund, part of TIAA-CREF, and urge greater emphasis on selecting stocks according to social and moral character of corporations; some investors complain about poor performance of their pension and retirement plans during last three years of depressed markets; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the annual meeting yesterday of the largest investment organization catering to university and college faculties and staff, investors raised questions about the chief executive's pay and urged greater emphasis on selecting stocks according to the social and moral character of corporations.</p>
        <p>Some of those attending the meeting in New York of the College Retirement Equities Fund, part of TIAA-CREF, the pension fund giant, complained about the poor performance of their pension and retirement plans during the last three years of depressed markets. But a message echoed repeatedly was that here was a group of investors who would accept a little less profit in exchange for making the world a little better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a meeting of a collegiate investment organization, investors urged greater emphasis on selecting stocks according to the social and moral character of corporations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the annual meeting yesterday of the largest investment organization catering to university and college faculties and staff, investors raised questions about the chief executive's pay and urged greater emphasis on selecting stocks according to the social and moral character of corporations.</p>
        <p>Some of those attending the meeting in New York of the College Retirement Equities Fund, part of TIAA-CREF, the pension fund giant, complained about the poor performance of their pension and retirement plans during the last three years of depressed markets. But a message echoed repeatedly was that here was a group of investors who would accept a little less profit in exchange for making the world a little better.</p>
        <p>''It's not only important how much income you get, but how you get it,'' said Donald W. Shriver, a former president of Union Theological Seminary in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Herbert M. Allison Jr., who joined TIAA-CREF as chief executive last fall after stepping down as president of Merrill Lynch, said, ''We are mindful of the social issues.'' He added that the company tried to balance social concerns with its legal obligation to do its best to provide financial security and earnings for its more than 3.2 million investors.</p>
        <p>But both Mr. Allison and Martin L. Leibowitz, the chief investment officer, indicated that the company's long-held, relatively conservative policy of investing in stock indexes, or baskets of stocks, meant that it would inevitably put money into companies that sell harmful products like cigarettes or that have been accused of abusive labor practices. Investors in an index, by definition, give up the freedom to pick and choose.</p>
        <p>CREF already offers one of the largest funds that invests only in corporations that meet certain social criteria. But of the roughly $300 billion of TIAA-CREF's assets invested on behalf of clients, only about $5 billion is in its ''social choice'' fund.</p>
        <p>The investors, many of them identifying themselves as Ph.D.'s as they rose to speak, seemed pleased at several changes that Mr. Allison announced in the company's corporate governance. For the first time, an independent trustee, not employed by the company, is to become chairman of the board of trustees, he said, and terms of the eight trustees will be reduced to one year from four years, which means that all will stand for election annually. As of today, the chairman will be Martin J. Gruber, a finance professor at the Stern School of Business at New York University.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allison's $8 million in salary and bonuses, which the company disclosed early last month, is nearly 50 percent more than his predecessor was paid. For some investors, the pay increase contrasted painfully with Mr. Allison's earlier announcement that he was laying off 500 employees.</p>
        <p>James W. Keady, the founding director of Educating for Justice, a nonprofit organization that advocates social awareness for high school and college students, calculated that even without the roughly $4 million Mr. Allison was expected to receive in bonuses for long-term performance, he was being paid more than $10,000 a day. ''If you have more money than you need,'' Mr. Keady said, quoting Gandhi, ''you're stealing from somebody.''</p>
        <p>The roughly 150 investors at the meeting, more than double last year's turnout, broke into applause. Mr. Allison then turned the floor over to Ronald L. Thompson, the chief executive of a Midwest manufacturing company and chairman of the committee that conducted the chief executive search. Mr. Thompson said that the company had been in competition with ''many large, aggressive organizations'' to hire Mr. Allison, and that the compensation had to be competitive.</p>
        <p>Throughout the meeting, Mr. Allison stood at a lectern at the front of the auditorium, listening more than talking. He remained calm, and so did most of the investors.</p>
        <p>''We were very pleased with the meeting,'' said Steven Goldstein, a spokesman for TIAA-CREF.</p>
        <p>The investors left in good spirits, too. ''This is the most welcoming situation I've ever walked into,'' Mr. Keady told Mr. Allison and the others as the meeting ended.</p>
        <p>He was speaking from experience at many conferences on corporate responsibility. ''The atmosphere was much more open than I've found at other meetings,'' Mr. Keady said later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
