<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Krone Injured in Spill, but Not Badly</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="736761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GULFSTREAM PARK RACETRACK (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRONE, JULIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D81F3AF937A25752C0A963958260" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Krone Injured in Spill, but Not Badly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julie Krone, who surmounted a star-crossed career to become the most successful female jockey in racing history, suffered a broken finger on the left hand, a possible hairline fracture of the left wrist and a bruised right hand yesterday in a four-horse spill at Gulfstream Park in Florida.</p>
        <p>But the 4-foot-10-inch, 100-pound rider apparently escaped more severe injuries that could have endangered her career. She was reported in fair condition at Hollywood (Fla.) Memorial Hospital, where she was kept overnight for observation after earlier reports from the Gulfstream medical department had suggested more extensive injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Julie Krone, who surmounted a star-crossed career to become the most successful female jockey in racing history, suffered a broken finger on the left hand, a possible hairline fracture of the left wrist and a bruised right hand yesterday in a four-horse spill at Gulfstream Park in Florida.</p>
        <p>But the 4-foot-10-inch, 100-pound rider apparently escaped more severe injuries that could have endangered her career. She was reported in fair condition at Hollywood (Fla.) Memorial Hospital, where she was kept overnight for observation after earlier reports from the Gulfstream medical department had suggested more extensive injuries.</p>
        <p>Her agent, Larry Cooper, reported by telephone at her bedside in the emergency room:</p>
        <p>"It's a lot better than we thought. Her legs are O.K. There's a possible hairline fracture of the left wrist."</p>
        <p>And Krone herself interrupted to say, "I'm O.K., but I can't hold the phone."</p>
        <p>But it was clear that one more painful blow had been dealt to the career of the 31-year-old rider, who has undergone surgery three times in the last year and a half. What was not clear is how much time she would miss now.</p>
        <p>It was only 10 days since she had returned from a two-month absence, during which a metal plate and 13 screws were removed from her left ankle, which was fractured in a spill at Saratoga in August 1993. She underwent nine months of painful rehabilitation at that time before returning last May 25. And five years before that, she suffered a broken left arm in a spill at the Meadowlands in New Jersey and missed nine months of riding.</p>
        <p>But between injuries, she resumed her career and pushed it into new dimensions of success.</p>
        <p>She became the leading jockey at the Meadowlands in 1989 despite the first spill. She became the leading jockey at Belmont Park in the spring of 1992. She became the first woman to win a Triple Crown event when she won the 1993 Belmont Stakes with Colonial Affair. And she was the leading jockey at Gulfstream Park in 1992 and again in 1993, and made a triumphal return there 10 days ago when she won the opening-day stakes aboard Nick Zito's Mr. Greely, who became an instant candidate for the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>But her most recent return to racing took a nasty turn yesterday just after she entered the homestretch of a mile-and-a-half handicap aboard a 6-year-old mare named Saratoga Source, owned by the Augustin Stable and trained by Jonathan Sheppard. She, like all jockeys, was wearing a protective vest that is required in most racing jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>This time, she and Saratoga Source had just moved sidewise from the railing to the outside, where they were running in the back of the field of nine but clear of traffic. But as they came out of the turn for home, Saratoga Source suddenly checked, buckled and went down with a broken right foreleg, throwing Krone into the air and then apparently rolling over her.</p>
        <p>Joe Bravo, riding behind Krone aboard the mare Mrs. Marcos, saw them go down and had little room to escape.</p>
        <p>"I got lucky and jumped her horse and her," he said. "She tucked and rolled up. I pray she's all right."</p>
        <p>Krone tumbled off Saratoga Source with her arm protecting her head as Heberto Castillo Jr. aboard Allen Paulson"s Berga swerved to avoid hitting her, and was thrown to the ground. Next came Dave Penna aboard John Franks's My Mandy, who also was thrown trying to avoid trampling the fallen jockey. And finally, Katy Sweeney aboard the August Moon Farm's Spectacular Image was thrown trying to avoid the melee.</p>
        <p>The three other riders and their horses somehow survived the encounter unhurt. Penna seemed at first to have injured his leg, but after limping off the track, he reported:</p>
        <p>"I'm O.K. My ankle hurts a bit, but it will be all right."</p>
        <p>But Krone and her mount took the full impact. The mare, who had won 6 of her 24 races and run in the money 14 times, was destroyed by injection.</p>
        <p>Krone, who has been matching Mike Smith in riding winners since returning to racing on Jan. 4, reflected on her life and injuries during the opening-day "Salute to Julie Krone."</p>
        <p>"When I started breezing horses," she related, "there was a feeling from some people like walking on eggshells. After a spill like that, people question your heart."</p>
        <p>But she never questioned where her own heart belonged. In an interview last June, she considered the fear of falling from a swiftly moving horse, and said:</p>
        <p>"I think fear gets replaced by competitiveness. You trade fear for the passion of riding. You develop a kind of selective amnesia. I'm not here just in body. I'm here in body and soul."  HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
