<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sermon on Child Neglect and Crime</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="718813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1994 CAMPAIGN: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DA133CF93BA25753C1A962958260" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sermon on Child Neglect and Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M., Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton flew west today to give a speech to police chiefs about crime. But by its end, he had instead spun an angry sermon on the nation's duty to a generation of children whose hearts, he said, were being "turned to stone" by violence and neglect.</p>
        <p>Asked if the President had strayed from his prepared text, the White House press secretary, Dee Dee Myers, replied, "He sure did."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton flew west today to give a speech to police chiefs about crime. But by its end, he had instead spun an angry sermon on the nation's duty to a generation of children whose hearts, he said, were being "turned to stone" by violence and neglect.</p>
        <p>Asked if the President had strayed from his prepared text, the White House press secretary, Dee Dee Myers, replied, "He sure did."</p>
        <p>But hardly anyone seemed displeased by the digression, which showcased Mr. Clinton in the role he plays best: a preacher, speaking with undisguised passion on an issue that engages him.</p>
        <p>After concluding a speech devoted largely to recent Federal anti-crime legislation, Mr. Clinton finally said the words, "I'd like to end today." But he did not. Instead, expanding on a theme he had made early in his speech, that "random violence among young people, people under the age of 18, is going up dramatically in sickening ways," the President spoke without notes for perhaps 10 minutes more.</p>
        <p>"You now have the tools to deal with this problem," he said to the chiefs, referring to the anti-crime bill, "but you've got a whole country out there full of people who have to help. Parents have to recognize that the real war on crime begins at home. If the first responsibility of government is to provide law and order, the first responsibility of parents is to teach right from wrong."</p>
        <p>Recalling recent news accounts of a 5-year-old boy in Chicago who was pushed to his death by two 10-year-olds because he had refused to steal candy for them, the President wondered aloud how young children could become so cold-hearted, and then he answered his own question.</p>
        <p>"Kids are going to look up to somebody, and it's up to the adults in this country to decide who they're going to look up to," he said. The 5-year-old looked up to parents who had taught him the difference between right and wrong, Mr. Clinton said, but "who did the other two kids look up to? Who did they come in contact with who could have taught them right from wrong, and didn't?"</p>
        <p>"What about that little kid who was set on fire?" he asked, referring to a report that two children, ages 10 and 11, had been convicted of dousing a toddler with gasoline and setting him afire. "Who taught those children right from wrong?"</p>
        <p>The President said children learned such horrific behavior from adults.</p>
        <p>"These kids are looking up to somebody," he said. "Who are they going to look up to? How are they going to learn this? We can hire five million police officers. And if we keep losing the battle for what these kids think is right and wrong, we're going to be in a lot of trouble."</p>
        <p>The nation need not worry, Mr. Clinton said, if it rolls up its sleeves and sets about saving its young people.</p>
        <p>"But what we must be worried about is wave upon wave upon wave of these little children, who don't have somebody both good and strong to look up to, who are so vulnerable that their hearts can be turned to stone by the time they're 10 or 11 years old. And when there is a good one -- a 5- or 10-year-old kid in difficult circumstances, blooming like a flower in the desert, knowing that it's wrong to steal candy -- he actually has his life at risk."</p>
        <p>The White House says that the issue of adults' responsibility to children is a favorite of the President, and he has touched on it from time to time, most recently in speeches to black ministers in New Orleans last month and at a black church outside Washington this summer.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clinton has been looking for a chance to emphasize that the issue is not confined to one slice of the population, and today he found it.</p>
        <p>Although crime is the top domestic issue in this campaign season, the White House officially called Mr. Clinton's appearance at the annual meeting of the International Association of Chiefs of Police nonpolitical.  In his prepared remarks, the President talked about the $30 billion anticrime legislation's provisions to help finance the hiring of 100,000 new officers and the construction of 100,000 prison cells in the next six years; about its "three strikes" provision that imprisons some violent offenders for life after a third conviction, and about its bevy of new death-penalty offenses and prevention programs for young people at risk of becoming criminals.</p>
        <p>He also mentioned that "in this election season there are many who are campaigning on a 'Contract with America,' " and they, he said, could "indirectly" derail his efforts against crime by rendering the Government too broke to pay for it. The many are about 300 Republican candidates for Congress whose self-described contract effectively pledges to return the nation to the economic policies of the Reagan Administration, like tax cuts, increased military spending and the balancing of the Federal budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also restated several points he had made in campaign speeches this fall, reminding the police chiefs that he had cut the Federal work force, streamlined Federal purchasing rules, helped bring peace to Haiti, Northern Ireland, the Middle East and Eastern Europe and had persuaded the Russians to point their nuclear missiles somewhere other than the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's extemporaneous remarks were met with applause from the police chiefs, who, as he has noted, support many of the programs in the crime legislation that intended to keep youngsters out of trouble.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also brought the chiefs a present, a new $226 million program that would help large departments start recruiting and hiring new officers before the bulk of the Federal grants under the crime bill begin flowing to them.</p>
        <p>A related initiative announced today would allow small police departments to seek grants for new officers by way of a short form that asks only the most basic information about the department, like its size and the starting salary of an officer.  THE 1994 CAMPAIGN: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
