<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Bush's New Stress on Science, Lobbying by Republican Executives</title>
    <meta content="02research" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/02/business/02research.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1736520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4D91F3FF931A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Bush's New Stress on Science, Lobbying by Republican Executives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Behind Bush's New Stress on Science, Lobbying by Republican Executives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF; Warren E. Leary contributed reporting from Washington for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's proposal to accelerate spending on basic scientific research came after technology industry executives made the case for such a move in a series of meetings with White House officials, executives involved said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In his State of the Union message Tuesday evening, Mr. Bush called for a doubling within 10 years of the federal commitment to ''the most critical basic research programs in the physical sciences.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Industry officials eager to see a greater government commitment to research held a series of discussions with administration officials late last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's proposal to accelerate spending on basic scientific research came after technology industry executives made the case for such a move in a series of meetings with White House officials, executives involved said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In his State of the Union message Tuesday evening, Mr. Bush called for a doubling within 10 years of the federal commitment to ''the most critical basic research programs in the physical sciences.''</p>
        <p>The president's science adviser, John H. Marburger III, said Mr. Bush would request $910 million for the first year of the research initiative, with a commitment to spending $50 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>Computer scientists have expressed alarm that federal support for basic research is being eroded by shifts toward applied research and shorter-term financing. But in his speech, Mr. Bush pointed to work in supercomputing, nanotechnology and alternative energy sources -- subjects that were favorites in the Clinton administration but had not been priorities for the current White House.</p>
        <p>What was different this year, according to a number of Capitol Hill lobbyists and Silicon Valley executives, was support on the issue by Republican corporate executives like Craig R. Barrett, the chairman of Intel, and John Chambers, the chief executive of Cisco Systems.</p>
        <p>Industry officials eager to see a greater government commitment to research held a series of discussions with administration officials late last year that culminated in two meetings in the Old Executive Office Building on Dec. 13.</p>
        <p>There, a group led by Mr. Barrett and Norman R. Augustine, a former Lockheed Martin chief executive, met with Vice President Dick Cheney. A second group headed by Charles M. Vest, the former president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, met with Joshua B. Bolten, director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>The industry and science leaders told the officials that the administration needed to respond to concerns laid out in a report by a National Academy of Sciences panel headed by Mr. Augustine. It warned of a rapid erosion in science, technology and education that threatened American economic competitiveness.</p>
        <p>The report, ''Rising Above the Gathering Storm: Energizing and Employing America for a Brighter Economic Future,'' has been circulating in draft form since October. It was put together by a group of top technology and science leaders, who say the country faces a crisis that the Bush administration is ignoring.</p>
        <p>''The gravitas of that group,'' Dr. Vest said, ''has a lot to do with how we got as far as we did.''</p>
        <p>Still, even after the meetings, the executives and educators were not certain that the administration would respond. So President Bush's proposal on Tuesday night came as something of a surprise.</p>
        <p>Albert H. Teich, director of science policy for the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the nation's largest professional organization for scientists, called Mr. Bush's proposal ''a breath of fresh air.''</p>
        <p>''We haven't seen this interest in basic research from this president before,'' Mr. Teich said. ''We in the science community have talked about the state of basic research for quite a while, with its flat or declining budgets, and we are hopeful about this initiative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett of Intel, according to people who worked with him, had grown particularly frustrated with the lack of progress on the matter.</p>
        <p>In a speech to the National Academy of Engineering in October, in which he described the findings of the Gathering Storm report, Mr. Barrett said: ''If you look at the achievement of the average 12th-grade student in math and science, which is of interest to us here, that 12th-grader in the U.S. ranks in the bottom 10 percent among their international peers. I think it is incumbent upon all of us to look at that report and help raise our voices collectively to our local officials, state officials and national officials.''</p>
        <p>The executives said that the administration had also been induced to respond by a growing bipartisan movement in Congress supporting basic research and education.</p>
        <p>Two bills tackling this matter have recently been introduced. One is the Protect America's Competitive Edge Act, by Senators Pete V. Domenici, Republican of New Mexico; Jeff Bingaman, Democrat of New Mexico; Lamar Alexander, Republican of Tennessee; and Barbara A. Mikulski, Democrat of Maryland. A similar bill was introduced by Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut. Several of the senators met with President Bush in December to encourage him to support the competitiveness legislation.</p>
        <p>''We're excited the president has jump-started this and that it is very bipartisan,'' Dr. Vest said.</p>
        <p>Now the technologists and the educators are waiting to see the specifics of the financing when the president's budget is introduced next week. The report had called for an annual 10 percent increase over the next 10 years, and several executives said they now expected a rise of 7 percent annually, putting annual spending around twice the current level in 10 years.</p>
        <p>Peter A. Freeman, the National Science Foundation's assistant director for computer and information science and engineering, said the president's initiative would make a big difference.</p>
        <p>''We're obviously not at liberty to say what will be in the president's budget next week,'' Mr. Freeman said, ''but we're very hopeful based on the State of the Union address. This is a strong sign that this administration will continue to be very supportive of fundamental science and engineering.''</p>
        <p>Despite there being little detail yet with precise figures, even those who had been publicly critical of the administration were enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''This is really a huge deal and I'm very encouraged,'' said David A. Patterson, a computer scientist at the University of California, Berkeley, who is president of the Association for Computing Machinery, a professional group.</p>
        <p>At the same time, though, Mr. Patterson was concerned that the president's proposal to double funds for basic research drew little applause from the Congressional audience on Tuesday night. ''It just shows the challenge we have,'' he said. ''It wasn't obvious to the legislators.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
