<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE NAMES</title>
    <meta content="23BOLD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/23/nyregion/23bold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1613632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface Names"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, Lily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Paula</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Boldface Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Stephen Sondheim</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Broderick, Matthew</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baldwin, Alec</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Parker, Sarah Jessica</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Garland, Judy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Trump, Ivana</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Toi, Zang</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Marlo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hart, Kitty Carlisle</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sondheim, Stephen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">David, Hal</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rivers, Joan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Garland, Judy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwartz, Paula</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tisch, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Collins, Glenn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DA1039F930A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is There Any Feature More Beloved Than Boldface's 'Your Questions Answered'?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joyce Wadler; With Lily Koppel and Paula Schwartz, and Glenn Collins at Feinstein's</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce; Collins, Glenn; Schwartz, Paula; Koppel, Lily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boldface Names column resonds to reader questions about celebrities, movies and show biz (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is there any feature more beloved than Boldface's ''Your Questions Answered''?</p>
        <p>(Excuse us, an e-mail message from SOCRATES@stilldead.com: Heck no!)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is there any feature more beloved than Boldface's</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is there any feature more beloved than Boldface's ''Your Questions Answered''?</p>
        <p>(Excuse us, an e-mail message from SOCRATES@stilldead.com: Heck no!)</p>
        <p>Yes, when Boldface answers your show biz questions, readers dance, children weep for joy, and publicists clutch their pounding hearts, as they think but one thought: Maybe (SOB!) I will be able to hold on to this miserable job a few more days after all.</p>
        <p>Weren't you going to tell us about the premiere for ''The Last Shot,'' the comedy starring MATTHEW BRODERICK as a down-and-out screenwriter and ALEC BALDWIN as the producer who hustles him? And wasn't the last part of that question redundant?</p>
        <p>Right you are on both counts! By the way, you know what worried us about this event?</p>
        <p>On the red carpet, SARAH JESSICA PARKER, who as usual was much more animated than Mr. Broderick, told us that their son's first words were ''taxi'' and ''shoe.''</p>
        <p>Later, at the after-party, we sat down with Mr. Broderick.</p>
        <p>In ''Last Shot'' his character wonders what it would be like to be interviewed on the red carpet. How does Mr. Broderick find the experience?</p>
        <p>''It's still a little bit exciting,'' Mr. Broderick said, ''but as you do it more, you get defensive. I'm a little bit frightened that somebody has some strange motive -- ''</p>
        <p>(Oh, golly! He reads us!)</p>
        <p>''Paranoia sets in as you age. But it's still very exciting,'' Mr. Broderick said, trying to cultivate some enthusiasm. ''A premiere is always an exciting thing; it sort of always is. I sound like JUDY GARLAND.''</p>
        <p>Well, thank you for your time.</p>
        <p>''I can't think of any jokes,'' Mr. Broderick apologized. ''Thank you.''</p>
        <p>As long as the lady's paying, why not take the vicuña?</p>
        <p>''I cannot be with an older man,'' IVANA TRUMP told us at the ZANG TOI show the other day. ''You know, he dies! I mean in a month he dies because I have too much energy.''</p>
        <p>When a woman talks this way, it means only one thing -- she's flogging a reality show.</p>
        <p>Ms. Trump's, a two-hour special for Fox, is called ''Ivana Young Man.'' It was inspired by Ms. Trump's relationship with ROSSANO RUBICONDI, who is more than 20 years her junior.</p>
        <p>''My show is really empowering the woman,'' said Ms. Trump, who's been holding on to that Czech accent an awfully long time. ''The woman has the upper hand in the relationship. She's the one who is choosing the man. We have about 10 gorgeous hunks from the age of 22 to 28. My girl, she's about 36 to 38 years old and she has everything. She has great job. She has beautiful penthouse in New York. She has a lot of MANOLO BLAHNIKs in her closet, but what she doesn't have, she doesn't have a man -- because a lot of men, older men especially -- are threatened by a woman's success.''</p>
        <p>Let's get back to the younger man, who's modeling that very day in the Zang Toi show.</p>
        <p>''He's a model, dancer and actor,'' Ms. Trump said.</p>
        <p>Ah, yes, the professions one longs to see in a personal ad.</p>
        <p>A few moments later, Mr. Rubicondi sashayed down the runway in white pants and a black see-through shirt.</p>
        <p>Ms. Trump giggled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubicondi grinned.</p>
        <p>After the show, Ms. Trump picked out 18 outfits that retail for $130,000. We're told by a publicist for Zang Toi that Fox paid.</p>
        <p>Was that VALENTINO that MARLO THOMAS was wearing at the ''Parade magazine is going to be stuffed into The New York Post'' party at the Four Seasons on Tuesday ?</p>
        <p>Yes.</p>
        <p>Talk dirty to me, Mario.</p>
        <p>Hey, that's not a question.</p>
        <p>Talk dirty to me, Mario?</p>
        <p>KITTY CARLISLE HART -- who starred with GROUCHO, CHICO and HARPO in ''A Night at the Opera'' and has been squeezing that pineapple dry for the last 69 years -- opened at Feinstein's at the Regency on Tuesday night. Age 94, still glam and game, Ms. Hart wore a beaded chiffon dress.</p>
        <p>She opened her set with STEPHEN SONDHEIM's ''Old Friends.'' In the audience: MARIO and MATILDA CUOMO, HAL DAVID, VERNON JORDAN, JOAN RIVERS and BOB TISCH.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Cuomo said Ms. Hart's was ''basically a magnificent musical sermon on life.'' She was, he added, ''a great ontologist.''</p>
        <p>''The other great ontologist is TEILHARD DE CHARDIN, and they both have the same message,'' he said. ''Squeeze all you can out of life.''</p>
        <p>With Lily Koppel and Paula Schwartz, and Glenn Collins at Feinstein's</p>
        <p>Boldface Names</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
