<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baghdad Journal; Holiday Prayer: Thanks for Survival</title>
    <meta content="Y26IRAQ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1072481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presbyterian Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinzer, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presbyterian Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DE163FF935A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baghdad Journal; Holiday Prayer: Thanks for Survival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinzer, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Dec. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraqi Catholics and Presbyterians attend Christmas services, thanking God that they survived US bombing; say the live and worship freely; their leaders have condemned bombing and economic sanctions that United Nations imposed on Iraq after invasion of Kuwait; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Probably no priest or pastor outside Iraq opened a Christmas sermon today the way the Rev. Gabriel Marie did at the Church of Our Lady of Assumption here.</p>
        <p>''Thanks be to God that we have survived the bombing,'' Father Marie told Catholic parishioners who filled his church to overflowing for two Masses this morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Probably no priest or pastor outside Iraq opened a Christmas sermon today the way the Rev. Gabriel Marie did at the Church of Our Lady of Assumption here.</p>
        <p>''Thanks be to God that we have survived the bombing,'' Father Marie told Catholic parishioners who filled his church to overflowing for two Masses this morning.</p>
        <p>He went on to lament modern technology that allows warriors ''to push a button on a computer and kill people,'' and said it was the duty of all Christians ''to build a new world full of peace.''</p>
        <p>As Iraqi Christians gathered for Christmas services today, the sounds of the American and British bombing raids last week were still echoing in their heads. Their spiritual leaders used the occasion to remind them that, as Father Marie said, ''no bomb is powerful enough to kill the spirit of Christianity.''</p>
        <p>Parishioners at Our Lady of Assumption joined loudly in singing hymns and listened attentively to Bible readings that told the age-old story of the Nativity.</p>
        <p>As they were filing out into the midday sunshine, the choir of about 35 young people, evidently unable to restrain its exuberance, broke spontaneously into an Arabic-language version of ''Jingle Bells.'' When it was finished, members of the choir hugged and kissed each other.</p>
        <p>''Because of Christmas, I am very happy,'' said Anman George, 19, who was among the most enthusiastic singers. ''We believe in Jesus, and that his spirit will prevail to resolve these difficulties. His teachings are the way to peace in this country.''</p>
        <p>Christians who attended Catholic and Protestant services in Baghdad today said in interviews that they live and worship freely here. The Chaldean Catholic community, by far the largest Christian denomination in Iraq, has roots in the earliest days of Christianity and is widely accepted as part of this country's spiritual heritage. Perhaps its most prominent member is Deputy Prime Minister Tariq Aziz.</p>
        <p>''Some Muslims with backward minds don't like Christians,'' said Wasan Wadia, 28, who attended a Catholic Mass with her family today. ''But most of them, especially the more educated, are friendly to us or even envy us because our tradition is very open-minded. They like talking and mixing with us.''</p>
        <p>As recently as 20 years ago, Christians constituted nearly 10 percent of the Iraqi population. But many worked for foreign companies and began emigrating in the 1980's as the companies shut down after the outbreak of war with Iran. Today they make up about 6 percent of the country's 22 million people.</p>
        <p>Iraq's Christian academies, run by Jesuits and Presbyterians from the United States, were shut down when the Government expelled most foreign missionaries in the late 1960's. Many young Christians now attend selected public schools where the history of Christianity is taught alongside that of Islam. Their community is known as highly educated and relatively prosperous.</p>
        <p>Leaders of Christian denominations here have issued statements condemning last week's bombing and the economic sanctions that the United Nations imposed on Iraq after the invasion of Kuwait eight years ago. The bombing and sanctions are intended to force changes in the Iraqi Government and curb what the United States describes as Iraq's threat to neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>As a sign of the friendly ties between the Government and Christian denominations here, the Minister of Religious Affairs, Abdul-Muneim Ahmed Saleh, visited several churches today. At the Baghdad National Presbyterian Church, founded by American missionaries in the 19th century, he told the parish council that Christians ''are not a minority, but an integral part of our nation.''</p>
        <p>The Presbyterian pastor, the Rev. Ikram Ibrahim, referred obliquely to the country's troubles in his sermon today. ''Jesus, we are praying to you,'' he said. ''You are the Prince of Peace, and you are the one who can lift the sanctions from our country.''</p>
        <p>Later the chairman of the parish council, Georges Hormis Sada, said Iraqi Christians shared the widespread anger and puzzlement here over the West's hostility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sada is a retired military officer who fondly recalls his two years of pilot training at Randolph Air Force Base in Texas during the 1960's, when Iraqi-American relations were still friendly.</p>
        <p>''We don't say anything about politics,'' he said, ''but when we see aggression against children, women and old people, we think this should not be. We don't think Jesus would like it. We feel sad that Christian countries are doing this to us. Christians should be able to solve these problems in a different way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sada said the council had decided to cancel traditional church parties. There will be prayer services instead.</p>
        <p>''You can't be very happy when people are being killed, when people are depressed and suffering,'' he said. ''How can you have parties and sing and dance? We feel we should share the sadness of our people and only worship.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
