<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If it embraces everything from CD's to films, it must be the New Synergy.</title>
    <meta content="20TECH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1033160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY: DIGITAL COMMERCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Postlinear Entertainment (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martinez, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDC1030F933A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If it embraces everything from CD's to films, it must be the New Synergy.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Denise Caruso</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caruso, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Technology column on so-called New Synergy: digital, interactive media and its emerging role in pop culture; Ron Martinez of Postlinear Entertainment, a New Synergy pioneer, claims Internet is becoming superset of all other media; some highly acknowledged artists in many genres developed entertainment enviroment that defines New Synergy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SYNERGY -- that notorious buzzword of the 80's routinely invoked to sanctify hundreds of ultimately failed mergers and acquisitions -- is back in heavy rotation.</p>
        <p>This time, it is being called into play by the media industry. With the cable televisionary Geraldine B. Laybourne departing the Walt Disney Company to start her own television and Internet studio, and with the magazine mogul Tina Brown leaving the resolutely mono-media New Yorker to do a print-film-television start-up for Miramax Films, ''synergy'' has become the media world's high-concept du jour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SYNERGY -- that notorious buzzword of the 80's routinely invoked to sanctify hundreds of ultimately failed mergers and acquisitions -- is back in heavy rotation.</p>
        <p>This time, it is being called into play by the media industry. With the cable televisionary Geraldine B. Laybourne departing the Walt Disney Company to start her own television and Internet studio, and with the magazine mogul Tina Brown leaving the resolutely mono-media New Yorker to do a print-film-television start-up for Miramax Films, ''synergy'' has become the media world's high-concept du jour.</p>
        <p>Boiled down, what the term describes is parking old content in a new garage: If you liked the movie, then you'll love the TV show, the book, the magazine piece, the video game, the soundtrack, the action figures, the desk accessories and -- au courant! -- the Web site.</p>
        <p>Nearly 10 years ago, when interactive digital media were first appearing, old-line media executives had another name for this. They called it ''repurposing.''</p>
        <p>But was it ever a bust. The overwhelming number of failures (among the most notable a CD-ROM of Life magazine covers) gave the concept a black eye and made it hard for a budding interactive entertainment industry to find any buyers for its own inventive gestalt.</p>
        <p>That gestalt -- call it the New Synergy -- is all that the digital world has come to represent: interactive and decentralized, and networked right down to its DNA. New Synergists believe that what traditional companies try to pass off as ''synergy'' will continue to fail until they embrace digital, interactive media and its emerging role in pop culture.</p>
        <p>Ron Martinez, the chairman of a San Francisco-based interactive production company, Postlinear Entertainment, is a New Synergy pioneer.</p>
        <p>In what he dubs the ''postlinear world,'' an entertainment property starts simply as a very loose story structure, ''populated only with characters and ambient conflicts.'' From those loose elements, Mr. Martinez said, you can create films, games, comic books, whatever you like.</p>
        <p>But because media companies now want to control all the options for any project -- or ''chew all the flavor out of the gum,'' in Mr. Martinez's words -- the only way for independent producers like Postlinear to succeed is by the flukiest, most unpredictable of phenomena, a crossover hit.</p>
        <p>These are rare indeed; the most successful is Carmen Sandiego, the dashing international thief whose career as a star of television and books was begun in a Broderbund Software video game. More recent is Lara Croft, the vastly endowed cyber-Barbie star of a popular video game, Tomb Raider.</p>
        <p>''Lara's Book,'' by Kip Ward and Douglas Coupland, author of ''Generation X,'' was published this month. Paramount Pictures will release a Tomb Raider movie in 1999, and the ''Lara Croft Come Alive'' CD is already on shelves in France. Croft worship has spawned more than 2,000 Web sites in many languages, including The Croft Times (http://www.cubeit.com/ctimes/).</p>
        <p>Amid today's Internet boom, with industries left and right making the global network the core of their businesses, many New Synergists are amazed that traditional media companies continue to treat the Net as some ancillary distribution medium.</p>
        <p>''How could you not care about the Internet?'' Mr. Martinez said. ''The Internet is becoming a superset of all other media. At some point, interactive media producers are going to have to create flat-out digital labels as the first medium and move them into things like film and TV -- not the other way around.''</p>
        <p>That ''other way around'' problem has plagued other notable New Synergists, as well. Allee Willis and Prudence Fenton, two of the most innovative artists in the interactive world, have just come off a bad trip of more than five years trying to sell their cutting-edge Willisville interactive media project to Hollywood.</p>
        <p>Highly acknowledged artists in many genres -- including songwriting, animation, film and television production -- they developed an entertainment environment that defined New Synergy. Willisville -- a ''cul-de-sac on the information superhighway'' populated with bizarre and charming characters -- was to have its richest presence on the Web.</p>
        <p>Willisville was built for fluid, continuing connections to and from television, shopping, E-mail, creativity tools and more. But in the days when they were shopping the project, the reaction was always the same.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was really excited to see it,'' Ms. Willis said. ''We'd go through elaborate conversations before we took these meetings and say, 'We are in complete opposition to the way entertainment is being developed for the Web. We don't think the idea is to have a TV show and go on line and buy a T-shirt and be able to chat with the actors.' And everyone would say, 'Of course, we believe in a totally radical approach; we're the place for you.' ''</p>
        <p>Then, she added, ''their eyes would cross as soon as we'd start talking about it, and they'd start talking about doing these stupid 'Web-isodes.' ''</p>
        <p>Susan Lammers, chief executive of the children's entertainment company Headbone Interactive, was luckier than Ms. Willis. She will take Headbone's popular ''Elroy'' video game character to the TV screen this fall. But it took years to sell television executives on the idea.</p>
        <p>''The frustrating part of dealing with traditional media companies is they've got a huge business and infrastructure to support, so they limit the creative risk they're willing to take,'' Ms. Lammers said. ''You can cross over from TV to the Web, but the most original material, the brain surgery stuff, is going on in the new media because that's the hard part.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY: DIGITAL COMMERCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
