<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Three Dinners, a Shower of Truffles and Michelin Stars</title>
    <meta content="05PIER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="913360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tavern on the Green (Manhattan)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Les Celebrities (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beard, James, Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franey, Pierre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delouvrier, Christian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DD1430F936A35750C0A961958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Three Dinners, a Shower of Truffles and Michelin Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some of the world's top chefs prepare dinners honoring Pierre Franey, the late chef and writer, at Tavern on the Green, Les Celebrities and James Beard House; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was the food world's equivalent of a tripleheader: three events on Monday night, involving more than 20 top chefs.</p>
        <p>The biggest crowd was at Tavern on the Green, where nearly 500 people celebrated the memory of Pierre Franey, the chef, cookbook author, television personality and food columnist for The New York Times. Mr. Franey died in October at age 75. The menu for the dinner included everything from oysters, sea urchins, foie gras and squab to coulibiac of salmon, a pastry-wrapped tour de force that was one of Mr. Franey's favorites. Several of the courses were showered with fresh black truffles, nearly $7,500 worth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was the food world's equivalent of a tripleheader: three events on Monday night, involving more than 20 top chefs.</p>
        <p>The biggest crowd was at Tavern on the Green, where nearly 500 people celebrated the memory of Pierre Franey, the chef, cookbook author, television personality and food columnist for The New York Times. Mr. Franey died in October at age 75. The menu for the dinner included everything from oysters, sea urchins, foie gras and squab to coulibiac of salmon, a pastry-wrapped tour de force that was one of Mr. Franey's favorites. Several of the courses were showered with fresh black truffles, nearly $7,500 worth.</p>
        <p>There was a galaxy of Michelin stars in the kitchen: Paul Bocuse and Gerard Boyer, with three each, and Alain Ducasse, newly anointed with a total of five (article, page C3).</p>
        <p>At Les Celebrites in the Essex House, Alain Senderens, another Michelin three-star chef, cooked eight courses -- more oysters, truffles, duck and foie gras -- with Christian Delouvrier, the restaurant's chef and his protege. This black-tie dinner for 55 was a reunion for the two chefs, who had worked together at the Maurice restaurant in the Parker Meridien in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>And at the James Beard House in Greenwich Village, 37 guests started with hors d'oeuvres -- truffles, oysters, quail, caviar and snails -- before sitting down to an eight-course dinner featuring more truffles, crayfish, squab and venison. The feast was orchestrated by Charlie Trotter, the Chicago chef, with Charles Palmer of Aureole and Daniel Boulud of Daniel in New York.</p>
        <p>Robert Waxman, a Canadian industrialist, had bid $32,000 for the meal at the James Beard Foundation's benefit auction last fall. To accompany the dinner he brought rare wines from his own cellar, including an imperial (five liters) of 1962 Chateau Petrus, a 1900 Chateau Margaux and an 1811 Chateau d'Yquem.</p>
        <p>Of the three events, only the dinner at the Essex House was open to the public, at $250 a person. And only the memorial party for Mr. Franey threatened to turn into a food fight.</p>
        <p>Originally the Franey event was to have been a reception attended by the chef's friends. But Mr. Franey's widow, Betty, and their children wanted a seated dinner, and more people wanted to attend than they had expected. ''I thought it would be a dinner for 60 or 80 people,'' Mrs. Franey said, ''but it skyrocketed.''</p>
        <p>The dinner, with tickets priced at $200 and up, was a benefit for scholarships at the Culinary Institute of America in Hyde Park, N.Y., and Johnson &amp; Wales University in Providence, R.I. Another memorial, which will be free and open to the public, is being planned for the spring at the French Culinary Institute in SoHo.</p>
        <p>Though Mrs. Franey provided the guest list, she left the delicate task of deciding who would be invited to cook to the three organizers, Sirio Maccioni, the owner of Le Cirque; Charles Pinsky, Mr. Franey's television producer, and Warner LeRoy, the owner of Tavern on the Green.</p>
        <p>The organizers of the party said they had tried to invite chefs to cook who had worked with Mr. Franey. But they wound up not including -- and upsetting -- a number of well-known chefs. ''It was really a shock,'' said Roger Fessaguet, the former chef at La Caravelle in Manhattan, who was not invited to cook. ''I was very close to Pierre.''</p>
        <p>Mr. LeRoy said the organizers had done the best they could. ''There will always be grumbling with something like this,'' he said. ''The point is the chefs are not supposed to be making personal statements. It's a cooperative effort for Pierre.''</p>
        <p>And with some 60 cooks working side by side, camaraderie reigned in Tavern on the Green's giant kitchen. In the dining room, the spirit was festive, with film clips showing Mr. Franey cooking, fishing, eating and playing with his grandchildren. ''We kind of thought he would go on forever,'' Julia Child said.</p>
        <p>It was a busy night, perhaps too busy for chefs like Mr. Boulud and Mr. Palmer, who had committed themselves to more than one event. Mr. Boulud sent Francois Payard, his pastry chef, to represent him at the Franey dinner while he did the cooking at the Beard House. He and Mr. Palmer finally made it to Tavern on the Green around 11:30, just as dessert was being served.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
