<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equity Issues This Week</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="704980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DF1F31F93BA3575BC0A962958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equity Issues This Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>A.S.V. Inc., Marcell, Minn., an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares. Summit Investment Corp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>A.S.V. Inc., Marcell, Minn., an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares. Summit Investment Corp.</p>
        <p>Acmat Corp., New Britain, Conn., 2.375 million class A shares. Advest Inc.</p>
        <p>Adtran Inc., Huntsville, Ala., an initial public offering of two million shares. Dean Witter Reynolds.</p>
        <p>Amerlink Corp., Columbus, Ohio, an initial public offering of one million shares. Legg Mason Wood Walker Inc.</p>
        <p>Applied Imaging Corp., Santa Clara, Calif., an initial public offering of 1.5 million shares. Allen &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Boston Chicken Inc., Naperville, Ill., two million shares. Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Cali Realty Corp., Cranford, N.J., an initial public offering of 9.1 million shares. Prudential Securities.</p>
        <p>Canterbury Park Holdings Corp., Shakopee, Minn., an initial public offering of two million units, each representing one share and one-half warrant. R. J. Steichen&amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Carlyle Golf Inc., Denver, an initial public offering of 1.7 million shares. Neidiger, Tucker, Bruner Inc.</p>
        <p>Carnegie Bancorp, Princeton, N.J., 500,000 shares and 500,000 warrants. Janney Montgomery Scott Inc.</p>
        <p>Cherry Corp., Waukegan, Ill., 2.5 million class A shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Evans Wythcombe Residential Inc., Scottsdale, Ariz., an initial public offering of 9.18 million shares. Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Global Market Info Inc., New York, an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares and 1.2 million warrants. First Hanover Securities Inc.</p>
        <p>HMG Worldwide Corp., New York, 3.045 million shares. Jefferies &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Newvision Technology Inc., Burlington, Mass., an initial public offering of three million units, each representing one share and one warrant. D. Blech &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>PMT Services Inc., Nashville, an initial public offering of 3.1 million shares. Alex. Brown &amp; Sons.</p>
        <p>Photoball USA Inc., San Diego, an initial public offering of one million units, each representing one share and one warrant. Gaines Berland Inc.</p>
        <p>Polish Telephones and Microwave Corp., Plano, Tex., an initial public offering of 500,000 units, each representing two shares and one warrant. Dickinson &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Sirena Apparel Group Inc., South El Monte, Calif., an initial public offering of 1.5 million shares. Wedbush Morgan Securities Inc.</p>
        <p>Steinbrecher Corp., Burlington, Mass., an initial public offering of three million shares. Alex. Brown &amp; Sons.</p>
        <p>Team Rental Group Inc., Daytona Beach, Fla., an initial public offering of 2.65 million shares. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>Trigen Energy Corp.,White Plains, an initial public offering of 3.2 million shares, 2.56 million in the United States and Canada. Lazard Freres.</p>
        <p>Tower Automotive Inc., Minneapolis, an initial public offering of 4.25 million shares. Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>U.S. Diagnostic Labs Inc., Valley Stream, L.I. an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares. Winthrop (Colin) &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Wave Technology International Inc., St. Louis, an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares. Janney, Montgomery &amp; Scott.</p>
        <p>Weirton Steel Corp., Weirton, W. Va., 17 million shares, 14.45 million in the United States and Canada. Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Source: MCM CorporateWatch.</p>
        <p>Ratings: Moody's/Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
