<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell Missing, But Not Forgotten</title>
    <meta content="21KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/21/sports/basketball/21KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1433869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chaney, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0DA1F3DF932A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell Missing, But Not Forgotten</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sprewell Missing, but Not Forgotten</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks hold open practice to spark local interest and incur fan support, but absence of Latrell Sprewell is hot topic among media; Sprewell was barred from attending practices for failing to notify team of wrist injury (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks tried. They held an open practice at St. John's yesterday, handing out tickets for it to community groups. They ran through drills and scrimmaged, players and coaches taking the microphone to explain to the crowd how they worked. Shandon Anderson lifted a child over his head and allowed her to drop a ball through the basket. Allan Houston and Kurt Thomas shot free throws with fans, and the rookie hopeful Jemeil Rich played tag with a handful of youngsters while dribbling around in circles.</p>
        <p>But no festivities, canned music or random acts of kindness would allow the Knicks to forget who was not there and wonder what will come next with Latrell Sprewell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks can't seem to forget about Latrell Sprewell or stop wondering what will come next with their estranged and injured star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Knicks tried. They held an open practice at St. John's yesterday, handing out tickets for it to community groups. They ran through drills and scrimmaged, players and coaches taking the microphone to explain to the crowd how they worked. Shandon Anderson lifted a child over his head and allowed her to drop a ball through the basket. Allan Houston and Kurt Thomas shot free throws with fans, and the rookie hopeful Jemeil Rich played tag with a handful of youngsters while dribbling around in circles.</p>
        <p>But no festivities, canned music or random acts of kindness would allow the Knicks to forget who was not there and wonder what will come next with Latrell Sprewell.</p>
        <p>Sprewell, their estranged and injured star, remained away from the Knicks for another day after slipping into their practice facility on Friday and Saturday. He is sidelined with a broken right hand; on Oct. 7, the Knicks fined him and barred him from practices and games for failing to notify them of the injury.</p>
        <p>Sprewell's next scheduled appearance will be without the Knicks' blessing; he has arranged a news conference on Monday morning in Manhattan while the team practices at its facility in Greenburgh, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Among management and even some players, a mention of Sprewell brings a bristling grumpiness.</p>
        <p>Scott Layden, the Knicks' president and general manager, fielded the first question about Sprewell yesterday and replied: ''With respect, we're not making any more comments about Latrell. We've been consistent about that. So I'm going to leave it at that.''</p>
        <p>Asked if Sprewell could continue his conditioning at the practice site, Layden said: ''Like I said, we're not going to do daily updates. I'll just leave it at that.'' Asked about the news conference, he sighed and said, ''Once again, with respect, I'm not commenting on Latrell's situation.''</p>
        <p>Coach Don Chaney was equally reluctant to talk about Sprewell. Shortly after Sprewell arrived at the practice site on Saturday, Chaney entered, too. But there was little indication that the time in the same building had soothed the animosity between team and player.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to even talk about him at this point,'' Chaney said. ''Later on I guess we'll probably meet, but I'm not even thinking about him now. I'm not talking about him, I should say. I'm thinking about him, but I'm not talking about him.''</p>
        <p>Chaney added, ''If you want to talk about the team, I'll be more than happy -- the present team.''</p>
        <p>Despite their sweep of last week's Western trip to Utah, Sacramento and San Antonio, the Knicks were not fooled that the preseason victories meant much. And the crowd yesterday at St. John's hardly buzzed with excitement. The stands were half empty even with the tickets being given away, and only the dunks at the end of layup drills brought a rise from the fans.</p>
        <p>''We're here playing a game,'' Houston said. ''We have a job to do. We go out and we're a team. We've kind of left Spree and his situation to management to handle it. If we get caught up into it, it would just be a soap opera. So we go into practice every day with a job to do. Whether Spree's there or whoever is there, we have a job to do and we have to do it to the best of our ability.</p>
        <p>''I'm finished commenting on it until he gets back, honestly.''</p>
        <p>Houston acknowledged that ''everybody's curious'' what could come from the news conference today.</p>
        <p>''But it's not something I'm going to ponder all day,'' Houston said. ''When he gets back, we'll address that then. When he talks, we'll hear it. But until then, to me, it's a moot point or issue.''</p>
        <p>Thomas added, ''I think management and Sprewell need to work that out so he could be here.''</p>
        <p>When told of the news conference, Thomas laughed and said, ''I guess we'll find out.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>SCOTT LAYDEN said that the team was hoping to use the $4.5 million medical exception granted by the league because of ANTONIO McDYESS's season-ending knee surgery to work out a trade. ''This injury exception is another opportunity to make the team better,'' Layden said. ''If we can make it better, we will.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
