<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Failings</title>
    <meta content="Thomas.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/04/books/review/Thomas.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hoffman, Alice</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Skylight Confessions (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DC173FF937A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Failings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Family Failings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUISA THOMAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Louisa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Skylight Confessions</p>
        <p>By Alice Hoffman.</p>
        <p>262 pp. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $24.99.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Alice Hoffman’s latest novel, the Moody family has seen its share of extreme, even extraordinary circumstances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Skylight Confessions</p>
        <p>By Alice Hoffman.</p>
        <p>262 pp. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $24.99.</p>
        <p>Certain words and phrases tell you a lot about a book. ''Forevermore'' is one of them -- a ''once upon a time'' for adult readers. In Alice Hoffman's latest novel, ''Skylight Confessions,'' the word appears almost exactly halfway through the story: ''Lost and then found. Discovered in some deep way. He was stuck there, he realized that now; that young girl with red hair sifted through his reality forevermore.'' This rhetorical flourish -- not just ''forever,'' but ''forevermore'' -- is a clear sign that Hoffman is aiming for the kind of lofty truths that can be reached only by going to extremes.</p>
        <p>''Skylight Confessions'' tells the story of the Moody family, which has seen its share of extreme, even extraordinary, circumstances. Seventeen years old and newly orphaned, Arlyn Singer tells herself the first man who walks down her street ''will be my one love'' -- just before John Moody, an architecture student, turns up at her door, looking for directions. But their two nights of intense, passionate intimacy become a marriage of mutual despair and loneliness. Arlyn has two children (the second fathered by the man, she comes to think, she was truly meant to love) and then dies of cancer. Her first-born child, Sam, always slightly different, becomes a drug addict as a teenager. As he slips away, his sister, Blanca, becomes increasingly alienated, turning to fairy tales to find meaning in her broken life. The target of both children's anger, Arlyn's selfish and withdrawn widower, John, is haunted by her ghost.</p>
        <p>It's not entirely clear what Arlyn is doing from beyond the grave. Like Blanca's fairy tales, ghost stories can provide, as Hoffman puts it, ''maps formed of blood and hair and bones.'' But here the haunting seems arbitrary. Despite his realization that Arlyn would ''sift through his reality forevermore,'' John's attachment to her is unconvincing. He's more tortured by frustrations in his architectural practice and his fractious relationship with his son. The children's nanny also sees Arlyn's ghost, but she isn't very spooked either.</p>
        <p>Novelists need tricks, but here the trickery is unconcealed. A surfeit of sentence fragments (''Soot. One of the signs of a specter.'') gives Hoffman's prose a melodramatic quality, and much of her character development is declared instead of illustrated (''Meredith's time in Connecticut had allowed her to learn who she was and what she wanted''). These moments of clumsiness, of the magician showing her hand, draw attention to themselves rather than their occasion.</p>
        <p>Hoffman's focus on the fantastic -- on the sky rather than the ground -- is a shame, because it clouds the novel's enduring lessons: There are many things in life that can't be explained. Some attachments can transcend death. Love isn't the opposite of hate -- and can be more powerful. These are some of the insights Hoffman seems to want to convey, but they're more often obscured than illuminated by her novel's magical effects.</p>
        <p>Louisa Thomas is on the editorial staff of The New Yorker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Louisa Thomas is on the editorial staff of The New Yorker.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
