<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You've Seen the E-Mail, Now Buy the Art</title>
    <meta content="04fink" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/04/arts/design/04fink.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkel, Jori</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Gagosian Gallery</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFD7143FF937A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You've Seen the E-Mail, Now Buy the Art</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">You’ve Seen the E-Mail, Now Buy the Art</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JORI FINKEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkel, Jori</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More and more art shows are selling out before opening as collectors buy works they have seen only as digital images; since condition of work can be a problem, especially for older works, most galleries have generous return policy; advantages to dealers and buyers explored; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR his fall show the artist Tom Friedman planted two dozen characteristically demented sculptures throughout the Gagosian Gallery in Beverly Hills. He set a giant Excedrin box, made from dozens of cut-up Excedrin boxes, on the floor near the entrance. He placed three identically crumpled wads of paper on a shelf. And he affixed to the ceiling a bunch of colorful papier-mâché balloons, which magically appeared to float despite their weight. Their strings were held together not by a hand but by a pair of men's briefs suspended in midair.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Friedman's first outing with Gagosian after years of showing at the much humbler Feature Gallery in New York, and the exhibition sold out, with works priced up to $500,000. But most of the buyers did not see the installation. They did not personally see the pieces at all. Gagosian sold out the show before it opened, in large part through a flurry of e-mail messages and digital images.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s another sign of the acceleration of the contemporary art market: New works, even in the six-figure range, are sold by digital image alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR his fall show the artist Tom Friedman planted two dozen characteristically demented sculptures throughout the Gagosian Gallery in Beverly Hills. He set a giant Excedrin box, made from dozens of cut-up Excedrin boxes, on the floor near the entrance. He placed three identically crumpled wads of paper on a shelf. And he affixed to the ceiling a bunch of colorful papier-mâché balloons, which magically appeared to float despite their weight. Their strings were held together not by a hand but by a pair of men's briefs suspended in midair.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Friedman's first outing with Gagosian after years of showing at the much humbler Feature Gallery in New York, and the exhibition sold out, with works priced up to $500,000. But most of the buyers did not see the installation. They did not personally see the pieces at all. Gagosian sold out the show before it opened, in large part through a flurry of e-mail messages and digital images.</p>
        <p>When asked at the opening if the show had really sold out in three days, Deborah McLeod, the gallery's director, replied, ''More like three minutes.''</p>
        <p>It's another sign of the acceleration of the contemporary art market: New works, even in the six-figure range, are selling by digital image alone. For the Friedman show, Gagosian set up a private section on its Web site, accessible only by a password sent via e-mail message to select collectors. More typically, gallery directors send off e-mail messages with JPEGs -- a format for digitally storing and transmitting images -- to potential clients.</p>
        <p>As with so many aspects of the art world, industrywide figures do not exist. But anecdotes abound. Howard Read of Cheim &amp; Read in Manhattan said the gallery sold by JPEG alone ''about a third'' of its current show: paintings of Mexican-American laborers by the California artist John Sonsini, with prices from $25,000 to $65,000.</p>
        <p>The Chicago dealer Kavi Gupta has presold -- in large part through JPEGs -- his current exhibition of paintings by Claire Sherman, a 2005 graduate of the School of the Art Institute of Chicago. ''We debuted a painting at Basel last year, and Marty Margulies bought it,'' he said, referring to a major Miami collector. ''Since then we've been selling her work based on digital images.'' The show opened this weekend, but it has been sold out since December, with prices up to $15,000.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, Timothy Blum of Blum &amp; Poe said he sold a ''handful'' of works by the conceptual artist Dave Muller, sight unseen, from his January show, at prices up to $100,000. ''This happens routinely now,'' he said. ''I've also sold paintings by Mark Grotjahn, for over $200,000, to buyers who never saw them in person.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blum was quick to add that these buyers already knew Mr. Grotjahn's work, an off-kilter updating of abstract painting. Other gallerists made the same point. This is not the case of an Internet surfer discovering a picture on an e-commerce site and tossing it in a shopping cart, but more a sign of how efficient the high-end contemporary art market has become.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if this is the beginning of something wonderful, or the end of something wonderful,'' said Amy Cappellazzo, co-head of postwar and contemporary art at Christie's. ''But we've seen the use of JPEGs increase dramatically, exponentially, in the last few years. It's all about the speed of the market. Without the use of digital images, this market would come to a grinding halt.''</p>
        <p>Lisa Schiff, a New York art consultant, agreed, saying that ''99 percent'' of her sales now involve a JPEG at one stage or another. ''It's changed the way we all do business,'' she said. ''People have begun using JPEG as a verb: JPEG me this work.'' (On the resale market, where many art consultants operate, JPEGs can be shopped so widely that a seller can find himself in the puzzling position of being offered his own work.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gupta said about half of his sales take place without the presence of the buyer. ''Being in Chicago, without the walk-in traffic of a gallery in New York or even L.A., I can't imagine working without digital images,'' he said. ''We have a ton of European collectors, and we reach them through art fairs and digital images, a combined effort.''</p>
        <p>The advantages for galleries are abundant: Digital images are easier to produce than the catalog and magazine reproductions that have long helped to get the word -- or image -- out. And they are cheaper than transparencies, which now tend to serve more archival purposes.</p>
        <p>But what do collectors have to gain from buying this way, without the pleasure of interacting with the work itself or the security of hands-on inspection? Don't buyers want to see the art in person?</p>
        <p>Don Rubell of Miami says he does. ''I hate to be judgmental,'' he said. ''But I think a lot of people buying this way are buying the name of an artist, not a particular work.'' He and his wife, Mera, are known for going to great lengths to see a new work, ''sometimes spending nearly as much on plane tickets as the piece is worth.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Blum conceded, ''Yes, there are speculators. But what I see is that some of the best collectors in the world also operate by digital images, coupled with rampantly seeing art.''</p>
        <p>Such collectors say that hopping on a plane is not always possible, especially when there's a real, or manufactured, sense of urgency. ''Maybe something in Europe comes our way, and we can't make it there or send our curator,'' said Cindy Rachofsky of Dallas, who with her husband, Howard, was an early supporter of Mr. Friedman. ''Or maybe it's something that's been on our wish list for a long time, where a decision needs to be made quickly.''</p>
        <p>The Rachofskys purchase via digital image ''maybe 10 percent of the time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Kent Logan, a collector in Vail, Colo., said, ''Buying this way is necessary to stay competitive.'' He puts his digital purchases as high as 50 percent. ''I haven't been to an art fair in three years where I haven't already seen images in advance and known what I was going to buy.'' Has he been pressured to buy this way, or enticed with a lower, friends-and-family price? ''Sure, that happens,'' he said. ''But that's the reality of the marketplace. If you can't stand the heat, get out of the kitchen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Logan recently paid more than $100,000 for a landscape painting by Li Songsong based on a digital image from the Urs Meile Gallery in Beijing. He has purchased work for ''close to a million dollars, sight unseen,'' he said, but only under certain conditions. ''I have to know the artist's work, and I have to trust the dealer.''</p>
        <p>A NEW YORK collector, Sheri Levine, agreed: ''Generally speaking I will only do this with an artist whose work I already own, so I have a very good sense of what the work will look like in person.'' She gave two recent purchases as examples: a digital print by Chiho Aoshima from Blum &amp; Poe, and a Loretta Lux photograph from the New York gallerist Yossi Milo, each priced around $10,000.</p>
        <p>''Both pictures turned out to be exactly what I expected, and I was thrilled,'' Ms. Levine said. ''But keep in mind that it's easier to buy a photograph than a painting this way. A JPEG often distorts a painting.''</p>
        <p>And that hints at the potential danger of buying art this way: The image representing the work of art could be, however subtly, misrepresenting it. First there are the limitations of the JPEG itself. As a compressed file format, it is small enough to easily send via e-mail, but the compression causes some loss of information.</p>
        <p>There are also the inaccuracies created whenever a three-dimensional work is captured in two dimensions. The texture of a painting especially, experts warn, is bound to get lost in translation. As Mr. Gupta put it: ''A JPEG will give you a general picture but usually will not deliver the surface detail at all.'' With Claire Sherman's work, for example, ''you're not going to see the energy of the brushwork,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another challenge is color, which can vary depending on computer and monitor settings.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schiff discovered this when buying a canvas by the German painter Stefan Kürten for a client. ''We knew that the artist does kind of metallic surfaces, very detailed and ornate, so there would be nuances you can't get from a JPEG,'' she said. ''But we never expected the work to be quite so pink in person.'' She said it was a nice surprise -- ''the painting was amazing in person'' -- but it served as a warning to her that ''you can't be so cavalier about these things.''</p>
        <p>A FINAL caveat relates to condition, which is more of a problem for older pieces that have repeatedly changed hands. ''Condition is the No. 1 issue for secondary market material,'' said Ms. McLeod of Gagosian. She recalled closing a $2.2 million sale of a ''Diamond Dust Shoe'' painting by Andy Warhol by letting clients who couldn't personally see the work choose their own conservators to provide a condition report.</p>
        <p>Condition anxiety, however, is hardly unique to digital images. Collectors often complain of reproductions in auction catalogs masking an artwork's wear and tear. Many people pointed out that buying by JPEG is a lot like absentee bidding at auction.</p>
        <p>With at least one crucial difference: Should clients be disappointed with their purchase of new work, most galleries will let them return it. It's one way that major galleries take the uncertainty out of buying art by JPEG, much as other retailers take the risk out of buying clothes or electronics online.</p>
        <p>So did anyone return work by Tom Friedman to Gagosian? Ms. McLeod said no. But, she added, she wouldn't mind if they did. ''In this business supply is always the problem, not demand,'' she said. ''I'd actually be delighted to have something back. If I got it back, I could sell it again.''</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
