<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlight: N.B.A.; All-Star Also-Rans Hoping for a Reprieve</title>
    <meta content="04hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All-Star Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2D9123FF937A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlight: N.B.A.; All-Star Also-Rans Hoping for a Reprieve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Contentious NBA All-Star Game picks are result of tumultuous season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it was only appropriate given the paradoxical nature of Las Vegas -- Sin City or family playground? -- that N.B.A. coaches sent mixed messages in choosing reserve players for the All-Star Game there.</p>
        <p>The coaches' snubs as well as the subs seemed to pose questions, if not a dilemma, central to the league. Do individual statistics ultimately matter more than team success? Do punches matter more than trade demands, or can both transgressions be forgiven in the grand scheme of celebrity drawing power and image control in the N.B.A.?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it was only appropriate given the paradoxical nature of Las Vegas -- Sin City or family playground? -- that N.B.A. coaches sent mixed messages in choosing reserve players for the All-Star Game there.</p>
        <p>The coaches' snubs as well as the subs seemed to pose questions, if not a dilemma, central to the league. Do individual statistics ultimately matter more than team success? Do punches matter more than trade demands, or can both transgressions be forgiven in the grand scheme of celebrity drawing power and image control in the N.B.A.?</p>
        <p>Carmelo Anthony, the fourth-year Denver Nuggets forward, was the league's leading scorer before his December hit-and-run at Madison Square Garden cost him a 15-game suspension and, in turn, cost him respect from the Western Conference coaches.</p>
        <p>Dallas forward Josh Howard has been posting career numbers as Dirk Nowitzki's wingman, propelling the Mavericks to the best record in the N.B.A. through Friday. He was not named to the All-Star team with Nowitzki. Yet.</p>
        <p>Commissioner David Stern can easily substitute Anthony and Howard for two injured Western Conference All-Stars, Houston's Yao Ming and Utah's Carlos Boozer. Provided Boozer does not make a miraculous recovery, Stern will most likely reward both of them with All-Star berths for the first time.</p>
        <p>But putting Anthony on the team means Stern will have to defy the very image of basketball without brawls he was trying to protect and the one his coaches upheld.</p>
        <p>If he keeps the repentant Anthony off the roster after he served his time, Stern will look vindictive.</p>
        <p>Anthony was contrite immediately after receiving the harshest penalty of the 10 Knicks and Nuggets players involved in the fight. He chose not to appeal, met with Stern in New York and apologized to season-ticket holders in Denver, which will probably help his cause.</p>
        <p>Stern is not rushing to make this decision. He will most likely wait a week, until the Jazz get the results back from Boozer's magnetic resonance imaging exam showing how the hairline fracture in left leg -- originally expected to keep him out until March -- is healing.</p>
        <p>For now, Suns Coach Mike D'Antoni does not know who will be on his Western Conference All-Star roster for the game Feb. 18. Anthony missed 36 voting days. The Nuggets were 13-9 as he averaged a league-high 31.6 points a game and were 7-8 without him. They are 3-4 since his return.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little surprised,'' D'Antoni said Friday in a telephone interview, ''but I can also understand why coaches didn't put him in. He didn't play 15 games because of the suspension, and I think they went with that theme.''</p>
        <p>D'Antoni sidestepped the question of whether the brawl was the deciding factor. ''It's hard to comment, but obviously there was a hang-up there that coaches had a hard time voting for him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Clippers Coach Mike Dunleavy would not say whether he had voted for Anthony. In an interview Friday, he simply said: ''I voted on his play. The fight was not a good thing, but I didn't penalize him for the fight.''</p>
        <p>Still, if the Knicks-Nuggets brawl was a painful reminder of the infamous Pacers-Pistons brawl in 2004, Anthony helped perpetuate that problem.</p>
        <p>''I can't speak for the coaches,'' Chicago Bulls General Manager John Paxson said. ''But I know we're all concerned about the image of the league.''</p>
        <p>The All-Star Game itself is a grand exhibition, a stage to promote the stars and story lines of the first half of the season. The coaches celebrated the Suns' dazzling success by voting for guard Steve Nash and forwards Shawn Marion and Amare Stoudemire. The Suns have more All-Stars than any other team this season. A year ago, the Detroit Pistons had four starters, a tribute to their league-best 43-9 record.</p>
        <p>But not all good numbers are noticed. Somehow, the Mavericks have the best record in the N.B.A. and Nowitzki is their only representative. San Antonio, several games behind Dallas and a step slow this season, had point guard Tony Parker named Thursday as a reserve. He will join his teammate Tim Duncan, who was chosen as a starter in fan balloting.</p>
        <p>Jason Kidd and Vince Carter of the underachieving Nets each received his eighth All-Star berth. Chicago, whose record is tied for third best in the East, had no players selected. Not Ben Gordon, Luol Deng or even center Ben Wallace, the Bulls' premier off-season acquisition, who made the past four All-Star teams with Detroit.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed,'' Paxson said. ''But we have not gotten to a point where we have earned the respect of other teams. Our guys are still young. Hopefully this will show them that we need to win as a team to get recognized as individuals.''</p>
        <p>The Clippers, charmed upstarts last season, also have no All-Stars.</p>
        <p>''It's about wins, and that's the way it should be,'' Clippers forward Elton Brand, a 2006 All-Star, said Friday in a telephone interview. His slow start has mirrored that of his team, which has been hurt by injuries.</p>
        <p>Brand is holding slim hope that he will be named as an injury replacement. But he sees Anthony, Howard and Utah's Mehmet Okur as deserving.</p>
        <p>Fans saw Allen Iverson as deserving an All-Star start seven seasons in a row when he played for Philadelphia in the East. He did not have enough fan support to compete in the West after he was traded to Denver. Coaches, knowing how hard he plays and perhaps siding with the comforts of celebrity, rewarded Iverson despite the fact he asked for a midseason trade from Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Who would have thought in November that Iverson, not Anthony, would be Denver's All-Star?</p>
        <p>''Self-inflicted wounds cannot be mitigating factors,'' the ESPN analyst Bill Walton said Friday, referring to Anthony's suspension. ''It's not like he was out with an injury.''</p>
        <p>Howard's snub was much more of a surprise to Walton.</p>
        <p>''They always preach team, they always preach defense, they always preach stats don't matter,'' Walton added. ''You have a near-perfect player in Josh Howard on a near-perfect team and you only get one All-Star off of that? I just don't understand.''</p>
        <p>Washington's Eddie Jordan will coach the Eastern All-Stars, a tribute to his Wizards being the conference's breakthrough team, with the breakthrough player, Gilbert Arenas, starting at guard. His teammate Caron Butler joins Orlando's Dwight Howard as a first-time All-Star.</p>
        <p>Tayshaun Prince, the only Detroit starter not to be named an All-Star last year, conceded Butler's selection over his own.</p>
        <p>''Washington right now is the best team in the East the way they're playing, and the reason is Caron,'' Prince said Wednesday in New Jersey, adding that Arenas is a given while Butler is an X-factor.</p>
        <p>There were few surprises among those left off the East team, if only because injuries, poor team records or both depleted the pool. That was the case with Milwaukee's Michael Redd and Boston's Paul Pierce. Joe Johnson is learning that being ''the man'' in Atlanta has far less currency than the maximum contract he signed.</p>
        <p>In the West, Ray Allen, a six-time All-Star averaging 26.6 points, was passed over this year, and his Seattle SuperSonics are also an afterthought.</p>
        <p>Lost games and missed games did not deny everyone. Miami center Shaquille O'Neal has played only eight games this season, but his towering, charismatic personality is to the N.B.A. what Wayne Newton is to Las Vegas. (Newton will croon during the All-Star introductions.)</p>
        <p>The fans voted O'Neal into his 14th All-Star Game -- the most among active players -- even though he missed 35 games recovering from knee surgery and Miami's record was below .500.</p>
        <p>O'Neal's selection represents more of a lifetime achievement award. Will it be his last All-Star Game? As the question lingers, Anthony only hopes he can make his first appearance and earn a second chance from Stern.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
