<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Tinkering with success, Visa tries to create new, invigorating installments of a longtime campaign.</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT CARDS AND ACCOUNTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">VISA USA INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BBDO NEW YORK</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN EXPRESS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SODERSTROM, JANET L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DB1130F936A15752C0A962958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Tinkering with success, Visa tries to create new, invigorating installments of a longtime campaign.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE 1985, Visa has been proclaiming, through advertising by BBDO New York, that "It's everywhere you want to be."</p>
        <p>But where does Visa want to be?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE 1985, Visa has been proclaiming, through advertising by BBDO New York, that "It's everywhere you want to be."</p>
        <p>But where does Visa want to be?</p>
        <p>That question has been reverberating for some time among executives in the credit card and advertising industries. All agree that Visa's twin strategies of emphasizing its omnipresence and denigrating American Express, its more upscale rival, have produced one of the most consistently effective, and effectively consistent, campaigns of the last decade.</p>
        <p>"It has served to break the parity situation we faced in 1985, when Visa and Mastercard were perceived to be interchangeable," said Janet L. Soderstrom, senior vice president of advertising and marketing services at Visa U.S.A. in San Mateo, Calif. "It has worked so well because it has created real points of difference."</p>
        <p>Ms. Soderstrom cited the results of tracking studies among consumers that show Visa besting Mastercard and American Express in categories including acceptance, value and best overall card. And Visa is the undisputed leader in charge volume, with an estimated 45 percent of the $421.3 billion general-purpose card market.</p>
        <p>But an intensified competition among credit card marketers and a drastic shift in consumer attitudes from prizing status to seeking value has called into question the campaign's continuing efficacy.</p>
        <p>It is a problem many marketers confront as they seek to balance the benefits derived from the constancy of a long-running campaign with the novelty and freshness offered by frequent changes.</p>
        <p>No one seems more aware of that than Carl F. Pascarella, who in August replaced H. Robert Heller as president and chief executive at Visa U.S.A. after 11 years with the parent Visa International in Asia.</p>
        <p>"Nothing is sacrosanct in my book," he said. "I don't believe there are any times in any business when you should rest on your laurels and say, 'Boy, aren't things great?' "</p>
        <p>"By the same token," he added, "I won't change for change's sake." For instance, he said he sees "nothing on the horizon that would change our relationship with BBDO."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pascarella listed three immediate goals: to put Visa's disparate promotional campaigns "under an umbrella, bundling them to leverage our strengths"; to "re-look at what we're doing and how we're doing it, to refresh the program," and "just taking a blank wall and throwing things up, an exercise to get the creative juices rolling, if nothing more than to have something on the shelf."</p>
        <p>Already, differences are noticeable.</p>
        <p>"We're following societal trends to show more everyday, common-type situations in the campaign," Rich Kronengold, senior vice president and account director on Visa at BBDO New York, said. Settings for the latest commercials include the chef Wolfgang Puck's Granita restaurant in Malibu, Calif., more casual than his chic Spago establishment; the Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus, to be featured in a promotion beginning in May, and Threadgill's, "a hamburger joint" in Austin, Tex.</p>
        <p>"Our 1986 commercial, set in a French chateau, obviously would not be proposed to the client in 1994," Mr. Kronengold added.</p>
        <p>And for the first time, the agency has produced two versions of a Visa television commercial, one for the mainstream market and one for younger, particularly college age, credit card users. The latter version of the spot, which highlights the Telluride ski resort in Colorado, is faster paced and funkier, and appears during programs like "Melrose Place."</p>
        <p>Another obvious difference is that Visa and BBDO New York are no longer benefiting from the uncertainties caused by frequent shifts in campaigns and agencies at American Express and Mastercard, which yesterday announced the resignation of its chief executive.</p>
        <p>"There's no question we sat here glibly watching other credit cards changing," Philip B. Dusenberry, chairman and chief executive at BBDO New York, said. "At Mastercard, it was like the campaign du jour."</p>
        <p>"Finally, they seem to have settled into what seems like campaigns that work for them," he added, referring to new ads for Mastercard by Ammirati &amp; Puris and new ads for American Express by Ogilvy &amp; Mather New York.</p>
        <p>"In the end, consumers will tell us which one works for them," he continued. "So far, from what we see, Visa still comes out on top."</p>
        <p>To assure that outcome, Visa is increasing its 1994 ad budget to more than $100 million, from $80 million in 1993. It will run three commercials during NBC's telecast of Super Bowl XXVIII on Sunday and will return as a major Olympic sponsor during CBS's coverage of the 1994 Winter Olympics, which begins on Feb. 12.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
