<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bethlehem Journal; John Updike Returns to His Source</title>
    <meta content="Y06LEH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1059943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Books and Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bethlehem (Pa)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">John Updike</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronner, Ethan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Updike, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D8173EF935A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bethlehem Journal; John Updike Returns to His Source</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ETHAN BRONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bronner, Ethan</byline>
      <dateline>BETHLEHEM, Pa., Nov. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Author John Updike, who was born and raised in eastern Pennyslvania, returns to Bethlehem for two-day visit to speak to Lehigh University class studying his work; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John  Updike has lived  in Massachusetts  so long  more than four decades -- that it is hard to remember he was born and raised in eastern Pennsylvania. This area is, he says, still his emotional and literary home, the setting of his four ''Rabbit'' books and the yeasty source of much of his keen observation of the American middle class.</p>
        <p>As he once wrote of Shillington, the farm town 30 miles southwest of here where he spent his early years, ''I love Shillington not as one loves Capri or New York, because they are special, but as one loves one's own body and consciousness, because they are synonymous with being.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John  Updike has lived  in Massachusetts  so long  more than four decades -- that it is hard to remember he was born and raised in eastern Pennsylvania. This area is, he says, still his emotional and literary home, the setting of his four ''Rabbit'' books and the yeasty source of much of his keen observation of the American middle class.</p>
        <p>As he once wrote of Shillington, the farm town 30 miles southwest of here where he spent his early years, ''I love Shillington not as one loves Capri or New York, because they are special, but as one loves one's own body and consciousness, because they are synonymous with being.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Updike was back for a two-day visit this week to read from his work at Lehigh University here and speak to a class studying his work. It was a visit filled with the poignancy and irony that permeate his writing, at once a victory lap for an esteemed man of letters and an encounter with a generation that does not tend to view high-minded writers as cultural heroes.</p>
        <p>He said being back in the area had a slightly unreal quality, as if time had been stretched. He took note of the solid church spires rising from Bethlehem's russet countryside, the diner where his sandwich cost $1.75 and the rusting hulks of steel that evoke a time memorialized in his early novels.</p>
        <p>Bethlehem, whose steel works used to employ 30,000, is trying to turn its old steel mills into a museum of industrial history in cooperation with the Smithsonian Institution. The changing face of American industry is not a foreign theme to Mr. Updike, whose character Harry (Rabbit) Angstrom got rich when American car buyers turned suddenly to Toyotas in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Dressed in gray flannel slacks, penny loafers, tweed jacket and striped tie, Mr. Updike, 66, sensed there was something quaint, if not strange, about his presence at the seminar, attended by a dozen students. ''I must seem like a dinosaur,'' he said by way of self-mocking introduction. ''You study it but you don't expect it to show up in your classroom.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Updike's appearance was especially charged because the title of the class is, ''Should John Updike Be Awarded the Nobel Prize?'' and the professor, Jack De Bellis, is among the most knowledgeable and obsessed of Mr. Updike's devoted readers (he himself calls it ''my gentle madness''). ''Jack knows more about me than I know about myself,'' Mr. Updike said with a twinkle, deferring to Professor De Bellis about a character in an early Updike story.</p>
        <p>Professor De Bellis, 63, has published an Updike bibliography -- no mean feat given the prodigious Updike output of stories, novels, poems, essays and other writing -- and is completing an 800-page Updike encyclopedia with plot summaries, descriptions of characters and personal and historical background.</p>
        <p>Mr. De Bellis also has one of the world's most extensive collections of Updikeana, including scores of signed books and a 1968 cover of Time magazine with a painting of a sandy-haired, turtle-neck-clad Updike, who had just published the best-selling and then-shocking novel ''Couples.''</p>
        <p>So there the two sat in class, the author and his chronicler, a Philadelphia native who has spent the last 30 years here, with their matching mops of unruly hair, finely pointed noses and light Pennsylvania accents, as Mr. Updike defended himself against accusations from students that the women in his fiction lacked substance and that he wrote of incest to shock and sell books.</p>
        <p>''No, I don't think women are dumb,'' Mr. Updike said, his face mottling pink over traces of psoriasis, a condition he painstakingly described in the essay, ''At War With My Skin.''</p>
        <p>On incest, he replied: ''All love comes from the family. Yet it is an effort to break out of the familiar, to become intimate with another, to reconstruct the cuddling, the tickling and the comfort. It is part of being human. Eros is everywhere. It is what binds.''</p>
        <p>On his hopes and chances for a Nobel Prize, Mr. Updike, who has won nearly every major American literary award, including the Pulitzer, tried to be dismissive without being disrespectful.</p>
        <p>''Some Greek leader was once asked why there was no statue to him in the town square,'' he told the students. ''He replied that he would rather people ask why there isn't one than why there is one.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Updike has clearly given the question some thought. His latest book, ''Bech at Bay,'' his third about Henry Bech, a Jewish-American writer who serves as a satirical alter ego, ends with Bech collecting the prize in Stockholm as the surprise winner from a split Nobel committee. ''I thought that by giving the prize to Bech I could end the speculation,'' he offered. ''It seems to me that the Nobel committee is not in search of aging, white Western men these days.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, Mr. Updike gave what he called ''an all-Pennsylvania reading'' of poems and stories to a packed audience of several hundred. He selected a story from his previous Bech book, ''Bech Is Back.''</p>
        <p>In it, Bech finds himself in Pennsylvania being paraded around a small university. While in the area, Bech visits Marvin Federbusch, a collector of Bech books whose voice and manner seem an odd mirror of the fictitious author's.</p>
        <p>And so the inside laughter rang out as a number of those present recognized their colleague, Professor De Bellis, as Mr. Updike's own Federbusch. The line was long for those seeking a signature. Most of the seekers were middle aged.</p>
        <p>For the students, the visit was not like, as Bech had described in that story, ''a god descending -- whimsical as Zeus, radiant as Apollo.'' It was interesting, they said, to see the man in the flesh. But they were not in awe. ''I think what writing was in his era, television and MTV are to ours,'' said Dennis Zehner, a senior from Allentown. ''Today, writing is like everything else, a commodity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
