<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Gold Glover Wins a Game With His Bat</title>
    <meta content="13METS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/13/sports/13METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cincinnati</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Anaheim</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Norfolk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cincinnati</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Valentine, Bobby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zeile, Todd</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Mark</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shinjo, Tsuyoshi</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jordan, Brian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lopez, Javy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rusch, Glendon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DA1231F930A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Gold Glover Wins a Game With His Bat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Atlanta Braves, 1-0, in extra innings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Rey Ordóñez was scheduled to lead off the ninth inning on Wednesday, Mets Manager Bobby Valentine called for a pinch-hitter. It was a cold night, Valentine reasoned, and he had pinch-hitters who had spent the game in the clubhouse, keeping warm. Valentine regretted the move, and not just because it did not work. ''I kicked myself a little,'' Valentine said last night. ''He's swinging the bat too well.''</p>
        <p>Todd Zeile approached Ordóñez after the Mets lost that night and patted him on the shoulder for encouragement. ''We're going to need you all year,'' Zeile said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Rey Ordóñez was scheduled to lead off the ninth inning on Wednesday, Mets Manager Bobby Valentine called for a pinch-hitter. It was a cold night, Valentine reasoned, and he had pinch-hitters who had spent the game in the clubhouse, keeping warm. Valentine regretted the move, and not just because it did not work. ''I kicked myself a little,'' Valentine said last night. ''He's swinging the bat too well.''</p>
        <p>Todd Zeile approached Ordóñez after the Mets lost that night and patted him on the shoulder for encouragement. ''We're going to need you all year,'' Zeile said.</p>
        <p>Last night, Ordóñez's turn came up again in the Mets' last time at-bat, and the team did not necessarily need him. Valentine had Lenny Harris and Mark Johnson on his bench, and Ordóñez was not sure he would be allowed to hit.</p>
        <p>But when Valentine told the shortstop, ''You're the guy,'' Ordóñez said he exhaled deeply. With Zeile on second and one out in the 10th inning, Ordóñez drove Kerry Ligtenberg's first pitch into the left field corner for a game-winning single, lifting the Mets to a 1-0 victory.</p>
        <p>If Ordóñez ever had another game-winning hit, he said he could not remember it.</p>
        <p>''I think it was nearly as important to send him up as it was to watch him get the hit, just for confidence,'' said Zeile, who had reached base on a leadoff walk. ''Guys in here know we're counting on Rey all year long to do more than just make phenomenal plays in the field.''</p>
        <p>The victory gave the Mets their second series victory against the Braves this season. Last week, the Mets took two out of three in Atlanta. This week, they did it again at home.</p>
        <p>The games were packed with likely and surprising heroes, exquisite pitching and showy offense, questionable base-running decisions and flawlessly executed fundamentals. And the series still has 13 regular-season games left.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what it is,'' said Mets second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo. ''But this is a tremendous series with Atlanta. Every time, we beat them by one run or they beat us by one run. That's the way fans and the people like to see it.''</p>
        <p>Alfonzo, who batted fifth last night after not hitting there at all last year, was 0 for 4 but said he is staying positive. The surprising slugger -- at least for now -- is Ordóñez, who is batting .276. Ordóñez batted .188 last year in a season that ended on Memorial Day when he broke his left forearm.</p>
        <p>''I'm standing a little bit up, doing work with my hands,'' Ordóñez said. ''See the ball and hit it.''</p>
        <p>Standing upright in the batter's box has allowed Ordóñez to see the ball better and it has kept him from lunging at pitches. He is recognizing pitches better, showing more discipline and, Valentine said, hitting the ball where it is pitched.</p>
        <p>Last night, Ordóñez was the only batter to get a hit with runners in scoring position. Before he came through, the Mets were 0 for 6 in that situation. The Braves were 0 for 11.</p>
        <p>After Zeile's leadoff walk in the 10th, Tsuyoshi Shinjo, who worked extensively on bunting in spring training, got a sacrifice down. Shinjo slid feet-first into first base, and received warm applause despite being out. He guessed that he bunted an average of once a year over 10 seasons in Japan.</p>
        <p>''Nobody likes bunting,'' Shinjo said through an interpreter. ''But I think it's a really important thing to contribute to the team winning, and I don't mind doing it.''</p>
        <p>Ordóñez came up a batter later with the game-winning hit, but the Braves might have scored in the top of the inning if not for Shinjo's arm. Rafael Furcal led off the 10th with a bunt single off Armando Benitez, who was working his second inning.</p>
        <p>Furcal stole second without a throw and advanced to third when Benitez threw a wild pitch while issuing an intentional walk. Brian Jordan was up next, and Benitez said he tried to pitch him outside, knowing that a shallow fly ball to Shinjo would be risky for the Braves to run on.</p>
        <p>The plan worked, and Jordan flied out to shallow right. Furcal held up, and Javy Lopez bounced to Ordóñez to end the threat.</p>
        <p>The Mets (.227) and Braves (a National League-low .217) entered the game with two of the three worst team batting averages in the league. This game lowered those marks.</p>
        <p>John Burkett, who dominated the Mets last year, and Glendon Rusch, who struggled against the Braves in 2000, both pitched seven shutout innings last night. Rusch permitted just three hits, Burkett five.</p>
        <p>The next meeting in this series is on June 22 at Shea Stadium, and Zeile said the bats should be warmed up by then. The rivalry, of course, is hot enough already.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Manager BOBBY VALENTINE will be featured on HBO's ''Real Sports'' on Monday, and if he watches the segment, he will see something he has never seen before: video of the play that changed his career. Valentine said he did not know a tape existed of the 1973 play in which he broke his leg running into the wall at Anaheim Stadium, turning him from a budding star to a utility player. Valentine said he is not sure he wants to relive the experience by watching the show.  Left fielder BENNY AGBAYANI, who is on the disabled list with a fractured hamate bone in his left wrist, said last night he hopes to remove his cast on Sunday and perhaps start taking batting practice then. The Mets believe it will take Agbayani two to four  weeks to return, but he said he will be back on April 24, when he is first eligible. . . . The reliever RICK WHITE (elbow inflammation) probably will return after pitching in the Mets' exhibition game at Norfolk next Thursday. . . . Shortstop REY ORDÓÑEZ's throwing error in the fifth inning was the first error by a Mets infielder this year. . . . The Reds' KEN GRIFFEY Jr., who has a strained left hamstring, is expected to be limited to a pinch-hitting role when Cincinnati plays at Shea this weekend.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
