<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; Four Women Swagger In Milan</title>
    <meta content="05DRES$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/05/fashion/shows/05DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1469838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Review"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milan (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Versace, Donatella</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castiglioni, Consuelo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prada, Miuccia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Missoni, Angela</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Milan (Italy)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D9143FF936A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; Four Women Swagger In Milan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Four Women Swagger in Milan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, March 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian fall 2003 fashion shows close in Milan; comment on designs by Donatella Versace, Consuelo Castiglioni, Miuccia Prada and Angela Missoni; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four women closed the Italian fall 2003 season today, their clothes changing the tempo and temperament of fashion. After years of male domination, have the women finally taken over macho Milan?</p>
        <p>Donatella Versace sent out her best collection since she took over her late brother's house six years ago. At Marni, Consuelo Castiglioni fled the commune -- the boho prints, the hippie fringe -- for sophisticated tweeds draped in cocoons of feather-light fur. Miuccia Prada continued to sort out the boys from the girls, creating a cerebral sisterhood at Miu Miu (and, inevitably, a few dunces and librarian types), while Angela Missoni let herself be a little bit of a diva.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donatella Versace, Consuelo Castiglioni, Miuccia Prada and Angela Missoni changed the tempo and temperament of fashion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four women closed the Italian fall 2003 season today, their clothes changing the tempo and temperament of fashion. After years of male domination, have the women finally taken over macho Milan?</p>
        <p>Donatella Versace sent out her best collection since she took over her late brother's house six years ago. At Marni, Consuelo Castiglioni fled the commune -- the boho prints, the hippie fringe -- for sophisticated tweeds draped in cocoons of feather-light fur. Miuccia Prada continued to sort out the boys from the girls, creating a cerebral sisterhood at Miu Miu (and, inevitably, a few dunces and librarian types), while Angela Missoni let herself be a little bit of a diva.</p>
        <p>This has been a season of design in which women, far more than men, drew from the well of their own personalities, none more so than Ms. Versace. It took a moment to realize tonight, as the models stalked an oval runway to the dance classic ''Pump Up the Jam,'' their ironed hair lengthened with extensions, that each was the lacquered essence of Donatella.</p>
        <p>She was spoofing herself -- her unabashed love of glamour, the womanly body going around in too-tight pants and tipsy heels. Yet she was also serious, getting down to business at the outset with streamlined pantsuits and pencil skirts in white or putty stretch wool. The neutral daytime palette remained constant, in sync with the emphatic silhouette, its line broken only by eye-popping coats in lynx and leather swinging with fringe. Pants stretched over the buttocks, leaving the soft part just below the waist showing; and some of the models might mind about the view from the rear. But what mattered more was that Ms. Versace was audaciously putting herself into the clothes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Castiglioni must have sensed, as her audience did, that she had become hemmed in by her arts-and-crafts style, and that if she didn't stretch herself, think harder, she was going to be some kind of den mother to the weird and dippy. Her most sophisticated gesture was to combine boyish tweed shorts (cuffed and worn over high brown boots) with frankly glamorous furs. Made out of horizontal strips of fox or raccoon connected by ribbons, they puffed weightlessly over the body.</p>
        <p>There were wrap skirts in tweed and rustic-looking tunic tops gathered with thin leather belts. Ms. Castiglioni revisited some of her artsy effects, scattering circles of red sequins over the yoke of a dress and putting loose jumpers in gray flannel over abstract print tops. But even these touches revealed a new dimension to her talent.</p>
        <p>Miu Miu is often a kind of junior addendum to the Prada collection, and this season Ms. Prada evidently felt she had still more to say about the evolving mix of men's and women's clothes. She opened with a stiff cotton coat fastened with turn-key locks, a style that instantly evoked the early 1960's and the American sportswear maverick Bonnie Cashin. Yoked over the shoulders was a mink that might have been vintage. In any case, it seemed to run into the fur tippet debouching from the model's neck. On her arms were long, wooly gloves.</p>
        <p>Too much? Perhaps. There were moments when the tweed and tattersall layers, puffed with motley fur and mixed with crepe, vintage-print skirts, seemed stuffy and overdreamed. And yet the collection was loaded with so many ideas, connected in some way to Ms. Prada's own eclectic approach to dressing, that it was impossible to dwell on a few dunces.</p>
        <p>Loose T-shirts, for instance, were an ingenious blend of knitting (across the shoulders) and cotton jersey printed with cartoon drawings. Those drawings also appeared in a print on nude chiffon dresses and skirts worn over sexy undergarments. The collection had an innocence, expressed in low-slung flannel trousers and manly oxfords. But it also had a knowing decadence, as if the sorority had broken into the old boys' club and made off with their vests.</p>
        <p>Ms. Missoni's collection had polish and steam. Snug jackets in a zigzag mélange of orange, brown and aqua, finished with a brown border and worn with hot pants, hinted of the 1960's. But a Missoni knit can bear only so much Mod simplification before it starts to look like the petrified reflection of a matron staring into the windows at Scully &amp; Scully after a comb-out.</p>
        <p>The designer gave everything more eccentric flavor, tossing fox stoles over clingy sweaters and pairing black tights with creamy hoyden stilettos. The clothes looked coordinated and not -- trousers in saffron yellow satin worn with a jersey blouse in sunset swirls, and the caprice of an apricot fox stole moseying over the shoulder.</p>
        <p>Review</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
