<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Family Apart</title>
    <meta content="13MESSUDT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messud, Claire</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ernaux, Annie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shame (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DB1F3FF930A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Family Apart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Claire Messud</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Messud, Claire</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Claire Messud reviews book Shame by Annie Ernaux (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHAME</p>
        <p>By Annie Ernaux.</p>
        <p>Translated by Tanya Leslie.</p>
        <p>111 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Seven Stories Press. $16.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHAME</p>
        <p>By Annie Ernaux.</p>
        <p>Translated by Tanya Leslie.</p>
        <p>111 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Seven Stories Press. $16.95.</p>
        <p>Annie Ernaux, whose crystalline autobiographical volumes have captivated French audiences for years, defies the contemporary demands of her genre -- the desire for melodramatic intimate revelation and the smoothness of fictional tale-telling. The scrupulous self-awareness and precision of a book like ''Shame'' offer a searing authenticity and reveal the slipperiness of much that we call memoir.</p>
        <p>Ernaux embarks from the premise that ''we have no true memory of ourselves'': time and experience inevitably distort our understanding of our past. And so, in attempting to do justice to the girl she was in June 1952, she explains, ''I shall not opt for narrative, which would mean inventing reality instead of searching for it.'' Instead, she writes, ''I shall carry out an ethnological study of myself.'' The purpose of her ''study'' is to explore the nature of her passage into shame, a shift that she dates from a specific, simply described incident: ''My father tried to kill my mother one Sunday in June, in the early afternoon.''</p>
        <p>Those familiar with Ernaux's earlier books will recognize the setting for this event and will know its central characters: the modest grocery-haberdashery-cafe run by her parents in a small Normandy town here referred to only as ''Y''; the quiet father of ''A Man's Place''; the powerful mother of ''A Woman's Story.'' ''Shame'' (superbly translated from the French by Tanya Leslie) provides, in impeccable detail, the physical and social geography of that town, of that cafe, of that family. Ernaux outlines the righteous laws by which her girlhood was governed. She lists the tacit expectations of a world in which ''to be like everyone else was people's universal ambition, the ultimate dream.'' Alongside the hierarchies of home, she draws a meticulous and forceful picture of the private Roman Catholic school by which her parents offered her a way out of their limited society. Religious education, with its immutable order, afforded her ''a world of truth, a world of light and perfection.''</p>
        <p>Of her father's attack on her mother and its internal repercussions (so vast that Ernaux believes ''it was responsible for my writing''), she explains, ''What happened that day could not be put into words, in either of the worlds that was mine.'' In her eyes, ''We stopped being decent people.'' But although for Ernaux this incident marks her fall from grace, her fall into adulthood, ''Shame'' is an unpeeling of the many layers of alienation for which her father's act was but the focus.</p>
        <p>Ernaux, who turned 12 in 1952, was awakened in that fateful summer not only to the subterranean violence between her parents but also to the shame of puberty and of a woman's physicality. She was exposed, too, in the course of a 10-day trip to Lourdes with her father, to the agonies of social shame, to the fact that her parents' place in society was a humble one. ''It was the first time we were in the situation of having to spend 10 days in the company of complete strangers, all of whom were better off than us, with the exception of the bus drivers.'' This revelation gave the lie to her school's insistence that ''there were neither rich girls nor poor girls but one big Catholic family.''</p>
        <p>The shame, then, is that of never wholly belonging, the young Ernaux's recognition that she was and would forevermore be stretched between the irreconcilable worlds of home and school, with the complex social distinctions this division entailed -- that of an inner life of personal and womanly secrets and an external life in which those secrets must be kept hidden.</p>
        <p>In short, it was around this particular domestic event that Ernaux began to construct her womanhood, much as the pearl grows around its grain of sand. The careful, unflinching specificities of ''Shame'' give voice to a resonant and universal truth; and Ernaux's particular discomfort is, most profoundly, that of being human.</p>
        <p>Claire Messud is the author of ''When the World Was Steady,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Claire Messud is the author of ''When the World Was Steady,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
