<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Washington; Hollywood, D.C.</title>
    <meta content="15APPLET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981115T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Basinger, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baldwin, Alec</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DC1E3EF936A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Washington; Hollywood, D.C.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R.W. Apple Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple Jr (On Washington) article says Clinton Administration has become more socially aligned with Hollywood celebrities, choosing the glamorous over most of people listed in the Green book; says Hollywood has diffferent take on Clinton's difficulties; photo of Bill and Hillary Clinton with Hollywood stars Kim Basinger and Alec Baldwin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I came to Washington, I always thought, with all the right stuff: an Ivy League degree, a job on a big-time newspaper, a belly full of skepticism and a brain littered with assorted information on throw-weights, T-bills and reapportionment. I knew who George W. Norris and Arthur Vandenburg and Rexford G. Tugwell were, and I knew the difference between grands crus and grand larceny. I had once had tea at Alice Roosevelt Longworth's.</p>
        <p>That pretty well did the trick in the 1970's and 1980's, but not, alas, in the 1990's. I'm out of some pretty important loops now, status-wise, because I know little about television and less about movies. Now that Hollywood narcissism has displaced Rhodes-scholar earnestness as Washington's controlling ethos, with Barbra Streisand and David Geffen supplanting George Stephanopoulos and Robert Reich as prototypical Buddies of Bill, you have to have a Tinseltown-size appetite for celebrity to keep up in the capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I came to Washington, I always thought, with all the right stuff: an Ivy League degree, a job on a big-time newspaper, a belly full of skepticism and a brain littered with assorted information on throw-weights, T-bills and reapportionment. I knew who George W. Norris and Arthur Vandenburg and Rexford G. Tugwell were, and I knew the difference between grands crus and grand larceny. I had once had tea at Alice Roosevelt Longworth's.</p>
        <p>That pretty well did the trick in the 1970's and 1980's, but not, alas, in the 1990's. I'm out of some pretty important loops now, status-wise, because I know little about television and less about movies. Now that Hollywood narcissism has displaced Rhodes-scholar earnestness as Washington's controlling ethos, with Barbra Streisand and David Geffen supplanting George Stephanopoulos and Robert Reich as prototypical Buddies of Bill, you have to have a Tinseltown-size appetite for celebrity to keep up in the capital.</p>
        <p>Time was, a stiff, black-on-ecru invitation to one of the soirees given by the grandes dames of Washington was the premier status symbol. At Evangeline Bruce's or Pamela Harriman's houses, you might meet the head of the C.I.A. or the members of the permanent Establishment, those people who had long outlived the administration that first brought them to town. You might impress them by your knowledge of the minutiae of politics and government. The Clintons were launched into Washington by a gala dinner at Harriman's, come to think of it, but they have long since turned their backs on most of the people listed in the Green Book, choosing the glamorous over the grandees.</p>
        <p>Me, I still get invited to the British Embassy once in a while, and before relations between The Times and the Clintons turned testy, I even got asked to the White House a time or two. But when I failed to recognize Annette Bening at a star-studded reception at the time of the Clinton inaugural, some of my friends pitied me. And when I expressed doubts about colleagues who were trying to turn themselves into celebrities through the pundit circuit, others dropped me.</p>
        <p>The litmus paper changed color especially quickly at the annual springtime black-tie dinners for Washington reporters and their guests. They used to be an occasion for us groundlings to chat with publicity-averse Administration officials. (I remember getting Bob Haldeman in a corner once, the only time I ever talked to him.) Now, in an effort to make the other guests forget the cheap wine and the lame jokes, the newsies ask Robert De Niro and Kim Basinger (and one year, disastrously, the New York shock-jock Don Imus) as well as Lloyd Cutler and Colin Powell.</p>
        <p>The new Washington ought to adopt Suzanne Stone as its mascot. She was the rapacious small-town weather girl in ''To Die For'' (played by Nicole Kidman, I think) who said you're nothing if you're not on television. ''What's the point of doing anything worthwhile,'' she asked, ''if nobody's watching?''</p>
        <p>Good question, thinks Washington, vintage 1998, and it has made Larry King, Tim Russert and Sam and Cokie -- or rather their air time -- the real forum of American political discourse, eclipsing the Senate and the House.</p>
        <p>During the debate in October about impeachment hearings, Representative Robert Wexler, a Florida Democrat, gave the game away. He said that he wanted to tell his colleagues, ''in the most friendly and respectful way that I know,'' that he and Representative Robert Barr, a Georgia Republican, were scheduled to appear that evening on the ''Crossfire'' program, so he planned to postpone his comments in the House ''in an effort not to ruin the show.'' No wonder it's been said that Washington is Hollywood for ugly people.</p>
        <p>Everybody's avocation in America is show business, said the man who wrote ''To Die For,'' Buck Henry. So I guess it's not all that surprising that President Clinton has got into the game, playing his sax and discussing his underwear on TV. Or that he spends almost as much time at fund-raisers in the ballroom of the Century Plaza as producers, stars and starlets spend in the Lincoln Bedroom.</p>
        <p>Plenty of other Washington heavy-hitters have been fascinated by Hollywood. But past Presidents kept their psychic distance. John F. Kennedy was always the star, not the Rat Pack. Bill Clinton, the unabashed fan of Elvis, is the first star-struck President. I didn't know Marilyn Monroe, but I know Markie Post is no Marilyn Monroe.</p>
        <p>The President does favors for movieland friends, like arranging for his national security adviser, Sandy Berger, to brief a group led by John Travolta on the Administration's stand on Scientology. They, in turn, do favors for him. It's all very chummy.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, former Presidents like Jimmy Carter and Gerald Ford and eminent Senators like Daniel Patrick Moynihan don't waste their breath defending Clinton. To the chattering classes of Georgetown and Cleveland Park, Washington seems critically short of political heroes these days. But maybe they don't listen to the right people or read the right publications.</p>
        <p>For Hollywood has a whole different take on Clinton's difficulties. Discussing the President with Elle magazine this fall, the actress Sharon Stone said this: ''I think Clinton's a fantastic President. He's done so much good in the world. And people do not want to assign him the successes of his office. They only want to assign him the failures. It's really ugly.''</p>
        <p>Marshall Herskovitz, executive producer of ''Thirtysomething,'' said recently that Hollywood was more forgiving of Clinton than other people because it does not see marriage as ''a monolithic simple entity.''</p>
        <p>And Bette Midler told Larry King: ''I feel that he and his wife have been hounded for the past six years, actually, since they walked in the door.. . .I think he's the smartest guy we ever had.''</p>
        <p>Nowhere else, except in the Congressional Black Caucus and among the trial lawyers -- surely not among his former aides and onetime enthusiasts in the universities -- does Bill Clinton get that kind of unconditional praise.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's not surprising that in Washington and in California, the gossips -- the same ones, now that politics is a subset of celebrity -- keep whispering that Clinton will go to work one day for Dreamworks, the entertainment company that Geffen runs with two other Clinton enthusiasts, Steven Spielberg and Jeffrey Katzenberg, and live next door to Tom Hanks.</p>
        <p>He certainly won't move to Georgetown, where I live, along with a lot of other people who don't quite fit the new mold. I admit that I'm of two minds about the status revolution in Washington. I rather enjoyed playing the old game -- when inside information was the coin of the realm -- and so naturally I wish I knew more about the new rules and the redrawn playing field.</p>
        <p>But I fear, square that I am, that the whole culture of celebrity worship has tainted the country, its politics and my trade as well. In Washington, as elsewhere, fame and fortune, not talent and perseverance, are now what's most widely respected. Ex-actors and ex-athletes and relatives of ex-politicians occupy more and more seats in Congress. They have instant ''name recognition,'' which is almost as useful in campaigns these days as money, which propels other people into high office. You have to wonder whether Abe Lincoln -- homely, provincial and poor -- would have had a shot at the modern White House.</p>
        <p>Note, too, that candidates have adopted the techniques of show business and of marketing, its comrade in hoopla. Both politicians and producers know that violence sells; as with car chases and gory murders in movies, TV commercials filled with distorted and negative language dominate our barren campaigns.</p>
        <p>Candidates for important offices no longer proclaim programs and ideas first and invite people to support them. They take polls to discover what people think and then develop policies. In other words, they convene focus groups (cf. sneak previews in Hollywood) before editing their ideas (cf. recutting the picture).</p>
        <p>Politicians' debilitating and humiliating loss of privacy is, of course, related to the celebrification of politics; we eavesdrop on Leonardo DiCaprio's love life -- why not on Bill Clinton's? The voyeur that lurks in each of us has been given more room to do his stuff, denying it all the while. Similarly, journalists' loss of standing must have something to do with the fact that they have emerged from relative anonymity, reporting less and talking more, part of an ever-growing mountain of commentary resting on an ever-shrinking base of fact.</p>
        <p>I don't blame the man in the street for making very little distinction between what I do and what Geraldo Rivera does, and thinking little of either of us. But I don't pretend to like that particular change in status.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 15, 1998, Sunday  The On Washington column on page 40 of The Times Magazine today misspells the surname of a former Republican Senator from Michigan. He was Arthur Vandenberg, not Vandenburg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 15, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>The On Washington column on page 40 of The Times Magazine today misspells the surname of a former Republican Senator from Michigan. He was Arthur Vandenberg, not Vandenburg.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
