<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From 'Hello, Central' to 'Hello, Conglomerate'</title>
    <meta content="15PHON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern New England Telephone Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dodd, Thomas J, Research Center (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slocum, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DE1731F936A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From 'Hello, Central' to 'Hello, Conglomerate'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL SLOCUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slocum, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Southern New England Telephone Co, celebrating its 120th anniversary, opens exhibit at Thomas Dodd Research Center in Storrs, Conn, featuring artifacts from 1878 to 1928; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE than 60 years later, John T. Steck still vividly remembers the day he rescued a man clinging to a tree amid floodwaters near the Housatonic River in New Milford.</p>
        <p>''The water was ice cold,'' Mr. Steck said of that day in 1936. ''Ice was coming down the river in big chunks 20 feet square and 2 feet thick. The chunks were so big they were knocking trees down.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE than 60 years later, John T. Steck still vividly remembers the day he rescued a man clinging to a tree amid floodwaters near the Housatonic River in New Milford.</p>
        <p>''The water was ice cold,'' Mr. Steck said of that day in 1936. ''Ice was coming down the river in big chunks 20 feet square and 2 feet thick. The chunks were so big they were knocking trees down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Steck, then a construction foreman for the Southern New England Telephone Company, fashioned a rope swing to slide across a telephone line and reach the man before the waters would have swept him into the Housatonic. For his feat, Mr. Steck won the Bell Telephone Company's Vail Medal of Honor and saw his act recorded in an issue of ''Heroic Comics.''</p>
        <p>Now 98, Mr. Steck is happy that the company he retired from in 1965 is commemorating stories like his as part of a S.N.E.T. 120th anniversary celebration, beginning with an exhibition at the Thomas Dodd Research Center in Storrs, where the corporate records of S.N.E.T. are now housed.</p>
        <p>''It's a good thing,'' Mr. Steck said. ''I think they ought to have more of it.''</p>
        <p>State residents don't have to reach back to 1936 to discover interesting things about S.N.E.T., which provides regular telephone service in all of Connecticut's 169 municipalities. So far in 1998 the telephone company has undergone a merger (it's now a subsidiary of SBC Communications of San Antonio) and a strike. Yet many of S.N.E.T.'s defining moments came within its first 50 years, from 1878 to 1928, the period covered in the Dodd Center exhibit.</p>
        <p>Only two years before, in 1876, Alexander Graham Bell invented the telephone. A teacher of the deaf who saw his invention as an educational tool, Bell was persuaded by backers to expand on the telephone's commercial potential. A year later, Bell demonstrated his device in Skiff's Opera House in New Haven, talking to assistants in Hartford and Middletown.</p>
        <p>It was the first practical demonstration of the telephone in Connecticut, and sales of local patent rights quickly followed.</p>
        <p>''Telephones were a franchise, like a McDonald's,'' said Bob Patterson, director of special programs at S.N.E.T. who is supervising the 120th anniversary program. ''If you wanted a telephone in your town, you went to a group in Boston and applied for a franchise.''</p>
        <p>George Coy was a disabled Civil War veteran and telegraph manager in New Haven whose franchise application was initially turned down.</p>
        <p>But when Western Union decided to forfeit their Bell franchise rights to develop a competing telephonic device, Mr. Coy and two other men were awarded the Bell franchise in New Haven and Middlesex counties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coy brought a new wrinkle to the telephone concept: An instrument made of carriage bolts, teapot-lid handles, and bustle wire that would allow several customers to communicate with each other through the same connection of lines. This crude switchboard, which Mr. Coy patented, inaugurated the first telephone exchange system in the world. ''What surprised me most about S.N.E.T.'s history is the innovation,'' said William J. Uricchio, an associate librarian at the Dodd Center. ''I didn't know it had such a long history of firsts. It's important for people to realize that Connecticut has long been a leader in communications.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Doolittle, another telephone pioneer, helped create both the first telephone booth (in Bridgeport in 1878) and the copper wiring still used in telephone lines today.</p>
        <p>The first telephone directory, the only known copy of which is on display at the Dodd exhibition, was no more than a single sheet of paper listing the names and addresses of subscribers to the New Haven exchange Mr. Coy helped found. The first person to subscribe to this service was a minister who lived at 227 Church Street, which 120 years later became the address for S.N.E.T.'s corporate headquarters.</p>
        <p>Under the direction of the S.N.E.T. chairman, Daniel Miglio, hundreds of boxes containing company memoranda, photographs, directories, expense account ledgers and items of general interest as well as highly esoteric were turned over to the University of Connecticut for safekeeping at the university's Dodd Center  beginning late last year. It is estimated to take 6 to 12 months before the archive is organized well enough to allow researchers to examine the collection, the second-largest business archive (next to those for the now-defunct New Haven Railroad Company) at the Dodd Center.</p>
        <p>''Companies have different attitudes toward their history,'' said the Dodd Center director, Thomas P. Wilsted. ''One asset here is the pride S.N.E.T. employers have in their company. There was a concern that all this information not be lost, because of the personal pride they have in what they accomplished.''</p>
        <p>The one restriction on the collection, when it is ready for scholars to start examining it, is that records 25 years old and less are off-limits due to proprietary concerns. ''I hope to see a lot of use, and I think they hope so, too,'' Mr. Wilsted said of S.N.E.T.</p>
        <p>One centerpiece of the Dodd exhibition is a book of minutes from the first meeting of the National Telephone Exchange Association, in Niagara Falls, N.Y., in 1880. The association, comprised of telephone company executives throughout the country, was formed in part to insure that their separately-developed technologies were compatible with each other.</p>
        <p>It was two years later, in 1882, that the Connecticut Telephone Company changed its name to S.N.E.T. It was a time of high science and low scheming, as captains of industry vied for position within the burgeoning business. Local ownership of Connecticut's telephone service was a close-run thing, as Western Union cast covetous glances on the unstable Connecticut Telephone Company through its early days. Only when Marshall Jewell, a former Connecticut governor, stepped in with the necessary capital did the company begin to enjoy relative security.</p>
        <p>Profitability was another story. Cindy DeLottie, S.N.E.T. project archivist at the Dodd Center, noted ''they didn't make money for many, many years.''</p>
        <p>''The executive officers didn't even take a salary,'' she said. One problem was a dearth of new customers during S.N.E.T.'s first two decades of existence, the 1880's and 1890's. ''There were 21 new customers one year.''</p>
        <p>S.N.E.T. did what it could to encourage business. The first switchboard operators in the state were boys, but their rudeness drew many complaints and by the turn of the century most telephone operators in Connecticut were women.</p>
        <p>As an employer, S.N.E.T. had several faces, at least as evidenced in the Dodd Center exhibition. The company gave women jobs at a time few other businesses would, and in 1908 opened the first operators' school in the country. But there are also signs in the collection of a harsher posture.</p>
        <p>''I notice that some operators, either carelessly or willfully, are continually violating the rule of the Company, in regard to the manner of answering any call by saying 'Hello,' instead of 'What number?' '', reads a general notice from the S.N.E.T. General Superintendent E. B. Baker in 1892. Such ''unnecessary talk'' and ''personal conversation'' was frowned on as the company tried to carve a business-first image for itself.</p>
        <p>That image became reality with the advent of the 20th century. By then a second war was underway, this time for customers, between S.N.E.T. and smaller telephone companies scattered across the state. S.N.E.T.'s dominance was sealed only by the formation of the Public Utilities Commission in 1911, which ended direct competition at least on a toll-free basis. Smaller telephone companies continued to service sections of Connecticut through to this decade until S.N.E.T. bought them up. Today the only part of Connecticut not managed by S.N.E.T. is Greenwich west of the Mianus River, which is served by Bell Atlantic.</p>
        <p>One reason the collection is so large, archivists say, is because it encompasses so many different areas. ''The collection cuts across business and technical history into personal history,'' Mr. Uricchio said, pointing out photographs of men's and women's basketball teams made up of S.N.E.T. employees.</p>
        <p>''It shows you Connecticut, too,'' Mrs. DeLottie added. ''Things like phone books, a genealogist's dream.''</p>
        <p>S.N.E.T. commissioned many photographs, especially after natural disasters like the Blizzard of 1888 and a 1938 hurricane that caused outages statewide.</p>
        <p>Such photographs are valuable not only for the devastation they record, but also for the glimpse they offer of Connecticut's changing character through the passage of time. One of Mr. Uricchio's favorite parts of the collection, one not on display at the Dodd Center, is a ledger book that records every vehicle purchased by S.N.E.T., repairs and alterations done on each, and their estimated value at the time the vehicle was retired from service.</p>
        <p>''You are able to get a much fuller, broader picture with this collection,'' Mrs. DeLottie said. ''Employee records are disposed of after a number of years, as you'd expect. But they kept things that other companies wouldn't keep.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Dodd Center exhibition, S.N.E.T. is putting together its own videocassette history of its history for release later this year. It will feature interviews with more than a score of former employees like Mr. Steck, who has seen three generations of his family work for S.N.E.T.</p>
        <p>''In the beginning it was mostly family,'' Mr. Steck said of the company. ''They were one of the best bunch of men to work for.''</p>
        <p>The Dodd Center exhibition will be open to the public Monday through Friday from 8:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. until Dec. 31.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
