<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Who, Ahead of It's Time'</title>
    <meta content="15EHRL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="VIDEO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Who, The (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehrlich, Dimitri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DB113EF936A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Who, Ahead of It's Time'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIMITRI EHRLICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ehrlich, Dimitri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dimitri Ehrlich reviews home video version of performance of The Who at Isle of Wight Festival recorded on August 30, 1970; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'THE WHO: ISLE OF WIGHT'  Rhino Home Video. 85 minutes. $19.98.</p>
        <p>From 2:00 A.M. until 5:00 A.M on Aug. 30, 1970, on a small island off the coast of England, the Who delivered one of the galvanic performances of the psychedelic era. The Who's set was only one part of the three-day Isle of Wight Festival, which also featured Jimi Hendrix, Joni Mitchell and Miles Davis.</p>
        <p>It was the biggest and final year of the concert series, which had begun three years earlier. A documentary of the event was filmed by Murray Lerner and released theatrically two years ago, and now Rhino has made a new home video available, focusing exclusively on the Who's performance. The 85-minute video, ''The Who: Isle of Wight,'' captures a moment when the innocence of the 60's was to be replaced by the materialism of the 70's, and the band's playing evoked a sense that everything was at stake and nothing much could be done about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'THE WHO: ISLE OF WIGHT'  Rhino Home Video. 85 minutes. $19.98.</p>
        <p>From 2:00 A.M. until 5:00 A.M on Aug. 30, 1970, on a small island off the coast of England, the Who delivered one of the galvanic performances of the psychedelic era. The Who's set was only one part of the three-day Isle of Wight Festival, which also featured Jimi Hendrix, Joni Mitchell and Miles Davis.</p>
        <p>It was the biggest and final year of the concert series, which had begun three years earlier. A documentary of the event was filmed by Murray Lerner and released theatrically two years ago, and now Rhino has made a new home video available, focusing exclusively on the Who's performance. The 85-minute video, ''The Who: Isle of Wight,'' captures a moment when the innocence of the 60's was to be replaced by the materialism of the 70's, and the band's playing evoked a sense that everything was at stake and nothing much could be done about it.</p>
        <p>The best material comes toward the second half of the concert, after the band had warmed up by running through early hits like ''Can't Explain,'' an adolescent and artless three minutes of blues and bluster during which the lead singer Roger Daltrey's sense of pitch was derailed by the sloppy backing vocals of the drummer Keith Moon.</p>
        <p>The later part of the concert drew from the band's rock opera ''Tommy,'' material that is more sophisticated, more harmonically complex than the group's earlier work, although it was performed with furious bombast that rendered even the most lilting melodies somewhat edgy.</p>
        <p>The Who's cover of the Beatles' hit, ''Twist and Shout,'' aborted after a single verse and chorus, was intended as a teeny-bopper crowd-pleaser that quickly degenerated into a thrashing jam session. The band fared better with its remake of Eddie Cochran's ''Summertime Blues,'' which held up under the band's rebellious, tattered reading. When Mr. Daltrey sputters, ''I hope I die before I get old,'' in one of the Who's signature songs, ''My Generation,'' what might have been a piece of youthful braggadocio now sounds eerily prescient: it's a sentiment that could easily have been expressed by Kurt Cobain.</p>
        <p>While the band's music was ahead of its time, its sartorial style wasn't. The bassist John Entwistle dressed in a skeleton suit that now looks silly; Mr. Daltrey wore a jacket with three-foot fringes while Mr. Townshend sported a white garage mechanic's jumpsuit; in his plain white T-shirt, Moon (who died in 1978) was the only member of the band who could appear on MTV today and not look like he was hoping for a slot in Lenny Kravitz's backup band.</p>
        <p>While many groups were still reveling in the afterglow of Woodstock's feel-good hippie mentality, the Who was anticipating the rougher and nastier sound that would soon sweep Britian and later America. In the days before synthesizers, Mr. Townsend coaxed a stunning array of tones from his guitar, summoning gut-wrenching power chords with his trademark windmill strumming. His controlled use of feedback during the concert predated similar musical explorations, including Lou Reed's ''Metal Machine Music'' and most of Sonic Youth's oeuvre.</p>
        <p>Mr. Townshend's slashing, bruising guitar solos were messy that night, but they were bursting with energy, which is ultimately what makes this performance so captivating. Rather than precise harmonies (like those being offered by California contemporaries like Crosby, Stills and Nash) or the increasingly complex progressive rock of British peers like Pink Floyd or Genesis, the Who's performance at Isle of Wight presaged punk, with its self-immolating rage and primitive, sexualized, druggy abandon. The Who played with manic effort, winding their songs into raga-like endings, four young men proverbially sacrificing themselves on the altar of rock-and-roll.</p>
        <p>DIMITRI EHRLICH</p>
        <p>VIDEO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
