<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting for His Father, on Screen and Off</title>
    <meta content="15COV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">My Father's Shadow: the Sam Sheppard Story (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D7133EF936A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting for His Father, on Screen and Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FA</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the bushy-haired intruder who did it after all.</p>
        <p>It was not Dr. Sam Sheppard who  bludgeoned his wife, Marilyn, to death in their affluent lakeside home in a Cleveland suburb in 1954, but a psychopathic window washer. And it was a killing that the Sheppard's only child, Sam Reese Sheppard, working with a team of lawyers, private investigators and DNA experts, has ''solved,'' more than four decades later, overcoming his own demons and continued hostility by the police and prosecutors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the bushy-haired intruder who did it after all.</p>
        <p>It was not Dr. Sam Sheppard who  bludgeoned his wife, Marilyn, to death in their affluent lakeside home in a Cleveland suburb in 1954, but a psychopathic window washer. And it was a killing that the Sheppard's only child, Sam Reese Sheppard, working with a team of lawyers, private investigators and DNA experts, has ''solved,'' more than four decades later, overcoming his own demons and continued hostility by the police and prosecutors.</p>
        <p>That is the intended message of ''My Father's Shadow: The Sam Sheppard Story,'' a two-hour CBS film to be shown on Tuesday night at 9, the latest installment of what, before O. J. Simpson, was known as the trial of the century and the inspiration for the television series ''The Fugitive'' and the movie of the same name.</p>
        <p>If enough people get the message, then making the new television film will have been worth the Faustian bargain for Sam Reese Sheppard. Making the movie, Mr. Sheppard said, ''has been very difficult, a real gamble,'' reopening wounds that had traumatized him since the night of July 4, 1954, when he was 7 and his mother was killed as he slept in a nearby room.</p>
        <p>He never woke up until the police came the next morning, and he was rushed past the bloody bedroom, down the stairs covered with blood, and out past a phalanx of reporters and flashbulbs popping in his face. Nor did he have a chance to speak with his father, a handsome, successful osteopathic surgeon, who was convicted first in the local press, then in court, and sentenced to death by a judge who had told a reporter before the verdict that ''Sam Sheppard is guilty as hell.''</p>
        <p>For the younger Mr. Sheppard, the murder was the beginning of a haunted life. As many people watching will know, the Supreme Court overturned the verdict against his father 10 years later, ruling that the trial was tainted by excessive press attention -- the courtroom was so jammed that reporters actually sat at the defense table -- and Dr. Sheppard was acquitted in a second trial in 1966.</p>
        <p>But the Sheppard family was devastated. Not only had Mrs. Sheppard been murdered, but Dr. Sheppard's father died of an ulcer soon after the trial, then his mother committed suicide, and so did Mrs. Sheppard's father. After Dr. Sheppard was finally released, the film shows in painful detail, he was an outcast, unable to resume his medical practice. To make ends meet, he eventually became a professional wrestler before dying an alcoholic.</p>
        <p>The film focuses on young Sam's emotional struggle, first to maintain a relationship with his incarcerated father, then as he got older, to try to find the truth about who killed his mother and prove his father's innocence. The producers deliberately have not recreated the murder scene, and they have also left out most of the courtroom drama. F. Lee Bailey, for example, who argued Dr. Sheppard's case before the Supreme Court and helped win his acquittal at his second trial, is not even mentioned by name.</p>
        <p>Although these omissions may disappoint some viewers, and may prove confusing for those unfamiliar with the case, the producers say they did not want merely to tell the Sheppard story again.</p>
        <p>William Jenner, an executive producer, grew up near Cleveland and remembers being a newspaper boy at the time of the murder. ''I remember the headlines, and the absolute belief among everybody that Dr. Sheppard was guilty, and the hysteria about it,'' he said. His father worked on a factory assembly line, and he recalled the anger at his family's dinner table that the police might let a rich doctor get away with murder.</p>
        <p>''I never heard one person say he was innocent,'' Mr. Jenner said.</p>
        <p>But even though his interest in the case led him to become a criminal defense attorney, Mr. Jenner did not want to produce a murder story or courtroom saga. ''I think it is much more interesting to see how a young boy saw these events,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To translate this to the screen, the producers have resorted to the difficult device of flashbacks within flashbacks, and have used three actors to portray Sam Reese Sheppard at age 7, as a teen-ager and as an adult. The adult Mr. Sheppard is played by Henry Czerny, whose credits include a role in the film ''Clear and Present Danger.''</p>
        <p>The producers also paint a harsh portrait of Dr. Sheppard to explain how the public and press could have been so universally convinced of his guilt. As played by Peter Strauss, he is an arrogant womanizer, chasing every nurse and lab technician in a skirt. After his release from prison, he is seducing his son's girlfriend, in his dormitory, when the son walks in on him.</p>
        <p>''That never happened,'' Sam Reese Sheppard said. ''The Hollywood phrase is, they were 'seeking emotional truth.' So they had to overdramatize certain details. I understand that. For me, the important thing was to show my dad's innocence of murder for posterity.''</p>
        <p>Occasionally the poignancy of the story also affected the actors and the crew. Mr. Strauss recalled that when  they re-enacted the young Sam Reese Sheppard's being led past his mother's bloody bedroom, the real Mr. Sheppard appeared on the set and walked up the stairs. ''The crew all just looked at each other, and we walked out,'' Mr. Strauss said.</p>
        <p>For those who want to know more about the murder, ''Nova'' on PBS is devoting a program to be shown next year on how DNA evidence and scientific analysis have cleared Dr. Sheppard and identified the window washer, Richard Eberling, the ''bushy-haired'' man Dr. Sheppard described as seeing in his wife's bedroom that night before being hit over the head.</p>
        <p>The Sheppard family had always believed Dr. Sheppard was innocent. Mrs.  Sheppard had bitten her assailant so violently that two of her teeth were broken out, causing her murderer to bleed profusely, but Dr. Sheppard had no cuts. There was also a long trail of blood from the bedroom down the stairs, through the kitchen and out on the porch. The prosecution contended that it was Mrs. Sheppard's blood, dripping from a knife carried by the killer. That a knife blade could not hold so much blood from the victim did not stop the prosecution's argument.</p>
        <p>Recent DNA testing has shown the blood was not from Mrs. Sheppard, and tissue samples taken from Dr. Sheppard's body, exhumed under a court order last year, have also concluded that it was not his blood. That means it must have been from a third person, and further DNA tests strongly indicate it was from Mr. Eberling, who was first implicated in 1959 when a ring of Mrs. Sheppard's turned up in his house. But prosecutors told the police not to investigate further.</p>
        <p>As the film shows, Mr. Sheppard has  asked an Ohio court for a trial to prove his father's innocence and win damages for wrongful imprisonment. The judge agreed, but in an unusual move, the Cuyahoga County Prosecutor sued the judge and appealed to the Ohio Supreme Court to block the trial. Mr. Sheppard has been waiting since January for the state Supreme Court's decision.</p>
        <p>One of the justices on the court was an assistant prosecutor at Dr. Sheppard's second trial and has refused to remove himself from the case.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Eberling died last summer in prison while serving a life sentence for the murder of an elderly widow. Before he died, he confessed to another inmate that he had killed Mrs. Sheppard.</p>
        <p>If the Ohio Supreme Court turns Mr. Sheppard down, he recognizes that he will never get a chance in court to exonerate his father. So this film, and the ''Nova'' show, he said, ''may be my only chance for the historical record.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
