<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official Warns S.I. Oil Leak Threatens Crucial Bird Area</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="314318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARTHUR KILL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AUDUBON SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASH, CAROL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLETON, ALBERT F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DA1E3BF936A35752C0A966958260" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official Warns S.I. Oil Leak Threatens Crucial Bird Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As efforts to clean up an oil leak of at least 200,000 gallons continued yesterday in the Arthur Kill, a New York State official warned that one of the most important feeding and nesting areas for rare birds on the East Coast would suffer major damage, unless the work was adequately performed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As efforts to clean up an oil leak of at least 200,000 gallons continued yesterday in the Arthur Kill, a New York State official warned that one of the most important feeding and nesting areas for rare birds on the East Coast would suffer major damage, unless the work was adequately performed.</p>
        <p>As efforts to clean up an oil leak of at least 200,000 gallons continued yesterday in the Arthur Kill, a New York State official warned that one of the most important feeding and nesting areas for rare birds on the East Coast would suffer major damage, unless the work was adequately performed.</p>
        <p>''There could be a major problem come spring, when it's feeding time,'' the regional director of environmental conservation, Carol Ash, said. ''We will require Exxon to remediate to the fullest extent possible, so that the spring feeding will be a healthy one.''</p>
        <p>''We're facing, basically, a wildlife catastrophe,'' said Albert F. Appleton, conservation chairman of the New York City Audubon Society. ''What no one realizes is that this is one of the country's premiere urban wildlife refuges.</p>
        <p>''Despite the image of the place as an industrial wasteland and weedy vacant lots, this area maintains a breeding population of 1,500 pairs of herons.'' The heron is an endangered species that has been replenishing its numbers, particularly in the area of the spill, in recent years.</p>
        <p>Rupture on Tuesday</p>
        <p>They neared extinction early in the century ''at the hands of plume hunters and because of marsh destruction,'' Mr. Appleton said. He added that the Goethals Bridge Pond, a 33-acre area north of the bridge, served more than 160 species of birds.</p>
        <p>The leak occurred on Tuesday morning, when an Exxon pipeline ruptured in the 13-mile waterway between Staten Island and New Jersey. Exxon said yesterday that it would do whatever was necessary to clean the marshes and preserve the nesting areas.</p>
        <p>''We will foot the bill to set this whole situation right,'' said Kitty Cochrane, who as manager of the Exxon terminal in Bayonne, N.J., is in charge of the pipeline.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ash said 12 additional dead birds were found yesterday on Pralls Island, the main bird sanctuary in the waterway, bringing to 24 the number known to have died because the oil had stripped their coats' protection against the cold. ''And it's the same mix, mallards, black ducks and Canada geese,'' she added. #30,000 Feet of Boom The commander of the Coast Guard district that covers the coast from Maine to New York, Rear Adm. Richard I. Rybacki, said the kill would remain closed several days.</p>
        <p>The Commander of the Port, Capt. Robert C. North, said that the effort was going well and that officials of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration had estimated that at least half the oil had evaporated by yesterday morning.</p>
        <p>''We have six skimmers and 26 vacuum trucks out there,'' Captain North said. ''There's about 30,000 feet of boom out.''</p>
        <p>The captain said that the guard had focused on 25 sites in the channel, ''and they are actively at work at 20 of those areas.'' Exxon is handling the cleanup.</p>
        <p>Guard officials stuck to their estimate that more than 200,000 gallons of No. 2 heating oil had leaked from the 12-inch-wide 6.7-mile pipe between the Bayway Refinery in Linden, N.J. under the Arthur Kill to the northwestern tip of Staten Island and under the Kill van Kull to Bayonne.</p>
        <p>Dependence on Exxon</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Exxon told the guard that 5,000 gallons had spilled. On Wednesday, saying that it was offering a ''worst-case scenario,'' Exxon raised the amount to more than 500,000 gallons. But the Guard, basing its estimate on observations from helicopters, revised the figure to 200,000. The guard considers spills of more than 100,000 gallons major.</p>
        <p>Asked again whether the guard was depending on Exxon for its estimates, Captain North said that was just in situations involving pipeline breaks.</p>
        <p>''In a pipeline situation, where there is no vessel with cargo tanks, we ask, 'What do you think you lost?' '' he said. ''When it's from a vessel with a loading manifest, we know exactly how much is lost.''</p>
        <p>Exxon said the leak was at a half-inch-wide four-foot-long tear in the pipe 150 feet from the Bayway dock, where the pipeline rises to enter the refinery and is supposed to be seven feet under water. The company said it appeared that a boat had hit the pipe, because it was 25 feet under the surface.</p>
        <p>'Out of the Navigational Channel'</p>
        <p>A Coast Guard pollution-response officer, Ens. Joseph Cost, said no further evidence had been found to support that theory. Captain North said the tear ''was out of the navigation channel lines, in shallow water.''</p>
        <p>Despite the guard's assessment, Nina Sankovitch, coastal project lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said:</p>
        <p>''We find that the oil-spill response is inadequate. Booms weren't deployed until several hours after the spill was observed. Pralls Island is soaked with oil.''</p>
        <p>''It's not oil on the water that's the worst problem,'' Mr. Appleton said. ''A more important problem is cleaning the marshes in time for the spring breeding season. If the oil stays down in the mud, all the worms and crayfish and small marine organisms are going to ingest it. The herons will feed their young on this poisoned food, and there will be a massive die-off in the spring.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ash said that cleaning the marshes and creeks was ''the main area we are concerned about'' and that substantial rain in the next few days could greatly aid cleansing tides.</p>
        <p>However, she added, Exxon cannot simply rely on nature to do the job.</p>
        <p>''You have to literally blot it out,'' she said. ''It's very time and manpower consuming.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
