<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honda to Hold Base Price on Accord Model</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="632127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DUMPING (TRADE TERM)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HONDA MOTOR CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DB1F3DF931A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honda to Hold Base Price on Accord Model</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>MARYSVILLE, Ohio, Sept. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Honda is maintaining the base price of its new 1994 Accord family sedan at $14,330 -- the same as the current model -- which could provoke protectionist pressure by the Big Three auto makers, which say they expect Japanese car makers to raise prices to reflect the stronger yen.</p>
        <p>Preparing to defend against possible attacks by Detroit's auto makers, Honda executives and engineers here explained today how they cut costs to avoid a price increase on the stripped-down Accord, modestly raised prices on other models and still expect to remain profitable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Honda is maintaining the base price of its new 1994 Accord family sedan at $14,330 -- the same as the current model -- which could provoke protectionist pressure by the Big Three auto makers, which say they expect Japanese car makers to raise prices to reflect the stronger yen.</p>
        <p>Preparing to defend against possible attacks by Detroit's auto makers, Honda executives and engineers here explained today how they cut costs to avoid a price increase on the stripped-down Accord, modestly raised prices on other models and still expect to remain profitable.</p>
        <p>Executives of the Honda Motor Company wish to guard against possible accusations by the Big Three that Honda is selling cars in the United States at prices that do not fully reflect their cost. In other words, if the Big Three could demonstrate that Honda was selling a comparable car for less money in the United States than it sold for in Japan, the American auto makers could have the basis for a "dumping" complaint. More U.S. Parts</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation, the Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Corporation had no immediate response to Honda's 1994 model prices.</p>
        <p>Honda said it had reduced costs by using more parts that were interchangeable among its models and continuing to use components from past models, thereby saving engineering and design costs. The auto maker has also been switching from Japanese to American suppliers at its factories in Ohio -- 25 new American suppliers on the latest Accord bring the total to 320 suppliers in the United States.</p>
        <p>Local content on American-built Accords rose to 82 percent of its value in 1994, Honda said, compared with 75 percent for the previous generation, built between 1990 and 1993.</p>
        <p>Spurred by the yen's 17 percent rise in the last year, Honda has raised prices three times in the period and may have to do so again soon, Honda executives said, after the new Accord goes on sale on Sept. 8.</p>
        <p>Richard Colliver, Honda's senior vice president for United States sales, said Honda hoped to sell 375,000 Accords in the new model year. The peak for Accord sales was in 1990, when Honda sold about 400,000.</p>
        <p>He also said Honda wants to hold the line on pricing as much as possible, while tailoring its advertisements to tell more about specific product attributes. Seen as More Expensive</p>
        <p>Gerry Rubin, president and chief executive of Rubin Postaer &amp; Associates of Los Angeles, Honda's advertising agency, said that "results of focus groups tell us that people perceive the Accord as a $20,000 car, and that comes from competitors' ads."</p>
        <p>A new Honda television commercial shows an old Accord driving away as the price sticker remains floating in the air; then a new Accord drives up and the sticker attaches to the rear window.</p>
        <p>The Accord, which was displaced by the Ford Taurus in 1992 as the nation's best-selling sedan, faces fierce competition in its segment. The lowest-priced versions of the Taurus and Toyota Camry cost more than $15,000 before price increases for 1994 models. But the 1994 Chevrolet Lumina costs $15,305 with air-conditioning and an AM-FM radio, neither of which is included in the base Accord DX. With the most popular options, including a sophisticated new engine, the 1994 Accord costs $20,500.  COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
