<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congressional Memo; Liquor-Warning Bill Reflects Personal Impact on Public Policy</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="609385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABELING AND LABELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUNKEN AND RECKLESS DRIVING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THURMOND, STROM (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF143EF935A25756C0A965958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congressional Memo; Liquor-Warning Bill Reflects Personal Impact on Public Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, a bill requiring advertisers to attach safety warnings to liquor commercials has collected more dust than votes. Then Nancy Moore Thurmond, the 22-year-old daughter of the Republican Senator from South Carolina, was run down and killed by a drunken driver last month.</p>
        <p>Her death gave the legislation a new life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, a bill requiring advertisers to attach safety warnings to liquor commercials has collected more dust than votes. Then Nancy Moore Thurmond, the 22-year-old daughter of the Republican Senator from South Carolina, was run down and killed by a drunken driver last month.</p>
        <p>Her death gave the legislation a new life.</p>
        <p>The legislation, called the Sensible Advertising and Family Education Act, would force advertisers to rotate warnings involving safety and health on all beer, wine and liquor commercials, like advising pregnant women that drinking posed a risk to their fetuses.</p>
        <p>The measure still faces an uphill fight against the broadcasting and liquor industries, which contend that it is an infringement of free speech and will hurt sports programs, many of which are financed by beer commercials.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of senators have said they will look at the issue anew in deference to Senator Strom Thurmond. His Democratic colleague from South Carolina, Ernest F. Hollings, is chairman of the Senate Commerce, Science and Transportation Committee and has promised that the committee will finally vote on the issue in the coming weeks after allowing it to languish in legislative limbo for three years. A Changing Atmosphere</p>
        <p>"Sometimes the atmosphere changes when something happens around here," Senator Paul Simon, Democrat of Illinois, said in an emotional speech supporting the legislation at a committee hearing on Thursday. "I think it would be a great tribute to Senator Thurmond and Nancy to pass this."</p>
        <p>The bill's sudden change of fate illustrates that even in the cold marble halls of Congress, where horse-trading and lobbying usually shape legislation, the actions of lawmakers are sometimes driven by personal or family problems. Some lawmakers even bend their philosophies when the cause hits home.</p>
        <p>The Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, for example, may not have passed or would have been weakened had it not received the pivotal support of Bob Dole of Kansas, the Senate minority leader.</p>
        <p>Senator Dole usually opposes Federal mandates on businesses, but he has a special empathy for people with disabilities because he lost the use of an arm while serving as an infantry officer in World War II, and he pushed for legislation that forces industry to accommodate the needs of disabled workers.</p>
        <p>Pete V. Domenici of New Mexico, the ranking Republican deficit hawk in the Senate, managed to persuade several colleagues to vote for more spending on mental health after his daughter suffered a still undiagnosed mental illness a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Harkin, an Iowa Democrat who has lost two sisters to breast cancer and has a deaf brother, has been a champion of more cancer research and expanded civil rights for people with disabilities.</p>
        <p>Fighting breast cancer was an epiphany for Representative Marilyn Lloyd, Democrat of Tennessee. She testified last year against a plan proposed by the Food and Drug Administration to restrict breast implants, arguing that an implant was important for her own recovery process.</p>
        <p>"Politicians are human beings," said Representative Joseph P. Kennedy 2d, the Massachusetts Democrat who is the oldest son of former Senator Robert F. Kennedy and a nephew of Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts. Pain Makes a Difference</p>
        <p>"When there is a degree of very personal pain that one feels toward an issue -- it might be gun control or my uncle's interest in fighting cancer -- the commitment level is higher and your willingness to compromise is lower," the Congressman continued. "Your higher energy level, your willingness to stay an hour longer or make one more speech, all of those make the difference sometimes in winning and losing."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy, who is a House sponsor of the liquor advertising bill, testified before the Senate Commerce Committee on Thursday that the death of his younger brother David of a cocaine overdose in 1984 helped inspire his effort against alcohol abuse. In an interview after the hearing, he noted that alcoholism had also been a problem for members of the Kennedy family.</p>
        <p>Producers of alcoholic beverages are now required to include warnings on the labeling of their containers, but not in their advertising. The proposed legislation would require advertisers to rotate warnings covering the risks of drinking during pregnancy, drunken driving, the addictive qualities of alcohol and other problems related to drinking. First Amendment Problem</p>
        <p>Burt Neuborne, a law professor at New York University, testified against the bill for the Association of National Advertisers, saying, "It is clear that content-specific, government-mandated speech poses a serious First Amendment problem."</p>
        <p>Such arguments have consistently swayed a majority of the Commerce Committee's members to drop the bill without even taking a vote. But after Senator Thurmond's daughter was killed, a wave of sympathy welled up in South Carolina that rippled all the way to Washington, where Mr. Hollings endorsed the bill and scheduled Thursday's hearing.</p>
        <p>Senator John C. Danforth of Missouri, the ranking Republican on the committee who has opposed the legislation, suggested a possible compromise that would require public service advertising with the same message to be broadcast separately from the commercials.</p>
        <p>At the hearing, both supporters and opponents of the bill repeatedly mentioned Senator Thurmond's daughter, making her almost as much the focus of the proceeding as the bill itself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thurmond argued that it was important to vote for the bill regardless of his daughter's death. He noted that he had long sponsored the legislation even before the accident.</p>
        <p>"Any incident of this kind," the Senator said in an interview later, "improves the prospects of passage because it comes home to people."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
