<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is Art for Our Feathered Friends or Us?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="609130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRICKLAND, CAROL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALDMAN, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF1E38F935A25756C0A965958260" item-length="1670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is Art for Our Feathered Friends or Us?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL STRICKLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRICKLAND, CAROL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a museum opened in Southampton last May its target audience was all atwitter. Visitors in their finest plumage flew in from all over to an exhibition by Roy Lichtenstein.</p>
        <p>At the opening, jazz by Charlie (Bird) Parker floated through the air. Spectators preened and chirped and fluffed their feathers. The show was never seen by critics, however, and never viewed by collectors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a museum opened in Southampton last May its target audience was all atwitter. Visitors in their finest plumage flew in from all over to an exhibition by Roy Lichtenstein.</p>
        <p>At the opening, jazz by Charlie (Bird) Parker floated through the air. Spectators preened and chirped and fluffed their feathers. The show was never seen by critics, however, and never viewed by collectors.</p>
        <p>Why? Because the new institution, soon to open for its second season, is the International Bird Museum, and the art it displays is for the birds.</p>
        <p>The museum is the invention of Paul Waldman, 56, a well-known painter who lives in Manhattan and Southampton. For five years Mr. Waldman has been constructing birdhouses as gifts for his wife, Diane, deputy director at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum.</p>
        <p>Mounted in his garden, the roosts are to birdhouses what the Trump Tower is to a Bowery flophouse. Each takes about five months to create and is composed of thousands of half-inch-long glazed bricks. Mr. Waldman adorns the structures with sculpture like a miniature Venus de Milo, copper roofs and metal whirligigs.</p>
        <p>One day when his wife asked Mr. Waldman whether he planned to build another birdhouse, he found himself replying, without forethought, "No, I'm going to build a bird museum."</p>
        <p>When Ms. Waldman asked, "What's that?" he found himself saying, "It's a museum where birds can see human art." Having said that, "all the pieces started to fall into place like little, tiny bricks and construct themselves," Mr. Waldman recalled in an interview.</p>
        <p>He then turned his inspiration into reality. Appointing himself Chairman of the Nest, he invited a roster of major figures from the art world like the dealers Leo Castelli and Arnold Glimcher to be on the advisory board of the newly hatched I.B.M., as it is informally called. A lawyer donated expertise to create a nonprofit institution. 'Get a Couple of Wings and a Beak'</p>
        <p>Last May, Mr. Waldman ran a full-page advertisement in The Southampton Press announcing the first schedule of exhibitions, including the Lichtenstein show. "Roy got a ton of calls," Mr. Waldman said, with people begging to see the art. Collectors asked Mr. Waldman whether they could take a peek inside the museum, which is mounted on a roof in Mr. Waldman's backyard. "No problem," he told them, "just get a couple of wings and a beak and fly up."</p>
        <p>Such a response indicates the project is a kind of "conceptual farce," as Donald Kuspit, an art historian at the State University at Stony Brook, has described Mr. Waldman's work. Yet in another sense, it is not really for the birds. "I consider the total concept as a work of Paul's art," said Mr. Glimcher, director of the Pace Gallery in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Waldman, who has a history of verbally improvising and then seriously following up on his impulsive outbursts, the museum offers an opportunity to create a not-for-profit-or-fame venue for art, an antidote to the greed-and-investment-driven art world of the 80's.</p>
        <p>"It celebrates the true spirit of art," said a dealer who is a museum trustee, Joseph Blum of BlumHelman Gallery. "It will be a great experience for all participants, whether they're feathered or mammals."</p>
        <p>Two art collectors, Gayle Worth and Robert Fisher, will sponsor the full-page announcement this year in The Southampton Press, at a cost of $1,500. "I hope artists will always do things for the sake of art and not just for commercialism," Ms. Worth said.</p>
        <p>"Part of the idea," Mr. Waldman said, "was to see how many people would do something that didn't have any benefit." When he suggested exhibiting to his art-world friends, they accepted with alacrity. "Every artist did something that was quite serious, with amazing integrity."  'Brancusi Would Have Loved It'</p>
        <p>"I thought it was a brilliant idea," Mr. Lichtenstein recalled. "It seemed to have its own beautiful, absurd quality." His exhibit for the museum -- which is about the size of a toaster oven -- consisted of small-scale works like "Bird in Flight," an abstract sculpture made of a tongue depresssor painted yellow. "I'm sure Brancusi would have loved it," the Pop artist said.</p>
        <p>A ceramic worm was another work, and the piece de resistance, which Mr. Lichtenstein described as "a lot of chaos and feathers," was a painting entitled "Birdica" in homage to Picasso's "Guernica."</p>
        <p>The nonmarket aspect of the project appealed to Mr. Lichtenstein. "The importance of art is in the process of doing it, in the learning experience where the artist interacts with whatever is being made," he said.</p>
        <p>Other participants last year also took their exhibitions seriously. Timothy A. Eaton, curator at the Boca Raton Museum of Art in Florida, devised an elaborate show. He mounted tiny reproductions of hummingbird paintings by the 19th-century American painter Martin Johnson Heade in ornate Victorian frames and designed a whole gallery with parquet floors, carved moldings and feeding tubes of sugar water.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eaton has gotten into the spirit to such an extent that he has opened the first branch of the I.B.M., housed in another of Mr. Waldman's birdhouses, at the Boca Raton Museum. "We're trying to serve the cultural needs of our flock," Mr. Eaton said.</p>
        <p>On his roster is Dennis Oppenheim, the contemporary artist, who embraced the idea. "Why not direct work toward some real alternative?" he asked. "Not just an alternative space, but an alternative species?"</p>
        <p>The branch, which includes not only galleries, but also a self-service restaurant called the Succulent Seed, is atop a 10-foot pole. The reaction from the human public has been "tremendous curiosity, amusement and a certain amount of befuddlement," Mr. Eaton said.</p>
        <p>"It's a flighty sort of thing," he added. "There's a lightheartedness about it among serious artists that is welcomed. The issue for humans is the concept, not the object."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Castelli, curator of a coming exhibition at Southampton, "there's some of the Dada spirit in what Paul Waldman is doing." Mr. Castelli, who has shown Mr. Waldman's work in his gallery for 20 years, said: "Only Paul could have this idea. It shows his extraordinary sense of humor."</p>
        <p>"His work has a surreal edge," Mr. Lichtenstein said.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Waldman's work is continually about dislocations and disconnections," Mr. Blum said. "He's a very surprising and inventive artist."</p>
        <p>"I knew there was something to this for myself," Mr. Waldman said. "It is my work I was really doing." 'In Many Cases Unfathomable'</p>
        <p>"Paul is no birdbrain," said Mr. Eaton, who wins the prize for the most bird jokes among those interviewed. "He's a very complicated person and a very complicated artist. His work is cryptic, in many cases unfathomable, inexplicable. That's part of the charm."</p>
        <p>Mr. Waldman's works are in the collections of institutions like the Museum of Modern Art, the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden and the Guggenheim. His show in 1991 at the Castelli included paintings like "Collaborator I," in which a nude is bound at her hands and feet by snakes and is accompanied by a tape of Maurice Chevalier's "Thank Heaven for Little Girls."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisher, who runs Fisher's antiques dealership in Sag Harbor, said he collected Mr. Waldman's work because he found its whimsical nature appealing. "He has a lot of fantasy in his work," Mr. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>The fantasy may be a reaction to the artist's unhappy childhood. He grew up on a farm in Erie, Pa., where "I came from a very dysfunctional home."</p>
        <p>"I was constantly terrified and humiliated by my parents," Mr. Waldman recalled.</p>
        <p>At 15 he ran away from home and ended up in New York, where body-building became his path to survival. By the time Mr. Waldman was 16 he had broken two world records for weight lifting and was voted as the Most Ideal High School Physique in America. In 1954 he was Mr. New York City.</p>
        <p>That career abruptly halted when "I discovered a bakery." He went to art school and began painting full-time when he was 21.</p>
        <p>"I've always joked about what I would do when I'm dictator of the world," Mr. Waldman said in an effort to explain why he had founded the museum. "The International Bird Museum gave me that spot. I could invite all these people and see how they behave."  'The Homes I Never Had'</p>
        <p>For Mr. Waldman, whose art is autobiographical and grounded in Freudian therapy, it was a chance to "watch the biographies of other people unfold." The participants reaffirmed his faith in them by responding to the endeavor with what he calls poetry and purity.</p>
        <p>In a sense the birdhouses "are the homes I never had," Mr. Waldman said. They are his private world, operating by his rules. They are also his manifesto that "a museum should be free," he said. Despite the budget deficits that plague museums, "art is always an expression of kindness and love, and you should never charge for that."</p>
        <p>The museum is "not anti-art," he insisted, saying: "It's terribly pro-art. It asks artists to remember when they just made things without pressure to sell. It reminds people to play."</p>
        <p>He hopes to expand, adding a museum each year for the next five years. A branch at the American Academy in Rome has been suggested to serve its international clientele. He then plans to take out an advertisement in a national publication announcing the existence of seven museums "with lots of love."</p>
        <p>Jackie Winsor, whose exhibition of new work will open the Long Island season, explained why she believed in the museum's mission. She cited the folk tale of a young prince enchanted by a bird's warbling its silvery song deep in the forest. When the prince caged the bird and took it to his palace, however, the songbird died, and the woods were silent.</p>
        <p>"The bird is happiness, but in New York City we don't have the song of birds," she said. "Something in us dies. The meaning of the bird museum is based on supporting your own song. We're not just taking care of some starving species. Who is the starving species? It's ourselves."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
