<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial TV Starting on East End</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATIONS AND NETWORKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TV-23 (SOUTHAMPTON, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHIMIZZI, ERNEST</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHIMIZZI, GREGORY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUMMINGS, MARY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DA133DF93AA35753C1A962958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial TV Starting on East End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY CUMMINGS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUMMINGS, MARY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A YEAR ago Gregory and Ernest Schimizzi purchased a low-power television station from the Channel America Network. Yesterday the brothers from Brooklyn were scheduled to go on the air with TV-23 Southampton, the first commercial television station intended specifically for East End viewers.</p>
        <p>A first for the Hamptons, the station, with a signal that will reach the five East End towns with 24-hour-a-day programming, is also a first for its owners. TV-23 is the initial foray into the broadcast end of the business for the brothers, whose company, Video Voice, has been involved in television production and distribution in Manhattan since 1977.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A YEAR ago Gregory and Ernest Schimizzi purchased a low-power television station from the Channel America Network. Yesterday the brothers from Brooklyn were scheduled to go on the air with TV-23 Southampton, the first commercial television station intended specifically for East End viewers.</p>
        <p>A first for the Hamptons, the station, with a signal that will reach the five East End towns with 24-hour-a-day programming, is also a first for its owners. TV-23 is the initial foray into the broadcast end of the business for the brothers, whose company, Video Voice, has been involved in television production and distribution in Manhattan since 1977.</p>
        <p>A few days before TV-23 was to start with coverage of an all-day meeting in East Hampton of citizens, officials and others interested in forming a new East End county, Gregory Schimizzi, 45, and his brother Ernest, 43, discussed their station in the studio of Channel 27, LTV, public access in East Hampton. The brothers rent space at LTV.</p>
        <p>As the sole investors in TV-23, the Schimizzis said, they have put close to $1 million into the venture.</p>
        <p>As his brother consulted workers installing equipment and connections to allow TV-23 to send its digitally encoded stereo signal along fiber-optic cables to a transmission tower, Gregory Schimizzi, a part-time resident of East Hampton since 1986, said: "Our main focus is marketing. Although we're here on the eastern end of Long Island we're part of the New York market."</p>
        <p>According to the Audience Demographic Index, he added, "there's no separation between this market and Manhattan." He and his brother felt that the area was ready for a commercial station, he said, and last year they seized an opportunity to be part of the Low Power Television Service. The service was created by the Federal Communication Commission in 1982 to increase community stations.</p>
        <p>TV-23, one of a limited number of unused frequencies made available by the F.C.C., is licensed to use up to the maximum for low-power television, 1,000 watts.</p>
        <p>The station will not be carried on cable at first, though the brothers hope that Cablevision will eventually include TV-23 in its basic package. The programs will reach viewers via what is known as over-the-air broadcasting, or cellular television.</p>
        <p>"This means that we're free over the air and available to anyone who has a television set," said Mr. Schimizzi. A small hoop-shaped antenna has to be attached to the back of the set to receive the signal. From the tower in East Hampton, the signal carries up to 35 miles.</p>
        <p>The emphasis, the brothers stress in a brochure, "will be on live new programs." The goal, Mr. Schimizzi added, is to entertain and inform year-round East End residents as well as tourists who want to know "what to do, where to go, what to see, what to wear, what's happening."</p>
        <p>He said the station would not try to expand beyond the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>LTV provides locally oriented noncommercial programs in East Hampton. Of the two commercial stations that regularly cover the Island, News 12 in Woodbury, serves the whole Island and TV-55, licensed in Riverhead, devotes a small part of its programming to East End issues on its two half-hour news programs.</p>
        <p>TV-23 plans to devote the bulk of its programming to local people, places and issues, according to Mr. Schimizzi. But it would be silly, he added, "to think that we could go 24 hours a day with just events that happen here on the East End."</p>
        <p>"To flesh out the day," he said, TV-23 will offer news, music videos and a political call-in program from Washington. He added that as a CNN affiliate his station would show "CNN Headline News" as well as live coverage of breaking news. The divided screen of Bloomberg Direct TV, with its simultaneous anchors, running stock ticker, sports scores and other bulletins, will also become familiar to TV-23 viewers, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schimizzi said he had received many suggestions for local programs. Ernest Schimizzi said, "We've received queries from people who want to do a cooking show, people who want to do a home-improvement type show and news."</p>
        <p>The singularity of the East End means that there were no models to study when planning TV-23, he said.  "This is not your usual hometown," he said, adding that resort television in the Hamptons had "pretty significant" marketing possibilities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schimizzi said that the station would begin operations with 30 advertisers and that his crews would help sponsors produce commercials.</p>
        <p>Programs like "A Walk Down Main Street," which will give advertisers opportunities to discuss their products and services with a strolling correspondent, represent another approach. "What we're gearing for is the small-business owners of the East End," Mr. Schimizzi said, "the wineries, the boating shops, all the people who don't really have a voice yet in the traditional television market."</p>
        <p>He would not release figures, but called the advertising rates extremely competitive, falling in the range of radio commercials.</p>
        <p>Packaging programs from glamour spots is another option. A series featuring a chef from a chic restaurant, for example, might have wide audience appeal, Mr. Schimizzi suggested, adding, "Our background is distribution." A series like that might be distributed across the United States, "and maybe even internationally," he said.</p>
        <p>The period from October and to Jan. 1 will be devoted to "fine tuning" programming, Gregory Schimizzi said. The brothers also made it clear that they would be devoting attention to placing TV-23 in the Cablevision package. The brothers stressed that being carried would be important for the success of TV-23, because more than 70 percent of the houses in the area have cable.</p>
        <p>"We feel that this is a necessity for us, because so many people do get their television with cable," Ernest Schimizzi said, adding that although Cablevision was not obligated to carry TV-23, Cablevision had not refused TV-23's bid. In its favor, he added, is that TV-23 will be provided free to Cablevision. "We've had excellent dealings with them," he said.  "We're tenants of Cablevision at their tower and we're their tenants with respect to fiber optics. So they have a vested interest."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
