<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bonilla's Hot Hand Loses to a Full Glove</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="612444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CINCINNATI REDS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREY, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONILLA, BOBBY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D61530F932A05756C0A965958260" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bonilla's Hot Hand Loses to a Full Glove</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER FREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREY, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Bonilla blasted a home run into the visitors' bullpen on his second at-bat yesterday. He did it again in the sixth inning, this time with a runner on base.</p>
        <p>And so when Bonilla came to the plate with two outs, the bases loaded and the Mets down three runs in the bottom of the seventh inning, the Shea Stadium masses rose to their feet. They expected nothing less than another homer from their prodigal son.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bobby Bonilla blasted a home run into the visitors' bullpen on his second at-bat yesterday. He did it again in the sixth inning, this time with a runner on base.</p>
        <p>And so when Bonilla came to the plate with two outs, the bases loaded and the Mets down three runs in the bottom of the seventh inning, the Shea Stadium masses rose to their feet. They expected nothing less than another homer from their prodigal son.</p>
        <p>This time, though, Bonilla could only come close.</p>
        <p>With the count 3-0 in his favor, he took a monstrous swing and sent the ball flying to deep center field. The whole Mets bench rose to watch the ball's path, many players convinced it was out of the park. But an airborne Bobby Kelly grabbed it with his glove, just before his body slammed against the blue-padded outfield wall.</p>
        <p>Kelly's spectacular fielding play guaranteed that the big moment in this game would belong not to Bonilla, but to Cincinnati's Joe Oliver, who launched a two-out, three-run homer off starter Pete Schourek in the top of the seventh. Those runs put the Reds ahead for good in what would be an 8-4 victory. Green Takes Blame</p>
        <p>The Mets, who were 1-2 against Davey Johnson's Reds this weekend, have not won back-to-back games since April 16 and 17.</p>
        <p>"They got as many big shots as we did today," said Bonilla, who had three homers over the weekend and now has 12 for the year. "And they got the big one by Oliver. It was a huge hit. Huge."</p>
        <p>Schourek threw the fateful pitch to Oliver, but Mets Manager Dallas Green took the blame for the home run. With two outs and a runner on second, Green had called for Schourek to intentionally walk Reggie Sanders to get to Oliver.</p>
        <p>"I just walked the wrong guy, that's all," Green said. "I make the choice to do it and I've got to take the responsibility for that." Gave Him Some Rope</p>
        <p>Oliver's homer, which came on Schourek's first pitch to him, was the fifth in the game. In addition to his shot and Bonilla's two, Mets rookie Tim Bogar hit a bases-empty home run in the third inning and Barry Larkin had a two-run blast off Schourek in the fifth to give Cincinnati a 4-2 lead.</p>
        <p>"You want to see a young pitcher get himself out of those problems," Green said, explaining why he left Schourek in the game for seven full innings that were marked by 12 hits. "You don't want to be always getting them out of problems by going to the bullpen."</p>
        <p>Cincinnati earned its first run after a bizarre third-inning rundown ended unhappily for the Mets. Five Mets touched the ball a combined total of eight times as a possible double play turned into a potential triple play, but ended up a single out -- thanks to a debatable call. Jeff Kent appeared to tag Jacob Brumfield in the base path between second and third, but Brumfield was ruled safe, and he scored when Bip Roberts grounded to second base.</p>
        <p>"We made it look ugly, but I did get him," Kent said. Doesn't Hear Crowd</p>
        <p>Bonilla tied the game at 2-2 with his first homer, and at 4-4 with the second. He got both his blasts off the Reds' starter, Tom Browning -- Bonilla is now hitting .409 lifetime against him -- and the second earned Browning the hook.</p>
        <p>Right-hander Bobby Ayala was on the mound when Bonilla came to the plate in the seventh, and Bonilla said he had decided not to pull the ball, but to just try to get it over Larkin's head. Instead, he airmailed it Kelly, the former Yankee, whose fielding prowess made such an impression on Bonilla that he did not even hear the crowd give him a standing ovation on his way out to right field for the top of the eighth.</p>
        <p>"I didn't really pay attention," said Bonilla, the target of frequent fan boos. "I was thinking about the great catch by Kelly. It was ooomph. He's a terrific center fielder." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DALLAS GREEN said after the game that he did not expect BRET SABERHAGEN to pitch Monday in Chicago and that Saberhagen, who has been suffering from acute bronchitis, would probably not be ready until after New York's three-game series against the Cubs. "My sense is he's not going to be strong enough to get the job done," Green said. . . . Green benched HOWARD JOHNSON for the second straight game, but used him in a double-switch in the seventh inning. Johnson, who is out of the lineup because of his hitting troubles, batted twice -- once drawing a walk and once being called out on strikes. Green would not say whether Johnson would start at third in Chicago. . . . CHICO WALKER broke an 0-for-23 slump with his pinch-hit single in the bottom of the seventh and EDDIE MURRAY broke an 0-for-19 streak with a sixth-inning single that put him on base for BOBBY BONILLA's second home run. . . . TIM BOGAR's home run was his first in the majors. . . . ROB DIBBLE, the Reds' closer, made his first appearance since April 21 and got the three outs in the bottom of the ninth. Dibble, who had been out with a broken forearm, was activated Friday afternoon.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
