<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heady Fittipaldi Picks Right Time to Step on It</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="612454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANAPOLIS 500 (AUTO RACE)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FITTIPALDI, EMERSON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUYENDYK, ARIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIANO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indianapolis 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD1030F932A05756C0A965958260" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heady Fittipaldi Picks Right Time to Step on It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH SIANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIANO, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day that required smart driving as well as aggressive driving, Emerson Fittipaldi blended both with such skill this afternoon that he was able to win his second Indianapolis 500 in a race that may have been the most competitive in the event's 77 runnings.</p>
        <p>Fittipaldi, a 46-year-old Brazilian who lives much of the time in Miami, took the lead in his Penske-Chevy on a restart on the 185th lap, out-accelerating Nigel Mansell of England and Arie Luyendyk of the Netherlands, both in Lola-Fords, into Turn 1. Fittipaldi held it from there, even on another restart with five laps to go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day that required smart driving as well as aggressive driving, Emerson Fittipaldi blended both with such skill this afternoon that he was able to win his second Indianapolis 500 in a race that may have been the most competitive in the event's 77 runnings.</p>
        <p>Fittipaldi, a 46-year-old Brazilian who lives much of the time in Miami, took the lead in his Penske-Chevy on a restart on the 185th lap, out-accelerating Nigel Mansell of England and Arie Luyendyk of the Netherlands, both in Lola-Fords, into Turn 1. Fittipaldi held it from there, even on another restart with five laps to go.</p>
        <p>He held on to beat Luyendyk, who was second, by 2.862 seconds, and Mansell, who was not far behind in third. Also within car lengths of the top three were Raul Boesel of Brazil in fourth and Mario Andretti in fifth, both in Lola-Fords. All told, the top 10 finishers were on the same lap as Fittipaldi, who led only 16 laps in all and whose winning average speed was 157.207 miles per hour.</p>
        <p>Before the race, the drivers were speculating that changes in the track layout at the Indianapolis Motor Speedway would make it hard to pass today. As it turned out, some of the cut-and-thrust maneuvers on the track made Manhattan traffic seem sedate.</p>
        <p>Fittipaldi, who also won the event in 1989, was the 12th different leader in this race, breaking the record of 10 set in 1980. The lead changed hands 21 times. So competitive was the race that even Kevin Cogan, the slowest qualifier, was able to lead four laps.</p>
        <p>The Brazilian said this victory was the most important of his career -- even more so than his 1989 victory -- "because of the time of my career now, my age now."</p>
        <p>And with that age came wisdom. "I think I am able to drive better now than when I was 25 years old," Fittipaldi said. "I have experience."</p>
        <p>He, along with all the other drivers, needed that today.</p>
        <p>After last year's crash-filled Indy 500, race officials and the speedway decided to slow the cars and make them safer by narrowing the turns by 12 feet and reducing the aerodynamic devices on the cars. They achieved that goal, as only four cars crashed today and there were no serious injuries.</p>
        <p>The changes also made it more difficult to pass. It took patience and intelligence to survive today, but the drivers seemed up to it. A total of 24 of the 33 starters finished, and none was more than eight laps behind over the 200-lap distance.</p>
        <p>"I was very impressed with the quality of driving from everybody," the winner said. Brains and Aggressiveness</p>
        <p>But no one was more impressive than Fittipaldi.</p>
        <p>"The guy with the most brains won today," said Eddie Cheever, who finished 16th after starting 33d and last.</p>
        <p>"He drove an outstanding race," said Roger Penske, Fittipaldi's car owner, who got his ninth Indy victory in 25 years of coming here. "He won this race himself."</p>
        <p>"To have a run on the guy ahead of you, you had to have the right timing," Fittipaldi said, explaining the need for patience and skill in passing. "But I think there was some aggressive driving sometimes."</p>
        <p>The most aggressive move, probably, was the one that won him the race. Mansell Misses a Beat</p>
        <p>After a yellow flag to tow in Lyn St. James's disabled car, the green came back out at the start of the 185th lap. At that point, Mansell was in the lead, but this was the first oval track ever for the defending Formula One world champion. And it was that inexperience that probably accounted for his failure to master one of the major tricks of American oval-track racing: hitting a restart just right.</p>
        <p>The rules say that once the pace car pulls off, the drivers can start racing again. Anticipating restarts can win races, as it did for Bobby Rahal here in 1986 and for Fittipaldi today.</p>
        <p>In this case, both Fittipaldi and Luyendyk were on the gas faster than Mansell, who must have been shocked to see both Luyendyk and Fittipaldi flashing by him as the three crossed the start-finish line and headed to Turn 1. 'I Messed Up'</p>
        <p>By the time they got there, the order was Fittipaldi, Luyendyk and Mansell. It stayed that way even after a final restart on lap 195, which came after Mansell brushed the wall in Turn 2.</p>
        <p>"I messed up a few things today," said an otherwise happy Mansell after the race. "I don't mind admitting it."</p>
        <p>Once Fittipaldi got ahead, he couldn't be caught. "The car was dialed in," he said. "We had the best set of tires, the balance of the car was perfect, and I was in clean air."</p>
        <p>By that, he meant he didn't have turbulent air from cars ahead of him making his car handle unpredictably. That helped him outrun Luyendyk to the finish.</p>
        <p>"I was worried about Luyendyk in that situation because he has a lot of experience," Penske said of Fittipaldi's winning restart, "but Emerson did a great job." Compliment From Luyendyk</p>
        <p>Luyendyk, who said the turbulent air from Fittipaldi's car kept him from challenging him at the end, gave Fittipaldi credit for playing the final restart perfectly.</p>
        <p>"He slowed the field down to such a slow speed that I had to go back to second gear," said Luyendyk, the 1990 Indy winner. "And he accelerated when his car was in a straight line, and I was still running through Turn 3."</p>
        <p>Fittipaldi got a big assist today from a not-so-patient piece of driving by his 24-year-old teammate, Paul Tracy of Canada.</p>
        <p>After 86 laps, Fittipaldi made a pit stop earlier than the leaders under a green flag. Two laps later, a yellow flag came out, allowing everybody else to stop without losing too much time. On the restart on lap 93, Fittipaldi was a few seconds away from being lapped by Andretti, which would have severely hurt Fittipaldi's chances.</p>
        <p>But on lap 95 another yellow came out, allowing Fittipaldi to get back to the pack and remain on the lead lap, when Tracy crashed while trying to get by Scott Brayton on the bottom of Turn 3. Tracy seemed to commit himself too far into the corner, and Brayton moved down in front of him, clipping Tracy's front wings and sending him into the wall. Tracy was unhurt and Brayton finished sixth.</p>
        <p>Andretti led 72 laps, more than anyone else, and was ahead with 26 laps to go. Andretti, Mansell's teammate, said his last pit stop spoiled what could have been his second victory, and his first here since 1969. The rear tires that were put on didn't have the proper inflation differential. This difference, called "stagger," helps steer the cars through the four left-hand turns.  AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
