<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.M.S. Merger Plan Details Emerge as Dispute Widens</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="669255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMERGENCY MEDICAL TREATMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMBULANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIRE DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D8163BF934A25751C0A962958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.M.S. Merger Plan Details Emerge as Dispute Widens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giuliani administration's plans to merge the Emergency Medical Service into the city's Fire Department will involve some crews' operating out of city firehouses as a way of reducing the time it takes to respond to emergencies, top city officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Although officials are still working out the details of the plan, they say they hope to have the merger in effect within the next fiscal year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giuliani administration's plans to merge the Emergency Medical Service into the city's Fire Department will involve some crews' operating out of city firehouses as a way of reducing the time it takes to respond to emergencies, top city officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Although officials are still working out the details of the plan, they say they hope to have the merger in effect within the next fiscal year.</p>
        <p>As part of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's broad goals to encourage competition in delivery of city services, the administration is considering offering contracts to operate ambulance service in some parts in the city, the officials said. Such a plan would force E.M.S. to bid for contracts against private companies or hospitals that operate ambulances.</p>
        <p>Details of the proposal emerged only a few days after E.M.S. workers were embroiled in a dispute over the handling of a case in Queens last Sunday in which a baby girl died as her mother went into labor. Two E.M.S. workers were suspended after officials determined that they had failed to promptly evaluate the mother's condition and that they had made her walk to the ambulance.  'Underscores' Problems</p>
        <p>The baby's death has not accelerated or changed the administration's plan, which has been in the works since the Mayor's election and was among the initiatives included in his preliminary budget plan earlier this month, said Richard J. Schwartz, the Mayor's senior adviser for policy.</p>
        <p>"It's only a factor in that it underscores some of the problems that people presently detect in the way E.M.S. is managed," he said.</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Peter J. Powers said a merger would allow the city to deploy workers better, training firefighters in emergency medical care and possibly even training E.M.S. workers to assist in fighting fires. He said a merger would also allow the city to respond more quickly to cardiac-arrest cases, where a response of less than four and a half minutes can prevent irreversible brain damage.</p>
        <p>The idea of merging the city's ambulances, now under the Health and Hospitals Corporation, into the Fire Department is not new. Andrew J. Stein, former City Council President, and others often raised the issue during the Koch administration amid a series of cases in which E.M.S. crews took an hour or more to respond. Fire departments in cities around the nation also operate ambulance services.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers said many details are still unresolved, including whether a merger would require legislative approval or whether there was resistance from the E.M.S. workers' union.</p>
        <p>But he said Mayor Giuliani believed that the Fire Department could manage the emergency service system more efficiently, improving the time it took for ambulances to respond to emergencies and reducing administrative overhead. "We really feel strongly we'll get better service," Mr. Powers said. "If you can save costs, that's an added benefit."</p>
        <p>The Uniformed Firefighters Association, which opposed taking on emergency medical duties in the past, supports the plan, its president, Thomas Von Essen, said yesterday.  More Than Repainting</p>
        <p>Tony J. Bernardo, president of Local 2507 of District Council 37, which represents E.M.S. workers, said the union did not necessarily oppose a merger, but he urged caution and said such plans needed to be carefully thought out. "Painting all the ambulances red doesn't do it," he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alexander E. Kuehl, director of emergency medical programs at New York Hospital, who was medical director of E.M.S. under Mayor Edward I. Koch, said a proposed merger reflected what other cities have done and what medical experts have recommended. "Mayor Giuliani recognizes that the city needs a coordinated, efficient, compassionate E.M.S. system," said Dr. Kuehl, a health policy adviser to Mr. Giuliani during the campaign and the transition. "The involvement of the Fire Department is critical to that."</p>
        <p>David L. Diggs, the E.M.S. director, declined to comment on the plan. Much Larger Volume</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers said the primary argument behind a merger would be the Fire Department's faster response time. The Fire Department responds to emergency calls citywide in about 5 minutes, while the emergency service average is 8.5 minutes. Yet E.M.S. handles a much larger volume of calls: 1.2 million a year, compared with 373,000 for the Fire Department.</p>
        <p>Of the 200 largest cities in the country, 51 percent operate emergency services through fire departments alone or supplemented by private ambulance services, said the Emergency Care Information Center, a research company in Carlsbad, Calif. Twenty-four percent of the cities have contracts with private companies, while only 16 percent, including New York, Boston and San Francisco, have independent municipal services.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey A. Cady, a research director for the center, said that while a number of cities were rethinking how best to provide emergency services, including using more private companies, no model was inherently better about having a service under the fire department or independent.</p>
        <p>The family of a pregnant woman, Tracy Ortega, charged that an ambulance crew had argued with them for half an hour on Sunday over whether to take her to New York Hospital Medical Center in Queens, which was closest, or to St. John's Hospital, where her obstetrician was based.</p>
        <p>An autopsy by the Medical Examiner's office found that the baby died because of an abnormality in her umbilical cord, but the autopsy did not conclude whether a delay contributed to the baby's death. The case is now under review by the city's Department of Investigation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
