<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diabetes, Heat and Irwin Aren't Enough to Stop Green</title>
    <meta content="Y05GOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/05/sports/golf/05GOLF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1413707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lightpath Long Island Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Hubert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, Hubert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Irwin, Hale</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC133BF936A3575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diabetes, Heat and Irwin Aren't Enough to Stop Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Diabetes, Heat and Irwin Aren't Enough to Stop Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>JERICHO, N.Y., Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hubert Green wins Lightpath Long Island Classic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hubert Green had given himself an insulin shot in the stomach after nine holes, enough to control his diabetes. Or so he hoped. He had not eaten since 9:15 a.m. and the thermometer was approaching 90 degrees as he found himself tied with Hale Irwin on what was supposed to be the final hole of the Lightpath Long Island Classic.</p>
        <p>But the tournament dragged on for another hour -- seven holes of sudden-death play that ended only when Green sank a 25-foot birdie putt, while Irwin's chip shot from below the green rolled 3 inches wide. It was the longest playoff on the Senior Tour this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hubert Green sank a 25-foot birdie putt to end a seven-hole sudden-death playoff against Hale Irwin and win the Lightpath Long Island Classic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hubert Green had given himself an insulin shot in the stomach after nine holes, enough to control his diabetes. Or so he hoped. He had not eaten since 9:15 a.m. and the thermometer was approaching 90 degrees as he found himself tied with Hale Irwin on what was supposed to be the final hole of the Lightpath Long Island Classic.</p>
        <p>But the tournament dragged on for another hour -- seven holes of sudden-death play that ended only when Green sank a 25-foot birdie putt, while Irwin's chip shot from below the green rolled 3 inches wide. It was the longest playoff on the Senior Tour this year.</p>
        <p>''It gets to be an ordeal,'' Green said after his victory, which was worth $255,000, the biggest payday in his career. His victory was set up when he birdied the 16th hole to creep a stroke behind the leader. Then Irwin, who had led since the second hole, bogeyed No. 17, and they were tied.</p>
        <p>This was the fifth time that Irwin, a three-time United States Open champion, has been in a Senior Tour playoff. He has lost all of them, including two in the last three weeks. But he pocketed $149,600 for his second-place finish.</p>
        <p>Green and Irwin, who started play today tied for the lead, both shot 68 for a three-day total of 199 (14 under par). Morris Hatalsky and Allen Doyle were tied for third at 202.</p>
        <p>If it was not exactly a slugfest, the sight of these two old pros (Green also has a United States Open title) stirred memories. Neither would wilt, and neither backed off. After all, these were golfers who competed against Nicklaus, Watson and Trevino when all were in their primes.</p>
        <p>Each playoff hole was a two-putt affair until the golfers returned to the 18th. It was the fourth time today they had played the hole, a 167-yard par-3. They were there in regulation, then played it three more times in the sudden-death playoff.</p>
        <p>By then, he later admitted, Irwin knew it was Green's tournament. Irwin faulted himself for not making a 5-foot birdie putt on No. 16 that could have put him two strokes ahead, then for blowing the lead on the 17th.</p>
        <p>''I think that gave all the momentum to Hubert,'' Irwin said. ''I can't believe his putt went in on 16 and mine didn't.''</p>
        <p>Irwin sounded slightly distressed that he was only $149,600 richer than he had been at the start of the weekend. ''To come out with second, that's delightful, but a waste of a great week of golf,'' he said. ''I was impressed with myself tee to green.''</p>
        <p>The par-71 course at the Meadow Brook Club played to 6,840 yards. Many of the golfers had been concerned with the unexpected turns and bumps on the greens. Even Green seemed mildly surprised that his winning putt went in.</p>
        <p>''It was supposed to break left, so I thought I'd hit it to the right,'' he said. In fact, he played the shot perfectly. Then again, Green said that his best putt on Saturday -- on No. 18, it turned out -- did not go where he expected. For failing to make that 6-footer, he got a bogey.</p>
        <p>All of which made Green thankful for his first victory on the Senior Tour since 2000. When he was asked whether he had checked his blood today, Green replied, ''No, I bleed enough on the golf course.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>CHI CHI RODRIGUEZ knew he did not have much of a chance by the time he reached the second hole of the final round. ''My pants cost more money than I'm going to earn in this tournament,'' he said. Rodriguez finished 74th in the field of 78 and earned $1,122. . . . The 60-ish crowd had 6 players among the 21 leaders teeing off on the final day. Two finished in the top 10: DALE DOUGLASS and MIKE HILL, who finished seven strokes back. . . . Before teeing off, HUBERT GREEN tossed a glove to a boy who was leaning on the ropes. After the first hole, the youngster asked Green to autograph it. ''You've got to follow the the rules,'' said Green, who signed it anyway. . . . Last year's winner, BOBBY WADKINS, finished eight strokes back at 207 with a final-round 68.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
