<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feminists And Darwin: Scientists Try Closing the Gap</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="694885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANGIER, NATALIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOWATY, PATRICIA ADAIR (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDA133DF932A15755C0A962958260" item-length="2297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feminists And Darwin: Scientists Try Closing the Gap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATALIE ANGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANGIER, NATALIE</byline>
      <dateline>ATHENS, Ga.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF there is any merit to F. Scott Fitzgerald's familiar observation that the mark of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two contradictory ideas in your head without cracking up, then there were a lot of very sane prodigies walking the halls of the University of Georgia last week. They were the participants in an unusual scientific conference called "Evolutionary Biology and Feminism," two terms that the meeting's organizer said had never before been paired under a single symposium rubric.</p>
        <p>And small wonder, for the disciplines have often been at loggerheads. Many feminists have eyed certain aspects of Darwinian thought with deep suspicion, particularly when evolutionary explanations have been marshaled to explain human characteristics like the inequality of the sexes in most cultures around the world, or boys' supposed superiority over girls in mathematics. To many feminists, the relentless search for an innate basis to complex human behaviors smacks of a quest for easy answers -- and handy excuses for the status quo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF there is any merit to F. Scott Fitzgerald's familiar observation that the mark of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two contradictory ideas in your head without cracking up, then there were a lot of very sane prodigies walking the halls of the University of Georgia last week. They were the participants in an unusual scientific conference called "Evolutionary Biology and Feminism," two terms that the meeting's organizer said had never before been paired under a single symposium rubric.</p>
        <p>And small wonder, for the disciplines have often been at loggerheads. Many feminists have eyed certain aspects of Darwinian thought with deep suspicion, particularly when evolutionary explanations have been marshaled to explain human characteristics like the inequality of the sexes in most cultures around the world, or boys' supposed superiority over girls in mathematics. To many feminists, the relentless search for an innate basis to complex human behaviors smacks of a quest for easy answers -- and handy excuses for the status quo.</p>
        <p>For their part, evolutionary scientists, like researchers in other fields, cherish the notion that science at its best is dispassionate and as free as possible of prejudices. They fear that those who approach their work from a feminist or any other ideological perspective are bound to seek out in nature only what they wish to find, and to reject observations that disturb their political cosmology.</p>
        <p>But for two days last week, top-flight biologists of both sexes who happen to be, in most cases, avowed feminists or sympathetic to the cause, put aside their qualms about labels and asked the sort of questions that scientists normally shun. They asked whether modern evolutionary theory has helped, hindered or made no difference at all to feminism, which as one of the scientists defined it is simply women's quest for equality and elbow room.</p>
        <p>Conversely, they wondered whether feminist thinking has helped or obstructed biologists' efforts to understand the mechanisms of nature -- human or otherwise.</p>
        <p>Dr. Patricia Adair Gowaty of the University of Georgia, the organizer of the conference and a field biologist known for her groundbreaking studies of infidelity among supposedly monogamous birds, said she put the meeting together because feminism and evolutionary theory were the two dominant intellectual themes in her life, and she wanted to try collating them in some way.</p>
        <p>"There's a pejorative meaning to the term feminist evolutionist," she told the audience. "Some of you may fear that you'll be seen as doing science in the interest of politics, rather than for science's sake. My defense to that has always been, I do science for science's sake, but being aware of the biases I have I believe makes me a better scientist."</p>
        <p>With few exceptions, the scientists did not come to denounce modern evolutionary biology. To the contrary, many expressed a healthy respect for the power of Darwinian thought as a framework for interpreting the behaviors and motivations of all creatures, including humans. They accepted that organisms inherit a complex mix of physical, behavioral and social characteristics, some of them useful for survival, others for attracting a mate, still others for nurturing offspring; and they believed it a noble goal to explore how and why a particular trait has evolved.  The Origin Of the Specious</p>
        <p>Because most of the participants were both scientifically mainstream and open to feminism, there were few verbal fireworks at the meeting, no blistering charges of sexism or fascism, no buckets of water dumped on anybody's head (as happened during at least one highly politicized biology meeting in the past).</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the scientists did denounce the ways in which evolutionary biology has been used against women. They criticized many of the comparisons that have been made between the behaviors of humans and those of apes, lions, pigeons, scorpionflies, comparisons that often seemed to confirm stereotypes about femininity and masculinity.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zuleyma Tang-Martinez of the University of Missouri pointed out that a number of evolutionary biologists have sought to understand innate human tendencies by looking at gorillas and chimpanzees, where the males are dominant and quite aggressive toward females; but such researchers could as easily choose to look at other primates, like lemurs and bonobos, where male aggression toward females is low. "Why do we assume that male aggression is the primate norm, while nonaggression must be explained as the exception to the rule?" Dr. Tang-Martinez asked.</p>
        <p>Others condemned simple formulations like the idea that evolutionary pressures have turned men into hopeless sexual profligates (because men want to spread their seed around) and women into coy monogamists (because they want to keep a steady mate at home to help them raise the child). They said these and other narrow characterizations of behavior arose partly as a result of the historically masculine flavor of evolutionary biology. But with so many women working in the discipline now, a few new spices are being added to the mix.</p>
        <p>Many scientists, for example, talked about how common female infidelity is in the animal kingdom. Dr. Judith Stamps of the University of California at Davis talked of female birds that cheat on their mates and offered a novel hypothesis of why the females seek to philander with males that themselves have spouses at home. The standard explanation for so-called extra-pair copulations is that those females who are mated to disappointing males covet outside liaisons with higher-quality males as a way of gaining superior genes for their offspring -- while still keeping the inferior male around to help rear the brood.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Stamps presented what she called a divorce-remarriage explanation. The female bird may be mating with a desirable though already "married" male not to get his sperm, she said, but because the male may be a better parent and have a better home territory. It may be that someday the superior male will either lose or drop his current wife, at which point the male may remember his recent tryst and accept the old lover as his new housemate, a position that brings with it all the benefits of terrific real estate.</p>
        <p>"There's more to copulation than a transfer of sperm," said Dr. Stamps.  "These females may be thinking of their futures."</p>
        <p>As preliminary support for the idea, she said, recent studies with blue-footed booby birds suggest that once a male has mated with a female, he will be far less aggressive toward her later on and less likely to resist her forays into his terrain.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jeanne Altmann of the University of Chicago, a renowned primatologist, discussed how female baboons living in the same group seem to synchronize their ovulatory cycles -- much as women living in the same dorm rooms have been shown to menstruate at the same time of month.</p>
        <p>Dr. Altmann proposed that the female baboons do so to prevent any single male from being able to monopolize all the fertile females. It is simply too much to expect one male to keep watch on more than a single female in heat and prevent competing suitors from approaching the others. Thus, the females can make their choices of mates and not fall under the dominion of one alpha male.  'Corrective' Lenses For Viewing Nature</p>
        <p>Most of the researchers agreed that feminism's clearest contribution to evolutionary biology has been to encourage researchers of both sexes to consider nature from a female's-eye view, offering a much-needed corrective after centuries of naturalists' obsessions with the antics and motivations of the male.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcy F. Lawton of the University of Alabama in Huntsville presented an amusing example of two otherwise excellent field workers who were led astray, Dr. Lawton said, because they accepted without question the often-cited wisdom that male hierarchies determine the structure of socially dwelling animals.</p>
        <p>In a lengthy report of their observations of a group of communally dwelling pinyon jay birds, Dr. Lawton said, the researchers described how they had tried valiantly to learn which was the alpha bird, which the runner-up, and so forth. But the male birds proved so peaceable and uncompetitive that the scientists admitted they had difficulty making out who was in charge.</p>
        <p>They set up experiments to force the birds to compete, for example, by giving them tiny food dishes and seeing who outmaneuvered whom for a meal. But even then, the most one male bird would do to the other was give it a dirty look, or maybe make a slight move in the contender's direction.</p>
        <p>"This is not exactly nature red in tooth and claw," said Dr. Lawton, who prepared her dissection of the field study with a colleague, Dr. William R. Garstka. After many hundreds of experimental manipulations, the researchers still had difficulty pinning down the male hierarchy.</p>
        <p>The jay watchers did finally observe extreme acts of aggression and competition among their subjects -- birds locking talons in combat and stabbing at one another with their beaks; feathers flying while the furiously entangled pairs fell to the ground. But these incidents turned out to be battles not between male birds, but between females, with the aggression occurring just as the females were reaching hormonal readiness for breeding.</p>
        <p>After noting the violent rituals in their report and dubbing the events "pre-breeding syndrome" in a humorous comparison to premenstrual syndrome, the scientists returned to their search for the elusive alpha male and thought no more about female aggression. Never, said Dr. Lawton, did they consider the possibility that the female jays might be the ones with a dominance hierarchy at the core of the birds' social system.</p>
        <p>"In this case, the mask of theory hid the face of nature," she argued.  The role of females in the pinyon jay society remains to be clarified.</p>
        <p>Dr. John Maynard Smith of the University of Sussex, one of the high priests of evolutionary biology who described himself as a theoretical feminist, said that when he was studying fruit flies 40 years ago, he and his colleagues determined that the production of eggs was quite costly to the female and ended up taking a toll on her health and longevity. By contrast, the male's tiny sperm cells had always been considered one of nature's cheapest resources, and their supposed cheapness the reason males can be cavalier about sex. But Dr. Smith admitted he had never thought to explore whether semen production was in fact as cost-free as everybody had assumed.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, scientists have lately determined in experiments with fruit flies and roundworms that making sperm is quite a drain on a male's faculties, and that the act does hasten death. (Whether these findings apply to humans remains unknown.)</p>
        <p>"It's annoying that it simply didn't occur to me to ask whether mating shortens a male fly's life as well," Dr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>Other scientists were more interested in discussing scientific theory than raw data, criticizing many of the methods used in the field of sociobiology, the study of the genetic and evolutionary basis of social behavior.</p>
        <p>They complained that all too often sociobiologists framed all their theories about biological motivations for behavior in terms of competition: males competing against males, females against females, and, above all, males against females, the eternal battle of the sexes.</p>
        <p>"Despite the wonderful examples of what adding the perspective of the female might do for evolutionary biology, I remain very disturbed that the entire construction of reproduction is thought of in terms of individual motivation rather than a collaborating pair," said Dr. Anne Fausto-Sterling, a geneticist at Brown University. "There's something odd about taking sexual reproduction, which requires two individuals to work, and then treating it theoretically as independent actions of separate individuals with separate interests."</p>
        <p>In applying any of their evolutionary insights to human behavior, the biologists conceded that they ran repeatedly into the quagmire of nature vs. nurture. They insisted that no good scientist today was a strict genetic determinist, one who believes a complete life script is written in the genes -- the nature half of the debate.</p>
        <p>They said of course every scientist recognizes the contributions of environmental influences in shaping behavior, personality and even many physical traits. They bemoaned public ignorance about the subtleties of evolutionary biology and genetics, and they worried that when people read news articles about genes for this or that trait, or the evolution of a particular characteristic like male aggression, they would conclude that the trait was predetermined and unchangeable.  Of Predisposition And Destiny</p>
        <p>Many of the researchers agreed that the most important lesson they had learned was that biological predisposition did not mean biological destiny. They insisted that inherited characteristics could be overridden or deeply modified through learning, environment, a conscious decision not to live by fleeting whims and impulses; otherwise, what is the use of having such a sizable forebrain? This awareness of humanity's enormous behavioral plasticity is particularly critical for feminists to keep in mind, the biologists said, to counter recurring assertions that women are naturally good at one thing, men at another.</p>
        <p>Yet some at the conference said scientists were not as wise as they liked to believe. It is easy to insist that the environment and biology play linked roles in shaping an individual's body and brain, but how the two great forces interact remains entirely mysterious.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
