<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rent Board Sets Increase Of 2 Percent</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="694807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENT CONTROL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDD133DF932A15755C0A962958260" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rent Board Sets Increase Of 2 Percent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAWN G. KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Rent Guidelines Board last night granted the smallest increase for rent-stabilized apartments in the board's 25-year history.</p>
        <p>The board voted to allow landlords an increase of 2 percent on one-year leases and 4 percent on two-year leases of some 800,000 rent-stabilized apartments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Rent Guidelines Board last night granted the smallest increase for rent-stabilized apartments in the board's 25-year history.</p>
        <p>The board voted to allow landlords an increase of 2 percent on one-year leases and 4 percent on two-year leases of some 800,000 rent-stabilized apartments.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the nine-member board granted owners of apartments that rent for less than $400 a month a surcharge of $15 per month. The increase applies only to buildings with fewer than 30 units. The measure was an attempt to assist owners of small buildings, whom housing studies have shown are often the most vulnerable to tax foreclosure and abandonment.</p>
        <p>The board's action seemed to satisfy few of the tenants or landlords who attended the board's meeting at One Police Plaza.  Removal of Critic</p>
        <p>"The surcharge amounts to a poor tax," said William Rowan, a board member of the Metropolitan Council on Housing, which lobbies for tenants' rights. "The apartments that rent for less than $400 are the ones that are most likely to have low-income tenants."</p>
        <p>Dan Marguies, executive director of Community Housing Improvement Program, a trade group for landlords, said the $15 surcharge for units renting for less than $400 was only partial compensation for the "unreasonably" low allowable increase for all units.</p>
        <p>The relatively decorous session turned chaotic when, during a break, Mr. Rowan was removed from the meeting by the police.</p>
        <p>The board's chairman, Edward Hochman, had earlier warned Mr. Rowan and others in the audience of about 300 tenants and landlord activists that he would not permit their shouting, cheering and booing, to interrupt the meeting.</p>
        <p>When the police handcuffed Mr. Rowan and and led him out of the auditorium, tenants in the crowd shouted at the police and then sought out Mr. Hochman demanding an explanation of the incident.  Quelling Interruptions</p>
        <p>Mr. Hochman said he had not called for Mr. Rowan's arrest but had asked the police to remove him after he refused to comply with the chairman's request that he refrain from further interruptions.</p>
        <p>"He said he would do what he wanted to do, so I asked that he be removed," said Mr. Hochman, who is serving his first year as board chairman. "I did not have him arrested."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hochman said the arrest was made after Mr. Rowan resisted the police when they tried to escort him from the auditorium.</p>
        <p>Some in the crowd said Mr. Hochman had overreacted to the Mr. Rowan's belligerence.</p>
        <p>Timothy Collins, executive director of the board, said the charges against Mr. Rowan were dropped by the police.</p>
        <p>The increases adopted by the board will affect about 800,000 rent-stabilized apartments in the city for leases signed between Oct. 1, 1994, and Sept. 30, 1995. Last year, the board voted to allow increases of 3 percent for one-year leases and 5 percent for two-year leases for rent-stabilized apartments.</p>
        <p>When the board proposed the rent increases of 2 and 4 percent in May, Mr. Collins said the board's statistics showed that while tenant income had dropped, landlord expenses had not risen significantly. The board's research found that between 1991 and 1992, the average rent collected by landlords rose by 3.5 percent, compared with 3.4 percent between 1990 and 1991.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
