<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Once Again, Calhoun Has Little Edge</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="675701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NCAA BASKETBALL TOURNAMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALHOUN, JIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JARVIS, MIKE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DF143CF933A15750C0A962958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Once Again, Calhoun Has Little Edge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Blunt but true, the players come and go, but Mike Jarvis and Jim Calhoun have had time to work on their relationship. They have known each other for over a quarter of a century, two tough guys from very different corners of Boston who last summer became friends over a series of what they said were cappuccinos.</p>
        <p>Now Calhoun is going to the regionals this Friday in Miami after Connecticut's talent outlasted the grittiness of Jarvis's George Washington team yesterday, 75-63. But this time, they insisted, they wouldn't let a game or a recruiting battle or a disagreement or a verbal joust get in the way of their newly salvaged friendship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Blunt but true, the players come and go, but Mike Jarvis and Jim Calhoun have had time to work on their relationship. They have known each other for over a quarter of a century, two tough guys from very different corners of Boston who last summer became friends over a series of what they said were cappuccinos.</p>
        <p>Now Calhoun is going to the regionals this Friday in Miami after Connecticut's talent outlasted the grittiness of Jarvis's George Washington team yesterday, 75-63. But this time, they insisted, they wouldn't let a game or a recruiting battle or a disagreement or a verbal joust get in the way of their newly salvaged friendship.</p>
        <p>"Mike told me he wasn't going to press against Alabama-Birmingham," Calhoun said. "Of course he pressed. I said, 'I'm not going to listen to you at all.' "</p>
        <p>And Jarvis was reminded that he once said he had taught Calhoun everything he knows. "Aw, I lie so much, I can't remember everything I say," Jarvis said.</p>
        <p>And when Calhoun dropped a paralyzing zone around 7-foot-1-inch Yinka Dare in the second half, the George Washington players praised the tactic before Jarvis even had a chance.</p>
        <p>Talent tells. This is why Florida was able to pull away from Penn, 70-58, in the second game. When Barry Pierce of Penn fouled out seconds from the end, three Florida players gave him respectful bumps and pats and fist handshakes as he trudged to the bench. Next stop for Pierce: a grueling last month at the Wharton School. Next stop for Florida: the regionals in Miami, along with Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The new-found friendship between Calhoun and Jarvis seems to be thriving, after a polarized beginning. Calhoun is a big, gruff Irish-American from Braintree, and Jarvis is a chunky, wary African-American from Cambridge, in a region that has made black people feel unwanted in the stands of Fenway Park (and often in the home dugout).</p>
        <p>"We're very different," Jarvis said the other day. "In the neighborhood we call The Coast in Cambridge, at the Ebony Club where the brothers hang out, they remember the chubby little kid with the catcher's mitt and the basketball. I wasn't good at either sport, so I had to play two."</p>
        <p>Jarvis got a half scholarship to Northeastern, a bootstrappers' university that prepares urban people to make a living. In the volatile 1960's, Jarvis spent a lot of time on the bench watching Northeastern play American International with its husky forward named Jim Calhoun.</p>
        <p>"Jim wasn't as good as he says he was," Jarvis said with a smile. "Neither of us was very good. It's just that I went to a better school."</p>
        <p>In fact, Calhoun was a Little All-America player, and he was white, and by 1972 he had the head coaching job at his old rival, Northeastern, where the freshman coach was, you guessed it, Mike Jarvis.</p>
        <p>"In those days, thank goodness, you had a freshmen team, and we scrimmaged every day," Jarvis said. "Jim was new and I had my own team, and there was competition."</p>
        <p>Calhoun said he always respected Jarvis: "He's a Northeastern graduate. He's got that good blue-collar mentality. Mike always makes his teams to be underdogs -- even if they're 20-point favorites."</p>
        <p>Things started to even out. Jarvis went to work at Harvard under Satch Sanders, and then he got the head job at Cambridge Rindge &amp; Latin High, where he polished Patrick Ewing, and that earned him a five-year hitch at Boston University.</p>
        <p>"Jim had Reggie Lewis and I didn't," said Jarvis, noting that this made it even harder for him to recruit in New England, which is not known for its basketball talent. "Jim and I went further and further apart, to be honest."</p>
        <p>It wasn't Calhoun's worst feud. Calhoun will admit, maybe with a trace of chagrin, that he and Rick Pitino "didn't speak for five years." Then Calhoun went to Connecticut, and he and Jarvis clashed over a game that was delayed because of a snowstorm, and their relationship became mostly grunts. But then Jarvis went south to George Washington, and last summer Roy Williams of Kansas recruited both to be his assistants on the national under-22 team.</p>
        <p>They circled each other for 24 hours or so, then sat down for that famous cup of cappuccino, and then some more frothy milk and coffee at the tournament in Argentina. A few anisette biscuits on the side, and they were better friends than they had ever been. Maybe cappuccino is to shaky relationships what chicken soup is to colds. As the saying goes, it couldn't hurt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
