<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Breast Cancer Fabrications</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="675724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BREAST</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FALSIFICATION OF DATA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DC143CF933A15750C0A962958260" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Breast Cancer Fabrications</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is one comforting element in last week's disturbing revelations of fabrication in the nation's most important breast cancer research program: the falsifications do not, apparently, affect any of the study's conclusions. But the sluggish handling of this tawdry episode by research leaders and government officials is no way to keep the confidence of cancer patients who need access to all relevant information in making life-or-death decisions.</p>
        <p>The revelations have embarrassed a federally financed research program that many experts consider the most important for breast cancer patients anywhere in the world. Known as the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project, it is headed by Dr. Bernard Fisher of the University of Pittsburgh and coordinates the efforts of more than 5,000 doctors at 484 medical centers and hospitals in the U.S. and Canada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is one comforting element in last week's disturbing revelations of fabrication in the nation's most important breast cancer research program: the falsifications do not, apparently, affect any of the study's conclusions. But the sluggish handling of this tawdry episode by research leaders and government officials is no way to keep the confidence of cancer patients who need access to all relevant information in making life-or-death decisions.</p>
        <p>The revelations have embarrassed a federally financed research program that many experts consider the most important for breast cancer patients anywhere in the world. Known as the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project, it is headed by Dr. Bernard Fisher of the University of Pittsburgh and coordinates the efforts of more than 5,000 doctors at 484 medical centers and hospitals in the U.S. and Canada.</p>
        <p>This pioneering program has generated data that have revolutionized the treatment of breast cancer over the past decade. Its most dramatic finding was that for women in the early stages of breast cancer there was no need to remove the entire breast; removing the tumor, followed by radiation therapy, was just as effective. But the program also provided decisive data on the effectiveness of chemotherapy and of the drug tamoxifen in treating women after surgery.</p>
        <p>Yet now it turns out that in one obscure corner of the vast complex -- a small community hospital in Montreal -- the head researcher falsified data to the point where all his results have to be thrown out. It seems the researcher did not slant his findings in an effort to bias the study's conclusions. But he fudged the facts frequently to get some 100 women admitted to the studies who did not qualify under the strict standards applied everywhere else.  These women were among some 1,500 women he enrolled in 14 studies between 1977 and 1990. Their presence threw an intolerable cloud over a project that depends on uniform standards being applied throughout. And no one knew if there were even more falsifications in his research, as yet undetected.</p>
        <p>Research officials insist that, when all the Montreal data are thrown out, the findings from the remaining institutions yield the same conclusions. And backing up those findings, they say, are a range of independent studies from around the world that have reached similar conclusions.</p>
        <p>It is nerve-racking that this case of falsification came to light through a fluke, when the Canadian hospital inadvertently submitted two copies of a patient's record that differed. But it is reassuring that the breast cancer program is so large and diverse that it can survive misconduct in one of the many participating institutions.</p>
        <p>The research project and its Federal overseers were inexplicably slow in pursuing the case after the first discrepancy was found in June 1990. Their task now is to publish those reassuring analyses that prove the conclusions were unaffected by eliminating the Montreal data. The program itself completed a reanalysis two years ago, and it has since been confirmed by Federal statisticians. Yet it took revelations about the falsification in The Chicago Tribune to force a commitment to make the analyses public.</p>
        <p>If breast cancer patients are now fearful and skeptical, the researchers have only themselves to blame.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
