<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pianist Takes the Classics on the Road</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNER, KEVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRUICE, VALERIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE1330F933A25750C0A967958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pianist Takes the Classics on the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRUICE, VALERIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"RELAX," said the tall, casually dressed pianist. "This is an 'informance,' not a recital. It's an informal performance."</p>
        <p>A collective sigh filled the cafeteria at Hillcrest Middle School in Trumbull. The 175 seventh-grade students had been riveted by the opening piece, a dazzling polonaise by Chopin, rendered on an upright piano that had seen better days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"RELAX," said the tall, casually dressed pianist. "This is an 'informance,' not a recital. It's an informal performance."</p>
        <p>A collective sigh filled the cafeteria at Hillcrest Middle School in Trumbull. The 175 seventh-grade students had been riveted by the opening piece, a dazzling polonaise by Chopin, rendered on an upright piano that had seen better days.</p>
        <p>"Any of you musicians?" asked the pianist, 27-year-old Kevin Kenner. Many hands shot up in reply.</p>
        <p>Throughout the presentation, Mr. Kenner, who won the title of Highest-Ranking Pianist of the United States in the 1989 Van Cliburn Competition, demonstrated how works by Chopin, Haydn and John Corigliano reflected their respective societies.  'Crazy About This Piece'</p>
        <p>After the opening Chopin, he pulled Nicole Natale, 12, from the audience, and together they danced the rhythms of the polonaise.</p>
        <p>"They were crazy about this piece in Paris about 180 years ago," said Mr. Kenner, as the two stepped and dipped.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Kenner seated himself in the blue molded-plastic chair that doubled as a piano bench and played a movement from a Haydn sonata, explaining that Haydn's was a time of optimism and balance. But Corigliano's "Etude Fantasy" drew the most vivid responses.</p>
        <p>"What is he trying to say about our society?" asked the pianist.</p>
        <p>Images erupted from the ranks: "Destruction, murder, stress, suspense."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kenner concluded by saying, "Classical music really gets inside of you."  'A No-Lose Situation'</p>
        <p>For two weeks recently, Mr. Kenner brought classical piano music not only to schoolchildren but also to factory workers, immobile elderly people, corporate executives and others in the Bridgeport area through the combined efforts of the Greater Bridgeport Symphony and the Xerox Corporation in Stamford. Mr. Kenner, a Californian, is a member of the Affiliate Artists Xerox Pianists. The program, underwritten by Xerox and the National Endowment for the Arts, sends promising young pianists around the country to share classical music while gaining valuable exposure performing with host orchestras.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kenner, the sixth pianist from the Xerox project to complete a residency with the Greater Bridgeport Symphony, performed the Grieg Piano Concerto No. 1 in A minor with the orchestra at the end of his stay. Since 1983, when the program began, pianists have also visited the Hartford, New Haven and Stamford Symphonies.</p>
        <p>Bette Kucklick of Stratford, who recently retired as manager of cultural affairs for Xerox, oversaw the program from its inception.</p>
        <p>"Everybody gets something out of it," she said. "It's a no-lose situation.</p>
        <p>"It took two years to get it off the ground. We had about 175 applications to start with. We were not looking for people right out of school. The artists had to have some kind of repertory. We had a prestigious board of judges from all over the country. In January 1981, six artists were chosen."</p>
        <p>Auditions are held every other year, and the number of artists selected varies. Affiliate Artists, a management organization that sends young musicians around the country, then arranges the two-week residencies with orchestras, which combine formal concerts with the more relaxed informances, Mrs. Kucklick, said.  'You Need This'</p>
        <p>Mr. Kenner has already completed residencies with orchestras in Kansas City, Mo., and Birmingham, Ala. His next stop is Wichita, Kan.</p>
        <p>"I must say, I was a bit scared at first," he said. "I'd never played with a lot of orchestras before. And I was quite nervous about the prospect of the informances -- verbalizing my own feelings.</p>
        <p>"A part of me said, 'You need this.' I think music education is vital to our society. I'm not a musicologist, but the informance is a wonderful way to spark interest, to reach out to people who haven't had exposure."</p>
        <p>After the Hillcrest presentation, 12-year-old Christine Smith seemed to agree. "I've never seen a pianist like him," she said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Kenner's polonaise partner, Nicole Natale, said, "I learned what you could do if you put your mind to it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
