<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exactly What Is It About Josephine Baker?</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JOSEPHINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSE, PHYLLIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE163DF933A25750C0A967958260" item-length="1780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exactly What Is It About Josephine Baker?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHYLLIS ROSE; Phyllis Rose is the author of "Jazz Cleopatra: Josephine Baker in Her Time" (Vintage).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BAKER, JOSEPHINE; ROSE, PHYLLIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My interest in Josephine Baker, which led me to spend five years writing a biography of her, began with a serendipitous mention of her name at a time when I felt my life had become predictable and boring. The only kind of music I could listen to was jazz, because I never knew where it would go next. I thought that Baker -- whose moves in every sense seemed unpredictable, whose whole life seemed a jazz improvisation -- was a subject I could spend time with and be psychically nourished by the contact.</p>
        <p>When I saw a photograph of her in a gorgeous beaded dress, crossing her eyes, making fun of herself and her own glamour, the bargain was sealed. I was claimed. She had a vitality, spontaneity, fearlessness and joy I very much wanted to appropriate. I was moved by the way she covered over her deepest emotions, often with a mask of comedy, seeming to let go with the greatest abandon yet insisting on an underlying control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My interest in Josephine Baker, which led me to spend five years writing a biography of her, began with a serendipitous mention of her name at a time when I felt my life had become predictable and boring. The only kind of music I could listen to was jazz, because I never knew where it would go next. I thought that Baker -- whose moves in every sense seemed unpredictable, whose whole life seemed a jazz improvisation -- was a subject I could spend time with and be psychically nourished by the contact.</p>
        <p>When I saw a photograph of her in a gorgeous beaded dress, crossing her eyes, making fun of herself and her own glamour, the bargain was sealed. I was claimed. She had a vitality, spontaneity, fearlessness and joy I very much wanted to appropriate. I was moved by the way she covered over her deepest emotions, often with a mask of comedy, seeming to let go with the greatest abandon yet insisting on an underlying control.</p>
        <p>My book concentrated on how a general enthusiasm for things African among white Europeans in the 1920's helped pave the way for Baker's success. So I quickly became aware that my attempt to appropriate her vitality reproduced the very phenomenon I was studying. This made me so self-conscious about my interest in Baker that I cringed whenever someone asked me the reasonable question, "How did you become interested in Josephine Baker?"</p>
        <p>Josephine Baker, born poor in St. Louis in 1906, clowned and danced her way to stardom -- first on black Broadway, then in Paris, where her rubber-legged impudence on stage and outrageous glamour off stage (she walked her leopard on a diamond leash) made her an icon of the Jazz Age. Funny and sexy at the same time, she danced bare-breasted at the Folies Bergere, but within a decade had transformed herself into an elegant French music-hall performer.</p>
        <p>She worked with the French Resistance during World War II, helped de Gaulle propagandize North Africa, and was honored as a war heroine. Later, unable to have children herself, she adopted 12 of different races and nationalities. In 1948 and 1951, she returned to the States and was active for civil rights.  Her stage career lasted 50 years, and she was still performing at the time of her death in 1975.</p>
        <p>From youth through age, her winsome sweetness endeared her to audiences. Langston Hughes said she reached out from the stage and took everybody's heart in her hands. But when you see early footage of her, it's above all a comic, mocking energy -- mockery of herself and mockery of the role she has been cast in -- that captivates and explains her wild success in the 20's.</p>
        <p>She was the first black woman to achieve international stardom. Her success in Europe was a source of joy and inspiration to an older generation of African Americans, and now she is being rediscovered for a younger generation. "Black Americans see the glory and poignancy in her story -- her having to go abroad to make it," said Arnold Rampersad, Langston Hughes's biographer. "She was both international star and home girl, a brave and creative human being."</p>
        <p>She never had as great a success in America as she wanted, but now it seems her time has come. HBO will present "The Josephine Baker Story," starring Lynn Whitfield and directed by Brian Gibson, on Saturday at 8 P.M. TNT plans another version of Baker's story with Diana Ross, and Dolly Parton's Sandollar company intends to make a feature film, with Hugh Hudson ("Chariots of Fire") directing. Moreover, two French films Baker made in the 1930's, "Princess Tam-Tam" and "Zou-Zou," have been subtitled, re-released and screened for turn-away crowds at the Film Forum in Manhattan and elsewhere around the country. The films have also been released on videocassette. A 1987 British documentary on Baker, "Chasing a Rainbow," has been shown often on the Arts &amp; Entertainment cable channel. Why suddenly all the interest?</p>
        <p>Since my own interest was, I thought, quirky and personal, I decided to ask some other people, especially in African-American academic circles, what was bringing this belated attention to the expatriate star. It turned out their answers weren't so far from my own, with most of them emphasizing what was liberating in the way Baker led her life and worked her art.</p>
        <p>"She wasn't just pushed out onto a stage," said Robert G. O'Meally, professor of American studies at Barnard. "She invented herself as part of a complicated tradition." Referring to 1926 footage included in "Chasing a Rainbow," Professor O'Meally said it was a revelation to see how she "bootlegged traditional black dance moves onto a broader stage. The people she was dancing for didn't know the tradition she was part of, but looking back now, we can appreciate it."</p>
        <p>Cheryl Wall, who screens "Princess Tam-Tam" as part of a course on the Harlem Renaissance at Rutgers, likes the way in which Baker mocks her role in that film even as she plays it. There is something complex and manipulative at work in Baker's stage presence: "In Paris she created a persona that played to racist fantasies," she says, "yet she was not controlled by those fantasies. She retained her freedom and her integrity."</p>
        <p>In Baker's life, comedy served as a strategy for mocking her audience and asserting control and cultural identity.</p>
        <p>In the lavish, fast-paced HBO film, comedy is conspicuously absent. The television film portrays her shedding her clowning as soon as she can in favor of a more authentic "savage" self. Her early dances, as re-created in the HBO film by the choreographer George Faison ("The Wiz"), are sultry rather than joyous; he turns her funny, frenetic jazz performances into artily sensual, pseudo-African ballet.</p>
        <p>Hazel Carby, professor of English at Yale, dislikes the way the narrative structure of the British documentary "left Baker no will," presenting her as passive. "How did she get the aggressiveness to move, to change? These women got up and went. That's why they're fascinating."</p>
        <p>Professor Carby also criticizes an occasional "moralistic" quality in the current search for black women heroines, on the part of audiences as well as the culture industry. "There's a touchiness among feminists about representing black women as complex," she says. "People are happier if you portray them as morally superior because of suffering or victimization. I get irritated by representations of black women from the past that are simplistic -- that deny their complexity, their dangerousness, their refusal to be policed.</p>
        <p>"As we recover these women, we're seeing that they have dimensions people don't want to hear about. They might drink too much or fight, and you're not supposed to recover that. Is that any different from re-creating the morally upright mammy who raises your children and does no wrong?"</p>
        <p>If, as some of the people who are rewriting the history of black culture say, the image of a feisty, willful, manipulative Baker is an important corrective to images of black women as passive victims, "The Josephine Baker Story" does not accentuate the right things.</p>
        <p>Partly, Baker herself is responsible. A devoted self-mythographer, Baker told her own life story over and over in books and shows, emphasizing its many acts and taking especially seriously her later war and civil rights work. Yet most of the people I spoke to valued the earlier part of her career and a subtler form of protest implicit in her early stage performances. Her own version of her life has been hard to break away from, which is why many people have had the idea of presenting her story, but few have succeeded.</p>
        <p>HBO focuses on her erotic image, untinged by wit or irony. In a publicity still, Ms. Whitfield, seen nude from the side, assumes a famous Baker pose but misses the chaste elegance of the original. Baker is presented as a foremother of sex queens rather than heroines of color. "Before Madonna," the copy reads, "Before Marilyn. There was Josephine."</p>
        <p>The emphasis on erotically charged material leads Deborah McDowell of the University of Virginia to wonder if the sudden interest of the film industry in Josephine Baker is exploitative, "a revival of the age-old cultural myth of the libidinousness of black women."</p>
        <p>But even sex queens can be models of power, according to Camille Paglia, author of the learned and lively "Sexual Personae," who recently wrote on the Op-Ed page of this paper about Madonna as a feminist heroine. In a recent conversation she rejected the comparison between Josephine Baker and Monroe, who was a victim, but said she thought the link between Baker and Madonna was valid.  They're both scrappy, sensual, funny. They both know how to invoke and violate taboos. Each is a "feisty woman with male will and female sensuality who assaults the citadel. In Baker's case the citadel was Paris and her exoticism was African, whereas for Madonna the exoticism is Italian Catholicism."</p>
        <p>For Baker to serve as a model of power and will for a new generation, however, rather than just another star in the pantheon of victims or do-gooders, her funniness and feistiness have to be taken into account -- even if she herself would have preferred to be remembered in modes less playful, more stridently heroic. BEYOND THE FEATHERS</p>
        <p>It was the allure of Josephine Baker -- the joy and the glamour -- that first attracted Lynn Whitfield (in photograph) to the title role in "The Josephine Baker Story." By the time shooting began, however, the actress had discovered that there was more to Baker than her flamboyant stage career.</p>
        <p>"Growing up black in America, I certainly understood racism," said Ms. Whitfield during a recent trip to New York from her home in Los Angeles. "But I didn't know the racism she experienced informed the rest of her life."</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitfield, who was born in Baton Rouge, La., and has acted in theater, film and television (she has a recurring role on the ABC series "Equal Justice"), found this to be her most demanding part. In the film, directed by Brian Gibson ("Murderers Among Us: The Simon Wiesenthal Story"), she dispensed with a double for most of the dance scenes. "I'd had some ballet and jazz, but I did lots of catch-up work," she said.</p>
        <p>Although she did not do the singing, she worked closely with Carol Dennis, who performed the songs in the production, to pinpoint the emotional factors that would have influenced the entertainer's voice at different times.</p>
        <p>"I found out that she was horrified of sleeping alone," Ms. Whitfield said, and that fact helped her understand Baker's determination to perform. "Being in front of thousands of people loving her had more meaning than just being successful." -- Laurel Graeber  TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
