<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Financial Giant's Slippery Slope</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NOMURA SECURITIES CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TABUCHI, YOSHIHISA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D7143DF933A25750C0A967958260" item-length="3063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Financial Giant's Slippery Slope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tokyo stock market is finally recovering from a vicious year-long plunge, Wall Street is showing signs of a rejuvenation and, most important, financial systems around the globe are being deregulated. It would seem to be a time of fresh opportunity, yet Yoshihisa Tabuchi, the most powerful individual in Japan's financial markets, speaks like a troubled man.</p>
        <p>"Over the past few years, we may have overemphasized the positive side of all the changes taking place," said Mr. Tabuchi, president and chief executive of the Nomura Securities Company, the world's largest brokerage house. "There was a relatively small amount of discussion of the negative side, the limits that we would face. Especially when I look at the American financial markets, I see confusion."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Tokyo stock market is finally recovering from a vicious year-long plunge, Wall Street is showing signs of a rejuvenation and, most important, financial systems around the globe are being deregulated. It would seem to be a time of fresh opportunity, yet Yoshihisa Tabuchi, the most powerful individual in Japan's financial markets, speaks like a troubled man.</p>
        <p>"Over the past few years, we may have overemphasized the positive side of all the changes taking place," said Mr. Tabuchi, president and chief executive of the Nomura Securities Company, the world's largest brokerage house. "There was a relatively small amount of discussion of the negative side, the limits that we would face. Especially when I look at the American financial markets, I see confusion."</p>
        <p>Indeed, even for a formidable global colossus like Nomura -- it has a staggering $14.7 billion in equity behind it, four-and-a-half times as much as Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, America's largest brokerage house -- these are trying times. The firm's profits are expected to plunge up to 60 percent in the fiscal year ending March 31, from $2.1 billion the previous year.</p>
        <p>The performance is expected to be better than Nomura's Japanese rivals, the other members of the so-called Big Four. All were battered by the market plunge, set off by a steep rise in interest rates and then Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. But that is scant comfort since none of the others -- Daiwa, Nikko and Yamaichi -- has set its sights as high, or taken such bold steps to become a global financial supermarket.</p>
        <p>Nomura's dominant position in many businesses is under siege, too. For instance, it retained its No. 1 ranking last year for underwritings in the Euromarket, the fourth straight year it has held the top spot. But its market share was slashed almost in half, to less than 9 percent. In Tokyo, it was late in taking up the newest imported fad, computerized program trading, and thus finds itself a distant fourth in the lucrative activity -- behind three American securities houses. Worried and Ambivalent</p>
        <p>The firm's challenges run much deeper than a bad year, however, and that is what worries the 58-year-old Mr. Tabuchi, who became chief executive in 1985. Securities executives have long claimed their business thrives on change, and fundamental shifts are indeed gripping the financial world. But Mr. Tabuchi expressed a thoroughly ambivalent attitude toward those prospects: while fighting to instill new thinking at Nomura, where he has spent his entire 35-year career, Mr. Tabuchi is resisting mightily the fundamental liberalization of the heavily regulated Tokyo financial markets, the source of Nomura's raw power.</p>
        <p>It is a contradiction that speaks volumes about Nomura. It also provides a sobering insight into how elusive a goal globalization, in which Nomura had been expected to take a lead, is proving.</p>
        <p>There are two types of deregulation being debated here. One is to permit the use of new financial products and to ease outmoded controls, such as those on interest rates. The other type, lowering the rigid barriers that limit competition between different kinds of financial institutions, is much more threatening. Japanese trust banks, commercial banks and long-term credit banks cannot invade each others' turf, and thus enjoy cartel-like benefits.</p>
        <p>More important, Japanese banks are prohibited from entering most areas of the securities business -- as in the United States. Those days appear to be ending, however. In a historic move, Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady early last month proposed scrapping the wall separating the two financial areas in the United States. Japan's Finance Ministry has also made it clear that, in one form or another, it intends to force Nomura and the other securities houses to share their cozy domain with Japan's giant banks, perhaps by 1993. Question of Ethics</p>
        <p>Nomura is fighting hard against that threat, warning of the damage liberalization has allegedly caused.</p>
        <p>"During the course of deregulation and financial innovation, people tended to forget about the ethics of the market," Mr. Tabuchi said. "Whatever new business you do you must remember to protect your customers and investors. But the tendency was for players to forget these ethics for their own immediate profits. The desirable approach is not to ask who does what and who is not supposed to do what, but how efficient and how convenient the new financial system will be."</p>
        <p>"Having said that," Mr. Tabuchi added, in a telling afterthought, "further deregulation of new financial products should progress. That is an entirely different issue, how to innovate and make these new securities available to investors."</p>
        <p>Mr. Tabuchi issued his brooding, if ambiguous, verdicts in firm but measured tones, puffing on one cigarette after another in an executive suite that lies on the most elite plane in Japan's securities world. The whisper-quiet hallways at Nomura's squat brick headquarters are elegantly hung with Chagalls and Corots. There is an air of haughty self-assurance, for few Japanese companies dominate their business as Nomura does.</p>
        <p>To stand on Nomura's immense, sparkling new trading floor is to be at the center of power in the Japanese market. Along with its affiliates, Nomura, which has total assets of $47 billion, accounts for almost 20 percent of the trading volume on the Tokyo market and about 30 percent of the investment trust, or Japanese mutual fund, business. It has 4,400 retail brokers, the backbone of its business, and another 2,900 salespeople, all women, who peddle stocks and other investments door-to-door.</p>
        <p>With that heft, it is widely believed Nomura can manipulate individual stocks, even the market, at will. Officially, that is always denied; in private, Nomura executives occasionally acknowledge that their firm, as well as the other Big Four, can -- and do -- push share prices at times. Nomura, in short, is feared as much if not more than it is respected.</p>
        <p>Although expanding profits are important to the money machine over which he presides, Mr. Tabuchi, a hard-driving man who is also a fancier of fine wines and art, has set an even more ambitious goal for his tenure. He is attempting to transform what is essentially a huge distribution network, which relies on raw marketing muscle to outsell everyone else, into a genuinely modern securities house with the innovative savvy of Wall Street's best.  New World Order</p>
        <p>Nomura wants to be as comfortable cutting real estate deals, devising new mortgage-backed securities, constructing computer trading strategies, writing sophisticated lease financings, arranging mergers and creating new corporate structures anywhere in the world as it is at sales of stocks and bonds.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, in better times, its leap into a greater global role had seemed a modest step considering its success, size and willingness to experiment. But the hurdles in its path are growing more obvious:</p>
        <p>* Its once-booming European business has slowed as Japanese companies, stung by soaring interest rates, have pulled back from issuing Euromarket securities. A major portion of Nomura's business in the Euromarkets is still with Japanese companies and institutions, not Europeans. "In 1988 and 1989, the contribution to our profits from Japanese money flowing to the Euromarkets had been staggering," said Hitoshi Tonomura, head of international operations. "That has been substantially reduced."</p>
        <p>* Nomura has taken the lead in acquiring a stake in specialized American financial firms to advance into businesses in which it lacks expertise, including mergers, leasing and real estate. Just a week ago, it formed a joint venture with a commodities trading specialist, the Tudor Investment Corporation. Some Nomura executives in the United States have complained, though, that those operations have left Nomura's activities fragmented.</p>
        <p>* The firm suffered a black eye with the publication last year of "The House of Nomura," a book that suggested Nomura routinely breaks the rules -- manipulating share prices, for example. Nomura has filed a libel suit against Al Alletzhauser, the author, which is pending in London, but that only attracted more attention to the reported improprieties.</p>
        <p>* The firm is still struggling to cast off its image as a "kabuya," a derisive term that might be translated as "stock shop," the way one would refer to a fish store. The moniker suggests the giant securities houses are nothing but merchants, selling their wares for a commission. In fact, since commission rates are fixed in Japan, those simple fees for executing trades still account for 41 percent of Nomura's consolidated revenues. Merrill Lynch, to which Nomura is sometimes compared, gets 15 percent of revenues from commissions. Coveted Role</p>
        <p>Brokerage houses here have traditionally relied on these basic transactions rather than building intimate relationships with the real movers of corporate Japan. That coveted role, which is essential for the future, is held by commercial banks.</p>
        <p>"In Japan, the banking industry and the securities industry are oriented on very different cultures," conceded Hideo Sakamaki, Nomura's head of strategic planning and human resources, who is leading the diversification effort.</p>
        <p>When Wasserstein, Perella &amp; Company, the American mergers specialist that sold a 20 percent share to Nomura, initially considered taking on a Japanese partner, it spoke first to the elite Industrial Bank of Japan as the best entree to corporate Japan. (A Wasserstein, Perella executive disputed this, but others with knowledge of the dealings confirmed the discussions, led by Joseph Perella.)</p>
        <p>"If you come right down to it, Nomura has a franchise called the Tokyo Stock Exchange," said Robert Zielinski, an analyst at Jardine Fleming Securities and author of a recent book on the Japanese market. "They have exploited that franchise to the fullest extent. But except for size, there's nothing to distinguish them from the other Big Four firms. They'll never do as well in any other market as they have here."</p>
        <p>Evidence of the struggle to adopt a new image crops up everywhere. Asked if its sales network was not the heart of Nomura, Yoshikazu Kitsuda, who runs the securities sales and trading operations and is rumored to be a possible successor to Mr. Tabuchi, responded crisply, "Exactly! Placement power." He was quickly corrected by Michio Katsumata, a public relations executive, who added, "And brain power, too."</p>
        <p>An even more telling sign is the acknowledged weakness of Nomura's operations in the United States, despite years of effort and the expenditure of hundreds of millions of dollars. On Wall Street, Nomura's operations generated just $20 million in pre-tax income in the last fiscal year -- a third of the income Nomura earned in Hong Kong and one-eighth of its income in London. Using another measure, Nomura devoted about 20 percent of its assets to the United States in the last fiscal year, but received just 4 percent of its overall revenues there.</p>
        <p>Because Wall Street is the most liberalized major financial market, it is regarded as a test of how well the giant broker can compete in an arena where ideas and an ability to take risks count for more than a huge capital base and sales muscle.</p>
        <p>"Nomura has a lot of marketing power in Japan and Europe," Mr. Sakamaki commented. "But we are really just starting in the United States. It will take a little more time."</p>
        <p>Max C. Chapman Jr., a former top executive at Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company, is co-chairman of Nomura's American unit. Last year, he was invited to join the parent company's board in Tokyo, the first time an outsider had been so honored. It was a pithy symbol, but Mr. Chapman said he still has to work hard to get Nomura's executives to appreciate that some of the practices that are an asset in Tokyo are liabilities in the more competitive Wall Street arena. Pushing for Change</p>
        <p>These include the traditional aversion to using the firm's own capital in trading, called principal trading; the lack of a history of maintaining tight bonds between the research, trading and investment banking departments in order to create new products, and the practice of rotating professionals every couple of years. That creates generalists who often lack the expertise needed to engage in higher-risk and demanding businesses.</p>
        <p>"We have to turn this into more of a principal business," Mr. Chapman said. "That makes them nervous."</p>
        <p>Some at Nomura agree such skills might be needed overseas, but shrink from the idea that the firm should adopt them at home. "We have to add some Japanese flavor to whatever we bring back," said Mr. Tonomura.</p>
        <p>However, to underscore the need to change the old patterns of thought, Nomura broke out its training division as a separate company, giving it more visibility and influence. Mr. Tabuchi is chairman of the unit, the only subsidiary at which he has a title, another sign of the unit's importance.</p>
        <p>As chief executive, he has prodded and pulled at this unwieldy giant, which has 16,000 employees, to try to shake it from its old ways. In one published interview, Mr. Tabuchi even said it might be a good thing if Nomura suffered some sort of failure -- an almost unthinkable calamity for a proud Nomura man -- to pry his executives away from the view that what worked in the past will work in the future.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tabuchi has been bold in his overseas moves, something rare at a large Japanese company, and more successful than his Japanese competitors. But the setbacks of the past year have made his task heavier rather than lighter as he moves into what are expected to be the final few years of his rule.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tabuchi does not deny feeling frustrated on the road to globalization: "A C.E.O. who has no frustrations better resign at once. Frustration in running a large organization is a burden a C.E.O. has to bear." DANCING TO WALL STREET'S M.&amp;A. TUNE</p>
        <p>If there is one business that symbolizes the kind of firm the Nomura Securities Company hopes to remake itself into, it is mergers and acquisitions. The business involves selling ideas rather than products, requires tact and nimbleness and is becoming increasingly international.</p>
        <p>In fact, Nomura has been in the business for some time in Japan. But there is one big difference between the traditional Japanese style of M.&amp;A. and Wall Street's: in Japan, rarely has it generated fees.</p>
        <p>"This business was often done by politicians or some kind of fixer, and they would receive a gift, not really a fee," said Mitsuo Goto, head of Nomura's budding mergers practice. "When it was done by a securities firm, it was a free service."</p>
        <p>Nomura has set out to change that. It has joined forces with Wasserstein, Perella &amp; Company, the Wall Street merger specialist. The Americans have a great deal more experience in the nuts and bolts of these deals, and if there is one thing Wasserstein, Perella does well, it is to charge fees.</p>
        <p>Nomura bought 20 percent of the American firm for $100 million in 1988, and set up a new unit in Japan, the Nomura Wasserstein Perella Company, as a joint venture.</p>
        <p>Nomura has picked up another authentic American practice from its new partner: an unashamed desire to grab credit for deals. That is something of a contrast to the discretion expected of corporate matchmakers in Japan, but times are changing.</p>
        <p>The shift was never more in evidence than during the acquisition of MCA Inc. late last year by the Matsushita Electric Industrial Company. Matsushita disclosed that its investment banking adviser was Allen &amp; Company. But no sooner had the two sides shaken hands than N.W.P. announced that it had also advised Matsushita, albeit in a secret capacity. That prompted a miffed Matsushita executive to quip that he found it a bit unusual to publicly declare supposed secrets.</p>
        <p>"I can say we've learned a lot about M.&amp;A. from the U.S.," said Mr. Goto, president of N.W.P.</p>
        <p>The creation of the mergers unit, one of four such partnerships between Nomura and American financial specialists, is an admission of Nomura's inability to develop the businesses from within, Mr. Goto acknowledged, adding that he felt the arrangements had been a success.</p>
        <p>"Investment banking is a kind of clubby world," he said. "We were invited to the party, but we couldn't get the business."</p>
        <p>Nomura Wasserstein Perella has not engaged in the series of blockbuster deals some had envisioned, but Mr. Goto said it has served as an adviser in 44 completed transactions.  HOMEY SIDE OF THE HARD SELL</p>
        <p>To most Japanese, the Nomura Securities Company means hard sell. Its broker force is renowned for its don't-take-no-for-an-answer style.</p>
        <p>But there are still many Japanese who disdain such aggressive methods and prefer a homier, traditional approach. Nomura has an answer for them, too: what it calls "middies," women who peddle investment products door-to-door like Avon ladies.</p>
        <p>Middies is short for middle-aged, a reference to the fact that the 2,900 troops who fill these slots in the Nomura sales army are women in their late 30's to early 50's. Nomura says they generally are housewives with a family who take the job for the extra money. They are paid a salary plus commissions and usually have a regular group of long-time customers.</p>
        <p>Nomura first employed middies in 1953, in the lean postwar years. Housewives were given locked boxes in which they could deposit savings. When the boxes were filled, Nomura sent women around to pick them up in exchange for shares in investment trusts, or mutual funds.</p>
        <p>Nomura is not alone. The other large brokerages also employ this shoe-leather approach, and much of the life insurance sold in Japan is peddled door-to-door, by one housewife to another.</p>
        <p>The middies are a throwback in more ways than one. They can sell only bonds and investment trusts. Their license forbids them from selling stocks or the fancier products becoming popular here, futures and options. That job is left to the regular branch office sales force, which is largely male.</p>
        <p>Nomura says the middies do not account for a major share of its retail sales. But their continued role is a symbol of the firm's deep roots in the retail brokerage business, and the stubbornly traditional style of salesmanship that business demands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
