<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="708136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EED81239F937A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD  Christie Runs Spectacular 100  Linford Christie completed a spectacular return to the Commonwealth Games yesterday in Victoria, British Columbia, winning the 100 meters with the sixth-fastest time in history. The 34-year-old Englishman bowed and blew kisses to the crowd after he won the gold medal in 9.91 seconds, his third games record in as many races over the past two days at Centennial Stadium. Christie, the world champion and 1992 Olympic gold medalist, won his 20th gold medal in an international competition and repeated as games champion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD  Christie Runs Spectacular 100  Linford Christie completed a spectacular return to the Commonwealth Games yesterday in Victoria, British Columbia, winning the 100 meters with the sixth-fastest time in history. The 34-year-old Englishman bowed and blew kisses to the crowd after he won the gold medal in 9.91 seconds, his third games record in as many races over the past two days at Centennial Stadium. Christie, the world champion and 1992 Olympic gold medalist, won his 20th gold medal in an international competition and repeated as games champion.</p>
        <p>Christie was the oldest entrant in the 100 meters. The second-oldest, Horace Dove-Edwards, 32, of Sierra Leone, was a surprising second in 10.02. Earlier yesterday, Christie won his semifinal heat in 9.98, breaking the games record of 10.02 he set in New Zealand four years ago and tied in Monday's quarterfinals.</p>
        <p>The 110-meter hurdles world champion, Colin Jackson, running for Wales, repeated as the title holder and matched the games record of 13.08 he set four years ago. Mary Onyali led a 1-2 Nigerian finish in the women's 100, winning in 11.06 seconds. The defending champion, Catherine Freeman of Australia, broke a 24-year-old Games record in winning the women's 400 in 50.38. Another Australian, Daniela Costian, won the women's discus gold with a games record of 209 feet 1 inch. Charles Gitonga of Kenya won the men's 400 gold in 45.00 seconds. LITTLE LEAGUE  Northridge Moves Ahead  Peter Tuber of Northridge, Calif., throwing curveballs his opponents have seldom seen, struck out 13 in a 6-4 victory over Middleboro, Mass., in the second round of the Little League World Series at Williamsport, Pa., yesterday. "We play a 22-game schedule without curveballs," Middleboro Manager Steve McKenna said. "They do not allow curveballs in our league. They feel that throwing them too early tends to destroy a kid's arm." In the international bracket, Saudi Arabia, made up mostly of sons of Americans living in that country, beat Glace Bay, Nova Scotia, 6-3. Saudi Arabia scored five runs on wild pitches in its victory. The top two teams in both the United States and international brackets play tomorrow to determine who goes to Saturday's championship game. (AP) TENNIS  Sanchez Defeats Hirszon  Sasa Hirszon, the highest-ranked Croat entered in the $400,000 Croatian Open, could not continue his match yesterday against Emilio Sanchez. With temperatures at a humid 104 degrees in Umag, the 266th-ranked Hirszon suffered a combination of dehydration and sunstroke in the second-round match. Sanchez had broken Hirszon's serve and led by 5-4 in the opening set when Hirszon felt ill. Hirszon was immediately taken to a Umag hospital, where he was recovering, said Igor Vrcic, the tournament physician. After the match, Sanchez complained of a headache and sickness, Vrcic said. (AP) Lendl Starts Slowly but Wins: Ivan Lendl survived a slow start on the way to an 0-6, 6-2, 6-3 victory over Rodolphe Gilbert of France yesterday in Schnectady, N.Y., in the first round of the OTB International. The fourth-seeded Lendl dismissed the notion that recent back problems were the cause of his rough start, saying, "I missed easy balls at the beginning." In other men's matches, top-seeded Sergi Brugera of Spain defeated Andrei Cherkasov of Russia, 6-2, 6-0, Mats Wilander of Sweden beat eighth-seeded Richard Fromberg of Australia, 6-1, 4-6, 6-3, and Alex Antioch of Austria, ranked 147th in the world, upset third-seeded Paul Haarhuis of the Netherlands, 6-3, 6-1. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
