<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fresh Taste, Simplicity and Low Cost</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="775266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARVEST BAKERY (SALISBURY, CONN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REHAB SNACK BAR (DARIEN, CONN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FJORD FISH N'CHIPS (STAMFORD, CONN, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D8173CF935A25754C0A963958260" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fresh Taste, Simplicity and Low Cost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FINDING a quick, no-frills lunch where the food is freshly made can be more of a quest than it sounds. At the following twosome, however, the food tastes fresh and the setting is simple but agreeable.</p>
        <p>THE HARVEST BAKERY in Salisbury is in a pale yellow frame house with white trim just off the main thoroughfare. In addition to excellent breads (including crusty Italian, sourdough baguettes, foccacia, seven grain and cinnamon raisin), there are several soups and as many as 18 salads available daily to take out or eat in. And after 4 P.M., there are 12 gourmet pizzas (including smoked salmon, Mexican, vegetarian and fruits de mer).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FINDING a quick, no-frills lunch where the food is freshly made can be more of a quest than it sounds. At the following twosome, however, the food tastes fresh and the setting is simple but agreeable.</p>
        <p>THE HARVEST BAKERY in Salisbury is in a pale yellow frame house with white trim just off the main thoroughfare. In addition to excellent breads (including crusty Italian, sourdough baguettes, foccacia, seven grain and cinnamon raisin), there are several soups and as many as 18 salads available daily to take out or eat in. And after 4 P.M., there are 12 gourmet pizzas (including smoked salmon, Mexican, vegetarian and fruits de mer).</p>
        <p>To eat on the premises, the routine is simple: Order at the display counter, then carry your lunch on a tray to one of five indoor or five outdoor tables. The salads are so tempting, it is wise to select small scoops of several on one plate. The plate is then billed according to weight.</p>
        <p>Following this pattern, three of us sampled eight different salads at one lunch. The zestiest choices were sweet-sour tofu with cashews and mushrooms, bowtie pasta and fresh salmon, oven-roasted root-vegetable salad (beets, turnips and parsnips), Mediterranean salad (with artichokes and mushrooms, penne pasta and duck), Greek salad (with feta cheese, broccoli, tomatoes, roasted garlic cloves and calamata black olives) and a summery tomato-mozzarella-red onion salad.</p>
        <p>We also polished off a cup of delicious hot leek and potato soup, a rather oily white gazpacho (made with chicken stock, cucumbers, onions and tomatoes), some fresh-squeezed lemonade, iced cappuccino, a brownie and two yummy oatmeal and chocolate chip cookies.</p>
        <p>While the setting is casual, real china plates, cups and saucers and flatware are used, not the paper or plastic picnic stuff. This is also a good place to stop for morning coffee and some of the best fresh-made muffins (the puffy cranberry-walnut are exceptional) that we we've tasted in ages.</p>
        <p>Hours: 9 A.M.-9 P.M. Tuesday through Sunday. Major credit cards accepted. 10 Academy St., Salisbury, 435-1302.</p>
        <p>On the second floor of the Darien Sport Shop in Darien is the REHAB SNACK BAR, run as a volunteer effort for the benefit of the Easter Seal Rehabilitation Center in Stamford. There are a mere six tables, plus three more in an alcove overlooking the parking lot.</p>
        <p>The guiding spirit of the snack bar, which has expanded considerably over the years, is Gretchen Gregory, who prepares all the food. The blackboard menu lists five or six soups, a few sandwiches, three salads and half a dozen cakes and tarts.</p>
        <p>The $7.50 soup and sandwich or salad special, with beverage (tea or coffee, hot or iced), is a real buy. We enjoyed the chilled curry carrot soup (a refreshing puree) and tangy-tart artichoke-lemon soup, curried chicken salad (which came with a muffin), a generous smoked turkey-muenster cheese sandwich on rye, and iced tea. Moist, flavorful apple spice cake with butter cream frosting and a bundt chocolate chip cake sprinkled with powdered sugar were worthy extras at $3.00 a slice.</p>
        <p>The reasonably priced food has a homemade flair, the setting is tearoom-pretty and the cause is worthy. How can you miss? Hours: 12-2 P.M., Monday through Friday. No credit cards. 1127 Post Road, Darien, 655-2575. A LA CARTE</p>
        <p>Something new in Stamford is FJORD FISH N'CHIPS (a branch of Fjord Fisheries, the Scandinavian restaurant on the other side of town), located in Springdale on premises last occupied by Harry's TX &amp; AZ. Lunch entrees are $4.25 to $19.95; dinner entrees, $5.75 to $19.95. The menu is small, mostly seafood (crabcakes, fried clam bellies, salmon and, of course, fish and chips). There are also burgers, grilled chicken and Norwegian meatballs. The lobster dinner with one ($12.95) or two ($19.95) steamed lobsters is good value. Major credit cards accepted. No reservations, no liquor license yet. Hours: noon-4 P.M., Tuesday through Saturday; 4 P.M.-10 P.M. Tuesday through Saturday, 5 P.M.-9 P.M. Sunday. Closed Monday. 934 Hope Street, Springdale, Stamford, 324-1882.  RESTAURANT REVISITED</p>
        <p>It has been a while since we last visited MAKO OF JAPAN in Fairfield. The little storefront restaurant in a small shopping center looks much the same, with the sushi bar in the rear and several tatami mat tables (where shoes are removed and feet tucked beneath the table). Happily, the food is the same, the sashimi/sushi fish especially fresh and inviting. A special treat: sukiyaki is prepared the traditional way, at tableside, not short-cutted as at so many Japanese restaurants these days.  Hours: 5-9 P.M. Tuesday through Thursday, 5-10 P.M. Friday and Saturday, closed Sunday and Monday. Credit cards accepted. 941 Black Rock Turnpike, Fairfield, 367-5319.  DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
