<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jordanian Is Lionized In Israel</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="775106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN SERVICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISRAEL-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-JORDAN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JORDAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENBERG, JOEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUASHER, MARWAN (AMB)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D61F38F935A25754C0A963958260" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jordanian Is Lionized In Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENBERG, JOEL</byline>
      <dateline>TEL AVIV</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the three months since he arrived as Jordan's first Ambassador to Israel, Marwan Muasher has become a celebrity, although sometimes a reluctant one.</p>
        <p>He is a sought-after guest at dinners and receptions. He has appeared on television. He gives lectures. He has been interviewed by the Israeli press.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the three months since he arrived as Jordan's first Ambassador to Israel, Marwan Muasher has become a celebrity, although sometimes a reluctant one.</p>
        <p>He is a sought-after guest at dinners and receptions. He has appeared on television. He gives lectures. He has been interviewed by the Israeli press.</p>
        <p>But when news photographers have tried to coax him into casual shots on the beaches and streets of Tel Aviv, he has declined, preferring instead the more sober setting of his office.</p>
        <p>Back home, pictures of him at ease in Tel Aviv might cause criticism, especially from Muslim opponents of the peace treaty that Israel and Jordan signed in October. But Mr. Muasher insists that the problem is his own discomfort with star status.</p>
        <p>Almost nine months after Israel and Jordan made peace, their peoples still view each other differently, forming a fault line that Mr. Muasher has had to straddle.</p>
        <p>"The reception here is overwhelming, to the point where the Ambassador in some cases is almost treated as a celebrity," Mr. Muasher said, sitting in his small office, part of a hotel suite that is serving as Jordan's Embassy until permanent quarters can be found.</p>
        <p>"People invite the Jordanian Ambassador many times because they want the Jordanian Ambassador to be there, not because they want to listen to what he has to say," he said. "And when you start focusing on the person rather than on the issue, I get worried."</p>
        <p>Mr. Muasher, the 39-year-old former spokesman for Jordan's delegation to the Middle East peace talks, holds a doctorate in computer engineering from Purdue University in Indiana, but has specialized in public and media relations during his career in government. He is only the second Arab ambassador in Israel. Egypt has had one since signing its peace treaty with Israel in 1979.</p>
        <p>The Israeli embrace of Mr. Muasher and his measured response mirror a larger reality. While Israelis pour into Jordan to visit and want to establish economic and cultural relations right away, ordinary Jordanians have been more reserved, lagging behind the peace policies of King Hussein and the Government in Amman. Some Jordanian professional groups have punished members who have had dealings with Israelis, and relatively few Jordanian tourists cross the border.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muasher tries to allay concerns that relations with Jordan will turn out to be much like Israel's cool -- some would say icy -- peace with Egypt.</p>
        <p>"The peace we seek is a warm one," he said in a recent lecture at Tel Aviv University. But he cautioned that it will take time. The Jordanian Government cannot force normal relations on its people, he said, adding that Israeli "over-eagerness" had raised fears among some Jordanians of economic and cultural domination.</p>
        <p>Many Jordanians of Palestinian origin feel that there is still unfinished business, like the future of Palestinian refugees, Jerusalem and Jewish settlements in the West Bank.</p>
        <p>"While Jordanians want to wait until all the political and economic problems are resolved before building relations on a people's level with Israel, Israelis tend to minimize existing problems and assume they do not affect their dreams of becoming part of the region," he said at the university.</p>
        <p>In general, the Ambassador said in an interview, living in Israel has given him a better sense of Israeli hopes and fears.</p>
        <p>Israel's terrain reminds him of home, he said, as do the names of Palestinian families with branches in Jordan. But he said he had been apprehensive at first about living in a country that used to be an enemy, and it intrigued him to discover that Israel is a mixture of the West and the Middle East, more raucous and faster-paced than Jordan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
