<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minor Figure in Iraqi Kidnapping Gets a Life Sentence</title>
    <meta content="06iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/06/world/middleeast/06iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1767167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hassan, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jibouri, Mustafa Muhammad Salman al-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zobai, Hussein Ahmed Salman al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">CARE</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hassan, Margaret</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DA1431F935A35755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minor Figure in Iraqi Kidnapping Gets a Life Sentence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Minor Figure in Iraqi Kidnapping Gets a Life Sentence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE; Reporting for this article was contributed by Sarah Lyall from London, and Mona Mahmoud, Qais Mizher, Sahar Nageeb and Omar Neami from Baghdad.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraqi court imposes life sentence on Mustafa Muhammad Salman al-Jibouri, who apparently played minor role in kidnapping of British aid worker Margaret Hassan; two men are acquitted; sheik suspected of key role eludes arrest; violence continues in Baghdad as armed men seize 24 people in commercial district dotted with bus companies; photos; morgue recorded 1,375 bodies in May, record for single month; testimony links Hassan killing to mosque in Jadriya and its sheik, Hussein Ahmed Salman al-Zobai; kidnapping recounted; Hassan family blames British government for refusing to negotiate with kidnappers; Italian soldier reported killed and three others wounded by bomb in south (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A judge imposed a life sentence on Monday on a man who apparently played a minor role in the kidnapping of Margaret Hassan, a British-Iraqi aid worker whose disappearance and death showed that no one was immune from insurgent viciousness.</p>
        <p>The verdict, the first in a kidnapping of a foreigner in Iraq, brought an inconclusive end to the case of Ms. Hassan, 59, who was abducted on her way to work in Baghdad in October 2004. Two other men were acquitted and a sheik suspected of having played an important role in the kidnapping has eluded arrest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The kidnapping of Margaret Hassan, a British-Iraqi aid worker, opened a more dangerous era for foreign nationals working in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A judge imposed a life sentence on Monday on a man who apparently played a minor role in the kidnapping of Margaret Hassan, a British-Iraqi aid worker whose disappearance and death showed that no one was immune from insurgent viciousness.</p>
        <p>The verdict, the first in a kidnapping of a foreigner in Iraq, brought an inconclusive end to the case of Ms. Hassan, 59, who was abducted on her way to work in Baghdad in October 2004. Two other men were acquitted and a sheik suspected of having played an important role in the kidnapping has eluded arrest.</p>
        <p>The kidnapping of Ms. Hassan, the director of CARE International in Iraq who had dedicated her life to helping the country's poor, stunned Iraqis and opened a more dangerous era for foreign nationals working here. In one enduring image from a grainy video broadcast on television, she was seen crumpled and pleading. Her body was never found.</p>
        <p>Judge Saab Khorshid of the Central Criminal Court sentenced Mustafa Muhammad Salman al-Jibouri, a man associated with a Sunni mosque in central Baghdad, to life in prison, a British Embassy official said. The charge, according to an Iraqi lawyer who watched the trial, was aiding and abetting: Mr. Jibouri held Ms. Hassan's purse after she was abducted, though he said he did not know whose it was at first.</p>
        <p>The spasm of violence in the capital continued Monday, with armed men dressed as police commandos seizing 24 people in Salheya, a bustling commercial district in the heart of the city that is dotted with bus companies that take travelers to Syria and Jordan. Families of those who were seized, including bus owners, riders and a kebob seller, formed an impromptu demonstration and demanded their release.</p>
        <p>''What happened today is a catastrophe, something unnatural,'' said one of the relatives on the Iraqi evening news here.</p>
        <p>Security in the capital has deteriorated precipitously in recent months. Increasingly brazen assassinations torment neighborhoods and no longer seem to follow any obvious patterns. In May, the Baghdad morgue recorded the highest number of bodies received since the beginning of the war: 1,375, approximately double the toll of May 2005.</p>
        <p>The surge in killings comes as Iraqi political leaders remained deadlocked for a seventh week over the most important positions in the Iraqi cabinet, the ministers of defense and interior. The stalemate has left Iraq rudderless when it most needs a full government.</p>
        <p>''It's a real problem,'' said Mowaffak al-Rubaie, the national security adviser, who said a new security plan for Baghdad cannot begin until the ministers are in place.</p>
        <p>The trial in Ms. Hassan's killing, which was completed in only two and a half hours, went virtually unnoticed by Iraqi television outlets, and raised more questions than it answered. The testimony connected Ms. Hassan's kidnapping to a mosque in Jadriya, a leafy neighborhood of university professors in central Baghdad, and the sheik who presided there, identified by defendants as Hussein Ahmed Salman al-Zobai.</p>
        <p>The sheik had given Mr. Jibouri, a resident of Madaen, an angry Sunni Arab town south of Baghdad, Ms. Hassan's purse and identification cards in a plastic bag for safekeeping, according to Shawkat al-Samarrai, an Iraqi lawyer who watched the trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jibouri, who denied he played a part in the kidnapping, said he looked inside the purse two months later and discovered it belonged to Ms. Hassan. The sheik, who had moved to Jamiya in western Baghdad, an area dominated by insurgents, said he would come to collect it, but never did, Mr. Samarrai said.</p>
        <p>Two other men, Mohsin Ahmed and Qasim Muhammad, identified by The Associated Press as a guard and a worshiper from the mosque that figured in the case, were acquitted. It was not clear from the testimony what happened to the sheik, but some participants in the trial said that he had fled, according to Mr. Samarrai. Court officials were not available for comment on Monday afternoon.</p>
        <p>In a frustrating tale of missed opportunities and painful waiting, Ms. Hassan's husband, Tahseen Hassan, took the stand on Monday. In a calm voice, he spoke of the ordeal of losing his wife, beginning from the morning of her disappearance on Oct. 19, 2004.</p>
        <p>She left the house at 7:30 a.m., he said, according to Mr. Samarrai, riding with her driver and bodyguard in her Toyota Camry to her office in Quthat, a neighborhood on the edge of Jadriya. Two hours later, her secretary called Mr. Hassan and told him his wife was missing. The driver, an Iraqi, and the guard, an Egyptian, had been badly beaten.</p>
        <p>In the days after his wife was abducted, Mr. Hassan received several telephone calls -- her relatives said on Monday that four were made from her cellphone -- from people he did not know, asking for the numbers of the British Embassy in Baghdad, and of Ms. Hassan's office.</p>
        <p>Shortly after that, a caller who identified himself as Abu Mustafa reassured him that his wife was doing well, and proposed a meeting in the Shiite neighborhood of Kadhimiya. Mr. Hassan said he went there with the Iraqi police, but that the caller never showed up. Abu Mustafa later called back, according to Mr. Samarrai, and asked Mr. Hassan why he had come with the police.</p>
        <p>In a statement released in England on Sunday, Ms. Hassan's family accused the British government of contributing to her death by refusing to negotiate with her kidnappers.</p>
        <p>''The hostage-takers demanded to speak to a member of the British Embassy, but Tahseen had been told by the British that they would not speak to the kidnappers,'' said Ms. Hassan's siblings -- Deirdre, Geraldine, Kathryn and Michael Fitzsimmons. ''We believe that the refusal by the British government to open a dialogue with the kidnappers cost our sister her life.''</p>
        <p>In an interview with the BBC on Monday, Deirdre Fitzsimmons said that the last phone calls were made on Nov. 7, and that Mr. Hassan was essentially left on his own by an unhelpful British government.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he knew what to do,'' she said. ''He did the best he could. After all, this was a man in a house on his own, his wife had been taken hostage, he had seen terrible videos of her. He was really left on his own with this advice.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the British Embassy in Baghdad said: ''Our thoughts are with her family.''</p>
        <p>Typical of the breakdown in the capital, confusion prevailed late into the evening in Salheya, where the 24 people were taken Monday. The head of the commandos said his forces had not been in the area, but an official in the Interior Ministry said that a special police unit, possibly from the Ministry of Transportation, might have conducted the raid.</p>
        <p>One witness, who runs the Tiger Bus Company, said the armed men blindfolded the people they were leading away and fastened their hands with plastic ties.</p>
        <p>''I knew that if they will take me, that means I am dead,'' said the man who asked that his name not be used out of safety concerns. ''We knew this was the end. We ran out the back.''</p>
        <p>In other violence, Iraqi television reported that one Italian soldier had been killed and three others wounded by a bomb in southern Iraq. Two students were killed in the southern neighborhood of Dawra, part of a spate of recent killings of students, an Interior Ministry official said. Reuters reported that 11 students had been killed.</p>
        <p>''There is no logic,'' said a young woman who works as a secretary in a government office. ''It is killing just for killing now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
