<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Victorious, D'Amato Reconsiders Vow Not to Run Again</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="568233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 ELECTIONS: NEW YORK STATE -- THE WINNER'S DAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'AMATO, ALFONSE M (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABRAMS, ROBERT (ATTY GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DC1630F936A35752C1A964958260" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Victorious, D'Amato Reconsiders Vow Not to Run Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBERTS, SAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hours after winning a re-election victory, Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato retreated from a campaign promise yesterday: he said he might seek a fourth term.</p>
        <p>Trying to neutralize anti-incumbent sentiment by joining the crusade for term limits, Mr. D'Amato announced last month that his race against Attorney General Robert Abrams would be his final campaign for public office. "This will be the last time I run for public office," he said on Oct. 17, after one of the debates with his Democratic challenger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hours after winning a re-election victory, Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato retreated from a campaign promise yesterday: he said he might seek a fourth term.</p>
        <p>Trying to neutralize anti-incumbent sentiment by joining the crusade for term limits, Mr. D'Amato announced last month that his race against Attorney General Robert Abrams would be his final campaign for public office. "This will be the last time I run for public office," he said on Oct. 17, after one of the debates with his Democratic challenger.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, magnanimous and modest in victory and limping from a knee injury sustained when his 23-year-old son Daniel gave him a celebratory tackle, Mr. D'Amato said he was still disinclined to run again and added: "These are my thoughts. They were genuine. But in this business, you never say never."</p>
        <p>Similarly, he said that while he did not intend to run for Governor, he would never say never about that race either.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Senator made two new pledges yesterday. He promised "the best six years I can possibly give." And he vowed that in serving for the first time with a Democrat in the White House he would be part of the "loyal opposition," not an obstructionist.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato defied the 15-point Clinton landslide in New York to score a victory by outspending and outmaneuvering Mr. Abrams, who had emerged wounded from the Democratic primary seven weeks earlier, and by subjecting him to an incessant barrage of attacks and negative campaigning.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Abrams described those attacks as a "viscious onslaught that sought to distort who I am as a person and what my positions are.</p>
        <p>"But there's always a tomorrow, and one thing that I'm lucky about is that I have a great job," Mr. Abrams said. He added that he hoped to retain it when his term expires at the end of 1994, and he did not foreclose the possibility of running for Governor if Mario M. Cuomo doesn't.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Abrams blamed the attacks for his failure in the polls, Mr. D'Amato and others pointed to the strategic and personal inadequacies of the Abrams campaign. "He did the best he could," Mr. D'Amato said of Mr. Abrams, an assessment that politicians from both parties expressed.</p>
        <p>Kieran Mahoney, the D'Amato campaign manager, noted pointedly that the Abrams campaign was much slower to adjust to shifts in political circumstances. "We reacted within eight hours and Abrams was a day behind us on his good days," he said.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Abrams had both the Democratic and Liberal Party lines, this was the first time Mr. D'Amato ran against a single opponent. But if incumbency was considered a political handicap -- and no statewide elected incumbent has lost a general election since 1964 -- it was a fund-raising bonanza. Mr. D'Amato spent over $12 million, including $1 million a week during the seven weeks after the Democratic primary. More than half the budget was for television and radio advertising that kept Mr. Abrams on the defensive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abrams said he raised about $4.3 million for the primary and more than $3 million for the general election.</p>
        <p>More than 100,000 paper absentee and affidavit ballots were ordered impounded yesterday pending the official count, but both sides agreed that the preliminary count is unlikely to be reversed.</p>
        <p>Unofficially, Mr. D'Amato collected 2,999,156 votes, or 51 percent, to 2,890,956, or 49 percent, for Mr. Abrams. It was the closest statewide election since Mr. D'Amato was first elected in 1980 in a three-way race.</p>
        <p>About 65 percent of the registered voters turned out Tuesday. Mr. Abrams did best among women, blacks and Jews, but, in spite of a surge in registration, he did not run well enough in New York City to compensate for Mr. D'Amato's strength in the suburbs and upstate. Mr. D'Amato trailed but ran strongly in Brooklyn and Queens.</p>
        <p>According to exit polls conducted by Voter Research and Surveys, 1 in 4 voters who identified themselves as Democrats and as Clinton supporters voted for Mr. D'Amato as did 4 in 10 Jewish voters, about two-thirds of the voters of Irish and Italian origin and among all non-Hispanic whites, a majority.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 ELECTIONS: NEW YORK STATE -- THE WINNER'S DAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
