<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Is Sued By a Woman Whose Home Was Raided</title>
    <meta content="14COPS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East New York (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Soto, Sandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DE1230F937A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Is Sued By a Woman Whose Home Was Raided</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sandra Soto, whose East New York, Brooklyn, apartment was raided by police on June 5, 1997, files $20 million lawsuit against Police Dept and city; police officials say they are confident officers had raided right apartment, even if it was not one named in warrant and even though no drugs were found; they question timing of lawsuit, suggesting that she is trying to capitalize on recent cases in which police have been accused of raiding wrong apartments or carrying out improper drug raids; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The no-knock search warrant, for a drug raid that the police carried out last June at 396 New Jersey Avenue in East New York, Brooklyn, was quite specific. ''Upon reaching the second-floor landing,'' it said, ''one turns to the left and proceeds to the gray metal door clearly marked with the letter and number '2M.' ''</p>
        <p>There was just one problem: there is no apartment 2M at 396 New Jersey Avenue. The only apartments on the second floor are marked 2L and 2R. And both doors are red, not gray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The no-knock search warrant, for a drug raid that the police carried out last June at 396 New Jersey Avenue in East New York, Brooklyn, was quite specific. ''Upon reaching the second-floor landing,'' it said, ''one turns to the left and proceeds to the gray metal door clearly marked with the letter and number '2M.' ''</p>
        <p>There was just one problem: there is no apartment 2M at 396 New Jersey Avenue. The only apartments on the second floor are marked 2L and 2R. And both doors are red, not gray.</p>
        <p>But the family who lives in apartment 2L claims that the discrepancy did not prevent a team of police officers from breaking down its door about 8:30 A.M. on June 5. Instead of finding the heroin or handguns they were looking for, the family said, the police found only a woman and her two children, who were ages 6 and 1.</p>
        <p>The woman, Sandra Soto, 27, held a news conference yesterday to announce that she had filed a $20 million lawsuit on Tuesday against the Police Department and the city. ''They just broke down the door,'' she said. ''I told them, 'Please, can I take the baby out of the crib?' She was screaming. They said, 'No.' ''</p>
        <p>But police officials said yesterday that they were confident the officers had raided the right apartment, even if it was not the one named in the warrant and even though no drugs or contraband were found.</p>
        <p>And they questioned the timing of Ms. Soto's lawsuit, suggesting that she was trying to capitalize on recent cases in which the police have been accused of raiding the wrong apartments or carrying out improper drug raids.</p>
        <p>''It's just like a number of other cases,'' Police Commissioner Howard Safir said yesterday at his weekly news conference, ''that are popping up as people line up to see if they can sue the city for big dollars with attorneys who hold press conferences rather than litigate.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Soto's lawyer, Susan Karten, said that Ms. Soto filed a complaint with the Civilian Complaint Review Board on the day of the raid and filed a notice of claim against the city -- which paved the way for the lawsuit -- last July.</p>
        <p>''We believe that this incident, as well as the others that followed in its wake,'' Ms. Karten said, ''represents a continuing systemic problem within the New York City Police Department with regard to the way they confirm and verify information obtained by confidential informants in connection with drug raids.''</p>
        <p>The search warrant stated that a confidential informer -- who had been a heroin user for eight years and who said he had sold the drug from time to time -- told a police officer that he had been in apartment 2M and had seen a man named  Lucky ''cutting heroin and placing it in plastic glassine envelopes stamped '%.' '' The informer also said that he had seen a 9-millimeter pistol and a .38-caliber handgun in the apartment, according to the warrant.</p>
        <p>A police official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said yesterday that the informer had proved himself reliable before and after the raid on New Jersey Avenue. And he said the police felt sure that they had raided the right apartment.</p>
        <p>''He went on the description of the location, rather than any letters or numbers on that door,'' the official said of the officer who led the raid.</p>
        <p>Ms. Soto said that she did not know anyone named Lucky. ''I don't mess with anybody in the building,'' she said. ''I'm always in the apartment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
