<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 More Israelis Are Killed as Rain of Rockets From Lebanon Pushes Thousands South</title>
    <meta content="15voices" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/15/world/middleeast/15voices.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1776023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TURMOIL IN THE MIDEAST: THE BORDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Safed (Israel)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myre, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hezbollah</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DD1F30F936A25754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 More Israelis Are Killed as Rain of Rockets From Lebanon Pushes Thousands South</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 More Israelis Are Killed as Rain of Rockets From Lebanon Pushes Thousands South</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG MYRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myre, Greg</byline>
      <dateline>SAFED, Israel, July 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Over 100 rockets strike northern Israel on third straight day of attacks, killing woman and her grandson, while thousands of residents evacuate Safed region; Israeli military says attack was carried out by Hezbollah; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 100 rockets rained down on northern Israel on Friday in a third straight day of attacks, killing a woman and her 5-year-old grandson, while thousands of residents around here packed their cars, boarded buses and hitched rides out of a region that normally enjoys a large influx of tourists on summer weekends.</p>
        <p>The woman and boy were killed when a rocket slammed into the family dining room as they ate a traditional Sabbath dinner in the town of Meron. Several other family members were wounded in the attack, which was carried out by Lebanon's militant Shiite Muslim group Hezbollah, according to the Israeli military. The names of the family were not immediately released.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rockets rained down on northern Israel for a third straight day, killing a woman and her 5-year-old grandson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 100 rockets rained down on northern Israel on Friday in a third straight day of attacks, killing a woman and her 5-year-old grandson, while thousands of residents around here packed their cars, boarded buses and hitched rides out of a region that normally enjoys a large influx of tourists on summer weekends.</p>
        <p>The woman and boy were killed when a rocket slammed into the family dining room as they ate a traditional Sabbath dinner in the town of Meron. Several other family members were wounded in the attack, which was carried out by Lebanon's militant Shiite Muslim group Hezbollah, according to the Israeli military. The names of the family were not immediately released.</p>
        <p>At the bus station in nearby Safed, a town pounded by rockets on Thursday and Friday, Israelis scrambled to grab buses heading south before the start of the Jewish Sabbath at sundown Friday.</p>
        <p>''Safed was a town that had never been hit by rockets until Thursday, so people were quite shocked,'' said Galia Kubi, 66, whose family has lived in this hilltop town for seven generations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kubi planned to spend the weekend with her son in Haifa, a port city that had never been hit by rockets until two exploded there on Thursday evening. That attack alarmed Israelis, particularly those in the north, because Haifa and other nearby cities, at nearly 20 miles south of the Lebanese border, were previously out of range of Hezbollah rockets.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kubi dipped into her travel bag and pulled out a black-and-white photo of her parents' wedding in Safed in 1931, noting that many of the guests were Arab residents of the town.</p>
        <p>She said her father was a close acquaintance of the father of Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian Authority president. Mr. Abbas and other Arab residents of Safed became refugees in the Arab-Israeli war that broke out at Israel's independence in 1948.</p>
        <p>''At least on a personal level, many Jews and Arabs got along,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Soon after, a rocket crashed into the base of an apartment building on a residential street close by, wounding six people, spraying parked cars with shrapnel and covering the road with shattered glass.</p>
        <p>''The force was so strong it blew our front door off its hinges and broke every window,'' said Hammer Heibi, 19, a resident of the three-story building.</p>
        <p>As rescue workers descended on the scene, another rocket crashed not far away, but wounded no one.</p>
        <p>With much of the town deserted, except for a few dogs roaming the streets, Safed's hospital was one of the few places with signs of life.</p>
        <p>Revital Mor grimaced as she sat up in her hospital bed, her right leg broken and her body covered with cuts from a Katyusha rocket that bored into her home on Thursday night as she was preparing dinner.</p>
        <p>Her husband and four of her five children, age 1 to 7, were also wounded, including a daughter who received a serious head wound.</p>
        <p>''I felt the heat and the fire, and then everything went black,'' said Mrs. Mor, 36, who was sharing her hospital room with two of her wounded children. ''My children were crying and I tried to stand up and help, but I couldn't. It happened so suddenly I didn't understand what was happening.''</p>
        <p>Safed, also known as Tsfat, has long attracted artists, who are drawn to its picturesque setting and sweeping views, and religious Jews, who revere the scholars and mystics who made their home here for centuries. Secular tourists and strict Orthodox Jews are commonly seen on the winding, hilly streets of the ancient town.</p>
        <p>Many who live here have a fierce attachment to Safed, including Avi Lebi, 48, a lifelong resident who ignored calls to leave or take cover.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Lebi insisted on keeping his small grocery and restaurant open, cheerfully making falafel sandwiches with pita bread while rockets pounded nearby neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>''I was born here, and this will always be my home,'' Mr. Lebi said. ''Why should I go? I've been to five continents and seen a lot of beautiful places in the world, but this my favorite. There's no way I'll reward the terrorists by leaving.''</p>
        <p>The Israeli government had called for about a half-million residents in the north to head south or take shelter, and most had already heeded the warning.</p>
        <p>On Friday, virtually all the traffic on the main roads was heading south. The few vehicles in the north consisted of police cars, fire trucks, ambulances and army jeeps.</p>
        <p>While many of the Katyushas are hitting towns and cities, a fair number land in open fields in thinly populated regions, touching off brush fires. Large clouds of smoke hung over a forested area near Safed for a second day Friday.</p>
        <p>The Israeli military said that Hezbollah had unleashed more than 100 rockets by late evening on Friday, bringing the total to more than 300 since it began firing on northern Israel on Wednesday in conjunction with a cross-border raid on Israeli soldiers. Two soldiers were seized in the raid and taken to Lebanon, while eight died in fighting on the two sides of the border.</p>
        <p>In all, four Israeli civilians have been killed by rockets since Wednesday, and the more than 30 wounded on Friday brought the three-day total to nearly 150, the military said.</p>
        <p>TURMOIL IN THE MIDEAST: THE BORDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
