<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Painful Questions Trail Barbaro's Race for Life</title>
    <meta content="15rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/15/sports/15rhoden.ready.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1776086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDC1F30F936A25754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Painful Questions Trail Barbaro's Race for Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Barbaros Owners, Painful Questions in a Race for Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William C. Rhoden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the morning of May 20, the day of the Preakness, I received a phone call from a veterinarian who said he had bad news. Our 12-year-old dog, an Australian shepherd named Bear, had internal bleeding in his spleen. The vet felt that if he didn't operate immediately, the dog might die.</p>
        <p>The operation would be expensive but lifesaving, although only in the short run. Our dog had lymphoma and no matter what we did, he might live for only six months. The vet asked me: What did I want to do?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jacksons now face an agonizing question: When do you let go?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the morning of May 20, the day of the Preakness, I received a phone call from a veterinarian who said he had bad news. Our 12-year-old dog, an Australian shepherd named Bear, had internal bleeding in his spleen. The vet felt that if he didn't operate immediately, the dog might die.</p>
        <p>The operation would be expensive but lifesaving, although only in the short run. Our dog had lymphoma and no matter what we did, he might live for only six months. The vet asked me: What did I want to do?</p>
        <p>This was stunning news.</p>
        <p>Anyone who owns a pet understands the trauma of being faced with such decisions about their fate. Animals put absolute trust in owners to do the right thing, to make the right judgments on their behalf. Pets can't tell us when to pull the plug or how much pain they are willing to suffer. I instructed the vet to perform the operation. Bear was family, after all.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there was a Preakness to cover.</p>
        <p>But what was supposed to have been a great afternoon at Pimlico turned into a nightmare. Seconds into the race, the super horse, Barbaro, took a bad step and shattered his right hind leg. The track was quickly filled with medical personnel and ambulances. As a group of track medical officials hurried from the track to Barbaro's barn, I found myself walking next to Roy Jackson, who owns Barbaro with his wife, Gretchen.</p>
        <p>In the span of a few seconds, we said something about our attachment to animals. I shared the news I had received about my own pet earlier that morning. He was a dog, not a million-dollar racehorse like Barbaro, but there was a parallel in the attachment we each felt for an animal so close to us.</p>
        <p>The nation would maintain a vigil for Barbaro in the weeks that followed. There would be a fascination with the advances of veterinary medicine and also with the financial lengths to which the Jacksons were willing to go to save Barbaro's life.</p>
        <p>Then everything suddenly began to unravel in recent days, culminating with the announcement on Thursday that Barbaro had severe laminitis, a condition that occurs when a horse bears excessive weight on one limb, often because of a serious injury to another.</p>
        <p>The Jackson now face an agonizing question: When do you let go?</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, Gretchen Jackson told Joe Drape of The New York Times, ''Barbaro is alive and he is going to be alive and is acting like he wants to live.</p>
        <p>''He is having trouble with his good leg,'' she added. ''We, and he, are not quitting. We're a long way from that.''</p>
        <p>But perhaps not that long. The outlook, simply, is not great, although yesterday the horse's chief veterinarian, Dr. Dean Richardson, said the horse's condition had improved. At least for now, there was a little bit of hope.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, I sat in a veterinarian's examining room, kneeling next to our dog during the final moments of his life. In the weeks after receiving the doctor's call on the morning of the Preakness, Bear had steadily lost strength, though daily medication seemed to provide a degree of comfort. This robust creature who, up until a year ago, could run and walk for hours, could now barely move. After watching him become virtually crippled by arthritis and weakened by lymphoma, we made the decision to euthanize. The subsequent emptiness has been enormous in a way our family never anticipated.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the decision about our dog was easier than any decision the Jacksons might have to make about Barbaro, and not simply because their decision is being played out on a national stage.</p>
        <p>One animal was diagnosed with terminal disease: no matter what was done immediately, there was little we could ultimately do. Death was certain.</p>
        <p>Barbaro's condition is more ambiguous; laminitis, as painful as it is, is not an automatic death sentence. If Barbaro can somehow navigate through the pain and discomfort he faces, he could ultimately live a relatively normal life, although certainly not the life he was bred to live.</p>
        <p>The issue for the Jacksons is just what it might take to get through the next six months, the time needed for Barbaro to grow a new hoof to replace the one damaged by laminitis, and the time also needed for his surgically repaired right leg to keep mending.</p>
        <p>In the last week and a half alone, Barbaro has had four cast changes, a plate and screws replaced and part of his left hoof removed. How many more procedures can he tolerate? Can the Jacksons allow Barbaro to endure some degree of pain and keep hoping?</p>
        <p>If Barbaro's life were now a race, what would be the odds for survival? Twenty to one? Forty to one? His misfortune underlines the hazards of an industry in which powerful animals on spindly legs risk injury and occasional death with just a single misstep.</p>
        <p>And yet everyone involved with Barbaro -- from horse racing fans to horse lovers to veterinarians to the owners -- has run a great race. Somehow, in some way, you would like to see the race continue.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
