<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Female Sailor Quits In Conflict on Crew</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="YACHTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAILBOATS AND SAILING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOCH, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLOYD, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, LARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEARNS, LINDA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AMERICA'S CUP</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1231F932A25752C1A966958260" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Female Sailor Quits In Conflict on Crew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LLOYD, BARBARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Klein, a San Diego yachtsman who was to be a helmsman for William Koch's new America's Cup defense syndicate, resigned unexpectedly last week. His abrupt departure came in the wake of an incident last month in which Klein balked at having a woman assigned to his all-male crew during a regatta in Annapolis.</p>
        <p>Gary Jobson, a co-skipper with Koch on the America 3 defense team, said Koch asked for Klein's resignation. Koch took action as the result of Klein's attitude toward Linda Stearns of Baltimore during the Columbus Cup, a match-racing series Oct. 9-13 on Chesapeake Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry Klein, a San Diego yachtsman who was to be a helmsman for William Koch's new America's Cup defense syndicate, resigned unexpectedly last week. His abrupt departure came in the wake of an incident last month in which Klein balked at having a woman assigned to his all-male crew during a regatta in Annapolis.</p>
        <p>Gary Jobson, a co-skipper with Koch on the America 3 defense team, said Koch asked for Klein's resignation. Koch took action as the result of Klein's attitude toward Linda Stearns of Baltimore during the Columbus Cup, a match-racing series Oct. 9-13 on Chesapeake Bay.</p>
        <p>"There's a lot more to it," Klein said Friday, referring to an apparent power struggle with Koch officials. "But I can't say anything yet because of the internal politics."</p>
        <p>Klein is the 1989 Rolex Yachtsman of the Year and a world champion one-design sailor. He was to work for Koch as an alternate helmsman with Buddy Melges of Zenda, Wis. Stearns Drawn From Pool</p>
        <p>The racing format for the Columbus Cup required skippers to bring three of their own crew members and agree to accept four others from a pool of experienced sailors. Klein drew Stearns, a 43-year-old yachtswoman who was the only female sailor in the pool.</p>
        <p>Stearns has sailed for 34 years. She has extensive experience on large keelboats, including the 44-foot sloops designated for the Columbus Cup regatta. Eight teams competed in the race series; Klein finished third.</p>
        <p>After the first day of racing with Klein, Stearns decided to quit. "I did it for one basic reason," Stearns said. "I thought there was a lot of friction on the boat; that he didn't want a female."</p>
        <p>Mark Fischer, regatta chairman, said last week that Klein was unhappy from the beginning with Stearns. "He was concerned that he didn't know some of the people on his crew, that he didn't know their caliber of sailing," Fischer said. "And he was concerned he had a woman on the boat and maybe nobody else did." Concern on Speed and Strength</p>
        <p>The first day of racing, which allowed for only one match because of light winds, Klein went back to Fischer. Klein was unsure about sailing with Stearns because she did not appear to be "fast enough or strong enough," Fischer said.</p>
        <p>The next morning, with the winds blowing harder, Klein was concerned about being "disadvantaged" by having a woman on board who might not be as strong as the male crew members. But Fischer, who is a friend of Stearns, refused to remove her from the crew.</p>
        <p>"She is probably a more accomplished big-boat sailor than any woman in the country," Fischer said. Knowing her experience and the fact that Klein had agreed in the first place to a lottery for choosing crew, Fischer asked Klein to continue racing. He had not known then of her decision to withdraw.</p>
        <p>Many of the men competing in the regatta weigh about 160 pounds, Fischer said. Stearns, who had sailed with Fischer numerous times on large boats, weighs 145 pounds. Determined to Leave</p>
        <p>Fischer said he tried to talk Stearns out of leaving the boat, but she was determined not to interfere with Klein.</p>
        <p>"I didn't want to psyche him out, so I said I'd get off the boat," Stearns said. "It wasn't that I didn't want to deal with it. I just didn't have the time to."</p>
        <p>Stearns owns and manages a North Sail service loft in Baltimore. She also plans to sail with a woman's team in the next Whitbread Around the World Race.</p>
        <p>Klein has sailed with women before. Last year, the 38-year-old helmsman won the J-24 World Championship with Leslie Deardorff, a sailor from Carpinteria, Calif. "He doesn't treat women on the boat any differently than he would treat a guy," she said on hearing of Klein's resignation. "He never ever gave me the impression he was the least bit chauvinistic toward women. I think the fact that he asked me to sail in the worlds is proof of that."</p>
        <p>Klein had started his own cup defense group last year. Unable to obtain the funding he needed, he agreed to merge his efforts last month with Koch's America 3 team.</p>
        <p>YACHTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
