<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Vietnam, Telling Stories About 'All of Us'</title>
    <meta content="11JENK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/11/arts/theater/11JENK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1414944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vietnam</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Youth Theater (Hanoi)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hung, Le</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jenkins, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Vietnam</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED7113BF932A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Vietnam, Telling Stories About 'All of Us'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Vietnam, Telling Stories About 'All of Us'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Ron</byline>
      <dateline>HANOI, Vietnam</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In Vie</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST Vietnamese are reluctant to discuss the emotional scars left by their country's war with America, but private feelings on the subject sometimes emerge unexpectedly. In May, in Phu Dong, a village on the outskirts of Hanoi, dozens of women sat on the dusty stone floor of an outdoor Buddhist temple, tears streaming down their faces as they watched a play about a family torn apart by war.</p>
        <p>The performance was staged by a troupe of traveling actors who specialize in a style of traditional folk theater known as Ceo (pronounced CHEE-ow). Acted on a bare platform to the live music of a single-stringed lyre and a drum, the plot of the dance-theater piece was set in the 11th century, but the women in the audience wept as if the abused children in the drama were their own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through a traditional folk theater form known as Ceo, audiences in Hanoi find catharsis in an ancient plot about a war-ravaged family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST Vietnamese are reluctant to discuss the emotional scars left by their country's war with America, but private feelings on the subject sometimes emerge unexpectedly. In May, in Phu Dong, a village on the outskirts of Hanoi, dozens of women sat on the dusty stone floor of an outdoor Buddhist temple, tears streaming down their faces as they watched a play about a family torn apart by war.</p>
        <p>The performance was staged by a troupe of traveling actors who specialize in a style of traditional folk theater known as Ceo (pronounced CHEE-ow). Acted on a bare platform to the live music of a single-stringed lyre and a drum, the plot of the dance-theater piece was set in the 11th century, but the women in the audience wept as if the abused children in the drama were their own.</p>
        <p>Boundaries between the suffering endured in the ancient world of the story and the hardships of contemporary Vietnam were blurred by the actors' choice to step off the stage and walk through the crowd. Portraying children reduced to poverty when their father leaves home to fight against foreign invaders, two adult performers roamed through the temple, begging the audience to put money in a ragged straw hat, while a narrator sang of their misfortune in plaintive tones.</p>
        <p>The spectators were mostly women old enough to have lived through the war with the United States, and they responded generously, sobbing as they placed bank notes of Vietnamese dong into the hat. On one level, they understood that they were being asked to support the performers, who rely on contributions from the public, but at the same time the audience members seemed to be responding to deeper impulses, stopping to take the actors' hands or to reach out to them in gestures of comfort and compassion. The collective catharsis was so compelling that even a teenage girl in jeans and a rock 'n' roll T-shirt wiped a tear from her cheek and put a few bills into the hat.</p>
        <p>For nearly half an hour, tears poured from the eyes of Nguyen Thi Thuy, 51, the black-haired actress who had portrayed the destitute young girl. When the play ended, she retreated to a corner to collect herself, still weeping, while her colleagues went on to enact another story.</p>
        <p>''I am crying for the character in the play,'' Ms. Thuy said a few minutes later, through a translator. ''But I am also remembering things that happened to my family and praying that they do not happen to my children.''</p>
        <p>She declined to elaborate, but later that evening, the leader of the troupe, Nguyen Thi Tin, suggested that almost everyone in the audience had memories that allowed them to identify with the play's war-ravaged family. Speaking through a translator in a temple shrine, where the troupe was spending the night before returning to its home in Lam Duong, north of Hanoi, Ms. Tin, 60, smiled, but her voice was somber. ''Many people in Vietnam have lost a father to war,'' she said. ''When we perform this play, the people cry a lot. It fits the situation that their families have lived through.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tin, like the other actors in her troupe, earns her living primarily as a farmer, but believes it is important to help revive the tradition of Ceo that she had first learned as a child. ''For many years after the war,'' she said, ''the government discouraged performances of Ceo, but because it is a tradition that was passed on to us from our ancestors, we want to keep it alive.'' Current government policy, people in the theater here said, now encourages traditional arts.</p>
        <p>Theater artists in the large cities also use Ceo, as well as other traditional drama forms, to create a modern hybrid that resembles Western theater but maintains its Vietnamese roots. Their companies, once fully subsidized by the government, now survive on smaller subsidies and box-office receipts. As a result, they must find a blend of new and old staging styles that can compete for audiences with television and film.</p>
        <p>About half a dozen of these companies exist in Hanoi, performing a repertory that includes everything from adaptations of Shakespeare and American musicals to new plays by Vietnamese writers. But because most theaters have erratic performance schedules, foreign visitors usually end up at a large downtown theater with a built-in pool, the renowned Thang Long Water Puppet Theater of Hanoi, which presents two shows a night. On weekends tourists can also see a company of Ceo folk performers who present excerpts from a variety of plays at the Ngoc Son Temple, a Buddhist shrine on a small island in Hoan Kiem Lake, in the center of Hanoi. These fragments give spectators a taste of the lyrical physical movements and stylized vocal rhythms that are characteristic of Ceo performances, but they lack the intensity of audience interaction that is at the root of the form's power.</p>
        <p>For those unable to trek into the villages for traditional festival performances of Ceo, the best way to experience it is to visit Hanoi's Youth Theater, which is not a theater for children but the city's most vibrant contemporary theater company. Besides being the only modern company that performs regularly in Hanoi and tours to Saigon (Ho Chi Minh City), the Youth Theater maintains a link to the Ceo tradition through the musicality of its acting style and commitment to connecting with the audience.</p>
        <p>Le Hung, 50, the theater's director, studied Western drama for eight years in Moscow but treasures the bond between actors and audiences that is characteristic of traditional Vietnamese theater forms like Ceo. He explained: ''In the Russian tradition of Stanislavsky, the actor says, 'I will tell you a story about me.' In the German tradition of Brecht, the actor says, 'I will tell you a story about them.' In the Vietnamese tradition, the actor says, 'You and I will tell each other a story about all of us.' ''</p>
        <p>Speaking in a small studio at the Hanoi Academy of Cinema and Theater, where he was conducting a workshop for professional actors from all over Vietnam, the bearded Mr. Hung wore a green United States Army combat shirt and parachute pants emblazoned with a Nike swoosh. To demonstrate his point about the participatory nature of Vietnamese drama, he asked two actors to stage a famous scene from the repertory of Ceo. A middle-aged man and woman, who said they had studied Ceo since their first days of acting school, re-enacted a conflict between an unmarried pregnant woman and a mandarin government official who tries to denounce her morals.</p>
        <p>''I am in charge of this village,'' he shouted. ''There is order because of me. I may take bribes, but only a little.'' Although the mandarin had a stick and the woman was unarmed, she won the argument by mocking his hypocrisy through suggestive gestures that involved her grabbing at his words as they left his mouth and throwing them on the ground. The actors watching the scene cheered her on with hoots of laughter and applause.</p>
        <p>When the same scene was performed by Ms. Tin's company in Phu Dong, the audience's response was similarly boisterous, as if the humiliation of the medieval stage mandarin provided them with vicarious revenge for every corrupt government official they had ever encountered.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Hung directs his own plays at the 800-seat Youth Theater, the exuberant audience reaction is also an essential element of the performance. After laughing throughout an evening of Mr. Hung's plays, a 20-year-old university student, Nguyen Thu Ha, pointed at the stage, saying, ''That is exactly what our life is like.''</p>
        <p>The highlight of the evening had been a short satirical farce about a man who could not stop talking and was imprisoned in a mental hospital, where he discovers that the doctor who stops up his mouth to silence him talks even more than he does and makes less sense. The play clearly made use of the heightened rhythms and earthy acting style that characterize Ceo, but the fact that the characters were in modern dress helped the young urban audience to identify with them.</p>
        <p>''Our society is afflicted by this talking disease,'' said Mr. Hung in his acting studio the day after the performance. ''And it is our responsibility to try to cure it so that people in power spend more time doing things and less time speaking words that have no meaning.''</p>
        <p>The overall title that Mr. Hung uses for his evening of one-act plays is ''Laughing and Crying,'' a reference to the double-edged aspect of his work, a quality that can also be found in the tragicomic folk plays of Ceo. To demonstrate the connection between comedy and tragedy, Mr. Hung asked his actors to improvise another classic scene from the Ceo repertory. In it, a man looks for justice from a trio of judges made up of a deaf man, a blind man and a mute. The humor, sometimes crude, had an exhilarating effect on the onlookers, who howled with delight.</p>
        <p>''You see how the actors talk to the audience, at the same time that they talk to each other,'' said Mr. Hung. ''That is why the bond between Vietnamese actors and their audiences is the strongest in the world. It makes the spectators have fun, but it also gives them something to think about when they go home. It is very Vietnamese to be laughing when we are hiding tears. The audience laughs at the deaf, mute and blind men, and then goes home and cries that maybe these are the people running our country.''</p>
        <p>While Vietnamese artists are not exempt from government censorship, they seem to understand intuitively how far they can stretch the limits of artistic license, using satire and historical distance to make their points indirectly.</p>
        <p>When ''Laughing and Crying'' ended its run at the Youth Theater, it was to be followed by Mr. Hung's adaptation of ''Macbeth,'' which employs the techniques of another traditional Vietnamese theater form called Tuong. (Both productions were scheduled to tour Ho Chi Minh City this month.) Similar in style to Beijing Opera, Tuong provides Mr. Hung's company with techniques that he said ''give Shakespeare a Vietnamese point of view.''</p>
        <p>As an example, he cited witches' scenes that would be accompanied by the frenzied drumming rhythms of Tuong, traditionally used with ancient stories of betrayal and regicide. Mr. Hung pounded with a pencil to demonstrate the percussive techniques that he said would set the mood for characters whose ''relentless pursuit of power explodes into the madness of desire.''</p>
        <p>''This is also a story that the history of Vietnam has prepared our audience to understand,'' he said. ''As if Shakespeare had written it just for us.''</p>
        <p>THEATER Ron Jenkins, the author of ''Dario Fo and Franca Rame: Artful Laughter,'' is the translator and director of Mr. Fo's play ''Peasants' Bible,'' opening on Aug. 22 at the 7 Stages Theater in Atlanta.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ron Jenkins, the author of ''Dario Fo and Franca Rame: Artful Laughter,'' is the translator and director of Mr. Fo's play ''Peasants' Bible,'' opening on Aug. 22 at the 7 Stages Theater in Atlanta.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
