<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Little Leaguer's Age Ends His Team's Hopes</title>
    <meta content="11SLAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1415007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="FOR THE RECORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bedford Hills (Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maruri, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5D9163AF932A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Little Leaguer's Age Ends His Team's Hopes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Little League team in Bedford Hills, NY, which will not be allowed to play in 13- and 14-year-old division championship because star player Alex Maruri is only 12; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE world championship of the Little League Junior Division for 13- and 14-year-olds will be contested this week in Taylor, Mich. A champion is to be crowned Saturday night.</p>
        <p>But in Bedford Hills there is a team that was not eliminated on the field, yet lost its chance to play for that championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE world championship of the Little League Junior Division for 13- and 14-year-olds will be contested this week in Taylor, Mich. A champion is to be crowned Saturday night.</p>
        <p>But in Bedford Hills there is a team that was not eliminated on the field, yet lost its chance to play for that championship.</p>
        <p>After winning the district and sectional championship and reaching the New York State finals, Bedford Hills was forfeited out of the competition 12 days ago for having a player who violated the age requirements.</p>
        <p>Last year, the Bronx Little League made headlines and was removed from the championship round when it was discovered that its star, Danny Almonte, a pitcher, was competing with a revised birth certificate that took two years off his age.</p>
        <p>Bedford Hills's problem also revolved around its star's age. Alex Maruri was hitting .727 in the junior tournament. He had won the sectional final with a last-inning grand slam. In the game that put his team in the state final, he was 3 for 4 with a triple and 6 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>And then some team in the state finals field -- which was not identified -- complained about his age.</p>
        <p>Maruri was only 12. To be eligible, a player had to be 13 by July 31. Maruri will be 13 next Feb. 4.</p>
        <p>''My kids were robbed of a dream,'' Kevin Leonaggeo, the Bedford Hills manager, said. ''They still don't understand it. A half-hour before we were to go up to Stony Point for the state finals, we were informed we were forfeited out.''</p>
        <p>The Bedford Hills situation, unlike Almonte's, was a case of a misunderstanding, not deception.</p>
        <p>''I thought the age requirement was 14 and under,'' said Leonaggeo, whose team had advanced into the Little League juniors competition from the 14-and-under division of the Westchester-Putnam Baseball Association. Virtually all local leagues have a 14-and-under division; apparently no one involved was aware the Little League competition had narrower age rules.</p>
        <p>''Why did they wait until the state finals?'' Leonaggeo continued. ''We originally turned in his birth certificate before the tournament to get a waiver for Alex because he is from Chappaqua. We turned a copy of it in before the district tournament, again before the sectionals and yet again before the states. Didn't anyone check it?''</p>
        <p>According to Little League national headquarters in Williamsport, Pa., each team is responsible for following the strict age guidelines in its rule book. For Lance Van Auken of the Little League Baseball Tournament Committee, the issue was clear-cut.</p>
        <p>''Any time there is an ineligible player,'' he said, ''we universally forfeit the last game. The committee's decision was unanimous.''</p>
        <p>How often has a tournament team been forfeited for using an underage player? ''This is the first time since I joined the committee in 1996,'' Van Auken said.</p>
        <p>The forfeit was Bedford Hills's second loss in the state championships, thus knocking it out.</p>
        <p>Maruri cried for his teammates' loss. ''I found it unfair,'' he said. ''They had my birth certificate the whole time.''</p>
        <p>Victor Maruri, Alex's father, mourned ''a magic season with such an unfortunate ending.''</p>
        <p>''Alex may be 12 but he is 5-foot-8, 160 pounds and hits the ball 350 feet,'' the father said. ''In regular Little League for 11- and 12-year-olds, they pitch from only 45 feet away, not 60 feet as in juniors. The baselines are just 60 feet. I would be genuinely concerned that he might hurt someone with a batted ball. I put him where his ability dictated. That's 14-and-under leagues.''</p>
        <p>Leonaggeo's son, also Kevin, was on the Bedford Hills team. ''I could understand if Alex was too old,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Two days after the forfeit, Leonaggeo gathered his team and the parents together. ''I showed them the district flag,'' he said. ''I showed them the sectional flag. And I told them that in my mind they were state champions.''</p>
        <p>FOR THE RECORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
