<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New U.N. Monitor Says Iraq Is Still Hiding Data on Weapons</title>
    <meta content="T08IRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butler, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6D9163CF93BA35753C1A961958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New U.N. Monitor Says Iraq Is Still Hiding Data on Weapons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Butler, in his first report since taking office in July as United Nations' chief monitor of Iraq's weapons programs, says Saddam Hussein's Government is continuing to hide information on biological arms and is also withholding some data on chemical weapons and missiles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first report since taking office in July, the new United Nations chief monitor of Iraq's weapons programs concludes that the Government of Saddam Hussein is continuing to hide information on biological arms and is also withholding some data on chemical weapons and missiles.</p>
        <p>The report is by by Richard Butler, the Australian arms control expert who is now executive chairman of the United Nations Special Commission, set up by the Security Council in 1991 to disarm Iraq after the Persian Gulf war. It rejects Iraq's contention that it has met all the requirements for the lifting of sanctions imposed after its 1990 invasion of Kuwait. United Nations satisfaction that Iraq has met disarmament requirements is tied to the nation's freedom to sell oil beyond the limited quantities allowed to raise money for urgent civilian needs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first report since taking office in July, the new United Nations chief monitor of Iraq's weapons programs concludes that the Government of Saddam Hussein is continuing to hide information on biological arms and is also withholding some data on chemical weapons and missiles.</p>
        <p>The report is by by Richard Butler, the Australian arms control expert who is now executive chairman of the United Nations Special Commission, set up by the Security Council in 1991 to disarm Iraq after the Persian Gulf war. It rejects Iraq's contention that it has met all the requirements for the lifting of sanctions imposed after its 1990 invasion of Kuwait. United Nations satisfaction that Iraq has met disarmament requirements is tied to the nation's freedom to sell oil beyond the limited quantities allowed to raise money for urgent civilian needs.</p>
        <p>''There is incomprehension of why Iraq is persisting so strongly with both refusing to make the facts known about its biological weapons program and why it is so insistent on blocking the commission's own efforts to reach those facts,'' Mr. Butler wrote. ''The outstanding problems are numerous and grave.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday Mr. Butler, a former Australian representative at the United Nations, will discuss the report with the five permanent members of the Security Council -- Britain, China, France, Russia and the United States. The full Security Council is expected to begin debating the Iraq situation on Oct. 16.</p>
        <p>The report, while finding some progress in accounting for chemical weapons and missiles, suggests that Mr. Hussein will not find Mr. Butler any less vigilant or insistent on complete disclosure than his predecessor, Rolf Ekeus, now Sweden's Ambassador to the United States, who devised and ran the inspection system for six years.</p>
        <p>A separate monitoring system for nuclear weapons was established in Iraq by the International Atomic Energy Agency, which is close to declaring Iraq free of arms.</p>
        <p>The newest findings on other prohibited weapons, based on investigations as late as the beginning of this month, will not give much support to Security Council members like Russia, France and Egypt, which (often with the backing of China) have argued for a quicker pace in ending sanctions.</p>
        <p>''Iraq's behavior has not improved,'' said James P. Rubin, the State Department spokesman in an interview today. ''There is no reason for any serious proposal to ease the sanctions. On the contrary, the only question is how strongly the council will react to their continued intransigence.''</p>
        <p>In September, Tariq Aziz, Iraq's Deputy Prime Minister and chief negotiator on the sanctions issue, declared in a letter to the United Nations that Baghdad had made a ''full, final and complete disclosure'' on its biological weapons programs, which it says have all been terminated. But today's United Nations report replies that Iraq, which had been experimenting with some of the deadliest germ warfare compounds known to science, has still failed to give ''a remotely credible account'' of the weapons.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi failure to respond satisfactorily to increasingly direct questions about suspected biological weapons projects, coupled with what the commission describes as obvious efforts to conceal evidence or move it out of the way of inspectors, makes it easier for the United States to press for additional sanctions against Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
