<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Art; Works of Myron Stout, Standing on Their Own</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="397497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRENSON, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOUT, MYRON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUPKA, FRANTISEK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILVERMAN, MARTIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMSON, PHILEMONA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE173FF931A35752C1A966958260" item-length="1704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Art; Works of Myron Stout, Standing on Their Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRENSON, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the early 1950's, when the Abstract Expressionists were changing the scale and character of American art with their big, expansive, "all over" paintings, Myron Stout was moving toward small, highly concentrated black-and-white abstractions in which all signs of spontaneity, heroism and personality seemed to have vanished. During this crucial moment of his career, he was painting both with the current and against it, charting a course that would make him one of postwar American art's more influential outsiders.</p>
        <p>There is more than a touch of contrariness in Stout's career and, before the black-and-white paintings that became, in effect, a series of journeys without end, a good deal of movement. Stout was born in Denton, Tex., in 1908, and taught art in Honolulu both during and after the war. In 1949, he -- like his teacher and friend Hans Hofmann -- began dividing his time between New York City and Provincetown, Mass. In 1954, just as New York was establishing itself as</p>
        <p>the</p>
        <p>artistic center, Stout settled in Provincetown, where he lived until his death in 1987. In his small studio by the water, with the companionship of sun and sand, he painted in black and white.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the early 1950's, when the Abstract Expressionists were changing the scale and character of American art with their big, expansive, "all over" paintings, Myron Stout was moving toward small, highly concentrated black-and-white abstractions in which all signs of spontaneity, heroism and personality seemed to have vanished. During this crucial moment of his career, he was painting both with the current and against it, charting a course that would make him one of postwar American art's more influential outsiders.</p>
        <p>There is more than a touch of contrariness in Stout's career and, before the black-and-white paintings that became, in effect, a series of journeys without end, a good deal of movement. Stout was born in Denton, Tex., in 1908, and taught art in Honolulu both during and after the war. In 1949, he -- like his teacher and friend Hans Hofmann -- began dividing his time between New York City and Provincetown, Mass. In 1954, just as New York was establishing itself as</p>
        <p>the</p>
        <p>artistic center, Stout settled in Provincetown, where he lived until his death in 1987. In his small studio by the water, with the companionship of sun and sand, he painted in black and white.</p>
        <p>The two-gallery exhibition in Manhattan -- at Kent Fine Art on 57th Street and the Barbara Flynn Gallery in SoHo -- is the largest Stout has been given in New York City since his retrospective at the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1980. Some of the roughly 60 works at the two galleries were at the Whitney. Many of the relatively busy, warmly colored, urban-inspired paintings of 1948 to 1953 (most of them at Kent) -- suggesting tipped floors, or odd ground plans, or irregular scaffoldings -- were not. Nor was there as large a sampling of the landscape sketches Stout did in Provincetown in the summer of 1953, which clarify his attraction to light and his feeling for the drift and swirls of wind and sand.</p>
        <p>One big difference between Stout and Abstract Expressionism is temperament. A Stout painting does not impose itself or ask for attention. It has an air of comfortable but slightly edgy self-sufficiency. The painting is there for the viewer, but it also seems to exist on its own. If you want to address it, fine, but if you do not want to, that's all right too. It wants, but it does not need, the viewer to complete it.</p>
        <p>Like some of the Minimalism that both built upon and reacted against Abstract Expressionism, Stout's work is in many ways rooted in 19th-century American painting. Following such Hudson River School painters as Thomas Cole and FredericEdwin Church, Stout approached painting almost as a form of asceticism and prayer. In the black-and-white paintings, he was as painstaking in his quest for pictorial perfection as Church, as mesmerized by light as Martin Johnson Heade, as enthralled by the moon as Albert Pinkham Ryder.</p>
        <p>As different as Stout was from the Abstract Expressionists in tone and scale, he was also taught by Hofmann, he admired Barnett Newman, and he shared many Abstract Expressionist concerns. He was drawn to Greek myth and tragedy and believed that human life was fundamentally conflicted. In one of the black-and-white abstractions at Kent, white beams cut though a charcoal ground like blades; in another, two sides of segments suggesting a tile floor, one side black, the other white, seem pitted against each other like armies.</p>
        <p>Like some of the Abstract Expressionists, and like another Texas-born abstract painter of his generation, Forrest Bess, Stout believed in symbols as powerful and necessary forms of reconciliation. In an entry in his journal from 1953, cited by Henry Geldzahler in his introduction to the current exhibition's catalogue, Stout wrote: "The life of a symbol is in its refusal to become fixed. It is through its metaphorical quality that it takes on a thousand meanings." He wanted his curious shapes, like a flexed arm, or a U-turn sign, or a straitjacket, to become concentrations of affection, tension, acceptance and struggle.</p>
        <p>In a painting like "Aegis," on which he worked for 25 years, he nearly succeeds. The white form largely occupying a black ground is shaped like a head or shield that gradually seems to fill with light and take on a sense of purpose that makes the image seem inevitable. Stout loved engaging pictorial questions for which there were no absolute answers. How do you get the right light? How do you get the entire edge of a shape to be equally finished and equally active? How do you find the right balance between black and white? Questions seem more important to Stout than answers. The pictorial journey meant as much to him as any notion of pictorial home.</p>
        <p>Stout's light is worth a study in itself. The shield shape in "Aegis" holds light, much as a Greek column inhales sunlight into stone. Stout's primary light is nocturnal. The mature paintings carry within them the memory of moonlight on sand and water, or on a wide, open plain. In "Moon Lady," from 1964-71, six crescents turn into the full moon's arms and legs. Although Stout lived for 35 years in a place by the water known for its crisp, warm, glowing light, it is from the moon that all of his light seems to pour. It is under the light of the moon that the dance begins. Although Stout's work usually seems right there, directly in front of you, it is clear from this show that more often than not it is someplace else.</p>
        <p>The work of Myron Stout remains at Kent Fine Art, 41 East 57th Street, through Nov. 10 and at the Barbara Flynn Gallery, 113 Crosby Street, through Dec. 15. Frantisek Kupka Claude Bernard Gallery 33 East 74th Street Through Nov. 10</p>
        <p>With the Kasimir Malevich show coming to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in February and the Burgoyne Diller show currently at the Whitney Museum of American Art, it is also useful to get a glimpse of Frantisek Kupka, one of the more mystical pioneers of abstract art. The show includes some good and some quirky paintings and it helps define continuities and changes within the Kupka esthetic. It certainly suggests the many chapters of the history of abstraction into which Kupka can be written.</p>
        <p>The roughly 20 paintings and gouaches, some of them museum loans, span almost 40 years of a long career. (Kupka was born in Bohemia in 1871 and died outside Paris in 1957.) An early, undated watercolor reveals the kind of freewheeling romantic approach that preceded his move into abstraction. The most expressionist work, the "Study for a Tale of Pistils and Stamens II," from 1919-20, has a good deal of force in its landscape of earthy, marine and female forms. We are not far here from the nature abstractions of Georgia O'Keeffe and Arthur Dove.</p>
        <p>Most of the works in the show, however, are in the realm not of flowingly organic but of hard-edged architectural abstraction. Dynamism was crucially important to him. In his meticulously carved rectangles and carefully built conduitlike lines, he presents abstraction as the architecture of a new life. His rectangles can be like forests of skyscrapers. Sometimes his architectural forms seem to be building themselves. For reasons linked to his spiritualism and nature philosophy, Kupka was fascinated by ideas of levitation and growth.It is the love of verticality that links together the organic and industrial abstractions in this show. Martin Silverman Michael Walls Gallery 137 Greene Street Through Nov. 10</p>
        <p>Martin Silverman's new work includes ink drawings on Hebrew, Chinese, American and Hispanic newspapers and small painted bronze sculptures of performing figures. One reason why much of the work is funny and convincing is the skillful modeling. Another is the theatrical sense that comes in part from a real feeling for the history of vaudeville and film. One figure, holding a cane in his right hand and with his left foot in the air, is called "Vaudevillian." "Harold," inspired by the comedian Harold Lloyd, is a sculpture of a man hanging for dear life from the long hand of a huge clock face. Something is always about to happen. Throughout the show, the artist, like the man in "Pie," seems to be waiting to hit us with a pie in the face.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Silverman clearly identifies with his performers, he also makes sculpture about his personal life. "Country Life," with its benign cow standing on top of -- and face to face with -- a supine, quizzical man, is inspired by his farmland experience. The show is also inspired by current events. "Gulf" is a gas mask made up of an oil-bottle mouth and drainpipe nose and eyes. "The Endowment" consists of a part boy, part man looking embarrassed as he holds his gigantic top hat over his crotch. Like a good performer, Mr. Silverman knows how to make a point and still show us a good time.  Philemona Williamson June Kelly Gallery 591 Broadway (near Houston Street) Through Nov. 6</p>
        <p>All eight of the canvases by Philemona Williamson in this show are the same size (5 by 4 feet, or 4 by 5 feet), which makes them seem like pages in a gigantic children's book. The story the canvases tell is about the moment between childhood and adulthood. Sex is in the air. Competition is fierce. Everything is between innocence and experience. Everyone is self-absorbed. No one really knows what is happening. In just about every work there is one face that looks out at us with a deadpan expression, as if someone inside or outside the painting had just told a stinker of a joke.</p>
        <p>These are antic works, some of them dangerously close to being anecdotal or illustrational, but all of them containing something that is wacky and bizarre, starting with the preference for lemon yellow. In "Blue Doughnuts," the doughnuts are actually dark blue and one girl, who brings to mind a madonna of Piero della Francesca, sits on a peculiar-looking rocking horse, a ram without rockers. The children in these paintings do not always wear matching shoes. A girl skidding almost out of a painting suggests one of Picasso's noble Neo-Classical women. Balthus is everywhere in this vision of childhood as a manic, playful, incoherent place. What will be the next chapter in a pictorial world in which nothing is stable, no one listens and adulthood lurks?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
