<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Chief Fights Rising Pressure</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="433225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRUTALITY AND HARASSMENT CHARGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GATES, DARYL F (POLICE CHIEF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1339F93BA15750C0A967958260" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Chief Fights Rising Pressure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As pressure increased for his resignation after the beating by police officers of a motorist, Police Chief Daryl F. Gates of Los Angeles announced a program today to reduce incidents of police brutality in the city.</p>
        <p>City Councilman Micheal Woo today became the first elected city official to call for Chief Gates's resignation, and Mayor Tom Bradley edged closer to making a similar demand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As pressure increased for his resignation after the beating by police officers of a motorist, Police Chief Daryl F. Gates of Los Angeles announced a program today to reduce incidents of police brutality in the city.</p>
        <p>City Councilman Micheal Woo today became the first elected city official to call for Chief Gates's resignation, and Mayor Tom Bradley edged closer to making a similar demand.</p>
        <p>"In order for the healing process to effectively begin, there must be a retirement of the chief," the Mayor said. "He must remove himself from the center of this controversy before that process can begin."</p>
        <p>Mr. Woo, who has been a critic of the chief in the past, said, "The time has come for Chief Gates to resign."  Misconduct Complaints Logged</p>
        <p>Mr. Woo said his decision to speak out had been influenced by a legislative analyst's report that found that the Police Department's internal affairs division had investigated only 36 of 140 reports of police misconduct brought to its attention in the past five years.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates, who has held his job for 13 years, is a Civil Service appointee who can be removed only for cause, through a potentially long and complicated legal process.</p>
        <p>The City Attorney, Kenneth G. Hahn, said in a legal opinion today that the chief could be removed through a recall vote under the city charter. A citizens' petition has already been filed with the city government.</p>
        <p>Announcing a 10-point program to monitor and improve police service, Chief Gates said that a five-member panel would examine past incidents of excessive force and that training procedures and policies regarding the use of force would be reviewed.</p>
        <p>"We must look for any and all conditions that may have contributed to the development of attitudes and patterns of behavior that could have led to this kind of gross misconduct," he said.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates and his department have been under intense criticism since the national broadcast of an amateur videotape of police officers beating Rodney G. King, a black motorist who was stopped for speeding.  Refusing to Answer Agents</p>
        <p>A sergeant and three patrolmen have pleaded not guilty to charges of assault in the March 3 incident, and a grand jury continues to review evidence that could implicate some of the 17 other police officers who were present.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation, preparing for a possible Federal civil rights indictment in the case, has attempted this week to interview all 250 officers assigned to the Foothill Division station to which the indicted officers belong. But at least 25 of those officers have told bureau agents they would cooperate only under duress, at which point the agents have terminated the interviews, lawyers for the officers said.</p>
        <p>Diane Marchant, a lawyer working for the Los Angeles Police Protective League, the police union, said officers were refusing to cooperate voluntarily because to do so would open them to possible use of their testimony against them. She also said the officers were under standing departmental instructions, repeated in a recent memorandum, to cooperate with outside investigations. Failure to do so could amount to insubordination and could jeopardize their jobs, she said.</p>
        <p>"When that is the reason you are talking, it is the same as having it beaten out of you with a rubber hose," she said, referring to the possible loss of a job.</p>
        <p>The refusal of the officers to cooperate except under duress has its legal roots in the 1967 United States Supreme Court case Garrity v. New Jersey. In that case the Court said a police officer who was compelled to answer questions in the course of a criminal investigation could not be made subject to the later use of his statements in a criminal proceeding against him.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Carlos Fernandez, a spokesman for the F.B.I., said, "If any officer does not wish to be interviewed he will not be interviewed."</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mayor Bradley expressed disappointment with the failure of officers to cooperate fully with Federal investigators.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates has not commented pulicly on the officers' actions regarding the investigation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
