<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Tamest of Starts, the Seeds of Enchantment</title>
    <meta content="10GAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/10/technology/circuits/10game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1503418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nintendo Company Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0D6133DF933A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Tamest of Starts, the Seeds of Enchantment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Tamest of Starts, the Seeds of Enchantment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles Herold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold Game Theory column reviews The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Walker and Kung Fu Chaos; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LEGEND OF ZELDA: THE WIND WAKER  Developed and published by Nintendo for the GameCube; $49.99; for all ages.</p>
        <p>KUNG FU CHAOS  Developed by Just Add Monsters and published by Microsoft Game Studios for the Xbox; $49.99; for ages 13 and older.</p>
        <p>I LIKE a game that starts like a tornado, a game that immediately catches you up in frenzied fun or stunning beauty, a game that grabs you and runs. That in no way describes Nintendo's The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Waker, which breaks from the gate like a snail on Valium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A visitor to the planet Zelda finds its dragons, fairy goddesses and especially its puzzles charming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LEGEND OF ZELDA: THE WIND WAKER  Developed and published by Nintendo for the GameCube; $49.99; for all ages.</p>
        <p>KUNG FU CHAOS  Developed by Just Add Monsters and published by Microsoft Game Studios for the Xbox; $49.99; for ages 13 and older.</p>
        <p>I LIKE a game that starts like a tornado, a game that immediately catches you up in frenzied fun or stunning beauty, a game that grabs you and runs. That in no way describes Nintendo's The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Waker, which breaks from the gate like a snail on Valium.</p>
        <p>After sitting through the recounting of a long, dull myth about an ancient savior, the player is put in control of the protagonist, Link, and begins to explore his small island village, getting to know the controller setup and learning the fundamentals of battle. I had previously started two other games in the Zelda series but found both so lackluster that I stopped playing within a couple of hours. While these games had received glowing, almost fanatical reviews, I concluded they simply weren't for me.</p>
        <p>After a couple of hours with the latest Zelda, I was once again feeling a little bored. The repetitive score got on my nerves and the game play seemed unexceptional. But there were nice moments here and there, so I kept playing. After about five hours, I was thinking that Zelda was a decent little action adventure with enjoyable game play. You jump from cliff to cliff, wield your sword against a variety of funny-looking creatures and swing from ropes, as in many other games. It struck me as a pretty good game for children.</p>
        <p>Around the 10th hour, I realized that I was completely immersed, enthralled, and unable to stop playing. Somehow the game had gone from being passable to being absolutely mesmerizing.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Zelda starts so slowly because it has such a long way to go. Zelda is immense, a huge world with a seemingly inexhaustible supply of new places to visit and new things to discover. Like Ravel's ''Bolero,'' it begins as a barely noticeable wind and slowly builds into a symphonic cacophony.</p>
        <p>The first indication of the game's scope comes when Link takes charge of a boat with a talking dragon head and begins to sail the vast ocean of Zelda, depths filled with treasures and sea monsters. As you travel from island to island, the sun rises and sets, storms pass by and cyclones occasionally pick you up and hurl you to a new place. Link's missions have a mythic quality, as the world of Zelda is full of talking trees and dragons and ancient stone idols that come to life. With his magic flute, Link can control the wind itself, sailing wherever he wants or riding across the sky on a giant leaf.</p>
        <p>Zelda is essentially a game of exploration in which the player is encouraged to find every treasure and secret, revisiting locations as new tools are acquired that will open new areas. Link must exhibit strong battle skills to fight the world's many monsters and great ingenuity to solve the game's myriad puzzles. I love puzzles, and this was one of the elements that began to win me over. Challenging but logical, Zelda's brain teasers hit that fine line between torture and delight. The smarter I had to be to play Zelda, the more fun I had.</p>
        <p>I still don't love Zelda quite the way others do. While many reviewers have lauded the game's graphics, they left me for the most part unmoved, although I was impressed by the absolutely gorgeous fairy goddess rooms. The dialogue can be painfully repetitive; the fish from whom you can request sea maps all begin with the same little speech when you meet them. The music is generic and repetitive, and the game's story is inconsequential. An inventory system in which you must assign one of the many items in Link's possession to a controller button to use it is a complete pain.</p>
        <p>Yet none of that really matters. As you progress through the game, acquiring tools, learning tunes for your magical flute, discovering secrets and finding places to explore, Zelda keeps you transfixed. The game doesn't grab you in the first five minutes, but once it has got you, it refuses to let go.</p>
        <p>While Zelda is like a grand symphony, complex, varied and deep, the fighting game Kung Fu Chaos is more reminiscent of a police siren. Zelda builds from a whisper, but Chaos starts at a loud scream and stays there. Frenetic and noisy, it tosses the player into the role of a martial arts actor who is led through scenes of chaos and carnage by a high-strung movie director. One can play as a variety of actors, including a fighting monkey and a disco skater. The battle is fast and furious as you punch, kick and flip your attackers. Shout out a few good insults as you knock an opponent to the ground, and you will build up the power for a supermove that will wipe out everyone around you.</p>
        <p>In contrast to fighting games that take place in an arena, Chaos features battles that may travel forward. You might have to run up a flight of rickety stairs as the room behind you fills with gas, or leap along a treacherous series of collapsing bridges; in one mission you find yourself on board the Titanic, battling ninjas as water laps at your feet and pianos and passengers slide down the deck toward you.</p>
        <p>Chaos is not so much a fighting game as an arcade-style action game with a lot of fighting in it. Many levels have no battles at all, but rather simple arcade action in which you must catch falling objects or throw things; one sequence is basically a fast-paced clone of PacMan. It's a somewhat lazy way to pad out the game, but Chaos's frenetic pace makes pretty much everything in it fun, even if you've seen it before.</p>
        <p>To win each level of Chaos, you must vanquish enough ninjas to acquire at least three of five possible stars. This apparently affects the success of your movie; one star is described as ''direct to video'' while four is a ''sleeper hit.'' I never managed to get five stars, but I assume that would be a blockbuster.</p>
        <p>The framing scenes of the wacky ranting director are, one presumes, supposed to be funny; the developers seem to believe that humor is best when loud, and they're wrong. Fortunately, the game moves at such a furious pace that one hardly has time to be annoyed by the director's ravings and pratfalls.</p>
        <p>Chaos packs more excitement into its first 30 minutes than Zelda does into its first five hours, yet Zelda's deep, engrossing game play leaves a more lasting impression. Chaos twirls you around, leaving you breathless, but the slow-building tornado of Zelda will pick you up and carry you someplace you may never want to leave.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
