<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Turns Another Corner</title>
    <meta content="19FRI2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jiang Zemin (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D81138F93AA2575AC0A961958260" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Turns Another Corner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that centerpiece of Chinese Communist Party Congress was Pres Jiang Zemin's call for sale, merger or closing of vast majority of China's state-owned enterprises; asserts that his declaration exceeded expectations and signals boldest economic transformation attempted by Beijing since early 1980's; maintains that Jiang and his party colleagues regrettably showed no parallel interest in political liberalization (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The centerpiece of this week's Chinese Communist Party Congress was President Jiang Zemin's call for the sale, merger or closing of the vast majority of China's state-owned enterprises. His declaration exceeded expectations and signals the boldest economic transformation attempted by Beijing since the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>Regrettably, Mr. Jiang and his party colleagues showed no parallel interest in political liberalization, the key to consolidating a market economy and relieving chronic tensions between China and the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The centerpiece of this week's Chinese Communist Party Congress was President Jiang Zemin's call for the sale, merger or closing of the vast majority of China's state-owned enterprises. His declaration exceeded expectations and signals the boldest economic transformation attempted by Beijing since the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>Regrettably, Mr. Jiang and his party colleagues showed no parallel interest in political liberalization, the key to consolidating a market economy and relieving chronic tensions between China and the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jiang emerges from the conference with his personal authority strengthened and his chief party rival, Qiao Shi, nudged into premature retirement. Next month he will try to enhance his diplomatic prestige with a long-sought state visit to Washington. The chances of a successful meeting would be improved by a good-will gesture like an amnesty for political prisoners, including the democracy advocates Wei Jingsheng and Wang Dan.</p>
        <p>Even after two decades of market liberalization under Deng Xiaoping, China's 305,000 state companies still account for more than half of urban employment, though a far smaller share of total output. Overstaffed, inefficient and obliged to provide a full range of welfare benefits to their employees, these enterprises had threatened to exert an increasing drag on China's future growth potential. They now absorb 90 percent of business credits provided by the state banking system, and the  special privileges enjoyed by their managers also made these companies seedbeds of official corruption.</p>
        <p>Despite artful language casting the move to shareholding and market relations as appropriate to ''the primary stage of socialism,'' Mr. Jiang's initiative sharply challenges the party's guardians of Marxist ideology, something he had been conspicuously unwilling to do during the long and delicate transition of power occasioned by the frailty and death of Mr. Deng.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Jiang now seems to feel confident enough to embrace accelerated economic reform leaves room for hope that he will go further and reopen the issue of political reform, off-limits since the 1989 blood bath in Tiananmen Square. In a modestly encouraging sign, China's officially controlled press permitted a slightly broadened range of political debate in the weeks leading up to this week's Communist Party Congress. Chinese leaders traditionally use these congresses, held every five years, to unveil major shifts in ideology, leadership or economic structure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jiang's privatization plan calls for the vast majority of state-owned firms to pass into the market, leaving only about 500 of the very largest in government hands. Many of the details, including the timetable, have yet to be filled in. What is most important is that government monopolies not give way to private monopolies and that privatization not become a smoke screen for handing over public assets cheaply to the well connected.</p>
        <p>Shutting down these state enterprises carries social and political risks. That partly explains why it has been put off so long. There is likely to be a  jump in unemployment and considerable suffering as workers lose their present entitlements to company-provided schools, health care, pensions and other social benefits. Worker protests are already on the rise in China and could grow, all the more so since Chinese citizens still have no real political outlet for their grievances.</p>
        <p>Beijing can partially mitigate these problems by moving quickly to build a universal government-guaranteed safety net to replace benefits now provided mainly to employees of state enterprises through their workplaces. But it is unlikely to achieve lasting stability until it recognizes the virtues of decentralizing political as well as economic power and unleashing the civic as well as the productive energies of its people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
