<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mindful of 9/11, Many Rush to Aid Storm Victims</title>
    <meta content="13help" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/13/nyregion/13help.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1701786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFD61031F930A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mindful of 9/11, Many Rush to Aid Storm Victims</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mindful of 9/11, Many Rush to Aid Storm Victims</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHADI RAHIMI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman from Queens has organized a clothing drive that stretches into northern New Jersey. A boy from Port Chester, N.Y., has joined students nationwide in collecting backpacks stuffed with pencils and notebooks, and has received 156. A man from New Jersey has driven to New Orleans in a 24-foot-long truck filled with clothing, sanitary napkins and diapers.</p>
        <p>Many of the thousands of New York and New Jersey residents who are donating time, money or items to assist the victims of Hurricane Katrina hail from Louisiana, Alabama or Mississippi. But many who have never visited the Gulf Coast are driven by the same desire to help, to feel that they are needed, or to give back to those who helped New York City after Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many New York and New Jersey residents who have never visited the Gulf Coast are driven by the desire to give back to those who helped New York City after 9/11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A woman from Queens has organized a clothing drive that stretches into northern New Jersey. A boy from Port Chester, N.Y., has joined students nationwide in collecting backpacks stuffed with pencils and notebooks, and has received 156. A man from New Jersey has driven to New Orleans in a 24-foot-long truck filled with clothing, sanitary napkins and diapers.</p>
        <p>Many of the thousands of New York and New Jersey residents who are donating time, money or items to assist the victims of Hurricane Katrina hail from Louisiana, Alabama or Mississippi. But many who have never visited the Gulf Coast are driven by the same desire to help, to feel that they are needed, or to give back to those who helped New York City after Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>''New Yorkers know what it's like to wake up and it's like your whole world has ended,'' Mikki Lanclos, 29, said. ''They made it through that, and now they are helping others to show that there is hope -- that your world can seem normal again.''</p>
        <p>But those who want to help have found, at least in the first days after Katrina struck, that helping can be easier said than done. Even now, the means to deliver food, clothing and toiletries to the Gulf Coast remain problematic. Some are so frustrated waiting for overworked relief agencies that they are mailing items themselves, or driving south.</p>
        <p>Bill Graves drove to New Orleans with two friends last week in a truck stacked with items donated by residents, stores, churches and mosques in his neighborhood in East Orange, N.J.</p>
        <p>''We just got so angry,'' Mr. Graves, 65, said by cellphone on Friday while driving to Louisiana. ''I called my buddy, who is a long-distance truck driver, and told him, 'Get behind the wheel right now; we're driving to New Orleans.'''</p>
        <p>Though well-intentioned, the desire to help victims of tragedy has in the past often compounded problems on the ground. During the hurricane season in Florida last year, dozens of Kentucky residents left carloads of diapers and bottles of water on roadsides because there was no one to receive them, said a spokesman for the Kentucky National Guard, Sgt. David Altom.</p>
        <p>The American Red Cross is taking a survey to determine the places that are most in need of the 40,000 volunteers it expects to recruit by Nov. 30, said a spokesman, Nick Shapiro. But determined New York and New Jersey residents who want to take immediate action said in interviews that they would not be deterred from helping in whatever way they see fit.</p>
        <p>''You can't tell a Cajun girl that she can't do something,'' said Ms. Lanclos, who organized a collection drive last week after the Red Cross turned down clothing contributions from her and others. The Red Cross, which welcomes donations of money, does not accept clothing because of the hidden costs of sorting and distributing it, Mr. Shapiro said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lanclos, who lives in Queens, still speaks in the easy drawl of her small Louisiana hometown, Breaux Bridge, a two-and-a-half-hour drive from New Orleans. She formed her donation drive via an online posting board, Craigslist, with more than a dozen homes in New York and New Jersey serving as drop-off points for donations from strangers.</p>
        <p>A shipping company, DHL, has agreed to cover the cost of delivering the donations to New Orleans. But Ms. Lanclos said yesterday that she was panicking nonetheless because she had collected many more items than she expected. ''My biggest fear now is that we have too much stuff, and no way to get it there,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Most other attempts by individuals to help the hurricane victims over the past week have quickly blossomed into widespread efforts, with restaurants and nightclubs agreeing to sponsor fund-raisers, shipping companies offering to send aid packages, hospitals providing medical care, and city governments giving housing or food vouchers to evacuees.</p>
        <p>But the logistics of delivering most donated food or clothing is still being worked out because the whereabouts of many displaced residents are unknown, and relief agencies are overwhelmed. Often, those who have a direct connection to a devastated region or a relief agency find satisfaction in immediate results.</p>
        <p>At Mara's Homemade, a Cajun restaurant on Sixth Street in the East Village, 5 percent of every bill is being donated to the nonprofit organization Habitat for Humanity and three New Orleans universities, said the owner, Mara Levi.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the St. Barnabas Health Care System has provided medical care to 31 people from New Orleans and is waiting to serve more people, said the senior vice president for clinical and emergency services, Dr. John Brennan.</p>
        <p>All this help is in addition to the many police officers and firefighters from the region who have traveled South. Still more are going. Last week, the Yonkers Fire Department sent 24 firefighters to assist the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and more than 180 police officers and decontamination experts from New Jersey were deployed. On Sept. 3, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority sent about 140 bus drivers to New Orleans.</p>
        <p>One of those drivers, Charlie Giblin, 48, who is also a firefighter in Carle Place, on Long Island, was dispatched to ground zero in 2001 to assist in both capacities. All last week, Mr. Giblin transported Army and National Guard soldiers from a naval air station in New Orleans to patrol areas where chaos had erupted.</p>
        <p>The bus drivers, who had volunteered for the task, slept in their buses, ate meals ready to eat and washed up at a hotel that was damaged by the hurricane but still had working showers, Mr. Giblin said by cellphone on Sunday, on his way back to New York City with the 73-bus convoy.</p>
        <p>''It was an adventure,'' he said. ''I wanted to help everyone who helped us during 9/11. It felt great to pay them back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
