<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.A.W. Wants Trade Payoff in Jobs</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="659344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED AUTOMOBILE WORKERS (UAW)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNET, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIEBER, OWEN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4DF123EF932A35752C0A962958260" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.A.W. Wants Trade Payoff in Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNET, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looming over the Edsel Ford Freeway near the General Motors Corporation headquarters here, a billboard recently proclaimed one of the many benefits vaunted by supporters of the North American Free Trade Agreement: 15,000 new auto-related jobs in the United States in the first year.</p>
        <p>The billboard is gone now, but the promise is far from forgotten by one group defeated in the free-trade battle: the United Automobile Workers union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looming over the Edsel Ford Freeway near the General Motors Corporation headquarters here, a billboard recently proclaimed one of the many benefits vaunted by supporters of the North American Free Trade Agreement: 15,000 new auto-related jobs in the United States in the first year.</p>
        <p>The billboard is gone now, but the promise is far from forgotten by one group defeated in the free-trade battle: the United Automobile Workers union.</p>
        <p>"We're going to be waiting and looking with bated breath for those 15,000 good-paying jobs," said Owen F. Bieber, president of the U.A.W.</p>
        <p>Union leaders were not impressed recently when the Ford Motor Company announced that it would shift production of some vehicles among its American, Canadian and Mexican plants as a result of the trade agreement, recalling 300 workers in Mexico and creating 550 new jobs north of the border.</p>
        <p>All told, Ford said, the move could lead to 6,000 new auto-related jobs. But those jobs, Ford said, would be created in the United States and Canada. And some of them, Ford said, would not be new jobs, but "job equivalents" -- that is, overtime worked by already employed workers.</p>
        <p>Such fuzziness, the U.A.W. claims, has overtaken other once-clear benchmarks set by the North American Free Trade Agreement's proponents before the agreement passed.</p>
        <p>Before the passage, boosters including President Clinton asserted that in the first year of the agreement, the Big Three would export 60,000 cars to Mexico, compared with 7,700 currently. But recently, top executives of the Big Three -- like their critics before the trade accord passed -- have cast doubt on that number.</p>
        <p>"The 60,000 number -- I have to tell you, I have not ever discussed that number, nor do I know the origin of it," Robert J. Eaton, the chairman of the Chrysler Corporation, told reporters.</p>
        <p>"Well, they do know where it came from," Mr. Bieber retorted, pointing out that the American Automobile Manufacturers Association, the Big Three's trade association, pushed the number. "If it was false, then they had an obligation to say, wait a minute. We're for Nafta, but don't get us into a box where we're going to be expected to sell 60,000 cars."</p>
        <p>Now that the auto makers are in that box, Mr. Bieber clearly relishes keeping them there, insisting that they sell all 60,000 and create all 15,000 new jobs. "By God, I'll tell you this, we're going to keep tabs of how many are sold there, and we're going to remind people of this," he said. Parts Supplier Movements</p>
        <p>While he does not expect the auto makers to move assembly plants to Mexico overnight, Mr. Bieber said he thought they would begin pushing their parts suppliers to relocate there in pursuit of lower-cost labor.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview at Solidarity House, the U.A.W.'s headquarters here, Mr. Bieber reflected both on his recent defeat on the trade agreement and on what most auto analysts regard as his recent victory over the Big Three in national labor contract negotiations. As he spoke about the future of labor and of his union -- whose diverse but declining membership includes not only auto workers but state employees and jai alai players -- he adopted a wait-and-see attitude toward Mr. Clinton, whose support he acknowledged he needs to fulfill a broad legislative agenda.</p>
        <p>"I have great respect," Mr. Bieber allowed with the faintest of grins, "for his ability to get people to vote his way."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Bieber has not taken the big picture of him with Mr. Clinton off his office wall, despite the irony that the President's scribble has acquired since the trade agreement vote: "with thanks for all your help."</p>
        <p>"We worked hard in 1992 to help elect Bill Clinton President of the United States," Mr. Bieber said. "I have no regrets." Fourth and Final Term at U.A.W.</p>
        <p>At 65, Mr. Bieber, a hulking man and a tenacious bargainer, is serving his fourth and final term as U.A.W. president. He will retire in 1995, ending a career with the U.A.W. that began in 1949.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the time Mr. Bieber started negotiating for auto workers, the legal deck is now stacked heavily against labor, he said, which he contends is one reason union membership is declining. The U.A.W.'s membership has dropped from 1.5 million in 1979 to about 850,000 today.</p>
        <p>To restore labor's bargaining power, Mr. Bieber said, Mr. Clinton needs to finish making his appointments to the National Labor Relations Board. Mr. Bieber contends that the board tilted drastically toward management during the Reagan-Bush years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bieber also said the President should lobby for the so-called striker-replacement bill. That proposal, which Mr. Clinton has said he strongly supports, would make it illegal for companies to replace striking workers permanently, a practice that became much more common in the last decade. The bill was held up by a Republican filibuster in the Senate.</p>
        <p>"The President can help himself tremendously among the trade-union movement by going out and actively campaigning for the right of the Senate to vote" on the bill, Mr. Bieber said. "To say, 'permanently replace' -- you might as well say you don't have the right under law to strike, when you have a situation with a shortage of jobs and a large unemployment pool."</p>
        <p>With the playing field leveled again, Mr. Bieber said, unions would begin to grow, which he argued is the best way to preserve the country's middle class.</p>
        <p>"You can't just keep talking about good high-paying jobs," he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bieber acknowledged that his union had suffered because of inroads overseas competitors had made in the auto industry, seizing about a quarter of the domestic market for new cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>To help stem the flow of industrial jobs overseas, Mr. Bieber said, the U.A.W. will continue fighting for Mr. Clinton's health-care plan. While the union favors a single-payer approach, Mr. Bieber said, Mr. Clinton's plan, as presented, offers the best hope for restraining health-care costs for large employers, which will help keep their labor costs competitive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
