<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Privatization Is Crucial for Italy's ENI</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="737522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVATIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENTE NAZIONALE IDROCARBURI (ENI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERNABE, FRANCO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDD1531F934A25752C0A963958260" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Privatization Is Crucial for Italy's ENI</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE,</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Jan. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Franco Bernabe, who spent much of the last two years cleansing Ente Nazionale Idrocarburi S.p.A., the big Italian oil and petrochemicals group, of an aura of political corruption, the biggest challenge now is to sell off the state-owned company to the public without more political interference.</p>
        <p>The outcome is crucial for ENI, the world's fifth-largest oil company by sales, as the international chemical industry awakes from recession and major oil companies stake out claims in the former Soviet Union and China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Franco Bernabe, who spent much of the last two years cleansing Ente Nazionale Idrocarburi S.p.A., the big Italian oil and petrochemicals group, of an aura of political corruption, the biggest challenge now is to sell off the state-owned company to the public without more political interference.</p>
        <p>The outcome is crucial for ENI, the world's fifth-largest oil company by sales, as the international chemical industry awakes from recession and major oil companies stake out claims in the former Soviet Union and China.</p>
        <p>The proposed privatization of ENI is just part of Italy's campaign to sell state-owned industries to private shareholders. Two previous governments made a good start, thanks to the independence of the industries from political parties, which were crippled after 1992 by Italy's wave of corruption scandals.</p>
        <p>Previous privatizations brought to market some of the largest banks and financial service companies. But the companies now on the agenda, like the big Stet telecommunications group, and the public utility Enel, in addition to ENI, are pillars of the economy. ENI supplies more than 50 percent of Italy's energy needs, a bigger share than any company in any other European country except Spain.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bernabe, an owlish 46-year-old economist, took over ENI in 1992, the company was losing $515 million a year, and was shaken by disclosures of illegal payments to political parties totaling more than $20 million in the 1980's. The chairman, Gabriele Cagliari, was arrested, as were the heads of major divisions, like AGIP oil, the Nuovo Pignone turbine unit, the Saipem pipeline company and the Snam gas division. Mr. Cagliari later committed suicide.</p>
        <p>To stanch the financial hemorrhaging, Mr. Bernabe made drastic cuts, shedding 65 subsidiaries and gaining powerful new partners, like Union Carbide, for the ailing Enichem chemicals division. Yet chemicals will still produce operating losses of $600 million to $700 million this year, and only profits in oil and gas will enable ENI as a whole to turn a net profit, which Mr. Bernabe estimates at "largely above $1 billion," on sales of $33.6 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernabe slashed thousands of jobs, bringing last year's total payroll down to 100,000. To raise cash, he sold off some family jewels like the Nuovo Pignone turbine unit, which an American consortium led by General Electric bought last year for $690 million.</p>
        <p>Such streamlining may help little unless ENI can aggressively expand its drilling and producing operations. To do so, Mr. Bernabe is focusing on natural gas, an increasingly popular alternative to oil because of its abundance and cleanliness as a fuel for industry, power generation and home heating.</p>
        <p>Geographically, he is shifting ENI's traditional focus from North Africa and the Middle East to Eastern Europe and Asia, striking gas and oil deals in Russia and Kazakhstan, on the Caspian Sea, and in the Caucasus, and in Asia in the China Sea and in China's central Tarim Basin.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts give the company's oil and gas business high marks.</p>
        <p>"On the oil side, they are very organized and in good shape; they bounded back well," said Edward Morse, the publisher of Petroleum Intelligence Weekly, a leading trade publication. The company, he added, is "positioned remarkably well to become a global gas player."</p>
        <p>Yet streamlining may be of little long-term use unless Rome presses ahead with its privatization drive. "We're not yet at a critical stage," Mr. Bernabe said, "But at a certain point, if the process does not move ahead, inevitably there's going to be a lack of tension, a lack of motivation, a lack of determination."</p>
        <p>Italy's fractious Government politics do not make things easier. Calls for Mr. Bernabe's resignation come occasionally from the neo-Fascist National Alliance, which has been keen to purge the top ranks of Government-run banks and industries. Mr. Bernabe also made enemies when he swept out ENI's old guard, dismissing top managers in 250 subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>The Government faces several hurdles in preparing legislation for ENI's privatization. One is a lack of large domestic institutional investors. Pending pension-system reform would permit the creation of large funds capable of stabilizing Italy's volatile investment market. Another problem is the need to create a new energy authority to represent public interests in energy matters once ENI is privatized.</p>
        <p>Some legislators fear a foreign takeover, as occurred when Britain privatized British Petroleum in the 1980's and Kuwaiti investors snapped up a large stake, prompting London to force a buyback of the Kuwaiti shares. In Italy, national emotions, as well as economics, are at play, thanks to the National Alliance, whose heritage goes back to Fascism's traditions of national economic self-reliance and Government control of the economy.</p>
        <p>When ENI goes to market sometime this year, Mr. Bernabe expects Government rules requiring a majority stake to stay in Italy and prohibiting majority control by individuals or investor groups. In addition, a decisive, or "golden," voting share will remain in the hands of the Italian Treasury, which technically owns ENI.</p>
        <p>Doubts also persist within the Government over whether to sell ENI whole or to break out profitable parts like the AGIP oil and gas operations and sell them off piecemeal.</p>
        <p>Yet the sale of ENI is likely to be popular with investors. Massimiliano Casini, who follows Italian shares at Robert Fleming Securities in London, said investors broadening their portfolio to include Italian companies and energy shares would want ENI. "There are no real gas or oil shares in Italy, so you would have a novelty effect," he said.</p>
        <p>To succeed in the long run, analysts say ENI must match the streamlining of industry leaders like Exxon and British Petroleum. "The industry is coming out of one of its worst oil recessions," said Paul Spedding, an oil analyst at Kleinwort Benson in London. "Once, $18 a barrel was considered the oil price floor. Now, companies want to be profitable at $14."  COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
