<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Messier Remains No Big Fan of Neilson</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEILSON, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MESSIER, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONDY, FILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D9133AF930A35754C0A964958260" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Messier Remains No Big Fan of Neilson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FILIP BONDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONDY, FILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before Mark Messier went to dinner last night with General Manager Neil Smith, the Ranger captain sounded as resolute as ever about his nonendorsement of Coach Roger Neilson.</p>
        <p>"I haven't said one way or another about Roger," Messier said yesterday, during a telephone conference call from Hilton Head, S.C. "I just think when you don't win when you have as good a team as we do, everyone in the organization has to be evaluated by the organization. You have to have the right people in the right spots."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before Mark Messier went to dinner last night with General Manager Neil Smith, the Ranger captain sounded as resolute as ever about his nonendorsement of Coach Roger Neilson.</p>
        <p>"I haven't said one way or another about Roger," Messier said yesterday, during a telephone conference call from Hilton Head, S.C. "I just think when you don't win when you have as good a team as we do, everyone in the organization has to be evaluated by the organization. You have to have the right people in the right spots."</p>
        <p>Smith has said in the past he would not discuss Neilson's job security with Messier, but the general manager has also refused to commit himself on the question of Neilson's return next season. Smith was in Hilton Head, Messier's off-season home, to attend the American Hockey League meetings. Presumably, Smith also hoped to settle the thorny Neilson matter with his star player.</p>
        <p>Neilson expects to return, hopes to extend his contract past the end of next season and appears to be honestly surprised at any objections by Messier. A Conservative Coach</p>
        <p>The clash is one of hockey style, not personality. Neilson is a conservative coach who loosened his system a bit during the regular season to accommodate Messier. Apparently, he did not go far enough. Messier hinted that Neilson's playoff strategy was too defensive, too reactive.</p>
        <p>Messier also bristled at the notion that the team's problems stemmed from a lack of commitment to defense, a theory that Neilson offered after the Rangers were eliminated by the Penguins in the second round of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>"When you've got a team that can skate like ours, you want to apply pressure all over the ice," Messier said. "It wasn't our defensive problems. If we have the puck 75 percent of the time, we're going to win. Defense doesn't mean waiting for the other team to bring the puck up."</p>
        <p>Citing the wide-open styles of Edmonton and Pittsburgh as models for long-term success, Messier complained that some of his teammates weren't certain about their roles last season under Neilson.</p>
        <p>"Players like Kris King and Adam Graves should be given specific jobs while on the ice," Messier said. "Those players can make a difference." After Lindros, What Next?</p>
        <p>Messier, like most Ranger fans, sounded a bit disappointed that arbitration had sent Eric Lindros to Philadelphia instead of New York. He thought that the Rangers must now find another way to evolve beyond Pittsburgh, just as clubs in the Smythe Division needed to find a way past Edmonton.</p>
        <p>"Lindros is a force to be reckoned with," Messier said about the 19-year-old player. "He's a franchise player already. God knows what he'll be like at 23, 24. Hopefully, I won't be around to find out.</p>
        <p>"It was worth a shot trying to get him. Obviously, we weren't good enough last season. But we have three great young players in Tony Amonte, Doug Weight and Aleksei Kovalev. Who knows? Maybe we're better off."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
