<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="620278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61339F93AA35754C0A965958260" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Activated Brady Anderson, outfielder, from the 15-day disabled list. Placed Leo Gomez, third baseman, on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE BREWERS -- Placed Bill Wegman, pitcher, on the 15-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of Matt Maysey, pitcher, from New Orleans of the American Association.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Activated Brady Anderson, outfielder, from the 15-day disabled list. Placed Leo Gomez, third baseman, on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE BREWERS -- Placed Bill Wegman, pitcher, on the 15-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of Matt Maysey, pitcher, from New Orleans of the American Association.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND ATHLETICS -- Optioned Kevin Campbell, pitcher, to Tacoma of the Pacific Coast League. National League</p>
        <p>NL -- Announced Ramon Martinez, Los Angeles Dodgers pitcher, has withdrawn his appeal of a five-game suspension for throwing at Charlie Hayes of the Colorado Rockies on June 15.</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI REDS -- Optioned Mike Anderson, pitcher, to Indianapolis of the American Association. Recalled Keith Gordon, outfielder, from Chattanooga of the Southern League.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK METS -- Named Joe McIlvaine executive vice president of baseball operations and signed him to a two-year contract. Optioned Kevin Baez, shortstop, to Norfolk of the International League. Recalled Eric Hillman, pitcher, from Norfolk.</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Promoted Brent Bish, infielder, from Rancho Cucamonga of the California League to Wichita of the Texas League. Assigned Jeff Brown, pitcher, to Rancho Cucamonga.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS -- Optioned Greg Brummett, pitcher, to Phoenix of the Pacific Coast League. Recalled Paul Faries, infielder, from Phoenix. Purchased the contract of Eric A. Johnson, infielder, from Phoenix. Placed Mike Benjamin, infielder, on the 15-day disabled list. Transferred Craig Colbert, catcher, from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list. Basketball  National Basketball Association</p>
        <p>DALLAS MAVERICKS -- Named Tom Newell and Randy Wittman assistant coaches.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY NETS -- Signed Kevin Edwards, guard, to a multiyear contract. Continental Basketball Association</p>
        <p>HARTFORD HELLCATS -- Named Randy Smith coach.</p>
        <p>QUAD CITY THUNDER -- Acquired Sean Gay, guard, Kenny Miller, forward, and the rights to Litterial Green, guard, from the Hartford Hellcats for 1993 first and third round draft picks.</p>
        <p>RAPID CITY THRILLERS -- Traded Hubert Henderson, forward, to the Hartford Hellcats for Kevin Williams, guard, a 1994 third round draft pick, and future considerations.</p>
        <p>TRI-CITY CHINOOK -- Acquired Winston Bennett, forward, and future considerations from the Rapid City Thrillers for a 1993 third round draft pick and future considerations. Hockey</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League  BIRMINGHAM BULLS -- Announced an affiliation with the Florida Panthers of the National  Hockey League. International Hockey League</p>
        <p>LAS VEGAS THUNDER -- Signed Jean-Marc Richard, defenseman, Patrice Lefebvre, right wing, and Bobby Joyce, left wing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
