<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Tobacco might thrive with a $1.50-a-pack rise for cigarettes.</title>
    <meta content="Y25SCE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bulow, Jeremy I</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DE1E3BF936A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Tobacco might thrive with a $1.50-a-pack rise for cigarettes.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic Scene column on Pres Clinton's demand that price of cigarettes should rise $1.50 a pack to deter teen-age smoking; says close look at Clinton's demand suggests that industry could live--conceivably thrive--with such consequences; holds combination of taxes and penalties built into original tobacco settlement totaled 72 cents a pack; Jeremy I Bulow, economist at Graduate School of Business at Stanford University, comments; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IS the tobacco industry playing Brer Rabbit to President Clinton's Brer Fox? The President's assertion that if necessary, the price of cigarettes should rise by $1.50 a pack to deter teen-age smoking evoked bitter denunciations from Big Tobacco. ''The industry should be not held solely accountable for social behavior that neither it, nor the Government, can control,'' read the cigarette manufacturers' collective response.</p>
        <p>But a close look at Mr. Clinton's demands suggests that the industry could live -- conceivably thrive -- with the consequences. Jeremy I. Bulow, an economist at the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University, calculates that a settlement on the President's terms would cost the tobacco companies less than the continuing uncertainty over legal liability. ''The best estimate now is that $1.50 a pack would increase the market value of tobacco stocks,'' Mr. Bulow argues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IS the tobacco industry playing Brer Rabbit to President Clinton's Brer Fox? The President's assertion that if necessary, the price of cigarettes should rise by $1.50 a pack to deter teen-age smoking evoked bitter denunciations from Big Tobacco. ''The industry should be not held solely accountable for social behavior that neither it, nor the Government, can control,'' read the cigarette manufacturers' collective response.</p>
        <p>But a close look at Mr. Clinton's demands suggests that the industry could live -- conceivably thrive -- with the consequences. Jeremy I. Bulow, an economist at the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University, calculates that a settlement on the President's terms would cost the tobacco companies less than the continuing uncertainty over legal liability. ''The best estimate now is that $1.50 a pack would increase the market value of tobacco stocks,'' Mr. Bulow argues.</p>
        <p>''Reducing youth smoking is the Administration's bottom line,'' President Clinton said. ''One of the surest ways'' to meet the Administration's goal of a 60 percent cut in teen-age smoking over a decade, he added, is to ''increase the price of cigarettes.''</p>
        <p>Since teen-agers have less money than adults and are not yet addicted to nicotine, their consumption of tobacco is more responsive to price changes than that of adults. Nonetheless, to cut teen-age smoking by 60 percent would probably require a $1.50 price increase.</p>
        <p>The combination of taxes and penalties built into the original settlement proposal -- a proposal the Federal Trade Commission staff argued this week could actually increase industry profits -- totaled 72 cents a pack. When a reporter asked Bruce N. Reed, director of the President's Domestic Policy Council, whether the Administration's approach would double the 72-cent penalty, Mr. Reed said it would. That, in turn, led to the speculation that the President's approach would have doubled the cost of the original settlement, to about $700 billion.</p>
        <p>But Martin Feldman, a tobacco industry analyst at Smith Barney, begs to differ. He notes that the 72 cents does not include the 15-cent-a-pack increase in the Federal excise tax on the books for the year 2002. Nor does it include future increases in state taxes, or in markups by retailers. All told, Mr. Feldman estimates that the abandoned settlement would have raised the price of a pack by $1.45 in just five years -- almost as much as the President's proposed maximum increase over a decade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bulow of Stanford expects there is more daylight between the cost of the two proposals than Mr. Feldman argues because competition would prevent retailers from fattening their markups significantly. Nonetheless, the university economist is confident that cigarette makers could live with measures that would increase the supermarket price by $1.50 a pack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bulow's conclusion is based on the idea that the cigarette makers' goal is to maximize the total return for stockholders. He cites estimates by Gary Black, a tobacco analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein, that the domestic tobacco businesses of Philip Morris and RJR Nabisco are currently valued by the market at just one-third what they would be worth in the absence of uncertainty about future litigation and regulation.</p>
        <p>He estimates that a tax of $1.50 a pack would reduce cigarette consumption by about one-third. The lost sales would mean a more-than-proportionate fall in profits, but Mr. Bulow estimates that part of the costs of the settlement would be recouped since marketing costs would also fall. On balance, he calculates that a $1.50 tax would pare the industry's $5 billion annual profit by a bit less than half.</p>
        <p>That is hardly what the cigarette companies hoped for. But Mr. Bulow reckons that it is better than living with the current level of legal uncertainty, which has reduced the market value of the business by two-thirds. And since the Administration appears eager to set goals in terms of reduced youth smoking, rather than reduced smoking over all, the companies may find ways to salvage a portion of the lost profit.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Bulow expects that an increase in the minimum legal smoking age to, say, 19, would deter teen-age smokers, yet have little effect on adults in the near term. So by supporting tougher restrictions on access to cigarettes, the companies might get away with a smaller tax that cut less deeply into profits from sales to adult addicts.</p>
        <p>Concentrating on youth smoking directly has a social advantage, too. Smokers, on average, have lower incomes than nonsmokers. So relying more on direct regulation of youth smoking and less on cutting demand with across-the-board price increases reduces the regressivity of the policy. ''It would be a shame to put most of the burden of the antismoking settlement on the backs of adults earning less than $10 an hour,'' Mr. Bulow said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
