<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspicion, Part 2: The Landlord's Story</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVITCH, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5D61039F934A35754C0A960958260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspicion, Part 2: The Landlord's Story</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE landlord is fighting a cold and an eye infection, and perhaps the betrayal of a dream. Landlords can be idealists, too, although tenants rarely think so. Thirty-five years ago, Richard Ravitch, who is 63, envisioned four architecturally handsome towers of rental apartments on the East River in a racially and economically integrated enclave that would throb with a sense of community. It would be a monument to the liberal imagination, and eventually would turn a liberal profit.</p>
        <p>It took him 10 years to get his plan approved, he said. It was called Waterside Plaza, and was built under the Mitchell-Lama laws, with limited profit for limited risk and affordable housing if tenants agreed to certain restrictions and were within minimum and maximum income levels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE landlord is fighting a cold and an eye infection, and perhaps the betrayal of a dream. Landlords can be idealists, too, although tenants rarely think so. Thirty-five years ago, Richard Ravitch, who is 63, envisioned four architecturally handsome towers of rental apartments on the East River in a racially and economically integrated enclave that would throb with a sense of community. It would be a monument to the liberal imagination, and eventually would turn a liberal profit.</p>
        <p>It took him 10 years to get his plan approved, he said. It was called Waterside Plaza, and was built under the Mitchell-Lama laws, with limited profit for limited risk and affordable housing if tenants agreed to certain restrictions and were within minimum and maximum income levels.</p>
        <p>For a long time, Waterside Plaza was a seemingly placid island in the city off First Avenue, around 25th Street, a village of 1,500 families, secure, self-contained. But now many tenants speak ill of Mr. Ravitch, organize against  him and, in the ultimate modern expression of ingratitude, are suing him (and the city) to overturn a rent increase.</p>
        <p>Last week, in this corner, Rafael and Mildred Blechman, an elderly couple who 12 years ago moved into a two-bedroom apartment with stunning views of the river and the skyline, took us through their Waterside Plaza. Their rent had recently  risen from $1,322 per month to $1,520 (Mr. Ravitch estimates market value at more than double that), and they were concerned about future raises. Services had deteriorated, they said. At a meeting, we heard a tenants' council member, Jim Mahon, shout, "Rent strike!" in a crowded room.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ravitch's view of Waterside Plaza is a little different.</p>
        <p>"When these programs were created," he said, "the purpose was to give developers 20 years of limited return before the restrictions would end and the  apartments would go onto the free market. That was the contract. No one thought  through the problems of tenants who might still be in place after 20 years. And  then, for political reasons, the laws were changed and so was the contract. Something went awry.</p>
        <p>"People in Waterside had not had a rent increase in 10 years. If rent stabilization had been in effect they would have been paying much more than they are now."</p>
        <p>Rent subsidies are, of course, a very touchy issue in a city that went co-op  and condo crazy. There is no shortage of stories about greedy landlords evicting tenants illegally and warehousing empty apartments. On the other hand, who hasn't heard about illegal sublets, and millionaires still snug in rent-controlled apartments?</p>
        <p>Both sides at Waterside have suspicions. The Blechmans told me that Mr. Ravitch's plan was to turn Waterside into a co-op and sell it, turning a $3 million investment into more than $300 million. Mr. Ravitch says that the original investment was indeed somewhere around $3 million (his investment group gets a $190,000 annual return, he says, and his management group gets $850,000), and that he would love to co-op and sell, but how could he do that and who would buy it? "I tried, but the legislation never passed," he said. "And it would cost me millions in real-estate taxes to take it out of Mitchell-Lama. Yes, I'm stuck."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Ravitch, says the tenants' real fear is that if their lawsuit  fails, they will be subject to "certification," a new look at their qualifying incomes. He says he knows of at least one "middle-income" tenant who qualified 20 years ago but now earns $750,000 a year. He also thinks that Mr. Mahon, a Republican district leader, is stirring up tenants for political reasons, a theory that occurred to me listening to his entertaining rants two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Tenants are also concerned because Mr. Ravitch, an energetic, thoughtful and  well-connected man, now has time on his hands to be a landlord (he also developed Manhattan Plaza). His mayoral aspirations seem long past, and his recent interest in becoming baseball commissioner was not returned. Once a Brooklyn Dodger fan, he does not go to baseball games anymore, because "as Bismarck said, if you make sausages you don't want to eat them."</p>
        <p>He was feeling just a little sorry for himself last week; a contagious viral  eye infection was threatening a long-planned trip to London to see his grandchildren. The medical compromise was that he could go, but that he could not hug them.</p>
        <p>Urged to make a pronouncement, he said: "The best thing for New York is for the existing housing stock to go to market value when it becomes vacant, with some protection for existing tenants. I happen to believe that government should subsidize people with limited means, but that's my own political view. I have investors in Waterside who believe that the city has not met the basic understanding. I don't blame tenants for wanting to pay less, but that is no more moral than my position. And I'm still proud of Waterside."</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
