<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks Sputter as G.M. Strike Ends First Day</title>
    <meta content="04UAW.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="881138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canadian Automobile Workers Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers (Uaw)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DA123FF937A35753C1A960958260" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks Sputter as G.M. Strike Ends First Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Negotiations between General Motors Corp and Canadian Automobile Workers union show little progress after 15,000 assembly workers go on strike; GM officials contend they cannot accept same deal that union negotiated with Chrysler Corp, and union says it will settle for nothing less; auto industry labor experts say compromises needed for a deal could prove elusive; in United States, leaders of United Automobile Workers had been close to reaching their own deal with GM, and are disappointed by Canadian strike; some analysts say Canadian union used such strong rhetoric in recent weeks that it was forced to go on strike, but that it will soon reach compromise with GM (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Negotiations between the General Motors Corporation and the Canadian Automobile Workers union showed little progress today after 15,000 assembly workers went on strike early this morning.</p>
        <p>G.M. officials said that they could not accept the same deal that the Canadian union negotiated with the Chrysler Corporation, while the  union insisted that it could settle for nothing else. With both sides staking out unusually clear and differing positions, auto industry labor experts said that the compromises needed for a deal could prove elusive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Negotiations between the General Motors Corporation and the Canadian Automobile Workers union showed little progress today after 15,000 assembly workers went on strike early this morning.</p>
        <p>G.M. officials said that they could not accept the same deal that the Canadian union negotiated with the Chrysler Corporation, while the  union insisted that it could settle for nothing else. With both sides staking out unusually clear and differing positions, auto industry labor experts said that the compromises needed for a deal could prove elusive.</p>
        <p>Jane Armstrong, a spokeswoman for the Canadian union, said that negotiators met for an hour this morning here and would meet again, but were accomplishing very little. ''Talks are continuing, but absolutely no progress,'' she said.</p>
        <p>D. Stewart Low, a G.M. spokesman, said this afternoon that while a deal did not appear imminent, the very continuation of top-level talks was a good sign. ''The fact they took place after a fairly heated discussion last night is a positive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the United Automobile Workers had been close to reaching their own deal with G.M. this week, and were disappointed by the Canadian strike. Stephen P. Yokich, the U.A.W. president, said at a news conference today in Detroit that while the union supported the strike, ''we were hoping that our brothers and sisters in Canada could settle.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts were convinced that the Canadian union, which has engaged in strong rhetoric for months and even went as far as printing up strike placards, was forced to go on strike at least briefly but would soon reach a compromise. ''I think it was just a way to vent these guys' frustration,'' said Nicholas Lobaccaro, an analyst at Bear, Stearns &amp; Company. ''I don't see this thing lasting a whole long time.''</p>
        <p>The union demands that G.M., like Chrysler, agree that for every job ended through the purchase of parts from outside vendors, another job must be created in the same community.</p>
        <p>G.M. insists that it retain the right to buy more outside parts without such restrictions, Mr. Low said.</p>
        <p>But the Canadian union and G.M. have been trying to negotiate a settlement on one of the touchiest issues, G.M.'s plans to sell two parts factories in Ontario. The union has offered to let the sale proceed, provided that the workers maintain their current pay and work rules, an arrangement that G.M. has rejected so far for fear that the requirement would scare off potential buyers.</p>
        <p>The 15,000 striking assembly workers are at pickup truck and midsize sedan factories in Oshawa, Ontario, and a sports car factory in Ste. Therese, Quebec.</p>
        <p>Analyst estimates of the cost to G.M. of the strike vary, from $5 million a day at first to as much as $50 million a day within a couple of weeks if the threatened closing of Canadian auto parts factories forces G.M. to shutter some auto assembly plants in the United States. If a settlement is not reached soon, the Canadian union plans to extend the strike to an engine and transmission factory in Ontario on Sunday night and several more auto parts factories on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Wesley R. Brown, the director of global product analysis at CSM Forecasting, an automotive consulting company in Farmington Hills, Mich., said that the engine and transmission factory supplied transmissions for the Chevrolet Malibu, a midsize sedan that G.M. plans to introduce this winter. One of the assembly plants already being struck makes bumper parts for the new Chevrolet Silhouette mini-van that G.M. also plans to introduce soon.</p>
        <p>What remains unclear, Mr. Brown said, is how large an inventory of these parts G.M. has accumulated in preparation for a strike. Mr. Hargrove has been threatening a strike since early summer, and G.M. executives have been anxious about this possibility for months.</p>
        <p>The Canadian union scheduled a meeting of G.M. factory union representatives from Ontario and Quebec for Friday here, but Ms. Armstrong said it was unlikely a deal would be ready to be presented then.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
