<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russia's Zhirinovsky Must Be Paid Heed</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZHIRINOVSKY, VLADIMIR V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LICAMELE, SCOTT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZHIRINOVSKY, VLADIMIR V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LICAMELE, SCOTT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED6163BF93BA15751C1A965958260" item-length="416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russia's Zhirinovsky Must Be Paid Heed</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "Panic Over Mr. Z" (column, Dec. 16), William Safire argues that Vladimir Zhirinovsky's surprise victory in the Russian parliamentary elections is not a cause for alarm. On the contrary, Mr. Zhirinovsky's showing in the election is a clear indication that the Russian political environment is extremely fragile and that the social costs of economic reform policies will increase that fragility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "Panic Over Mr. Z" (column, Dec. 16), William Safire argues that Vladimir Zhirinovsky's surprise victory in the Russian parliamentary elections is not a cause for alarm. On the contrary, Mr. Zhirinovsky's showing in the election is a clear indication that the Russian political environment is extremely fragile and that the social costs of economic reform policies will increase that fragility.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Safire notes, some who supported Mr. Zhirinovsky did so as a protest and did not necessarily support the nationalist-fascist platform of the Liberal Democrats. But Mr. Zhirinovsky's presence in parliament may contribute to the radicalization of Russian politics. If his party, along with the Communists, attempts to derail President Boris N. Yeltsin's policies, either reform will be retarded (further worsening economic conditions), or Mr. Yeltsin will be forced to rule by decree. And if the latter happens, an alienated people may lose its confidence in an increasingly authoritarian government. Along with this will be the mass unemployment resulting from the end of government credits and subsidies to unprofitable state enterprises.</p>
        <p>If nationalist politics then becomes more appealing to suffering voters, Mr. Zhirinovsky would then be able to emphasize that his agenda could be implemented only if his party controlled the powerful executive branch. So passing legislation now is less important to him than justifying his eventual run for the presidency by criticism of Mr. Yeltsin.</p>
        <p>Finally, polls indicate that a significant percentage of the Russian military voted for the Liberal Democratic party. This, combined with the alarmingly slow response of the military units during October's political violence, suggests dissension within the armed forces. Mr. Zhirinovsky could forge alliances with the military; his platform includes better compensation for military personnel, not to mention a more "expansive" role for them in the affairs of state. If Mr. Yeltsin were to dissolve parliament again, he might have to consider the armed forces' allegiance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhirinovsky's true intentions remain nebulous, and Mr. Safire interprets his success as ephemeral, something that "sometimes happens in democracies." However, Russia is not a stable democratic society, and it seems Mr. Zhirinovsky's career has just begun. SCOTT LICAMELE  St. Petersburg, Russia, Dec. 20, 1993 The writer teaches English and economics at Moscow State University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
