<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; For its latest golden age, radio has recast itself to advertisers as the home of niche markets.</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KATZ RADIO GROUP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">KATZ RADIO GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADELSON, ANDREA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HASTINGS, GORDON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADELSON, ANDREA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HASTINGS, GORDON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KATZ RADIO GROUP</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB1F3FF93BA15751C1A965958260" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; For its latest golden age, radio has recast itself to advertisers as the home of niche markets.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrea Adelson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ADELSON, ANDREA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER having fallen from favor among national advertisers enamored with the huge audiences drawn to television, the radio industry is now experiencing what some executives say is its second renaissance since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Radio stations and networks should tally a record $9.4 billion in advertising revenue for 1993, according to estimates by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation. That would be a 9 percent growth rate -- outpacing estimated increases of about 3 percent each for television and newspapers, both media that face threats from rival new technologies. And the faster growth for radio is expected to continue at least through 1997, according to an industry forecast by Veronis, Suhler &amp; Associates, a media consulting company, which expects radio revenue to break $10 billion in 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER having fallen from favor among national advertisers enamored with the huge audiences drawn to television, the radio industry is now experiencing what some executives say is its second renaissance since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Radio stations and networks should tally a record $9.4 billion in advertising revenue for 1993, according to estimates by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation. That would be a 9 percent growth rate -- outpacing estimated increases of about 3 percent each for television and newspapers, both media that face threats from rival new technologies. And the faster growth for radio is expected to continue at least through 1997, according to an industry forecast by Veronis, Suhler &amp; Associates, a media consulting company, which expects radio revenue to break $10 billion in 1995.</p>
        <p>Radio's revenue growth reflects a new pursuit among advertisers for cost efficiency and niche marketing, as well as a resurgent popularity for a low-tech medium that is creating celebrities, industry executives and analysts say.</p>
        <p>"Two years ago, advertisers wanted to make sure they put money in the target market," Gary R. Fries, president of the Radio Advertising Bureau, said. "Now they want to hit the bull's eye and put it down the throat of the potential audience."</p>
        <p>Radio executives say they are arguing more persuasively for ad dollars by trumpeting radio's fragmentation. Since radio's first revival in the 1960's, when rock music bolstered the value of FM frequencies, more stations are experimenting with format boundaries. They range from stations airing all-children's programming to all-business or all-grunge-rock. Wielding demographic program research, station representatives can carve up a market into segments far more specific than competing "mass reach" media can.</p>
        <p>Referring to advertisers and their agencies, Les Goldberg, president of the Interrep Radio Store, a company that represents stations in selling commercial time to agencies, said: "We hadn't learned their language. They don't want to know about cost per points; advertisers want to know how radio can fill a specific need."</p>
        <p>Once, he said, the Interrep sales staff would suggest to advertisers a list of stations where they could hope to reach a particular demographic group at the lowest cost per thousand. Now, Interrep will suggest a more selective package of stations with the largest number of listeners likely to buy a particular product.</p>
        <p>Radio benefits from that shift by advertisers, said Richard N. Silipigni, sales vice president for the CBS Radio Network, the nation's third-largest provider of radio programming. "Tonnage isn't the way to go," he said.</p>
        <p>This year, industry executives say, radio's share of advertising budgets has been rising among auto makers like Cadillac and Chrysler, retailers like Sears, J. C. Penney and Kmart, and packaged goods marketers like Procter &amp; Gamble.</p>
        <p>Motel 6 relies exclusively on radio for marketing. Since 1987, when the lodging chain began running a campaign carrying the theme "We'll leave the light on for you," created by the Alaskan humorist Tom Bodett, it has expanded nationally from its Western regional base.</p>
        <p>"Our customers are making a through-the-window decision," said F. Ross Crusemann, Motel 6's marketing director in Dallas. "I believe other hotel companies have taken a second look at using radio since the success of this campaign."</p>
        <p>National advertisers are also rediscovering radio partly because the AM band has been jolted back to life by Rush Limbaugh, G. Gordon Liddy and Larry King, hosts of talk shows that, after country music, are the industry's fastest-growing format.</p>
        <p>"Radio is standing taller; it's being looked at as a big-reach medium," said Gordon Hastings, president of the Katz Radio Group of New York, another agency that buys commercial time on radio stations for agencies. "You can't turn away from a national program that delivers 19 million cume listeners in a week."</p>
        <p>His reference was to cumulative audience estimates for "The Rush Limbaugh Show," which is heard on 500 stations daily and generates $25 million a year in advertising revenues, or about $3,200 a spot. Mr. Limbaugh's show is second only to Paul Harvey's, the ABC Network mainstay, as the most sought-after airtime on radio.</p>
        <p>By comparison, advertisers pay $325,000 for a 30-second television spot during "Home Improvement," according to Advertising Age. The ABC program is the No. 1-rated prime-time television show this season, watched by 34.2 million people weekly, according to the A. C. Nielsen Company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
