<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Digest</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB1E3CF93BA15751C1A965958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Digest</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>The insurance industry is changing the way it sells homeowner insurance after big losses from Hurricane Andrew. Companies say they are using new techniques to measure risk better and to price coverage more appropriately, raising prices for higher-risk customers while reducing costs for those at less risk.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>The insurance industry is changing the way it sells homeowner insurance after big losses from Hurricane Andrew. Companies say they are using new techniques to measure risk better and to price coverage more appropriately, raising prices for higher-risk customers while reducing costs for those at less risk.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Life will offer refunds to customers who were misled in buying life insurance policies since 1990, and it dismissed or forced out seven executives, including its highest-paid salesman, in the wake of charges of improper sales activities.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Prudential is accepting claims from estates of clients who died since buying partnerships that went sour. The administrator of a fund to settle fraud charges said he would require their acceptance; Prudential said statements barring them had been wrong.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The dismissal by Campbell Soup of 62 employees at an Ohio plant, based on accusations of drug use from other workers and hired agents' testimony, raised questions on the company's tactics and whether it had evidence to justify the discharges.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A group of TLC Beatrice shareholders plans to sell as many as 1.69 million common shares in the company.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>QVC and Nasdaq denied they got S.E.C. inquiries about a trading halt in QVC stock before the QVC-Paramount merger.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Nynex might still benefit from its Viacom investment, even though Viacom's bid for Paramount has been topped.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Veritas Capital bought two Bethlehem Steel mills and plans to reopen and modernize them beginning in 1994.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Host Marriott seized a 28.6 percent interest in the New York Marriott Marquis hotel after a partner defaulted on a loan.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>A Polish version of The Wall Street Journal's European edition is planned as a weekly supplement to Poland's biggest daily.  [ D17. ] International</p>
        <p>Foreign makers' share of the Japanese computer chip market dropped again in the third quarter, worsening trade friction and prompting the United States to invoke a provision for special talks with Japan, a step that could lead to trade sanctions.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Mazda will give more management control to Ford Motor, its largest shareholder, in hopes of stemming losses and reshaping its strategy. The move gives Ford more board seats.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A member of Saudi Arabia's principal banking family and an associate paid $225 million to settle B.C.C.I. charges.  [ D2. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>Conflicts between economic growth and environmental preservation are being resolved increasingly through habitat conservation planning, a concept pioneered in California that is being embraced by the Clinton Administration.  [ C4. ]  Markets</p>
        <p>Blue-chip stocks surged, with the Dow industrials jumping 35.21 points to another record close, of 3,792.93.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq uncovered short positions edged up to another record last month, but it was the smallest gain of 1993.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury prices were mixed in slow trading amid an unenthusiastic response to the weekly bill auction.  [ D14. ]</p>
        <p>Cold weather pushed up commodities prices. But Florida's groves were untouched, and orange juice prices plunged.  [ D16. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar rose against leading currencies. Gold prices rose in New York after being mixed overseas.  [ D16. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Investors are likely to find the home computer software market more fragmented than the business market, dominated by a few companies led by Microsoft. Market Place.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Radio revenue growth will exceed that of television and newspapers this year, as advertisers turn to the medium seeking niche markets as an alternative to mass reach. Advertising.  [ D17. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
