<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Districts Ready Budgets for Voters</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="843514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBERG, MERRI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DC1139F937A25757C0A960958260" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Districts Ready Budgets for Voters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBERG, MERRI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE lack of action on state and Federal budgets, the county's 34 noncity  school districts have had to do their homework in order to be on time with their proposed budgets for the 1996-97 school year. Voters in 30 of those 34 districts will vote on May 8. Tuckahoe, Bronxville, Eastchester and Briarcliff Manor will  present their budgets variously between May 1 and May 23. The cities of Mount Vernon, Peekskill, New Rochelle, Rye, White Plains and Yonkers do not need voter approval because their school expenses are included in their municipal budgets.</p>
        <p>The uncertainty generated by the state and Federal budget void is compounded  this year by concern about diminished revenue, created in part by reduced property tax assessments, cutbacks in state aid, costs associated with tax refunds known as certioraris, probable shifts in the cost of special-education programs from state to district level and efforts to maintain academic programs  with only modest or, in many cases, no increases in spending even in the face of increasing enrollments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE lack of action on state and Federal budgets, the county's 34 noncity  school districts have had to do their homework in order to be on time with their proposed budgets for the 1996-97 school year. Voters in 30 of those 34 districts will vote on May 8. Tuckahoe, Bronxville, Eastchester and Briarcliff Manor will  present their budgets variously between May 1 and May 23. The cities of Mount Vernon, Peekskill, New Rochelle, Rye, White Plains and Yonkers do not need voter approval because their school expenses are included in their municipal budgets.</p>
        <p>The uncertainty generated by the state and Federal budget void is compounded  this year by concern about diminished revenue, created in part by reduced property tax assessments, cutbacks in state aid, costs associated with tax refunds known as certioraris, probable shifts in the cost of special-education programs from state to district level and efforts to maintain academic programs  with only modest or, in many cases, no increases in spending even in the face of increasing enrollments.</p>
        <p>I've been doing this for 20 years," said John S. Whearty, Superintendent of the Mount Pleasant Central School District. "I keep waiting for the easy years,  but this is as bad as it gets. We're maintaining existing programs. We want to keep the district to the point where we've built it up. We're trying to preserve the quality of our programs and still have the community able to afford it." His district's proposed budget of $21.1 million reflects a 4.4 percent budget-to-budget increase and a 7.07 percent tax-rate increase.</p>
        <p>For many superintendents, the normal anxieties and pressures connected with budget preparation were exacerbated by the lack of hard numbers from the state and the Federal Government.</p>
        <p>"Whether the state acts or not, the local school districts must act," said Dr. John J. Russell, Superintendent of the Hastings-on-Hudson Union Free School  District. "We have to provide our best guesstimate. There's a real effort to contain costs. The problem is on the revenue side. There has been a decline in assessables. We've lost over $1 million, which translates into 2.3 percent of the tax rate. It's a tricky balancing act."</p>
        <p>For Dr. Richard S. Maurer of Tuckahoe, whose Board of Education will present  a proposed budget of $11.4 million, this has been a particularly frustrating endeavor. "We took the Governor at his word and factored in his proposed cuts in state aid and special education," Dr. Maurer said. "We also had a big hit on certioraris, for $1 million. The tax rate went up 4 percent without doing anything. We had to cut back on expenditures. Our spending increase is 1.2 percent, which is the lowest in the county."</p>
        <p>The lack of Federal and state budgets compounds the pressure on school districts, the superintendents insist.</p>
        <p>"We have no national budget and no state budget, which raises the level of alarm and places enormous pressure on the local level," said Dr. Ronald Valenti, Superintendent of the Harrison public schools and president of the Lower Hudson Council of Superintendents. "The stakes are much higher than in the past. Getting a budget passed in this environment is going to be much more difficult.  It could also be a wonderful opportunity to look at the financing of public education, which is at a crossroads. I think districts have responded remarkably well to the economic difficulties we face."</p>
        <p>In his own district, which has to pay a certiorari of $900,000 as a result of a summary judgment last month, the tax-rate increase is at 4.7 percent. The proposed budget is $37.1 million.</p>
        <p>Dr. Valenti added: "In the last five years, we've had to deal with two dragons: tax certioraris and reduced assessables. Hopefully, the taxpayer will understand and see the certiorari as something separate and apart."</p>
        <p>Certioraris are a demon that continues to plague many districts. Irvington, for one, has been particularly hard hit by the need to comply with court-ordered refunds. The district's proposed $20.7 million would require a 13.62 percent increase in the tax rate.</p>
        <p>"We're dealing with large certioraris," said Richard A. Hajek, the Irvington  Superintendent, who also serves as the high school principal as part of a cost-cutting measure. "This budget would include the payout. The cert payment is 8.88 percent; the drop in assessments is 3.8 percent, and the educational piece  of the tax increase is 0.94 percent. Our budget is very tight."</p>
        <p>Many districts, mindful of the pressure on residents, have proposed tax-rate  increases that fall between 4 and 5 percent.</p>
        <p>"We've been very frugal," said Dr. Frank P. Tota, Superintendent in Dobbs Ferry. "We're not hit with the depth of certioraris that we were hit with three  years ago, and I believe we have a very positive budget."</p>
        <p>The proposed budget of $15.4 million reflects a tax-rate increase of 5.9 percent, which is at the same level as last year. To contend with a 5.7 percent  increase in enrollment, the proposed budget would add teachers. Some funds would also be allocated to replace outdated technology.</p>
        <p>For some districts, budgetary realities prevent expanding educational programs.</p>
        <p>"We would like to be able to fund more educational initiatives, but we have to deal with the realities from a fiscal standpoint," said Nancy L. Taddiken, Superintendent of the Edgemont Union Free School District. The proposed budget of $20.8 million, which will be presented to the Board of Education on Tuesday,  calls for a 4.5 percent tax-rate increase and reflects a 2.76 percent budget-to-budget increase.</p>
        <p>In Ardsley, the district has taken an aggressive approach with regard to both cost- cutting and revenue enhancement, said the Superintendent, Stanley Toll. The proposed budget requires a 4.3 percent tax-rate increase.</p>
        <p>"We've been building into the budget-planning process ways to keep costs down," said Dr. Toll, whose district has a $2 million appropriated fund balance. "This is a great budget. It has been a good year for us. Our health care costs didn't go up this year. Instead of seeing 6 to 7 percent staff salary increases, we're talking about a 3 percent or less salary increase. Everything we can, we put the noose on.</p>
        <p>"It has to be cost effective. Our tight budgeting also includes maximizing our revenues. We've done an especially good job at looking at special-needs youngsters who could be served in-district instead of going to a Boces special-education program. There are also special-education youngsters from out  of district who pay tuition to attend our special-education program. We actively solicit rental income as well."</p>
        <p>Such cost-cutting efforts by districts have an impact at the Boards of Cooperative Educational Services, which are consortiums of local districts.</p>
        <p>"We are looking to reduce costs to the districts we serve by 21 percent," said Vincent Beni, district superintendent of the Southern Westchester Board of  Cooperative Educational Services, who will be reducing staff by 8 percent this spring instead of the usual 5 percent layoffs. Top administrative salaries will  be frozen for a year, and mid-level managers will receive only merit raises of up to 2 percent as part of the cost cutting.</p>
        <p>Dr. Beni added: "There will be 0 increase in tuition for all our programs. We are fully aware of the difficulties districts are having. We're directly involving the districts in our own budget planning."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
