<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers May Try To Lure Sather</title>
    <meta content="21RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Edmonton Oilers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sather, Glen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Edmonton Oilers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFDE1F31F932A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers May Try To Lure Sather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers reportedly are interested in hiring Edmonton Oilers president and general manager Glen Sather as their new general manager (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a silent spring at Madison Square Garden regarding the vacancies in the Rangers' hierarchy, while Garden President Dave Checketts methodically undertakes his search for a new general manager. That effort could shift gears as soon as tonight, if the Dallas Stars wrap up their first-round series against the Edmonton Oilers in Game 5.</p>
        <p>Once the Oilers are eliminated from the National Hockey League playoffs, their longtime team president and general manager, Glen Sather, can be wooed. Even though Sather has two seasons remaining on his contract, he also has an escape clause. According to several people in hockey, the Rangers are interested in Sather as a replacement for Neil Smith, who was fired on March 28 along with John Muckler, the coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a silent spring at Madison Square Garden regarding the vacancies in the Rangers' hierarchy, while Garden President Dave Checketts methodically undertakes his search for a new general manager. That effort could shift gears as soon as tonight, if the Dallas Stars wrap up their first-round series against the Edmonton Oilers in Game 5.</p>
        <p>Once the Oilers are eliminated from the National Hockey League playoffs, their longtime team president and general manager, Glen Sather, can be wooed. Even though Sather has two seasons remaining on his contract, he also has an escape clause. According to several people in hockey, the Rangers are interested in Sather as a replacement for Neil Smith, who was fired on March 28 along with John Muckler, the coach.</p>
        <p>Before the playoffs began, Sather said he was not going anywhere. But in a telephone conversation Wednesday night, Sather did not rule out the possibility of a move.</p>
        <p>''I suppose I'm flattered that people mention my name when jobs open up around the league,'' the 56-year-old Sather said from Dallas. ''I'm really not in a position to make any comments about that. I haven't given it one second of thought. As far as what I'm going to do, I haven't made any public statements about it. When the time comes, I'll deal with it.''</p>
        <p>Not only is the Garden interested in Sather, but also, according to one person in hockey with knowledge of the situation, ''whoever's second is a distant second.''</p>
        <p>Because of Sather's escape clause, the Rangers would not have to ask for permission to speak with him. That is something they would have to do with Pittsburgh if they pursue the Penguins' general manager, Craig Patrick, who is also believed to be on the Rangers' list.</p>
        <p>''That's the proper protocol,'' Sather said. ''But I, on the other hand, have a loophole that I wrote into my contract.'' The loophole says that Sather can talk to other teams freely if he decides to leave Edmonton.</p>
        <p>One longtime league executive said earlier this week that both Wayne Gretzky, who played for Sather in Edmonton in the 1980's, and Commissioner Gary Bettman have encouraged the Rangers to pursue Sather.</p>
        <p>''That rumor is not correct,'' Bettman said yesterday. ''I don't do that. It's up to the teams to decide. I don't get involved in personnel decisions.'' But it is no secret that Bettman and others hold Sather in high regard.</p>
        <p>Sather played for 10 N.H.L. seasons as a left wing for six teams, including the Rangers from 1970 to 1973. He became the Oilers' coach in 1977, when they were a part of the World Hockey Association.</p>
        <p>Three seasons later, Sather became the team's general manager and was the architect of the Oilers' dynasty in the 80's, when the franchise won four Stanley Cups in five seasons (plus a fifth without Gretzky in 1990).</p>
        <p>The Oilers have not advanced past the second round of the playoffs since 1992, but the Rangers have failed to qualify for the playoffs in the last three seasons. And there are many league executives who believe that Sather will allow himself to be wooed by the Rangers.</p>
        <p>But many are also skeptical about the Rangers' chances of actually persuading him to leave Edmonton. Sather has been there for 24 years, the last 21 as general manager. That gives him the second-longest tenure as a general manager in the N.H.L. behind Boston's Harry Sinden.</p>
        <p>Sather has long said he is comfortable in the West. He owns houses in both Palm Springs, Calif., and Banff, Alberta, and enjoys outdoor life.</p>
        <p>Sather's current contract calls for him to be paid just under $2 million in each of the next two seasons. One thing in the Rangers' favor is their ability to pay him significantly more.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
