<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fortune Is Smiling on Yankees, and They Smile Back</title>
    <meta content="21YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DE1F31F932A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fortune Is Smiling on Yankees, and They Smile Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees have won 11 of their first 14 games of season, and have eight-game winning steak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Part of being good is knowing when you have been lucky, and when Bernie Williams smiled and chuckled softly after Monday night's 11-inning victory against Texas, and David Cone arched his eyebrows, it was apparent the Yankees realized they had been fortunate.</p>
        <p>The Yankees bore the same incredulous expressions often in 1998, when they were good and lucky and set an American League record with 114 victories. They are winning games in that style in the early weeks of this season, having taken 11 of their first 14, including their current eight-game streak of victories. They begin a three-game series here Friday against Toronto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Part of being good is knowing when you have been lucky, and when Bernie Williams smiled and chuckled softly after Monday night's 11-inning victory against Texas, and David Cone arched his eyebrows, it was apparent the Yankees realized they had been fortunate.</p>
        <p>The Yankees bore the same incredulous expressions often in 1998, when they were good and lucky and set an American League record with 114 victories. They are winning games in that style in the early weeks of this season, having taken 11 of their first 14, including their current eight-game streak of victories. They begin a three-game series here Friday against Toronto.</p>
        <p>There have been too few games to determine whether the Yankees are as good as they were two years ago. But it appears that they could dominate the American League, with their deep pitching staff and a diverse offense, and they could approach 114 regular-season victories again.</p>
        <p>''I think it could be done,'' said Chad Curtis, the outfielder who played for the Yankees from 1997 to 1999, before being traded to Texas in the off-season.</p>
        <p>Curtis watched his former teammates win Monday's game in a manner he recognized. The Rangers' Darren Oliver held the Yankees hitless for six and one-third innings, but Cone pitched well and kept the score close, until Williams tied the game with a homer. The Yankees tied the game again in the ninth with a two-out, two-strike hit from Tino Martinez, and in the 11th inning, an umpire blew a call that destroyed a Texas rally and the Yankees came away feeling fortunate.</p>
        <p>''But when you put yourself in a position to win, like they did that whole game, you're going to win a lot of games,'' Curtis said. ''You look back on '98, and I can remember a series we played against Kansas City where there's two games in a row where we had no business winning. There was a line drive smoked at Scott Brosius for a double play, with the bases loaded with one out in the ninth inning.</p>
        <p>''After you win 114 games, you look back and you remember those. Things like that have to happen to win that many games.''</p>
        <p>Karma is not the only reason the Yankees could approach 114 victories again. Orlando Hernandez has developed into one of the best pitchers in the league -- he is 3-0 with a 1.74 earned run average after four starts, giving the Yankees an ace the way David Wells was their ace in 1998. Cone, coming off a season in which he finished second in the American League in earned run average, pitched effectively in his last start, as did Roger Clemens, and Andy Pettitte is expected to come off the disabled list next week. Ramiro Mendoza pitched six and one-third hitless innings in his first start last weekend.</p>
        <p>In all but two games, the Yankees have never trailed by more than two runs at any point, mostly because of the starters. ''The key is that we run a starter out there every night who is going to give us a chance, keep us in the game, that's what you really need,'' Cone said. ''There's a feeling you have a chance to win every day.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees ran the bases brazenly in 1998, something they lost in 1999, something they have regained this year. Two crucial runs in Wednesday's 5-4 victory over Texas were the result of stolen bases from Lance Johnson and Jorge Posada, and collectively they are averaging 1.4 stolen-base attempts a game; last April the Yankees had about two attempts for every three games.</p>
        <p>They have had an effective offense in recent years, even when they did not run, because they have so many good hitters. They continue to be a patient team that wears down opposing starters, forcing them to pitch deep into ball-strike counts, and the Yankees do have power from all parts of their lineup. The re-emphasis on aggressive base running gives them a more rounded attack.</p>
        <p>Posada came into this season as the team's most significant question mark, but so far he is hitting well (.327 with 3 homers and 10 runs batted in) and catching effectively; he could give the Yankees far greater production at this position than they have had. Paul O'Neill, coming off a difficult season, looks re-energized, even at 37, and is batting .396. The reliever Jeff Nelson has been exceptional in a year in which he will seek a contract extension.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have the best record in the majors, but it is not as if everything has gone smoothly thus far. Darryl Strawberry was supposed to be their designated hitter, and instead, he is out of baseball, suspended after a positive drug test. Brosius was injured on the second day of the season, and his replacements at third have six errors; Brosius could be back next week. Derek Jeter and Chuck Knoblauch have not really hit that well yet, and Ed Yarnall, who was expected to be the fifth starter, had a terrible spring and is working his way back toward the majors.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most incredible aspect of the Yankees' success in 1998 was how they maintained their will to win almost every single day of the grueling regular season. The Yankees won 98 games last year and went on to blitz through opponents in October, but during the regular season they occasionally slipped into a malaise, particularly against mediocre teams. In 1998 they hammered teams like Kansas City (winning 10 of 10 games), Minnesota (7 of 11) and Detroit (8 of 11).</p>
        <p>Last year they had losing records against struggling teams like Anaheim (4-6) and the Royals (4-5); at one point, Manager Joe Torre called a meeting to ask his players why this was. To approach 114 victories, the Yankees would have to muster that almost incomprehensible will once more.</p>
        <p>''The core players are the same,'' said Curtis, referring to the likes of O'Neill and Tino Martinez, ''so there's definitely no doubt about it -- they've got that mind-set, that attitude.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees open a three-game series with Toronto on Friday night. . . . The Yankees reached a four-year agreement to sign the pitcher ADRIAN HERNANDEZ two weeks ago, but the contract has not been completed, and in the interim, the Cuban defector -- who throws with a delivery fashioned after that of ORLANDO HERNANDEZ -- has been working out at the Yankees' facility in Tampa, Fla. The commissioner's office informed the Yankees on Thursday that until Hernandez's agreement was completed, he could not work out at the team's facility.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
