<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mora's Shot Warms Mets At Cold Shea</title>
    <meta content="21METS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Milwaukee Brewers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Milwaukee Brewers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DD1F31F932A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mora's Shot Warms Mets At Cold Shea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets beat Milwaukee Brewers, 5-4, in 10 innings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melvin Mora dropped his bat and acted as if he had just hit a single. He motored to first base while keeping his eyes focused on center field, watching his booming shot off Curtis Leskanic sail higher and higher. Could it go? Would it go?</p>
        <p>Yes, it could. Yes, it did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Melvin Mora dropped his bat and acted as if he had just hit a single. He motored to first base while keeping his eyes focused on center field, watching his booming shot off Curtis Leskanic sail higher and higher. Could it go? Would it go?</p>
        <p>Yes, it could. Yes, it did.</p>
        <p>Mora's first regular-season homer in the major leagues gave the Mets a 5-4 victory over the Milwaukee Brewers in 10 innings at Shea Stadium last night. He finally started trotting when he got past first base. A swarm of Mets waited for him at home plate. The postseason hero was suddenly a hero in April, too.</p>
        <p>There was a lifeless feeling at Shea before the game even started. The upper deck was completely empty, the mezzanine was mostly empty and the fans were mostly chilly. Al Leiter could have changed this dull atmosphere with a nifty outing, but he failed to enhance it because he was constantly in danger and was simply trying to survive.</p>
        <p>The Mets survived in a game in which they trailed by 4-1, and finally they thrived because Mora, who went into the game in the top of the 10th, crushed Leskanic's 95-mile-an-hour fastball. The homer caromed off the television camera stands beyond the center-field wall, a 417-foot shot that was not as momentous as his homer against Atlanta in his first National League Championship Series at-bat last October. But Mora was smiling as if this one was momentous, too.</p>
        <p>''Well, this is big,'' Mora said. ''I like this one.''</p>
        <p>Before Mora faced Leskanic, Edgardo Alfonzo told him that Leskanic throws a powerful fastball, a nasty slider and a cut fastball. As Mora strode to the plate, he said later, ''I wanted to jump on the fastball,'' which he did.</p>
        <p>It helped the Mets sweep a three-game series, beat the Brewers for the eighth straight time and win for the sixth time in their last seven games.</p>
        <p>''I've seen him hit like that in B.P.,'' said Derek Bell, referring to batting practice. ''He got a hold of one and I was like, 'Wow.' ''</p>
        <p>Although Leiter struggled all evening while allowing four earned runs on eight hits and three walks, this would have been a difficult game for the Mets to lose. The Brewers are more hapless than pesky and they look like the junior varsity trying to play the varsity. When Charlie Hayes, who had a homer among his three hits, is the cleanup batter, the team is not exactly fearsome.</p>
        <p>But Steve Woodard, who has not won a game since July 16, 1999, squelched the Mets, except for Mike Piazza's monstrous second-inning homer, through the first six innings. Bell homered to begin the seventh, and a single and a walk ended Woodard's night. Todd Zeile hit a run-scoring single off David Weathers and the Mets' fourth run scored on Jeromy Burnitz's throwing error.</p>
        <p>Leiter had trouble navigating through the first inning last season and searched for remedies to solve this problem. The problem emerged again last night as the Brewers quickly put him in a 1-0 hole. Marquis Grissom doubled and later scored on Burnitz's sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>Piazza helped the Mets tie the score as he blasted a 438-foot homer over the picnic area in left field off Woodard. It was Piazza's 17th hit in his last 33 at-bats, and it was the most majestic one.</p>
        <p>But James Mouton hit a broken-bat two-run homer off Leiter in the third, and Hayes poked a homer in the fifth to push the Milwaukee lead to 4-1.</p>
        <p>Three Mets relievers helped tame the Brewers after that, as Bell keyed a three-run rally in the seventh and then Mora played the hero in the 10th.</p>
        <p>Mora is obviously new at this. After a television interview on the field, a fan threw a T-shirt that hit him in the face. Mora stopped, picked the shirt up, signed it and politely returned it to the fan.</p>
        <p>Why not? It had been a good night for the utility player with a penchant for heroics.</p>
        <p>''I do want to play every day,'' Mora said. ''I'm the kind of player who likes to play every day. Now I'm going to continue to do this because this is how they want me to help.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>BILL PULSIPHER tossed seven solid innings for Class AAA Norfolk in a 3-0 loss to Charlotte yesterday. Pulsipher gave up three earned runs and six hits while striking out six and walking one. . . . REY ORDONEZ started at shortstop for the Mets after receiving a pain-relieving injection in his stiff neck, but grounded out with a chance to win the game in the ninth. He is 0 for 16 with runners in scoring position. . . . DEREK BELL has told Manager BOBBY VALENTINE to trust him in the second spot in the batting order. But Valentine declined to say Bell would be any kind of fixture there because he also likes using him in the fifth and sixth spots. . . . Left fielder JAMES MOUTON of the Brewers ran full speed into the back of shortstop MARK LORETTA while pursuing a pop-up down the third-base line. Mouton's chin rammed into Loretta's head. Both players were down for more than a minute and Loretta left the game because of dizziness.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
