<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Absent Fathers, a Ray of Hope</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HARD-CORE JOBLESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERATION FATHERHOOD</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TRENTON (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PETERSON, IVER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD1239F93AA1575AC0A964958260" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Absent Fathers, a Ray of Hope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVER PETERSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PETERSON, IVER</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Sept. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an old law office building on East Hanover Street here, a dozen men, all fathers of welfare children, are trying to leave the rootlessness of street life behind and learn how to become responsible parents, wage earners, maybe even husbands.</p>
        <p>These are the goals of Operation Fatherhood, the New Jersey version of a federally assisted experimental program called Parents Fair Share. While there are numerous programs to help welfare mothers, the program's reasoning goes, little has been done to help the absent fathers straighten their often tangled lives so that they can take responsibility for their offspring and start paying child support.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an old law office building on East Hanover Street here, a dozen men, all fathers of welfare children, are trying to leave the rootlessness of street life behind and learn how to become responsible parents, wage earners, maybe even husbands.</p>
        <p>These are the goals of Operation Fatherhood, the New Jersey version of a federally assisted experimental program called Parents Fair Share. While there are numerous programs to help welfare mothers, the program's reasoning goes, little has been done to help the absent fathers straighten their often tangled lives so that they can take responsibility for their offspring and start paying child support.</p>
        <p>But for the dozen or so men in the program here, the goal is a less lofty one: They just want a job that pays better than minimum wage. It does not have to be much better.</p>
        <p>"Here's the difference this place makes for me," said Leroy Johnson, a recovering alcoholic who brought his 9-month-old daughter Aleena with him to class. "It's making $7 or $8 a hour instead of making $4 or $5 an hour. That's all I'm asking."</p>
        <p>But even that step up from work in a fast-food restaurant to a job in a company mail room or as a security guard can be difficult for men without high school diplomas, with a history of arrests, and with a habit of ignoring small problems, like a traffic ticket, until they become catastrophic.</p>
        <p>"They've been in a different society from the rest of us," said Al Walker, the executive director of Operation Fatherhood. "They're from the society of sneakin' and runnin' and duckin'. Now we've got to introduce them to the mainstream society."</p>
        <p>Along the way, the program organizers hope, the man may learn to work things out in their relationships with women instead of simply running from them. They may even learn tenderness when, during a class on making relationships last, they field questions like, "What is your partner's favorite movie?" "What is her shoe size?" "What's the one thing she is really afraid of?" Emphasis on Achievement</p>
        <p>Operation Fatherhood is open only to fathers of children on welfare who are not the parent with custody.  About half a dozen participants, the older ones, have been referred to Operation Fatherhood by the Mercer County welfare office with the promise that their child-support obligations will be lowered or suspended while they are enrolled.</p>
        <p>The younger men, who must acknowledge paternity of their child or children to remain in the program, come for the promise of help in getting a job.</p>
        <p>But before they can join the Job Club and apply for work with sympathetic employers that Operation Fatherhood has recruited, they must take the four-to-six-week peer support program, the core of the program to change attitudes and outlooks.</p>
        <p>"This is the first place I've been to where they tell you how life really should be," said David Chaviez, an 18-year-old who dropped out of school at 15 and who, a year later, became the father of Devonica, now being raised by her mother, who is on welfare.</p>
        <p>"I was scared being out in the world," Mr. Chaviez said. "I didn't know what I was going to do from the next day to the next. I feel like I have some hope now."</p>
        <p>Larry Davis, a 35-year-old who owes about $15,000 in child support for his three children, conceded that he had been coached earlier in his life on the basics of job hunting -- be on time, wear a tie, look the interviewer in the eye. But he credits Operation Fatherhood with having a higher level of caring.</p>
        <p>"The mother of my children will only let me come around and see them when I got some money," he said. He recalled discussing the problem with the welfare caseworker, "and she said, 'Well, I guess you better go out and pick up some cans.' That's their attitude -- go pick up some cans."</p>
        <p>Since Operation Fatherhood started in July, 12 men have been found jobs, with the rest of the participants still in training.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson said he just likes the way Joseph Steele, the peer support teacher, talked with the participants.</p>
        <p>"See, I never had a father," he said.  "I was brought up by my mother, and I learned from a woman's point of view. Everything else I learned in the streets. Joe Steele, he teaches me from a father's point of view. It's like a refresher course."</p>
        <p>Barbara Kelley-Sease, the executive director of Trenton's Industrial Home for Children, which administers Operation Fatherhood for the state Department of Human Services, said the men were not used to anyone paying attention to their problems.</p>
        <p>"People call them deadbeat dads or runaway fathers," she said. "But nobody has ever addressed these questions with them, no one has taken the time to help them develop into the kinds of parents they would like to be."</p>
        <p>The program tries to help the men put the troubles and the turmoil of the street behind them.</p>
        <p>The other day, some of the fathers were standing out on East Hanover Street, taking a break from the classwork inside, when a police van drove slowly by. Jonathan Ledlow, a big man in overalls, instinctively stiffened, but Al Walker laid a reassuring hand on his arm.</p>
        <p>"Relax, Jon," he said. "You're with us now."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ledlow, who owes $10,500 in support for two children by two women, has decided that, with such support, the basic middle-class dream -- a home, a wife, kids and a picket fence -- could one day be his after all.</p>
        <p>"Maybe not the picket fence," he said on reflection. "Probably a barbed-wire fence. But the wife, the kids, a home, yeah. Maybe I can."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
