<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Americans Say Genetic Information Is Public Property</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTH DEFECTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETICS AND HEREDITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVACY, RIGHT OF</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARCH OF DIMES BIRTH DEFECTS FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARRIS, LOUIS, AND ASSOCIATES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANGIER, NATALIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D6153BF93AA1575AC0A964958260" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Americans Say Genetic Information Is Public Property</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATALIE ANGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANGIER, NATALIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A MAJORITY of Americans believe that people found to carry a genetic disease or a defective gene do not have a right to absolute privacy about their condition, a survey has found. Among those thought to have a right to information about a patient's genetic defects are not only people with an immediate concern, like spouses and other family members, but insurance companies and even employers.</p>
        <p>The results, being released today, suggest that Americans are not as wedded to the concept of unequivocal patient confidentiality as many ethicists and legal scholars might have thought or hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A MAJORITY of Americans believe that people found to carry a genetic disease or a defective gene do not have a right to absolute privacy about their condition, a survey has found. Among those thought to have a right to information about a patient's genetic defects are not only people with an immediate concern, like spouses and other family members, but insurance companies and even employers.</p>
        <p>The results, being released today, suggest that Americans are not as wedded to the concept of unequivocal patient confidentiality as many ethicists and legal scholars might have thought or hoped.</p>
        <p>But the findings also imply to some that the public is extremely optimistic about the progress of gene therapy and other experimental approaches to taming inherited diseases, and that therefore the more open everybody is about genetic disorders, the more quickly all will benefit. Enthusiasm and Ignorance</p>
        <p>The survey was commissioned by the March of Dimes Birth Defects Foundation and conducted by Louis Harris and Associates. In the study, 1,000 adults were asked a series of questions about gene therapy and genetic testing. The survey, which was conducted in April, has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus 3 percentage points.</p>
        <p>The findings painted a portrait of a public at once deeply enthusiastic about the new science of gene therapy, in which patients receive healthy copies of genes they lack, but admittedly ignorant of any details about who might benefit or how. For example, 89 percent said they approved of using the novel approach to thwart genetic disorders, yet 60 percent confessed they had heard almost nothing about the technique.</p>
        <p>"This is what I find so surprising," said Dr. Jennifer L. Howse, president of the March of Dimes. "There's a real anomaly between the public's overwhelming approval for gene therapy, and its overwhelming lack of knowledge."</p>
        <p>More disturbing to other experts was that a sizable minority of respondents condoned the possible use of gene therapy for conditions beyond disease. About 43 percent of those polled said they either somewhat or strongly approved of the use of gene therapy to "improve the physical characteristics that children would inherit," while 42 percent approved of gene therapy, for example, to "improve the intelligence level that children would inherit." Open to Altering Traits</p>
        <p>"It's startling that people are so open to the use of genetic techniques for the enhancement of certain traits, rather than the treatment of disease," said Dr. LeRoy Walters, a bioethicist at the Kennedy Institute of Ethics at Georgetown University in Washington.</p>
        <p>Experts suggested that these results could reflect the idea, which has won wide exposure in recent years, that intelligence is largely a product of inheritance. But scientists emphasize that they were far from being in a position to manipulate the genes governing intelligence, if such genes exist.</p>
        <p>In questions about genetic testing, the public's answers again proved unexpected. When asked whether someone other than a patient had a right to know that the person had a genetic defect, 57 percent said yes. Of those who answered positively, 98 percent said a spouse or fiance had a right to know, 58 percent said an insurer had a right to know, and 33 percent said an employer deserved to be so illuminated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Howse said the figures were surprising given how patients found to carry the virus that causes AIDS have had such widely publicized difficulty in obtaining or keeping medical coverage. And people suspected of carrying the gene that causes Huntington's disease, a devastating neurological disorder that normally strikes when a person is about 40, have testified before Congress that they have been refused medical coverage. In theory, when insurance companies discover that a person carries a genetic predisposition toward, say, breast cancer, they could refuse coverage or make it prohibitively expensive.</p>
        <p>So far, only eight states have laws that prohibit employers from discriminating against a person because of the results of a genetic test, and most of those laws apply only to people found to carry the trait for sickle-cell anemia. For other genetic diseases, the legal future remains an enormous unknown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
