<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Victories Speak for Themselves</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA HAWKS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BASKETBALL ASSN (NBA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARATON, HARVEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILKENS, LENNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Atlanta Hawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDA123BF937A35752C0A963958260" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Victories Speak for Themselves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Harvey Araton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARATON, HARVEY</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Red Auerbach all but in the rearview mirror by yesterday afternoon, Lenny Wilkens was asked to take a moment and consider possible goals on the road ahead. It was a tossup question, beginning a fishing expedition for affirmation that Wilkens, soon to become pro basketball's top-winning coach, also fancies the helm of the next United States Olympic team.</p>
        <p>Wilkens brushed aside this clumsy bait, and countered with a line of his own, typically direct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Red Auerbach all but in the rearview mirror by yesterday afternoon, Lenny Wilkens was asked to take a moment and consider possible goals on the road ahead. It was a tossup question, beginning a fishing expedition for affirmation that Wilkens, soon to become pro basketball's top-winning coach, also fancies the helm of the next United States Olympic team.</p>
        <p>Wilkens brushed aside this clumsy bait, and countered with a line of his own, typically direct.</p>
        <p>Who wouldn't want to?" he said, with a trademark half-smile that quickly fades, like a ray of sunshine poking through clouds. "Of course."</p>
        <p>It would be a rare occasion that Wilkens ever had the team everyone was expecting to win.</p>
        <p>A third of the way through his 22d season as a head coach in the National Basketball Association, victory No. 939 again eluded Wilkens last night, when his starless, blue-collar Atlanta Hawks rallied from 17 points down, but lost to the Portland Trail Blazers, 103-98, at the Omni. Tonight, the 57-year-old Wilkens returns to his birthplace, New York City, to play the Knicks at Madison Square Garden, still looking to become the new holder of the Auerbach record for victories that has stood for 28 years.</p>
        <p>"It's going to happen when it happens," Wilkens said, after a depressing night in a half-empty arena. "The thing that's special about it is that we --meaning we, as coaches -- never thought it would be broken."</p>
        <p>He, as the man to break it, requires a special appreciation, in that Wilkens, unlike Auerbach, coached no dynasties, no Bill Russells. And, as Wilkens put it, "No Hall of Famers," like the Hall of Fame point guard he was. Oh, he had Bill Walton for the blink of an eye in Portland, but Walton was hurt and Jack Ramsay was destined to replace Wilkens for the 1977 championship ride. In Seattle, where Wilkens won his one N.B.A. title in 1979, it could be argued that the young Dennis Johnson was a great player, but then, he was easily eclipsed as the premier guard in the West a year later by Magic Johnson in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mark Price and Brad Daugherty in Cleveland were second-tier stars, and fragile to boot. By the time Wilkens reached Atlanta last season, Dominique Wilkins was older and slower, but alas, no wiser. So Wilkens has made his coaching career out of inheriting teams on their backs and making them stand erect, proud, professional, a progression he himself undertook as a poor and fatherless 5-year-old in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>To reach this place, it took a magnificent love of the game, and its people, and not necessarily in that order. It took a thick skin for an African American male, whose father was black and whose mother is white, to successfully navigate an industry dominated by whites. It took a temperament that could tolerate noisier, ego-driven peers who usually got the better breaks and the bigger bucks.</p>
        <p>He has come to No. 939 without the need to rhapsodize, or psychoanalyze. There has never been gimmickry in his game plan. There has been no celebrated Lenny Wilkens system, the catch word for coaches who seek to create no-lose scenarios whereby the System succeeds when they win, but ill-suited players fail the System when they don't.</p>
        <p>"I maximized the talent I had," Wilkens said, in about as glowing a testimonial as he will give himself.</p>
        <p>It has become fashionable now to say that Wilkens has been the most unappreciated coach in the N.B.A., as if the news media has been asleep for too many years. The simple truth is that it is not human nature to glorify teams that lose in the second round of the playoffs, or their coaches. But in a business where you're absolutely brilliant with Superstar X and a dithering idiot the morning after he retires, the number of championships should never be the sole determinant for coaching prominence. By that flawed line of thinking, Pat Riley would have to be considered a failure in New York.</p>
        <p>N.B.A. people, Chuck Daly said recently, have admired and, in many cases, borrowed from Lenny Wilkens for years. Don Nelson, facing emotional exhaustion at Golden State, said recently that he would like to work the game "more like Lenny." That would be with an outward calm, a control that represents a firm, no-nonsense approach and doesn't include the need to make a spectacle out of one's self.</p>
        <p>"It was the American way," Wilkens said of the stereotypical coach as a berating bully. He has done more than his share to alter, if not junk, that perception. Although dedicated, even addicted, to the "coaching life," Wilkens has also allowed himself to be a balanced human being. A husband, a father of three, a coach who stays up late watching not game films but feature films, or reading nonsports books.</p>
        <p>In this time, when so many complain that today's players just don't want to listen, Wilkens says, uncompromisingly, "I'm not going to embarrass anyone, but I tell them, 'If you have a problem with me being honest with you, then you'll have to go someplace else.' "</p>
        <p>Why wouldn't his players, any players, listen to Lenny Wilkens? His life has been like so many of theirs, staggering out of the gate. And why, after all the ridicule the last collection of megamillionaires brought on themselves at the 1994 world championships in Toronto, would anyone -- least of all the U.S.A. Basketball Committee -- object to Wilkens out front of the 1996 Olympic team?</p>
        <p>"There are other aspects to it, political aspects, and I would never campaign for it," he said. "Never."</p>
        <p>He shouldn't have to. The Games, after all, will be here in Atlanta. And he, Lenny Wilkens, will be the sport's top-winning coach. A perfect fit.  ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
