<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Part-Time College Teaching Rises, as Do Worries</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PART-TIME EMPLOYMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDUCATION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D61731F937A35752C0A963958260" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Part-Time College Teaching Rises, as Do Worries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>CLAREMONT, Calif., Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They call themselves "freeway fliers," the Ph.D. graduates who cannot find full-time faculty teaching jobs and who spend their days commuting back and forth among part-time jobs at various colleges where they have no certainty of employment from one semester to the next.</p>
        <p>They are a sign of the times as colleges and universities seek economies by leaving staff jobs vacant, relying on part-time teachers to fill the gaps and save them money on higher salaries and benefits. And they have aroused debate in academia over whether institutions have acted responsibly in turning out so many highly qualified specialists only to leave them stranded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They call themselves "freeway fliers," the Ph.D. graduates who cannot find full-time faculty teaching jobs and who spend their days commuting back and forth among part-time jobs at various colleges where they have no certainty of employment from one semester to the next.</p>
        <p>They are a sign of the times as colleges and universities seek economies by leaving staff jobs vacant, relying on part-time teachers to fill the gaps and save them money on higher salaries and benefits. And they have aroused debate in academia over whether institutions have acted responsibly in turning out so many highly qualified specialists only to leave them stranded.</p>
        <p>"In one day I drive 100 miles and teach 100 students at three different colleges," said Susan Imbarrato, an English instructor who has been commuting this way for five years. "I feel like this information machine, sort of Teach "R" Us. What are we doing in our cars, all these Ph.D.'s on the freeways, listening to talk radio?"</p>
        <p>At the annual convention of the Modern Language Association last week in San Diego, the group's president, Patricia Meyer Spacks, called the growing reliance on part-time college instructors an urgent problem. Their schedules, she said, are "insanely demanding."</p>
        <p>David Merkowitz, a spokesman for the American Council on Education, which represents 1,600 colleges and universities, said the use of part-time faculty members had risen sharply in the 1990's after cutbacks in state support for higher education. He said more than half of the colleges had increased their use in 1993 and another one-third last year.</p>
        <p>About 40 percent of the college faculty members today are part-timers, twice as many as two decades ago, said Jack H. Schuster, professor of education and public policy at the Claremont Graduate School, who has studied the numbers for the Modern Language Association. Among these part-timers, he said, "the raw numbers of frustrated would-be full-time faculty members has surely expanded considerably in recent years."</p>
        <p>The situation, Professor Schuster said, is the result of a delay in the expected widespread retirement of professors hired in the 1960's and the slowness of many institutions in replacing those who do retire.</p>
        <p>The retirements are inevitable over the next decade or more, he said, and should coincide with the increase in college enrollments predicted by demographers, creating an active job market. But several experts said that with graduate schools continuing to turn out more specialists, Ms. Imbarrato's generation of scholars could fall through the cracks.</p>
        <p>"I walk around and I think, All I want to do is teach," said Ms. Imbarrato, who specializes in early American literature. "It's not like I want to rob a bank. What else can I do with a Ph.D. in English?"</p>
        <p>This is how she describes her schedule:</p>
        <p>"I remember last year I taught at 8 A.M., drove 30 miles from Claremont to Cal State, taught two hours, had office hours, got back in my car and drove 20 miles to teach a community college class. Then I would get back in the car, eat a candy bar and drink some juice and drive 20 miles back to the campus I was at in the morning. I'd get caffeinated, walk in and teach another two hours."</p>
        <p>The exhaustion of driving back and forth while full-time teachers can meet with students, work on committees and produce their own academic work is compounded by a daily diet of humiliation, some part-timers said.</p>
        <p>They must accept the early morning and late evening classes, they said, and even these offers often do not come until days before a semester starts. Their colleagues often do not know their names, they added, and their students sometimes treat them with less respect.</p>
        <p>"The worst thing is the sense of alienation," said Amanda Donta, a 31-year-old English instructor who has been a part-timer for six years and is now working on a master's degree in classical flute performance.</p>
        <p>"I don't even have a phone extension," she said. "All I have is a mailbox, and it changes every term. Once it was a Cheez Whiz box, just a cardboard Cheez Whiz box. That was my home base."</p>
        <p>People like Ms. Imbarrato and Ms. Donta sometimes juggle the schedules of different colleges on the quarter and semester systems. For each course they are paid a fee that ranges from about $900 a semester at a community college to as much as $3,000 at a private college. Together, the patchwork of classes they put together may equal the annual $28,000 to $30,000 starting salary for a Ph.D. at a California state college.</p>
        <p>By using part-time instructors, several of them said, colleges can avoid providing the benefits they would be entitled to if they had more than a minimum teaching load.</p>
        <p>Iris Molotsky, a spokeswoman for the American Association of University professors, agreed. "Administrators say they use part-time faculty because they want greater flexibility," she said. "But the reality is that these people are just hired over and over again. What they really want is not to pay health benefits and life insurance and so on. It's just exploitation."</p>
        <p>Professor Schuster said the nationwide proportion of part-time college faculty members, also known as gypsies or nomads, had risen to the current 40 percent from about 33 percent in the mid-1980's and 22 percent in the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>By the year 2008, he calculated, nearly half the 595,000 full-time college faculty members in the nation are likely to retire. But he said it appeared clear from current trends that not all would be replaced by full-time teachers.</p>
        <p>As college faculty hiring has slowed sharply, the number of people seeking jobs in higher education has risen, said William Zumeta, a professor at the graduate school of public affairs at the University of Washington.</p>
        <p>"In the last five years or so the numbers of Ph.D.'s granted in this country has jumped by about 5,000 a year, up from about 33,000, where it was for a long time, to about 38,000," Professor Zumeta said. "More people are seeking fewer jobs."</p>
        <p>These job-seekers make up 15 percent to 20 percent of part-time faculty members, said Howard Tuckman, dean of the college of business at Virginia Commonwealth University, who has written books on part-time faculty members.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tuckman has dubbed them part-mooners, as opposed to full-mooners, who may have a full-time job in another field, as lawyers or businessmen or journalists, or may be spouses of full-time faculty members or writers who are happy with a part-time teaching job.</p>
        <p>Some institutions, like junior colleges, rely more heavily than others on part-time faculty members. At California State University at San Bernardino, Ms. Imbarrato is one of 237 part-timers on a faculty that totals 626. At Pomona College last semester, she was one of just 20 part-timers on a faculty of 180.</p>
        <p>Though part-time faculty members may bring high qualifications and enthusiasm to their jobs, an increasing reliance on their work could do long-term damage to academic institutions, said Emory Elliott, the former head of the English department at Princeton University, who now teaches English at the University of California at Riverside.</p>
        <p>"A pretty important shift has happened in the last five years that is clearest in California," Professor Elliott said. "The senior ranks of the professoriate are being really emptied by early retirements, and not only are they not being replaced but there is no plan to replace them because people are not working their way up through the system."</p>
        <p>A result, he said, is that some departments have no senior faculty members to give them focus or to direct graduate studies.</p>
        <p>Some part-time professors settle in for years, like Jean Mather, who said she had "flown the freeways" since 1981 and called her part-time arrangements, which earn her about $25,000 a year, "the perfect job for a mom with a family."</p>
        <p>Some, like Deborah Dietrich, who managed to compose an article for publication while she drove on the freeways, do win full-time jobs. She is now an assistant professor of English at California State at Fullerton.</p>
        <p>Others, like Julie LaMay Abner, keep driving and hoping.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abner, 36, who specializes in Native American literature, has been a freeway flier for three years. She calculated that she traveled 758 miles every five-day week last semester to classes at various institutions, including Boron Men's Prison in Boron, Calif.</p>
        <p>"We are not guaranteed any more employment from one semester to the next," she said, "so every semester we have to be dynamic and energetic and productive and not complain.</p>
        <p>"But I do have a goal in life. My goal in life -- my ultimate goal -- is to drive somewhere, park my car, teach all day, get in my car and drive home. That's it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
