<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Won't Run in '96; Kemp Likely to Follow Suit</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="735010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHENEY, DICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEMP, JACK F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF1331F937A35752C0A963958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Won't Run in '96; Kemp Likely to Follow Suit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the former Defense Secretary and a prominent Republican Presidential prospect, announced today that he would not seek his party's nomination in 1996. The field may narrow still further because advisers to another well-known contender, Jack F. Kemp, said it appeared increasingly unlikely that Mr. Kemp would run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney appeared to be preparing a campaign for national office as he toured the country in the last two years on behalf of Republican candidates. But in recent months he had been less visible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the former Defense Secretary and a prominent Republican Presidential prospect, announced today that he would not seek his party's nomination in 1996. The field may narrow still further because advisers to another well-known contender, Jack F. Kemp, said it appeared increasingly unlikely that Mr. Kemp would run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney appeared to be preparing a campaign for national office as he toured the country in the last two years on behalf of Republican candidates. But in recent months he had been less visible.</p>
        <p>In a brief statement made public by his office here, Mr. Cheney, 53, a former Congressman from Wyoming who was Defense Secretary under President George Bush, gave no reasons for his decision.</p>
        <p>"After careful consideration, I have decided not to become a candidate for the Presidency in 1996," his statement said. "I appreciated very much the kind words of encouragement and support I received from the many Americans who had urged me to seek the Presidency."</p>
        <p>Advisers to Mr. Kemp, another former Congressman who also served in the Bush Cabinet, as Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, said he had not made a decision about running for President. But several people who have had conversations with him about the race said they had increasing doubts that he would run. They said he was still ambivalent, and noted that he had done nothing to lay the groundwork for a race.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people are increasingly convinced that he's not going to run," said an associate of Mr. Kemp, speaking on the condition that he not be named.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kemp, who is 59, is expected to make a final decision after meeting here late next week with longtime supporters from Congress, where he served 18 years as a Representative from Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Even before any candidates have formally announced their intentions, the Republican field is beginning to take shape, with Senator Phil Gramm of Texas, former Gov. Lamar Alexander of Tennessee and Senator Bob Dole of Kansas the most active candidates. Mr. Dole, the incoming Senate majority leader, said today that he might announce the formation of an exploratory committee in the next week or two, and Mr. Gramm has already scheduled his announcement for Feb. 23.</p>
        <p>Senator Dole described Mr. Cheney as "a quality person who would have been a formidable Presidential candidate."</p>
        <p>Former Vice President Dan Quayle has also been telling advisers he plans to seek the nomination. But it was unclear if his recent health problems would affect his decision. Today Mr. Quayle was in a hospital in Indianapolis for the surgical removal of an enlarged appendix later this week. He was treated for blood clots in his lungs just last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's withdrawal is unlikely to have a discernible effect on the Republican field because he did not have a particularly large base of support. Many Republican operatives had described him as an attractive second-choice candidate: though he is not flashy, Mr. Cheney presented himself as a reassuring leader on matters of war and peace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, who headed the Pentagon during the Persian Gulf war in 1990 and 1991, was relaxing today in Jackson Hole, Wyo., and was giving no interviews, a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said Mr. Cheney's foreign affairs background seemed less relevant when Congress seems consumed with domestic matters.</p>
        <p>Others said that even though Mr. Cheney had raised more than $1 million through his political action committee, he was not eager to make the personal sacrifices necessary to run. He has had three heart attacks, though it was not known whether his health was a factor in his decision not to run.</p>
        <p>"I don't think he found a compelling message in the last couple of years," said former Representative Vin Weber of Minnesota. "In terms of the test, 'Will you sleep soundly with this guy in the White House?' he passed the test. But I never found that Dick was articulating a cutting-edge message."</p>
        <p>Mr. Weber, who is closer to Mr. Kemp, said the former Housing Secretary was discussing his options with his family. "He's genuinely uncertain," Mr. Weber said. "Part of him really wants to do it, but part of him also enjoys the private life. The major question in his mind is: Is his message going to be the right message in 1996?"</p>
        <p>After Mr. Bush lost the 1992 election, Mr. Kemp was mentioned by many leading Republicans as the party's strongest contender to regain the White House. But now that Republicans have taken control of Congress, there may be less appeal in the party for Mr. Kemp's proposals for helping the poor and rebuilding inner cities.</p>
        <p>In discussing Mr. Cheney's possible reason's for not running, William Kristol, the Republican policy analyst who was Mr. Quayle's chief of staff, said Mr. Cheney learned that "foreign policy is just not on anyone's radar screen right now." But then Mr. Kristol put forth a less obvious explanation.</p>
        <p>"You have to be a little bit crazy to run for President," he said, "and Dick Cheney is a very sane man."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
