<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Worlds Meet at Kennedy Center</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="654314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KENNEDY CENTER HONORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KENNEDY CENTER HONORS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE WITT, KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SONDHEIM, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARSON, JOHNNY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ARTHUR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOLTI, GEORG (SIR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, MARION</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE WITT, KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SONDHEIM, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARSON, JOHNNY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ARTHUR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOLTI, GEORG (SIR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, MARION</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Stephen Sondheim</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD8103EF935A35751C1A965958260" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Worlds Meet at Kennedy Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DE WITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DE WITT, KAREN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the whoop of gospel music to the crash of a Nebraska marching band, the 16th annual Kennedy Center Honors seemed as much a celebration of a rapprochement between the arts world and lawmakers as a tribute to the five artists honored.</p>
        <p>"You can feel the change in the air," said the composer and lyricist Stephen Sondheim, who received one of the honors, given at at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the whoop of gospel music to the crash of a Nebraska marching band, the 16th annual Kennedy Center Honors seemed as much a celebration of a rapprochement between the arts world and lawmakers as a tribute to the five artists honored.</p>
        <p>"You can feel the change in the air," said the composer and lyricist Stephen Sondheim, who received one of the honors, given at at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts here.</p>
        <p>At the awards program, Mr. Sondheim shared a box with President Clinton and his wife, Hillary; Vice President Al Gore and his wife, Tipper, and the other recipients: the entertainer Johnny Carson; Arthur Mitchell, the founder of Dance Theater of Harlem; the conductor Sir Georg Solti, and the gospel singer Marion Williams.</p>
        <p>At a White House reception tonight, Mrs. Clinton joked to a crowded audience that this year's honors program was a standing-room-only event. Many guests at the reception were in fact standing because there were too few seats.</p>
        <p>The President paid tribute to each artist honored. He confused Mr. Mitchell's name with that of the playwright Arthur Miller, but deftly recovered.</p>
        <p>At a brunch earlier in the day given by George Stevens Jr., who co-produces the awards with Don Mischer, Mr. Sondheim said, "The arts are on an upswing because of Clinton."</p>
        <p>The gala, always a hot ticket despite its $1,500-a-person cost, drew many more artists from across the country than in the past. Several, including the actress Kathleen Turner, had been on a waiting list for the event, which is to be broadcast by CBS, on Dec. 29.</p>
        <p>This year, there was a rapport between the Clinton Administration and the artistic world, partly attributable to the appointment of the actress Jane Alexander as the head of the National Endowment for the Arts.</p>
        <p>"We feel we have a friend in the White House," said the actress Angela Lansbury,who began an impressive career in Broadway musicals in Mr. Sondheim's "Anyone Can Whistle." She introduced the segment honoring Mr. Sondheim, who she said "has taken all of us along on his glorious voyage to a new musical world."</p>
        <p>During the evening performance, Ms. Alexander introduced the segment honoring Ms. Williams, describing her as the "golden voice of gospel's golden age" and noting that her career had inspired those of Aretha Franklin and others.</p>
        <p>Ms. Franklin, Little Richard and Billy Preston performed a rousing gospel tribute to Ms. Williams that included a 100-voice gospel choir.</p>
        <p>Ms. Williams said she was particularly pleased by the honor because "gospel has been on the back burner and ignored through the years."</p>
        <p>The conductor and pianist Daniel Barenboim paid tribute to Sir Georg. And Andre Previn, the conductor, said he was "always happy that when someone from the classical music field wins." Visitors From Nebraska</p>
        <p>One surprise of the evening was the University of Nebraska marching band, which marched down the aisle of the red-and-gilt Opera House in a tribute to Mr. Carson, an alumnus of the university. Ted Koppel, who as the host of ABC's "Nightline" was Mr. Carson's late-night competitor for many years, drew laughter by graciously acknowledging the man who "for 30 years tucked us in, and we lay in the dark and laughed." And David Letterman, whose "Late Night" show used to follow Mr. Carson's, also offered a tribute, including his Top 10 list of "things we miss about Johnny Carson."</p>
        <p>The segment that drew the most laughter of the evening was a clip of Mr. Clinton's 1988 guest appearance on the "Tonight" show, when Mr. Carson gave a long introduction before actually inviting Mr. Clinton, then Governor of Arkansas, onstage. Mr. Carson's spiel was a reference to Mr. Clinton's extraordinarily long speech at the 1988 Democratic National Convention.</p>
        <p>As in past years, Walter Cronkite, the former CBS News anchor, was host of program. He ended the show with a tribute to all the artists.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
