<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; From the Origins of Life to Its Future</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="636590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SECRET OF LIFE, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DA163FF936A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; From the Origins of Life to Its Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Make way for a mind-expanding science series that gets to the genes of things. "The Secret of Life," a remarkably lucid and visually vivid explanation of the nature and promise of DNA, goes in eight engrossing hours from the mists of prehistory into the fog of the future.</p>
        <p>The opener tomorrow night suggests how life might have begun about four billion years ago, not in the "warm little pond" imagined by Charles Darwin but in some sulfuric steam bath like the one that Karl Stetter, a German biologist, is seen admiring near Naples. From the bacteria he finds there, he extracts what he believes is ancient DNA of a sort that has carried instructions down the ages for the making of many species, including humans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Make way for a mind-expanding science series that gets to the genes of things. "The Secret of Life," a remarkably lucid and visually vivid explanation of the nature and promise of DNA, goes in eight engrossing hours from the mists of prehistory into the fog of the future.</p>
        <p>The opener tomorrow night suggests how life might have begun about four billion years ago, not in the "warm little pond" imagined by Charles Darwin but in some sulfuric steam bath like the one that Karl Stetter, a German biologist, is seen admiring near Naples. From the bacteria he finds there, he extracts what he believes is ancient DNA of a sort that has carried instructions down the ages for the making of many species, including humans.</p>
        <p>With his jargon-free narration, engaging manner and puckish looks, the series guide, Dr. David Suzuki, a professor of zoology at the University of British Columbia, becomes the latest star of public broadcasting. Don't be surprised if he turns up as a guru in some Steven Spielberg extravaganza.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow he visits an entomologist who is extracting the DNA from insects caught in amber tens of millions of years ago (with the obligatory nod to "Jurassic Park"); scientists at the National Institutes of Health who are deciphering the code in the human brain that controls much of what we do and may explain why we do it; a researcher at Cambridge University who is studying the nematode, a little worm that is a sort of microcosm of the human animal, and a researcher at Oxford University who is finding clues to the behavior of humans in the behavior of yeast.</p>
        <p>How such investigations may be helping scientists nudge human development in a benign direction is the hopeful subject of the succeeding programs. In the second hour tomorrow, you can learn all about mutations, the random errors that have enabled humans, animals and plants to adapt and endure.</p>
        <p>In the quest for visual variety, the producers occasionally prettify things (the famous double helix is shown as a sort of lace trimming from a fancy ball gown), and the glowing pictures of animal life may remind you of innumerable nature shows. (Sure, fish got to swim and birds got to fly, but do they have to look like greeting cards?) And the generally down-to-cases Dr. Suzuki goes trendy with rhapsodies upon the "oneness of life" he finds in the religions of Indians in British Columbia. The laboratory scenes with that worm are at least as impressive and more in the scientific spirit of the series.</p>
        <p>But these are pardonable lapses in a considerable accomplishment. Tune in Monday for possible answers to the ever interesting question of what makes girls different from boys and the ever urgent one of how to cure some forms of cancer. Tuesday's episode goes into genetically engineered foods, drugs and human organs and the workings and misworkings of the human immune system. The series ends on Wednesday with examples of gene therapy that can help the body operate the way one wants it to and of efforts to learn through studies of identical twins what makes people the same and different.</p>
        <p>It must be mentioned that the executive in charge of "The Secret of Life" is Paula Apsell, the director of the science unit at WGBH, the Boston public station, and the executive producer of "Nova." Do we owe it all to her genes? THE SECRET OF LIFE PBS, tomorrow through Wednesday at 9 (Channels 13 and 49 in the New York area) An eight-part documentary produced by James F. Golway, Andrew Liebman, Tim Haines, Paul Gasek, Christine Zurbach Wiser, Graham Chedd, Larkin McPhee and David Sington. Paula Apsell, executive in charge; Mr. Chedd, executive producer. Produced for PBS by WGBH/Boston and the BBC-TV; Dr. David Suzuki, host.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
