<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="13PATT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Burberrys Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saks Fifth Avenue</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tucker, J Stanley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiro, Anne-Marie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5DC1239F930A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne-Marie Schiro</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiro, Anne-Marie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patterns column on J Stanley Tucker, widely regarded as dean of men's wear buyers, is leaving Saks Fifth Avenue after seven years to go to Burberrys Ltd as the senior vice president for men's wear worldwide (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Saks to Burberrys</p>
        <p>J. Stanley Tucker, widely regarded as the dean of men's wear buyers, is leaving Saks Fifth Avenue after seven years to go to Burberrys Ltd. as the senior vice president for men's wear worldwide. He will assume the new position on Feb. 2.</p>
        <p>Rose Marie Bravo, who left her position as the president of Saks last year to become the chief executive of Burberrys, announced his appointment yesterday, saying in a prepared statement that he will oversee the company's wholesale, retail and licensing operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From Saks to Burberrys</p>
        <p>J. Stanley Tucker, widely regarded as the dean of men's wear buyers, is leaving Saks Fifth Avenue after seven years to go to Burberrys Ltd. as the senior vice president for men's wear worldwide. He will assume the new position on Feb. 2.</p>
        <p>Rose Marie Bravo, who left her position as the president of Saks last year to become the chief executive of Burberrys, announced his appointment yesterday, saying in a prepared statement that he will oversee the company's wholesale, retail and licensing operations.</p>
        <p>At Saks, he was a vice president and the fashion director for men's and children's wear and home furnishings. He has gained prominence  in the fashion industry for his knowledge, taste and vision in recognizing design talent and promoting it.</p>
        <p>Before joining Saks, he was a vice president of the Associated Merchandising Corporation; the managing director for the United States operations of Gieves &amp; Hawkes of London, and the chief operating officer of Geoffrey Beene Inc.</p>
        <p>''At Geoffrey Beene I was in charge of worldwide sales and licensing,'' Mr. Tucker said yesterday, ''so this is a similar job. I'll have worldwide responsibility for creating a new image. The image now is classic and traditional with some English bent. That wonderful plaid is an icon,  and I think we can make it more modern.''</p>
        <p>Judith Leiber Is Retiring</p>
        <p>Judith Leiber is calling it a day. At age 77, after 34 years of designing handbags that became collector's items and even museum pieces, she is retiring at the end of this week.</p>
        <p>Her company, which she sold five years ago to Time Products Inc., an accessories conglomerate in London, will go on with a team of designers and with Victor Lipko as the chief executive. Mrs. Leiber's last collection will arrive in stores in March, but she is leaving some designs in the works for the future.</p>
        <p>''It can take two years to perfect some of the metal bags,'' Mrs. Leiber said in a telephone interview yesterday. ''I've designed 4,000 styles in my life, and that's enough. Now I'm going to concentrate on reading, gardening and cooking.''</p>
        <p>Her most popular of the 4,000 styles are the jewel-encrusted minaudieres in whimsical shapes like cats, flowers, violins and birds, which sell for as much as $7,500. She has also designed bags in snakeskin, lizard and alligator.</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton, Nancy Reagan, Barbara Bush, Beverly Sills, Joan Rivers and Bette Midler have all carried Leiber bags. Miss Sills owns more than 70, but Bernice Norman, an arts patron in New Orleans, owns nearly 300.</p>
        <p>Leiber bags are sold at stores like Bergdorf Goodman, Neiman Marcus and Saks Fifth Avenue and in Judith Leiber boutiques in Geneva; Bangkok; London; Costa Mesa, Calif., and New York, at 987 Madison Avenue (77th Street). Annual sales are about $20 million.</p>
        <p>Although Time Products plans to  expand the Leiber franchise into other products, the question remains whether a Leiber bag will maintain its cachet without the high-profile presence of the designer herself.</p>
        <p>Dana Buchman's New Line</p>
        <p>Dana Buchman is venturing into a new area with a collection called Dana Buchman Luxe, which is priced higher than either her signature bridge line of career clothes or the Dana B. &amp; Karen line of casual clothing. Ads featuring Nadja Auerman will appear in fashion magazines and on billboards and buses in March.</p>
        <p>Ms. Buchman and her co-designer for the last nine years, Karen Harman, are designing the Luxe collection, which is smaller and more concise.</p>
        <p>''Luxe doesn't try to cover everything,'' Ms. Buchman said. ''It's more about desire and less about need.'' In the signature collection, ''you have to balance everything with a more conservative piece,'' she continued, adding: ''If we show a halter top under a jacket, we also have to offer one with sleeves. We have to have a single-breasted jacket and a double-breasted jacket. In Luxe, we make an outfit what we think it should be.''</p>
        <p>The price range for Luxe is $138 to $468, about 25 percent higher than the Dana Buchman collection. Luxe will be in Neiman Marcus and Saks Fifth Avenue in March and in the Dana Buchman store at 65 East 57th Street. In late summer, a Dana B. &amp; Karen store will open next door to it, at No. 57, in the Four Seasons Hotel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
