<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Erhardt Retires As a Coach With Jets</title>
    <meta content="13JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erhardt, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DC1339F930A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Erhardt Retires As a Coach With Jets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets quarterbacks coach Ron Erhardt announces his retirement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ron Erhardt called an end to his 25-year pro coaching career yesterday by stepping down as the Jets' quarterbacks coach.</p>
        <p>Erhardt, 66, who had one year remaining on his contract, had a diminished role last season when Bill Parcells took over as head coach. In 1996 he was the offensive coordinator and called the plays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ron Erhardt called an end to his 25-year pro coaching career yesterday by stepping down as the Jets' quarterbacks coach.</p>
        <p>Erhardt, 66, who had one year remaining on his contract, had a diminished role last season when Bill Parcells took over as head coach. In 1996 he was the offensive coordinator and called the plays.</p>
        <p>There was a hint in Erhardt's farewell remarks that play-calling was his favorite part of the job. He had been a coordinator in three Super Bowls -- for the Giants in their two victories and for the Steelers in their loss to the Cowboys two years ago.</p>
        <p>''The first Super Bowl was really big,'' Erhardt recalled yesterday, reflecting on the Giants' victory following the 1986 season. ''What's pleasing about it is that you're calling the plays. It makes you feel pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Last season, though, Parcells anointed Charlie Weis as the Jets' play-caller, although Parcells asked Erhardt to sit next to Weis in the coaches' box.</p>
        <p>''I sort of figured that was going to happen,'' Erhardt said. ''Here they hire Bill and come in with a staff that just came off the Super Bowl and they have their own terminology.''</p>
        <p>Erhardt's coaching career spanned five decades, beginning with a high school in his native North Dakota. Along the way his team captured a state championship. He went on to North Dakota State and a legendary career that included a pair of college-division national titles. He joined the Patriots and during a three-year stint as head coach, he hired Parcells to be his linebackers' coach. The Patriots were winners in Erhardt's first two seasons.</p>
        <p>Parcells said yesterday he ''enjoyed every bit of'' his long relationship with Erhardt. ''At this time my feelings professionally are only incidental to my personal feelings about Ron and his career.''</p>
        <p>Parcells gave no idea about what plans, if any, he had for replacing Erhardt at quarterbacks coach.</p>
        <p>Erhardt, meanwhile, declined to comment on the Jets' quarterbacks. His relationship at Pittsburgh with Neil O'Donnell was instrumental in bringing O'Donnell to the Jets for the 1996 season. But O'Donnell's status has been clouded ever since he was benched by Parcells midway through the season in favor of Glenn Foley. O'Donnell finished the year as the starter after Foley was injured.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to comment about the quarterback situation,'' Erhardt said. He has tried to contact O'Donnell, though, and said he plans to speak to him sometime this week.</p>
        <p>O'Donnell remains the club's biggest question of the off season: will the Jets try to re-sign him, but at a significantly lower salary and bonus arrangement? The other intrigue surrounding the team -- whether the assistant head coach Bill Belichick will take a head-coaching job if it is offered -- may have less drama than it would appear. Because of Belichick's role on the Jets, and the fact he has virtually been guaranteed the right of succession to Parcells, a move elsewhere is unlikely.</p>
        <p>''I'd been thinking about retiring when the season ended and I felt I had to do it pretty quick and this was just as good a time as any,'' Erhardt said. ''It had nothing to do with football, or personality, or coaching or anything like that -- I was thinking of doing it anyway.</p>
        <p>''I'm thinking at the age level I'm at, where am I going, I'm not getting a head job. I'm maxed in the pension situation, I'm in good health, so let's do it now.''</p>
        <p>Erhardt's offenses always featured the run. His most memorable games, he said, were the Giants' playoff victories over the 49ers en route to the pair of Super Bowl titles.</p>
        <p>He and Parcells had teamed up again in 1982 as assistants with the Giants. A year later, Parcells became head coach.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on his success, Erhardt explained: ''I tried to stay abreast of the game. I really thought you had to run the football to control the game. You had to throw the football to score but had to run the football to win.''</p>
        <p>Erhardt, a throwback to the era when the run was dominant, also had a retro idea for his retirement. Instead of taking on television, this is what Erhardt is contemplating:</p>
        <p>''I've always had a fantasy or interest in being a radio color guy. I had it in the back of my mind to do some college games.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
