<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>November Consumer Prices Up 0.4%</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="493896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LABOR DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1E3CF937A25751C1A967958260" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>November Consumer Prices Up 0.4%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consumer prices climbed four-tenths of 1 percent in November, with what may prove temporary surges in food, clothing and energy not fully offset by lower inflation for housing and medical care, the Labor Department reported today.</p>
        <p>The rise, which followed a one-tenth of 1 percent advance in October, was a bit more than expected, but analysts said the latest figures did not significantly undermine the conviction that inflation was under control, and with the economy weak, it was unlikely to flare up anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consumer prices climbed four-tenths of 1 percent in November, with what may prove temporary surges in food, clothing and energy not fully offset by lower inflation for housing and medical care, the Labor Department reported today.</p>
        <p>The rise, which followed a one-tenth of 1 percent advance in October, was a bit more than expected, but analysts said the latest figures did not significantly undermine the conviction that inflation was under control, and with the economy weak, it was unlikely to flare up anytime soon.</p>
        <p>"The outlook for inflation remains excellent," said William C. Dunkelberg, dean at the Temple University business school and a consultant to the National Federation of Independent Business. He cited a new membership survey showing that more companies cut prices over the last six months than increased them -- the first time this has happened since the survey began in 1973 -- and that companies' plans to raise prices in coming months were also at a record low.</p>
        <p>Some analysts, however, struck a cautionary note, saying that while a weak economy produces little demand, it does not significantly expand supplies, a factor that could create bottlenecks and consequently price spikes.</p>
        <p>Even though the Consumer Price Index for all urban consumers rose at a 3.6 percent annual rate in the latest three months, up from a 2.7 percent rate in the three months through August, analysts say the Federal Reserve is likely to move again shortly to cut interest rates in an effort to reinvigorate the economy.</p>
        <p>Prices in the New York metropolitan area jumped six-tenths of 1 percent last month after edging down slightly in October. Of the other four major cities for which prices are published on a current basis, Los Angeles posted a four-tenths of 1 percent increase, but Chicago, Philadelphia and San Francisco showed no significant change.</p>
        <p>A separate Government report today showed that business inventories rose four-tenths of 1 percent in October, the second straight increase, on soaring retailer inventories. Sales grew by three-tenths of 1 percent, however, and the inventory-sales ratio remained at 1.50, meaning it would take a month and a half to clear shelves at the current sales pace. Consumer Sentiment Index</p>
        <p>In the first bit of data for December, the University of Michigan told subscribers that its preliminary reading of consumer sentiment rose slightly, to 70.4, from the 69.1 to which the index plunged in November.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that little could be learned from the inventory figures, but that the consumer confidence figures at least seemed to contribute to a rise in the stock market; the Dow Jones industrial average gained 19.23 points today.</p>
        <p>Food was one of the biggest factors driving up consumer prices, rising six-tenths of 1 percent after two months of negligible up and down. The price of fruits and vegetables spurted 4.4 percent, with lettuce and tomatoes soaring 44.5 and 12.7 percent, respectively, reflecting whitefly infestations in California. Beef and veal prices rose nine-tenths of 1 percent after five straight declines, but pork, poultry and eggs declined and oranges dropped 17.1 percent after a 14.4 percent drop in October.</p>
        <p>Energy prices advanced eight-tenths of 1 percent, with gasoline, fuel oil and natural gas rising sharply, while electricity fell seven-tenths of 1 percent. Core Rate Up 0.3%</p>
        <p>The so-called core rate of inflation, which excludes the often gyrating food and energy components, rose three-tenths of 1 percent in November, about the same pace as the average increase for the two preceding months.</p>
        <p>In transportation, the price of new vehicles rose two-tenths of 1 percent -- the proportion of 1992 car models in the index is now just over 50 percent -- and airline fares rose 2.2 percent. But automobile finance charges fell 1.4 percent, their third straight decline.</p>
        <p>Clothes prices advanced 1 percent, with women's and girls' clothes up nearly twice that much, the report showed. Seasonal adjustment factors contribute to big swings in apparel, which accounts for only 6 percent of the Consumer Price Index.</p>
        <p>Inflation in medical care, which was five-tenths of 1 percent in November, has now eased one-tenth of a point in each of the last three months. Since November 1990 medical costs have risen 8 percent, with prescription drugs up 10.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Among other goods and services, a 1.9 percent leap in tobacco prices accounted for nearly two-thirds of the month's increase of seven-tenths of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>Viewing the Consumer Price Index market basket another way, goods rose six-tenths of 1 percent last month, twice as much as in October, while inflation in services remained at three-tenths of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>A separate index covering urban wage earners and clerical workers, the C.P.I.-W, rose five-tenths of 1 percent last month after a one-tenth of 1 percent increase in October.</p>
        <p>Despite the sanguine view taken in today's report, some analysts see little if any further improvement in inflation, which has run at a 3 percent rate over the last 12 months.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
