<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Independent Panel Calls for Clean Slate at U.S.O.C.</title>
    <meta content="20OLYMPIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/20/sports/othersports/20olympics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1498419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Olympic Committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5DC1F38F933A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Independent Panel Calls for Clean Slate at U.S.O.C.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Independent Panel Calls for Clean Slate at U.S.O.C.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outside commission investigating beleaguered United States Olympic Committee suggests that board of directors be pared down from 124 members to nine in interest of much-needed reform (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An outside commission examining the dysfunction and ethical lapses at the United States Olympic Committee recommended today that the organization's fractious and politically conflicted 124-person board of directors be replaced by a largely independent nine-member panel.</p>
        <p>The commission, which grew out of Congressional hearings this winter that exposed the Olympic committee's myriad inefficiencies and internal strife, said in a 67-page report that the organization ''has breached the trust of the American people and betrayed the Olympic ideals it has pledged to preserve.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commission examining the ethical lapses at the United States Olympic Committee recommended that the organization's board of directors be replaced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An outside commission examining the dysfunction and ethical lapses at the United States Olympic Committee recommended today that the organization's fractious and politically conflicted 124-person board of directors be replaced by a largely independent nine-member panel.</p>
        <p>The commission, which grew out of Congressional hearings this winter that exposed the Olympic committee's myriad inefficiencies and internal strife, said in a 67-page report that the organization ''has breached the trust of the American people and betrayed the Olympic ideals it has pledged to preserve.''</p>
        <p>Roberta Cooper Ramo, co-chairwoman of the commission, said at a news conference that ''the entire governance structure of the United States Olympic Committee has to be reformed; it's in disarray.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, she added, ''We need a clean slate and fresh blood.''</p>
        <p>The work of the commission, and an internal U.S.O.C. task force that made recommendations in April, demonstrate a fervor to remove nearly anyone associated with the way that the organization has been managed in recent years.</p>
        <p>Dick Ebersol, a member of the commission and the chairman of NBC Sports, said that the existing structure of the Olympic committee, with its political infighting and blurry lines of authority, led to the choosing of various ''boobs and incompetents'' to run the organization.</p>
        <p>The U.S.O.C.'s interim management -- the president, William C. Martin, and Jim Scherr, who is running the day-to-day operations -- has quelled the turmoil that earlier this year was characterized by leaked e-mail messages, public sniping and contentious Congressional hearings.</p>
        <p>The commission's report is the latest attempt to reform the Olympic committee, which has been beset by turf wars between paid staff and volunteers, has had four presidents and chief executives in four years, and has watched its chief executive, Lloyd Ward, resign in April over ethical violations.</p>
        <p>''There's been a massive loss of confidence in the American Olympic movement by its athletes, which is a bloody shame,'' Ebersol said.</p>
        <p>Two months ago, the U.S.O.C.'s task force made public preliminary reforms that were quite similar to the commission's, including the wording of a new mission statement for the organization. Over many years, other reports have been issued but their reforms rarely enacted.</p>
        <p>''What's real gratifying is that we went down separate paths and came up with similar conclusions,'' Frank Marshall, the co-chairman of the task force, said in a telephone interview. ''Now we can get the reform done quickly.''</p>
        <p>Marshall said he was pleased that the commission did not bow to various constituencies in the Olympic movement who want to increase the number of board members to avert losing their power to a shrunken board.</p>
        <p>Ramo said she expected that there would be opposition ''around the margins'' from people ''who are threatened by such changes.''</p>
        <p>The Olympic committee is to use the final findings of the task force, which are to be released Friday, as the basis for radically changing its constitution.</p>
        <p>The commission's intention is to create a template for Congress to amend the 1978 Amateur Sports Act by including its recommendations.</p>
        <p>Senator Ben Nighthorse Campbell, Republican of Colorado, an unyielding critic of the Olympic committee, praised the commission's report.</p>
        <p>''They've done yeoman's work and took a giant step forward,'' he said after the commission's news conference.</p>
        <p>Campbell would not commit to seeking amendment of the Amateur Sports Act by Jan. 1, the date by which Ramo said she hoped that a new board would be in place. But he said it was important for Congress to ''put the changes in concrete.''</p>
        <p>Campbell added: ''If one task force said to make these changes, then another can say, 'Change it back.' If we do it, it's much harder to change it back.''</p>
        <p>The commission recommended that a new nine-member U.S.O.C. board comprise five public figures free of connection to -- or taint from -- the domestic or international Olympic movements, and two each chosen by the committee's Athlete Advisory and National Governing Bodies Councils.</p>
        <p>''There will be independent people the nominating committee will approach,'' Ramo, a former president of the American Bar Association, said. ''They will not be campaigning for the job.''</p>
        <p>There would be four officer-members whose voting would be limited to certain issues and whose four ballots would add up to one vote. They would be the three International Olympic Committee members now on the U.S.O.C. board, and the speaker of a proposed 116-member Assembly, an advisory group that would be composed nearly entirely of the disenfranchised members of the current board. (A similar group was recommended by the task force.)</p>
        <p>The task force, which in April proposed a nine-member board, including four independents and one I.O.C. member, will in its final report include all three I.O.C. representatives but give them a combined one vote.</p>
        <p>The U.S.O.C.'s plan to put only one member of the international committee on its board met with resistance when the I.O.C. said that the charter requires that all three of its members from the United States, Anita DeFrantz, James Easton and Bob Ctvrtlik, be included.</p>
        <p>An I.O.C. spokeswoman said today that although it supports the ''general thrust'' of the commission's planned reform, it is concerned that it does not fully comply with its charter. ''It needs further discussion,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Donald M. Fehr, co-chairman of the commission, said that his group had made clear various portions of its report to the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>''We believe it complies with the charter,'' said Fehr, the executive director of the Major League Baseball Players Association.</p>
        <p>The commission made other recommendations.</p>
        <p>Set strict limits on expenses and travel for a chief executive and a board chairman.</p>
        <p>Establish whistleblower procedures that would give employees the freedom to report accounting and ethical improprieties without the fear of retaliation by supervisors.</p>
        <p>Provide audited financial statements to the public.</p>
        <p>Eliminate nearly two dozen committees, leaving the organization with four -- the audit, compensation, ethics and nomination and governance committees -- which mirrors the plan set forth by the task force.</p>
        <p>Report annually to Congress, a change from the U.S.O.C.'s current four-year requirement.</p>
        <p>Require annual certification by the chief executive, elected board members, officer board members and paid management that they do not belong to organizations that discriminate on the basis of religion, race, ethnicity or gender.</p>
        <p>When Ward became the U.S.O.C.'s chief executive in November 2001, he did not disclose his membership at Augusta National Golf Club, which does not admit women as members.</p>
        <p>The contents of the commission's report will be the subject of a hearing Tuesday by the Senate Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
