<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moscow Circus Struggles in Orlando</title>
    <meta content="Y27CIR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Orlando (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Moscow Circus</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Navarro, Mireya</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Orlando</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Circuses</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DE143AF934A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="1430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moscow Circus Struggles in Orlando</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIREYA NAVARRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Navarro, Mireya</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moscow Circus struggles to survive in Orlando, Fla, where it hoped to establish a permanent home, and its plight raises questions about whether a one-ring show with clowns, jugglers and dancing bears stands a chance in Orlando area, home of glitzy, multimillion-dollar, state-of-the-art amusements; original troop of 85 performers has been reduced by defections to 50; they blame inadequate promotion for their false start and are looking for new investors; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As part of the Moscow Circus, Svetlana Nugzarov and her family performed daring acrobatics on galloping stallions to packed houses all over the world, including in this city. But upon their return to Orlando this year, the Nugzarovs received standing ovations from as few as 50 people.</p>
        <p>Poor ticket sales were just the beginning of a dispiriting American run for a renowned Russian circus that moved here envisioning a permanent one. Instead, the performers went out of business within weeks, got evicted from their condos for failing to pay rent and have been forced to stand guard by their 120-foot tent to keep creditors from hauling it away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As part of the Moscow Circus, Svetlana Nugzarov and her family performed daring acrobatics on galloping stallions to packed houses all over the world, including in this city. But upon their return to Orlando this year, the Nugzarovs received standing ovations from as few as 50 people.</p>
        <p>Poor ticket sales were just the beginning of a dispiriting American run for a renowned Russian circus that moved here envisioning a permanent one. Instead, the performers went out of business within weeks, got evicted from their condos for failing to pay rent and have been forced to stand guard by their 120-foot tent to keep creditors from hauling it away.</p>
        <p>The performers hope to carry on. But their plight raises the question of whether a one-ring show with clowns, jugglers and dancing bears stands a chance in Orlando's glitzy fantasy world of multimillion-dollar resorts, state-of-the-art computer simulation, water parks disguised as ski resorts and not one, but two, simulated Manhattan streetscapes. Can artistry and tradition compete in the high-tech marketplace of ''Terminator 2'' and ''Back to the Future,'' or even Shamu the killer whale and Mickey the make-believe mouse?</p>
        <p>''It's hard to believe a program like this couldn't succeed,'' Mrs. Nugzarov, who has been with the Moscow Circus for 45 years, said through an interpreter. ''We'd never failed before.''</p>
        <p>The original troupe of 85 performers, 11 horses, 20 dogs, 2 leopards and 6 brown bears is dwindling as some of the acts, such as the 14-member Doveiko aerialists, have accepted job offers in Las Vegas and elsewhere. But most of the circus is hanging on while looking for new investors to raise their tent again, blaming their false start on inadequate promotion.</p>
        <p>Orlando city officials say that with 35 million tourists a year who on average visit for five days or longer, the Moscow Circus could find a niche even among audiences weaned on special effects, and in an entertainment capital with leviathans like Disney World and Universal Studios.</p>
        <p>''There are plenty of smaller entertainment operators that do very well and marketing is key for them,'' Mayor Glenda Hood said. ''They could do well because it's an outstanding circus.''</p>
        <p>That possibility is what keeps the 50 hold-out performers from running away to join other circuses. It took about $400,000 just to bring them and their equipment to the United States, Moscow Circus members say. Most left circus jobs in Russia to come together for the new Orlando venture and work for twice or more their salary.</p>
        <p>All that and pride, they say, has made them wait.</p>
        <p>''This is about a great circus, that's what we're trying to preserve,'' said Sergei Tolstikhin, the circus ringmaster and a linguist who now mostly performs as interpreter for the non-English-speaking company. ''The idea of having a circus here is very appealing because we know something beautiful could happen.''</p>
        <p>The Russians, who came here last February, wanted to establish the first United States franchise of the Moscow Circus, a prestigious circus known for stars like the Flying Cranes and for worldwide touring, including shows at venues such as Radio City Music Hall and Madison Square Garden in New York City. The 11 acts for the Orlando production were gathered from circuses in the former Soviet Union, where the circus is a centuries-old art form and a state-run institution. Unlike in the United States, where most circuses are touring enterprises, Russian circuses usually operate out of permanent buildings in major cities.</p>
        <p>Difficult economic times at home since the collapse of the Soviet Union, however, have made scores of circus performers from the former Soviet Republics head West, and today many of them are found in American shows, like Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey, and stage productions, like those in Las Vegas casino hotels. But after falling on hard times at home, the Moscow Circus fell on harder times in Orlando.</p>
        <p>An original opening date of October 1996 was delayed to the following March, meaning the circus missed the winter tourist season, Mr. Tolstikhin said. Finally able to open last March, the circus was forced to close after seven weeks last May because of poor attendance -- once they had to cancel a performance when only 10 people showed up in a tent with a seating capacity of 1,600. Since then things have been so dire that a Christian charity, thinking the performers were starving, sent them food when they got in trouble with neighbors for fishing carp out of a landscaping pond.</p>
        <p>Two major investors, DAJ Guani Investors and Burkett Contracting Corp., both of Central Florida, are now suing the New York promoter who brought the circus here, Alex Valdez and his First Capital Investment Group, for breach of contract. The investors, who said their contract called for at least six months of performances, with two daily shows, want to recoup an investment of $307,800.</p>
        <p>The investors also name in their suit Rasul Abdullaev, the Moscow Circus producer who assembled the troupe, over ownership of assets such as bleachers, lights and the circus tent. Twice, a crane has been sent to take the red and blue striped tent now plopped down on the asphalt behind the bear mouth facade of the Moscow Circus site here, but both times the performers have managed to hold on to it, their lawyer said.</p>
        <p>''They put their bodies under the wheels of the crane to stop it,'' said Scott E. Siverson, a lawyer for Orlando tour operator Jorge C. Aznar, an investor who is paying the performers' housing in a hotel while trying to get it going again.</p>
        <p>Calls to Burkett Contracting Corporation were not returned and Mr. Valdez could not be reached for comment. But Ralph Hadley, a lawyer for DAJ Guani Investors, said he empathized with the circus performers, calling them ''victims just like my clients are.''</p>
        <p>The Moscow Circus performers say they are owed more than $250,000 in wages after being abandoned by their American sponsors. Their travails have been compounded by negative publicity after Florida regulators last June said they would seize the circus bears if the animals were not moved out of their small traveling cages, and the landlord who evicted them last July sued, claiming to be owed more than $37,000 in back rent. Neighbors also accused some of the Russians of unruly behavior, including fishing in the pond.</p>
        <p>But the performers have been able to stay here partly because of the support of many fans here and all over the United States, Mr. Siverson said, including people who have donated transportation, housing for the animals and money. What they need the most, however, is an investment of about $500,000 to start over, Mr. Tolstikhin said.</p>
        <p>While they wait, performers like Vladimir Dovgan and Anatoliy Yeni, ''the extraordinary balancing duo,'' Margulim, the clown, and the Nugzarovs, including Mrs. Nugzarov, her husband, Tamerlan, and two sons, spend days trying to keep fit, exercising the animals and working the telephones from a room in Mr. Siverson's office to raise money.</p>
        <p>The circus performers will probably make a decision about their fate by next month.</p>
        <p>''If nothing happens within a month maybe the time has come to express my appreciation to the actors and pack up and go to other places,'' said Mr. Abdullaev, a former builder of circus tents who moved here with his wife and two children.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Nugzarov said her family and the 11 other performers in the horsemanship act will probably seek the help of the Russian state circus company to return home, where they last worked with the Old Moscow Circus. She said that they have received offers from American circuses but that the constant traveling required would not allow them enough time to rehearse and maintain their artistic quality.</p>
        <p>She predicted a sad homecoming.</p>
        <p>''Every time we came back to Moscow we were happy and proud,'' said Mrs. Nugzarov, who has performed for audiences of 60,000 people. ''Now it's going to be difficult. But we can't blame ourselves for what's happened here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
