<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL REPORT</title>
    <meta content="27STRO0AB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickson, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6D8173AF934A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL REPORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRANT GLICKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glickson, Grant</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of New York City metropolitan area high school football news (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey</p>
        <p>He was a 14-year-old freshman when he was handed the starting quarterback job over a senior. His passes were too hot for his Ramapo High teammates to handle. His father was a famous quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey</p>
        <p>He was a 14-year-old freshman when he was handed the starting quarterback job over a senior. His passes were too hot for his Ramapo High teammates to handle. His father was a famous quarterback.</p>
        <p>Chris Simms was not the most popular guy on campus.</p>
        <p>''I felt a little uncomfortable because I didn't know my place,'' Simms  recalled.</p>
        <p>But after throwing for 1,600 yards in his freshman season and amassing 1,855 yards en route to Ramapo's Group 3 final appearance against Hoboken last season in his sophomore year, the Raiders are now as much Chris Simms's team as the National Football League Giants were his father's.</p>
        <p>''The more I became acquainted with them and the better I played, the more they rallied around me,'' said the 6-foot-4-inch, 210-pound left-handed quarterback. ''Now I have so many friends on the team.''</p>
        <p>With Simms handing off to Greg Toal Jr. (1,387 yards and 29 touchdowns) and throwing strikes to Mike Miano, Rob Barrabee and his favorite target, Rob Milanese (38 receptions for 708 yards), Ramapo boasts one of the most well-balanced offensive attacks in the state.</p>
        <p>Hoboken, the No.1-ranked team last year, defeated Ramapo, 20-13, in the state final. The Red Wings, winners of three successive Group 3 titles, extended their winning streak to 30 games with a 35-12 victory last night over Shabazz of Newark. Keon Walker and Dion Casey, who combined for more than 2,000 rushing yards last year, lead Hoboken.</p>
        <p>Hackensack, owner of five consecutive Group 4 championships and winner of 16 straight games, will try to make it six titles without Greg Toal Sr., the team's coach of eight years. Toal (51-3-1) stepped down so he could coach his second-youngest son, Greg, at Ramapo as an assistant, and watch his oldest son, Mike, at William &amp; Mary. He was replaced by Ralph Dass. The Comets' Sean O'Connor is the state's top-rated quarterback. O'Connor (1,200 yards and 12 touchdowns last season) has two speedy running backs (Dawud Hanif and Sterling Wynn) at his disposal.</p>
        <p>Union, a perennial power out of the Watchung Conference, will be guided by its third coach in three years, Gary Zakovic, a 13-year assistant to the former coach Lou Rettino and head coach of Dover's 11-0 Group 2 championship team last year. Zakovic will try to carry on Rettino's winning tradition by ''playing the game the way he taught it.'' Zakovic will count on quarterback Damien Lowe, fullback Nygiem Calhoun and halfback Brian Yawnick to return the Farmers to glory.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth, Union's nemesis, is again dotted with Division I college prospects. Craig Sporer, a 6-4, 275-pound tackle, Maurice McClain, a 6-1, 170-pound wide receiver and defensive back, and Asad Abdul-Khaliq, a 2,000-yard passer in his junior year, are the Minutemen's headline players.</p>
        <p>Although Elizabeth routed Eastside of Paterson, 44-0, last week, Eastside is loaded with big-time players. Shawn Seabrooks, a 5-9, 190-pound tailback, is a complete runner, and David Thompson, a 6-4, 245-pound defensive end, has already received offers from Michigan, Michigan State and Tennessee. Tororris Hill, a receiver and defensive back, has been recruited by West Point and some of the Ivy League schools.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
        <p>Derric Rossy, a preseason all-America linebacker from Medford, said that when his Patchogue Raiders (9-1-1) won the Class 1 Long Island championship last year, ''it was like, 'Pinch me, I can't believe this is real.' ''</p>
        <p>Rossy, who set a school record with 154 tackles last year, said that the euphoria of repeating would be even more mind-boggling. ''I think we have a real good shot at it,'' he said. ''The only thing we lost is our quarterback and three good linemen.''</p>
        <p>Patchogue will place its hopes in the hands of Mike Cirigliano, a speedy sophomore quarterback who can get the ball downfield. Mike Funaro (1,300 yards) and Greg Murphy (700) combined for 2,000 yards rushing last year.</p>
        <p>The Raiders will be challenged in Suffolk County's Division 1 by Sachem, whose most prominent player is tackle Jesse Brush, and Longwood, whose best player, tailback Marc Riley, was the first junior to be honored with the Hansen award, which is given to Suffolk County's best player.</p>
        <p>Bellport, which is the only Suffolk County team to twice capture the Long Island championship, is the favorite in Division 2. The Clippers are led by William Griffin, a preseason all-America running back and kick returner. Alex Lazo, a 6-1, 205-pound linebacker, has verbally committed to Buffalo. Mike Jorgensen, a 6-4, 268-pound tackle, is being pursued by Iowa.</p>
        <p>Some years ago, N.F.L. quarterback Boomer Esiason led East Islip to a Suffolk County championship. Now his nephew, Randy Williams, will get that chance as the Redmen will try to avenge last year's 43-0 loss to Bellport in the county final.</p>
        <p>North Babylon, which was upset last year by Comsewogue, 13-12, in the Suffolk County Division 3 final, is expected to resurface as the class of its division. Sayville's Jonathan Hart and Comsewogue's Kevin Cassesse are the quarterbacks who could engineer North Babylon's downfall.</p>
        <p>Terry Smith, a tailback who rushed for 1,843 yards last year, should lead Southampton to a Division 4 title now that Harborfields has moved up to Division 3. Jerry Williams, a 6-5, 290-pound all-county lineman, could keep Babylon in the hunt.</p>
        <p>Uniondale, which claimed its first Nassau County Conference I title in the school's 42-year history last season, could repeat on the strength of two running backs, Brian Manigault (1,200 yards) and Ale Whyte, a transfer from Carle Place.</p>
        <p>Lawrence, Division, Hewlett and Garden City, which went to the final eight straight seasons until last year, should fight it out for the Conference II title.</p>
        <p>Conference III belongs to Bethpage, which has won 41 straight conference games. Howie Vogts, Bethpage's coach of 45 years, has the second highest victory total (257) in the history of New York State.</p>
        <p>Top-seeded Manhasset, led by its quarterback, Kevin Cherry, the son of Coach Bill Cherry, and its all-county lineman, Harry Hristoforatos, will battle Roosevelt for the Conference IV title.</p>
        <p>GRANT GLICKSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
