<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.C. May Move Party From Bourbon Street</title>
    <meta content="29COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/29/sports/ncaafootball/29COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1546764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sugar Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rose Bowl (Football Game)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Louisiana State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Oklahoma</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Southern California</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Southern California</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Michigan</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Louisiana State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD7123EF93AA15751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.C. May Move Party From Bourbon Street</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S.C. May Move Party From Bourbon Street</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Drape</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Drape Inside College Football column discusses Louisiana State University's preparations to face Oklahoma University in Sugar Bowl; Southern California University is getting ready for Rose Bowl contest against Michigan University; two games will most likely decide national championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French Quarter seemed more hung over than usual yesterday afternoon. A dozen blocks away at the Superdome, the New Orleans Saints were finishing off another season without a playoff game. Intermittent rain and humidity kept the sidewalks steamy and empty.</p>
        <p>Two buses filled with the Louisiana State football team and flanked by a police escort briefly revived the heartbeat of one the nation's most vibrant party quadrants. But for now, at least, the Big Easy is an uneasy host for what is billed as the Bowl Championship Series's national title game next Sunday in the Sugar Bowl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Trojans defeat the Wolverines in the Rose Bowl on Thursday, they could give college football its first split championship since 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The French Quarter seemed more hung over than usual yesterday afternoon. A dozen blocks away at the Superdome, the New Orleans Saints were finishing off another season without a playoff game. Intermittent rain and humidity kept the sidewalks steamy and empty.</p>
        <p>Two buses filled with the Louisiana State football team and flanked by a police escort briefly revived the heartbeat of one the nation's most vibrant party quadrants. But for now, at least, the Big Easy is an uneasy host for what is billed as the Bowl Championship Series's national title game next Sunday in the Sugar Bowl.</p>
        <p>The real steam, however, is bubbling out west in Pasadena, Calif., where on Thursday, Southern California (11-1) will take on Michigan (10-2) in the Rose Bowl. The Trojans, you see, are the people's choice for champion-in-waiting on the strength of the No. 1 ranking in the Associated Press news media poll and in the USA Today/ESPN coaches poll.</p>
        <p>If the Trojans defeat the Wolverines, they will retain the top spot in the A.P. poll and could give college football its first split championship since 1997.</p>
        <p>No one here is mad at the Tigers (12-1) -- a brass band and enough purple-and-gold partisans were on hand at their hotel to give the ''L-S-U'' chant some hefty bass.</p>
        <p>It is L.S.U.'s opponent, 12-1 Oklahoma, that has sobered up the French Quarter and college football aficionados across the nation. On Dec. 6, Kansas State humiliated the Sooners, 35-7, in the Big 12 Conference championship game.</p>
        <p>When Oklahoma Coach Bob Stoops and his team arrived here Saturday, this pointed question asked by a reporter sounded louder than any brass band: ''Why do you deserve to be here?''</p>
        <p>Stoops, whose volubility usually matches his confident manner, did not have a prepared five-paragraph answer at the ready.</p>
        <p>He did earlier in the season when he proclaimed that this was the best bunch of Sooners he had coached in his five seasons at Oklahoma. He did late in the season, before the Kansas State debacle, when he declared that his quarterback, Jason White, was the only logical choice to win the Heisman Trophy.</p>
        <p>No, yesterday, Stoops relied on two sentences. ''Because we're No. 1 in the B.C.S.,'' he said. ''It's pretty simple.''</p>
        <p>Yes and no, Coach. The B.C.S. computers weighed the Sooners' strength of schedule and spit out Oklahoma as the best team in the nation. The voters in each poll decided the Sooners were no better than No. 3.</p>
        <p>Whether this is a fair and efficient way to make a championship game is being debated by presidents from the have and the have-not sides of the aisle. The one thing they all seem to agree on is that some kind of changes will be made when the B.C.S. contract expires after the 2005 season.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, this season's glamour matchup is not officially called the title game and will occur three days earlier in the Rose Bowl.</p>
        <p>Michigan cornerbacks Jeremy LeSueur and Markus Curry squaring off with the Trojans' talented and highlight-ready receivers, Mike Williams and Keary Colbert, is more compelling than Oklahoma, which has the highest-scoring major college offense, playing chess with the nation's stingiest defense, L.S.U.'s.</p>
        <p>Make no mistake, the Sugar Bowl is a fine game. White did capture the Heisman Trophy by leading the Sooners to an average of 45.2 points. The Tigers, behind an efficient if not spectacular quarterback, Matt Mauck, averaged 34.9 points while giving up just 10.8.</p>
        <p>When L.S.U. Coach Nick Saban climbed off the bus yesterday, he was faced with the usual questions about how he intended to keep his team out of the French Quarter in the wee hours of the morning.</p>
        <p>''We've been to some bowl games before, and I think most of the players on our team understand what it takes to focus on a bowl game, that there are a lot of distractions,'' Saban said. ''If you're truly a champion, you can deal with clutter.''</p>
        <p>But this B.C.S. national title game boasts distractions that stretch beyond banquets, field trips and Bourbon Street. Saban is fending off questions about the possibility of beginning next season as a coach in the National Football League, perhaps with the Giants.</p>
        <p>Stoops, too, has become a perennial candidate for vacant pro jobs, which may become more abundant in the next several days as N.F.L. teams clean house of losing coaches. And, at least until the final minutes of the Rose Bowl are ticked off, the Trojans will remain No. 1 in the polls, which is perhaps the most consuming clutter for both teams.</p>
        <p>The coaches have promised their national title to the winner of the Sugar Bowl. But if Southern Cal defeats Michigan, can either L.S.U. or Oklahoma be considered a true champion?</p>
        <p>How hung over the French Quarter is next Monday will tell the tale. Either the Sooners or the Tigers faithful will be happily sleeping off a night of celebrating, or a split championship will leave all of college football with a splitting headache.</p>
        <p>INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
