<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Remix; Origin of the Species</title>
    <meta content="02remix.firsts.hed-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Men's Fashion Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="76" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Underwood, Paul L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5D91731F932A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Remix; Origin of the Species</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul L. Underwood</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Underwood, Paul L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on origins of several men's fashion staples; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Credit -- or blame -- for today's conspicuously visible logos belongs to the French tennis star René Lacoste, who in 1933 added the company's crocodile to its polo shirts and inadvertently invented branded clothing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Credit -- or blame -- for today's conspicuously visible logos belongs to the French tennis star René Lacoste, who in 1933 added the company's crocodile to its polo shirts and inadvertently invented branded clothing.</p>
        <p>Pringle of Scotland's archives were ruined in a fire, which only adds to the legend of how the knit specialist created the first argyle: by request. In the 1920s, the Duke of Windsor asked Pringle for a special sweater to go with his argyle socks; inspiration ensued, and traditional plaid had a rival.</p>
        <p>Until Charles Macintosh combined dissolved rubber with two pieces of wool in 1823, waterproofing did not exist. The result: the natty raincoat that bears his name. If only they could do the same for suede.</p>
        <p>Long before anti-glare aviator glasses were sported by every top-gun wannabe in Hollywood, they were worn by actual pilots. Designed by Ray-Ban for the Air Force in 1936, these metal-framed specs were eventually hijacked by the fashion and music sets.</p>
        <p>With suspenders figuring large in the spring wardrobe, it's interesting to note who received the first American patent for them: Samuel Clemens, better known as Mark Twain, in 1871.</p>
        <p>Before 1896, men's shirt collars flew about willy-nilly. Then Brooks Brothers introduced the button-down shirt, without which no one would know how to describe Bob Newhart's brand of comedy.</p>
        <p>To keep French feet warm, Jean-Baptiste Doré brought together his neighbors in the village of Grès in 1820 to create the region's first sock manufacturer, which is now Doré Doré.</p>
        <p>Since Levi Strauss first came up with the denim work pant, it's taken the bluejean less than 133 years to make the journey from outhouse to penthouse.</p>
        <p>The first driving shoe may have been created by Carshoe in the 1960s. This claim has fueled a controversy: Tod's maintains that it was first; Prada, which owns Carshoe, insists otherwise.</p>
        <p>Skinny suits aren't for everybody, and double-breasted suits can look baggy (or bossy) on the wrong guy. So the Belgian designer Raf Simons introduced the one-and-a-half-breasted suit in his spring collection for Jil Sander, bringing the Aristotelian mean to men's wear.</p>
        <p>PAUL L. UNDERWOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
