<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="11welistings0WC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DD1231F932A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Tarrytown Chelsea Handler, stand-up comedian. March 17 at 8 p.m. $32.50. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''Who the #$&amp;% is Jackson Pollock?'' Documentary. Wednesday through March 17. $6 to $8. The Emelin Theatre, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-3045</p>
        <p>Katonah Annual Katonah Film Project Series: ''Network,'' directed by Sidney Lumet. March 17 at 7:30 p.m. $5. Katonah Village Library, 26 Bedford Road. (914) 232-3508.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Music Makers of New Rochelle in the 20th Century,'' an exhibition and film festival: ''Aladdin,'' directed by Ron Clements and John Musker. March 11 at 1:30 p.m. Free. ''Beauty and the Beast,'' directed by Gary Trousdale and Kirk Wise. March 18 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Ossie Davis Theater, 1 Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''The Quiet Man,'' directed by John Ford. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $6 and $8. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Pelham ''It Happened One Night,'' romantic comedy directed by Frank Capra. Friday at 7 p.m. Free. Huguenot Memorial Church, 901 Pelhamdale Ave. (914) 738-3488.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Malena,'' directed by Giuseppe Tornatore. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Elmsford ''Nursery Rhyme Time,'' songs, rhymes and movement. Thursday through March 29 at 10 a.m. Free. Greenburgh Public Library, 300 Tarrytown Road. (914) 993-1600.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''Milk n' Cookies Playhouse,'' musicians, jugglers, and puppet show hosted by Bossy Frog. March 17 at 10 a.m. $7 and $9. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''Songs and Stories of the Animal World,'' presented by Danny Einbender. Ages 4 to 9. Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. Purchase Free Library, 3093 Purchase Street. (914) 948-0550.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Fun Facts About Dinosaurs,'' hands-on fossil presentation. March 17, 2 to 3:30 p.m. $15. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Fun Family Sundays,'' parents and children art work shop. March 11, 3 to 4:30 p.m. Registration required. Belle School , 1088 Central Park Avenue. (914) 723-9229.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. Ages 2 to 5. Through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 Extension 360.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''St. Patrick's Day Celebration,'' stories and crafts. Ages 4 to 6. Wednesday at 4 p.m. Free. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 Extension 360.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Mother Goose Time,'' nursery rhymes, stories, songs and finger plays. Ages 2 to 4. March 11 through May 17. Registration required. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Annandale-on-Hudson Melvin Chen, pianist. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Olin Hall, (518) 537-6665.</p>
        <p>Beacon Thomas Earl, vintage folk rock. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Chthonic Clash Coffeehouse, 453 Main Street. (845) 831-0359.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Blue Fringe, Jewish rock band. March 18 at 1 p.m. $18 and $25. Greenburgh Hebrew Center, 515 Broadway. (914) 693-5121.</p>
        <p>Katonah ''Parker String Quartet,'' performs Mozart's String Quartet in G major among others. March 18 at 4 p.m. $25. Caramoor Center for Music and the Arts, 149 Girdle Ridge Road. (914) 232-1252.</p>
        <p>Middletown Marshall Crenshaw, rock, singer, songwriter and musician. March 11 at 3 p.m. $22 and $25. The Mansion, 14 Wilcox Avenue. (845) 343-3049.</p>
        <p>New City Sing We Enchanted, a cappella chorus directed by Nell Macdonald. March 11 at 7 p.m. Suggested donation $10. Saint Augustine Church, 140 Maple Avenue. (845) 634-2407.</p>
        <p>Ossining T. Broussard and the Zydeco steppers. March 18, 5 to 9:30 p.m. $18. Zydeco Hall, 7 Old Albany Post Road. (914) 528-7612.</p>
        <p>Peekskill Steve Chizmadia, singer and songwriter. Friday at 8 p.m. Free; donation encouraged. Peekskill Coffee House, 101 South Division Street. (914) 739-1287.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie Rebecca Frezza, children's music singer. March 18 at 3 p.m. $8 and $10. Jewish Community Center of Dutchess County, 110 Grand Avenue. (845) 471-0430.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Music Tech Fair,'' hands-on multimedia presentation. March 11, 12:30 to 4:30 p.m. Free. Michael Finckel, cellist; performs works by Debussy, Kodaly and Schumann. Friday at 8 p.m. $11 to $13. Hoff-Barthelson Music School, 25 School Lane. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''An Evening of Vocalists,'' presented by the Lagond Music School. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Coffee Labs, 7 Main Street. (914) 332-1479.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown Solas, Celtic band. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>White Plains Brian Conway, Irish fiddler. March 11 at 4 p.m. $10 and $20. Divine Compassion Center, 52 North Broadway. (914) 948-4086.</p>
        <p>White Plains Spring Choral and Orchestra Concert, directed by Timothy Lewis; works by Bach, Handel and Haydn. March 11 at 4 p.m. $18 and $20. Grace Church, Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 949-0384.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Kids on Central,'' children's music series presented by the Westchester Philharmonic and the Music Conservatory of Westchester: ''The String Thing.'' March 17 at 2 p.m. $10. Music Conservatory of Westchester, 216 Central Avenue. (914) 761-3900.</p>
        <p>Yonkers  Yonkers Philharmonic Orchestra, concert directed by Maestro James; works by Beethoven and Bizet. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Robert Dodson School , 105 Avondale Road. (914) 476-3711.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Highlights Tour,'' introductory tour of the center's lawns, gardens, trails and other outdoor facilities. March 11 at 11:30 a.m. $3 to $5. ''Old Fashioned Maple Sugaring Party,'' tree tapping, sap collecting, and syrup and sugar making. March 18, 1 to 4 p.m. $5 and $7. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Armonk Peter R. Limburg, author of ''Deceived: The Story of the Donner Party;'' discussion. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. North Castle Public Library, 19 Whippoorwill Road. (914) 273-3887.</p>
        <p>Hastings-on-Hudson ''Rwanda, a Journey From Hope to Healing,'' discussion by Melody Cooper, playwright. March 18 at 1 p.m. Free. First Unitarian Society of Westchester, 25 Jackson Avenue. (914) 478-2710.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle Dr. Diane Sharon hold discussion on blurred boundaries and sacred spaces. Thursday at 8 p.m. $10. Beth El Synagogue-Center, 1324 North Ave # 1. (914) 235-2700.</p>
        <p>Purchase Edwin G. Burrows, author of ''How New York Became the Big Apple''; discussion and lecture. Thursday at 4:30 p.m. Free. Dance Lab Theater, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6830.</p>
        <p>Purchase Mary-Lou Weisman, author; reading and discussion. March 18 at 3 p.m. Free. Reid Hall, 2900 Purchase Street. (140) 323-5300.</p>
        <p>Rye Bill Mayher, author of ''Joel White: Boatbuilder, Designer, Sailor''; slide show and discussion. March 11 at 4 p.m. Free. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Sleepy Hollow Danielle Trussoni author of '' Falling through the Earth'' and Abigail Thomas author of '' A Three dog Life''; reading and discussion. March 11 at 4:30 p.m. $3 and $ 5. Hudson Valley Writers' Center, 300 Riverside Drive. (914) 332-5953.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Annandale-On-Hudson ''Oklahoma'' by Richard Rodgers and Oscar Hammerstein, presented by the Bard Theater directed by Daniel Fish. March 11 at 7 p.m. $15. Bard College, (845) 758-7900.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''From the Mississippi Delta,'' by Dr. Endesha Ida Mae Holland. March 11 at 3 p.m. $12. The Studio Theater, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard. (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''The Complete Works of Shakespeare(abridged),'' comedy presented by M and M productions. March 18 at 2 p.m. Free. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''The Importance of Being Earnest,'' comedy, presented by the National Players. March 11 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Westchester Community College, Academic Arts Theater, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-6262.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Run for Your Wife,'' comedy by Allan Samuels; presented by the Fort Hill Players. Friday through March 24. $12 and $15. Rochambeau School for Adult and Continuing Education, 228 Fisher Avenue. (914) 761-7463.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''More of Loesser,'' musical featuring the lyrics and music of Frank Loesser; presented by New York Cabaret Unlimited. March 11 at 2 p.m. Free. ''The Glories of Ziegfeld,'' musical celebrating the 100th anniversary of the Ziegfeld Follies; presented by Three For the Show. March 18 at 2 p.m. Free. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Annandale-on-Hudson ''Now You See It,'' mixed-media works by Susan Hiller, Zoe Beloff and Jennifer Bornstein. March 11 through March 25. Reception: March 11, 1 to 4 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bard College, Center for Curatorial Studies. (845) 758-7598.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''New Boots and Panties,'' portraits by Kit Keith. March 11 through April 1. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Go North: A Space for Contemporary Art, 469 Main Street.</p>
        <p>Beacon '' Models on Main Street,'' photography group show. Through June 3. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturdays, 7 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 10 p.m. Muddy Cup Coffee House, 129 Main Street. (845) 440-8855.</p>
        <p>Beacon Mixed -media group show, featuring works by Stevan Jennis, Molly Rausch and Simon Draper. Through April 2. Hours: daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Van Brunt Gallery, 460 Main Street. (845) 838-2995.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Sly,'' mixed-media group show. Friday through April 21. Reception: March 16, 6 to 9 p.m. Suggested donation $5. Bronx River Art Center, 1087 Tremont Avenue. (718) 589-5819.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Sugar buzz,'' mixed-media group show. March 11 through May 15. Reception: March 12, 5:30 to 7 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Lehman College Art Gallery, Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8731.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''The Orchid Show'' and sale. Through April 8. $5 to $20. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road. (718) 817-8616.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Emily Dickinson Rendered,'' mixed-media group show of art inspired by the poetry of Emily Dickinson. Through May 25. Reception: April 15, 1 to 4:30 p.m. $2 to $4; members and under 6, free; free for everyone on Tuesdays; free for everyone Saturdays, 9 a.m. to noon. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Paintings by Herb Youner. Through March 25. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 12:30 to 5:30 p.m. Upstream Gallery, 26 Main Street. (914) 674-8548.</p>
        <p>Hudson ''View Three,'' works by three Native American artists. March 11 through April 7. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 6 p.m. Nicole Fiacco Gallery, 506 Warren Street. (518) 828-5090.</p>
        <p>Irvington ''Housekeepers of Irvington,'' photographs by Judith Ebenstein. Through March 31. Free. Irvington Public Library, 12 South Astor Street. (914) 591-7840.</p>
        <p>Katonah ''Tools as Art: The Hechinger Collection,'' curated by Sarah Tanguy. Through April 8. Admission: $5 and $3 Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>Kingston ''Quilting as an Art Form,'' quilts by members of the Wiltwyck Quilters Guild. ''Mixed-Media Dolls,'' by member artists. Both through March 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 1 to 6 p.m. Arts Society of Kingston Arts Center, 97 Broadway. (845) 338-0331.</p>
        <p>Kingston ''Recycling'' and ''The Patient,'' short-films by Bruce Pileggi. Tuesday at 6 p.m. Free. ASK Arts Center, 97 Broadway. (845) 338-0331.</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Images of Human Spirit: The Refugees of Darfur,'' photographs by Richard Levine. Through March 30. Free. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon ''Overlooked Hero: John Glover and the American Revolution,'' historical documents and prints; continuing. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>New Paltz ''From Impressionist to Modernist: The Paintings of Woodstock Artist Charles Rosen.'' Through May 20. Free. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Samuel Dorsky Museum of Art, SUNY New Paltz. (845) 257-3844.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Scenes from Bulgaria,'' paintings by Mark Patnode. Through March 24. Hours: Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 5 p.m. Third Rail Studio, 49 Plain Avenue. (914) 712-9831.</p>
        <p>Peekskill ''First Look II,'' mixed-media exhibition by art students. Through Sept. 30. $5, adults; $1, children; members, free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; group tours available by appointment. Hudson Valley Center for Contemporary Art, 1701 Main Street. (914) 788-7166.</p>
        <p>Pelham ''Lovely Dark and Deep: Women Artists Retake the Fairy Tale'';mixed-media group show. Through April 28. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Pelham Art Center, 155 Fifth Avenue. (914) 738-2525.</p>
        <p>Port Chester ''Rising Stars: A student show,'' clay art group show. March 11 through March 24. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''For the People: American Mural Drawings of the 1930's and 1940's,'' group show. March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Vassar College, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center. (845) 437-5632.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''New Media: When,'' group show. Through May 20. ''Lesley Dill: Tremendous World,'' installations. Through June 3. ''Fugitive Artist: The Early Work of Richard Prince, 1974-77.'' Through June 24. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.</p>
        <p>Rhinebeck ''Center's Edge,'' posters from productions by the Center for Performing Arts, by David Forman and Joe Morgan. Through March 17. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays, 9 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Montgomery Row Second Level, 6423 Montgomery Street (Route 9). (845) 876-6670.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Student Studio: Emerging High School Talent,'' mixed-media group show. Through March 24. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Spotlight on Historical Costumes,'' a collection of seasonal costumes. Through June 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. Square House Museum, 1 Purchase Street. (914) 967-7588.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Recurrents,'' mixed-media group show. Monday through April 21. Reception: March 22, 4 to 6 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Thursdays 6 to 8 p.m. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>West Nyack ''A Sequence of Steps,'' photographs by Elizabeth Knowles. '' Jiffy Pop,'' mixed-media group show. Both through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockland Center for the Arts, 27 South Greenbush Road. (845) 358-0877.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Tourists and Residents,'' paintings by Leeza Doreian. Through March 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Barbara Walters Gallery, Sarah Lawrence College, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 385-2220.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Language of Abstraction,'' paintings and prints by Meg Lindsay. Through March 31. Esther Raushenbush Library, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2470.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Westchester and Putnam Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to westweek@nytimes.com, or by mail to Westchester Cultural Calendar, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Tarrytown Chelsea Handler, stand-up comedian. March 17 at 8 p.m. $32.50. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Mamaroneck ''Who the #$&amp;% is Jackson Pollock?'' Documentary. Wednesday through March 17. $6 to $8. The Emelin Theatre, 153 Library Lane. (914) 698-3045</p>
        <p>Katonah Annual Katonah Film Project Series: ''Network,'' directed by Sidney Lumet. March 17 at 7:30 p.m. $5. Katonah Village Library, 26 Bedford Road. (914) 232-3508.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Music Makers of New Rochelle in the 20th Century,'' an exhibition and film festival: ''Aladdin,'' directed by Ron Clements and John Musker. March 11 at 1:30 p.m. Free. ''Beauty and the Beast,'' directed by Gary Trousdale and Kirk Wise. March 18 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Ossie Davis Theater, 1 Library Plaza. (914) 632-7878.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''The Quiet Man,'' directed by John Ford. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $6 and $8. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Pelham ''It Happened One Night,'' romantic comedy directed by Frank Capra. Friday at 7 p.m. Free. Huguenot Memorial Church, 901 Pelhamdale Ave. (914) 738-3488.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Malena,'' directed by Giuseppe Tornatore. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Elmsford ''Nursery Rhyme Time,'' songs, rhymes and movement. Thursday through March 29 at 10 a.m. Free. Greenburgh Public Library, 300 Tarrytown Road. (914) 993-1600.</p>
        <p>Nyack ''Milk n' Cookies Playhouse,'' musicians, jugglers, and puppet show hosted by Bossy Frog. March 17 at 10 a.m. $7 and $9. Riverspace, 119 Main Street. (845) 348-0741.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''Songs and Stories of the Animal World,'' presented by Danny Einbender. Ages 4 to 9. Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. Purchase Free Library, 3093 Purchase Street. (914) 948-0550.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Fun Facts About Dinosaurs,'' hands-on fossil presentation. March 17, 2 to 3:30 p.m. $15. Rye Nature Center, 873 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-5150.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Fun Family Sundays,'' parents and children art work shop. March 11, 3 to 4:30 p.m. Registration required. Belle School , 1088 Central Park Avenue. (914) 723-9229.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Music and Merriment,'' children's program. Ages 2 to 5. Through June 20. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 Extension 360.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''St. Patrick's Day Celebration,'' stories and crafts. Ages 4 to 6. Wednesday at 4 p.m. Free. Yonkers Crestwood Library, 16 Thompson Street. (914) 337-1500 Extension 360.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Mother Goose Time,'' nursery rhymes, stories, songs and finger plays. Ages 2 to 4. March 11 through May 17. Registration required. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Annandale-on-Hudson Melvin Chen, pianist. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Olin Hall, (518) 537-6665.</p>
        <p>Beacon Thomas Earl, vintage folk rock. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Chthonic Clash Coffeehouse, 453 Main Street. (845) 831-0359.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Blue Fringe, Jewish rock band. March 18 at 1 p.m. $18 and $25. Greenburgh Hebrew Center, 515 Broadway. (914) 693-5121.</p>
        <p>Katonah ''Parker String Quartet,'' performs Mozart's String Quartet in G major among others. March 18 at 4 p.m. $25. Caramoor Center for Music and the Arts, 149 Girdle Ridge Road. (914) 232-1252.</p>
        <p>Middletown Marshall Crenshaw, rock, singer, songwriter and musician. March 11 at 3 p.m. $22 and $25. The Mansion, 14 Wilcox Avenue. (845) 343-3049.</p>
        <p>New City Sing We Enchanted, a cappella chorus directed by Nell Macdonald. March 11 at 7 p.m. Suggested donation $10. Saint Augustine Church, 140 Maple Avenue. (845) 634-2407.</p>
        <p>Ossining T. Broussard and the Zydeco steppers. March 18, 5 to 9:30 p.m. $18. Zydeco Hall, 7 Old Albany Post Road. (914) 528-7612.</p>
        <p>Peekskill Steve Chizmadia, singer and songwriter. Friday at 8 p.m. Free; donation encouraged. Peekskill Coffee House, 101 South Division Street. (914) 739-1287.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie Rebecca Frezza, children's music singer. March 18 at 3 p.m. $8 and $10. Jewish Community Center of Dutchess County, 110 Grand Avenue. (845) 471-0430.</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Music Tech Fair,'' hands-on multimedia presentation. March 11, 12:30 to 4:30 p.m. Free. Michael Finckel, cellist; performs works by Debussy, Kodaly and Schumann. Friday at 8 p.m. $11 to $13. Hoff-Barthelson Music School, 25 School Lane. (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown ''An Evening of Vocalists,'' presented by the Lagond Music School. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Coffee Labs, 7 Main Street. (914) 332-1479.</p>
        <p>Tarrytown Solas, Celtic band. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. Tarrytown Music Hall, 13 Main Street. (914) 631-3390.</p>
        <p>White Plains Brian Conway, Irish fiddler. March 11 at 4 p.m. $10 and $20. Divine Compassion Center, 52 North Broadway. (914) 948-4086.</p>
        <p>White Plains Spring Choral and Orchestra Concert, directed by Timothy Lewis; works by Bach, Handel and Haydn. March 11 at 4 p.m. $18 and $20. Grace Church, Mamaroneck Avenue. (914) 949-0384.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Kids on Central,'' children's music series presented by the Westchester Philharmonic and the Music Conservatory of Westchester: ''The String Thing.'' March 17 at 2 p.m. $10. Music Conservatory of Westchester, 216 Central Avenue. (914) 761-3900.</p>
        <p>Yonkers  Yonkers Philharmonic Orchestra, concert directed by Maestro James; works by Beethoven and Bizet. March 11 at 3 p.m. Free. Robert Dodson School , 105 Avondale Road. (914) 476-3711.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Scarsdale ''Highlights Tour,'' introductory tour of the center's lawns, gardens, trails and other outdoor facilities. March 11 at 11:30 a.m. $3 to $5. ''Old Fashioned Maple Sugaring Party,'' tree tapping, sap collecting, and syrup and sugar making. March 18, 1 to 4 p.m. $5 and $7. Greenburgh Nature Center, 99 Dromore Road. (914) 723-3470.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Armonk Peter R. Limburg, author of ''Deceived: The Story of the Donner Party;'' discussion. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. North Castle Public Library, 19 Whippoorwill Road. (914) 273-3887.</p>
        <p>Hastings-on-Hudson ''Rwanda, a Journey From Hope to Healing,'' discussion by Melody Cooper, playwright. March 18 at 1 p.m. Free. First Unitarian Society of Westchester, 25 Jackson Avenue. (914) 478-2710.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle Dr. Diane Sharon hold discussion on blurred boundaries and sacred spaces. Thursday at 8 p.m. $10. Beth El Synagogue-Center, 1324 North Ave # 1. (914) 235-2700.</p>
        <p>Purchase Edwin G. Burrows, author of ''How New York Became the Big Apple''; discussion and lecture. Thursday at 4:30 p.m. Free. Dance Lab Theater, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6830.</p>
        <p>Purchase Mary-Lou Weisman, author; reading and discussion. March 18 at 3 p.m. Free. Reid Hall, 2900 Purchase Street. (140) 323-5300.</p>
        <p>Rye Bill Mayher, author of ''Joel White: Boatbuilder, Designer, Sailor''; slide show and discussion. March 11 at 4 p.m. Free. Rye Free Reading Room, 1061 Boston Post Road. (914) 967-0480.</p>
        <p>Sleepy Hollow Danielle Trussoni author of '' Falling through the Earth'' and Abigail Thomas author of '' A Three dog Life''; reading and discussion. March 11 at 4:30 p.m. $3 and $ 5. Hudson Valley Writers' Center, 300 Riverside Drive. (914) 332-5953.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Annandale-On-Hudson ''Oklahoma'' by Richard Rodgers and Oscar Hammerstein, presented by the Bard Theater directed by Daniel Fish. March 11 at 7 p.m. $15. Bard College, (845) 758-7900.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''From the Mississippi Delta,'' by Dr. Endesha Ida Mae Holland. March 11 at 3 p.m. $12. The Studio Theater, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard. (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>Pleasantville ''The Complete Works of Shakespeare(abridged),'' comedy presented by M and M productions. March 18 at 2 p.m. Free. Mount Pleasant Public Library, 350 Bedford Road. (914) 769-0548.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''The Importance of Being Earnest,'' comedy, presented by the National Players. March 11 at 3 p.m. $10 to $20. Westchester Community College, Academic Arts Theater, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-6262.</p>
        <p>White Plains ''Run for Your Wife,'' comedy by Allan Samuels; presented by the Fort Hill Players. Friday through March 24. $12 and $15. Rochambeau School for Adult and Continuing Education, 228 Fisher Avenue. (914) 761-7463.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''More of Loesser,'' musical featuring the lyrics and music of Frank Loesser; presented by New York Cabaret Unlimited. March 11 at 2 p.m. Free. ''The Glories of Ziegfeld,'' musical celebrating the 100th anniversary of the Ziegfeld Follies; presented by Three For the Show. March 18 at 2 p.m. Free. Yonkers Public Library, Grinton I. Will branch, 1500 Central Park Avenue. (914) 337-1500.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Annandale-on-Hudson ''Now You See It,'' mixed-media works by Susan Hiller, Zoe Beloff and Jennifer Bornstein. March 11 through March 25. Reception: March 11, 1 to 4 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bard College, Center for Curatorial Studies. (845) 758-7598.</p>
        <p>Beacon ''New Boots and Panties,'' portraits by Kit Keith. March 11 through April 1. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Go North: A Space for Contemporary Art, 469 Main Street.</p>
        <p>Beacon '' Models on Main Street,'' photography group show. Through June 3. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Saturdays, 7 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 10 p.m. Muddy Cup Coffee House, 129 Main Street. (845) 440-8855.</p>
        <p>Beacon Mixed -media group show, featuring works by Stevan Jennis, Molly Rausch and Simon Draper. Through April 2. Hours: daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Van Brunt Gallery, 460 Main Street. (845) 838-2995.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Sly,'' mixed-media group show. Friday through April 21. Reception: March 16, 6 to 9 p.m. Suggested donation $5. Bronx River Art Center, 1087 Tremont Avenue. (718) 589-5819.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Sugar buzz,'' mixed-media group show. March 11 through May 15. Reception: March 12, 5:30 to 7 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Lehman College Art Gallery, Bedford Park Boulevard West. (718) 960-8731.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''The Orchid Show'' and sale. Through April 8. $5 to $20. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road. (718) 817-8616.</p>
        <p>Bronx ''Emily Dickinson Rendered,'' mixed-media group show of art inspired by the poetry of Emily Dickinson. Through May 25. Reception: April 15, 1 to 4:30 p.m. $2 to $4; members and under 6, free; free for everyone on Tuesdays; free for everyone Saturdays, 9 a.m. to noon. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Wave Hill, 675 West 252nd Street. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Dobbs Ferry Paintings by Herb Youner. Through March 25. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 12:30 to 5:30 p.m. Upstream Gallery, 26 Main Street. (914) 674-8548.</p>
        <p>Hudson ''View Three,'' works by three Native American artists. March 11 through April 7. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 6 p.m. Nicole Fiacco Gallery, 506 Warren Street. (518) 828-5090.</p>
        <p>Irvington ''Housekeepers of Irvington,'' photographs by Judith Ebenstein. Through March 31. Free. Irvington Public Library, 12 South Astor Street. (914) 591-7840.</p>
        <p>Katonah ''Tools as Art: The Hechinger Collection,'' curated by Sarah Tanguy. Through April 8. Admission: $5 and $3 Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Katonah Museum of Art, Route 22 at Jay Street. (914) 232-9555.</p>
        <p>Kingston ''Quilting as an Art Form,'' quilts by members of the Wiltwyck Quilters Guild. ''Mixed-Media Dolls,'' by member artists. Both through March 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 1 to 6 p.m. Arts Society of Kingston Arts Center, 97 Broadway. (845) 338-0331.</p>
        <p>Kingston ''Recycling'' and ''The Patient,'' short-films by Bruce Pileggi. Tuesday at 6 p.m. Free. ASK Arts Center, 97 Broadway. (845) 338-0331.</p>
        <p>Larchmont ''Images of Human Spirit: The Refugees of Darfur,'' photographs by Richard Levine. Through March 30. Free. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Larchmont Public Library, 121 Larchmont Avenue. (914) 834-2281.</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon ''Overlooked Hero: John Glover and the American Revolution,'' historical documents and prints; continuing. St. Paul's Church National Historic Site, 897 South Columbus Avenue. (914) 667-4116.</p>
        <p>New Paltz ''From Impressionist to Modernist: The Paintings of Woodstock Artist Charles Rosen.'' Through May 20. Free. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Samuel Dorsky Museum of Art, SUNY New Paltz. (845) 257-3844.</p>
        <p>New Rochelle ''Scenes from Bulgaria,'' paintings by Mark Patnode. Through March 24. Hours: Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 5 p.m. Third Rail Studio, 49 Plain Avenue. (914) 712-9831.</p>
        <p>Peekskill ''First Look II,'' mixed-media exhibition by art students. Through Sept. 30. $5, adults; $1, children; members, free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; group tours available by appointment. Hudson Valley Center for Contemporary Art, 1701 Main Street. (914) 788-7166.</p>
        <p>Pelham ''Lovely Dark and Deep: Women Artists Retake the Fairy Tale'';mixed-media group show. Through April 28. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Pelham Art Center, 155 Fifth Avenue. (914) 738-2525.</p>
        <p>Port Chester ''Rising Stars: A student show,'' clay art group show. March 11 through March 24. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Clay Art Center, 40 Beech Street. (914) 937-2047.</p>
        <p>Poughkeepsie ''For the People: American Mural Drawings of the 1930's and 1940's,'' group show. March 11. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Vassar College, Frances Lehman Loeb Art Center. (845) 437-5632.</p>
        <p>Purchase ''New Media: When,'' group show. Through May 20. ''Lesley Dill: Tremendous World,'' installations. Through June 3. ''Fugitive Artist: The Early Work of Richard Prince, 1974-77.'' Through June 24. $3 to $5; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Neuberger Museum of Art, 735 Anderson Hill Road. (914) 251-6100.</p>
        <p>Rhinebeck ''Center's Edge,'' posters from productions by the Center for Performing Arts, by David Forman and Joe Morgan. Through March 17. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays, 9 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Montgomery Row Second Level, 6423 Montgomery Street (Route 9). (845) 876-6670.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Student Studio: Emerging High School Talent,'' mixed-media group show. Through March 24. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. (914) 967-0700.</p>
        <p>Rye ''Spotlight on Historical Costumes,'' a collection of seasonal costumes. Through June 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. Square House Museum, 1 Purchase Street. (914) 967-7588.</p>
        <p>Valhalla ''Recurrents,'' mixed-media group show. Monday through April 21. Reception: March 22, 4 to 6 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Thursdays 6 to 8 p.m. Fine Arts Gallery, 75 Grasslands Road. (914) 606-7867.</p>
        <p>West Nyack ''A Sequence of Steps,'' photographs by Elizabeth Knowles. '' Jiffy Pop,'' mixed-media group show. Both through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockland Center for the Arts, 27 South Greenbush Road. (845) 358-0877.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Tourists and Residents,'' paintings by Leeza Doreian. Through March 27. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Barbara Walters Gallery, Sarah Lawrence College, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 385-2220.</p>
        <p>Yonkers ''Language of Abstraction,'' paintings and prints by Meg Lindsay. Through March 31. Esther Raushenbush Library, Sarah Lawrence College. (914) 395-2470.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
