<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singh Can't Accept Sorenstam as a Foe</title>
    <meta content="13GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/13/sports/golf/13golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1488692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colonial Tournament (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singh, Vijay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DF113FF930A25756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singh Can't Accept Sorenstam as a Foe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Singh Joins Dissonant Chorus on Sorenstam</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vijay Singh expresses disapproval over Annika Sorenstam's participation in Colonial Tournament, during which she will face men; Singh threatens to withdraw if paired with Sorenstam; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh is the latest PGA Tour member to express disapproval over Annika Sorenstam's plans to play against men in next week's Colonial tournament.</p>
        <p>Singh, the winner of the 1998 P.G.A. Championship and the 2000 Masters, threatened to withdraw from the Colonial yesterday if he were paired with Sorenstam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh, the winner of the 1998 P.G.A. Championship and the 2000 Masters, threatened to withdraw from the Colonial if he were paired with Annika Sorenstam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vijay Singh is the latest PGA Tour member to express disapproval over Annika Sorenstam's plans to play against men in next week's Colonial tournament.</p>
        <p>Singh, the winner of the 1998 P.G.A. Championship and the 2000 Masters, threatened to withdraw from the Colonial yesterday if he were paired with Sorenstam.</p>
        <p>''I hope she misses the cut,'' Singh was quoted as saying by The Associated Press. ''Why? Because she doesn't belong out here. If I'm drawn with her, which I won't be, I won't play.</p>
        <p>''What is she going to prove by playing? It's ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, the No. 1-ranked woman in golf, with 43 career L.P.G.A. victories and 4 major championships, was given a sponsor's exemption to play in the Colonial, which begins May 22 in Fort Worth. She will be the first woman to compete in a PGA Tour event since Babe Zaharias at the 1945 Los Angeles Open.</p>
        <p>Singh cannot be paired with Sorenstam at the start; his name will be drawn from a pool of PGA Tour winners when the pairings are made. Still, he added a strong voice to a group of players who have offered a cool reaction to Sorenstam's plans.</p>
        <p>Nick Price, the defending champion at the Colonial, suggested recently that Sorenstam should have declined the invitation to compete and said her decision ''reeks of publicity.''</p>
        <p>Scott Hoch, a member of the 2002 United States Ryder Cup team, was quoted as saying that he wanted Sorenstam to play well in the tournament but only to prove a point: If she plays well and still finishes back in the pack, Hoch said, it will demonstrate ''how much separation there is between us and the ladies' tour.''</p>
        <p>Even Tiger Woods, the No. 1 golfer in the world, who considers the 32-year-old Sorenstam a friend, has questioned the wisdom of her decision to play. Woods said in February, after Sorenstam made her announcement, that Sorenstam could damage women's golf if she did not play well.</p>
        <p>Singh, a 40-year-old native of Fiji, is mild-mannered and normally low-key. In the early 1990's, when some in golf tried to use the dark-skinned, broad-shouldered Singh to temper the sport's segregated, country club image, he simply let his golf do the talking. Yet Singh, who is ranked No. 7 in the world, held nothing back in an interview with The A.P. as he left the locker room at Quail Hollow on Sunday after the Wachovia Championship in Charlotte, N.C. ''She's the best woman golfer in the world, and I want to emphasize 'woman,''' Singh said of Sorenstam. ''We have our tour for men, and they have their tour.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam was returning yesterday from Japan, where she won the Nichirei Cup by nine shots.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Woods Says He Will Skip the Colonial</p>
        <p>OLYMPIA FIELDS, Ill., May 12 (AP) -- Tiger Woods is skipping the Colonial, and he will most likely go to the United States Open here next month having played only two tournaments since the Masters.</p>
        <p>Woods has always played at least three times between the Masters and the Open. But he said today that he was trying to stick to a lighter schedule after having knee surgery in December.</p>
        <p>''I'll probably play fewer events than I did last year, just to make sure everything is O.K.,'' he said. ''I'm taking more time off and just making sure everything is all right for the future.''</p>
        <p>Woods missed five tournaments early in the season after having surgery to remove fluid and benign cysts that had caused ligaments in his left knee to swell. He has not played since finishing in a tie for 15th at the Masters, a four-week break.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
