<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Too Famous To Suffer Unnoticed</title>
    <meta content="03VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/03/sports/othersports/03VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1532411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blindness</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Runyan, Marla</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blindness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blindness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Runyan, Marla</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DE1130F930A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Too Famous To Suffer Unnoticed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Runyan Too Famous to Suffer Unnoticed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marla Runyan, who is legally blind, finishes 20th in New York City Marathon women's division; Runyan, 34, has hereditary condition called Stargadt's disease; now she has aspirations of being long-distance medalist in her athletic old age; photo (Sports of The Times column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BECAUSE she is so recognizable, with her thick wraparound shades, Marla Runyan could not suffer anonymously.</p>
        <p>All three times she slowed to a walk yesterday, the acutely verbal New York fans shouted encouragement -- exactly the kind of stick-to-it-girl sympathy that a world-class athlete does not want to hear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marla Runyan, who finished a disappointing 20th in the New York City Marathon, was having "a bad day" in public, in front of millions who called her by name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BECAUSE she is so recognizable, with her thick wraparound shades, Marla Runyan could not suffer anonymously.</p>
        <p>All three times she slowed to a walk yesterday, the acutely verbal New York fans shouted encouragement -- exactly the kind of stick-to-it-girl sympathy that a world-class athlete does not want to hear.</p>
        <p>''Every time I was walking, I felt so ashamed,'' Runyan said after finishing a disappointing 20th in the New York City Marathon. ''I just wanted to hang my head.''</p>
        <p>Runyan was one of the crowd favorites on a glorious, warm day in the five boroughs and 100 nations of New York. Many lining the streets know she is legally blind and has made herself a mainstream Olympic athlete. People in Bay Ridge and Greenpoint and the Bronx tend to like an underdog.</p>
        <p>Like all the other elite runners on the course, Runyan tuned out the colors and the banners, the buildings and the faces that make the marathon the finest single sporting day in the city. But she could hear the many accents imploring her to keep going.</p>
        <p>''Such a diverse unification of people, all cheering you on,'' she said, despite the disappointment in her legs.</p>
        <p>Runyan, 34, has a hereditary condition called Stargardt's disease, which caused her retinas to begin deteriorating at age 9. She cannot drive a car or read normal-size newspaper type, but she can work her way through a crowded news media center, as she did after her race yesterday, stopping to help herself at the buffet after a close-range inspection.</p>
        <p>It has not been easy for her to switch from competing as a disabled athlete. But in 2000 in Sydney, Australia, Runyan became the first legally blind American athlete to compete in the Summer Games, finishing eighth in the 1,500 meters.</p>
        <p>Now she has aspirations of being a long-distance medalist in her athletic old age. Yesterday she started with the Kenyans and the other top women, climbing the vacated roadway of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge.</p>
        <p>''It's a spectacular moment,'' she said of leaving Staten Island, catching the sea breeze, with ships in the harbor far below, and the crowds of Brooklyn waiting just ahead.</p>
        <p>There was an official road sign on one of the ramps that said ''Leaving Brooklyn -- Fuhgeddaboudit,'' in the patois of the borough. She had no time to observe local color, even though her peripheral vision is functional.</p>
        <p>''I'm pretty focused on the road ahead of me,'' said Runyan, who receives no special assistance like a guide runner or cyclist. She is on her own in the scrum. At a water station yesterday, she bumped into Catherine Ndereba of Kenya, who finished second, but the contact did not seem to affect either of them.</p>
        <p>''Today it was all in my legs,'' Runyan said, meaning her problems came from within rather than from the heat or the other runners.</p>
        <p>She stuck near the front of the pack for the first half. Tall and slender, her shoulders seemed to work overtime. Directly in front was a red Dodge van with the television camera staring out the back. On the sides was New York in all its glory:</p>
        <p>A handwritten sign that said ''Yo! Welcome to Brooklyn.'' A solitary man with a scarf from Wales. A brass band playing ''God Bless America'' outside a Korean church. Chadors and Mexican flags and a sign that advertised ''Divorce -- $299.'' Thousands of orange balloons outside the Brooklyn Academy of Music and the band from Bishop Loughlin High playing ''Eye of the Tiger.''</p>
        <p>In the Williamsburg section of Brooklyn, thousands of Hasids lined the street, most of them gazing impassively at the runners. When Fred Lebow, the impresario of the New York Marathon, was alive, he would implore the Hasids to show a little spirit and cheer for the runners. Fred would, of course, do the imploring in Yiddish.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, around the midway point, nearing the border with Queens, Marla Runyan felt the race getting away. She is no fan of the heat, but she would not use that excuse. ''There was just soreness in the legs,'' she said wanly, much later. ''I was just not rested enough.''</p>
        <p>She slowed to walk once, twice, three times. The Kenyans were now many minutes ahead.</p>
        <p>''I started thinking of a D.N.F.,'' she said, meaning Did Not Finish, the worst phrase in a marathoner's vocabulary. ''But then I said, the goal was just to finish.''</p>
        <p>What made her finish? Charity, she said. She would earn money for charity by finishing. So she did. She plodded through the Bronx, where crowds seemed bigger than in past years; into Harlem, past church people in their Sunday finery; into the welcome shade of Fifth Avenue; then into the park, past people in T-shirts and shorts; and on to Central Park South with its ubiquitous odor of horse manure, and the normal cacophony in the narrow roadways of the park. She finished in 2:45:12, far behind Margaret Okayo of Kenya, whose course-record time was 2:22:31.</p>
        <p>Later Runyan would thank the people for their attention, but at the time it only made her feel worse. Marla Runyan is an elite athlete (who happens to be legally blind) and she was having ''a bad day'' in public, in front of millions who called her by name.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
