<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Brown's Flat Tax: Tilted</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAX CREDITS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALL, ROBERT (ECONOMIST)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RABUSHKA, ALVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, EDMUND G JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD163FF934A15750C0A964958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Brown's Flat Tax: Tilted</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking Jerry Brown seriously means taking his flat tax proposal seriously. Needlessly, he's made that hard to do. By being careless, the former California Governor has bent a good idea out of shape. He could fix it, but until he does, Bill Clinton is right to attack the plan as a budget-buster and a dagger aimed at poor families.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's basic idea -- creating a simplified code that encourages saving -- is exactly right. But he ignores all-important details. The tragedy is that his cavalier attitude has armed his critics to denounce the one truly creative and important idea to emerge from this Presidential campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Taking Jerry Brown seriously means taking his flat tax proposal seriously. Needlessly, he's made that hard to do. By being careless, the former California Governor has bent a good idea out of shape. He could fix it, but until he does, Bill Clinton is right to attack the plan as a budget-buster and a dagger aimed at poor families.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's basic idea -- creating a simplified code that encourages saving -- is exactly right. But he ignores all-important details. The tragedy is that his cavalier attitude has armed his critics to denounce the one truly creative and important idea to emerge from this Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The present tax code is riddled with wasteful contradictions and complexity. For example, profit from corporate investment is taxed twice -- when earned by the corporation and again when distributed to shareholders. That powerfully discourages savings and investment -- the exact opposite of what the economy needs to grow.</p>
        <p>The remedy is, in a word, integration, meshing personal and corporate codes so that the brunt of taxes falls on consumption, not saving. Tax reform should also simplify the code, making loopholes harder for Congress to disguise, and enact. And for reasons of elemental decency, tax reform shouldn't come at the expense of the poor.</p>
        <p>Remarkably, there is a reform that achieves all these objectives. Robert Hall and Alvin Rabushka, economists at the Hoover Institution, have proposed an integrated code that applies a single rate to both personal and corporate income. Their plan wipes away most deductions and exemptions, permitting a low tax rate of 19 percent. The important term is not</p>
        <p>flat</p>
        <p>but</p>
        <p>integrated.</p>
        <p>Under the Hall-Rabushka plan, individuals would pay taxes on earnings and corporations would pay tax on interest, dividends and profits. That way, every dollar of income would be taxed once and only once. The plan would subsidize saving, and create an exemption that would protect the poor.</p>
        <p>For that very good reason, Hall-Rabushka isn't perfectly flat. But it is perfectly simple; the tax return would fit on a postcard.</p>
        <p>Jerry Brown borrowed some of the elements of Hall-Rabushka. He too would eliminate wasteful exemptions, adopt a single rate and favor saving by exempting corporate investment. But at that point, he turns glib.</p>
        <p>He would impose on corporations a value-added tax, similar to a national sales tax. That eliminates the elegant symmetry of Hall-Rabushka. Indirectly, Mr. Brown's variation would tax some income twice -- which is why his supposed 13 percent rate would collect revenue equal to about 20 percent of total income.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's plan would also eliminate Hall-Rabushka's low-income exemption. That makes his reform even more unfair. The value-added tax, acting as sales tax, would drive up consumer prices regressively. The poor, unlike the rich, must spend most of their income on necessities.</p>
        <p>With even a little thought, Mr. Brown could have averted these disabling details. He could have built in exemptions, credits and progressive rates to ease burdens on low- and middle-income families.  He could have raised rates high enough to make his plan truly revenue neutral. And he could have followed Hall-Rabushka closely enough to produce a truly integrated code.</p>
        <p>But for no obvious reason, he has done none of these things. He may go on contending that his campaign represents poor and alienated voters. But as it stands, his version of a superb idea turns the tax tables against them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
