<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Green Replaces Piniella As Manager of Yankees</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="186000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBRENNER, GEORGE M 3D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PINIELLA, LOU</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREEN, DALLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D81431F93BA35753C1A96E948260" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Green Replaces Piniella As Manager of Yankees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: George Steinbrenner, as expected, changed managers yesterday for the 16th time in his 16 years as the Yankees' principal owner. Steinbrenner dismissed Lou Piniella for the second time in 355 days and replaced him with Dallas Green, a former major league pitcher, manager, general manager and club president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: George Steinbrenner, as expected, changed managers yesterday for the 16th time in his 16 years as the Yankees' principal owner. Steinbrenner dismissed Lou Piniella for the second time in 355 days and replaced him with Dallas Green, a former major league pitcher, manager, general manager and club president.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner, as expected, changed managers yesterday for the 16th time in his 16 years as the Yankees' principal owner. Steinbrenner dismissed Lou Piniella for the second time in 355 days and replaced him with Dallas Green, a former major league pitcher, manager, general manager and club president. Green received a two-year contract.</p>
        <p>The Yankees - and the Chicago White Sox, who dismissed Jim Fregosi as manager - made their announcement with the approval of Commissioner Peter Ueberroth, who temporarily lifted his policy against such personnel announcements during the pennant playoffs and the World Series.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner's move came after he met with Piniella in Tampa, Fla. Harvey Greene, the Yankees' media relations director, said neither the owner nor Piniella would be available for comment.</p>
        <p>Piniella, who was replaced by Billy Martin last Oct. 19 after two years as manager, has a three-year, $1.2 million contract that he signed after agreeing to replace Martin on June 23. It was not known immediately if Piniella would remain with the Yankees in another capacity. Job Openings</p>
        <p>He instantly became a candidate for other managerial vacancies, especially the ones in Houston and in Seattle, where Woody Woodward is the Mariners' general manager. Piniella worked closely with Woodward when he was the Yankees' general manager.</p>
        <p>Ueberroth recently reiterated his policy about clubs not making announcements during post-season play, but he approved yesterday's announcements.</p>
        <p>''I received five requests for exceptions, each one presented eloquently,'' Ueberroth said. ''Arguments like, 'If I'm going to make a change, it doesn't give the individual a chance to apply for some of the other openings until after the World Series,' some others saying the leaks and rumors are too tough on the guy's family.</p>
        <p>''I listened to those and said my opinion still stands, but I will allow a hiatus for Friday afternoon, the day that only one game is being played; it's a travel day for the American League. I said, 'If you feel it's an absolute necessity, go ahead on that day and I will not consider it to be very negative.' The five clubs indicated that they would avail themselves of that timing.'' Premature Burial?  The Mariners were apparently premature in announcing Thursday that Jim Snyder, their interim manager, would not be given the job permanently. No other announcements were forthcoming yesterday, but it was believed that the other two clubs Ueberroth referred to were the Astros and the California Angels, who have managerial vacancies.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner's selection of Green came as no surprise. If Piniella had rejected the chance to return in June, Green would have become the manager then.</p>
        <p>When Piniella replaced Martin, the Yankees had a 40-28 record and were in second place, two and one-half games from first. Under Piniella, the Yankees had a 45-48 record and slipped to fifth place on the last two days of the season, finishing three and one-half games out. For the seventh consecutive season the Yankees failed to win the American League East championship.</p>
        <p>''I thought Lou did a great job holding them together,'' Green said in a telephone conference call from his farm in West Grove, Pa. ''The pitching broke down a little bit, and we had some physical problems that hurt us at times.''</p>
        <p>Why, then, did Steinbrenner feel a change was necessary?</p>
        <p>''The bottom line with Mr. Steinbrenner is winning,'' Green said, ''and apparently he wasn't satisfied with the way Lou went about it or the results.'' Comments From Clark</p>
        <p>Jack Clark, who has been unhappy with the often-chaotic atmosphere around the club, saw yesterday's move as more of the same kind of turmoil that bothered him during the season.</p>
        <p>''They're in such a hurry to win that it seems like they do things spur of the moment, and the result is a lot of confusion,'' Clark said. ''It's tough to get consistency on the field that way.''</p>
        <p>Charles Hudson blamed Piniella's demise on the players. ''We had a job to do and we didn't do it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Green, who compiled a 20-22 record as a major league pitcher in the 1960's, mostly with Philadelphia, managed the Phillies to the World Seroes championship in 1980, becoming only the fourth rookie manager to win the Series. He moved to the Chicago Cubs one year later as general manager and took on the duties of president three years after that. The Cubs dismissed him a year ago, citing philosophical differences.</p>
        <p>''They wanted to change things that Dallas Green deeply believed in,'' he said. ''I wasn't comfortable with that.''</p>
        <p>Green said he was not blindly walking into the Yankee job.</p>
        <p>''I know it can be difficult at times,'' he said, ''but there's no job in baseball that you're not going to have problems, that you're not going to have somebody second-guess you and insist on their way.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of Steinbrenner, he said: ''George and I go back a lot further than people realize. When I was a minor league player in Buffalo, who do I run into in a couple of my favorite haunts but George Steinbrenner? Later, I attended a lot of meetings in behalf of the Cubs that Mr. Steinbrenner was at. I've listened to him talk. I've been in conversation with him. I think I know him and I think he, in turn, knows me.''</p>
        <p>Green, 54 years old, cited his varied baseball background as a reason why he could possibly succeed where others have failed.</p>
        <p>''All of those things,'' he said, ''have given me an insight that perhaps I'll be able to accomplish some of the things that maybe some of the other guys haven't been able to do. What I intend to do is instill in this team the discipline that I think is necessary in today's baseball to get things done. If that doesn't work, I'll probably go the way of all Yankee managers.''</p>
        <p>Green, the type of disciplinarian Steinbrenner likes, said the owner would allow him to bring in his own coaches. The 1988 coaching staff, he said, would not return.</p>
        <p>Because Green has front-office experience, it was thought that he might gain authority over personnel decisions and trades. He said he would discuss such matters with Steinbrenner and General Manager Bob Quinn but that he would not have final say. ----Philosophical Dispute The dismissal of Fregosi by the White Sox came after two years of what General Manager Larry Himes called ''philosophical differences.''</p>
        <p>Himes never criticized Fregosi's managerial abilities and didn't when the dismissal was announced. He said he hoped to name Fregosi's successor before the annual winter meetings in the first week of December.  THE BOTTOM LINE  The managing records of Dallas Green and Lou Piniella.  Green with the Phillies</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Year</p>
        <p>W-L</p>
        <p>Pct.</p>
        <p>1979</p>
        <p>19-11</p>
        <p>.633</p>
        <p>1980*</p>
        <p>91-71</p>
        <p>.562</p>
        <p>1981</p>
        <p>59-48</p>
        <p>.551</p>
        <p>Totals</p>
        <p>169-130</p>
        <p>.565</p>
        <p>*Won World Series.  Piniella with the Yankees</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Year</p>
        <p>W-L</p>
        <p>Pct.</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>90-72</p>
        <p>.556</p>
        <p>1987</p>
        <p>89-73</p>
        <p>.549</p>
        <p>1988</p>
        <p>45-48</p>
        <p>.484</p>
        <p>Totals</p>
        <p>224-193</p>
        <p>.537</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
