<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Menace, Glitter and Rock in Visions of Dystopia</title>
    <meta content="29ps1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/29/arts/design/29ps1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070103T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">P S 1 Contemporary Art Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEEDB1F31F93AA15751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Menace, Glitter and Rock in Visions of Dystopia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Menace, Glitter and Rock in Visions of Dystopia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is architecture destiny where museums are concerned? As more and more of them mortgage their futures to big, expensive destination buildings, it sure seems that way. So maybe the recurring, often surprising vitality of the P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center is worth considering from an architectural standpoint. Sure, the place has great DNA from a gene pool that reaches back to the 1970s, when art was being reinvented and museums were too, partly through the rise of alternative spaces, one of which became P.S. 1.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, P.S. 1 managed to procure a great stage for its alternative act: a rambling, neglected Romanesque Revival public school building in Long Island City, Queens. Over the years the building has been extensively upgraded without being substantially altered or made posh. In addition, it was brilliantly reconfigured in a single stroke in 1997, when the structure's back door was converted into a front entrance centered on a large, walled-in courtyard. There have been losses, including the elimination, for more gallery space, of the International Studios Programs, which provided artists from around the world a yearlong foothold in New York. But if P.S. 1 has shifted its commitment from production to display, as some observers have charged, it has also evolved into a place that serves art by giving another put-upon group -- museum curators -- the freedom and space to learn their craft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rationales behind “Defamation of Character,” “The Gold Standard,” “Altered, Stitched and Gathered” and “Music Is a Better Noise,” all at P.S. 1, are disparate, if not antagonistic, and run the gamut from formal to formless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is architecture destiny where museums are concerned? As more and more of them mortgage their futures to big, expensive destination buildings, it sure seems that way. So maybe the recurring, often surprising vitality of the P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center is worth considering from an architectural standpoint. Sure, the place has great DNA from a gene pool that reaches back to the 1970s, when art was being reinvented and museums were too, partly through the rise of alternative spaces, one of which became P.S. 1.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, P.S. 1 managed to procure a great stage for its alternative act: a rambling, neglected Romanesque Revival public school building in Long Island City, Queens. Over the years the building has been extensively upgraded without being substantially altered or made posh. In addition, it was brilliantly reconfigured in a single stroke in 1997, when the structure's back door was converted into a front entrance centered on a large, walled-in courtyard. There have been losses, including the elimination, for more gallery space, of the International Studios Programs, which provided artists from around the world a yearlong foothold in New York. But if P.S. 1 has shifted its commitment from production to display, as some observers have charged, it has also evolved into a place that serves art by giving another put-upon group -- museum curators -- the freedom and space to learn their craft.</p>
        <p>This is especially true right now, with the building filled to overflowing by four large group shows. The rationales behind ''Defamation of Character,'' ''The Gold Standard,'' ''Altered, Stitched and Gathered'' and ''Music Is a Better Noise'' are disparate, if not antagonistic, and run the gamut from formal to formless. But combined, they present new and recent work by more than 130 artists, forming an inadvertent, four-part biennial that reaches back to the 1970s, when P.S. 1 was founded.</p>
        <p>''Defamation of Character'' and ''The Gold Standard,'' the two largest shows, are unified, even visually coherent, in an almost traditional curatorial sense. They arrive at similarly dystopic views of contemporary life by radically different paths, one dark and tortured, the other paved in gold.</p>
        <p>In ''Defamation of Character'' the British-born, New York-based writer Neville Wakefield, who became a curatorial advisor at P.S. 1 at the beginning of 2005, has created a bracing black hole in which movements like Dada, Fluxus, Punk, Pop, Conceptual and neo-Conceptual mingle with performance art, feminism, abject art with a capital A and various forms of appropriation.</p>
        <p>Largely devoid of color, these works by 46 artists take issue with most aspects of contemporary, and especially American, society. A high premium is placed on shock value, with frequent references to sex, violence, bodily functions, celebrity, consumerism and power.</p>
        <p>In the show's opening gallery black lines and shades of gray mingle to visually lively effect. ''Cioran Handrail,'' a long, free-floating squiggle of black polyurethane (toxic smoke? excrement?) by Urs Fischer, spirals toward ''The Period,'' by Glenn Ligon, which spells out the word America in lighted neon tubing that has been painted matte black. The letters, treated this way, look inert, implacable and yet somehow stifled -- giving an impression of menace and oppression. On the walls politics, abstraction, the female body and self-loathing, as well as appropriation, collage, erasure and drawing, are effectively broached by Lutz Bacher, Christopher Wool, Dash Snow and Martin Kippenberger.</p>
        <p>While similar to previous exhibitions organized by Mr. Wakefield, this one sustains its curatorial vision while venturing beyond a predictable clique of hip male artists overly prone to using black. It might be described as the usual suspects with invited guests, including more women.</p>
        <p>Artists like Sue Williams, Kathe Burkhart, Sarah Lucas, Karen Kilimnik and Ms. Bacher get credit for cultivating dystopic visions before the current crop of young men, and every gallery contains a combination of new and older work. Contemporary needn't mean today; artistic discontent has a long history. It includes, for example, Richard Hamilton's 1967 news-clip collage about the Rolling Stones' drug bust; works from the 1970s by the Los Angelinos Paul McCarthy, Chris Burden and Jack Goldstein; and the famously antiroyal montages of Queen Elizabeth II by the British graphic designer Jamie Reid, one of which appeared on a Sex Pistols album cover.</p>
        <p>There are some telling juxtapositions. J P Munro's shadowy little painting ''Goebbels Delivers Total War Speech'' (2003-4) is seen, literally, in the light of Mr. Goldstein's 1975 film loop of the Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer lion roaring repeatedly, as if on cue, like the frenzied crowd at a Nazi rally.</p>
        <p>One of Sean Landers's obsessively and abjectly confessional stream-of-consciousness drawings from 1991 finds an appropriate soundtrack in Jonathan Horowitz's recent audio piece ''Talking Without Thinking,'' an excruciatingly incoherent monologue that the artist imagines was spoken in 1980 by George W. Bush while he was very much under the influence. Nearby, Ms. Williams's 1992 painting ''Your Bland Essence'' trades grotesqueries with Jake and Dinos Chapman's 1997 mannequin sculpture ''Disasters of Yoga.''</p>
        <p>This show is so dourly antidecorative and didactic that it becomes a bit tedious. If you emerge feeling beat up, proceed directly to ''The Gold Standard,'' where the filthy lucre is used to give radiant form to a jaundiced view. That is, once you get past the stark dose of reality provided by Alfredo Jaar's short video ''Introduction to a Distant World,'' in which laborers struggle up the steep paths of an open-pit South African gold mine, carrying bags of mud.</p>
        <p>This show was organized by the artist Walead Beshty and P.S. 1's longtime curatorial adviser, Bob Nickas, and installed on creamy yellow walls. It glows like treasure and seems perfect at a moment when investing in contemporary art is irrationally considered almost as good as investing in gold. A work from 1970-71 by Marcel Broodthaers draws the comparison with terse directness, using an excellent facsimile of a small gold ingot. Thomas Demand makes the point more obliquely with a photograph of sleek, fake bullion.</p>
        <p>But really, it is a little scary how good gold, real or not, makes almost everything look and how it colors experience. For further adventures in its raw, seductive power and use throughout history, I recommend ''Gold,'' an exhibition at the American Museum of Natural History. Both gold shows make the same point: If you accept the postmodern premise that value is a transitory attribute that humans arbitrarily assign to things, including art, gold may make you think again. It is not by chance that mankind became obsessed with gold rather than iron or bronze. It gives off light, is the most malleable metal, exists in nature in a pure state and, all told, makes a strong case for inherent value.</p>
        <p>But gold -- present at P.S. 1 as paint, foil, gilt or leaf -- also heightens awareness of value, and today most artists use it with subversive intent. Andy Warhol, represented here by gold-leaf drawings from his commercial art days, is a frequent reference, whether in the copy of Warhol's gold tondos of Marilyn Monroe by Sturtevant, the well-known pioneer appropriation artist from the '60s, or in Louise Lawler's photographs of the real thing at Christie's, on their way to auction.</p>
        <p>Some high points include Terence Koh's ''Bottle Rack,'' which pays homage to Duchamp with a small, somewhat excremental mountain of gold leaf spiked with wood skewers and crosses; Kurt Hendrickson's large embroidered silk screen, which appears to insert the Ku Klux Klan into Colonial America; Andisheh Avini's marquetry (plastic) skull; and Jessica Diamond's large, enigmatic wall drawing/poem, ''Ode to a Bamboo Triangle.''</p>
        <p>Compared with ''Defamation,'' ''The Gold Standard'' is visually exhilarating, but both exhibitions leave an unpleasant taste in the mouth -- one worth thinking about.</p>
        <p>After all the carefully orchestrated doom and glitter of these two shows, ''Altered, Stitched and Gathered'' has a breakout feeling. It spurns the coherent for the motley, following the use of found material in several directions at once. (Including a recent front page of The New York Times Weekend section, redrawn by Serkan Ozkaya.)</p>
        <p>This show was organized by Christopher Y. Lew, Erica Papernik and Elna Svenle, members of P.S. 1's junior curatorial staff, with Jelena Kristic as project director. Their 26 selections operate in the wide gap between modernist assemblage and postmodern appropriation, with references to Fluxus (Yoko Ono and Ben Vautier) and streetwise collage (the French poster artist Jaques Villeglé) thrown in for good measure.</p>
        <p>The materials used range from e-mail messages (the basis of Emily Jacir's small paintings) and presidential addresses (all of Ronald Reagan, restaged and read by Sharon Hayes), to discarded clothes and whatnot (gathered into a hovering storm cloud by Shinique Smith) and new plastic clothes hangers from Wal-Mart (assembled into a black and white striped tower by Jacob Dahlgren). One of the most hilarious alterations is by Rä di Martino, who has reduced ''Rambo'' to a three-minute silent movie, complete with tinkling piano accompaniment, dialogue cards and accelerated action.</p>
        <p>While El Anatsui's ''Society Woman's Cloth,'' a glorious wall hanging made entirely of aluminum liquor bottle caps and copper wire, would have fit right into the ''Gold'' show, Ted Riederer's ''Resurrectionists'' provides the perfect bridge to the final show, ''Music Is a Better Noise.'' It consists of video of a rock band smashing its instruments to smithereens and one of the destroyed electric guitars, reconstituted shard by shard.</p>
        <p>Nearly all the artists in ''Music'' are under- or above-ground musicians, which is to say that the show is all over the map stylistically. It occupies two galleries selected by different curators. Nick Stillman, an artist-curator-critic and another of P.S. 1's new curatorial advisers, has overseen a three-artist, dark-to-light progression. It starts with the fetish-crucifix wall sculptures of Alan Vega of the 1970s electric-punk band Suicide; proceeds through the atmospheric pinhole photographs of Barbara Ess, who has recorded with Y Pants, the Static, Ultra Vulva and Radio Guitar; and ends with the sparkling assemblages of the rapper Rammellzee, whose latest efforts include a clever, shrinelike recycling of images, cardboard and action figures titled ''Fame Cube.''</p>
        <p>The second gallery, selected by Mr. Nickas, is populated by several generations of the musically inclined: the singer-songwriter-draftsman Devendra Banhart; Don Van Vliet, a Neo-Expressionist painter by day and Captain Beefheart by night; and Thurston Moore and Kim Gordon of Sonic Youth. Ms. Gordon's black glitter paintings hang next to the work of (and might almost have been created by) Jutta Koether, the underground musician-painter who is represented by a sampling of silver and black artworks.</p>
        <p>Other artists who, like Ms. Koether, straddle both spheres with equal ease include Christian Marclay, Kai Althoff and Richard Aldrich, an erstwhile producer, as well as Chuck Nanney, whose quiet music-and-light installation in a nearby stairwell is one of the show's best moments. Another is the digital scan collage of Meredyth Sparks, whose blown-up images of the singer Ian Curtis of the band Joy Division evoke the allure and generosity of performing live music through the simple addition of two long, narrow silvery strips trailing from Mr. Curtis's eyes.</p>
        <p>''Defamation of Character'' and ''The Gold Standard'' are on view through Jan. 15; ''Altered, Stitched and Gathered,'' through Jan. 22; and ''Music Is a Better Noise,'' through Jan. 29. All are at P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens; (718) 784-2084.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 3, 2007, Wednesday  An art review in Weekend on Friday about four shows at the P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center in Queens misstated the name of the artist who has a large embroidered silk screen in the ''Gold Standard'' show. He is Kent Henricksen, not Kurt Hendrickson.</p>
        <p>The review also misidentified the country in which workers at a gold mine are shown in a short video by Alfredo Jaar called ''Introduction to a Distant World.'' It is Brazil, not South Africa.</p>
        <p>It also misstated the year that Neville Wakefield, who put together the ''Defamation of Character'' show, became a curatorial adviser at P.S. 1. It was at the beginning of 2006, not the beginning of 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 3, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An art review in Weekend on Friday about four shows at the P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center in Queens misstated the name of the artist who has a large embroidered silk screen in the ''Gold Standard'' show. He is Kent Henricksen, not Kurt Hendrickson.</p>
        <p>The review also misidentified the country in which workers at a gold mine are shown in a short video by Alfredo Jaar called ''Introduction to a Distant World.'' It is Brazil, not South Africa.</p>
        <p>It also misstated the year that Neville Wakefield, who put together the ''Defamation of Character'' show, became a curatorial adviser at P.S. 1. It was at the beginning of 2006, not the beginning of 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
