<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Yale, Remembering a Slain Undergraduate</title>
    <meta content="11YALE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ravo, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jovin, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DB113AF932A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Yale, Remembering a Slain Undergraduate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK RAVO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ravo, Nick</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, Dec. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several hundred friends and relatives of murdered Yale University student Suzanne Jovin attend memorial service for her at Battell Chapel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bitter wind carried sobs of grief, mournful farewells and the funereal tones of Bach through Old Campus at Yale  today, as several hundred friends and relatives of Suzanne Jovin, the senior who was slain last Friday not far from the university, gathered at  Battell Chapel for a memorial service.</p>
        <p>The New Haven police said they have no suspects in the killing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A bitter wind carried sobs of grief, mournful farewells and the funereal tones of Bach through Old Campus at Yale  today, as several hundred friends and relatives of Suzanne Jovin, the senior who was slain last Friday not far from the university, gathered at  Battell Chapel for a memorial service.</p>
        <p>The New Haven police said they have no suspects in the killing.</p>
        <p>A Yale lecturer who was Ms. Jovin's adviser, James Van de Velde,  told The New Haven Register that he had been questioned twice by the police, but he denied that he was involved in the slaying.</p>
        <p>''I'm an innocent person,'' Mr. Van de Velde said in today's issue of The Register. ''I hope in a week from now there will be a story on the real killer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Van de Velde did not return a message left on his answering machine.</p>
        <p>The developments in Ms. Jovin's killing come on the heels of another case that has disturbed the Yale campus, the accusations against Antonio C. Lasaga, a Yale geology professor who last month was charged with possessing child pornography retrieved from the Internet.</p>
        <p>According to published reports, Mr. Lasaga was re-arrested on Wednesday after Federal agents testified that he had been spotted near the home of a minor who was a victim in the case, a violation of the conditions for his release. Officials did not say how the child was related to the case.</p>
        <p>Today, the focus at Yale was not so much on the facts of the killing of Ms. Jovin, who was found stabbed to death on a street in the East Rock neighborhood, about two miles from her home off campus. Instead, thanks to a speaker system set up on the Old Campus green, the air was filled with remembrances of Ms. Jovin, a 21-year-old political science major from Gottingen, Germany.</p>
        <p>''My wife and I gave Suzanne the gift of her life -- it was taken away last week by the act of a wanton and senseless individual,'' said her father, Thomas Jovin, who faltered at times through his speech.</p>
        <p>About 500 students, teachers, university officials, family members, and friends attended the hour-and-a-half memorial service at the chapel.</p>
        <p>Mourners blinked away tears when a friend read a tribute from one of the people who knew Ms. Jovin from the Yale chapter of Best Buddies, a program she ran that pairs mentally disabled people with students. Ms. Jovin was making pizzas with the group an hour before she was killed.</p>
        <p>''Suzanne was a sweet person and a good friend who did a lot for me -- she always helped me feel better when I was stressed,'' said a letter from Ms. Jovin's Best Buddy, Lee Brown, that was read by Rebecca Rosen, a Yale senior.</p>
        <p>In tributes printed in Wednesday's Yale Daily News, Ms. Jovin was remembered as an energetic, optimistic woman dedicated to helping others. One of those tributes came from Mr. Van de Velde.</p>
        <p>''When I met Suzanne this past September,'' he wrote, ''I was immediately taken by her deep enthusiasm for life, her infectious positive outlook, her insightfulness, and her commitment to learning. She inspired me with her enthusiasm and her interest in making a difference in the world. She is someone I will always remember.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
