<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INSIDE ART</title>
    <meta content="11INSI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Getty, J Paul, Museum</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schaefer, Scott J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saatchi, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9103AF932A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INSIDE ART</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; 130 contemporary works of art from Charles Saatchi's collection are sold by Christie's in London this past week; some odd works noted; photo; Scott J Schaefer will become paintings curator for J Paul Getty Museum (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Organs of Cows? Young Art Sells</p>
        <p>A naked polyester baby boy, a polished steel gun, a man's suit shot through with holes and four cabinets containing assorted jars of cows' organs were among the 130 works by 97 contemporary artists that were sold by Christie's in London on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Organs of Cows? Young Art Sells</p>
        <p>A naked polyester baby boy, a polished steel gun, a man's suit shot through with holes and four cabinets containing assorted jars of cows' organs were among the 130 works by 97 contemporary artists that were sold by Christie's in London on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>This wasn't just any auction of contemporary art. It represented about 5 percent of Charles Saatchi's famed collection. Mr. Saatchi, the advertising magnate who is one of London's biggest contemporary art collectors, has been able to use his promotional skills to market and sell his art over the years.</p>
        <p>The auction was for a good cause. Its proceeds will be used, in part, to set up a scholarship program to help pay for students' projects and commissions at four London art schools: Chelsea, Goldsmiths', the Royal College and the Slade. The money will also help pay for the projects of young British artists who have left college. The benefits will not all flow in one direction. Some of these artists will also show their work at Mr. Saatchi's gallery on Boundary Road in the St. John's Wood section of London, and he may buy their work.</p>
        <p>The sale took place in an abandoned warehouse in London's financial district, a space that could better accommodate the large scale of some of the pieces than could Christie's more intimate salesrooms at its King Street headquarters. The auction's sales totaled $2.6 million, $1 million more than Christie's estimate, proving that the market for young art is booming.</p>
        <p>Much of the sale's art was by leading ''Y.B.A.'s,'' or Young British Artists, like Damien Hirst, Rachel Whiteread and Jenny Saville. Also on the block were works by contemporary American artists like Cindy Sherman, Charles Long, Jessica Stockholder and Kiki Smith.</p>
        <p>Over the years Mr. Saatchi has helped create a booming market for many of the artists he buys, in part by showing them at his 13-year-old gallery. But last year he received worldwide attention when he lent 120 works, all by young British artists, for ''Sensation,'' a show at the Royal Academy in London that attracted record-breaking crowds. It has since traveled to Berlin and is at the Hamburger Bahnhof through Jan. 17. (Experts in the museum world say the Brooklyn Museum of Art will  mount the show some time next year, although officials there said it was too early to confirm that.)</p>
        <p>But even as Mr. Saatchi has been credited with boosting sales of contemporary artists, he has occasionally sold some artists' works in bulk, causing their prices and desirability to plummet. As a result, before Tuesday's sale many experts said Mr. Saatchi was taking a big gamble.</p>
        <p>If so, the gamble paid off. Prices for many artists reached more than twice the pre-sale estimates. Some of the high prices were for works by artists who had never been at auction before. Among the top sellers was ''Grosse Geister,'' a group of three larger-than-life robotlike aluminum figures from 1996 by the cerebral German sculptor Thomas Schutte, which sold to an unidentified London dealer for $245,000, above its $200,000 high estimate.</p>
        <p>Past and present winners of the coveted Turner Prize, an award given annually by the Tate Gallery in London to a contemporary British artist, performed well. Mr. Hirst, the 1995 winner, broke a record for his pharmaceutical paintings when ''Acetic Anhydride,'' a 1991 example, sold to an unidentified telephone bidder for $202,125, nearly five times its $42,000 high estimate. Mr. Hirst's ''Lovers (Spontaneous, Committed, Detached, Compromising),'' a series of four cabinets containing jars of cows' organs, sold to another unidentified telephone bidder for $229,350, far above its $170,000 high estimate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Whiteread, who won the Turner Prize in 1993 and has received much attention in New York for the translucent resin water tower that was installed on a SoHo rooftop this summer, scored a record price for her work, too. Her ''Untitled (Square Sink),'' a 1990 negative plaster cast of a sink, sold for $220,275, nearly three times its $84,000 high estimate. A record price for work by Chris Ofili, this year's Turner Prize winner, was set when his ''Them Bones,'' a 1995 painting of a skeleton holding in each hand balls of the artist's signature elephant dung, brought $36,052, more than twice its $17,000 high estimate.</p>
        <p>''Nearly 4,000 people visited the viewing,'' said Graham Southern, who heads Christie's contemporary art department in London. ''And about 50 percent of the people had never been to an auction before.''  Christie's said 74.8 percent of the buyers were European and of those, 39.1 percent were British. Americans represented 24.6 percent of the buying pool and Asians 2.9 percent.</p>
        <p>''Certainly 'Sensation' helped,'' Mr. Southern said, adding that excitement over the construction of the Tate Gallery of Modern Art, scheduled to open in 2000, also motivated buyers. ''It's now obvious to the public that these artists are making a place in history,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A $3.6 Million Richter</p>
        <p>While few buyers at the Saatchi sale were identified, one of the most conspicuous consumers at another notable auction in London this week was the Pritzker family, who bought Gerhard Richter's ''Cathedral Square, Milan'' (1968) at Sotheby's sale of contemporary art on Wednesday. It is the largest of his photo paintings from the 60's -- 9 feet by 9 1/2 feet -- and shows the Piazza del Duomo.</p>
        <p>The Pritzkers paid $3.6 million, nearly twice the work's $1.98 million high estimate. The family plans to put it in the lobby of their Park Hyatt Hotel, which is being built on Michigan Avenue in Chicago. But until the hotel is completed, a Sotheby's official said, the family will lend the painting to the Art Institute of Chicago, which has the largest collection of Richters in America.</p>
        <p>A Curator for the Getty</p>
        <p>After a six month search, the J. Paul Getty Museum announced that Scott J. Schaefer, an expert in Sotheby's Old Master department, would be the its new curator of paintings.  He succeeds David A. Jaffe, who resigned in September to become senior curator at the National Gallery in London. Mr. Schaefer begins his new job early next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
