<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Maverick, Of the Violin and Generally</title>
    <meta content="30KENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Personal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Nigel Kennedy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy (Nigel Kennedy)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Personal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DB173FF933A05753C1A96E958260" item-length="2566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Maverick, Of the Violin and Generally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>English violinist Nigel Kennedy, returning to classical stage after five-year absence working on rock projects, has dropped first name from billings; comments on change that irks British critics, interview; photos; current US tour includes performances with New York Philharmonic and recital at Avery Fisher Hall (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Probably the first thing to know about the English violinist Nigel Kennedy is that having returned to the classical concert stage after a five-year self-imposed exile, during which he worked almost exclusively on rock projects, he is no longer using his first name. In the tradition of Madonna, Prince (in his pre-glyph days) and the British pianist Solomon, he is now listed on concert programs and recordings simply as Kennedy. At the end of his program note for a recent Elgar recording, he added: ''P.S. I've changed my name because I never liked the name Nigel. Cheers!''</p>
        <p>The second thing to know, though, is that he doesn't really mind being called Nigel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Probably the first thing to know about the English violinist Nigel Kennedy is that having returned to the classical concert stage after a five-year self-imposed exile, during which he worked almost exclusively on rock projects, he is no longer using his first name. In the tradition of Madonna, Prince (in his pre-glyph days) and the British pianist Solomon, he is now listed on concert programs and recordings simply as Kennedy. At the end of his program note for a recent Elgar recording, he added: ''P.S. I've changed my name because I never liked the name Nigel. Cheers!''</p>
        <p>The second thing to know, though, is that he doesn't really mind being called Nigel.</p>
        <p>''I suppose it was partially a contemptuous thing to do, to rile the British critics,'' Kennedy said during a recent stopover in New York, before starting a tour that includes a run of performances with the New York Philharmonic and a recital at Avery Fisher Hall this weekend. Wearing a torn and faded Disney T-shirt, a frayed leather jacket, nondescript work pants and two-tone hair (brown and blond), Kennedy, who is 41, sat on the lawn in Central Park and reflected on the fallout from this minor provocation.</p>
        <p>''I was amused that certain people were calling me arrogant for calling myself only one name,'' he said, ''but they never questioned their own arrogance in telling me how I should call myself. But I don't care what people call me.''</p>
        <p>And there you have a defining glimpse of the artist formerly known as Nigel. A product of both the Yehudi Menuhin School and the Juilliard School, he built his career on producing a sound that can be ear-catchingly bracing or uncommonly beautiful and on performances that are sometimes illuminating and sometimes wayward but that consistently bear the imprint of a willful, original interpreter.</p>
        <p>No one could accuse him of being risk-averse. When he recorded Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons'' in 1987, he added some extremely idiosyncratic touches, among them a wildly modernist violin overlay in the slow movement of the ''Autumn'' Concerto and cadenzas linking several movements. Critical brickbats notwithstanding, the recording sold more than a million copies.</p>
        <p>Since then, Kennedy has made a game of thumbing his nose at the classical music world. He gave up wearing concert dress, preferring punk fashion and a variety of trendy haircuts. Reviewing his last performance in New York, in 1992, Bernard Holland of The New York Times wrote, ''With his coonskin-cap haircut, patched jacket, flowing scarf, running shoes and amazing parti-colored socks, Mr. Kennedy moved among the tail-coated members of the New York Philharmonic like a myna bird among penguins.'' In England, he has been known to wave the colors of his favorite soccer team, Aston Villa, during performances.</p>
        <p>But baiting critics is only one of his joys. He also likes to keep everyone around him guessing what he'll do next. Arriving at his hotel for a midafternoon interview, for example, a visitor encountered delegations from Columbia Artists (his managers), EMI (his record label) and the Philharmonic, all waiting in the lobby because Kennedy had decided to shower at the time of his appointments. Eventually he bounded out of an elevator, aggressively cheerful but firm about seemingly arbitrary ground rules.</p>
        <p>''I no longer do posed shots,'' he told a photographer, meaning he had no intention of being photographed with his violin; he had no problem, however, posing with a hot dog he bought from a street vendor. He rebuffed a manager's invitation to dinner, suggesting a phone call instead, and was unfazed by how his idea of being interviewed in Central Park -- he said he had cabin fever -- threw the emissaries from the business world into mild disarray, since they had planned further meetings with him later in the day.</p>
        <p>''Oh well, you'll find us,'' he said, and wandered out to Seventh Avenue. His nattily dressed entourage trailed along in the hope of fixing his location, using their cellular telephones to leave messages about their own whereabouts.</p>
        <p>Because Kennedy is eminently marketable and sells lots of records, no one is about to tell him to behave differently. And there would be no point in trying; his five-year hiatus, from 1992 to 1997, was his response to efforts by his managers and record label to persuade him to play the classical music game more conventionally.</p>
        <p>In particular, they wanted him to focus on classical projects and soft-pedal his interest in rock and jazz. But Kennedy, who grew up in Brighton and now lives near Bristol, has always been drawn to popular music. As a 14-year-old student at the Menuhin School, he spent his weekends playing jazz with Stephane Grappelli, and soon after he went to Juilliard at 16, he was sitting in with Stan Getz. The day he made his first recital album, in 1984, he also recorded a collection of standards. On one of his albums, works by Bartok and Ellington sit side by side. And since the late 80's, he has played on recordings by Kate Bush, Paul McCartney, Talk Talk and the Stranglers and has made two jazz-fusion albums of his own material, ''Let Loose'' and ''Kafka.''</p>
        <p>''When I said I was leaving classical music,'' he said, ''it was an exaggeration, a way to get people around me to understand that I was going to have another side to my musical life and that it was going to be a big part of it. And I had to believe that myself. At the time I was on the verge of making 'Kafka.' If that album hadn't seemed satisfactory to me, I would have carried on and made another one, and then another after that until I had made something I could stand on. So it was a kind of indefinite period that I was going to be away from classical music, or at least the public performance of it. Because I carried on playing Bach and other things.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy's programs for this weekend suggest that he may have found the balance he wants. With the Philharmonic, he is playing the Elgar Violin Concerto, a work he has recorded twice. The first recording, with Vernon Handley conducting, established Kennedy as a young violinist to watch when it was released in 1984. The second, conducted by Sir Simon Rattle and released last year, was his return to classical recording, and it has a breadth and fluidity that the earlier account lacked.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't consciously trying to do anything differently,'' he said. ''But I think music is a voyage of self-discovery and also discovery of other people -- namely, the composers. You don't want to play the same way many times. Even within a couple of weeks, it doesn't have to be the same, and after 12 years you hope you have new enlightenment. My first recording -- I think it was a decent album but a little too close to the textbook in nature. Now I think I'm more attracted to the emotional moments in the music.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy's recital at Avery Fisher fills out the picture. Half of his program is devoted to demanding unaccompanied works by Bach and Bartok. The program's centerpiece, though, is Kennedy's tribute to Jimi Hendrix, a chamber work he is calling ''Concerto in Suite Form.'' The work is based on five Jimi Hendrix songs -- ''1983 . . . (A Merman I Should Turn to Be),'' ''Third Stone From the Sun,'' ''Drifting,'' ''Little Wing'' and ''Purple Haze'' -- and ''Hey Joe,'' the Billy Roberts song that Hendrix recorded as his first single.</p>
        <p>''I relate to Jimi Hendrix's material very strongly,'' Kennedy explained, ''because he had such big ears for so many different types of music. You can hear germs of jazz harmony, rhythm-and-blues, even a Celtic feeling in the melody structure. What I've done is deconstructed his compositions and put them together in a totally different type of way. I've written out the parts for the other players, and I'm out there on a free mission, so to speak, in the same way that Jimi had lots of well-sorted-out rhythms going on that enabled him to be free. But that's probably where the similarity ends.</p>
        <p>''The melodic and harmonic structures will be recognizable, but it will be very much an acoustic feel -- although it's funny, because by using the bow down at the bridge of the violin you can get all those feedback kind of sounds that Jimi used to get. But you can do it in the quietest, most personal moments. It's almost the inverse of the way Jimi used feedback to heighten everything.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy has tackled Hendrix before. In 1993, he contributed a high-energy reading of ''Fire'' to ''Stone Free'' (Reprise), a tribute album that also includes performances by the Cure, Eric Clapton, the Spin Doctors, Living Colour and the Pretenders. Now he is about to record the Concerto in Suite Form, and he said the recording was likely to differ from the version he is playing live. In concert, he will use only his 1735 Guarneri; in the studio, he will also use an electric violin and is talking about adding elements influenced by current English bands he likes, most notably Portishead, Massive Attack and Radiohead.</p>
        <p>''His recording plans are a little mysterious,'' said Roger Evans, a spokesman for EMI who ended up in Kennedy's parade to Central Park. ''He's talking about making an album that will be called 'Klassic Kennedy' -- classic with a K -- which I guess will have the Hendrix on it, but I don't know what else. He isn't telling us much. I hope I don't read about it in the paper first.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy, when asked about his recording plans, was hardly tight-lipped. ''Klassic Kennedy'' -- he plans to change the name -- is to be an album of short classical works that he has arranged for violin and orchestra. The Hendrix project is something else.</p>
        <p>''The Hendrix isn't going to be on EMI,'' he said. ''They think it is, but it isn't, because I'm contractually free, and I'm irritated after 10 years of trying to get them to adequately represent my music outside the classical arena. Not so much the American office but the English office has been on the verge of obstructing it. They put out 'Let Loose,' which was fine, and 'Kafka.' But I really didn't find the same enthusiasm for it as if I had done 'Vivaldi 2' or something. Because I've sold a few copies of classical music -- mainly things like the 'Four Seasons' -- they see me as an immature artist doing frivolous projects that gets in the way of what they might have as a preconceived marketing formula for me.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy's view of the pop world is not much more sanguine. Just as his nonconformist antics have made him a lightning rod in the classical press, his incursions into pop have drawn attacks from that side of the business. The irreverent rock magazine Q skewered him mercilessly a few years ago, and John Peel, the influential BBC disk jockey, spoke dismissively of his rock efforts.</p>
        <p>''The music business is format-orientated, largely for the convenience of the record companies that are trying to sell it,'' Kennedy said with a diplomatic calmness when reminded of these slights. ''And in pop, they get just as upset as they do on the classical side when someone tries to rock the boat. Someone like John Peel has done great things for music in Britain, but nevertheless, he does tend only to be into bands that sulk and come in dressed in black. So I'm viewed as classical, and somehow that's threatening. Anyone who does what I do and tries to come into their world is going to get flak.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most surprising thing about Kennedy is that beneath his distaste for the music business and beyond his provocative responses to it, he is really an old-fashioned Romantic. That comes through in the broad coloristic palette and luminous phrasing of his second Elgar Concerto recording.</p>
        <p>And it is clearer still on his latest disk, a collection of works by Fritz Kreisler in which he confounds the listener's expectations by playing such chestnuts as ''Liebeslied'' and ''Tamborin Chinois'' with warmth and suppleness while stripping away the interpretive treacle that has accrued to them over the decades. And whenever the conversation turns to the music that moves him, he drops his guard entirely.</p>
        <p>''This 'Klassic Kennedy' album, for want of a better title,'' he said, ''is the kind of music I've never really done on record before. It's not virtuoso fodder, which I really don't relate to, but more melodic stuff, which I really love. Things like Satie and Chopin, maybe 'The Flight of the Bumblebee,' and some Sarasate, where Gypsy music meets the violin. That's what fills my heart well enough to represent it with true passion. I'm looking for things that have something more than the pyrotechnic quick route to impressing people.</p>
        <p>''The Kreisler is similar in a way. Sometimes I think people represent Kreisler's short works as virtuoso showpieces too easily. I'm not interested in them from that vantage point. I just love the timeless quality of the music, the golden spirit which comes through, and I hope that in my own way I've captured some of that essence. My goal was not to copy the way Kreisler played them or recreate what he did, in the same way that when I'm interpreting Hendrix, I don't care what solo he played. I'm playing them my own way.''</p>
        <p>The 2 Programs</p>
        <p>Kennedy's program with the New York Philharmonic includes Elgar's Violin Concerto, completed in 1910. A deeply personal work with nostalgic themes and impassioned bursts of solo and orchestral writing, it is the kind of music in which Kennedy delights. Kennedy's fondness for Elgar is shared by Leonard Slatkin, who is conducting the performances. The program also includes Haydn's Symphony No. 99 and Barber's ''Capricorn'' Concerto, with three Philharmonic members -- Joseph Robinson, the principal oboist; Sandra Church, the associate principal flutist, and Philip Smith, the co-principal trumpeter -- playing the solo lines. Today at 2 P.M., tomorrow at 8 P.M. and Tuesday at 7:30 P.M., Avery Fisher Hall, Centercharge, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $14 to $73.</p>
        <p>In his recital, Kennedy will play the Bach Adagio and Fugue from Sonata No. 3 in C (BWV 1005) and Bartok's four-movement Sonata for Solo Violin. The real curiosity, though, is the New York premiere of Kennedy's own ''Concerto in Suite Form,'' a work based on Jimi Hendrix songs and scored for solo violin, double bass, cello, bass flute, oboe, two guitars and a vocalist who also plays African percussion instruments. Sunday at 7 P.M., Avery Fisher Hall, Centercharge, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $20 to $40.</p>
        <p>ALLAN KOZINN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
