<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>French Said to Hurt Plan to Capture Karadzic</title>
    <meta content="T23SER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karadzic, Radovan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gourmillon, Herve (Maj)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED9143FF930A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>French Said to Hurt Plan to Capture Karadzic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senior US and Western officials say planning for possible capture of Bosnian Serb leader Radovan Karadzic was set back late last summer after US officials discovered that French military officer, Maj Herve Gourmillon, had held secret meetings with Karadzic and French were covering it up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Planning for the possible capture of the Bosnian Serb leader, Radovan Karadzic, was badly set back late last summer after United States officials discovered that a French military officer had held secret meetings with Dr. Karadzic and the French were covering it up, senior American and Western officials said late today.</p>
        <p>The officials said the incident badly damaged the trust between the American and French military planners who had to work together if Dr. Karadzic, who is wanted on war crimes charges in The Hague, was to be captured from his stronghold in Pale, which is in the French sector of Bosnia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Planning for the possible capture of the Bosnian Serb leader, Radovan Karadzic, was badly set back late last summer after United States officials discovered that a French military officer had held secret meetings with Dr. Karadzic and the French were covering it up, senior American and Western officials said late today.</p>
        <p>The officials said the incident badly damaged the trust between the American and French military planners who had to work together if Dr. Karadzic, who is wanted on war crimes charges in The Hague, was to be captured from his stronghold in Pale, which is in the French sector of Bosnia.</p>
        <p>The officials confirmed the details of the setback, which was first reported in Thursday's editions of The  Washington Post.</p>
        <p>But the officials said that even last summer, when the episode occurred, there had been no specific plan to capture Dr. Karadzic, only ''a planning process aimed at the capture of generic war criminals'' in Bosnia by the NATO-led troops there.</p>
        <p>''That process was badly impacted,'' one official said. But the officials denied reports that a major NATO operation specifically to capture Dr. Karadzic had been close to taking place and was then suspended.</p>
        <p>The secret meetings between the French officer, Maj. Herve Gourmillon, and Dr. Karadzic, deeply troubled the Americans and other NATO allies and undercut trust in the French military, the officials said.</p>
        <p>The French have acknowledged the meetings, according to the Post, but have said the officer acted on his own.</p>
        <p>The officials said that such planning is still under way, despite wariness about the French military, and they pointed to recent exercises where NATO-led troops occupied police headquarters and other buildings in Pale, measures which have helped drive Dr. Karadzic underground and limit his once-supreme influence over the Bosnian Muslims.</p>
        <p>But the officials also cautioned that a raid to capture Dr. Karadzic is not imminent.</p>
        <p>The officials also confirmed The Post's account that Major Gourmillon was reassigned to Paris, and that he suffered no punishment for his actions.</p>
        <p>This incident followed another dust-up between Washington and Paris in June of last year, when French military officials pulled out of active military planning for a raid to capture Dr. Karadzic because the American military was not willing to participate except for logistical and intelligence help.</p>
        <p>At the time, Dr. Karadzic's influence was stronger than it is now, and any effort to capture him was going to involve hundreds of commando troops and other soldiers and a significant risk that some of those soldiers would die.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
