<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Committee Releases 39,000 Tobacco Documents</title>
    <meta content="T23TOB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reynolds, R J, Tobacco Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meier, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EEDA143FF930A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Committee Releases 39,000 Tobacco Documents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meier, Barry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R J Reynolds Tobacco Co document prepared in 1985 by outside lawyers hired to review cigarette maker's legal defenses indicates that company destroyed records and suppressed research about cancer hazards and other toxic effects of smoking; document is one of 39,000 internal tobacco company records released by House Commerce Committee on April 22 after lengthy fight by companies to keep them confidential (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company document prepared in 1985 by outside lawyers hired to review the cigarette maker's legal defenses indicates that the company destroyed records and suppressed research about the cancer hazards and other toxic effects of smoking.</p>
        <p>The document, which lawyers for R. J. Reynolds defended as a routine legal review, was one of 39,000 internal tobacco company records released yesterday by the House Commerce Committee, after a lengthy fight by the companies to keep them confidential. The committee subpoenaed the records after the judge in a Minnesota lawsuit against tobacco companies ruled that the documents contain potential evidence of fraud and other crimes by cigarette company executives and their lawyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company document prepared in 1985 by outside lawyers hired to review the cigarette maker's legal defenses indicates that the company destroyed records and suppressed research about the cancer hazards and other toxic effects of smoking.</p>
        <p>The document, which lawyers for R. J. Reynolds defended as a routine legal review, was one of 39,000 internal tobacco company records released yesterday by the House Commerce Committee, after a lengthy fight by the companies to keep them confidential. The committee subpoenaed the records after the judge in a Minnesota lawsuit against tobacco companies ruled that the documents contain potential evidence of fraud and other crimes by cigarette company executives and their lawyers.</p>
        <p>The vast collection of records, an estimated 150,000 pages, was released over the Internet, but because of the volume and the records' disorganized state, it will take news organizations and interest groups days to sort through them. In Washington, meanwhile, lawmakers are trying to determine what effect, if any, the records might have on the current debate over tobacco legislation. Previously released records indicated that companies knew of the health hazards of cigarettes for decades and that some companies marketed their products to young teen-agers.</p>
        <p>R. J. Reynolds and other cigarette makers argued all the way to the Supreme Court this year that the records released yesterday should be barred from public disclosure because of attorney-client privilege. But the Court declined to review their appeal.</p>
        <p>An anti-tobacco lawmaker, Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, described the R. J. Reynolds document as painting an ''enormous and shocking picture.''</p>
        <p>Other lawmakers, however, said the new records, while potentially revealing, might add little to the now well-documented history of industry wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure that any new revelations, while troubling, will be particularly surprising,'' said Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, chairman of the Senate Commerce Committee and author of the pending tobacco bill. ''It has been well established that the tobacco industry has been dishonest and deceitful to Congress and the American people.''</p>
        <p>Along with lawmakers, lawyers for the Justice Department, which is pursuing a criminal investigation of tobacco makers, will be reviewing the records. And the new documents may provide new ammunition to smokers and states that are suing the cigarette producers.</p>
        <p>Lawyers representing the state of Minnesota, which is suing the tobacco industry to recover public money spent for smoking-related illnesses, have already begun to use the new records in that trial, which is under way in a St. Paul courtroom.</p>
        <p>Joel Seligman, dean of the University of Arizona law school, said documents that defense lawyers seek to suppress can be especially damaging if they subsequently are revealed in a courtroom.</p>
        <p>''When a lawyer says 'And here's another document that the tobacco industry didn't want you to see', that will hurt the case before a jury,'' said Dean Seligman.</p>
        <p>It was the 1985 R. J. Reynolds document that Minnesota state officials seized upon yesterday as evidence of a vast conspiracy between industry executives and their lawyers.</p>
        <p>''Tobacco lawyers, not scientists, were the gatekeepers controlling research on smoking and health and blocking important research that could have saved lives,'' said Hubert H. Humphrey 3d, the Attorney General of Minnesota.</p>
        <p>The document, prepared by the Cleveland law firm of Jones, Day, Reavis &amp; Pogue, reviewed the interaction of R. J. Reynolds researchers, executives and lawyers before 1985, when the Cleveland firm was hired to defend the company in smoking-related cases.</p>
        <p>The report notes, for example, that company lawyers rejected a 1978 request by an R. J. Reynolds researcher to investigate the potential of tobacco smoke to damage the genetic structure of cells because such work might help the ''other side'' in lawsuits. And the document also states that cigarette maker had a policy in the 1970's barring external publication of internal research about cancer hazards found in cigarettes as well as toxic substances like hydrogen cyanide and carbon monoxide, which are produced when tobacco burns.</p>
        <p>In addition, the paper, which was based in part on interview with company employees, also suggests that problem documents were destroyed at the order of company executives. An internal Reynolds document says that Allan Rodgman, a top company researcher, recalled destroying reports related to tests ''because of legal concerns with biological results with Camel cigarettes,'' which were used as controls in company research. In addition, the document refers to a 1975 report that was to be ''destroyed immediately after all top-level management'' had reviewed it.</p>
        <p>But John Strauch, a lawyer with the Cleveland firm, said the document was prepared at the time of its hiring by R. J. Reynolds in 1985 as a worst-case scenario to ''try and identify problem areas and other things that might be seized upon by the other side in the litigation.''</p>
        <p>Paul Crist, another lawyer with that firm, said Mr. Humphrey had mischaracterized the document because some records that the Minnesota official suggested were destroyed had been furnished to the state as part of its lawsuit. He pointed in particular to the Camel-related research document.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crist acknowledged that R. J. Reynolds, a unit of the RJR Nabisco Holding Corporation, did have procedures in place in the past to restrict the publication of certain scientific research. A 1971 document attached to the report explicitly lays out the ban on such publication.</p>
        <p>''There is no corporation in America that publishes every piece of research it conducts,'' Mr. Crist said.</p>
        <p>In the 1986 R. J. Reynolds document, company officials who were interviewed said that publication of research was often suppressed because of fears that the results might used by the industry's enemies.</p>
        <p>Some documents released yesterday also showed the involvement of cigarette company lawyers in research, a theme that has been struck before in other industry documents.</p>
        <p>One 1985 Brown &amp; Williamson Tobacco Corporation document stated that, in order to qualify for public release, all scientific documents related to smoking and health had to be reviewed by the top company executives and lawyers.</p>
        <p>In other documents, companies refer to keeping potentially sensitive documents in foreign countries. Regulators and plaintiffs' lawyers have argued that companies took such actions to make the data harder to find.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
