<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CUNY May Let Politicians Plan Remediation</title>
    <meta content="23CUNY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DD143FF930A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CUNY May Let Politicians Plan Remediation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Informed sources say that despite what appears to be growing consensus among many of trustees of City University of New York on plan to limit remedial education, they predict that no plan will be adopted at monthly board meeting because solution acceptable to both Mayor Rudy Giuliani and New York State Gov George Pataki has not yet been reached (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite what appeared to be a growing consensus among many of the trustees of the City University of New York on a plan to limit remedial education, some trustees predicted yesterday that no plan would be adopted at a monthly board meeting on Monday because a solution acceptable to both the Mayor and the Governor had not yet been reached.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the board's long-range planning committee yesterday, attended by 9 of the board's 17 trustees, a consensus seemed to emerge around a plan drawn up this week by CUNY's chairwoman, Anne A. Paolucci. That proposal would limit remediation to one semester at the senior colleges and one year at the community colleges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite what appeared to be a growing consensus among many of the trustees of the City University of New York on a plan to limit remedial education, some trustees predicted yesterday that no plan would be adopted at a monthly board meeting on Monday because a solution acceptable to both the Mayor and the Governor had not yet been reached.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the board's long-range planning committee yesterday, attended by 9 of the board's 17 trustees, a consensus seemed to emerge around a plan drawn up this week by CUNY's chairwoman, Anne A. Paolucci. That proposal would limit remediation to one semester at the senior colleges and one year at the community colleges.</p>
        <p>Such limits are more moderate than those in a previous version the board was considering, which would have eliminated remedial courses at the senior colleges. The imposition of any time limits, however, would still make CUNY unusual, since most public universities take in many students who need catch-up work in one or more subjects before they are ready to tackle college-level courses.</p>
        <p>Despite this, many of the trustees and college presidents at the long-range planning meeting yesterday said the new plan was an acceptable compromise, and that with minor changes, they could live with it. Edith Everett, a trustee, complemented Dr. Paolucci on assembling a consensus after weeks of deadlock.</p>
        <p>But some trustees said the plan falls far short of the more radical change that Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has been demanding, and, as a result, would not have the nine votes needed for passage. They said that Dr. Paolucci herself, who was appointed chairwoman by Gov. George E. Pataki, would most likely follow Mr. Pataki's lead once he and Mr. Giuliani had agreed on a plan.</p>
        <p>The Mayor appoints 5 trustees and the Governor 10, and the students and faculty each have one representative on the board, although the faculty trustee does not vote.</p>
        <p>The Mayor has said repeatedly that CUNY's standards are too low, and that all remedial instruction should be conducted by a private company or by another university, not by CUNY. He has also urged that students be barred from the university until they have completed all remedial work. The proposals being discussed by CUNY's trustees so far would allow students to take remedial courses at the colleges under CUNY's direction.</p>
        <p>One person close to the Mayor's negotiations over CUNY, who spoke on the condition that he not be identified, said that the Mayor and the Governor were discussing a plan that would impose a stricter limit on remediation at the senior colleges, following the Baruch College model, which calls for ending all remedial courses but providing extra tutorial help to students who need it.</p>
        <p>He said that what would happen at the community colleges was less clear, but that a decision on that front might be postponed while the Mayor and Governor keep searching for a mutually acceptable plan.</p>
        <p>The Governor's office said yesterday evening that no one was available to comment because of work on the budget.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Paolucci said in a telephone interview that the remedial plan was still a work in progress, and that what is put before the board on Monday may look different from this week's plan. She also said that a vote might need to be put off to allow the public to comment on a new version.</p>
        <p>''It is really not clear yet,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
