<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the Fighting Men Felt About the Civil War</title>
    <meta content="06HAUP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BOOKS OF THE TIMES" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="913570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcpherson, James M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">For Cause and Comrades (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3DF1230F935A35750C0A961958260" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the Fighting Men Felt About the Civil War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christopher Lehmann-Haupt reviews book For Cause and Comrades: Why Men Fought in the Civil War, by James M McPherson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR CAUSE AND COMRADES  Why Men Fought in the Civil War  By James M. McPherson  237 pages. Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>The question must occur to anyone who stands on a deserted battlefield. It came to James M. McPherson when he took a group of his students to Gettysburg, Pa. Mr. McPherson teaches American history at Princeton and has written 11 books on the Civil War era, including ''Battle Cry of Freedom'' (1988), which won a Pulitzer Prize for history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR CAUSE AND COMRADES  Why Men Fought in the Civil War  By James M. McPherson  237 pages. Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>The question must occur to anyone who stands on a deserted battlefield. It came to James M. McPherson when he took a group of his students to Gettysburg, Pa. Mr. McPherson teaches American history at Princeton and has written 11 books on the Civil War era, including ''Battle Cry of Freedom'' (1988), which won a Pulitzer Prize for history.</p>
        <p>When he walked with his students over the ground where Pickett's Charge took place and spoke of ''those 13,000 Confederate soldiers'' who ''had come under artillery and then rifle fire almost every step of the way,'' his students asked in awe: ''What made these men do it? What motivated them to advance into that wall of fire? What caused them to go forward despite the high odds against coming out safely?'' The seed was planted that grew into ''For Cause and Comrades: Why Men Fought in the Civil War.''</p>
        <p>To answer these questions, Mr. McPherson read unpublished letters and diaries written by 1,076 soldiers, 647 Union and 429 Confederate. This may seem a highly selective approach, but, as the author points out, Civil War soldiers were unusually literate (if unpredictable at spelling), their letters were not censored,  and his sampling is highly representative of all the men who fought. If any bias occurs, he says, it is ''toward native-born soldiers from the middle and upper classes who enlisted early in the war,'' and this skewing serves Mr. McPherson's purpose, because these are the men ''who did the real fighting.''</p>
        <p>What he found surprising and contrary to conventional wisdom is the extent to which Civil War soldiers were aware of the big issues of the war. Newspapers were widely read, he reports. Debates were held in winter quarters. Both sides were conscious of what he calls ''the heritage of 1776'' and interpreted it in opposite ways: the South to justify avoiding ''subjugation'' and maintaining the freedom to enslave; the North to preserve the nation conceived in liberty from dismemberment and destruction.</p>
        <p>''I do feel that the liberty of the world is placed in our hands to defend,'' Mr. McPherson quotes a private in the 33d Massachusetts Infantry as writing in 1862, ''and if we are overcome then farewell to freedom.'' In the Civil War, patriotism was ''not the last refuge of the scoundrel,'' Mr. McPherson concludes; ''it was the credo of the fighting soldier.''</p>
        <p>Of course, such high-blown sentiments are relatively easy to feel in reflective moments of letter writing. As one soldier remarked in his diary after the Battle of the Wilderness: ''When I first started on the charge this morning I felt that I could fight &amp;  do any thing for my bleeding country. But after I had got out the first time my patriotism had died &amp; I thought of nothing but to keep clear of the enemy's bullets -- zip, zip, zipping around me.'' What sustained the soldier then, one wonders.</p>
        <p>Mr. McPherson is respectful of the difference between anticipating battle and experiencing it, between wanting to ''see the elephant,'' a contemporary expression for ''any awesome but exciting experience,'' and the shock of actually doing so. ''Mary I went into the fight in good hart,'' an Ohio soldier wrote after his first big battle, ''but I never want to get in another it was offal $(awful$) mary you cant form any idy how it was the bulets and cannon ball and shells flew thick as hail.''</p>
        <p>In the crunch, an indifference to  fear came over some fighters, a ''combat narcosis,'' as Mr. McPherson calls it (adrenaline wasn't identified until 1901). Or a fear of showing fear, which several of Mr. McPherson's letter writers define as the true meaning of courage. Some men found themselves shouting. Others sang. Still others were too afraid of their leaders to be afraid. Others were too bonded to their brothers-in-arms.</p>
        <p>Such anodynes didn't work for everyone. Mr. McPherson writes that during the Civil War ''a consensus existed that in many regiments about half the men did most of the real fighting.'' The rest were known, in Civil War slang, as ''skulkers, sneaks, beats, stragglers, or coffee-coolers.'' They would play sick, or sneak to the rear with wounded buddies, or simply run.</p>
        <p>Even those who fought bravely could do so only for a limited time, until they were overcome by what would now be known as post-traumatic stress disorder. ''Studies of modern armies have shown that a unit is wrecked psychologically if it twice suffers casualties equivalent to one-third of its strength,'' Mr. McPherson writes.</p>
        <p>This raises the question of what sustained soldiers between battles during the war, and leads Mr. McPherson to discuss issues like morale, the effect of letters from home, the complex relevance of emancipation and the simpler motives of hatred and revenge. ''Saw much of the work I had done in the way of severed limbs, decapitated bodies, and mutilated remains of all kinds,'' wrote a grandson of the architect Benjamin Latrobe (who helped design the United States Capitol and the White House) in his diary after the Battle of Fredericksburg. ''Doing my soul good. Would that the whole Northern Army were as such &amp; I had my hand in it.''</p>
        <p>Still, one seeks to know what it was like to face almost certain death in the hail of gunfire like that faced by the soldiers in Pickett's Charge. Mr. McPherson says many soldiers were able to do so because they had found religious faith and truly believed they were going to heaven. But too often they failed to report the experience of deadly battle simply because they had died. The announcement that his correspondents were killed in one battle or another knells throughout Mr. McPherson's moving text.</p>
        <p>As for those who survived, they were too often struck dumb. For them the gulf between normal life and seeing the elephant remained unspeakable. All one can do is pray never to have to experience what they did, and reflect that just because of what they went through, most of us may well never have to.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
