<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Picks Voting Machine Supplier</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIJACKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">POLICE DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LORCH, DONATELLA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D8113FF930A35753C1A966958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Picks Voting Machine Supplier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN BAQUET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After five years of political infighting and allegations of corruption and favoritism, the New York City Board of Elections voted yesterday to begin negotiations for a $50 million computerized voting system that would change the way votes are cast in the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After five years of political infighting and allegations of corruption and favoritism, the New York City Board of Elections voted yesterday to begin negotiations for a $50 million computerized voting system that would change the way votes are cast in the city.</p>
        <p>After five years of political infighting and allegations of corruption and favoritism, the New York City Board of Elections voted yesterday to begin negotiations for a $50 million computerized voting system that would change the way votes are cast in the city.</p>
        <p>Bowing to pressure from the administration of Mayor David N. Dinkins, the board, with several members expressing serious reservations, selected the Sequoia Pacific Systems Corporation, of Jamestown, N.Y. as the supplier. Edged out was the R. W. Shoup Company, the descendant of the business that sold the city its original lever machines almost 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>The new computerized voting system, which would be the nation's largest, would not be fully in place until 1996 at the earliest. This would be 12 years after the city was told that its machines were falling apart.</p>
        <p>Intense Lobbying by Companies</p>
        <p>The highly contentious board vote - six for, three against and one abstention - was the bare minimum for approval under the state election law. It came after intense lobbying by the nation's biggest voting machine manufacturers.</p>
        <p>It was marked by allegations that some board members were trying to steer the contract to Shoup, which still has an agreement to maintain the old lever machines, and that one member tried to solicit a bribe from Sequoia. The city will now begin a negotiating process that could last several months. It will include an attempt to resolve allegations that computers are susceptible to tampering.</p>
        <p>Sequoia plans to sell the city lightweight machines that work by push button, somewhat like a telephone. Voters press the button next to their candidate's name, and the choice is stored in the computer's memory. The board would be able to tally votes almost immediately, rather than wait several days.</p>
        <p>Board members said the Dinkins administration, led by First Deputy Mayor Norman Steisel, had pressured them to go along with a 1988 consultant's report that said Sequoia offered the best system for the city. Despite the recommendation by the consultant, the Stanford Research Institute, some board members said they had misgivings. They cited the cost, the corruption allegations and the fact that neither of the two leading vendors could design a system that met all of the city's technical specifications.</p>
        <p>'Very Ill at Ease'</p>
        <p>Two board members - Alice Sachs, a Manhattan Democrat, and Vincent J. Velella, a Bronx Republican - objected strongly before voting for Sequoia.</p>
        <p>''I feel very ill at ease casting this vote,'' Mr. Velella complained.</p>
        <p>Two board members who voted against Sequoia - George M. Spanakos, a Brooklyn Republican, and Anthony Sadowski, a Queens Democrat -questioned whether the city should spend $50 million at a time when it is financially pressed.</p>
        <p>''It appears to me to be fiscal folly to vote on such a large, expensive contract not knowing where the city is going,'' said Mr. Spanakos. However, other board members pointed out that the money was set aside in the city's capital budget several years ago.</p>
        <p>The board's president, Vincent J. Cuttita, a Manhattan Republican, and Gertrude Strohm, a Staten Island Democrat, said Sequoia clearly offered the better product.</p>
        <p>''I have every confidence that we are not going to get stuck with a machine that will not meet the needs of the city's voters,'' Mrs. Strohm said.</p>
        <p>Bribe Allegation Investigated</p>
        <p>The Manhattan District Attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau, is investigating an allegation by a former Queens Councilman, Edward L. Sadowsky, a lawyer for Sequoia, that Mr. Sadowski, the board member, had solicited a bribe from him earlier this year. Mr. Sadowski has denied this contention.</p>
        <p>The process of buying new voting machines began in 1984, when the New York City Partnership, a civic group, said the city was desperately in need of a ''modern voting machine system.'' The criticisms of the old voting machines became even stronger during the 1988 Presidential primary when supporters of Jesse Jackson complained that machines were breaking down in minority neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>At one point during the selection process, Shoup executives acknowledged that they had obtained a copy of the Stanford Research Institute report, which was supposed to be confidential. The disclosure spurred contentions that Shoup's long-standing relationship with the board had given it an edge.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year the Dinkins administration, which includes some former Jackson campaign aides, began pushing the board to select a supplier.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
