<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Plain Folks, White House Style</title>
    <meta content="24GOOD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="879166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walters, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Elizabeth</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">20/20 (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E5DD113DF937A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Plain Folks, White House Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman Critic's Notebook review of Barbara Walters' interviews with Pres and Mrs Clinton and Bob and Elizabeth Dole, on television program 20/20; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Did you catch the Barbara and Bob and Elizabeth and Bill and Hillary and Barbara shows? On ''20/20'' Friday, Barbara Walters chatted up the First Couple, a week after chatting up the would-be First Couple. ''Open, intimate, off guard,'' promised Hugh Downs, Ms. Walters's right-hand man, of performances that had all the spontaneity of a convention biography: damp goods in a damp campaign season.</p>
        <p>On the Dole hour, you could hear about Mr. Dole's war injury and recovery, a subject that he bravely kept pretty much to himself until the Presidential urge came upon him. We were taken back to Russell, Kan., in the company, to borrow Ms. Walters's unsparing cliche, of ''this hometown boy who had made it big.'' Gee, there's the drugstore where he worked as a soda jerk; there's his 94-year-old teacher. There, in close-up, is the bad hand that he managed to keep off camera for years; lately it has been out front.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Did you catch the Barbara and Bob and Elizabeth and Bill and Hillary and Barbara shows? On ''20/20'' Friday, Barbara Walters chatted up the First Couple, a week after chatting up the would-be First Couple. ''Open, intimate, off guard,'' promised Hugh Downs, Ms. Walters's right-hand man, of performances that had all the spontaneity of a convention biography: damp goods in a damp campaign season.</p>
        <p>On the Dole hour, you could hear about Mr. Dole's war injury and recovery, a subject that he bravely kept pretty much to himself until the Presidential urge came upon him. We were taken back to Russell, Kan., in the company, to borrow Ms. Walters's unsparing cliche, of ''this hometown boy who had made it big.'' Gee, there's the drugstore where he worked as a soda jerk; there's his 94-year-old teacher. There, in close-up, is the bad hand that he managed to keep off camera for years; lately it has been out front.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Dole was brought on to sit thigh by thigh with her husband. No, the couple did not confess to Ms. Walters, wearing the deeply concerned expression etched in over the years, that they can't stand each other. It turned out that they like nothing better than being alone together with a good movie.</p>
        <p>And there was Ms. Walters, doing what she does. ''Has listening become important to you?'' she inquired of the hometown boy. ''When you listen around the country, what do you hear?'' Turning tough, she asked whether politics had ruined his first marriage. As for the second marriage, Mrs. Dole revealed, ''This is a very special relationship.'' She also admitted, under Ms. Walters's  coaxing, ''I have devotional time every day, 30 minutes.''</p>
        <p>Advertising that she would focus on ''domestic issues which could deeply affect the American people,'' Ms. Walters apportioned about 5 of the almost 40 minutes to tax cuts, assault weapons, choosing judges and other subjects of moment. Mr. Dole seemed to be quoting from his commercials.</p>
        <p>The most urgent issue, to judge by Ms. Walters's attention span, was whether the American Red Cross, not long since headed by Mrs. Dole, should accept contributions from tobacco companies. The Doles ducked, but agreed that the bottom line is that ''kids should not smoke.'' Ms. Walters was unrelenting. ''How important,'' she demanded of Mr. Dole, ''is it for the President to be a role model?'' He allowed as how it was real important.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, to his credit, was somewhat restrained during what may have been an ordeal for a man of stoic mien with an ironic view of politics. The professionally bubblesome Mrs. Dole, who had proved her talent for this sort of stuff at the San Diego convention, helped him along when he faltered, hastening to assure Ms. Walters that his spirituality was more private than her spirituality.</p>
        <p>The Clinton exercise was in a similar spirit, though not as spiritual. Toward the end, such matters as Iraq, welfare and drugs whizzed by, the President echoing the accentuate-the-positive lines that his surrogates have been spinning for weeks, although his smoky explanation of his famous non-inhaling sounded as though it had been concocted under the influence. (He allows, just as Mr. Dole does, that drugs are bad for you.) It was one of those encounters, not uncommon on television, in which the interviewer does her duty by reading off questions, never mind attending to the answers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters's interest was elsewhere, in the neighborhood where the interests of ''20/20'' and of the candidates profitably converge: ''I wonder what have the White House years meant to your marriage.'' Mrs. Clinton was admirably reticent, while her husband babbled away. (The main news was that Mrs. Clinton would work on welfare in a second Clinton Administration in some unofficial capacity.)</p>
        <p>There were reflections on an alcoholic stepfather's effects on young Bill. (Those early conflicts at home have made the President try to get people to stop being self-destructive and ''to do the right thing and bring them together and go forward.'')  There was Chelsea chat. (Her daddy will miss her a lot when she goes off to college next year.) And there was a life-in-the-White House tour. (You guessed it, the couple's happiest times are in the movie theater with two boxes of popcorn.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole and Mrs. Clinton seemed at moments to withdraw from the shamelessness of the thing; they ought to make a date for the movies and leave the popcorn to their spouses.</p>
        <p>The programs provided a showcase for the qualities that have elevated Ms. Walters to her high place on television: ''If you were a reporter,'' she asked the President in earnest tones, ''how far would you delve into someone's personal life?''</p>
        <p>For the candidates, the shows were happy marriages of pop journalism and pop politics: 40 network minutes apiece with a benign priestess of prime time, who could probably get more votes than Mrs. Dole and Mrs. Clinton put together if she ran for something. Forty minutes of calculated family-values piety before an audience of millions. Mr. Downs, that loyal retainer, pronounced the results ''very revealing profiles.''</p>
        <p>To despair over such displays, you have to believe that Presidential campaigns have other purposes than winning an election and that television news has other functions than winning the nightly ratings. You have to believe that both are opportunities for informing the nation instead of pandering to it. Rest easy. The alliance of news magazine programmers and political operatives is doing its best to save us from that heartless prospect.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
