<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Poets' Gathering, a Tribute to Diallo</title>
    <meta content="27POET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diallo, Amadou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boss, Kenneth (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Richard (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carroll, Sean (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcmellon, Edward (Police Officer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5D9113DF934A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Poets' Gathering, a Tribute to Diallo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Poets and artists gather at church in Fort Greene section of Brooklyn for commemoration of Amadou Diallo, West African immigrant killed last year by undercover police officers in Bronx; scene at ceremony described (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few blocks away from Patrick M. Dorismond's funeral in Brooklyn on Saturday afternoon, poets and artists gathered at another church for a more subdued ceremony -- a commemoration of Amadou Diallo, the West African immigrant killed last year by undercover police officers in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''This is one way of surviving,'' Angeli Rasbury, who helped organize the event, told the audience of about 90 people at the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church in Fort Greene. Above them, a soaring mural depicts a diverse streetscape of neighborhood residents, circa 1973, with a few smiling policemen painted in with the crowd. But below, the poets, artists and musicians spoke of their mounting frustration with the police, and audience members murmured and nodded in empathy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few blocks away from Patrick M. Dorismond's funeral in Brooklyn on Saturday afternoon, poets and artists gathered at another church for a more subdued ceremony -- a commemoration of Amadou Diallo, the West African immigrant killed last year by undercover police officers in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''This is one way of surviving,'' Angeli Rasbury, who helped organize the event, told the audience of about 90 people at the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church in Fort Greene. Above them, a soaring mural depicts a diverse streetscape of neighborhood residents, circa 1973, with a few smiling policemen painted in with the crowd. But below, the poets, artists and musicians spoke of their mounting frustration with the police, and audience members murmured and nodded in empathy.</p>
        <p>''Even black cops are critical of those four cops,'' said Tony Medina, his shoulder-length braids pulled back from his face, reciting a poem about Mr. Diallo's shooting by four undercover officers, who were acquitted in a trial last month. ''They said this means a black man can't carry a wallet, a beeper, a cell phone, umbrella, keys or a Mars Bar.''</p>
        <p>His voice rose in an emotional crescendo. ''Amadou, as you stood in front of your apartment, eating bullets, what did you see? The flash from the teeth of your executioners? The flash from the barrels of their guns?''</p>
        <p>A Palestinian poet, Suheir Hammad, told how the recent shootings had made her identify more urgently with other immigrants. ''I am worried about all the men I love tonight,'' she read. In a reference to Mr. Diallo's occupation, she said, ''I want to buy a pair of gloves and a hat and some batteries from every vendor in the street.''</p>
        <p>While the poems often veered into strident condemnation and ridicule of the police, not all participants judged them harshly. Patricia Spears Jones said: ''I think the cops, at this point, are afraid of themselves. It's an unseemly situation. We have a mayor who doesn't realize that there are consequences of putting the police in this intolerable situation, so cut off from the community they serve.''</p>
        <p>Participants said that in recent months, they have found public speaking to be healing, a constructive way to deal with their grief and rage. Debbie Cowell, a local resident who took a turn at the microphone, said afterward, ''I'd probably be doing something really crazy if I didn't have an outlet just to speak. It's that bad.'' She shook her head, adding, ''We shouldn't have to think about this stuff so long after being slaves.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps fittingly, the 143-year-old church was built by abolitionists, and counted among its supporters Frederick Douglass and Horace Greeley. The Emancipation Proclamation was drafted here, and the rooms downstairs once functioned as a stopping point along the Underground Railroad. ''This church has really felt grieved and outraged by what happened, and we've been looking for multiple ways to express it,'' said its pastor, the Rev. David Dyson.</p>
        <p>Kelli Curry, a Bedford-Stuyvesant resident, said that attending the reading had made her think twice about what she had read about the case. 'I was thinking to myself, ''I'm always believing the propaganda,'' she said. ''We don't think of it as, 'This man's been brutally murdered.' This really humanized him.''</p>
        <p>At the close of the reading, Ms. Rasbury made a brief announcement. ''A young man just came over here from the funeral of Patrick Dorismond, where he said a riot broke out. So it looks like there's a lot of hard work ahead of us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
