<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall St. Uses Webcasts to Give Opinions Directly to Investors</title>
    <meta content="27WALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Painewebber Group Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DE113DF934A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall St. Uses Webcasts to Give Opinions Directly to Investors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Merrill Lynch, PaineWebber and other brokerage companies are putting their securities analysts directly in contact with investors through their own Web sites; analysts have long been interviewed on financial television broacasts, and the new Wall Street Webcasts will further blur line between financial service companies and the traditional media; companies see no conflict, even though they, as the news providers, will have a financial interest in the transaction being presented to the public (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Interviews with analysts have been the stock in trade of financial television broadcasts for years. Now the large brokerage companies like Merrill Lynch, PaineWebber and others that have provided the analysts are putting them directly before clients, via their own Web sites.</p>
        <p>Using streaming video technology, which is essentially broadcasting over the Internet, the financial service companies are experimenting with daily programs that resemble half-hour newscasts but feature the companies' own analysts, reporting on market trends and recommending hot stocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Interviews with analysts have been the stock in trade of financial television broadcasts for years. Now the large brokerage companies like Merrill Lynch, PaineWebber and others that have provided the analysts are putting them directly before clients, via their own Web sites.</p>
        <p>Using streaming video technology, which is essentially broadcasting over the Internet, the financial service companies are experimenting with daily programs that resemble half-hour newscasts but feature the companies' own analysts, reporting on market trends and recommending hot stocks.</p>
        <p>Wall Street Webcasting stands to further blur the line between financial service companies and the traditional media -- a process that began years ago when some of the big brokerage firms started sending television stations recorded interviews with analysts and video news packages featuring the firms' big clients. The self-generated Webcasts also raise questions about maintaining objectivity, when the primary purpose of the information being given is to attract clients and sell services.</p>
        <p>The new Wall Street Webcasts are an example of how ''the walls that have separated e-commerce from the media are coming down,'' said Mark A. Thalhimer, director of the Future of News project at the Radio and Television News Directors Foundation.</p>
        <p>''What's happening now is that the news provider, to a much greater degree than before, has a financial stake in the transaction that is being presented to the public,'' Mr. Thalhimer said. ''I wonder how consumers will view that, and how they will make the distinction between the news and someone so closely associated with selling something.''</p>
        <p>For their part, the financial service companies see no conflict. They consider what they are providing to be information that helps both their large investor clients and the typical individual investor.</p>
        <p>''What we're providing is not just content, but context,'' said Frank Zammataro, first vice president of the Digital Business Development Group at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Still, there is no question that the brokerage firms are competing with Internet stock-trading services like E*Trade for investors' attention. ''If you understand how consumers are making decisions, then using the Internet this way presents an opportunity to shape those decisions,'' Mr. Zammataro said.</p>
        <p>What Merrill Lynch provides is not really news, company officials say, but information and opinion to help investors. ''What we feature can be newsworthy, but we are not a news organization,'' said Fred Yager, director of Merrill Lynch Global Broadcast Service.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch is far ahead of the other financial service companies in Webcasting. Since last March the firm has put out two daily menus, one on its general Internet site (www.merrilllynch.com) for casual browsers and another just for clients.</p>
        <p>''We were getting calls from clients asking, 'How come I've always got to see your analysts on CNBC -- why can't you get them to us first?' '' Mr.  Yager said.</p>
        <p>The Webcast on the company's general Internet site, which is available starting at 11 a.m. each day the stock market is open, includes streaming video reports about industry trends. Securities regulations force Merrill Lynch to stop short of discussing particular stocks, because the audience is too broad.</p>
        <p>At the end of the reports, however, viewers are told that if they want to know what Merrill analysts think about individual stocks in the featured industry, they should follow a link to the client site, askmerrill.com, which includes what is called the Global Investor Network. Once there, they have access to the complete Webcast. They can try a 30-day subscription, and get free permanent access by opening an account.</p>
        <p>While the company has spent only an estimated $2 million on the Global Investor Network, it can put out a half-hour report using Merrill Lynch analysts on trading floors in New York, London, Hong Kong and Frankfurt. The heart of this Webcast is the summary of Merrill Lynch's morning call, the 7 a.m. meeting at which analysts discuss the most widely held and active stocks of the day. There are also segments on mutual funds, international investing and personal finances, all with Merrill Lynch analysts who talk about stocks they recommend.</p>
        <p>With high-speed Internet connections, the Webcasts resemble television broadcasts, and once put on the site they can be downloaded by clients at any time. The connections tend to get clogged, which affects the video quality. At slower speeds, the images are hazy and movements quite jerky.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yager, a former reporter and television producer, said that since the project began last March, viewership had increased from a few thousand a day to more than 100,000 daily hits.</p>
        <p>In a few weeks, the site will be overhauled. Mr. Yager said that under the new format, clients would be able to switch from Webcast reports on one company to archived reports on other companies in the same field. They also will be able to download the text of complete research reports done by Merrill Lynch analysts on related stocks.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch has long been involved in television production. Through its television network, it provides video interviews with Merrill Lynch analysts to hundreds of local television stations around the world that subscribe to the service.</p>
        <p>Much of the production is handled by Bob Plunkett, a former Fox network television reporter who runs his own production company. Mr. Plunkett said the main difference between preparing a news segment for Merrill's Internet site and one for network television had to do with packaging. ''When you're putting something out on the Web, you're basically giving it a lot more raw, straight objective data because we know who the audience is,'' Mr. Plunkett said. ''If I was back at Fox, my audience would have been so broad that I'd have to present the material so that it could be understood by a big investment banker and the guy who shines his shoes.''</p>
        <p>Other financial service companies that do not have small clients do not have to put on separate Webcasts the way Merrill Lynch does. Goldman, Sachs, for example, plans to start a Webcast soon, but it will be directed toward its institutional investors.</p>
        <p>PaineWebber expects to begin a trial of a daily Webcast this summer, according to Dennis M. McCann, the firm's director of marketing communications. Clients will also be able to pay bills and transfer funds while viewing the analyst report.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest Wall Street firms, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, took a tentative step into streaming video earlier this month when it put on a widely publicized special Webcast about, appropriately, Internet stocks. The firm says it will follow up with other special Webcasts as warranted, but it is not ready to put out a daily report that includes video on demand.</p>
        <p>Bear, Stearns &amp; Company is already using streaming video to take the place of the investor roadshows it puts on in cities across the country to drum up support for new stock offerings. Peter D. Cherasia, head of e-commerce for Bear, Stearns, said he was discussing a deal with CNBC to use the firm's Web site to rebroadcast interviews done with its analysts after they appear on television. Once the company generates enough content, he said, it will revamp its Web site to include its own daily Webcast and other services.</p>
        <p>''We want to make our site as sticky as possible,'' Mr. Cherasia said, using a term that refers to visitor retention, ''so clients will have a reason to stay on or come back throughout the day.''</p>
        <p>Even as financial service companies seem intent on moving onto the terrain of the traditional media, broadcasters and news agencies are finding their way into financial services. In September, CNBC bought a 12.4 percent equity stake in Archipelago, a large electronic communications network that has applied to be registered as an Internet stock exchange. Other investors in Archipelago include Goldman, Sachs and Instinet, another electronic trading system that is part of the Reuters Group, the parent of one of the oldest news services in the world.</p>
        <p>The president of CNBC, William L. Bolster, said there was currently no plan to take CNBC in that same direction. He noted that General Electric, CNBC's parent company, already has a financial arm -- GE Capital. ''The CNBC business model doesn't envision that,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''I'm saying no, but I can't categorically say that it will be no forever.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
