<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Inflation Index Is Said to Overstate the Case</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="661358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE STYLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARD OF LIVING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PRICE INDEX</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LABOR DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUREAU OF LABOR STATISTICS (BLS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDA1531F932A25752C0A962958260" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Inflation Index Is Said to Overstate the Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers at the Bureau of Labor Statistics believe that its Consumer Price Index overstates annual inflation by up to six-tenths of a percentage point, a finding with implications for policy makers and the public.</p>
        <p>The index showing December results is scheduled to be issued on Thursday. For the latest 12 months, the rise in the index was reported at 2.7 percent, but the researchers say it actually rose by only 2.1 percent, meaning that inflation, for a variety of reasons, is being overstated by about one-fourth. The same phenomenon is showing up, they say, in many other developed countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers at the Bureau of Labor Statistics believe that its Consumer Price Index overstates annual inflation by up to six-tenths of a percentage point, a finding with implications for policy makers and the public.</p>
        <p>The index showing December results is scheduled to be issued on Thursday. For the latest 12 months, the rise in the index was reported at 2.7 percent, but the researchers say it actually rose by only 2.1 percent, meaning that inflation, for a variety of reasons, is being overstated by about one-fourth. The same phenomenon is showing up, they say, in many other developed countries.</p>
        <p>The discrepancy comes about not only because of the complexities of calculating inflation, but also because of the way people respond to rising prices, by shopping at discount stores or eating chicken instead of steak. Big Political Issue</p>
        <p>It suggests that people whose incomes are tied to the index, like Social Security recipients, may have done better maintaining their standard of living, one of the major political issues of the 1990's. "People may not be doing as badly as they thought, said Paul A. Armknecht, assistant commissioner for consumer prices and price indexes.</p>
        <p>But while the discrepancy between reported inflation and what might be called actual inflation seems to be larger than previously suspected, researchers here and elsewhere have realized for a decade or more that official gauges are prone to overstatement.</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve and other central banks, for example, are said to take this fact into account in formulating monetary policy. Even as they do so, however, they may be conveying a misleading impression of how much inflation they regard as tolerable.</p>
        <p>And though analysts have identified the factors causing overstatement, a host of technical and conceptual obstacles face bureau statisticians as they approach the next overhaul of the Consumer Price Index, which typically occurs every 10 years and was last conducted in 1987. But the work is sufficiently advanced that the bureau included five technical articles on the subject in the December issue of the Monthly Labor Review, to be distributed shortly.</p>
        <p>"We'd reached the point where we had something we wanted to share," said Deborah P. Klein, an associate commissioner.</p>
        <p>The bureau plans experimental alternative versions of the index for 1995. The issue is separate from the Government's planned introduction next month of an updated version of basic labor-market statistics that currently appear to understate the unemployment rate by about four-tenths of a point.</p>
        <p>Methodologically, the overstatement of inflation, to which Social Security and other Government and private-sector payments are linked, involves two central issues.</p>
        <p>The most obvious is the fact, periodically flaring into public debate, that the Consumer Price Index is a statistical artifact in that it is designed to measure a "basket" of goods and services that changes only infrequently and thus does not capture changes in what people actually buy.</p>
        <p>If the price of steak, for example, should rise sharply and consumers decide to buy chicken instead, the index, everything else being equal, would rise but the consumer's cost of living would not.</p>
        <p>"We work on the assumption that no substitution is made," Mr. Armknecht said.</p>
        <p>Although the Government has surveyed consumer spending patterns annually since 1979, the index is currently based on what people bought in the 1982-84 period. Since then, Americans have reduced the share of their budgets spent on alcoholic beverages, for example, while raising the proportion going for medical care and tuition.</p>
        <p>Price is often the reason for such shifts, but other common reasons are changed tastes or cultural attitudes, the lack of availability of a product, technological improvements or demographic changes in the population.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armknecht said the substitution effect accounted for about two-tenths of a point, or one-third of the overstatement.</p>
        <p>Most of the rest is attributed to a highly technical estimating process -- even the appendix to the bureau's equation-laden explanation contains footnotes -- currently used for the Consumer Price Index. Its formula, involving an arithmetic mean and named for a 19th-century French statistician named Etienne Laspeyres, tends to overstate price changes by giving more importance to increases than to declines. The effect is strongest when combined with consumer substitution of less expensive goods for more expensive ones.</p>
        <p>If a quantity of lettuce, for instance, rose to $5 from $4, this would be a 25 percent increase. If the price then retreated to $4, the decline would be 20 percent. Employing a geometric mean, however, would treat these changes symmetrically and avoid the upward bias, which is most pronounced when applied to items with gyrating prices, like fresh fruits and vegetables, which are often substituted.</p>
        <p>Using the geometric formulation, the price relatives -- 1.25 for the rise and 0.8 for the fall -- are multiplied together and then averaged by taking their square root.</p>
        <p>Another potential source of overstatement is in adjusting for changes in the quality of a product or service, such as when auto makers make previously optional equipment standard. To the extent that improvements, because of imperfect techniques for adjusting the Consumer Price Index, are counted as price changes, the index will overstate true inflation.</p>
        <p>While this process can also cause an understatement of inflation, the bureau notes that the chief contention is that it is improvements that are "predominantly missed" in the compilation of the index. Changes in quality also include such generally hard-to-value amenities as convenient store hours, delivery service and various options for paying.</p>
        <p>Similarly, bureau researchers acknowledge that failure to add new products promptly to the index exaggerates reported inflation. Typically, high-technology and some other products command very high prices when first reaching the market as supplies are limited and producers are seeking to recover high investment and start-up costs.</p>
        <p>The longer it takes for the Government to include the new product in the index, the less likely the inflation gauge is to pick up the almost inevitable, often rapid, price drop.</p>
        <p>Even if these technical problems can be resolved, however, and the Government is shown to be able to save billions of dollars a year through lower outlays for entitlements, strong opponents seek to preserve the current Consumer Price Index mechanism.</p>
        <p>One would be organized labor, whose leaders insist that being forced to give up steak, regardless of feelings about its replacement, reduces one's standard of living.</p>
        <p>"If they substitute hamburger, it's not that they have a preference for hamburger," observed Rudy Oswald, director of economic research for the A.F.L.-C.I.O. "You want to have a measure of the harm."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
