<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gentle Scents Enhance a Flower Bed</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="366609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF113CF93BA35754C0A966958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gentle Scents Enhance a Flower Bed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT had rained the night before, and all the plants were washed clean. They looked fresh and green. There was also a fragrance in the yard, but it was not apparent where it was coming from. Only a few plants were in bloom, as it was a between time, past the glories of spring, but not quite ready for the opulence of annuals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT had rained the night before, and all the plants were washed clean. They looked fresh and green. There was also a fragrance in the yard, but it was not apparent where it was coming from. Only a few plants were in bloom, as it was a between time, past the glories of spring, but not quite ready for the opulence of annuals.</p>
        <p>IT had rained the night before, and all the plants were washed clean. They looked fresh and green. There was also a fragrance in the yard, but it was not apparent where it was coming from. Only a few plants were in bloom, as it was a between time, past the glories of spring, but not quite ready for the opulence of annuals. Yet a gentle fragrance persisted. Perhaps it was coming from a neighbor's yard.</p>
        <p>After a bit of sniffing about, it was determined that the scent was not coming from the Siberian iris. They are almost odorless. Nor was it coming from the wild geraniums.</p>
        <p>One more sniff revealed the source. Astilbes are fragrant. The sturdy perennials were just coming into bloom, with their stately plumes of bright pink and deep red. Their scent was subtle, and by the end of the morning, when the sun was high, it was gone. Even the bees were having a good morning that day. They were busy visiting the newly opened plumes of astilbe flowers in droves, but by the time the sun was high, they, too, were gone.</p>
        <p>On that sunny morning, a new dimension of gardening opened. Many plants have a gentle fragrance, and because these plants do not flaunt this asset as others do, this fact is not too well known.</p>
        <p>So many plants are known for their scents: the powerful herb lavender or the rather insistent rose. There also are lilies of the valley, heady carnations and the not-so-subtle sweet peas.</p>
        <p>But more appealing, in a way, are plants with a subtle fragrance that does not overwhelm but adds a delightful dimension to being outdoors.</p>
        <p>These lovely floral surprises add to the garden. Here are some flowers to include for this delightful dimension. They will never make features or draw crowds of sniffing noses, and this may be a good thing. But the subtlety of their scent and their gentle sweet smells are what make a garden great.</p>
        <p>The name sweet alyssum hints that there may be a reason for this sort of title. Its slight dimension of fragrance is especially appealing in the early evening. Sweet alyssum is well named, as it is a great tumble plant to drape over containers, window boxes and redwood tubs. It also provides endless edging color to any border. Although the white sweet alyssum is the most popular, probably more spectacular are edges of combination plantings with the white-flowered plants alternated with the violet-colored forms.</p>
        <p>Petunias are also fragrant, but not many people plant them for this quality. They think of petunias as splashy annuals for summer to color the pool area, wooden deck or brick patio or to face down a flower border. Yet on a sunny afternoon when picnic time comes, these colorful annuals provide a delightful scent. When cut and taken indoors, they also keep this quality.</p>
        <p>Phlox are fragrant. Few people plant them for their scent, but they have a decided appeal. Although there are many, many of kinds of phlox that can be planted, the ones that have a delicate fragrance are the huge garden perennials, Phlox paniculata, as well as some of the lesser known species.</p>
        <p>And if there is a true sunny patch in the garden with exceptionally well-drained soil, save it for one of the showiest flowers of all, sweet william. Just a few seeds sown now will come up quickly, and bloom can be expected next year to provide bouquets of fragrance. This flower invites cutting, too, and if taken indoors, it will scent an entire room.</p>
        <p>Certain woody plants have delightful fragrance, and they are worth treasuring a garden spot for one of them. Of course, few gardens can be without the lovely lilac, particularly some of the newer members of the clan with their scaled-down growth habits. A particular favorite is the Korean lilac with its mounded form and delightfully fragrant blooms. This one flowers later than the Maytime lilacs and is rich with perfume. The flowers, though smaller, rival the handsome shape of the shrub.</p>
        <p>For winter-weary gardeners who just cannot wait for spring, the evergreen groundcover Sarcococca possesses a magnificent fragrance. This plant is a must near the kitchen door, as it is one of the first scents of spring, assurance that a new season is coming. The flowers are not much to consider, but their fragrance is overwhelming. Just a patch of it is sufficient.</p>
        <p>Another one to have near the house is the beautifully scented Viburnum carlcephalum, which needs space, but one or two flowers cut in early spring are enough to scent a room.</p>
        <p>GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
