<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Action Outshines Stars in C.F.L.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="366836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OTTAWA (ONTARIO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CANADIAN FOOTBALL LEAGUE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH COLUMBIA LIONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLUTIE, DOUG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Ottawa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D91F30F93BA35754C0A966958260" item-length="1759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Action Outshines Stars in C.F.L.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 20,000 fans mill merrily into Lansdowne Park for an evening of pro football unlike any to be found on a Sunday afternoon in Mile High Stadium or Candlestick Park or Soldier Field during the fall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 20,000 fans mill merrily into Lansdowne Park for an evening of pro football unlike any to be found on a Sunday afternoon in Mile High Stadium or Candlestick Park or Soldier Field during the fall.</p>
        <p>Nearly 20,000 fans mill merrily into Lansdowne Park for an evening of pro football unlike any to be found on a Sunday afternoon in Mile High Stadium or Candlestick Park or Soldier Field during the fall.</p>
        <p>No tailgate parties here. The first 10,000 fans, however, receive pink-and-blue baby rattlers to shake from kickoff until the final gun. This is the home team's way of calling its rivals crybabies.</p>
        <p>It is the Fourth of July in the United States but here in Canada's capital it's only a Wednesday night of football. Nonetheless, there are plenty of fireworks. Seventy-three total points are scored. Several skirmishes among the players unfold. Yet, the backdrop is serene.</p>
        <p>Lansdowne Park is an open-end stadium built nearly adjacent to the Rideau Canal. A tour boat glides past with fans waving and leaning over the boat's edge trying to gain a glimpse of the football action. Majestic pine trees are just beyond the road near the canal. The Sunshine Girls chant cheers and wiggle on the field to a variety of records. Is everybody having fun? You bet. It is only a preseason game in which the Toronto Argonauts beat the Ottawa Rough Riders by 43-30, but who cares?</p>
        <p>''We were 4-14 and pitiful last year, so this is an improvement,'' said Doran White, a Rough Riders fan donning a Washington Redskins jersey with a No. 7 and ''Theismann'' printed across the back. ''We lost this one, but we're a better team and we'll go all the way this year. And heck, even if we don't, I've always got the Redskins to root for.''</p>
        <p>Welcome to the Canadian Football League. If the National Football League, as one coach here said, is the walking encyclopedia of football, then the C.F.L., at least, makes for a nifty pocket dictionary.</p>
        <p>The C.F.L. offers a fast-paced game with footballs flying through the air so frequently that one could suffer a cramped neck keeping track. It is a game played on a longer and wider field than the N.F.L.'s and a game played with rules designed to increase scoring. It is a game where a team can easily win by 40 points, lose to the same team in the next few weeks by 40 points, and a game where 40-point leads are by no means insurmountable.</p>
        <p>The C.F.L. is a league that is heavenly for quarterbacks and receivers, hellish for defensive backs. It is a league often perceived as dangerously near the brink of extinction but one that has always found new life. And it is a league where American players have long found new careers and made new homes.</p>
        <p>Live C.F.L. action returns to American television for the first time in six years beginning Friday on SportsChannel America. The C.F.L. kicks off its season Thursday and ends Nov. 25 with the Grey Cup Championship.</p>
        <p>The addition of notable American names, including Tony Rice of Notre Dame, Major Harris of West Virginia and Doug Flutie, plus Mark Gastineau's comeback, have fueled more interest in the league here and in the United States.</p>
        <p>''A large percentage of Americans still perceive Canadians as living like Eskimos,'' J. Donald Crump, the C.F.L. commissioner, said at the league's headquarters in Toronto last week. ''But, we're not unlike most cities in the U.S. A cold winter here in Toronto isn't much different from Minneapolis or Detroit. Unfortunately, though, a big difference is we don't have any place where we grow palm trees.</p>
        <p>''There is no better football player in the world than those in the National Football League from a technical and physical standpoint. We are a different game with different rules that requires a different athlete. But if you look at our entertainment value, it compares favorably with the N.F.L.'s. We provide an alternative for the players and the fans. People pay to see action, and that's exactly what they get.''</p>
        <p>Highlights of the C.F.L. game, an outgrowth of the rugby that dates to 1861 in Canada, and rules include the following:</p>
        <p>* Twelve men are on the field on each play as opposed to 11 in the American game.</p>
        <p>* The field is 110 yards long, 10 more than the American standard, and end zones are 20 yards long, 10 more than in the United States.</p>
        <p>* The field is 65 yards wide, nearly 11 yards wider than American fields.</p>
        <p>* Offenses have only three downs to make a first down and only 20 seconds between plays.</p>
        <p>* A team that punts or kicks a ball into or past the end zone gains a point (The defending team can catch the ball and return it out of the end zone to deny the score).</p>
        <p>* After scoring a touchdown, teams can attempt a 2-point conversion as in the American college game (not in the N.F.L.). Defenses can score 2 points on a failed attempt by returning a fumble or interception the length of the field into their opponent's end zone.</p>
        <p>The league, which took its current form in 1958, features eight teams divided into two divisions and an 18-game schedule. Three teams from each division make the playoffs. Rosters are 35 players a team during the season with a maximum 14 import players, though 2 more are allowed only if they are quarterbacks. An import player is one who played football outside of Canada before his 17th birthday.</p>
        <p>The league's essence is this: quickness is a premium because of the field's width; passing is a must with only two downs to make a 10-yard first down before punting. And it's action, action, action.</p>
        <p>''I don't think people here appreciate the entertainment factor of the C.F.L.,'' said Joe Theismann, who left Notre Dame in 1971 to play three seasons with Toronto at quarterback before leaping to the N.F.L. and the Redskins. ''We get more caught up in the star quality of the N.F.L., but I found the Canadian people warm and the game more exciting. Two of my three children were Canadian-born. People think the C.F.L. is a lesser league, but I say that's wrong. It's definitely a different style of football.''</p>
        <p>Among N.F.L. teams that scour the C.F.L. for overlooked players are the Los Angeles Raiders and the Atlanta Falcons.</p>
        <p>''I've been coming here for seven years,'' said Angelo Coia, a Raiders scout. ''I look at the younger players who weren't drafted by us and the ones we have rights to, like Major Harris. It's a smaller league in terms of player size, and I'm not sure they are quicker than us. But one thing for sure is these teams make things happen right away.''</p>
        <p>Bill Baker, a Falcons scout, said: ''It's a league tough to gauge. The talent level is a notch below the N.F.L. though there are several players here quite good enough to be in the N.F.L. We look for Americans and skill position players. I'm impressed.''</p>
        <p>The C.F.L. boasts that it has a collective-bargaining agreement in place through the 1991 season - the N.F.L. will enter its fourth consecutive season this fall without one -and that its recent Grey Cups have been far more exciting than the N.F.L.'s Super Bowls. The last three Grey Cups have each been decided in the final minute of play and by scores of 38-36, 22-21 and 43-40.</p>
        <p>The C.F.L.'s financial standing, however, has long been in jeopardy. Crump readily admits the league needs money, though other league officials say the eight teams generate a total of $200 million in their communities.</p>
        <p>The flap in Ottawa last week was generated by the Rough Riders signing five free agents - all in one day -before the preseason. Most teams had abstained from free agency in fear of escalating salaries (each team has a $3 million salary cap). Toronto's management was critical of Ottawa's and last month boycotted a scrimmage against Ottawa. Thus, the Ottawa baby rattlers surfaced.</p>
        <p>All here are edgy about the World League of American Football, supported by the N.F.L. and scheduled to begin play next spring, diminishing the C.F.L. talent pool. And the league's drug policy is also a concern to some: it doesn't have one.</p>
        <p>''We have little ways of testing players here because of their strong rights in the courts,'' Crump said. ''That's a big problem, but it has it's own self-policing way. It will show up in their performance and it's up to the general manager and teams to handle it in their own way. The laws are tough in Canada on this, and we support the law fully. Education looks as if it is working here and in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Some coaches and players have made the C.F.L. the last stop in their football careers, but most still yearn to reach the N.F.L. The league is full of success stories about those who made the leap, such as Bud Grant and Marv Levy as coaches and Joe Kapp and Warren Moon as players.</p>
        <p>''This is the fans' game all the way,'' said Dan Daniel, the Ottawa secondary coach, who was a defensive coach with the Kansas City Chiefs for four years and who also coached at several American colleges. ''You throw here 80 to 85 percent of all plays. Your team must learn how to throw, catch and defend the pass to have any chance. That puts a burden on any defensive coach. It's a real challenge and an exciting one.</p>
        <p>''When you only have 36 players, everybody plays special teams and is in motion on the sidelines between plays. Once we had a young man who was a backup to three or four positions. He was injured and we had already lost two defensive backs. We ended up putting a receiver out there to play safety. That's a coaching nightmare that can happen.''</p>
        <p>Damon Allen, the Ottawa quarterback and younger brother of the Raiders' Marcus Allen, is one of 10 black quarterbacks in the league.</p>
        <p>''For so many years, the C.F.L. has made it possible for young black quarterbacks to continue playing when the N.F.L. shut its doors,'' said Allen, who played at California State-Fullerton. ''It's still happening with Tony Rice and Major Harris this year. They'll do like so many others before them: come here and succeed and play fantastic football. Making the adjustment to the wider field isn't easy. A simple out pattern becomes a throw like you're heaving a deep bomb. A quarterback has to be able to move here and throw on the run. Everybody, linemen included, have to be mobile because the field is so wide.''</p>
        <p>''The scary thing about the league as far as the players is concerned is that there is little security,'' said Allen. ''You have one bad game, especially two, and you could be gone.''</p>
        <p>For the C.F.L. to flourish, it needs more stars and better marketing of the assets it already possess, Crump said. Many of Canada's 25 million people live near the American border, and the N.F.L. is as popular here as it is in the United States. Crump noted that on a fall weekend, as many as 14 N.F.L. games were available on Canadian television compared with only two Canadian games.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
