<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phelps Dodge Announces Deal to Buy 2 Big Nickel Miners</title>
    <meta content="26cnd-miners" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D91730F935A15755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phelps Dodge Announces Deal to Buy 2 Big Nickel Miners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and IAN AUSTEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phelps Dodge, the world's largest copper producer, said today that it had agreed to acquire two of the biggest nickel miners in a huge deal worth $40 billion. The deal, for Inco and Falconbridge, would create a mining behemoth that will reshape the industry as commodity prices continue to soar.</p>
        <p>The deal comes a day after steel giant Arcelor agreed to merge with Mittal Steel in a $33.5 billion deal. Mining and other commodity-related companies are increasingly seeking to merge to take advantage of the enormous economies of scale involved in the mining and processing of metals. Steel and nickel producers have become particular attractive in the past year as China's appetite for the metals has grown exponentially.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Phelps Dodge, the world's largest copper producer, said today that it had agreed to acquire two of the biggest nickel miners in a huge deal worth $40 billion. The deal, for Inco and Falconbridge, would create a mining behemoth that will reshape the industry as commodity prices continue to soar.</p>
        <p>The deal comes a day after steel giant Arcelor agreed to merge with Mittal Steel in a $33.5 billion deal. Mining and other commodity-related companies are increasingly seeking to merge to take advantage of the enormous economies of scale involved in the mining and processing of metals. Steel and nickel producers have become particular attractive in the past year as China's appetite for the metals has grown exponentially.</p>
        <p>The transaction will end a yearlong battle over Inco and Falconbridge, which had agreed to merge last October, by a cadre of rivals that had made hostile offers for both. Phelps Dodge, based in Phoenix, is swooping in as the white-knight to keep Inco and Falconbridge from its other suitors and to satisfy a growing chorus of investors that have contended the Inco-Falconbridge deal shortchanged its shareholders.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, Phelps Dodge would acquire Inco, which would in turn sweeten its offer for Falconbridge and complete that merger. Inco and Falconbridge are based in Toronto.</p>
        <p>For Phelps Dodge, the transaction would diversify its business and catapult it into the one of the largest diversified mining companies in the world. The chain of events that set off the deal stem largely from a decision in August of last year by Xstrata, a Swiss-based mining company with extensive interests in coal, to buy a stake in Falconbridge from Brascan, a Toronto holding company that was seeking to end its long association with natural resource companies to concentrate on commercial real estate and electrical generation.</p>
        <p>At the time, Xstrata's chief executive, Michael Davis made it clear that acquiring more of Falconbridge was on his agenda. But a condition of the sale made a quick move to control Falconbridge potentially costly. Xstrata had agreed that for the following nine months that if it acquired Falconbridge shares at any price above 28 Canadian dollars (about $25) a share, it would also retroactively pay the premium to Brascan.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Inco, Canada's nickel mining giant, had long coveted Falconbridge. Both companies have a major base of operations near Sudbury, Ontario. But the arrangement of their mines often verged on the irrational with, for example, material from Inco mines next door to Falconbridge processing facilities being moved long distances by rail to Inco's operations. The reverse case is often true as well.</p>
        <p>While Xstrata waited for the nine-month Brascan bonus period to expire, Inco moved in and announced last October that it would buy Falconbridge for 12 billion Canadian dollars in cash ($10.6 billion) and stock under a friendly bid. While that represented a 21 percent premium over what Xstrata paid Falconbridge, many investors complained that the offer was insufficient.</p>
        <p>Completion of that deal, however, was delayed by anti-trust reviews in Europe and the United States.</p>
        <p>Last month, just before the Brascan-Xstrata arrangement came to an end, Inco boosted its offer to 19.6 billion Canadian dollars ($17.5 billion) from its original 12 billion Canadian dollars. But the increased bid failed to deter Xstrata.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, Phelps Dodge will pay $80 a share (Canadian) for every share of Inco; $17.50 will be paid in cash and the rest in stock. Inco will in turn sweeten its offer for Falconbridge by about $5 a share (Canadian) and it's offer will further increase as a result of the increased value of its shares because of Phelps Dodge's bid.</p>
        <p>Inco's bid for Falconbridge's shares will be worth about $62 a share. Phelps Dodge will also announce a $5 billion stock repurchase program as part of the transaction. The deal is expected to be immediately accretive to Phelps Dodge and the companies expect to save about $900 million annually as a result of the three way combination, people involved in the negotiations said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
