<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living the Missing Life</title>
    <meta content="05HAMMERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hammer, Langdon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Glyn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Time's Fool: A Tale In Verse (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Boys At Twilight, The: Poems, 190-1995 (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D91E31F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living the Missing Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Langdon Hammer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hammer, Langdon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Langdon Hammer reviews books Time's Fool: A Tale in Verse and The Boys at Twilight: Poems, 1990-1995 by Glyn Maxwell (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Time's Fool</p>
        <p>A Tale in Verse.</p>
        <p>By Glyn Maxwell.</p>
        <p>396 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $27.</p>
        <p>The Boys at Twilight</p>
        <p>Poems, 1990-1995.</p>
        <p>By Glyn Maxwell.</p>
        <p>160 pp. Boston: Mariner Books/</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. Paper, $14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Time's Fool</p>
        <p>A Tale in Verse.</p>
        <p>By Glyn Maxwell.</p>
        <p>396 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $27.</p>
        <p>The Boys at Twilight</p>
        <p>Poems, 1990-1995.</p>
        <p>By Glyn Maxwell.</p>
        <p>160 pp. Boston: Mariner Books/</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. Paper, $14.</p>
        <p>WHEN he published his first book of poems in 1990, Glyn Maxwell seemed to capture, for British readers, a new generation's ways of speaking and feeling. Here was poetry that was literate and sophisticated but not stuffily literary, and sentiments that were liberal and democratic but not piously held. Maxwell could be poignant and cheeky, and often at the same time; the work felt fresh in both senses. One challenge for such a poet is how to grow older. So it seems fitting that the hero and narrator of Maxwell's new novel-length ''tale in verse,'' ''Time's Fool,'' lives under a curse, unable to age beyond 17. The poem comes to American readers alongside ''The Boys at Twilight: Poems, 1990-1995,'' a selection from Maxwell's three early books published in Britain.</p>
        <p>The plot of ''Time's Fool'' is a variation on the supernatural tales that attracted Coleridge in ''The Rime of the Ancient Mariner'' and Wagner in ''The Flying Dutchman.'' Edmund Lea rides a ''ghost train.'' Every seven years, on Christmas Eve, the train returns him to his hometown, Hartisle, and the doors slide open for the night, temporarily allowing him out. This ritual repetition begins in 1970, when a stranger arrives in town and seduces Edmund's beloved, Clare. When Edmund confronts him, the stranger tells a mad story: long ago he killed a man where he and Edmund now stand, and he has been doomed to wander ever since. Edmund is driven to repeat his crime, and he falls under the same spell. Over the next five decades, during his nights in Hartisle (the name suggests the island of the heart, surrounded by oceans of wasted time), Edmund seeks his freedom through love, repentance and death, only to find himself back on the train each time.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the world Edmund knew has been transformed. Clare marries and divorces. Her memory of Edmund grows fainter until she can't remember having loved him. In 1991 she says of her younger self, ''There's not one cell of me the same / as her. Only the name. Or one of them.'' Hartisle too changes, cell by cell. Still rooted in a rural village culture in 1970, it soon dissolves into the global economy. The town center is displaced by a mall, and Edmund's parents move from their quiet lane into a ''gated community,'' watched over by a uniformed guard in the blue glow of his television. Edmund's local pub, the Oak, is replaced by a brasserie in a ''silvered office block,'' later by an ''Ice-o-theque'' and a chain restaurant called ''Happy Eater.'' Edmund wonders what ''software'' is. His story becomes the subject of a rock album, then the focus of rival New Age cults.</p>
        <p>This much is social satire, trenchant at times, trivial at others. Maxwell's deeper concern is with the solitude and emptiness of Edmund's suspended existence. Once he knows there is nothing left for him in Hartisle, he sees that ''Home is the ride.'' During the seven-year periods between visits to Hartisle, Edmund is alone on the train, save for the train's spectral driver, a certain Inspector Stick, and a man Edmund nicknames Happy Hour, who gives him food and drink while speaking a language Edmund can't understand. Looking out and writing, yet always ''going nowhere,'' Edmund experiences time as a featureless medium passed through and viewed, not grasped and lived in. He is the embodiment of an expatriate writer's homelessness. ''It's living a missing life,'' he explains. But in this there is nothing very strange. ''We all live one, / really.'' Only our homes and our families convince us we belong.</p>
        <p>The feeling that life is somehow being missed is a central theme of modern English poetry, from William Empson to Philip Larkin. ''The Boys at Twilight'' belongs to this lyric tradition. Maxwell's contribution is to treat missed experience not as a private, psychological condition but as a social one, defining the blank quality of contemporary public life. A poem titled ''Tale of a Chocolate Egg,'' from Maxwell's first book, is a virtuoso treatment of the theme. Antic and rambling, Maxwell's narrator follows a few stock types, including a skinhead, an Indian girl and a ''brown-haired bloke,'' as they make their ways through a usual day, drawn by the magnetic appeal of a new product, a chocolate egg. The egg, which has no ''slogan'' but its own ''O,'' is pure advertisement, a symbol for the hollow center of a consumer society.</p>
        <p>The vacancy of political discourse is the issue in other early poems. ''The People's Cinema'' describes a screen on which myths of collective identity are projected: bare and blank, it is ''how riches look in daylight when there are none.'' In ''We Billion Cheered,'' Maxwell speaks of an unspecified social or political threat -- an ''it'' without a definite referent -- against which the national ''we'' gathers and defines itself, although ''We missed it how / You miss an o'clock passing and miss now.''</p>
        <p>Many of the poems in ''The Boys at Twilight'' are about England and Englishness. The style of living they depict is suburban, bland, gently self-mocking (''We shrugged the Home County shrug''). But the loss of weight and depth that Maxwell evokes touches the whole world, and it requires a new cosmology:</p>
        <p>The Earth is of course quite flat, and the heavenly bodies</p>
        <p>Twinkle explicably. One is as big as a Swatch.</p>
        <p>Today they are all gone away, gone away where God is,</p>
        <p>Where the dead play whist and the unborn ask can they watch.</p>
        <p>This is grim but fun. The mood can be darkened simply by changing the channel, so to speak, to the news from Eastern Europe. Maxwell does so in moving poems about violence in Bosnia and elsewhere. In ''a world that had forgotten it was round,'' not flat, Maxwell's fighting men fail to recognize that the other men ''up ahead, quite mad,'' are only ''their own tail,'' and ''they cut them to the ground.'' Here is the brilliant first stanza of a poem called ''The Sarajevo Zoo'':</p>
        <p>Men had used up their hands, men had</p>
        <p>offered, cupped, or kissed them to survive,</p>
        <p>had wiped them on the skirts of their own town,</p>
        <p>as different men had shinned up a ladder and taken</p>
        <p>the sun down.</p>
        <p>As these quotations suggest, Maxwell is a formal poet who uses rhyme and meter nimbly but often loosely, as if to be too exacting would be to risk pretentiousness. His shorter poems, even the most serious, resemble light verse and popular songs. He can be brisk and cutting (as in ''The High Achievers,'' a poem about people on the fast track: ''Made, / they counted themselves free''). But he seldom has the concentration to be pithy. His unique effects derive from rapid modulation between voices, levels of diction, tones. The poems in ''The Boys at Twilight'' race forward in run-on sentences, rubbing against the restrictions of traditional prosody, refusing to be mistaken for merely well-made things.</p>
        <p>Maxwell has an ear for empty statements, syntactic stumbles and conversational filler, the expressive contentlessness of so much that we say. Even when there are missing pieces or semantic gaps, however, Maxwell's poems plunge on, with the implication that life is like that -- a little out of control, a little out of reach. This rush of speech is hard to manage and sustain, even in a short poem. In the 396 pages of ''Time's Fool,'' there are passages where the writing thins out, and Maxwell's calculated slipperiness begins to feel like sloppiness.</p>
        <p>To be redeemed, Edmund must enter ordinary time and age. This he does magically and almost violently at the close of ''Time's Fool,'' passing from 17 to 66 in little more than an instant. This ending is less of an answer to the problem of how to grow older than a release from it. The sense of experience Edmund had missed is suddenly restored, but it remains impossible to articulate. Early in the poem, Edmund speaks of ''the present'' -- punningly -- as something to be unwrapped; and when he tries to get at it, he can't. At the end of the poem, as he watches the sunrise, Edmund is at last alive in the moment, but this new sensation is not so different from his former emptiness. The word that forms in him, Maxwell writes in a beautiful final couplet, only ''fades again, too bright in the bright day / for ink to cling to or for soul to say.''</p>
        <p>Langdon Hammer is the author of ''Hart Crane and Allen Tate: Janus-Faced Modernism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Langdon Hammer is the author of ''Hart Crane and Allen Tate: Janus-Faced Modernism.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
