<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Franks Counts on a Visit by Bush to Give an 11th-Hour Lift to His Senate Campaign</title>
    <meta content="05FRAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="58" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/05/politics/05FRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D91539F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Franks Counts on a Visit by Bush to Give an 11th-Hour Lift to His Senate Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Maria; Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON, N.J., Nov. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Robert D Franks, ending up his campaign for US Senate from New Jersey, receives 11th hour boost from campaign visit by Republican Presidential candidate George W Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After weeks of glad-handing in diners and stumping before groups of a few dozen, Representative Bob Franks finally got the chance to address thousands of wildly cheering New Jersey Republicans tonight when he introduced the party's presidential standard-bearer, George W. Bush, at a hastily arranged rally here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush squeezed his brief foray into New Jersey in between stops in the battleground states of Pennsylvania and Florida. He agreed to come here only after a poll commissioned by state Republicans showed Mr. Bush in a dead heat with Vice President Al Gore and Mr. Franks actually leading Jon S. Corzine, the Democratic Senate candidate who has outspent Mr. Franks by more than 10 to 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After weeks of glad-handing in diners and stumping before groups of a few dozen, Representative Bob Franks finally got the chance to address thousands of wildly cheering New Jersey Republicans tonight when he introduced the party's presidential standard-bearer, George W. Bush, at a hastily arranged rally here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush squeezed his brief foray into New Jersey in between stops in the battleground states of Pennsylvania and Florida. He agreed to come here only after a poll commissioned by state Republicans showed Mr. Bush in a dead heat with Vice President Al Gore and Mr. Franks actually leading Jon S. Corzine, the Democratic Senate candidate who has outspent Mr. Franks by more than 10 to 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush made only one reference to Mr. Franks before beginning his stump speech at Drew University, but it was memorable.</p>
        <p>''I'm so proud of the race Bob Franks has run,'' Mr. Bush said to a crowd of about 5,000 in heavily Republican Morris County. ''It's a campaign of big money versus big ideas, and big ideas is gonna win.''</p>
        <p>That was plenty for Mr. Franks, whose supporters began showing up before Mr. Bush arrived. Mr. Franks was counting on Mr. Bush's visit to mobilize the state's Republican base to compensate for the New Jersey Democratic Party's $3 million get-out-the-vote effort on Election Day.</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Bush arrived, Mr. Franks addressed the crowd, beginning with his signature line.</p>
        <p>''Ladies and gentlemen, my name is Bob Franks, and I'm running for the United States Senate,'' he said. ''But I'm running against a human A.T.M. machine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks then told voters that they had the chance to make history by defeating Mr. Corzine, who has set a new record for spending in a United States Senate race.</p>
        <p>''I believe with ever fiber of my body that New Jersey voters aren't for sale,'' Mr. Franks said, before shouting over and over to a roaring response, ''We need your help!''</p>
        <p>The euphoric crowd, blizzard of confetti and show of Republican unity were an emotional high point for Mr. Franks, who also shared the spotlight with Gov. Christine Todd Whitman and former Gov. Tom Kean, now the president of Drew.</p>
        <p>Most independent polls of New Jersey voters show Mr. Corzine and Vice President Al Gore both holding solid leads. But as he shuttled from rally to rally this morning on his campaign bus, Mr. Franks said he could feel that the dynamic of the race had shifted.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Franks basked in the glow of the national campaign, Mr. Corzine spent the day tending to the nuts and bolts of the state's Democratic political machine: the get-out-the-vote effort. Speaking at a half-dozen rallies for campaign workers in Democratic strongholds in Hudson County, Mr. Corzine told them that their work would help provide a margin of victory for him and Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>With the race down to its final three days, both candidates have focused on energizing their voting base. Mr. Franks has tried to rally supporters in his home base, Union County, and in the traditional Republican strongholds of Ocean, Morris and Somerset Counties. Because he cannot match Mr. Corzine's financial muscle, Mr. Franks has tried to generate media coverage by appearing with nationally prominent Republicans like Senator John McCain of Arizona, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani of New York City, Gov. George E.  Pataki of New York and former Senator Bob Dole of Kansas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine has spent much of his time recently trying to pump up the Democratic Party's core constituencies in places like Hudson, Essex and Camden Counties. Today he attended several grass-roots meetings in Veterans of Foreign Wars posts, diners and coffee shops in Hudson County.</p>
        <p>He was joined in his travels by Senator Robert G. Torricelli, Representative Robert Menendez, Hudson County Executive Robert Janiszewski and other New Jersey officials.</p>
        <p>''If there's one thing I've learned, in business and here in the political world, it's that teamwork is what helps you achieve success,'' he said, speaking to about 200 campaign workers at a breakfast buffet at the Broadway Diner in Bayonne. ''And the team we have here is going to make the difference.''</p>
        <p>The candidates have also traded increasingly negative television advertisements. Mr. Franks's have cast Mr. Corzine as a liberal who is using his wealth to buy a Senate seat and whose ill-considered spending would lead to deficits and tax increases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine has accused Mr. Franks of being an extremist so closely allied with the Republican right wing that he would endanger Social Security, gut Medicare and threaten an erosion of abortion rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine predicted that Mr. Bush's visit would backfire and hurt Mr. Franks, saying that Mr. Bush's positions on major issues were out of touch with New Jersey's relatively moderate electorate.</p>
        <p>''If they see Bob Franks stand next to Governor Bush, then look at Bush's record on gun control, a woman's right to choose and using the surplus to pay down the deficit, I don't think that will help in New Jersey,'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Franks appeared buoyed by Mr. Bush's decision to campaign with him during such a crucial point in the campaign season. Traveling on the bus with his wife, Fran, and their 2-year-old daughter, Kelly, Mr. Franks used each stop to portray himself as the candidate who best understood the struggles of New Jersey's middle-class families.</p>
        <p>Although his appearances today in Mays Landing, Hammonton, Wall Township, Lakewood and Woodbridge drew only small crowds, Mr. Franks said he was confident that the buzz created by Mr. Bush's appearance would excite Republicans and attract independents.</p>
        <p>''Two months ago, all the experts, all the pundits declared me dead and buried,'' Mr. Franks said. ''They said there was no way I could compete against someone who could spend $65 million of their own personal fortune in order to buy a Senate seat. Well, the pundits have been proven wrong. This race is down to single digits.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
