<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bossa Nova For a New Generation</title>
    <meta content="05RATL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/05/arts/05RATL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilberto, Bebel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDC1330F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bossa Nova For a New Generation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff column on success of new bossa nova album by Brazilian singer Bebel Gilberto; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE biggest-selling album by a Brazilian artist in North America right now -- and possibly since recordings by Sergio Mendes in the 1960's, though it's difficult to know for sure -- isn't by one of the usual suspects, a Caetano Veloso or a Gilberto Gil. It is Bebel Gilberto's ''Tanto Tempo.'' Released in the United States last spring by Six Degrees Records, ''Tanto Tempo'' is one of those slow-but-steady successes that executives at other labels of worldly, adult-oriented music -- even Nonesuch, the king of the genre -- are trying to figure out.</p>
        <p>Six Degrees reports that it has sold 130,000 copies in North America; that's far below the platinum level of Nonesuch's ''Buena Vista Social Club'' but just a little less than the sales for Nonesuch's popular Buena Vista spinoff records by Ruben Gonzalez and the Afro-Cuban All Stars. For a small label those are big numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE biggest-selling album by a Brazilian artist in North America right now -- and possibly since recordings by Sergio Mendes in the 1960's, though it's difficult to know for sure -- isn't by one of the usual suspects, a Caetano Veloso or a Gilberto Gil. It is Bebel Gilberto's ''Tanto Tempo.'' Released in the United States last spring by Six Degrees Records, ''Tanto Tempo'' is one of those slow-but-steady successes that executives at other labels of worldly, adult-oriented music -- even Nonesuch, the king of the genre -- are trying to figure out.</p>
        <p>Six Degrees reports that it has sold 130,000 copies in North America; that's far below the platinum level of Nonesuch's ''Buena Vista Social Club'' but just a little less than the sales for Nonesuch's popular Buena Vista spinoff records by Ruben Gonzalez and the Afro-Cuban All Stars. For a small label those are big numbers.</p>
        <p>Bebel Gilberto is the daughter of Joao Gilberto, and it's tempting to ascribe her success to her family name. But that seems misleading, because ''Tanto Tempo'' appeals to a weirdly wide swath of listeners. It's been a consistent seller at Other Music, the East Village record shop where aesthetes come to gnaw on whatever's new and strange. It's been a playlist favorite on KCRW in Los Angeles, the NPR station with famously judicious alternative programming practices. And its hit song, ''So Nice (Summer Samba),'' has been played on 10 smooth jazz stations across the country, most prominently at KKSF in San Francisco. It's hard to think of any other record in recent pop that appeals both to fierce music snobs and to those who use it as anodyne background.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilberto, who will perform at Irving Plaza in Manhattan on Nov. 20, wasn't an overnight success; after she came to New York in 1991 (she now lives in London), she spent nearly a decade working in obscurity at clubs and restaurants. But soon after she arrived from Rio, she met Beco Dranoff, who would become one of her producers. ''We had time to think,'' Mr. Dranoff said. ''We always spoke about the record we would make. There was no rush.'' (''Tanto Tempo'' translates from the Portuguese as ''So Much Time.'')</p>
        <p>Then in 1997 they met Suba, the Yugoslavian-born producer who had been working in Brazil through the 90's. Here's another part of the puzzle: from the start, Ms. Gilberto and Mr. Dranoff told Suba, whose strength was electronic music, that the soul of the record they wanted to make was acoustic. And while Ms. Gilberto's disposition is essentially light, Suba's -- to judge by his own album, ''Sao Paulo Confessions'' -- is considerably darker. There's a bit of tension in the music from these meetings of opposites.</p>
        <p>''Tanto Tempo'' sounds inevitable; even to listeners without much knowledge of its sources, it seems natural to hear bossa nova entwined with electronic music. Partly that's because bossa nova -- understated, rhythmically pushing and pulling -- seems eternally relevant; Antonio Carlos Jobim's best melodies, for example, are some of the strongest of the century and aren't obvious enough to wear thin easily. But the fact is that disc jockeys like Gilles Peterson, Rainer Truby and Jazzanova in Europe and Francois K with the Body and Soul collective in New York had been incorporating songs with samba rhythms into their dance-floor mixes since the early 90's. In one sense, ''Tanto Tempo'' is an extension of their market research; dancers know what to do with this album.</p>
        <p>If people in radio and retail are to be believed, ''Tanto Tempo'' isn't selling briskly because North Americans are learning to understand Brazilian culture and politics or even because Ms. Gilberto sparks memories of her father, one of the fathers of bossa nova. It's because dance culture is breaking down the aesthetic barriers of record production between different countries, and because its gentle tempos neatly bridge the gap between dance club and armchair.</p>
        <p>When queried about the appeal of ''Tanto Tempo,''  Frank Cody, president of Broadcast Architecture, a Princeton, N.J., company that conducts research for radio, talks about something he calls the ''chill movement.''</p>
        <p>''I've spent time recently in London, Amsterdam and Paris,'' Mr. Cody said, ''and almost all the clubs I've visited have a 'chill' room. Usually, what they play is somewhere between jazz, electronic and dance music. One woman I met in England called it coffee-table dance music -- music that's relaxing but bright and intelligent and won't put you to sleep.'' Mr. Cody, whose company was partly responsible for the proliferation of smooth jazz radio stations, sees a possibility for a new radio format here. At the same time, he can think of no other record beside Ms. Gilberto's that has gotten a foothold both on strong alternative and smooth jazz formats.</p>
        <p>It's nothing new that North Americans need a handrail to get to Brazilian music. In the 1960's it was jazz; if you were going to appreciate Joao Gilberto, it helped if you knew Gerry Mulligan. Now, apparently, it's dance music. Suba, who died in a fire in his Sao Paulo apartment last November shortly after finishing work on ''Tanto Tempo,'' looked as if he could have been a major facilitator in this process.</p>
        <p>As much as he was a pace-setter, Suba wasn't alone. There's a ton of new cheaply made music coming from Brazil that has many of the same elements of samba and electronics as ''Tanto Tempo.'' But as Mr. Dranoff points out, very little of it has been electronic music for its own sake, the kind of music that vests too much musical control in the capabilities of the computer. And the reason for that, to posit the most obvious explanation for the success of ''Tanto Tempo,'' is that the melodic and rhythmic resources of Brazilian music are too strong and persistent.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
