<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Claiming Victory, Strikers Rally in Cities Across France</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="816633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1D71739F934A25751C1A963958260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Claiming Victory, Strikers Rally in Cities Across France</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Dec. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of thousands of railroad and subway workers, students, teachers and  other state employees marched through Paris and other French cities today in demonstrations that celebrated a three-week public transportation shutdown protesting Government austerity plans as a victory.</p>
        <p>"We have won a battle, but not yet the war," said Jean-Jacques Carmentran, head of the rail section of the Workers' Force union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of thousands of railroad and subway workers, students, teachers and  other state employees marched through Paris and other French cities today in demonstrations that celebrated a three-week public transportation shutdown protesting Government austerity plans as a victory.</p>
        <p>"We have won a battle, but not yet the war," said Jean-Jacques Carmentran, head of the rail section of the Workers' Force union.</p>
        <p>Estimates by Government and trade union officials of the number of demonstrators indicated that there were somewhat fewer on the streets today than on Tuesday, when the unions said that 1.7 million to 2 million demonstrated.</p>
        <p>Railroad workers voted on Friday to return to work after Prime Minister Alain Juppe withdrew plans to change pension rules that allow some of them to retire at the age of 50 and all to retire after 37 1/2 years of service, compared to 40 years in private industry.</p>
        <p>Louis Viannet, Secretary General of the Communist-oriented General Confederation of Labor, called for another demonstration next Tuesday, but other union leaders conceded that many of their members would go back to work as the holidays approached. There was limited subway service on two lines of the Paris  Metro today, and about half the normal number of commuter trains, with not all destinations served. National rail service is not expected to get back to normal until late in the coming week.</p>
        <p>Marc Blondel, head of the Workers' Force, led a march through Paris today by  a little more than half the number of demonstrators who turned out last Tuesday. Today there were 45,000, according to police estimates, compared to 60,000 last  Tuesday; union organizers said there were 300,000 in the march through southern  sections of Paris.</p>
        <p>In Marseilles, 150,000 marchers paraded through the streets this morning, about as many as last Tuesday, according to the organizers. At least 20,000 demonstrated in Grenoble, 15,000 in Bordeaux, where Mr. Juppe is also Mayor, and similar numbers marched in Lyons and Toulouse, with smaller demonstrations in other cities. In Roanne, a Loire valley town of 40,000, the police, whose estimates tend to be on the low side, counted 10,000 demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Juppe, 50, a graduate of the elite National School of Administration, where President Jacques Chirac also received his training as a civil servant, became the focus of widespread public anger over the suddenness and severity of  the austerity measures.</p>
        <p>Explaining them on television halfway through the strike, Mr. Juppe sounded like a patronizing economics professor trying to convince a dull class that his  plans were good-faith attempts to save the national health insurance and pension system from ruin.</p>
        <p>The Paris demonstration today included demands for him to withdraw the plan,  which would decree a national income tax increase of 0.5 percent and increase the health premiums paid by retired people. But Mr. Juppe, backed by Mr. Chirac, has vowed to press on and has ignored demands from the unions to meet with them  before a "social summit" scheduled for next Thursday.</p>
        <p>When he announced the plan a month ago, along with the since-shelved measures to reorganize the deficit-ridden national railroad system and change pension rules for state employees, he said that his Government might be in danger of falling if two million people took to the streets.</p>
        <p>"That dumb remark of Juppe's about two million, we reached that number a long time ago," Mr. Blondel, wearing a red scarf at the head of the Paris demonstration, said this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blondel had vowed to keep up the strike pressure until Mr. Juppe went, but Mr. Blondel's aides conceded on Friday that many union members wanted to return to work. "The workers are hatefully angry because they hate being treated with contempt," Mr. Blondel said.</p>
        <p>Employees in the private sector, where less than 10 percent belong to unions, did not join the strike movement, and a public opinion poll published today by the daily Le Monde newspaper found that 49 percent of the French people thought  Mr. Juppe should pursue his plan, compared with 47 percent who thought he should withdraw it. Four percent had no opinion.</p>
        <p>Businesses estimate that retail sales in the peak Christmas buying season are down about 50 percent so far from last year's figures, and a small-business federation estimated that bill payments lost in postal strikes and transportation tie-ups that delayed deliveries could cause as many as 5,000 small businesses to go bankrupt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
