<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Workers and Bosses, a Society Askew</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="816471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG WHARF THEATER (NEW HAVEN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, ALVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KESSLER, LYLE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ROBBERS (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1D91739F934A25751C1A963958260" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Workers and Bosses, a Society Askew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIN, ALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TED, an egoless young man, is an undercover agent chosen by Feathers, the eccentric master of a surveillance racket. Ted's first assignment, for which he  is renamed Kenneth, is to turn in the employees who are ripping off a canning factory. The pseudonymous private eye takes to the job with "an incredible ability to enter an environment and become one with it."</p>
        <p>With that endorsement from Feathers arrives another assignment, this time in  a leather plant that employs hundreds of thousands, robbers all. And Ted a k a Kenneth is to have a new name: Dennis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TED, an egoless young man, is an undercover agent chosen by Feathers, the eccentric master of a surveillance racket. Ted's first assignment, for which he  is renamed Kenneth, is to turn in the employees who are ripping off a canning factory. The pseudonymous private eye takes to the job with "an incredible ability to enter an environment and become one with it."</p>
        <p>With that endorsement from Feathers arrives another assignment, this time in  a leather plant that employs hundreds of thousands, robbers all. And Ted a k a Kenneth is to have a new name: Dennis.</p>
        <p>How Ted is chosen in the first place sets the tone for a bizarre comedy. How the mysterious Feathers gives the innocent Ted an identity, and how the young man finds his own purpose are at the heart and soul of "Robbers," a new play of  immense imagination at the Long Wharf Theater's Stage II in New Haven.</p>
        <p>"Robbers" -- are they the underpaid exploited workers who pilfer ham or the bosses who say "Let 'em eat Spam"? -- is finally a rare thing to behold, a play  of conscience. Its sheer moral urgency is embodied by Vinnie, the ringleader of  the robbers.</p>
        <p>In the haunting performance of Paul Ben-Victor, Vinnie -- who can come up with questions like "Ain't that the simple truth of earthly existence?" -- boils over with the desperation of the philosophically correct. One cannot turn away from Vinnie's theory of "economic necessity" or his cry of the underclass: "Are  we no better than the rats?"</p>
        <p>"Robbers" is filled with such vivid resonating characters in performances that linger, especially Peter Rini's wide-open young man in victorious search of self, talking of Kafka and Kira Arne's Cleo, the factory worker who vulnerably represents the hold of love.</p>
        <p>Lucky for Long Wharf to have Marshall W. Mason's chameleonesque, terrifically swift staging of an uncommon play, although Judd Hirsch, as the many faces of Feathers (Japanese, Orthodox Jew, Russian lay priest) as well as the Indian owner, a real robber baron, does not take to all of them with equal reserves of  energy.</p>
        <p>It is now time to talk of the playwright Lyle Kessler, who wrote "Orphans," a striking 1984 play, with shades of Shepard and Pinter, about two strange brothers and the man they kidnap.</p>
        <p>"Robbers" -- hardly an instantly accessible play for everyone -- exists and shifts on a self-created reality plane that many prefer to perceive as fantasy,  given Mr. Kessler's learned and critical view of a society askew. We are perilously close to a thin line of derangement, Mr. Kessler seems to be saying.  (Feathers's wife and his son are confined to a mental hospital; he and his daughter Lucinda, of many guises played sassily by Katherine Hiler, are not.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessler also seems to believe that the "source of power" Kenneth finds, when he is no longer Ted, is good. In the search for signs of adventure and purity in theater, it is rewarding to listen to the voice of Mr. Kessler.</p>
        <p>"Robbers," Long Wharf Theater's Stage II, 222 Sargent Drive, New Haven. 787-4282. Performances through Dec. 23.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
