<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mexican Collapse</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="816743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDEN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CASTANEDA, JORGE G CARLOS SALINAS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MEXICAN SHOCK, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD61739F934A25751C1A963958260" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mexican Collapse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Timothy Golden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDEN, TIMOTHY;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MEXICAN SHOCK Its Meaning for the United States. By Jorge G. Castaneda. 254 pp. New York: The New Press. $23.</p>
        <p>MEXICO'S violent awakening from the first-world dreams it entertained during  the presidency of Carlos Salinas de Gortari has been a boon to the country's publishers. The struggle to explain what happened -- the peasant uprising, the political assassinations, the anticlimactic election and the economic collapse -- has become a melee of memoirs, exposes and campaign year kiss-and-tells. Book parties in Mexico City are often no parties at all, but political events attended by hundreds of people and by great debate about who did what to whom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MEXICAN SHOCK Its Meaning for the United States. By Jorge G. Castaneda. 254 pp. New York: The New Press. $23.</p>
        <p>MEXICO'S violent awakening from the first-world dreams it entertained during  the presidency of Carlos Salinas de Gortari has been a boon to the country's publishers. The struggle to explain what happened -- the peasant uprising, the political assassinations, the anticlimactic election and the economic collapse -- has become a melee of memoirs, exposes and campaign year kiss-and-tells. Book parties in Mexico City are often no parties at all, but political events attended by hundreds of people and by great debate about who did what to whom.</p>
        <p>Jorge G. Castaneda, a political scientist at the National Autonomous University of Mexico and a longtime critic of the Salinas Government, is among the first to produce a book-length study of the country's recent turmoil for readers in English. The effort already seems overdue. A new relationship with the United States was central to the bright future that Mr. Salinas promised; the image of a new Mexico that he appeared to embody helped win approval of the  North American Free Trade Agreement in Washington. The Clinton Administration and Republicans on Capitol Hill shared the shock when Mr. Salinas's chosen successor, Ernesto Zedillo, botched a long-postponed devaluation of the peso and needed commitments of almost $50 billion in foreign loans to save the economy from collapse.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Castaneda sees it, the Americans had it coming. Politicians, scholars, businessmen and the media all fell blindly in love with Mr. Salinas and his band of young, English-speaking technocrats, he asserts; thrilled with the Salinastas' faith in free markets and free trade, most of the gringos chose to ignore the undemocratic politics and unequal distribution of wealth that went along with them. "No one, it seems, was willing to analyze the overwhelming evidence of abuses and financial mismanagement in Mexico since 1988," Mr. Castaneda writes in "The Mexican Shock." "Those surprised by the economic collapse and the stench of it all had simply neglected to open their eyes."</p>
        <p>The steadiness of Mr. Castaneda's own skepticism cannot be faulted. When others praised the renegotiation of Mexico's huge foreign debt in 1990, he warned that the terms could condemn the country to indentured servitude. While most Mexicans welcomed the trade accord, he saw another raw deal: uncompetitive  Mexican industries left to perish, wrongheaded American immigration policies left intact. Mr. Castaneda, who sometimes advised leaders of the country's main  leftist political party, states proudly that his lens is one of "systematic, virtually across-the-board criticism of the Salinas administration's program and the authoritarian political system upon which it rested."</p>
        <p>His indictment is handed up in a series of essays written since mid-1993 for  audiences ranging from Inter-American Dialogue to The Atlantic Monthly's. The concerns of this somewhat disparate compilation have to do with the shortcomings of Mexico's economic model, the breakdown of the political system and the dangers looming for the United States should it fail to grasp Mexico's predicament. If there is a central argument, it is perhaps that a successful transformation of the heavily protected and state-dominated economy was impossible without deeper political change. Mr. Castaneda contends that the failure of a flawed economic strategy was predictable, even inevitable so long as the Government's authoritarian controls allowed it to ignore pressures for moderation, from a slower opening to foreign trade to adjusting the exchange rate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Castaneda's complaints about the refusal of the Salinas Government to adopt some sort of industrial policy and build domestic savings sound even more  valid now, as the Zedillo administration gropes for a way to absorb the growing  millions of unemployed. Some analysts will quarrel with his dismissal of the possibility that Mr. Salinas might have succeeded in his gamble to balance huge  deficits in Mexico's trade and debt accounts with foreign investment, but the case is at least clearly argued. Readers will probably have more trouble sorting out what Mr. Castaneda means to say about Mexican politics. At one point, he explains the violence that racked the country in 1993 and 1994 as a national equivalent of what French psychoanalysts call "the return of the repressed" -- "indirect results, consequences indecipherable in their precise mechanism, of a  problem left unresolved or buried in the national unconscious." Farther on, he attributes the killings of a Roman Catholic cardinal and two governing-party leaders to the partial dismantling of the patronage system that traditionally resolved disputes within the ruling elite. The problem with this idea is not simply that it is still rather speculative -- Government investigations have yet to show any clear tie between the various crimes and continuing struggles within the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party -- but that makes it harder to understand the party's resilience now.</p>
        <p>MR. CASTANEDA wonders whether the current chaotic state of affairs might not  in fact represent a kind of status quo. But while that notion represents a noteworthy break from the prevailing faith among Mexican intellectuals that the  PRI, as the governing party is called, will disintegrate any day now, readers unschooled in Mexican politics may be hard pressed to understand from the preceding discussion how Mr. Zedillo ever got elected and why he hasn't been overthrown. Mr. Castaneda emphasizes the fears of an opposition victory that the Government worked hard to build, particularly among the poor. Still, his triumphal focus on the evils of the Salinas regime tends to obscure other sources of the country's difficulties: the weakness of demands for political change among ordinary Mexicans, the failure of opposition leaders to articulate  convincing alternatives, the remarkable (if largely superficial) adaptation of traditional ruling-party bosses to changing rules of the game.</p>
        <p>Admirers of Mr. Castaneda's 1993 study of the political left in Latin America, "Utopia Unarmed," may wish that he had sat down and written a whole book about Mexico's moment, instead of patching one together from earlier writings. The sort of profile sketches that made "Utopia Unarmed" more readable  are missed here: Mexican political figures drop into the narrative like strange  guests and then quickly disappear, while others are mentioned but never identified, and the same statistics and ideas are sometimes marshaled more than  once in slightly different form. An essay written in mid-1993 makes clear what political consequences Mr. Castaneda foresaw for the free trade agreement before it passed, but it does not make for an irresistible read now. Throughout "The Mexican Shock," Mr. Castaneda makes a strong case for Americans' need to understand his country better. This time, however, he contributes less to that cause than he might.</p>
        <p>Tim Golden, who was Mexico City bureau chief forThe New York Times from 1991 to 1995, is on leave as a Neiman Fellow at Harvard  University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tim Golden, who was Mexico City bureau chief forThe New York Times from 1991 to 1995, is on leave as a Neiman Fellow at Harvard  University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
