<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspectors vs. Hotel on Chairless Atrium</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ZONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUILDINGS DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARKER MERIDIEN HOTEL (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL CONTROL BOARD (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITY PLANNING COMMISSION (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNLAP, DAVID W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARKER, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC123BF93BA15750C0A965958260" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspectors vs. Hotel on Chairless Atrium</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNLAP, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether you were staying there or not, had a dime in your pocket or didn't, you could always be a guest of the Parker Meridien Hotel in mid-Manhattan during the 1980's, just by taking one of the 40 or 50 seats arranged around little bistro tables in a welcoming mid-block atrium.</p>
        <p>David S. Perrin, whose office is next door, was one of the brown-bag regulars in those years. "It was a very nice lunch crowd," he recalled. "They could not have afforded the pricey restaurants on 57th Street, so they read the paper or read a book, and then went back to work."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whether you were staying there or not, had a dime in your pocket or didn't, you could always be a guest of the Parker Meridien Hotel in mid-Manhattan during the 1980's, just by taking one of the 40 or 50 seats arranged around little bistro tables in a welcoming mid-block atrium.</p>
        <p>David S. Perrin, whose office is next door, was one of the brown-bag regulars in those years. "It was a very nice lunch crowd," he recalled. "They could not have afforded the pricey restaurants on 57th Street, so they read the paper or read a book, and then went back to work."</p>
        <p>The chairs were among several amenities required by the City Planning Commission in return for a special permit that allowed the developer, Jack Parker, to build eight extra floors on the hotel, at 118 West 57th Street, between Avenue of the Americas and Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Parker Meridien executives said, the atrium began to attract a different sort -- people who disturbed and even preyed on hotel guests. 'Beautiful' but No Chairs</p>
        <p>Today, the chairs are gone, and so is the lunchtime crowd. And an administrative law judge for the New York City Environmental Control Board has upheld the hotel's decision to remove the seating. The judge, Irving Schwartz, dismissed a violation notice issued by the Buildings Department last year, saying that "this arcade, in its present condition, without chairs, remains a strikingly beautiful amenity for the public."</p>
        <p>The Buildings Department filed an appeal of the ruling last week. "The judge somehow didn't grasp the intent of the plaza," said Rudolph J. Rinaldi, the Buildings Commissioner. "When we give a zoning variance, we're looking for more than meeting a minimal standard. You have to make sure that the tradeoff gives you the quality of life you're seeking. The owner has to be willing to insure that the space is kept up."</p>
        <p>Without the chairs, one cannot do much more than walk through the atrium or spend a moment looking at its giant, peach-colored columns and mirror-filled arcades.</p>
        <p>"It's a shame to think that New Yorkers and visitors to this town can't sit and rest in such a lovely space," said Michael Presser, chairman of Community Board 5 in mid-Manhattan. "Amenities in a public sense mean not just being able to pass through and have access to them, but to enjoy them." 'Our Guests Were Harassed'</p>
        <p>But things were not quite that idyllic, said Rachel Spasser, director of public relations for the Parker Meridien. "We were getting people staying there for the entire day," she said. "We were getting people who came in specifically to eye people who were walking through the atrium."</p>
        <p>"Our guests were harassed," she said, "and, at times, followed out of the building and robbed. That's basically where the problem started. Unfortunately, we could not come up with a solution where we could both provide seating and provide our guests with the utmost security."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perrin, the office manager at the Jewish Board of Family and Children's Services office at 120 West 57th Street, said he had "never felt threatened" by anyone else in the atrium. He was the first to complain formally, in March 1991, that the chairs had been removed.</p>
        <p>Under the special permit, issued in 1979, Mr. Parker was given permission to construct a 40-story building, eight floors more than would have been allowed as a matter of right. In the permit, city planners specifically mentioned "public seating" and "movable chairs." One Answer Is Supervision</p>
        <p>"We did not set out to violate the agreement," Ms. Spasser said. "We tried lots of methods to alleviate the situation and came to the conclusion that it wasn't possible."</p>
        <p>Mr. Presser said he thought the answer was supervision. "It seems to me," he said, "that a properly maintained and supervised public space within an existing building, in which there's open access, proper lighting and so forth, would have a minimal element of risk."</p>
        <p>But Ms. Spasser said the hotel's security staff was limited in what it could do to protect guests once they left the building, which was where she said robberies had occurred. She had no tally of incidents but said it had been a "considerable problem," aggravated because the victims were out-of-towners who were not as cautious around strangers as New Yorkers might be.</p>
        <p>In his ruling last week, Judge Schwartz said the chairs were "not a point of emphasis" in the special permit and that their removal "furnishes no grounds for a ruling that respondent has not 'substantially' complied with the terms of the special permit."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rinaldi said: "We can't live with this. We're not going to sit here and say that an E.C.B. judge can change the whole way the department functions."</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Rinaldi discounted the potential legal influence of Judge Schwartz's decision, Vahe Tiryakian, a spokesman for the agency, said there was some concern that "it might encourage other developers or builders to remove some amenities themselves."</p>
        <p>A building inspector has already written out a new violation notice, citing the absence of chairs. The hearing is scheduled April 29.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
