<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Question No. 1 in the City Council President Race; Why Would Anyone Want the Job of Mostly Sitting Around Waiting to Break a Tie?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAMES, ORGANIZATIONAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D61130F93BA15750C0A965958260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Question No. 1 in the City Council President Race; Why Would Anyone Want the Job of Mostly Sitting Around Waiting to Break a Tie?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seven months before the election of the next City Council President, about a dozen people, from a comedian to an ex-convict, are hungrily eyeing the office. But, as many of them acknowledge, the most intriguing question about the race may be not who will run, but why.</p>
        <p>"It is frustrating to run for a job when the first thing out of people's mouths is, 'Why would you want to do</p>
        <p>that</p>
        <p>?' " said Donald M. Halperin, a State Senator from Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seven months before the election of the next City Council President, about a dozen people, from a comedian to an ex-convict, are hungrily eyeing the office. But, as many of them acknowledge, the most intriguing question about the race may be not who will run, but why.</p>
        <p>"It is frustrating to run for a job when the first thing out of people's mouths is, 'Why would you want to do</p>
        <p>that</p>
        <p>?' " said Donald M. Halperin, a State Senator from Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Cynics notwithstanding, Mr. Halperin has hired a campaign consultant and has begun plotting his candidacy, as one contender in a shadow campaign that is being waged by Mark Green, the city's Commissioner of Consumer Affairs; the comedian Jackie Mason; David A. Paterson, a State Senator from Manhattan; Ron Reale, the president of the New York City Transit Police Benevolent Association, and many more -- more, it seems, every day. As they cautiously size one another up and keep an eye peeled for unexpected hats flying into the ring, the probable major contenders are withholding formal announcements of their candidacies. 'We're All Waiting'</p>
        <p>"We're all waiting for someone to put their foot forward," said Ninfa Segarra, the Bronx representative on the Board of Education, who is also weighing a bid.</p>
        <p>All this interest may seem odd, given the hard times that have befallen the office of the City Council President, which Andrew J. Stein plans to vacate after eight years to run for Mayor.</p>
        <p>When the City Charter was revised four years ago, the City Council presidency was stripped of its greatest power: two votes on the Board of Estimate. The board was disbanded and most of its powers were given to the City Council, where the President does virtually nothing but cast a vote in the extremely unlikely event of a tie.</p>
        <p>This winter the Council deflated the office's name to Public Advocate, effective next year. The office's $3.7 million budget is likely to be cut -- Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone, who actually runs the Council, has proposed slashing it by $1 million. And the office is probably going to lose even its office, at least at City Hall, since the Speaker is planning to boot the Public Advocate out of his space after the election. Calls for Elimination</p>
        <p>Both Mayor David N. Dinkins and Mr. Vallone have called for outright abolition of the job, which would require a citywide referendum.</p>
        <p>Whoever wins the race, an aide to Mr. Vallone said, "will have an office as it slowly gets decimated." He added, "The only thing we can't take away is the salary."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Halperin gamely plans to forge ahead. "I believe people can respect the person who holds this position," he said, "and come to respect the position itself."</p>
        <p>Like other probable candidates, Mr. Halperin listed several benefits to holding the $105,000 job. As one of only three officials elected citywide (the Mayor and Comptroller are the others), the Public Advocate has great freedom to dig into different agencies, to expose problems and to propose new policies. The Public Advocate also succeeds the Mayor if he dies in office.</p>
        <p>And once the first Public Advocate proves the value of the job, several potential candidates said, the City Council leadership and the Mayor will stop trying to eliminate it. Possible Steppingstone</p>
        <p>Another benefit, which the potential candidates scrupulously did not cite, is that the position has traditionally been regarded as a possible steppingstone for politicians seeking higher office. "Anybody who wants to break into citywide office, who wants to be mayor, has got to find a platform that takes them beyond the borders of their jurisdiction," said John H. Mollenkopf, a political science professor at the City University of New York Graduate Center.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, however, whether the office, even in its more potent days, ever deserved its reputation as a political launching pad. The last several City Council Presidents did not go on to higher office, though not for lack of trying. "People focus on the politicians who have helped them, or who they perceive as having helped them," said Norman Adler, a political consultant. "And when you're City Council President, it's hard to make that impression."</p>
        <p>The impression the Council President tends to make, Mr. Adler said, is that of a "kvetchy politician," which may be one reason Mr. Stein currently lags in mayoral polls.</p>
        <p>Now that the office has been diminished, its holder's odds of establishing a nobler political image seem even longer. Indeed, two formidable city politicians who clearly aspire to higher office -- Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx Borough President, and Ruth W. Messinger, the Manhattan Borough President -- have shown no interest in the job.</p>
        <p>Of those who are interested, almost all are Democrats, although some might also seek the Republican nomination. Mr. Mason would run as an independent, said his campaign consultant, Martin McLaughlin. Only one candidate, Grady O'Cummings, a lobbyist from Brooklyn, has formally announced.</p>
        <p>Perhaps nothing better demonstrates the office's mysterious appeal than the fact that Mr. Green is probably going to run. At Consumer Affairs, Mr. Green already has many of the same watchdog functions as the Public Advocate -- in addition, as he pointed out, to five times the budget and staff.</p>
        <p>"I have to think long and hard about leaving a job I obviously love to run for a job that's been publicly belittled," he said. "If I should run, the biggest opponent may be the perception -- it's a do-little job that should be beheaded."</p>
        <p>Although he would surely face bigger opponents than that, Mr. Green would probably begin the campaign as the favorite, since he is the only potential candidate with a public record who is also well known citywide.</p>
        <p>Stephen DiBrienza, a City Council member from Brooklyn who is considering a bid, said he would abandon his plans if Mr. Green enters the race. "He's a winner, if he gets in," Mr. DiBrienza said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Adler, who does not yet work for one of the candidates but has held discussions with two of them, said a diverse field of candidates could divide Mr. Green's support and cost him the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>For example, he said, consider this convoluted but quite possible scenario: Dov Hikind, an Assemblyman from Brooklyn who is an Orthodox Jew and who is considering running, appeals to conservative Jewish voters, while Mr. Halperin attracts many moderate white Democrats. Mr. Green might then find himself left without much of a constituency. Then Mr. Paterson, who is black, might be able to defeat all the other contenders, including Mr. Green, by locking up black voters.</p>
        <p>In fact, the potential field is large enough that just about every constituency in the city seems to be represented. Israel Ruiz Jr., a City Council member from the Bronx who served four and half months in a Federal prison for overstating his assets on a bank loan application, proudly identified a very select element of the population as his political base, should he undertake a campaign: "the people that have been in jail -- the criminals that want a second chance," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
