<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo Says HUD Needs Added $5.6 Billion for Subsidies</title>
    <meta content="28HUD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="912134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDC1231F93BA15751C0A961958260" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo Says HUD Needs Added $5.6 Billion for Subsidies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Housing Sec Andrew M Cuomo tells House subcommittee that agency needs additional $5.6 billion in 1998 to avert 'greatest crisis HUD has ever faced,' possibility that millions of poeple would become homeless if they lost their housing subsidies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Housing Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo told a House subcommittee today that the agency needed an additional $5.6 billion in 1998 to avert the ''greatest crisis HUD has ever faced,'' the possibility that millions of people would become homeless if they lost their housing subsidies.</p>
        <p>In his first testimony in Congress since his Senate confirmation hearing this month, Mr. Cuomo said the extra money, which the Administration is seeking in its budget for the next fiscal year, is needed to cover expiring contracts that enable low-income, elderly and disabled people to receive rent subsidies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Housing Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo told a House subcommittee today that the agency needed an additional $5.6 billion in 1998 to avert the ''greatest crisis HUD has ever faced,'' the possibility that millions of people would become homeless if they lost their housing subsidies.</p>
        <p>In his first testimony in Congress since his Senate confirmation hearing this month, Mr. Cuomo said the extra money, which the Administration is seeking in its budget for the next fiscal year, is needed to cover expiring contracts that enable low-income, elderly and disabled people to receive rent subsidies.</p>
        <p>Without the additional appropriation, he said, more than six million people could lose housing by 2002, and many more would have to to seek inferior accommodations.</p>
        <p>''This is not an inside-the-Beltway story,'' Mr. Cuomo told the Human Resources Subcommittee of the Committee on Government Reform and Oversight. ''This affects every city across the country.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Cuomo's plea fell on generally sympathetic ears of lawmakers from both parties, the matter of increasing the agency's overall budget 30 percent, a huge leap at a time when most lawmakers favor reductions to balance the Federal budget by 2002, will be taken up this year by the House Budget Committee.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Cuomo laid out a somber, if hypothetical, picture of the country without a program that makes millions of housing units available to people on the lowest rungs of the economic ladder.</p>
        <p>The program in question, commonly known as Section 8, provides individuals, landlords and public housing authorities with vouchers for reduced monthly rents, none of which can exceed 30 percent of a family's monthly income. Some vouchers are valid for specific buildings. With others, renters can choose where they live.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government now has Section 8 contracts in effect through 2002 that cover 6.4 million adults and children who are living in 2.7 million rental units. Congress appropriated $3.6 billion for the program last year.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Cuomo said, with nearly two million contracts that expire in the 1998 fiscal year, which begins on Oct. 1, 4.4 million people could be made homeless over the next year if Congress failed to appropriate the additional request.</p>
        <p>Throughout his testimony and in answering questions, Mr. Cuomo, son of former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo of New York, emphasized that the problem would affect cities of all sizes. But the data he gave lawmakers showed that New York City would suffer worst of all, with 133,785 people who live in 55,453 subsidized units in jeopardy of losing their housing if the appropriation is not approved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said if Congress forced HUD to cover the contracts with its existing $19.2 billion budget, most of its major programs, including Section 8 and grants to spur economic development in urban areas, would suffer cuts of 35 percent.</p>
        <p>In leading a hearing that lacked any partisan tension, the chairman of the subcommittee, Representative Christopher Shays, Republican of Connecticut, praised Mr. Cuomo for calling attention to a potentially dangerous problem. Later, Mr. Shays told reporters that even by using a worst-case scenario, Mr. Cuomo was not necessarily playing the role of an alarmist.</p>
        <p>''Not at all,'' Mr. Shays said. ''I believe this is the worst crisis the agency has faced, and over the years, both parties, as well as the House and the Senate and Congress and the White House have been putting this problem off. There are no good guys here.''</p>
        <p>Those sentiments aside, Mr. Shays pressed Mr. Cuomo to explain how he planned to manage an agency that was racked by corruption and scandal in the Reagan Administration and described as ''high risk'' in a General Accounting Office study in 1994 for programs fraught with waste, fraud and abuse.</p>
        <p>''Clearly,'' Mr. Shays said, ''this is a massive undertaking.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo responded by telling the lawmakers that the agency was in the midst of vast reductions in personnel, now operating with 10,000 employees, 3,000 fewer than when President Clinton was elected in 1992. Mr. Cuomo said the goal was to reach 7,500, with a majority of the cuts in Washington, rather than field offices.</p>
        <p>He also said the agency was trying to shift power to give more decision-making responsibilities to ''high-performance'' local housing agencies, those that operate efficiently without constant vigilance from Washington.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see more devolution,'' he said. ''Then we can deal with the handful that really require attention.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
