<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stock Funds Still Register Big Inflows</title>
    <meta content="28STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="912149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Investment Company Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DA1231F93BA15751C0A961958260" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stock Funds Still Register Big Inflows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investment Company Institute estimates stock funds took in net new cash flows of $29.4 billion in January, surpassing both $28.9 billion in January 1996 and $24 billion previously estimated; Dow Jones industrial average falls 58.11 points, or eight-tenths of 1 percent, to 6,925.07; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index loses 10.61 points, or 1.3 percent, to 795.07, while Nasdaq composite index drops 27.89 points, or 2.1 percent, to 1,312.66 (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mutual funds got off to a bigger start this year than ever before, a mutual fund trade group reported yesterday, in contrast to its earlier estimates that last month's cash flows had fallen short of the record set one year ago.</p>
        <p>Stock funds took in net new cash flows of $29.4 billion in January, surpassing both the $28.9 billion in January 1996 and the $24 billion previously estimated by the Investment Company Institute. And so far in February, the cash has continued to flow at a rapid rate, according to fund companies and an independent tracker of cash flows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mutual funds got off to a bigger start this year than ever before, a mutual fund trade group reported yesterday, in contrast to its earlier estimates that last month's cash flows had fallen short of the record set one year ago.</p>
        <p>Stock funds took in net new cash flows of $29.4 billion in January, surpassing both the $28.9 billion in January 1996 and the $24 billion previously estimated by the Investment Company Institute. And so far in February, the cash has continued to flow at a rapid rate, according to fund companies and an independent tracker of cash flows.</p>
        <p>But that news did little to cheer equity investors yesterday, as a big selloff in technology stocks and continued fallout from cautionary comments by Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, combined to send stocks lower a second day.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average fell 58.11 points, or eight-tenths of 1 percent, to 6,925.07, while broader market barometers fell more sharply. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index lost 10.61 points, or 1.3 percent, to 795.07, while the Nasdaq composite index, heavy with the battered technology stocks, dropped 27.89 points, or 2.1 percent, to 1,312.66.</p>
        <p>The mutual fund data released yesterday gave substance to the theory that much of the fuel for this year's sharp run-up in stock prices has come from the large amounts of cash flowing into mutual funds that invest primarily in American stocks, particularly to more conservative stock funds that favor shares of large industrial companies.</p>
        <p>Domestic equity funds received roughly 80 percent of the net new cash deposited in stock funds last month, up from 72 percent in January 1996. Investors cooled their ardor for international stocks, however, putting only about 20 percent of net new cash into foreign funds, down from 28 percent a year ago.</p>
        <p>Setting records for monthly cash inflows were the two more conservative categories of domestic stock funds, growth and growth and income. In contrast, aggressive growth funds took in 40 percent less new money last month than in May 1996, the previous record month.</p>
        <p>Bond funds, meanwhile, added $2.9 billion in January, down from $4 billion in January 1996. Despite stellar performance last year by a number of funds specializing in foreign bonds, international bond funds suffered net outflows of $240 million last month, while domestic bond funds added more than $3 billion.</p>
        <p>So far in February, cash flows to equity funds have continued to be strong. Mutual Fund Trim Tabs, a newsletter published in Santa Rosa, Calif., estimates that this month's inflows of cash into stock funds have been at a monthly rate of about $20 billion. That is slightly slower than in February 1996, when stock funds took in $21.9 billion.</p>
        <p>The first four months of the year are typically the biggest for the fund industry, as investors deposit money into retirement accounts ahead of the April 15 tax deadline, and companies make annual payments into pension and other retirement programs.</p>
        <p>In addition, January tends to be a particularly large month, because investors often postpone new investments in December when fund companies are making annual distributions of capital gains and dividends, which could be taxable.</p>
        <p>The pent-up demand appeared to be particularly high this year. While net cash flows grew only about 1.5 percent from January of last year, gross sales of new stock fund shares soared more than 54 percent, to $64 billion. At the same time, redemptions more than doubled, to $38.1 billion, from the level recorded in January 1996. And the amount of money being exchanged into and out of stock funds also rose sharply.</p>
        <p>Ken Safian of Safian Investment Research in White Plains said that redemptions in domestic equity funds exceeded 2 percent of fund assets for only the third time since 1984. The two other times were October 1987 and February 1994.</p>
        <p>Mr. Safian said the combination of heavy redemption activity and low cash levels in stock funds suggested  an environment of bullish money managers and somewhat cautious public investors.</p>
        <p>Cash as a percentage of assets in domestic stock funds barely budged last month, creeping up to 5.26 percent of assets from 5.25 percent in December. One year ago, cash equaled 7.7 percent of assets in domestic stock funds.</p>
        <p>Mutual fund managers had been keeping less cash on hand through much of last year, because extra cash is a drag on performance when the stock market is rising sharply.</p>
        <p>ON THE WEB</p>
        <p>The latest stock and mutual fund quotations, along with news updates, are available on the Internet from The New York Times on the Web: www.nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
