<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Library to Expand Hours and Services, and Restructure Branches</title>
    <meta content="18NYPL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/18/books/18nypl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1628116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Public Library</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mellon, Andrew W, Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Robert W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Library</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DB133FF93BA25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Library to Expand Hours and Services, and Restructure Branches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Public Library to Expand Hours and Services, and Restructure Branches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Public Library, citing increase in budget from New York City, prepares to expand hours and services and restructure itself to coordinate branches more closely with central operations; will restore six-day schedule at its landmark building at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street in December, lengthen operating hours at nearly half of its 85 branches in Manhattan, Bronx and Staten Island and restore sixth day service at 14 additional branches early next year; announces record single-party donation of $25 million from financier and philanthropist Robert W Wilson and $5 million donation from Andrew W Mellon Foundation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Public Library, forced to cut services after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks hobbled the city's economy, is preparing to expand its hours and services and to restructure itself to coordinate the neighborhood branches more closely with the library's central operations.</p>
        <p>As part of the changes, the library's landmark building, at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, will adopt a six-day schedule next month, opening on Sundays for the first time since 1970, library officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The additional hours restore some but not all of the cuts in service caused by reductions in the city's budget after the terrorist attacks in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Public Library, forced to cut services after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks hobbled the city's economy, is preparing to expand its hours and services and to restructure itself to coordinate the neighborhood branches more closely with the library's central operations.</p>
        <p>As part of the changes, the library's landmark building, at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, will adopt a six-day schedule next month, opening on Sundays for the first time since 1970, library officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In addition, the library will lengthen operating hours at nearly half its 85 neighborhood branches in Manhattan, the Bronx and Staten Island beginning next month, adding one to four hours a week, mostly in the mornings, when demand is highest. Assuming the city does not cut financing unexpectedly, a sixth day of service will be restored at 14 additional branches early next year, the officials said. The changes do not affect libraries in Queens and Brooklyn, which operate independently. The money for the expanded hours comes from recent additions to the library's budget from New York City.</p>
        <p>The library also announced yesterday that it received $25 million, its largest single-party donation, from Robert W. Wilson, the financier and philanthropist, who is a former chairman of the New York City Opera. The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation gave another $5 million.</p>
        <p>Even at a time when books can be ordered online relatively cheaply and many bookstores function as libraries with cafes, the public library maintains an important role in the city's daily life. Nearly 2 million New Yorkers hold a library card, and the New York Public Library system had 15 million visitors last year. Roughly 98 percent of all computers with free public Internet access in New York City are in the public libraries.</p>
        <p>The additional hours restore some but not all of the cuts in service caused by reductions in the city's budget after the terrorist attacks in 2001. They also represent an expansion of operations being planned by Paul LeClerc, president of the library, and Catherine C. Marron, who yesterday was appointed chairwoman of the library, succeeding Samuel C. Butler.</p>
        <p>''We had a serious situation after 9/11,'' Mrs. Marron said in an interview. ''But we are changing to fit the needs of the public.'' Mrs. Marron, 48, a former investment banker who has served on the library's board since 1993, recently led an effort that raised $18 million in less than three years to buy books and materials for the branches.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks Dr. LeClerc has hired two senior librarians to oversee the expansion and integration of the library's two main divisions: its research centers -- four libraries that provide on-site access to collections but do not allow materials to be checked out -- and the neighborhood branches, which are traditional circulating libraries. These divisions have long maintained distinct operations, requiring separate library cards and with their own catalogs and administrative systems.</p>
        <p>David S. Ferriero, formerly the vice provost for library affairs at Duke University, is the new director and chief executive of the research libraries, and Susan Kent, a former city librarian for the Los Angeles Public Library, is the new director and chief executive of the branch libraries. In a joint interview, they said they would seek ways to better integrate their divisions.</p>
        <p>''It's confusing to have two different catalogs,'' Mr. Ferriero said. ''We're looking at everything in the system, focusing on what it looks like from a user's perspective.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kent, who as a graduate student at Columbia University fielded questions on the research desk of the Grand Concourse branch library in the Bronx, said New York's is ''the most complex library structure in the world,'' and that the top priorities are making the systems ''easier to use and more approachable by customers.''</p>
        <p>Among the other initiatives being planned, Dr. LeClerc said, are two digital projects. The first, scheduled to begin in February, would draw on the archives and resources of the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, the research branch at 515 Malcolm X Boulevard, at 135th Street in Harlem. Paid for partly with $2.5 million in new federal financing, that project would document the migration and integration of African-Americans in the United States, tracking mass movements from the South to the North and back again. The online collection would include 16,000 pages of material and 8,500 images, Dr. LeClerc said, as well as teaching materials and a curriculum guide for schools.</p>
        <p>The second project would place 500,000 images from the library's collections, all in the public domain, on the library's Internet site for public use.</p>
        <p>About $8 million of the $25 million from Mr. Wilson would support the cataloging of collections that have been unprocessed and inaccessible to researchers at the Library for the Performing Arts, the research branch at Lincoln Center. The other $17 million would pay for materials and technology and preserve existing collections at all the research libraries, including the Schomburg Center, the Science, Industry and Business Library in Midtown and the Humanities and Social Sciences Library, at the main building. The Mellon grant would also support acquisitions and the operating budget of the research libraries.</p>
        <p>Because of holidays and previous commitments, the new Sunday hours at the main building will be in effect Dec. 5 and Dec. 19, when the main branch will be open from 1 to 6 p.m., and every Sunday beginning on Jan. 9. Expanded weekday hours at 39 branch libraries will begin on Dec. 6. An updated schedule is at www.nypl.org/hours/.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
