<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Art;   Anselm Kiefer Explores And Confronts the Past</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIMMELMAN, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIEFER, ANSELM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA103CF932A25756C0A966958260" item-length="1343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Art;   Anselm Kiefer Explores And Confronts the Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIMMELMAN, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On the eve of German reunification - and with all the anxiety and apprehension that the event stirs in the minds of many people - the works of Anselm Kiefer increasingly compel our attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On the eve of German reunification - and with all the anxiety and apprehension that the event stirs in the minds of many people - the works of Anselm Kiefer increasingly compel our attention.</p>
        <p>On the eve of German reunification - and with all the anxiety and apprehension that the event stirs in the minds of many people - the works of Anselm Kiefer increasingly compel our attention.</p>
        <p>His latest paintings, at the Marian Goodman Gallery, court rejection. To some viewers they may appear, at first glance, bathetic evocations of concentration camps and the Holocaust. There are several canvases to which have been affixed model airplanes made of lead, and dresses -sometimes a single adult-sized dress with long strands of hair dangling from it, sometimes several children's dresses, as well. In the case of ''Karfunkel Fee,'' the clothes and plane are tangled in a web of copper, lead and steel wire, the whole of which is attached to a painted scene of what looks like part of an enormous bridge or perhaps one of the Nazi monuments designed by Albert Speer that have long obsessed the West German artist.</p>
        <p>The show also includes one of his deep-perspective, scorched landscapes, and an imposing and powerful sculpture consisting of huge, disheveled lead books on iron shelves before which is strewn shattered glass. Many of Mr. Kiefer's familiar themes are thus represented - the lead airplane, the barren landscape, the burned book. And to this has been added the dresses, encrusted with ash, that can seem such a transparent reference to the clothes discovered near the ovens of Auschwitz and Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kiefer's work is never so straightforward, even though the artist has clearly moved in this exhibition toward a simpler, less densely allusive style. Since he began to exhibit in the late 1960's and even more since his work became familiar to American viewers during the 1980's, Mr. Kiefer has provoked reactions of the strongest sort, causing some to interpret his appropriation of Nazi symbols and German myths as fascistic and anti-Semitic, prompting others to see him as a kind of artistic savior. By confronting so directly Germany's past, his proponents have argued, Mr. Kiefer has sought to surmount that past, to exorcise ghosts, to resurrect German culture.</p>
        <p>Both positions have done a great disservice to the artist, who would probably be the first to reject them. Working as he does on what might be called a Wagnerian scale, and dealing with subjects that have been virtually taboo for West and East German artists since World War II, Mr. Kiefer was bound to frighten and distress some people. But to consider him in any way fascist is to miss altogether the irony and sarcasm that have been a fundamental part of his art from the beginning. It is also to ignore the fact that Mr. Kiefer - unlike many of the neo-Expressionist painters with whom he was too loosely associated throughout the 1980's - paints effectively on a large scale.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Kiefer practices no exorcisms, proposes no resurrections. To the contrary, his works seem much of the time to be about the impossibility of overcoming the past. What optimism there is in them comes from the satisfaction of self-exploration.</p>
        <p>The latest paintings can serve as examples. If they at first resemble memorials to victims of the Nazis, they can also be interpreted as meditations on the nature of memorials and on the visual vocabulary of fascism.</p>
        <p>Like so many of Mr. Kiefer's other paintings, they have been given titles that evoke biblical or cabalist characters and events. Two of them are called ''Lilith's Daughters,'' in reference to the female demon who in post-biblical Judaism seduced men, gave birth to thousands of devils and strangled sleeping children. It was also Lilith who refused to lie beneath Adam when they had sex, and who is identified in cabalism as the consort of God. Lilith is the manifestation of evil, but she has in recent times become a symbol of female strength and independence. That is to say, she is an ambiguous figure.</p>
        <p>It is Lilith and her children who are ostensibly represented in Mr. Kiefer's paintings by the dresses; presumably the planes are meant to connote her destructiveness. But, of course, the associations with the clothes from the concentration camps cannot be negated by these titles, even though the artist scrawls the titles directly onto the canvases. (Nor can associations, it should be added, with other, very different sources, including the felt suits that became the trademark of Mr. Kiefer's mentor, Joseph Beuys.) Here, as in earlier works that depicted Speer's architecture or charred earth, Mr. Kiefer seems to confront the viewer with the visual cliches of war, and especially of Nazism, and to insist that these cliches be re-examined. In particular, he poses the question of how cliches can be retrieved from the maudlin or the macabre - how they can be reinvested with the force of truth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiefer's answer seems to be through complexity and contemplation. A viewer encounters paintings that open themselves up to various and divergent interpretations. Even the rough, physical way that Mr. Kiefer paints can be said to reinforce the impression of conflict and unresolve. This spirit of inquiry is at the heart of what makes Mr. Kiefer's art so important. His adaptations of ancient Egyptian, Greek, Babylonian, Norse and Jewish sources, of alchemy and Romantic poetry, can be vague, pretentious and misleading, and often seem imposed on the works rather than intrinsic to them.</p>
        <p>Yet it is obvious that Mr. Kiefer -whose richly painted canvases are distinctly sensuous and visually arresting - is nonetheless insisting that painting be more than purely visual. The recent ''Sefirot,'' with its references to the cabalist Tree of Life, recalls such earlier works by the artist as ''Ways of Wordly Wisdom'' from 1976-77, which attempted to construct a genealogy of German nationalism. Mr. Kiefer continues searching for methods of ordering the world, for connections and themes.</p>
        <p>His works recall, in this sense, the grand tradition of history painting, with its notion about the elevated role of art in society, except that they do not presume moral certainty. What makes Mr. Kiefer's work so convincing - and so timely, with the coming German reunification - is precisely its ambiguity and self-doubt, its rejection of easy solutions, historical amnesia and transcendence.</p>
        <p>The works of Anselm Kiefer remain on view at the Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, through June 16.</p>
        <p>'Folon's Folons'</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Museum of Art</p>
        <p>Through June 3</p>
        <p>A visitor to the Lila Acheson Wallace Wing at the Metropolitan Museum of Art might well be surprised to discover there an exhibition of about 65 watercolors and etchings done over the last 22 years by the Belgian-born commercial illustrator Jean-Michel Folon. If the museum's commitment in recent years to contemporary art might generously be called erratic, this show is an absolute puzzlement, especially with its full-color catalogue devoted to an artist who has said about himself, ''I do not have any historical importance, and my goal is not to feature in art history.''</p>
        <p>The illustrations on view are from the artist's own collection. Some are based on toys, some feature the Willy Lomanesque everyman who has been Mr. Folon's best-known creation, some tackle political and environmental subjects in a manner that is inoffensive enough to forestall disagreement. Mr. Folon has completed illustrations for numerous magazines and companies over the years, few of which are here; absent are the works he has done for Olivetti, the corporate sponsor of this show.</p>
        <p>Although lacking their complexity and wit, Mr. Folon has understandably cited Paul Klee and Saul Steinberg as sources of inspiration, a list to which can be added the French poster designer Cassandre and, perhaps, Antoine de Saint-Exupery, whose illustrations for ''Le Petit Prince'' achieve the air of childlike grace that seems to be Mr. Folon's aim. It is not, in the end, his fault if this display of watercolors and etchings serves principally to highlight the confusion that characterizes the Metropolitan's approach to contemporary art.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
