<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; Oh, What a Wonderful Time to Be Discovered in Childhood!</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MY MOTHER'S CASTLE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1030F935A15754C0A967958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; Oh, What a Wonderful Time to Be Discovered in Childhood!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever the interval that separates one's viewing of "My Father's Glory" from that of the equally enchanting "My Mother's Castle," it is only an intermission. This latter film, the second by Yves Robert based on the childhood memoirs of the popular French playwright and film maker Marcel Pagnol, picks up effortlessly where its predecessor left off. The hills of Provence still exert a magical attraction for the family of Marcel (Julien Ciamaca), a schoolboy who counts the days, minutes and hours that are spent away from the family's pastoral retreat. They will seem no less alluring to the viewer.</p>
        <p>Much of the appeal of these seductively scenic films is based on pure charm, the kind of charm that means young Marcel will be taking his cod liver oil from a bottle with a lovely antique label. Thanks to the rosiness of Pagnol's boyhood memories, and to the great affection with which Mr. Robert presents them, no event of daily life is seen as too trivial to be cause for delight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whatever the interval that separates one's viewing of "My Father's Glory" from that of the equally enchanting "My Mother's Castle," it is only an intermission. This latter film, the second by Yves Robert based on the childhood memoirs of the popular French playwright and film maker Marcel Pagnol, picks up effortlessly where its predecessor left off. The hills of Provence still exert a magical attraction for the family of Marcel (Julien Ciamaca), a schoolboy who counts the days, minutes and hours that are spent away from the family's pastoral retreat. They will seem no less alluring to the viewer.</p>
        <p>Much of the appeal of these seductively scenic films is based on pure charm, the kind of charm that means young Marcel will be taking his cod liver oil from a bottle with a lovely antique label. Thanks to the rosiness of Pagnol's boyhood memories, and to the great affection with which Mr. Robert presents them, no event of daily life is seen as too trivial to be cause for delight.</p>
        <p>This second film, like the first, is raised to the heights of voyeuristic pleasure by countless family feasts, happy occasions, warm smiles and intoxicating memories. Freshly baked breads are the size of skateboards. Children always appear in crisply starched clean clothes, even in the country, and their mothers never look the least bit overworked. Marcel's father shaves outdoors, looking into a mirror hung from a tree, humming to himself as he surveys the hills of his beloved countryside. At the end of a long, dusty journey to this remote spot, a man opens an enormous chocolate Easter egg to release a white dove.</p>
        <p>These films' greatest accomplishment, in light of so frankly magical a child's-eye view of the world, is that they maintain enough restraint to keep the prettiness from becoming overwhelming. In "My Mother's Castle," even more than in the earlier film, that restraint grows naturally out of the hindsight that shapes these recollections. "Such is the life of man, moments of joy obliterated by unforgettable sorrow," observes Marcel when he is seen fleetingly as a successful film maker in his 30's. "There's no need to tell children that."</p>
        <p>As "My Mother's Castle" begins, Marcel catches a brief glimpse of what adult life will be like as he studies for an important school exam, and as the film proceeds he is offered other such hints of the future. He meets a beautiful little girl, holding a bouquet and wearing flowers in her hair, who says: "My name is Isabelle. I'm telling you, and you'll never forget." Isabelle, who so enchants Marcel that he sits with his face pressed against a piano as he plays, impresses him with what he thinks is her superior upbringing, and persuades him to play knight to her queen, loyal slave to her Egyptian princess. "If girls make you do that now, what'll it be in years to come?" wonders the really commanding woman in his life, his beautiful mother, Augustine (Nathalie Roussel).</p>
        <p>"Each day saw a fresh start to the story of Augustine and her three men," says the narrator of this family drama, as the film begins to tell of how Augustine arranged for the family to spend more time in the country. As pioneering weekenders, proclaiming that "city air is poison," they use a change in the teaching schedule of Joseph (Philippe Caubere), Marcel's father, as an opportunity to travel to the country on foot each weekend.</p>
        <p>The film dwells at length upon the difficulties of this trip, and the miraculous shortcut provided by a special key, which opens doors to the grounds of several estates. And yet the story always sustains its air of sunny unreality. The family members never really look tired, even though they appear to be carrying an entire set of dishes as part of their baggage.</p>
        <p>"My Mother's Castle," a film that is all banquets and bouquets, concentrates as fully on life's smaller joys as on its larger ones, and does so with the kind of panache that has already charmed much of France. The abundance of fresh thyme, the jars of olive oil arranged neatly in the village market and the embroidered pillowcase from which young Marcel wakes to greet the day all contribute quietly but clearly to the film's sensual appeal. In many of these touches there is the kind of prescience that will make sound commercial sense to the comfortable contemporary audience at which the film is aimed. So Marcel's mother discovers the joy of the weekend house, to which the title refers. And Marcel's father is seen enjoying a turn-of-the-century white-wine spritzer.</p>
        <p>"My Mother's Castle" opens today at the Fine Arts, as "My Father's Glory" moves over to the Quad.</p>
        <p>"My Mother's Castle" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It includes the very mildest sexual suggestiveness. My Mother's Castle Directed by Yves Robert; written (in French with English subtitles) by Jerome Tonnere, Louis Nucera and Mr. Robert; edited by Pierre Gillette; music by Vladimir Cosma; production designer, Jacques Dugied; producced by Alain Poire; released by Orion Classics. At the Fine Arts Theater, 4 West 58th Street in Manhattan. Running time: 98 minutes. This film is rated PG.  Joseph . . . Philippe Caubere Augustine . . . Nathalie Roussel Marcel . . . Julien Ciamaca Uncle Jules . . . Didier Pain Aunt Rose . . . Therese Liotard</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
