<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PENTAGON CASTS DOUBT ON PHOTO</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSING IN ACTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTSON, JOHN L (COL)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUNDY, ALBRO JR (MAJ)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, LARRY (LT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GERSHANECK, KERRY (LT COL)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D8163FF935A15754C0A967958260" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PENTAGON CASTS DOUBT ON PHOTO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pentagon cast doubt tonight on the origins of a mysterious photograph that reportedly shows three lost Vietnam War fliers, saying the picture passed through the hands of known fakers of such information.</p>
        <p>In a report issued tonight, the Pentagon also said that biographical information that accompanied the photograph, including birth dates, Social Security numbers and home addresses of the three men, was false.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pentagon cast doubt tonight on the origins of a mysterious photograph that reportedly shows three lost Vietnam War fliers, saying the picture passed through the hands of known fakers of such information.</p>
        <p>In a report issued tonight, the Pentagon also said that biographical information that accompanied the photograph, including birth dates, Social Security numbers and home addresses of the three men, was false.</p>
        <p>But Lieut. Col. Kerry Gershaneck, a Pentagon spokesman, said the military was still not declaring the photograph a fake. "The bottom line is we are not discounting that photo," he said. "We have not come to any conclusions and we are still investigating it."</p>
        <p>The Pentagon made public the analysis of the photographs under heavy pressure from the families of the three Americans: Col. John L. Robertson of the Air Force, Maj. Albro L. Lundy Jr. of the Air Force and Lieut. Larry James Stevens of the Navy. The families have accused the Bush Administration of not taking seriously the possibility that their missing relatives are still alive.</p>
        <p>"There have been a lot of wild accusations about us ignoring information," Colonel Gershaneck said. Photo Called Authentic</p>
        <p>The families have identified the three men in the photograph as their relatives and said unequivocally that the snapshot is authentic. But many other families maintain that the servicemen shown are their relatives.</p>
        <p>At the same time, several Government officials have expressed reservations about the grainy picture of three men with mustaches standing in a wooded setting. They have said it might be a hoax by Southeast Asian bounty hunters seeking monetary rewards from American groups who hope that American servicemen listed as missing from the Vietnam War are still alive.</p>
        <p>In its report tonight, the Pentagon said that 20 sources, ranging from missionaries to bounty hunters to government officials and refugees, had identified the three men in the photograph as Colonel Lundy, Major Robertson and Lieutenant Stevens, but that none of the identifications were based on first-hand information. In addition, it said the origins of the picture were suspect.</p>
        <p>"One principal source of the photograph lies in a ring of Cambodian opportunists led by a well-known and admitted fabricator of P.O.W.-M.I.A. information," the Pentagon analysis said.</p>
        <p>Colonel Gershaneck acknowledged that the photograph may also have come from other sources. But he said any information that passed through the hands of the Cambodian ring had to be questioned.  Doubt Cast on Letter, Too</p>
        <p>The Pentagon report said that figures in Southeast Asia provided biographical information on the men reportedly shown in the picture and asserted that it had been provided by the missing servicemen themselves. But the information was wrong in many respects, the report said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the picture was accompanied by what was said to be a personal letter written by one of the men, Major Robertson.</p>
        <p>"The text of the letter bears little resemblance to anything that would have been written by an American officer possessing an intimate knowledge of the English language," the report said. "Correct grammar, syntax and spelling, for example, are lacking."</p>
        <p>It said one report from a figure claiming to authenticate the photograph included a tape recording that was said to have been made by Major Robertson but "apparently was made by a non-native English speaking male" who did not even pronounce Major Robertson's name correctly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
