<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling in Innocence To Make the Past Fresh</title>
    <meta content="15HAMI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/15/books/15HAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1527316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamill, Pete</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelb, Arthur</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">City Room (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gelb, Arthur</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">City Room (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DE1E3FF936A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling in Innocence To Make the Past Fresh</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recalling in Innocence to Make the Past Fresh</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETE HAMILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamill, Pete</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pete Hamill reviews book City Room by Arthur Gelb; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CITY ROOM  By Arthur Gelb  664 pages. Putnam's. $29.95.</p>
        <p>A sense of intelligent innocence permeates this affectionate memoir of Arthur Gelb's life across five decades at The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sense of intelligent innocence permeates this affectionate memoir of Arthur Gelbs life across five decades at The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CITY ROOM  By Arthur Gelb  664 pages. Putnam's. $29.95.</p>
        <p>A sense of intelligent innocence permeates this affectionate memoir of Arthur Gelb's life across five decades at The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Without falling into sentimental mush, he expresses clearly his love for his immigrant parents; his wife, Barbara; the city of New York; the imperfect craft of newspapering in general; and The New York Times in particular. The book's low-key triumph is that Mr. Gelb is able to look back with such innocent eyes and make the past as fresh as the present.</p>
        <p>''What I saw,'' he writes of his first view of the old Times city room in 1944, ''was a high-ceilinged room filled with clamor, clutter and cigarette smoke. There was an overwhelming sense of purpose, fire and life: the clacking rhythm of typewriters, the throbbing of great machines in the composing room on the floor above, reporters shouting for copy boys to pick up their stories. Some of the editors wore green eyeshades while others relied on fedoras to block the glare of the suspended lamps as they worked feverishly with pencils, scissors, paste pots and copy paper. Solid brass spittoons were placed strategically around the room and a carpet of cigarette butts all but obscured the gray cement floor.''</p>
        <p>He was then a gangly college dropout from the Bronx who had found a copy boy's job at The Times while waiting to be drafted. His reaction to the city room was love at first sight: ''It was where I wanted to stay forever.''</p>
        <p>The call from the draft board never came, but Mr. Gelb had found his own calling, and he recounts his apprenticeship in loving, understated detail. He runs copy. He observes editors, some stuffy and remote, some foppish, some (his favorites) earthy and profane. One evening at deadline time he sees the paper's star local reporter, Meyer Berger, leap from desktop to desktop in a victory lap. The other copy boys and the reporters treat this as a routine occurrence.</p>
        <p>More than 50 years later Mr. Gelb tells the Berger story with a mixture of awe and loss. Such glad eruptions could never happen today in any American city room, least of all the city room of The New York Times. But while learning his trade, Mr. Gelb was learning something of equal value: there were many ways to be a newspaperman.</p>
        <p>In that first year of his apprenticeship he had the good fortune, with two other copy boys and a friendly editor's support, to create a crudely produced in-house sheet called Timesweek, full of news about the people who put out The New York Times. The idea was to help the paper's war correspondents keep up with the home office, and for the professionals at home to keep up with one another. Mr. Gelb and his friends started interviewing those great professionals (including Berger and the returning war correspondents). He was soon a pupil in a continuing seminar that no journalism school could equal.</p>
        <p>Theory turned into practice on the foggy morning of July 28, 1945, when he was drafted to help cover the crash of a B-25 bomber into the Empire State Building. He was sent from the scene to Bellevue Hospital.</p>
        <p>''I managed to talk my way into the emergency room to ask the nurses some simple questions,'' he writes. ''Because of my youth and obvious inexperience, I guess they felt sorry for me, and they gave me a vivid account of their lifesaving efforts.''</p>
        <p>Then he tells us what he learned that day about his craft:</p>
        <p>''My success alerted me unwittingly to a journalistic virtue: naïveté. The best reporters, I began to realize, were masters of feigned innocence; by disarming their subjects, they collected perceptive details.''</p>
        <p>Such innocence, feigned or genuine, took him through a long, honorable career. He is certainly not naïve about the failings of the newspaper he loved so much. He remains angry about the appalling failure of The Times to cover the Nazi extermination of the European Jews, and to do it in depth while it was happening. He does not forget the uncertain response of the paper's management to the McCarthyite redbaiting of Times employees. He is conscious of the inadequate coverage of sports, poorer neighborhoods and the outer boroughs, even into the early 1960's. He remains annoyed by the calcified orthodoxies of Times style as imposed by the nomenklatura of the copy desks. And he admits that for too long his beloved city room was an all white, all-male preserve.</p>
        <p>For all of the failings of the paper (and he includes a critique of what he calls the paper's overreaction to this year's Jayson Blair scandal), Mr. Gelb makes clear that he would have chosen no other life and no other newspaper. The narrative is full of portraits of great reporters, including Homer Bigart, McCandlish Phillips, Gay Talese, David Halberstam, Harrison E. Salisbury and Peter Kihss. He remains grateful to Brooks Atkinson, the drama critic who gave him a license to indulge his own passions for theater. He has little use for James Reston, who in this account acts as if he were one of the Washington power brokers he was supposed to be covering (one reason The Times blew the Watergate story). But Mr. Gelb also gives great credit to those less famous rewritemen, (good) copy editors, headline writers, photographers and art directors who make every newspaper a daily miracle of craft.</p>
        <p>As it must be, this is also a tale of Mr. Gelb's long friendship with A. M. Rosenthal, a great newspaperman whose passion for the craft sometimes caused anguish in others. They met as young men in the city room near the end of the war, stayed in touch by mail when Mr. Rosenthal became a foreign correspondent, shared a sense of New York irony and worshiped great reporting and writing.</p>
        <p>Later they became known as Abe 'n' Arthur, a team that revitalized the newspaper in the 1960's and 70's, after Mr. Rosenthal's return from nine years overseas and his rise to the top editor's job. The tale of their friendship is woven in and out of detailed accounts of the major stories of their time together, from the Pentagon Papers, the eruptions of racial anger, the discovery and spread of AIDS, the conjoined New York plagues of drug addiction and police corruption and others. This is also as it must be. ''City Room'' is, after all, a newspaperman's book.</p>
        <p>As such, it also has some unavoidable nostalgia. Mr. Gelb clearly still longs for the lost world where typewriters were hammered at deadline, the bells of AP tickers always announced something new, and we all put cigarettes out on the floor. He's not alone.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES Pete Hamill is a columnist for The Daily News. He has been a newspaperman for 43 years and won the Meyer Berger Award from the Columbia School of Journalism in 1962 and the Peter Kihss award from the Society of the Silurians in 1992.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Pete Hamill is a columnist for The Daily News. He has been a newspaperman for 43 years and won the Meyer Berger Award from the Columbia School of Journalism in 1962 and the Peter Kihss award from the Society of the Silurians in 1992.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
