<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Table With a View</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="568877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TAUCK TOURS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARBER, LEONORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF153CF93BA35752C1A964958260" item-length="325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Table With a View</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor: Having recently completed a tour of the Canadian Rockies conducted by Tauck Tours, I'd like to share one persistent source of discomfort with your readers. Perhaps they will prove I am not paranoid!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor: Having recently completed a tour of the Canadian Rockies conducted by Tauck Tours, I'd like to share one persistent source of discomfort with your readers. Perhaps they will prove I am not paranoid!</p>
        <p>The group consisted of 42 people -- 17 husband-and-wife couples and 8 single women, mainly widows. My travel companion and I fall into the latter category. In four of the hotels we stayed at, our accommodations were inferior to those assigned to married couples. We were later told by Tauck it was "luck of the draw." To get a restaurant table with a view of the gorgeous scenery we had taken the trip to enjoy, we had to be almost obnoxiously persistent, because we were told those tables were reserved. At a photo session of the group, the "ladies" were asked to wait at the sidelines in order to position the couples first. LEONORA FARBER Jamesburg, N.J.  Michael Marino, product manager for Tauck Tours, responds: We were disturbed to learn of Mrs. Farber's discomfort during the tour, and of her perception of discrimination against single women travelers.</p>
        <p>Most visitors to the Canadian Rockies prefer to stay at the famous hotels built by the railroads decades ago. These facilities are charming in their own right, but are composed of rooms of many different shapes and sizes. This can lead to perceptions of inequity of room assignments, which are not limited to single travelers.</p>
        <p>It is regrettable that Mrs. Farber sensed discrimination in the method of arranging her group for a photograph. Most photographers will first arrange the spouses traveling together and then include the remaining members of the group in the pose. This method creates the most effective memento that the group photograph is intended to be. Perhaps more sensitivity could be promoted in the way in which photographers instruct their subjects. We will pass along Mrs. Farber's comments to all of our photographic suppliers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
