<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>UConn Remains Unbeaten In Big East</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="822749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PROVIDENCE COLLEGE UNIVERSITY OFCONNECTICUT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2D61039F937A25752C0A960958260" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>UConn Remains Unbeaten In Big East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</byline>
      <dateline>PROVIDENCE, R.I., Jan. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Connecticut's talented forces exhausted another Big East team tonight. The Huskies won their 13th straight game and remained undefeated in conference play  with a second-half flourish that put away an outclassed but stubborn Providence  squad, 83-74.</p>
        <p>The sixth-ranked Huskies (14-1, 6-0 Big East) twice had their lead reduced to a mere 4 points in the second half, at 47-43 and 55-51.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Connecticut's talented forces exhausted another Big East team tonight. The Huskies won their 13th straight game and remained undefeated in conference play  with a second-half flourish that put away an outclassed but stubborn Providence  squad, 83-74.</p>
        <p>The sixth-ranked Huskies (14-1, 6-0 Big East) twice had their lead reduced to a mere 4 points in the second half, at 47-43 and 55-51.</p>
        <p>UConn's response the second time was a two-minute, 12-0 run featuring Ray Allen, who hit four shots and had assists on the other two scores.</p>
        <p>The Huskies cruised thereafter before a full house of 13,106 at the Civic Center, where they had lost last season when ranked No. 4 in the nation.</p>
        <p>"We've now played six different Big East teams and I'd say Providence is pretty good," UConn Coach Jim Calhoun said. "We wore them down in the second half."</p>
        <p>The Friars fell to 8-6 and 1-5 in the Big East.</p>
        <p>Their coach, Pete Gillen, did not think much of his team's play.</p>
        <p>"We didn't play with any flair or fire," Gillen said. "We were too anxious against a great team."</p>
        <p>Like others this season, Gillen found it easy to compliment what may be Calhoun's best Connecticut team. "They were clearly better," Gillen said. "They  play so well together. And Allen is the best player in the country."</p>
        <p>Allen was UConn's scoring leader, as usual, with 23 points.</p>
        <p>UConn forward Kirk King had another perfect night, shooting 10 for 10 from the floor, which tied a Big East record. He was 9 for 9 against Villanova on Tuesday and his 19-for-19 streak is also a conference record.</p>
        <p>King finished with 20 points.</p>
        <p>Jamal Thomas came off the bench to lead the Friars with 17 points, 7 on 3-point field goals. Ruben Garces, the center from Colon, Panama, had 16 and the Austin Croshere added 15. The first half was typical of Connecticut's games this season. No matter how well the opponent plays -- and the Friars were a scrappy,  eager bunch -- the Huskies win out with their persistence. And depth.</p>
        <p>When Calhoun goes to his bench for players such as the freshman guards Rashmael Jones and Ricky Moore, he loses nothing.</p>
        <p>A typical UConn sequence in the first half saw a steal and a dunk by Allen; a Jones steal and pass to Rudy Johnson for a 3-point play; two lob passes to King  under the basket for scores, and a steal and breakaway pass to Allen, who was fouled. Of course he sank the free throw.</p>
        <p>The Huskies were 18 for 22 at the free-throw line and they sank their first nine before Doron Sheffer missed.</p>
        <p>Sheffer, the consummate cool guard, had 15 points and nailed two 3-point shots in the second half at the right moments to discourage any Providence uprising.</p>
        <p>The Friars had won two of the last three games between the teams and four of  the last seven, including the Big East championship at Madison Square Garden in  1994.</p>
        <p>However, the players most responsible for those victories -- Eric Murdock, Dicky Simpkins, Michael Smith and Eric Williams -- are now in the National Basketball Association. This season's cast is a modest group with only one standout -- Croshere, a second-team forward on the all-Big East preseason squad. Before tonight's game, Providence was in last place in the Big 7 division of the conference, having lost twice to both Seton Hall and Syracuse and with only  one victory, over St. John's.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
