<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Jersey Court, Tales of Sex, Extortion and Murder</title>
    <meta content="16DOCT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/16/nyregion/16doctor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1680639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD6163BF935A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Jersey Court, Tales of Sex, Extortion and Murder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Case Unfolds Against New Jersey Man in Wife's Death in '04</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILLER</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jonathan Nyce's world was falling apart.</p>
        <p>His marriage of 14 years was crumbling. His pharmaceutical company -- which he founded but had later been forced to leave -- was dying. His finances were stretched thin, and he was selling his home in Hopewell Township, N.J., for $1.6 million. His wife was cheating on him. And he knew it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, June 15 - Jonathan Nyce's world was falling apart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jonathan Nyce's world was falling apart.</p>
        <p>His marriage of 14 years was crumbling. His pharmaceutical company -- which he founded but had later been forced to leave -- was dying. His finances were stretched thin, and he was selling his home in Hopewell Township, N.J., for $1.6 million. His wife was cheating on him. And he knew it.</p>
        <p>It was against this backdrop, testimony reveals, that on a snowy January night in 2004, Dr. Nyce was in the garage of his home in central New Jersey, his three children tucked in their beds, his wife, Michelle, emerging from her Toyota Land Cruiser. She had just returned from a motel encounter with a landscaper, Miguel DeJesus, 35 -- a man Mrs. Nyce had promised her husband she would not see again.</p>
        <p>Soon Mrs. Nyce, 34, was dead, her body, bloodied and beaten, found the next day inside the Land Cruiser in a creek a mile from her home. Her husband became the prime suspect.</p>
        <p>What happened that night is now a matter for a State Superior Court jury in Mercer County to decide in a case fraught with betrayal, lust, extortion claims, lies and, possibly, videotapes.</p>
        <p>Testimony began last Thursday, and in the first few days jurors have heard an involved account. They learned that Mrs. Nyce had carried on a yearlong affair with the landscaper, who had planted trees in their yard, and that Dr. Nyce took steps to put a stop to it.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the landscaper, who said he had used several aliases, testified that he had, indeed, had an affair with Mrs. Nyce. He also testified that Dr. Nyce, 55, had called him on his cellphone in July 2003 and threatened him. ''He said, 'You put your hands on my wife again, you're going to be a dead man,''' Mr. DeJesus said.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors contend that Dr. Nyce confronted and viciously attacked his wife, repeatedly smashing her head into the concrete floor. They say he then stuffed her behind the driver's seat of her Land Cruiser and steered the car with an ice pick down to the half-frozen Jacobs Creek, where he left her. He faces two counts, first-degree murder and trying to cover up a crime. He could face life in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nyce's lawyer, Robin K. Lord, says that the death of Mrs. Nyce was ''an accident,'' and that she will prove that in court. She says that Dr. Nyce has been accused of a crime he ''did not commit'' and that she will show that his wife, who she says repeatedly cheated on him, tried to attack him first. She declined to elaborate on her strategy.</p>
        <p>''We know what occurred in that garage,'' she said in a recent interview, ''and hopefully the jury will agree, when it's all said and done.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Lord lost a crucial pretrial battle when a judge allowed as evidence a statement Dr. Nyce made to the police saying he had heard a thud that ''made me sick'' when his wife hit the concrete. And in his initial appearance in court in January, Dr. Nyce described his wife's death -- against the protest of his lawyer -- thus: ''This, what happened, was a pure accident.'' She said she has not decided whether Dr. Nyce will testify.</p>
        <p>The case has opened up a hidden world. Dr. Nyce was, by all accounts, a bright yet socially awkward man. He was about 20 years older than his Filipino wife, whom he met through a newspaper advertisement in 1990, when she was 19, her family said. A doctor of philosophy and a graduate of Temple University, Dr. Nyce was widely published in academic journals. His paper in Nature in 1997 suggested an innovative way to fight asthma, and he founded a company named EpiGenesis, now in Cranbury, N.J., to help create the drug. But the drug failed in early trials, and the company cut costs and staff. By 2003, Dr. Nyce was forced out.</p>
        <p>In the summer before his wife's death, Dr. Nyce went to F.B.I. agents to complain that he had been threatened with extortion by a man who claimed to have videotapes of his wife having sex with another man and who threatened to sell them unless he was paid $500,000.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nyce obtained a restraining order against Mr. DeJesus.</p>
        <p>In testimony on Tuesday, the lead police detective for Hopewell Township, Daniel B. McKeown, said he had investigated the extortion claims in 2003.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think Mr. Nyce was being completely honest,'' he said. So far no tapes have been found.</p>
        <p>The defense has focused heavily on the relationship between Mrs. Nyce and Mr. DeJesus, suggesting that Mr. DeJesus posed a threat to the family and may have been behind the extortion attempt. But the judge, Bill Mathesius, has shown little patience for such questioning and has repeatedly cut off and chastised Dr. Nyce's lawyer. At one point this week, the prosecutor, Doris Galuchie, exclaimed, ''This is a trial within a trial within a trial, and it's so irrelevant.'' Judge Mathesius added a day later that he did not want to be ''creating a thousand little trials.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
