<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prosecutors Challenge Psychiatric Defense of Mother Charged in Girl's Death</title>
    <meta content="24santiago" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/24/nyregion/24santiago.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1835103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Models (Professional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Nixzmary</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDA1530F937A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prosecutors Challenge Psychiatric Defense of Mother Charged in Girl's Death</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prosecutors Challenge Psychiatric Defense of Mother Charged in Girl’s Death</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors sought yesterday to challenge a psychiatric defense offered by the mother of Nixzmary Brown, a 7-year-old girl who was found beaten and starved to death in her family's Brooklyn apartment in January 2006.</p>
        <p>If successful, the move could prove to be a deciding factor in a murder case that has drawn an outpouring of grief, called top city officials to account and prompted changes to the child welfare system, all without ever going to trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The move could prove to be a deciding factor in a murder case that has drawn an outpouring of grief, called top city officials to account and prompted changes to the child welfare system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prosecutors sought yesterday to challenge a psychiatric defense offered by the mother of Nixzmary Brown, a 7-year-old girl who was found beaten and starved to death in her family's Brooklyn apartment in January 2006.</p>
        <p>If successful, the move could prove to be a deciding factor in a murder case that has drawn an outpouring of grief, called top city officials to account and prompted changes to the child welfare system, all without ever going to trial.</p>
        <p>''Are there any other pending issues?'' asked the judge overseeing the case, L. Priscilla Hall of State Supreme Court in Brooklyn. After a lengthy exchange in which it was determined that there were none, Justice Hall said, ''We're going to be thinking about a trial date pretty soon, then.''</p>
        <p>The girl's mother, Nixzaliz Santiago, and stepfather, Cesar Rodriguez, were charged with murder and manslaughter after they were accused of hitting Nixzmary, tying her up in their Bedford-Stuyvesant home and failing to provide her with medical attention. In a series of hearings, lawyers for Ms. Santiago have sought to establish a defense based on battered woman syndrome.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Rodriguez appeared in court separately from his wife. Though far less complex, his case has moved no faster. A hearing on Tuesday, set for his lawyers to challenge the admissibility of evidence gathered by the police, was cut short because a witness was unavailable. Mr. Rodriguez's handcuffs were never even removed.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Ms. Santiago have submitted a psychological report describing her as depressed, paranoid and unintelligent. They hired a psychologist, Joe Scroppo, who wrote that those factors ''significantly impaired her capacity to realistically appreciate and respond to the nature and extent of the events that were occurring around her.''</p>
        <p>A psychiatrist hired by the state interviewed Ms. Santiago yesterday, the first step in an examination set to continue next month. At trial, prosecutors could use their own expert's findings to contrast those made by Dr. Scroppo, but first they made a pre-emptive challenge.</p>
        <p>An assistant district attorney, Jane S. Meyers, argued yesterday that testimony about battered woman syndrome had been admitted in New York courts only to explain cases like a violent reaction against an abusive husband. Never, Ms. Meyers wrote, has such testimony been allowed to show that a defendant ''was incapable of forming the culpable mental states required for the commission of the crimes.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers requested a hearing that would place the burden of proof on defense lawyers to demonstrate a scientific basis for Dr. Scroppo's conclusions. Dr. Scroppo did not return calls seeking comment. Justice Hall did not rule on the request, allowing lawyers for Ms. Santiago time to respond in writing.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Abrams, a lawyer for Ms. Santiago, said he would file motions to exclude testimony by Nixzmary's siblings and evidence obtained through interviews with them.</p>
        <p>Justice Hall set a hearing for April 26 to address the remaining pretrial issues. ''I want to see you,'' she said, ''because I don't want too much time to pass.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
