<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mubarak Warns Israel to Stay Out of Gulf Conflict</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EGYPT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUBARAK, HOSNI (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D61739F933A25752C0A967958260" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mubarak Warns Israel to Stay Out of Gulf Conflict</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, Jan. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the fear of a Persian Gulf war sent thousands of Egyptians fleeing Iraq, President Hosni Mubarak warned Israel this week to stay out of the conflict, saying he would revise his policies on the crisis if Israel became embroiled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubarak's comments on Tuesday, reported in Egyptian newspapers today, reflected worries in many Arab countries that Israeli military involvement could transform the crisis into an Arab-Israeli dispute, splintering the anti-Iraqi Arab coalition. Egypt is the only Arab country formally at peace with Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the fear of a Persian Gulf war sent thousands of Egyptians fleeing Iraq, President Hosni Mubarak warned Israel this week to stay out of the conflict, saying he would revise his policies on the crisis if Israel became embroiled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubarak's comments on Tuesday, reported in Egyptian newspapers today, reflected worries in many Arab countries that Israeli military involvement could transform the crisis into an Arab-Israeli dispute, splintering the anti-Iraqi Arab coalition. Egypt is the only Arab country formally at peace with Israel.</p>
        <p>"We will not permit an Israeli involvement, or a military involvement in the gulf crisis," the Egyptian leader told a gathering of writers and intellectuals, according to newspaper reports and people at the gathering. "I do not think Israel would get involved, but if it did, Egypt would take a different position."</p>
        <p>He did not elaborate on the threatened policy shift. Many diplomats here have said it would be politically difficult, if not impossible, for Egypt or any other Arab country to be seen to be fighting alongside Israel against another Arab country. Disagreement on Missiles</p>
        <p>Echoing the views of some of his senior military advisers, Mr. Mubarak said he did not believe Iraqi missiles had the range to strike Israel from inside Iraq -- an assessment disputed by the United States.</p>
        <p>Iraq's principal missile is the Soviet-made Scud-B, which has a range of around 200 miles with a full payload of 1,000 pounds of explosives, according to accounts here. Iraq's westernmost borders are about 250 miles from Tel Aviv.</p>
        <p>During its eight-year war with Iran, Iraq extended the range to around 300 miles by reducing the weight of the warhead, but the modification reduced the weapon's accuracy. The missiles were fired at Teheran, the Iranian capital, but many of them malfunctioned, according to Egyptian accounts.</p>
        <p>Iraq also maintains it has developed a missile with a 400-mile range, but it is not clear whether it has been deployed or merely tested.</p>
        <p>"If war broke out, the American blow would be deadly, and Israel would not intervene because Saddam's missiles would not reach her," Mr. Mubarak said. Egyptians Aided Iraq Army</p>
        <p>Egypt's assessment of Iraqi missile abilities is partly based on reports by the many Egyptian military advisers attached to the Iraqi Army during the war with Iran, which ended with a cease-fire in August 1988. But some diplomats question the extent of their knowledge, and say Cairo may be underestimating the range of Iraq's missiles.</p>
        <p>At Egyptian ports, in the meantime, officials reported a dramatic increase in the number of Egyptian workers returning from Iraq and said the number could swell to 50,000 in next few days.</p>
        <p>Over the last nine days, officials said, 25,000 Egyptians had fled Iraq, adding to the 300,000 who left immediately after the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2. Port officials said they expected a flood of Egyptians in the next few days as the Jan. 15 date set by the United Nations for possible military action against Iraq approaches.</p>
        <p>Before the crisis, more than 1.5 million Egyptians were thought to be working in Kuwait and Iraq, over one million of them in Iraq. Despite the exodus last year, hundreds of thousands stayed on in Iraq despite much reported harassment of them by the Iraqi authorities. Main Arab Ally of U.S.</p>
        <p>Egypt is the most prominent Arab ally of the United States and the biggest Arab contributor to the multinational force assembled in the Persian Gulf to confront Iraq.</p>
        <p>Along with Syria, Iraq's longstanding adversary, it has formed a political axis with Saudi Arabia representing the so-called moderate Arabs demanding Baghdad's unconditional withdrawal from Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Syria has sent commandos and pledged an armored division of 14,000 men to Saudi Arabia. Egypt has sent some 4,000 commandos to the gulf and has deployed a mechanized division in Saudi Arabia. Additionally, an Egyptian armored division is still being deployed to bring Egypt's total troop strength to 35,000, according to official accounts.</p>
        <p>The divisions are said to be the most modernized in Egypt's 450,000-man army and use weapons, including tanks, artillery and armored personnel carriers, supplied under American aid programs supposed to wean Cairo's military from its one-time dependence on Soviet equipment.</p>
        <p>Syria's troops, by contrast, are Soviet-supplied, a result of the cold war rivalries that spurred Moscow to arm both the Syrian and Iraqi armies in the contest with both Israel and the United States.  Won't Fight on Iraqi Soil</p>
        <p>Technically, the Egyptian and Syrian units have been sent to Saudi Arabia to defend the kingdom against Iraqi attack, and both have insisted that they would not fight on Iraqi soil, in part because of the political sensitivities of a region deeply suspicious of Western intentions in turning one Arab against another.</p>
        <p>Diplomats here say, however, that both Egyptian and Syrian forces would deploy in the event of war to support American and other Western allies in a ground offensive to drive Iraqi forces out of Kuwait, probably after sustained aerial bombardment by United States and other Western air forces of Iraqi positions there.</p>
        <p>"The view is that if you sit down at the table with your chips, you are committed to playing the game," a knowledgeable diplomat said, referring to Egyptian military intentions.</p>
        <p>The readiness to join hostilities applies to fighting for Kuwait, however, not to a subsequent push into Iraq, Egyptian analysts say. "We would not fight in Iraq," said a well-versed Egyptian politician, who spoke in return for anonymity. "That would be politically impossible."  CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
