<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Finds Handles Are Faulty On Some Airliner Emergency Exits</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MD-80 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DC-9 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLIGHT ATTENDANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTHWEST AIRLINES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCDONNELL DOUGLAS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flight Attendants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE1E3FF933A25752C0A967958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Finds Handles Are Faulty On Some Airliner Emergency Exits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr., Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emergency exits on hundreds of McDonnell Douglas airliners have faulty handles that can snap in two if they are pulled hard the wrong direction by somebody trying to open the exits, Federal safety investigators said today.</p>
        <p>A handle of this type was broken on a DC-9 that burned on the runway in Detroit in December after the plane collided with another airliner. With no way to open the emergency exit, two people trapped on the plane died of smoke inhalation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emergency exits on hundreds of McDonnell Douglas airliners have faulty handles that can snap in two if they are pulled hard the wrong direction by somebody trying to open the exits, Federal safety investigators said today.</p>
        <p>A handle of this type was broken on a DC-9 that burned on the runway in Detroit in December after the plane collided with another airliner. With no way to open the emergency exit, two people trapped on the plane died of smoke inhalation.</p>
        <p>The National Transportation Safety Board, which is not expected to complete its investigation for several months, issued an urgent recommendation to the Federal Aviation Administration calling for all such aircraft to be inspected and said the handles should be redesigned.</p>
        <p>The safety board has no authority to enforce its recommendations, but the F.A.A. does.  F.A.A. to Seek Redesign</p>
        <p>Anthony J. Broderick, associate admistrator of the aviation agency, said airlines would be ordered this week to inspect the handles on all MD-80 and DC-9 aircraft, the two planes that use the handle. He said that the agency would also call for a new design for the handles and that the McDonnell Douglas Corporation was already beginning to work on the problem. Mr. Broderick said the design change could take months.</p>
        <p>John Thom, a spokesman for McDonnell Douglas, said that the company was performing further tests and that if the part needed to be redesigned the change would be made as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thom said that in decades of use the handles had never before been known to fail.</p>
        <p>There are 1,741 DC-9's and MD-80's, both built by McDonnell Douglas, in service worldwide, more than half of them operated by United States airlines. American Airlines, Northwest, Continental Airlines, USAir, Eastern Air Lines, Trans World Airlines and Delta Air Lines have the largest fleets of those planes in the United States.  'Serious Deficiencies' Found</p>
        <p>The board's recommendation cited "serious deficiencies" in the design of the handles used to open the emergency exits from inside or outside the planes.</p>
        <p>In the Detroit accident on Dec. 3, a flight attendent and a passenger on a Northwest Airlines DC-9 were killed trying to escape through the emergency exit at the tail of the jet, which burned on the runway at Detroit Metropolitan Airport after it entered the wrong runway in dense fog and collided with a jet that was taking off.</p>
        <p>Six other people on the DC-9, were killed and 22 people were injured.</p>
        <p>The handle that opens the emergency exit apparently snapped in the accident or earlier when it was pulled in the wrong direction, the safety board said. The board said it was not possible to determine whether the handle snapped as the flight attendent tried to open the exit or whether it had broken earlier and was still broken at the time of the accident.</p>
        <p>Northwest and other airlines have inspected their planes since the discovery of the broken door handle several weeks ago, but Mr. Broderick said the inspections would have to be repeated in light of other findings in the investigation.</p>
        <p>In a test of a similar handle after the accident, the board's investigators found that the shaft could break under "relatively low" stress but not if the handle was being operated normally, by pulling it straight outward from the door.  Jamming Is Seen as Possible</p>
        <p>Further, the safety board's tests suggested that wear and tear on the handle, caused by rubbing with other parts of the mechanism, might allow it to jam in a way that required extra force to be used to open it. A hard pull in the wrong direction then might snap the handle.</p>
        <p>Metallurgists from the safety board who examined the broken handle taken from the airplane involved in the accident determined that it had been worn in this way by contact with other mechanical parts during normal use, the board reported today.</p>
        <p>A second handle provided by the airline had a similar flaw on its shaft, which the board said was "much larger and deeper" than the wear found on the handle from the jet involved in the accident.</p>
        <p>Until the part is redesigned to prevent undue wear and to strengthen it, the board said, airline cabin crews should get special training in how to correctly pull the metal handle.</p>
        <p>The problem with the handle does not extend to other doors on the planes, which are used not only for escaping in emergencies but also for routinely getting on and off the planes. Other types of planes are not affected.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
