<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Prices Fluctuate Wildly, Then Settle Just 9¦ Higher</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="MARKETS' DAY OF WIDE SWINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IRAQ-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF133CF933A25752C0A967958260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Prices Fluctuate Wildly, Then Settle Just 9¦ Higher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oil prices took a wild ride yesterday but came to rest just about where they started. When Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d announced his disappointing news in Geneva just before 2 P.M., the price jumped nearly 30 percent in five minutes, rushing from $24 a barrel to $31.</p>
        <p>It was the widest price swing within one day's trading on the New York Mercantile Exchange since trading in crude oil began in March 1983.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oil prices took a wild ride yesterday but came to rest just about where they started. When Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d announced his disappointing news in Geneva just before 2 P.M., the price jumped nearly 30 percent in five minutes, rushing from $24 a barrel to $31.</p>
        <p>It was the widest price swing within one day's trading on the New York Mercantile Exchange since trading in crude oil began in March 1983.</p>
        <p>Worldwide, the price bounced throughout the day. Early in the morning, before futures trading opened in New York at 9:45, prices in this country and in London were slightly higher because of fears that war was likely. But then the meeting between Mr. Baker and Tariq Aziz, the Iraqi Foreign Minister, lasted longer than the market had expected, with reports of progress. Suddenly traders were afraid of holding oil or contracts for oil that would lose value because of peace.</p>
        <p>Then came word, which proved incorrect, that the two men would hold a joint news conference, and the market went lower, expecting an agreement. But when Mr. Baker said the talks had been inconclusive, "the market exploded," said Richard D. Donovan, senior vice president at Lehman Brothers. Traders became convinced that the oil or contracts they had sold in the morning would be worth much more later on because of war, and they all turned to buy.</p>
        <p>"It's staggering," said Mr. Donovan, who pointed out that oil is the world's biggest commodity. Describing what a move that size would mean on other markets, he said, "Can you imagine the Dow Jones going up 750 points in five minutes? Or gold going up $100?"</p>
        <p>Theodore R. Eck, chief economist at Amoco, called the jump "phenomenal."</p>
        <p>"It just tells us there's extreme uncertainty and the folly of trying to forecast prices," he said.</p>
        <p>Despite the size of the trading range, $7.65, the day ended with crude for February delivery up only 9 cents, at $27.26 a barrel. The surge had been preceded by a huge selloff, and the market, which frequently overshoots its mark, fell back after reaching its peak.</p>
        <p>The record change in closing price from one day's session to the next is $5.41, set last Oct. 22. Trading was heavy yesterday, at 126,000 contracts, but short of the record of 185,000 set last Aug. 7.  Petroleum Products Advance</p>
        <p>Heating oil for delivery next month closed at 77.09 a gallon, up 2.79 cents, and unleaded gasoline closed at 73.31 cents, up 3.13 cents.</p>
        <p>For some traders, however, the volatility yesterday was evidence that in a war, the market could test the price-movement limit recently set in place by the exchange -- a move of $15 a barrel in one day.</p>
        <p>"If the market can move $7 in five minutes on a just a press conference, you can well imagine that it could do more in a war," said Nauman Barakat, a vice president at Merrill Lynch. "It's certainly possible that the $15 limit could be reached."</p>
        <p>Another analyst, Peter C. Beutel, said, "The thing that has made this market so volatile is the black-and-white nature of the negotiations." Mr. Beutel, who is with the Pegasus Econometric Group, said, "There was no place to be in a middle ground."</p>
        <p>But other market-watchers said there was meaning to be gleaned from the fact that the swing was not even larger. At the Petroleum Finance Company, a Washington-based consulting group, J. Robinson West, the president, said, "Although we may be closer to war, timewise and in terms of options, the price was $10 lower than the peak reached earlier."</p>
        <p>The reason, he said, was that the trading yesterday "was not an international economic panic, just a traders' panic." When prices peaked above $40 a barrel in October, he said, "all eyes realized that there was a quantum change in trading oil, the fundamental commodity of international trade." This time, he said, it was "traders watching short-term spikes."</p>
        <p>Vahan Zanoyan, an analyst at the same company, said that if peace actually prevailed, prices would decline below yesterday's $24, and if war came, they would rise above $31.</p>
        <p>This is not the first instance of a huge increase in the price of oil, but the market yesterday was substantially different from the last two crises -- during the Arab oil embargo of 1973-74 and following the fall of the Shah of Iran in 1979. This price revolution is televised, on thousands of monitor screens around the world, making the volatility far more obvious and inviting participants -- oil producers, oil users and speculators -- to join in, perhaps driving the changes even further.</p>
        <p>But the market is working well, said Nachama Jacobovitz, a spokeswoman for the exchange. No matter what the price at any moment, she said, "people were able to lock in the prices they wanted to."  MARKETS' DAY OF WIDE SWINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
