<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gypsy Caravan Returns, Powered Up</title>
    <meta content="16GYPS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/16/arts/music/16GYPS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1334225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gypsy Caravan 2</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">City Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DB1E3FF935A25753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gypsy Caravan Returns, Powered Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gypsy Caravan Returns, Powered Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews concert by Gypsy Caravan 2 at City Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With flashy clothes, a huge voice and the ability to wring larger-than-life emotions from her songs, Esma Redzepova stole the show at Gypsy Caravan 2 at City Center on Saturday night. She's the kind of belter who can sob through one song, singing about the pain of a young woman sold into a loveless marriage, and then immediately promise to make everybody dance.</p>
        <p>Esma, as she is known, is from Macedonia, one stop on the path that the Rom people, or Gypsies, traveled from Rajasthan in India to Andalusia in Spain. Gypsy Caravan 2, which is touring the United States, covers four points on that path. The Rajasthani group Maharaja, formerly Musafir, represented its beginning: Indian desert traditions that the Roma may have carried with them. Both Maharaja and the dancer Antonio el Pipa's flamenco ensemble, from Andalusia, were part of the World Music Institute's Gypsy Caravan in 1999. This sequel introduced Esma and another powerhouse, the Romanian brass band Fanfare Ciocarlia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With flashy clothes, a huge voice and the ability to wring larger-than-life emotions from her songs, Esma Redzepova stole the show at Gypsy Caravan 2 on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With flashy clothes, a huge voice and the ability to wring larger-than-life emotions from her songs, Esma Redzepova stole the show at Gypsy Caravan 2 at City Center on Saturday night. She's the kind of belter who can sob through one song, singing about the pain of a young woman sold into a loveless marriage, and then immediately promise to make everybody dance.</p>
        <p>Esma, as she is known, is from Macedonia, one stop on the path that the Rom people, or Gypsies, traveled from Rajasthan in India to Andalusia in Spain. Gypsy Caravan 2, which is touring the United States, covers four points on that path. The Rajasthani group Maharaja, formerly Musafir, represented its beginning: Indian desert traditions that the Roma may have carried with them. Both Maharaja and the dancer Antonio el Pipa's flamenco ensemble, from Andalusia, were part of the World Music Institute's Gypsy Caravan in 1999. This sequel introduced Esma and another powerhouse, the Romanian brass band Fanfare Ciocarlia.</p>
        <p>Musicologists continue to debate the unity of Gypsy music and dance across its geographic span, and Gypsy Caravan 2 suggested some affinities. All the singers shared a raw, melismatic, unrestrained delivery. Briskly subdivided rhythms from drums, handclaps or clattering flamenco heels were ubiquitous. Both Esma and the members of Maharaja wore red turbans and plenty of glitter; upraised arms and delicately turned wrist gestures appeared in dances. Yet those were details of styles as disparate as Eastern Europe, India and Spain.</p>
        <p>Esma had a pop star's stagecraft. Like faithful retainers under her command, her trumpeter and clarinetist stepped forward to play slow introductory passages or toss phrases back at her. She could be queenly and tragic, prolonging and fluttering a sustained note with sorrowful devotion, or as jovial as a wedding singer getting the party started. Her group included an untraditional synthesizer that backed slow, incantatory songs with a phantom choir or, in uptempo songs, took the place of a tuba.</p>
        <p>Fanfare Ciocarlia had tubas aplenty: four of various sizes, which pumped out limber oompah chords while trumpeters and clarinetists raced through hairpin-turn melodies, then tripled the velocity for solos. In one tune the byplay between trumpet and clarinet took some bluesy turns suggesting New Orleans jazz. Now and then the tempo eased for a vocal, with the horns as a brass chorale. But for most of the set Fanfare Ciocarlia was a band of speed demons, laughing its way across the bumpiest musical terrain.</p>
        <p>Maharaja's members represent three different Rajasthani peoples: Langas, Manghaniyars and a Sapera dancer. They played sustained, ragalike melodies on sarangis (bowed lutes) and tunes in the style of qawwali (Sufi devotional music) that worked up from improvisations to hearty choruses. The crowd-pleasers were Maharaja's dancers: Sayeri, whose sinuous snake-charming dance was backed by the nasal double-reed aloogoza, and Harish Khan, a man dressed as a woman in a gleaming red-and-white-striped dress with a blue belt, saluting America as he twirled on his knees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pipa brought the contrasts of his group's flamenco -- hoarsely impassioned outbursts from his aunt, Juana la del Pipa, above Juan Moneo's adamantly strummed guitar -- to his own body. As his feet pattered furiously, his upper body moved with stately deliberation, tracing arcs as taut as a longbow. Near the end of the concert the Andalusians and the Indians collaborated on ''Maharaja Flamenca,'' adding flamenco chords to an Indian drone as the rhythms veered from East to West. Then all four groups got together, and Esma seized center stage with a voice that demanded to be heard.</p>
        <p>WORLD MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
