<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Startling Shift, Guatemala Makes Rights Aide President</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="613855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GUATEMALA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDEN, TIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE LEON, RAMIRO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC1731F934A35755C0A965958260" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Startling Shift, Guatemala Makes Rights Aide President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDEN, TIM</byline>
      <dateline>GUATEMALA, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a turn that astonished many Guatemalans even after days of political turmoil, the Government's crusading human rights ombudsman, a frequent critic of the military, was sworn in as President early today.</p>
        <p>Less than two weeks ago, the former ombudsman, Ramiro de Leon Carpio, was sneaking out the back of his home to escape a squad of military policemen who arrived as Jorge Serrano Elias, then the President, seized nearly dictatorial powers. In a Delicate Position</p>
        <p>The armed forces overthrew Mr. Serrano on Tuesday with support from business leaders, politicians and others, including Mr. de Leon Carpio. But when the Attorney General of Human Rights, as he was formerly titled, first emerged as a candidate to finish the remaining half of Mr. Serrano's five-year term, politicians said they discounted him as unacceptable to the army high command.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a turn that astonished many Guatemalans even after days of political turmoil, the Government's crusading human rights ombudsman, a frequent critic of the military, was sworn in as President early today.</p>
        <p>Less than two weeks ago, the former ombudsman, Ramiro de Leon Carpio, was sneaking out the back of his home to escape a squad of military policemen who arrived as Jorge Serrano Elias, then the President, seized nearly dictatorial powers. In a Delicate Position</p>
        <p>The armed forces overthrew Mr. Serrano on Tuesday with support from business leaders, politicians and others, including Mr. de Leon Carpio. But when the Attorney General of Human Rights, as he was formerly titled, first emerged as a candidate to finish the remaining half of Mr. Serrano's five-year term, politicians said they discounted him as unacceptable to the army high command.</p>
        <p>The eventual triumph of Mr. de Leon Carpio, 51, seemed to mirror the situation of Guatemala's civilians in their long struggle with the political weight of the armed forces, which ruled the country almost continuously from 1954, when the elected Government was overthrown by a Washington-backed military coup, until 1986. It was hopeful and resonantly symbolic, but also incomplete and perhaps unstable.</p>
        <p>"His position is extremely difficult and delicate," said Tracy Ulltveit-Moe, a researcher who has long monitored Guatemala for the human rights organization Amnesty International. "You can't be very sure whether, first, he's going to be able to stay in office. But there's also the difficulty of responding to all of the hopes that this has raised."</p>
        <p>As late as Saturday afternoon, business and political leaders said they were confident of having obtained the votes in Congress to elect a more moderate candidate, Arturo Herbruger Asturias, the 81-year-old head of the federal electoral court.</p>
        <p>But with Mr. de Leon Carpio's name ringing from the galleries of the somber stone chamber built by one of Guatemala's many military dictators, legislators gave him a narrow majority on their first secret ballot. He was still more than a dozen votes short of the required two-thirds vote in the 116-seat legislature. But as congressional leaders recessed to negotiate, Mr. Herbruger telephoned to withdraw.</p>
        <p>Before the Legislature voted again on Mr. de Leon Carpio, two representatives said, the telephone rang on the podium where the President of Congress sat. They said it was a senior military official, calling to say the army would accept its former antagonist as its new Commander in Chief. The Congress president, Jose Lobo Dubon, said he did not take such a call, but had received the same message from the Defense Minister earlier in the day.</p>
        <p>Pulling on the blue-and-white presidential sash, Mr. de Leon Carpio insisted in his inaugural speech to Congress that "the feeling of living in democracy is rooted in the Guatemalan people."</p>
        <p>But the events of the last two weeks have called such beliefs sharply into question, and the hard choices that Mr. de Leon Carpio will face began to present themselves immediately.</p>
        <p>As he arrived at the neo-classical Congress building nearly an hour past midnight, his audience was no more contained than the crowd at a wrestling match. Students and union members shook the chamber with demands for the dismissal of corrupt officials of Congress, the courts and the former Serrano Government.</p>
        <p>"Depuracion!" the crowd chanted again and again, using the Spanish word for purification or purge. "Resign! Resign! Resign!"</p>
        <p>They shouted as well for the prosecution of military leaders who supported Mr. Serrano's seizure of power and then ousted him, then backed an attempted takeover by his Vice President, Gustavo Espina Salguero, only to force Mr. Espina to resign.</p>
        <p>In his inaugural, Mr. de Leon Carpio mentioned neither the military nor the proposed laws that would give amnesty to various groups of the officials under public fire. And as he emerged from the legislative chamber, buoyed on a mass of supporters and police guards, he quickly backed away from the demands for prosecution that he had supported in days past.</p>
        <p>"After a crisis like the one we have just come through, we cannot have revenge," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Leon Carpio's speech drew only one strong ovation, when he vowed to do away with the tens of millions of dollars in confidential discretionary funds budgeted to the presidency, money that Mr. Serrano and his predecessor, Vinicio Cerezo Arevalo, were widely accused of having plundered for their own gain.</p>
        <p>Several analysts predicted that Mr. de Leon Carpio's political strength in Guatemala would depend partly on his success in bringing the country a more democratic reputation abroad. Although civilian leaders declared a final victory over the military when Mr. Espina was forced to resign and Mr. de Leon Carpio was chosen, the last two weeks also laid bare the military's continuing political power.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Leon Carpio's remarks seemed to reflect the same analysis. He called on foreign governments to renew and increase the aid to Guatemala that they suspended after Mr. Serrano -- who was elected to a five-year term in January 1991 -- dissolved Congress and the Supreme Court on May 25. Mr. de Leon Carpio also asked that the countries lift their threats of economic sanction.</p>
        <p>United States officials responded almost immediately. "We welcome a legal and peaceful constitutional resolution of this crisis, and we're looking forward to working with this Government," the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs, Bernard W. Aronson, told reporters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
