<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Learned Opposition to New Disney Park</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="686756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMUSEMENT PARKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIRGINIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PROTECT HISTORIC AMERICA</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DISNEY, WALT, CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED91039F931A25756C0A962958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Learned Opposition to New Disney Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prominent historians and authors with a special interest in the Civil War have formed a group to oppose the Walt Disney Company's planned theme park in a region of northern Virginia of particular historical significance. At a news conference today, one member after another decried the project as a calamitous mistake.</p>
        <p>"We have so little left that's authentic and real," said David McCullough, a biographer and historian. "To replace what we have with plastic, contrived history, mechanical history is almost sacrilege."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prominent historians and authors with a special interest in the Civil War have formed a group to oppose the Walt Disney Company's planned theme park in a region of northern Virginia of particular historical significance. At a news conference today, one member after another decried the project as a calamitous mistake.</p>
        <p>"We have so little left that's authentic and real," said David McCullough, a biographer and historian. "To replace what we have with plastic, contrived history, mechanical history is almost sacrilege."</p>
        <p>The new group, Protect Historic America, said that the 3,000-acre site for the park, Disney's America, in the hills and farmland between Washington and the Blue Ridge Mountains, would be situated within an hour's drive of 13 historic towns, 16 Civil War battle sites and 17 historic districts. 'Commercial Blitzkrieg'</p>
        <p>As a result, they said, the theme park, planned as a tribute to American history with a faux Civil War village and fort, among other attractions, would overpower the region -- and with more than just its own complex of hotels, shops and other amenities. Standing near enlarged photographs showing the urban sprawl that grew around Disneyland in Southern California and Disney World in central Florida, Mr. McCullough and others said they feared the region around the theme park would be flooded with motels, restaurants, gas stations and souvenir shops.</p>
        <p>"Once this commercial blitzkrieg comes," Mr. McCullough said, "it will never be the same again."</p>
        <p>The general manager for Disney's America, Mark Pacala, said from his office in Gainesville, Va.: "I think it's truly unfortunate that a group of historians, many we admire and respect, would prejudge Disney's America, drawing incorrect conclusions about out historical content and the potential impact on the surrounding community."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pacala said that Disney's America had historians on its side, according to The Associated Press, but declined to name any other than two hired as consultants: Eric Foner of Columbia University and James Oliver Horton of George Washington University. Pull of 19,000 Jobs</p>
        <p>Comparing Disney's America to the Disney park in Florida, he added, "This is planned as a six- to eight-hour experience. Orlando is a four- to seven-day experience, with lodging, food and shops. That's already in Washington. This is one tenth the size of Orlando."</p>
        <p>The Disney company announced plans for the park six months ago and won the strong support of Virginia's Governor, George F. Allen, eager for the 19,000 jobs the project would create and the six million visitors a year its backers predict. In March, the State Legislature approved $163 million in subsidies, most of which would be used to improve roads.</p>
        <p>But as plans for the park have proceeded, so has the opposition, with Protect Historic America joining citizens' groups and environmentalists in raising questions.</p>
        <p>Citing the local, state and Federal studies that have to be completed, Christopher G. Miller, a lawyer with the Piedmont Environmental Council in Warrenton, Va., said that each review would be "subject to very active public participation, and I can assure you the historical concerns are a very significant part of it." 'Blood, Glory, Hopes and Pain'</p>
        <p>The Protect Historic America group includes more than 30 writers, journalists, researchers and scholars bound by their passion for the region. They include James McPherson, a history professor at Princeton, author of several books about the Civil War and president of the group; C. Vann Woodward, retired Yale professor and a historian of the South; Shelby Foote, the Civil War historian, and Arthur Schlesinger Jr., the author of 16 books about American history.</p>
        <p>Another member of the group, Roger Wilkins, a professor of history and American culture at George Mason University outside Washington, said he often encourages students to visit the Civil War battlefields "to soak up the blood, the glory, the hopes and the pain of this country" by imagining the events that took place.</p>
        <p>Describing himself as a descendant of Virginia slaves and a member of an American family with roots into the 17th century, Mr. Wilkens said the theme park and the development it would attract would besmirch a "sacred ground where men fought and died for what this country is today."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
