<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PARENT &amp; CHILD</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TWINS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUTNER, LAWRENCE (DR)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PARENT &amp; CHILD (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D8153DF932A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PARENT &amp; CHILD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Kutner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KUTNER, LAWRENCE (DR)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of every 80 births results in twins. To the parents who raise them, twins bring a special set of frustrations, challenges and rewards. The relationship between twins is both a bond and a rivalry that begins in the womb and lasts until they die. For the one in three sets of twins who are identical, the closeness can lead to uncanny skills at communicating with each other. During infancy and toddlerhood, they may even develop their own language.</p>
        <p>The ways parents have been advised to raise twins have shifted dramatically in recent decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of every 80 births results in twins. To the parents who raise them, twins bring a special set of frustrations, challenges and rewards. The relationship between twins is both a bond and a rivalry that begins in the womb and lasts until they die. For the one in three sets of twins who are identical, the closeness can lead to uncanny skills at communicating with each other. During infancy and toddlerhood, they may even develop their own language.</p>
        <p>The ways parents have been advised to raise twins have shifted dramatically in recent decades.</p>
        <p>"Until the 1970's, parents and professionals were comfortable treating twins as a single unit instead of as individuals," said Dr. Judith Landau-Stanton, an associate professor of psychiatry and family medicine at the University of Rochester, and the mother of 20-year-old identical twins.</p>
        <p>"We now know that treating them identically can delay their physical and emotional development, their development of language, and possibly lead to a lower I.Q.," she said.</p>
        <p>All cultures recognize twins as something special. Even fraternal twins, whether they are of the same or opposite sex, receive extra attention from both family and strangers. Yet not all the attention is positive.</p>
        <p>"There's a lot of mythology associated with twins, who've been used since before the Bible as symbols for good and evil," said Patricia Maxwell Malmstrom, the mother of 17-year-old identical twin girls. She is the director of Twin Services in Berkeley, Calif., an education and social service agency for families expecting or rearing twins, triplets and quadruplets.</p>
        <p>"Some parents call us when their children are as young as four days old and say that they already know which one is the 'bad' one," Ms. Malmstrom said. "We can see these myths in the beliefs not only of parents but of nurses and teachers as well."</p>
        <p>Being a twin triggers more subtle expectations from most adults. "People expect them to be the same," said Dr. Norman Epstein, an associate professor of family and community development at the University of Maryland at College Park. "They pay more attention to similarities than to differences."</p>
        <p>Sibling rivalry is often more intense in families with twins. Because their intellectual capacities are so close, identical twins can be extremely competitive when it comes to school grades. Their constant competition often includes repeated wrestling matches as well.</p>
        <p>"Physical fights between identical twins can be especially violent and dramatic because each knows exactly how much punishment the other can take," Dr. Landau-Stanton said.</p>
        <p>Being the older brother or sister to newborn twins can be extremely stressful. "It's traumatic enough to be dethroned by a younger sibling," said Dr. Nancy Segal, the assistant director of the Minnesota Center for Twin and Adoption Research at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis. "But when the new arrivals are twins, the extra attention they receive often makes the older child feel ignored."</p>
        <p>She has found that fraternal twin brothers and sisters have special problems as well. Until they reach adolescence, girls tend to be ahead of their twin brothers on measures of physical, social and intellectual development. This reflects the natural differences between boys and girls during preschool and elementary school. But this can be very upsetting to the boys, who feel that they should be able to keep up.</p>
        <p>New studies of twins show the need to respect and encourage their individuality while acknowledging the special qualities of their unusual relationship. "If they're constantly treated as a unit, they're at risk for each developing half the skills they need for life," Dr. Landau-Stanton said.</p>
        <p>"One may feel responsible for schoolwork while the other handles their social life," she said. "Or one may become more dominant while the other feels obligated to withdraw in proportion. They may run into trouble when they have to face the world alone." TRYING TO TREAT EACH TWIN AS AN INDIVIDUAL</p>
        <p>RESEARCHERS offer several suggestions for parents of twins:</p>
        <p>Pay close attention to the names they are given.</p>
        <p>Their names can have a strong influence on how others respond to them as individuals. "There's a real problem if your children have similar names, like Mary Sue and Mary Jo," said Dr. Nancy Segal, the assistant director of the Minnesota Center for Twin and Adoption Research at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis. "That can lead to later problems developing their individual identities."</p>
        <p>Encourage family members and other adults not to refer to them as "the twins."</p>
        <p>Calling them by one name belittles their distinctiveness and often makes them feel that they are not being accorded the same respect as the other children in their family or classroom.</p>
        <p>"Get them into different play groups and separate classes at school," said Dr. Judith Landau-Stanton, an associate professor of psychiatry and family medicine at the University of Rochester. "That will help teachers and other children see them and treat them as individuals."</p>
        <p>They need to experience new situations both alone and with their twin so that they can take advantage of their special relationship without becoming overly dependent on each other.</p>
        <p>"Encourage your twins to develop separate friendships," Dr. Segal said. "If one of them is invited to a birthday party, the other one doesn't have to go."</p>
        <p>Give other family members ways of telling identical twins apart.</p>
        <p>That can be a simple as parting their hair on different sides.  "Something as simple as buying them separate wardrobes can make a big difference in the way identical twins are treated by outsiders," Dr. Landau-Stanton said.</p>
        <p>Don't force them to share possessions.</p>
        <p>Though they will end up trading practically every toy and piece of clothing they own, it is important that they know that certain objects are theirs and not their twin's. Put nametags or other marks on clothing and toys so they can tell which ones belong to whom.</p>
        <p>"They need to feel that they own certain things before they can feel comfortable sharing anything," said Patricia Maxwell Malmstrom, the mother of 17-year-old identical twin girls and the director of Twin Services in Berkeley, Calif. "If they have to share everything, they'll become extremely competitive."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
