<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese In Ministry Cut Pay</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BROKERS AND BROKERAGE FIRMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND
REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NOMURA SECURITIES CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NIKKO SECURITIES CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DAIWA SECURITIES CO LTD</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">YAMAICHI SECURITIES CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANGER, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC153CF932A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese In Ministry Cut Pay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANGER, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After weeks of denying that the Government bore any responsibility for Japan's giant stock scandal, the Finance Minister and several of his top deputies today cut their salaries by 10 percent and conceded that they had failed to guard against improprieties in the securities industry.</p>
        <p>The admission was the first formal acknowledgement that the Government's regulation of the securities industry had contributed to the stock scandal. The salary reduction is similar to one that top officials of the country's four biggest securities houses said on Monday they were imposing on themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After weeks of denying that the Government bore any responsibility for Japan's giant stock scandal, the Finance Minister and several of his top deputies today cut their salaries by 10 percent and conceded that they had failed to guard against improprieties in the securities industry.</p>
        <p>The admission was the first formal acknowledgement that the Government's regulation of the securities industry had contributed to the stock scandal. The salary reduction is similar to one that top officials of the country's four biggest securities houses said on Monday they were imposing on themselves.</p>
        <p>Government officials said the action by the Finance Minister, Ryutaro Hashimoto, marked the first time a Cabinet minister had returned part of his pay to take responsibility for the conduct of his ministry. Mr. Hashimoto receives about $10,000 a month. 2 Deputies Take Cuts</p>
        <p>Mr. Hashimoto said that Hiroshi Yasuda, a deputy who holds the highest-ranking nonpolitical job in the ministry, and Nobuhiko Matsuno, head of the securities bureau, would take similar pay cuts. The cuts remain in effect for three months. Two other ministry officials were "disciplined," he said.</p>
        <p>The ministry's announcement came on the first of four days during which the four biggest brokerages -- Nomura Securities, Nikko Securities, Daiwa Securities and Yamaichi Securities -- "voluntarily" suspended virtually all transactions with corporate clients to atone for the scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hashimoto's salary cut was only the latest in a series of ritual apologies and resignations that have filled Japan's television screens in recent weeks in an effort to quell mounting public indignation over admissions by the four brokerages that they had paid huge sums of "compensation" -- now totaling nearly $900 million -- to big corporate clients for losses they suffered in the stock market. No such compensation was offered to small investors, who also lost huge sums as the Tokyo Stock Exchange plummeted over the last two years.</p>
        <p>Almost nightly, some of the most respected leaders of Japanese business have appeared on television bowing and apologizing. But there is mounting criticism in the Japanese press that much of the contrition is mere window dressing, part of a carefully orchestrated effort to end the scandal with symbolism rather than real reforms.</p>
        <p>"This is a punitive measure I am imposing upon myself," Mr. Hashimoto said today. "It's very regrettable that the ministry did not properly control the market."</p>
        <p>Officials of Nomura, the world's largest brokerage, have charged that the ministry knew of its compensation practices; the ministry maintains that it had banned such payments through an "administrative guidance" and was lied to by the securities firms, which said they had not made such payments.</p>
        <p>Asahi Shimbun, one of Japan's largest and most influential dailies, called today for the resignation of Mr. Hashimoto, who has been considered a candidate for Prime Minister. So many former Ministry of Finance officials are now employed in Japan's securities firms, the newspaper said, that the securities industry and the Government regulators "have become, in a broader sense, a family."</p>
        <p>In anticipation of the London economic summit meeting next week, Japanese officials have said they are drawing up plans for legislation to make it illegal for brokerages to compensate clients for their stock market losses. But such legislation seems unlikely to pass any time soon, and it is not clear whether Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu will go to the summit meeting prepared to discuss specific reforms. Many foreigners active in the Tokyo markets say that the scandal proves what they have always contended, that insiders receive tremendous favors that are not available to foreigners or small investors.</p>
        <p>Usually, Japanese Government officials have denied charges of coziness. But today, in the most severe official criticism yet of the Government's performance during the scandal, Makoto Utsumi, the Deputy Minister of Finance for International Affairs, said the criticism was essentially correct. Payments Called Improper</p>
        <p>"We should use this unfortunate event as leverage to get more distance" from the securities industry, Mr. Utsumi said during a meeting with a group of foreign correspondents today. "If we had clearly written laws on these issues, the situation might never have happened." The schemes to compensate big companies for their losses violate no laws, but Mr. Utsumi said that "it is taken for granted as a matter of business ethics" that such payments were improper.</p>
        <p>Mr. Utsumi, however, would not endorse proposals here to create an independent watchdog group, similar to the Securities and Exchange Commission in the United States, to oversee the securities industry. The Ministry of Finance has opposed such a move, analysts say, because it would diminish its own power within the Japanese bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>It is hard to gauge the depth of public resentment over the scandal. But in many respects, the reaction seems stronger than during the Recruit scandal two years ago, in which a number of politicians received shares in a company that was seeking to influence Government decisions. That scandal seemed remote from ordinary investors; in this case, the market appears to have been rigged against small investors and in favor of large ones. No Laws Violated</p>
        <p>But because no laws were violated, the Government says there are few penalities it can impose. "It is like a policeman in a small village who discovers a crime, but lets the suspect go if he agrees not to do it again," the head of a medium-sized industrial company here said today.</p>
        <p>In addition to suspending corporate transactions for four days and reducing salaries of some executives by 10 to 20 percent, Nomura and Nikko also agreed to close operations at their headquarters for four days because of their extensive dealings with organized crime figures. The companies are accused of lending huge sums to leaders of the Japanese underworld and aiding them in questionable stock purchases.</p>
        <p>In Kabutocho, Tokyo's equivalent of Wall Street, the Nikko office was eerily dark today. Nonetheless, the stock market, which has tumbled in the wake of the scandal, climbed today on hopes that Mr. Hashimoto's action would finally put the scandal to rest. It closed at 23,121.30. up 512.34 points, a 2.27 percent rise.</p>
        <p>But the Government's hopes of putting a quick end to the series of revelations seemed likely to fail. Names Not Disclosed</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the securities houses disclosed that the amount of compensation they paid out was almost three times as high as what they had previously admitted. They have still refused to disclose the names of the companies that were the biggest beneficiaries of the compensation scheme, though some names -- including Hitachi Ltd. and the Tokyu Corporation -- have already leaked out.</p>
        <p>Today the police searched the offices of a company controlled by Susumu Ishii, formerly the head of the Inagawakai gangster group, looking for evidence in connection with shares he purchased in Tokyu, one of Japan's biggest railroad companies. Nomura and Nikko are accused of lending him money and participating in a huge runup in the price of Tokyu shares.</p>
        <p>A growing number of cities and prefectures around Japan have been announcing that they would suspend dealings with the four securities firms, at least temporarily. Hiroshima, Nagoya, and Sapporo have all suspended investment-management contracts, news service reports say, and Tokyo -- which manages enormous sums of money -- is considering a similar move.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
