<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE NAMES</title>
    <meta content="14BOLD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/14/nyregion/14bold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1596632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface Names"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Campbell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bentley, Farnsworth (Derek Watkins)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peck, Dale</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crouch, Stanley</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Don't the Moon Look Lonesome (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Boldface Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDC163AF937A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oscar Season Seems Like a Distant Dream</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Campbell Robertson; With Melena Z. Ryzik and Jess Wisloski</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Campbell Robertson interviews fashion plate Fonzworth Bentley (formerly Farnsworth Bentley) at two different book parties; interviews Stanley Crouch and Dale Peck about altercation they had after Peck wrote scathing review of Crouch's novel Don't the Moon Look Lonesome (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oscar Season Seems Like a Distant Dream</p>
        <p>One of the times last week we saw FONZWORTH BENTLEY (yes, it's no longer FARNSWORTH) was at the Hudson Hotel. It was at a party celebrating ''Gotham Diaries'' (by TONYA LEWIS LEE and CRYSTAL McCRARY ANTHONY) and Mr. Bentley was talking into a furry duck. We later discovered the duck was actually a ''plush cellphone cover'' (funfriends.com) and Mr. Bentley explained to us that he had another one, a pink dog, but that it was ''in the cleaners.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is July in Manhattan, and the inventory of Boldface Names in the city has dwindled to a small yet indefatigable few.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oscar Season Seems Like a Distant Dream</p>
        <p>One of the times last week we saw FONZWORTH BENTLEY (yes, it's no longer FARNSWORTH) was at the Hudson Hotel. It was at a party celebrating ''Gotham Diaries'' (by TONYA LEWIS LEE and CRYSTAL McCRARY ANTHONY) and Mr. Bentley was talking into a furry duck. We later discovered the duck was actually a ''plush cellphone cover'' (funfriends.com) and Mr. Bentley explained to us that he had another one, a pink dog, but that it was ''in the cleaners.''</p>
        <p>This little anecdote illustrates two things. One: the dapper Mr. Bentley, who was known as DEREK WATKINS before he gained fame as P.DIDDY's personal valet, is unfailingly on the cutting edge of style.</p>
        <p>And two: it is July in Manhattan, and the inventory of Boldface Names in the city has dwindled to a small yet indefatigable few: Mr. Bentley, STAR JONES and SYLVIA MILES.</p>
        <p>Anyway, the other book party where we saw Mr. Bentley was at Moda on 52nd Street.</p>
        <p>The book was ''The Au Pairs,'' a novel by MELISSA DE LA CRUZ about three young women who spend a summer baby-sitting in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bentley was sipping a cup of coffee, though we saw none being served. He was wearing a TOMMY HILFIGER pink-striped shirt, which he admitted wasn't out yet, a RALPH LAUREN tweed vest and a pink and white polka-dot bow tie. A retainer graced his teeth. Earlier in the day, he told us, he'd been fitted to be a Hilfiger underwear model.</p>
        <p>''I felt insecure about that,'' he said. ''But they're letting me do my own take on it. CALVIN KLEIN is known for having kind of feminine men, Ralph Lauren has beautiful, simple people, but Hilfiger I think stands for what I stand for: it's about fun, freedom and haberdashery.''</p>
        <p>Haberdashery?</p>
        <p>''Yes, haberdashery,'' Mr. Bentley said. ''It was JOHN F. KENNEDY who took off the fedora when he became president and that's when we started getting casual in our speech.''</p>
        <p>We were curious what the style-conscious Mr. Bentley's own take on underwear modeling might be. What sort of poses were they asking him to do, we asked.</p>
        <p>''Two girls just happen to walk in on me while I'm putting on my pants.''</p>
        <p>We'd Just Like to Say, We Thought It Was Great</p>
        <p>So many people have this idea that the writing life is idle, passive and physically unchallenging.</p>
        <p>At least that's why we got into the business. So imagine our surprise when we read of the following incident on Gawker.com.</p>
        <p>The setting: lunchtime yesterday at Tartine in the West Village.</p>
        <p>In this corner, we have STANLEY CROUCH, essayist, columnist and author of the novel ''Don't the Moon Look Lonesome.'' In addition to attacking sociological issues, Mr. Crouch also seems to have it in for journalists, reportedly having had physical altercations with reporters and critics.</p>
        <p>And in this corner, DALE PECK, author and critic known for his, um, gentility, evident in the essay in which he calls RICK MOODY ''the worst writer of his generation.'' Mr. Peck, who wrote a scathing review of Mr. Crouch's novel, was having lunch with the writer LINDA YABLONSKY.</p>
        <p>So, physicists and JOHNNY MERCER fans: what happens when an irresistible force meets an immovable object?</p>
        <p>''He walked over, he introduced himself and shook my hand,'' Mr. Peck said, when we reached him by phone. ''Then he hit me in the face and said 'If you ever do anything like that again, it'll be much worse.'''</p>
        <p>¡AY CARAMBA!</p>
        <p>The ''that'' probably has something to do with the part of Mr. Peck's review in which he wrote that Mr. Crouch's book ''is a terrible novel, badly conceived, badly executed, and put forward in bad faith; reviewing it is like shooting fish in a barrel.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peck said that he was not filing charges, but that he had told Mr. Crouch he would call the police if Mr. Crouch hit him again. The two returned to their seats.</p>
        <p>''As usual, the first-person pronoun -- in isolation -- is the only fully true thing one can believe from Dale Peck,'' Mr. Crouch said in an e-mail message. ''Our encounter was slight and unworthy of commentary.''</p>
        <p>Well, Dear Reader, now you know why some writers work for newspapers: health care plans. As for Mr. Peck's health, we're not so sure. We asked the obvious question.</p>
        <p>''I haven't met Mr. Moody,'' Mr. Peck replied.</p>
        <p>With Melena Z. Ryzik and Jess Wisloski</p>
        <p>Boldface Names</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
