<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3D9163CF935A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Russia Planning to Accept Nuclear Waste From Others  Russia is preparing to open its borders to become the largest repository for nuclear wastes. President Vladimir V. Putin has strongly backed the plan. Moscow estimates it can earn $21 billion over two decades by accepting 20,000 tons from 15 nations, money it says it will use to clean up the environment.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Freeing Sierra Leone's Children  More than 400 child soldiers were released by the Revolutionary United Front, the rebel group that has terrorized Sierra Leone for the last decade by kidnapping children and chopping off people's arms.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Russia Planning to Accept Nuclear Waste From Others  Russia is preparing to open its borders to become the largest repository for nuclear wastes. President Vladimir V. Putin has strongly backed the plan. Moscow estimates it can earn $21 billion over two decades by accepting 20,000 tons from 15 nations, money it says it will use to clean up the environment.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Freeing Sierra Leone's Children  More than 400 child soldiers were released by the Revolutionary United Front, the rebel group that has terrorized Sierra Leone for the last decade by kidnapping children and chopping off people's arms.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Jerusalem in Mourning  Jerusalemites struggled to deal with what some described as crisis overload after at least 24 people died when a wedding hall collapsed.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Powell Criticizes Zimbabwean  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, in assessing the state of Africa, called on President Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe to ''submit to the law and the will of the people'' in a fair presidential election next year instead of clinging to power.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Fencing In the Taliban  A panel on international sanctions in Afghanistan said border patrols of all neighboring nations needed to be strengthened to stop the export of Islamic militancy.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Mexico Ex-Governor Charged  Mario Villanueva, left, a fugitive former governor of Quintana Roo and one of Mexico's most-wanted men, was arrested in Cancún and then charged in New York with helping to ship 200 tons of cocaine to the United States in exchange for bribes.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Fleeing Macedonia's Offensive  Thousands of ethnic Albanian villagers fled their homes on foot this week from a government offensive against rebels in the northern hills.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Walter Eytan  An early British immigrant to Israel who developed a foreign service to meet the needs of a new state that was suddenly at war with its neighbors, he was 90.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-11</p>
        <p>Biggest Tax Cut in 20 YearsIs Facing Final Votes Today  Congressional negotiators agreed on all the aspects of the tax cut, and final votes are scheduled for today in the House and Senate. The government will send a rebate check this year to all Americans who pay income taxes. Tax rates will drop, taxes for married couples will fall, the tax credit for children will be expanded and the estate tax will eventually be repealed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Senate Shift in High Gear  The Democrats who are expected to lead the Senate's 15 committees are busy shaping the year ahead after their party takes control of the Senate for the first time since 1994.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Advises Free Thinking  A day after President Bush discovered that a touch of political risk-taking cost him control of the United States Senate, he told graduates of the United States Naval Academy that they need the freedom to roam in new directions even if ''some of your ideas may fail.'' The speech was drafted before the White House discovered Senator James M. Jeffords of Vermont was defecting.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Deaths Put Focus on Border  Immigrant rights groups said the deaths of 14 Mexicans in the desert near Yuma, Ariz., have caused them to consider stronger challenges to what they call hostile United States border policy. Doctors said the condition of the 12 Mexican immigrants who survived was improving.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Mexico's minister for migrant affairs said after visiting four of the survivors in the hospital there was much that both countries had to do to prevent more Mexicans from suffering such a fate. President Vicente Fox said he wanted the United States to grant legal status to as many Mexican migrants as possible.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Smithsonian Official Criticized  A group of curators and scholars at the Museum of American History has accused Lawrence M. Small, the Smithsonian Institution's secretary, of jeopardizing the integrity of the institution and breaching standard museum practices because of agreements he has reached with multimillion dollar donors.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Energy Hearings Sought  Senator Dianne Feinstein, Democrat of California, accused federal regulators of not doing their job and called for hearings into possible improprieties between members of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and private energy interests.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Pataki Faces Rough Race For Third Term as Governor  As Gov. George E. Pataki looks toward a probable run for a third term next year, New York's political landscape starts to resemble a minefield. A Republican, he leads a state that leans heavily Democratic now more than ever, and he is likely to face a well-known opponent. The economy has stalled and an electricity crisis may be just over the horizon. This shapes up as a very tough race for Mr. Pataki, strategists said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Window Shopping, Home-Style  Not everyone who goes to real estate open houses in Manhattan is interested in buying.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Rewards for Better Schools  In the first citywide application of merit pay in New York City public schools, Chancellor Harold O. Levy announced that he would award bonuses as high as $15,000 to principals and other administrators in 300 schools that saw the largest improvement in test scores.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-14</p>
        <p>A Royal Shake-Up  The Royal Shakespeare Company announced that it would dismantle its permanent company of actors and abandon its London base at the Barbican Center to attract bigger stars and present more productions in the showier West End. The move is one of many in what the artistic director Adrian Noble said would be a major reorganization of the company, which has nurtured the careers of actors like Ben Kingsley, above, John Gielgud, Laurence Olivier, Vanessa Redgrave and Kenneth Branagh.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Midwife on Trial Over Death  A midwife is on trial in Chicago on a charge of involuntary manslaughter after a baby died during a home birth.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Second Wind for Author  The United States Court of Appeals in Atlanta overturned a preliminary injunction blocking publication of ''The Wind Done Gone,'' a novel that revisits the plantation setting of ''Gone With the Wind'' from a slave's perspective. The ruling makes it all but certain that the book by Alice Randall, above, will appear in stores before the case is ultimately settled.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Hughes Chairman Quits  Michael T. Smith, chairman of the satellite concern Hughes Electronics, has resigned. Harry J. Pearce, vice chairman of General Motors, will lead Hughes.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Stock Prices Fall  The Dow Jones industrial average declined 117.05 points, or 1.1 percent. The Nasdaq composite index dropped 30.99 points, or 1.4 percent. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-index fell 15.28 points, or 1.2 percent.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Economic Growth Stays Slow  For the first time since 1995, the United States economy grew by less than 2 percent for two consecutive quarters, the government said.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A12-13</p>
        <p>Editorials: New threats to cleaner air; injustice in Egypt; a retreat on tax havens; Mr. Bruno and gay rights.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B12  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B14  Crossword</p>
        <p>B12  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
