<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drug Plan's Side Effect Is Severe; Co-Pay Means Many Don't Get Cancer Pills</title>
    <meta content="08copay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/08/business/08copay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1752873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D71130F93BA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drug Plan's Side Effect Is Severe; Co-Pay Means Many Don't Get Cancer Pills</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Drug Plan's Side Effect Is Severe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>YEADON, Pa.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government's new Medicare Part D program, touted as helping to provide prescription drug coverage for older Americans, has posed new complications for at least 10,000 Medicare patients who had been getting free cancer medicines in pill directly from manufacturers or through special programs run by insurance companies; Medicare has always covered injecttable drugs given in hospitals or doctors' offices but oral cancer drugs, which cost up to $4,000 a month, are now bound by rules requiring Medicare enrollees to pay $3,600 in out-of-pocket costs each year; added pressure is coming from drug makers that have begun restricting charitable free-drug programs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a result of the new Medicare drug program, thousands of people who take pills to fight cancer have suddenly found themselves with new bills to pay for their essential medicines. Frances Blue is one of them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blue, a retired teacher, learned five years ago that she had lung cancer. In December, her doctor decided that her old medicine was not working and that her best bet would be the cancer drug Tarceva, a medication from Genentech that costs about $3,000 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the new Medicare drug program, thousands who take pills to fight cancer have found themselves with new bills to pay for their essential medicines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a result of the new Medicare drug program, thousands of people who take pills to fight cancer have suddenly found themselves with new bills to pay for their essential medicines. Frances Blue is one of them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blue, a retired teacher, learned five years ago that she had lung cancer. In December, her doctor decided that her old medicine was not working and that her best bet would be the cancer drug Tarceva, a medication from Genentech that costs about $3,000 a month.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, on Jan. 1, the new Medicare Part D program, which is supposed to help provide prescription drug coverage for people like Ms. Blue, went into effect.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blue says she cannot afford the $3,600 in annual co-payments that are required before her Part D insurance fully kicks in. And her income from her teacher's pension and Social Security disability payments, about $4,000 a month, is too high to qualify for charitable programs that help patients with drug co-payments.</p>
        <p>Now, as her cancer spreads slowly through her lungs, Ms. Blue is getting no medicine at all. ''I've had a month of crying,'' she said in an interview in mid-March.</p>
        <p>The details of Ms. Blue's case are complex. But from interviews with doctors, patients, drug makers and charitable foundations, it is evident that Part D has posed new complications for at least 10,000 Medicare patients who had been getting free cancer medicines directly from manufacturers, or, in some cases, through special programs run by insurance companies.</p>
        <p>The drugs include Gleevec, for stomach cancer; Thalomid, for multiple myeloma; and Tarceva. They are all taken orally in pill form, rather than given by injection like most cancer medicines. Medicare has always covered injectable drugs given in hospitals or doctors' officers, but it generally did not cover oral medicines until Part D began on Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>Because the oral cancer drugs cost up to $4,000 a month, more than most people without coverage can afford, many Medicare patients received them free through charity programs from the drugs' manufacturers. Or, like Ms. Blue, they received them through extended Medicare policies provided by private insurers that charged minimal co-payments.</p>
        <p>But now that the oral cancer drugs are covered by Part D, they are bound by rules requiring Medicare enrollees to pay $3,600 in out-of-pocket costs each year.</p>
        <p>As the year continues, that proviso could put financial pressure on millions of Medicare patients. But it is already hitting hard at patients who take cancer pills, among the most expensive of the medicines covered by the new program. Patients taking these drugs often must meet their entire annual co-payment requirement when they fill their first two prescriptions -- a daunting prospect for retirees with limited savings and incomes.</p>
        <p>And in many cases, added pressure is coming from drug makers that have begun restricting their charitable free-drug programs and encouraging -- or in some cases, forcing -- patients to enroll in Part D coverage.</p>
        <p>Last year, about 4,500 patients in the United States received Gleevec free from its maker, Novartis. Not all of those people are eligible for Medicare. But Debra Freire, the company's director of patient assistance programs, said Novartis wanted all patients eligible for Part D to switch to Medicare. Novartis has not set a deadline for the switch.</p>
        <p>Medicare Part D, Ms. Friere said, is ''a wonderful opportunity for patients to gain access to a program that might provide them with prescription coverage that they might not have had.''</p>
        <p>Steven Hahn, a spokesman for AARP, the lobbying group for older Americans, said that once patients work through the upfront co-payments, sometimes called the doughnut hole, Part D provides excellent coverage for cancer drugs. But the high initial cost can be frightening, he said.</p>
        <p>''AARP would like to see the elimination of the doughnut hole altogether,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Leslie V. Norwalk, a deputy administrator for Medicare, acknowledged that some cancer patients were struggling with the transition to Part D. But over all, she said, the program has worked well for millions of people, offering new benefits for patients who might not have qualified for drug-maker assistance programs.</p>
        <p>In addition, low- and middle-income people can get co-pay relief, Ms. Norwalk said. For patients making less than about $15,000 a year, the co-pay requirements are lower, and for those making less than $40,000 some charities offer co-payment assistance.</p>
        <p>''There are terrific options for every beneficiary,'' she said.</p>
        <p>No firm statistics exist for how many cancer patients are being moved from free drug programs to Part D. But the number appears to be between 10,000 and 20,000, according to the drug makers and the charities that run co-payment programs.</p>
        <p>Since Jan. 1, for example, more than 5,000 people have applied for help with co-payments from the HealthWell Foundation, a Maryland charity that provides co-pay assistance, according to Krista Zodet, the foundation's director. Most of these people are in Part D, she said.</p>
        <p>Some patients without co-pay relief feel compelled to decline Part D coverage so they can continue to participate in drug-maker charity programs.</p>
        <p>For example, Maye Navarre, a 79-year-old retiree in Hertford, N.C., said she had been receiving free Tarceva from Genentech, its maker, until she signed up for a Part D program through Blue Cross in February. When she visited her pharmacy in early March to fill her Tarceva prescription, she learned the drug would cost her $1,425, not the $25 her insurance agent had told her to expect.</p>
        <p>Ms. Navarre says her only income is $932 a month in Social Security, and her savings total $4,000 in a money market account.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'O.K., pull the plug on me right there,' '' Ms. Navarre said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Navarre's income is low enough that she should qualify for a federal subsidy that would essentially eliminate her co-pay requirement. It is not clear why she was told her co-pay was so high. The insurance agent who arranged her Blue Cross coverage, David Parker, did not return calls for comment.</p>
        <p>In any case, Ms. Navarre said she had canceled her Part D enrollment so that she could again get Tarceva free from Genentech. In mid-March, in response to her pleas, Genentech shipped her another month of Tarceva free, so she is not out of medicine, she said.</p>
        <p>But Genentech warned her that the shipment would be her final free prescription until Blue Cross and Medicare processed her cancellation, she said.</p>
        <p>''So there I am, in limbo,'' Ms. Navarre said. ''They did send me a free month's supply, but they said that would be all. I got it on the 14th, so I have until the 13th of next month.''</p>
        <p>Genentech provides free medicines to people who do not have insurance and earn less than $75,000 annually, according to Walter K. Moore, the company's vice president for government affairs. In 2005, the company provided $200 million in free medicines to 18,000 patients and donated $21 million to co-pay assistance programs, he said.</p>
        <p>Unlike many drug makers, Genentech has not required Medicare patients in its free-drugs program to enroll in Part D. But once patients join Part D, Genentech bars them from participating in the company-run program, because it does not want to run afoul of Medicare's complex rules that cover patients who are enrolled in Part D but are also getting free drugs from manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Genentech is aware that some cancer patients in Part D are having problems affording their co-payments or filling prescriptions, Mr. Moore said. ''We understand that our drug has a significant co-pay, and we're trying to do something about it,'' he said. ''It's incumbent upon all of us that are trying to serve these patients to be vigilant and try to seek out ways to be certain that nobody falls through the cracks.''</p>
        <p>Still, patients like Ms. Blue seem to be slipping.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blue, who lives in a tidy brick house in Yeadon, a suburb a few miles southwest of Philadelphia, was told she had cancer in her left lung five years ago. Doctors removed the tumor, but the disease returned to her right lung in 2002. Despite chemotherapy, the cancer continued to spread slowly through her lungs, leaving a grim prognosis.</p>
        <p>In May 2004, she began taking Iressa, a drug from AstraZeneca. Since then, her cancer has remained relatively in check. She received the drug without co-payments through a supplemental Medicare policy offered by Independence Blue Cross. Although she is under 65 -- age 59 -- she is eligible for Medicare because her cancer has left her unable to work.</p>
        <p>In December 2005, her oncologist, Dr. Stephen Shore, decided to switch her from Iressa to Tarceva. Two clinical trials had cast doubt on Iressa's effectiveness.</p>
        <p>''All the indications were showing that the Iressa wasn't working, that she wasn't getting any benefit from it,'' Dr. Shore said. But in January, Ms. Blue learned her first Tarceva prescription would cost $2,800 -- not because she had switched drugs, but because of Part D's rules requiring co-payments.</p>
        <p>While Ms. Blue's income is too high to qualify for co-payment assistance, she has almost no assets aside from her house. She also has substantial credit card debt and fears adding to it by spending $2,800 on Tarceva, she said.</p>
        <p>''Who expects to have to come up with a couple of thousand dollars?'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shore said he had expected Ms. Blue to be able to find a way to get Tarceva through Medicare. If he were certain Tarceva would benefit her, he would advise her to pay the $2,800, he said. But uncertain that the drug will help, he does not want to make her spend money for a drug that may not work.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shore said he and his staff found Ms. Blue's case very frustrating.</p>
        <p>''We're used to roadblocks,'' he said. ''We're not used to this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
