<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Growth Was Solid Last Month</title>
    <meta content="08econ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/08/business/08econ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1752874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve System</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7D71130F93BA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Growth Was Solid Last Month</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Job Growth Was Solid Last Month</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bureau of Labor Statistics reports US work force expanded by 211,000 jobs in March and jobless rate dipped to 4.7 percent, suggesting economy has picked up speed; Pres Bush, claiming credit, cites increase in hiring as evidence of economic resurgence fueled by his tax cuts, which he is pressing Congress to extend; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation's work force grew by a healthy 211,000 jobs in March and the unemployment rate dipped to 4.7 percent, the government reported yesterday, suggesting that the economy has picked up speed and is likely to keep growing in the months ahead despite the prospect of higher interest rates from the Federal Reserve.</p>
        <p>Claiming credit, President Bush cited the latest increase in hiring as evidence of an economic resurgence fueled by his tax cuts, which he is pressing Congress to extend, particularly the lower tax rates on capital gains and stock dividends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The increase suggested that the economy is likely to keep growing in the months ahead despite the prospect of higher interest rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nation's work force grew by a healthy 211,000 jobs in March and the unemployment rate dipped to 4.7 percent, the government reported yesterday, suggesting that the economy has picked up speed and is likely to keep growing in the months ahead despite the prospect of higher interest rates from the Federal Reserve.</p>
        <p>Claiming credit, President Bush cited the latest increase in hiring as evidence of an economic resurgence fueled by his tax cuts, which he is pressing Congress to extend, particularly the lower tax rates on capital gains and stock dividends.</p>
        <p>With the March report from the Bureau of Labor Statistics, the work force has expanded for 31 consecutive months. Since November, the economy has added an average of 218,000 jobs a month and the unemployment rate has fallen consistently under 5 percent, from more than 6 percent three years ago. It was 4.8 percent in February.</p>
        <p>''The momentum in the labor market is now driving economic growth,'' said Ethan Harris, chief United States economist at Lehman Brothers, ''and that helps to offset some of the worries we all have about a potential downturn in housing.''</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, the jobs report suggested to many traders that the Federal Reserve might respond by continuing to raise the crucial interest rates that it controls, not only at the May meeting of the Fed's policy makers but also at subsequent meetings.</p>
        <p>Stock prices plunged, as they often do when rates seem likely to rise and bonds and other interest-bearing securities become more appealing as an investment.</p>
        <p>''Today's jobs report adds a little more pressure on the Fed to go to 5.25 percent,'' said Laurence H. Meyer, vice chairman of Macroeconomic Advisers, ''but we still think the Fed will stop at 5 percent in May.''</p>
        <p>President Bush argued that the good job numbers and the strength of the current recovery were a result of the tax cuts he pushed through Congress. ''Tax relief has done exactly what it was designed to do,'' he said in a statement, adding: ''Yet some are now proposing that we raise taxes, either by repealing the tax cuts or letting them expire.''</p>
        <p>Democrats were quick to attack the president's claim. Senator Jack Reed of Rhode Island, the ranking Democrat on the Joint Economic Committee, noted that job growth, despite its recent strength, is much weaker in this recovery than in previous ones.</p>
        <p>Bruce Bartlett, a conservative Republican economist who favors tax cuts as a source of economic growth but has turned against the White House because he views its economic policies as reckless, also argued that Mr. Bush's statement was misleading.</p>
        <p>''Tax cuts do lift the trend rate of growth over the long run,'' said Mr. Bartlett, who served in the Treasury Department under President Bush's father, George H. W. Bush. But ''tax policy doesn't affect business cycles; I don't see any evidence they are working.''</p>
        <p>By at least one standard, they are not. March was the fifth anniversary of the current business cycle, which started with a recession just after President Bush took office and then a painfully slow recovery in which the overall number of jobs continued to shrink until September 2003.</p>
        <p>By comparison with the four other business cycles since World War II that lasted at least five years, job growth has been considerably weaker in this upturn than in the past.</p>
        <p>In the weakest of those earlier cycles -- which began in the early 1990's -- the work force had grown 6.8 percent on the fifth birthday, compared with 1.9 percent today.</p>
        <p>''Our expectations have been pretty diminished,'' said Jared Bernstein, a senior economist at the labor-oriented Economic Policy Institute. ''A good month used to be 300,000 more jobs and now it is 200,000.''</p>
        <p>The work force has grown by 590,000 jobs so far this year, including a downward adjustment of 34,000 jobs in earlier estimates for January and February.</p>
        <p>The additions in March were across many industries, with the notable exception of manufacturing, which lost 5,000 jobs, continuing a decline resulting in part from the inroads that imported merchandise has made on the production of goods in this country.</p>
        <p>The biggest gains last month were in restaurant and hotel employment, in retailing, in health care and in government, mainly at the state and municipal level, with education accounting for most of the growth. The construction industry, on the other hand, added only 7,000 jobs in March, well below its usual pace.</p>
        <p>If there was anything puzzling to economists in the recent news from the job market, it is the combination of a jobless rate under 5 percent -- suggesting a shortage of workers available to hire -- with only mild wage increases. The average hourly pay of nonmanagement workers, about 80 percent of the nation's 135 million workers, rose by only 3 cents last month, to $16.49, the smallest increase this year.</p>
        <p>Over the last 12 months, hourly wages are up just 3.4 percent, a bit less than the increase in the inflation rate and well in line with productivity gains, undercutting concerns on Wall Street that a tight labor market is giving workers leverage to extract sharply higher pay.</p>
        <p>''There is some angst in the markets about potential inflation,'' said Stuart G. Hoffman, chief economist at the PNC Bank Corporation, ''but I don't think the Fed is overly concerned.''</p>
        <p>The job growth and rising incomes, particularly among those at the top of the income ladder, have emerged as a fresh source of support for consumer spending just as borrowing against the rising value of homes is slowing.</p>
        <p>''Job growth is a strong point in the economy,'' Mr. Harris of Lehman Brothers said, ''and it helps to offset some of the worries of a slowdown in consumer spending because of a potential downturn in housing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
