<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First, a Leak; Now, a Jam</title>
    <meta content="08assess" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/08/washington/08assess.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1752935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shane, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, I Lewis Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Libby, I Lewis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D61130F93BA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First, a Leak; Now, a Jam</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For President, First a Leak; Now, a Jam</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT SHANE; Thom Shanker contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shane, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Shane analysis holds that acccusation that Pres Bush, through Vice Pres Dick Cheney, authorized I Lewis Libby Jr to fight back against critics of war in Iraq by discussing classified pre-war intelligence estimate comes at awkward time for administration; notes that for months, Bush and his top aides have campaigned against leaks of classified information as danger to nation and as criminal acts; says Libby's acccount, describing Bush's approving Cheney's request in 2003 that Libby, then vice president's chief of staff, share reports on Iraqi weapons with Judith Miller, reporter then with New York Times, bares behind-the-scenes details that usually do not emerge until long after administration has left office; Bush photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>That President Bush authorized an aide to disclose classified intelligence on Iraqi weapons, as asserted in court papers, comes as no shock to official Washington. The leaking of secrets has long been a favored tool of policy debate, political combat and diplomatic one-upmanship.</p>
        <p>''We've had leaking of this kind since the administration of George Washington,'' said Rick Shenkman, a presidential historian at George Mason University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The accusation that President Bush authorized a leak comes at an awkward time for the administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>That President Bush authorized an aide to disclose classified intelligence on Iraqi weapons, as asserted in court papers, comes as no shock to official Washington. The leaking of secrets has long been a favored tool of policy debate, political combat and diplomatic one-upmanship.</p>
        <p>''We've had leaking of this kind since the administration of George Washington,'' said Rick Shenkman, a presidential historian at George Mason University.</p>
        <p>But the accusation that Mr. Bush, through Vice President Dick Cheney, authorized the aide, I. Lewis Libby Jr., to fight back against critics of the war by discussing a classified prewar intelligence estimate comes at a particularly awkward time for the administration.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Libby's account, describing Mr. Bush's approving Mr. Cheney's request in 2003 that Mr. Libby, then the vice president's chief of staff, share reports on Iraqi weapons with a reporter for The New York Times, bares behind-the-scenes details that usually do not emerge until long after an administration has left office.</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Bush and his top aides have campaigned against leaks of classified information as a danger to the nation and as criminal acts. A Washington Post report on secret overseas jails run by the C.I.A. and a New York Times report on domestic eavesdropping by the National Security Agency have led to criminal investigations, and scores of intelligence officers have been ordered to take polygraph tests.</p>
        <p>In that context, the report that the president was himself approving a leak may do serious political damage, said Mr. Shenkman, who has a blog on presidential politics. ''It does give the public such a powerful example of hypocrisy that I think it might linger for a while,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Scott McClellan, the president's spokesman, disputed the charge of a double standard on leaks. ''There is a difference between declassifying information in the national interest and the unauthorized disclosure'' of national security information, Mr. McClellan said Friday. Of the National Intelligence Estimate on Iraq, part of which Mr. Libby shared with Judith Miller, then a Times reporter, Mr. McClellan said, ''There was nothing in there that would compromise national security.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McClellan's tone contrasted sharply with that of administration officials after the N.S.A. story broke in December. Mr. Bush told a news conference at the time: ''My personal opinion is it was a shameful act for someone to disclose this very important program in a time of war. The fact that we're discussing this program is helping the enemy.''</p>
        <p>Others picked up the theme, including Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and Porter J. Goss, the C.I.A. director. On Feb. 2, Mr. Goss told a Senate committee, ''It is my hope that we will witness a grand jury investigation with reporters present being asked to reveal who is leaking this information.''</p>
        <p>Republicans in Congress, led by Representative Peter Hoekstra of Michigan, chairman of the Intelligence Committee, have also pressed the issue. By coincidence, the committee's report on the annual intelligence authorization bill was made public on Friday. It features a vehement attack, describing leakers as ''a small few who have taken it upon themselves to, for political or other motives, recklessly and illegally disclose America's necessary secrets and national security information.''</p>
        <p>Leaking intelligence information to the news media, the committee reports, ''costs untold millions of dollars in lost intelligence collection capabilities funded by U.S. taxpayers, literally puts lives in jeopardy, and makes the work by the honorable people of our intelligence community far more difficult.''</p>
        <p>In the case of Mr. Libby's disclosures to Ms. Miller, the consequences were hardly so dire. But neither was the political result evidently sought by the White House achieved.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miller wrote no newspaper article about the leaked weapons information, and 10 days later the administration formally declassified a summary of the intelligence document in question.</p>
        <p>Some earlier authorized disclosures by the Bush administration, to the reporter and author Bob Woodward, had far more impact. Mr. Woodward's 2002 book, ''Bush at War,'' based on extensive interviews with Mr. Bush and other officials, as well as access to internal White House documents, was a generally positive portrait. Mr. Woodward's 2004 book, ''Plan of Attack,'' was less warmly received at the White House.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration, like its predecessors, has also used formal, public declassification of secret intelligence for policy purposes. The prewar presentation to the United Nations by Colin L. Powell, then secretary of state, used N.S.A. intercepts of Iraqi military officers and satellite photos of Saddam Hussein's suspected weapons sites to make the case. In 1983, Jeane J. Kirkpatrick, President Ronald Reagan's United Nations ambassador, used dramatic N.S.A. recordings to denounce the Soviet Union for shooting down a South Korean civilian airliner.</p>
        <p>There have also been cases in which presidents, in the heat of the moment, have spontaneously revealed secrets. During the 1964 presidential campaign, under attack by Barry Goldwater, the Republican nominee, as soft on defense, President Lyndon B. Johnson chose to reveal the existence of a highly classified, experimental reconnaissance aircraft, the SR-71 Blackbird.</p>
        <p>In the Pentagon Papers case of 1971, the Nixon administration went to court to halt publication of a secret government history of the Vietnam War, which had been leaked by Daniel Ellsberg. Max Frankel, then the Washington bureau chief of The New York Times, filed an 18-page affidavit that gave a colorful insider's account of the role of leaked secrets as the lifeblood of Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel, who had spent a decade as a journalist in the capital, recalled President John F. Kennedy's staff members trying to prove his ''toughness'' by passing on quotations from an argument he had had with the Soviet foreign minister. Mr. Frankel told of standing beside President Johnson, ''knee-deep in his Texas swimming pool,'' as Mr. Johnson recounted for more than an hour his conversation of the day before with the Soviet prime minister.</p>
        <p>Without the use of secrets, Mr. Frankel argued at the time, ''there could be no adequate diplomatic, military and political reporting of the kind our people take for granted.''</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
