<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Muzzled and Opponents Jailed, Tajikistan Readies for Vote</title>
    <meta content="04tajik" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/04/world/asia/04tajik.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061114T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1802020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tajikistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Ilan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rakhmonov, Emomali (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Tajikistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tajikistan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rakhmonov, Emomali</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DA103FF937A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Muzzled and Opponents Jailed, Tajikistan Readies for Vote</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Media Muzzled and Opponents Jailed, Tajikistan Readies for Vote</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ILAN GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenberg, Ilan</byline>
      <dateline>DUSHANBE, Tajikistan, Nov. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tajikistan's mainline opposition parties, including 23,000-strong Islamic Renaissance Party, have boycotted impending presidential election, leaving four little-known opponents who have all but endorsed incumbent, Pres Emomali Rakhmonov; he has shuttered all independent news media and jailed several leading political opponents (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Voters in this dusty, dilapidated city have been given several choices in Tajikistan's presidential election on Monday, and from time to time they can be seen all together campaigning on the same bus.</p>
        <p>Tajikistan's mainline opposition parties, including the 23,000-strong Islamic Renaissance Party, have boycotted the election, leaving four little-known opponents who have all but endorsed the incumbent, President Emomali Rakhmonov.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although many see the upcoming presidential election as theater, its results could have implication for Tajikistan’s future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Voters in this dusty, dilapidated city have been given several choices in Tajikistan's presidential election on Monday, and from time to time they can be seen all together campaigning on the same bus.</p>
        <p>Tajikistan's mainline opposition parties, including the 23,000-strong Islamic Renaissance Party, have boycotted the election, leaving four little-known opponents who have all but endorsed the incumbent, President Emomali Rakhmonov.</p>
        <p>Beyond the occasional joint campaign appearance, there is little evidence of an impending election. Few election observers have bothered to show up, and election monitoring organizations like the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe arrived on Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rakhmonov, in power since 1997, has shuttered all independent news media and jailed several leading political opponents. Tajikistan's election follows presidential elections in nearby Azerbaijan and Kazakhstan, widely seen as rigged, that undercut predictions that the pro-democratic, so-called colored revolutions in Georgia, Ukraine and last year in neighboring Kyrgyzstan, might lead to a wave of similar uprisings across the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Tajikistan has few natural resources beyond hydroelectric power but is considered a significant strategic player in the region because of its location. Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld have recently paid visits, and Tajikistan is home to a NATO air base that is vital for the conflict in Afghanistan. American officials also praise Tajikistan's role in fighting drug trafficking, and they have given qualified praise to the Tajikistan government for some positive moves toward democratic development.</p>
        <p>There are ''issues that do need to be addressed during the process of improving a democracy, things like having access to the news media, so that the people of Tajikistan can hear all the different views of the political parties,'' the assistant secretary of state for south and central Asian affairs, Richard A. Boucher, said in May during a visit to Dushanbe, the capital. ''In the end, the issue is: how do you give the people of Tajikistan the right to choose their leadership and the information that they need to make that choice?''</p>
        <p>The subject of politics is rarely heard in Dushanbe's cafes and markets, and even politically engaged Tajiks say this campaign has produced little to discuss.</p>
        <p>''Whether this country gets better doesn't depend on politics,'' said Ali Abdulhafiz, a 30-year-old businessman having dinner in an upscale Dushanbe restaurant.</p>
        <p>The election ''is a kind of theater performance of the moment,'' he said, echoing the views of many in this city. ''I don't see any legitimate person who could replace the president.''</p>
        <p>Longtime observers of Tajikistan often characterize the country as profoundly averse to risk and skeptical of promises of reform, a political passivity they trace to the country's ruinous civil war. During much of the 1990s, heavily armed militias battled for supremacy across Tajikistan. The current president took power by imposing a peace, but not before the warring factions had succeeded in driving the country's development decades backward.</p>
        <p>Nine years after the end of the civil war, Tajikistan continues to be a very poor country. A recent United Nations survey stated more than half the population may suffer from malnourishment. Electricity and running water are mostly unavailable in Dushanbe, and totally absent in much of the countryside.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 14, 2006, Tuesday  An article on Nov. 4 about the presidential election in Tajikistan referred incorrectly to NATO's use of Tajikistan territory for operations in Afghanistan. (The error was repeated in a World Briefing report on Wednesday.) While Tajikstan permits NATO aircraft to refuel there, NATO has no airbase in Tajikistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 14, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Nov. 4 about the presidential election in Tajikistan referred incorrectly to NATO's use of Tajikistan territory for operations in Afghanistan. (The error was repeated in a World Briefing report on Wednesday.) While Tajikstan permits NATO aircraft to refuel there, NATO has no airbase in Tajikistan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
