<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Koppel Leaving ABC News in December</title>
    <meta content="01KOPP$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/01/business/media/01koppel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1661444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, Ted</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nightline (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC News</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Koppel, Ted</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED9103FF932A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Koppel Leaving ABC News in December</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Koppel Leaving ABC News and 'Nightline' in December</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ted Koppel, who has been host of Nightline on ABC, will leave network when his contract expires in early December; it is not immediately clear how ABC intends to replace him; network executives offer assurances that 11:35 pm time slot of Nightline will remain in hands of ABC News, at least in months immediately after Koppel leaves; industry executives note that network, owned by Walt Disney Co, is leaving as much as $100 million a year on table by not scheduling entertainment program at that hour; chart; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ted Koppel, who during a quarter-century as the host of ''Nightline'' on ABC has provided a hard-news alternative to the monologues and banter of Johnny Carson, Jay Leno and David Letterman, will leave the network when his contract expires in early December, ABC News announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppel said in an interview that he did not know what he might do next. And it was not immediately clear how ABC intended to replace him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ted Koppel, who provided a hard-news alternative as host of "Nightline," will leave ABC when his contract expires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ted Koppel, who during a quarter-century as the host of ''Nightline'' on ABC has provided a hard-news alternative to the monologues and banter of Johnny Carson, Jay Leno and David Letterman, will leave the network when his contract expires in early December, ABC News announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppel said in an interview that he did not know what he might do next. And it was not immediately clear how ABC intended to replace him.</p>
        <p>Network executives offered assurances yesterday that the 11:35 p.m. time slot of ''Nightline'' would remain in the hands of ABC News, at least in the months immediately after Mr. Koppel leaves. But industry executives noted yesterday that the network, owned by the Walt Disney Company, is leaving as much as $100 million a year on the table by not scheduling an entertainment program at that hour.</p>
        <p>In recent months, ABC executives have asked the news division to develop proposals for alternative programming for the ''Nightline'' slot that might prove more popular and draw a younger audience than Mr. Koppel's program, which generally focuses on one serious topic a night, and frequently follows it over several nights.</p>
        <p>The ideas produced thus far include an expanded one-hour ''Nightline'' developed by members of Mr. Koppel's staff, and two programs in more irreverent or informal styles, including one in a nightclub setting with audience members seated at round tables decorated with candles.</p>
        <p>Both the network and Mr. Koppel -- who is 65, and entitled under his contract to work only three nights a week -- agreed that he was not a viable candidate to lead the next incarnation of ''Nightline,'' which is intended to be live each night. (Mr. Koppel often prerecords his programs.) Instead, two executives briefed on the matter said, the network offered Mr. Koppel only one real alternative: to take the reins of the weakly rated Sunday program ''This Week,'' succeeding George Stephanopoulos.</p>
        <p>After mulling that proposal during a nearly three-week vacation that ended this week, Mr. Koppel told David Westin, the president of ABC News, that he was not interested.</p>
        <p>The seeds of ABC's announcement yesterday were sown three years ago, when the network sought, without Mr. Koppel's knowledge, to woo Mr. Letterman from CBS to the ''Nightline'' time slot on ABC.</p>
        <p>At the time, an ABC executive was quoted as saying ''Nightline'' no longer seemed relevant, especially with growing numbers of Americans getting their news on the Internet -- an assertion that angered Mr. Koppel.</p>
        <p>While the sides ultimately struck a deal to extend ''Nightline'' at least two more years, the wariness between Mr. Koppel's team and the network -- and the network's concerns about ''Nightline'' -- never abated.</p>
        <p>Asked if his disappointment in how the network handled the Letterman courtship had ever gone away, Mr. Koppel said, ''I can't tell you to what degree there is something lingering under the surface.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppel's bosses remained mindful that ''Nightline'' continued to lag in the ratings behind the first half-hour of both Mr. Leno's ''Tonight'' show on NBC, the most-watched program at that hour, and Mr. Letterman's ''Late Show.''</p>
        <p>Still, while ABC explored the possibility in recent months of moving Mr. Koppel off ''Nightline'' when his contract expired in December, the network had hoped to keep him at ABC News. With the recent departures of Tom Brokaw and Dan Rather from their evening news programs, Mr. Koppel's departure will leave only Peter Jennings, anchor of ''World News Tonight'' on ABC since 1982, as a broadcast journalist with comparable longevity and star power.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Koppel acknowledged that one job he had considered at ABC -- though he would not say whether it had been formally offered to him -- was ''This Week,'' which trails in the ratings behind ''Meet the Press'' on NBC and ''Face the Nation'' on CBS.</p>
        <p>''It was a possibility and it's certainly a fine platform and it's an interesting broadcast,'' Mr. Koppel said. ''But by the same token, I really feel there are other things I would rather do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppel said he had been concerned about what he saw as the uniformity of all the Sunday public affairs programs -- particularly when a viewer can flip from one channel to the other and see people like the secretary of defense or secretary of state interviewed on each.</p>
        <p>''That seems to be the general understanding in Washington these days,'' Mr. Koppel said. ''The administration sets the tone and theme and presents the same guests to all the programs at the same time. I don't think anyone is served by that.''</p>
        <p>Asked what he might do next, Mr. Koppel said, ''There are some very interesting prospects out there, let's put it that way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppel's longtime executive producer, Tom Bettag, who will leave ABC around the same time as Mr. Koppel, spoke in a separate interview about news organizations that do the sort of work he and Mr. Koppel admire: long-form reporting that is not necessarily skewed toward an audience 49 years old or younger, the holy grail of the broadcast networks and their advertisers.</p>
        <p>Specifically, Mr. Bettag cited National Public Radio, HBO and the CBS program ''60 Minutes,'' where Mr. Bettag worked in the early 1980's, as being supporters of that kind of broadcast journalism.</p>
        <p>Asked if the two, who intend to continue to work as a team, had engaged in any discussions with those particular organizations, Mr. Bettag said: ''We know everybody in the business. We believe there are people who would like to have us come.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Westin expressed disappointment that he had been unable to find a way to retain Mr. Koppel.</p>
        <p>''My preference was that he stay with us a while longer,'' Mr. Westin said. ''I thought he could contribute here in a number of ways and we would benefit from that.''</p>
        <p>At the root of the breach between Mr. Koppel and ABC, where he has worked for more than four decades, is the seismic change in the television landscape since he first went on the air in 1979 with a precursor to ''Nightline,'' called ''America Held Hostage,'' which provided a nightly update on the holding of American hostages in Iran.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday night's program -- which provided a retrospective of the hostage crisis and was edited only hours after Mr. Koppel informed Mr. Westin of his decision -- Mr. Koppel sought to give younger viewers in particular a history lesson on how different television news was in 1979 and 1980.</p>
        <p>''CNN was barely born, and all the other 24/7 cable outlets were still a thing of the future,'' he said. ''People wouldn't go to sleep without getting their final hostage fix of the night.''</p>
        <p>Asked if Wednesday's program had been intended as a timely reminder to Mr. Westin of what ''Nightline'' had once been, Mr. Bettag said it had not; instead, he said, the program had been roughly timed to the 25th anniversary of ''Nightline'' (March 24, when Mr. Koppel was away) and was contingent on the visa of a correspondent who had only recently managed to get into Iran.</p>
        <p>Richard Wald, a former president of NBC News who worked as a senior vice president at ABC during much of Mr. Koppel's tenure on ''Nightline,'' said the history lesson was well taken.</p>
        <p>Where ''Nightline,'' at its inception, was ''powerful, definitive and unique,'' Mr. Wald said, now a viewer ''can spend an entire day watching the same kinds of stories -- on morning news on the broadcast networks, on the afternoon news of the local stations, all day on the cable channels, and then on the evening news and magazine programs.''</p>
        <p>In such an environment, Mr. Wald said, it was hardly a failing of Mr. Koppel and Mr. Bettag that they could not find a way to produce a broadcast that would meet the network's goals.</p>
        <p>''Had Ted and Tom been able to invent a very different way to deliver the news, we might be in a very different moment now,'' Mr. Wald said. ''But that's asking a heck of a lot.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
