<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Audit Firm Facing Risk Of Lawsuits Over A.I.G.</title>
    <meta content="01AUDI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/01/business/01audit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1661434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American International Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pricewaterhousecoopers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American International Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0D9103FF932A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Audit Firm Facing Risk Of Lawsuits Over A.I.G.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Audit Firm Facing Risk of Lawsuits Over A.I.G.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>PricewaterhouseCoopers, longtime auditor of American International Group, faces possible lawsuits now that AIG has admitted that it accounted improperly for certain transactions with other insurance and reinsurance companies, with some of questionable transactions dating back more than decade ago; in intervening years, company filed various regulatory reports and statements, which were approved by PricewaterhouseCoopers; shareholders and bondholders may claim that they relied on those regulatory filings when making investments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where was the auditor?</p>
        <p>The insurance giant American International Group disclosed on Wednesday that it had accounted improperly for certain transactions with other insurance and reinsurance companies and that some of the questionable transactions may have occurred more than a decade ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where was the auditor?.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Where was the auditor?</p>
        <p>The insurance giant American International Group disclosed on Wednesday that it had accounted improperly for certain transactions with other insurance and reinsurance companies and that some of the questionable transactions may have occurred more than a decade ago.</p>
        <p>In the intervening years, the company filed various regulatory reports and statements, which were approved by A.I.G.'s longtime auditor, PricewaterhouseCoopers.</p>
        <p>The accounting firm could now find itself facing a wave of lawsuits brought by shareholders and bondholders asserting that they relied on those regulatory filings when making investments.</p>
        <p>Accounting firms have many defenses to lawsuits in such situations, securities lawyers said. ''The federal securities laws establish liability for auditors in registration statements, but at the same time provide auditors with the ability to establish a due diligence defense,'' said Joseph Grundfest, a law professor at Stanford University and a former commissioner of the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>In other words, the accounting firm can assert that it did nothing wrong, asked the right questions, checked the right numbers and should not be liable.</p>
        <p>''The challenge in the current environment,'' Mr. Grundfest said, ''is that there is not a lot of case law as to the substance of the due diligence defense.''</p>
        <p>''This situation has unfortunately become so common over the last several years,'' he said, ''that the audit firms have likely developed a fire drill scenario for addressing such contingencies.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for PricewaterhouseCoopers declined to comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>The statement released this week by A.I.G. suggests that some transactions with improper accounting may date back to 1991. Some of the transactions that have drawn scrutiny, according to the statement, took place in December 2000 and March 2001 between an A.I.G. subsidiary and a subsidiary of the General Re Corporation, a subsidiary of Berkshire Hathaway. Other issues involve reinsurance companies that were characterized as independent entities but may have to be reclassified as distinctly related to A.I.G.</p>
        <p>Since December 2000, A.I.G. has issued billions of dollars in stock and bonds, according to regulatory filings. Lawyers say that the filings would probably be the basis for lawsuits by shareholders and debtholders, who would argue that if they had known the company's true financial condition, they would have paid less for the stock and would have demanded a higher interest rate on the debt.</p>
        <p>''You're having your own forensic accountants -- which all of us now have on our staff -- forensic accountants with auditing experience,'' said Paul Geller, a partner at Lerach Coughlin Stoia Geller Rudman &amp; Robbins, a plaintiff-side securities law firm. ''We're going through all of the public filings and we're looking for red flags.''</p>
        <p>Accounting firms can also argue that any adjustments to A.I.G.'s financial statements are so small, given the size of the company, that the changes did not harm investors.</p>
        <p>Correcting the accounting for the Gen Re transaction, for example, ''will have virtually no impact on A.I.G.'s financial condition as of Dec. 31, 2004,'' A.I.G. said, ''but will reduce the reserve for losses and loss expenses by $250 million and increase other liabilities by $245 million.''</p>
        <p>But accounting firms face another challenge because of the increasing willingness to name them, law firms and investment banks as defendants in shareholder lawsuits.</p>
        <p>In the past, such firms could more easily avoid having to go to trial on the claims against them by arguing that they should not be held liable for wrongdoing at the company if they did not actively participate in any misdeeds.</p>
        <p>''For a while there, it was very, very difficult for auditors, law firms, investment banks to be held liable for the underlying fraud,'' Mr. Geller said. ''It's getting easier.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
