<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coats Take Off on Their Own</title>
    <meta content="24DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/24/fashion/24DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1606190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coats</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Burberry</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Moschino</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prada, Miuccia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D9143EF937A1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coats Take Off on Their Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Coats Take Off on Their Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cathy Horyn column on new coats for fall; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like those ancient rules governing the wearing of white after Labor Day, coats were something you were once supposed to buy in fall. Department stores added to the sense of urgency with Columbus Day coat sales, and not by a long shot were their advertised styles frivolous, or even exceptional. What you were buying was premeditated warmth.</p>
        <p>But times change, climates shift, winter clothes arrive in stores in the middle of summer, and the speed of fashion creates a new sense of urgency, if not a different reason to buy a coat. It was plain at the fall collections, with their emphasis on novelty and embellishment, that this was going to be a standout season for coats. Designers seemed to recognize that a coat could make a strong statement, just as accessories have done. So why not give her something so exceptional she might be tempted to wear it indoors (fabrics are now light enough) -- or, in the manner of countless literary heroines since Gloria Wandrous of ''BUtterfield 8,'' with practically nothing on underneath?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best of the new fall coats combine sweetness and dash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like those ancient rules governing the wearing of white after Labor Day, coats were something you were once supposed to buy in fall. Department stores added to the sense of urgency with Columbus Day coat sales, and not by a long shot were their advertised styles frivolous, or even exceptional. What you were buying was premeditated warmth.</p>
        <p>But times change, climates shift, winter clothes arrive in stores in the middle of summer, and the speed of fashion creates a new sense of urgency, if not a different reason to buy a coat. It was plain at the fall collections, with their emphasis on novelty and embellishment, that this was going to be a standout season for coats. Designers seemed to recognize that a coat could make a strong statement, just as accessories have done. So why not give her something so exceptional she might be tempted to wear it indoors (fabrics are now light enough) -- or, in the manner of countless literary heroines since Gloria Wandrous of ''BUtterfield 8,'' with practically nothing on underneath?</p>
        <p>The best of the new fall coats combine sweetness and dash, and to convey that spirit I asked the illustrator Joe Eula, who began his fashion career in the late 1940's and went on to work for Halston as well as to design album covers and concert posters for performers like Miles Davis and Liza Minnelli, to draw some models at his home in upstate New York. The models -- Acacia, Madelyn and Zoe -- were local, high-school age, pretty and inexperienced as models, though Acacia recently signed with the IMG agency. The idea was just to have a little fun.</p>
        <p>The girls assembled one morning in Joe's kitchen, where innocence reigned as Mercedes Fernandez, a makeup artist with the John Barrett Salon, and her colleague, Meyhae Millet, got them ready. As Mr. Millet teased and patted Zoe's voluminous brown hair, finally pinning it up, he said, ''You know, she looks like Daria.'' He meant Daria Werbowy, the model of the moment. Zoe looked gorgeously nonplused. Who on earth was Daria?</p>
        <p>While Madelyn got ready, Zoe went off to pose in a white Moschino coat with a fur collar and silly pompom buttons. The style's A-line shape and sloping shoulders are vintage 1950's, an era that also seduced designers like Dolce &amp; Gabbana, Marc Jacobs and Alberta Ferretti, whose collection included a pea green coat with a flat collar and covered buttons. Vintage-inspired coats are a dominant trend for fall, especially in nubby tweeds and colors that make you think of Mamie Eisenhower.</p>
        <p>But, to prevent the look from going granny, treat it casually. For instance, a Marni sea-foam green coat with three-quarter-length sleeves and a glint of silver Lurex, looks great over a black chiffon dress with a longer, asymmetrical hem. Zoe wore the Moschino coat unbuttoned over a 1920's-inspired slip dress, with turquoise gloves and a pair of dark green velvet slides. Joe loosened up things even more by undoing her hair until it was a cross between a Gibson Girl and Gwen Stefani.</p>
        <p>''With the emphasis on dressing up and ladylike clothes, the coat has almost replaced the jacket -- to the point where it can be worn indoors,'' said Robert Burke, the fashion director of Bergdorf Goodman. Among the first styles the store sold for fall were lightweight Chanel bouclé tweeds. ''They wouldn't keep anyone warm,'' Mr. Burke said. But, as he added, ''We bought coats that had fashion, and that's what is selling.'' You can find lower-priced versions of this boxy vintage look from Guess and Marc by Marc Jacobs.</p>
        <p>At the opposite extreme are the tough, vaguely military styles offered by Christopher Bailey of Burberry and Miuccia Prada in her Miu Miu collection. Mr. Bailey showed many more coats this season, including one in taupe cashmere with extravagantly rounded lapels that seemed based on the classic trench. Madelyn wore it over a striped turtleneck in aqua and beige, with raspberry colored stockings. Certainly Miu Miu's long, double-breasted khaki coat with a rough fur collar is hip enough not to make you care what's underneath.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
