<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lumumba, the African Castro or a Dazzling Ray of Hope?</title>
    <meta content="03BOOK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/03/books/03BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Congo (Formerly Zaire)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Witte, Ludo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lumumba, Patrice (1925-61)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Assassination of Lumumba, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Congo</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DC143CF930A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lumumba, the African Castro or a Dazzling Ray of Hope?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">African Castro or a Dazzling Ray of Hope?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews book The Assassination of Lumumba by Ludo De Witte; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ASSASSINATION OF LUMUMBA  By Ludo De Witte  Translated by Ann Wright and Renée Fenby.  Illustrated. 224 pages. Verso. $27.</p>
        <p>Patrice Lumumba was one of those charismatic figures -- martyrs, in the view of their supporters -- who stood on the public stage during that moment of ferment when colonialism was dying and a new force on the global scene, third world nationalism, seemed poised to replace it. Lumumba, who was assassinated in January 1961 during the terrible Congo civil war, was like Che Guevara in this sense, or perhaps Sukarno (overthrown but not assassinated in Indonesia), or maybe even the American Black Muslim Malcolm X. He was a fiery, commanding figure with a revolutionary aura about him, cut down before he was able to exercise power long enough for anybody to be sure how he would have reshaped the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ludo De Witte's book shows Patrice Lumumba as a man who might have led Congo, reluctantly granted independence by Belgium after a century of rapacious control, into a hopeful future</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ASSASSINATION OF LUMUMBA  By Ludo De Witte  Translated by Ann Wright and Renée Fenby.  Illustrated. 224 pages. Verso. $27.</p>
        <p>Patrice Lumumba was one of those charismatic figures -- martyrs, in the view of their supporters -- who stood on the public stage during that moment of ferment when colonialism was dying and a new force on the global scene, third world nationalism, seemed poised to replace it. Lumumba, who was assassinated in January 1961 during the terrible Congo civil war, was like Che Guevara in this sense, or perhaps Sukarno (overthrown but not assassinated in Indonesia), or maybe even the American Black Muslim Malcolm X. He was a fiery, commanding figure with a revolutionary aura about him, cut down before he was able to exercise power long enough for anybody to be sure how he would have reshaped the world.</p>
        <p>In one view, the view that has predominated in the seats of Western power, Lumumba was a dangerous figure who would have taken the newly independent Congo either into social chaos or into the Soviet camp. The director of central intelligence at the time, Allen Dulles, called him an African Castro. By contrast, Ludo De Witte, a Belgian sociologist and writer, takes a very different view in ''The Assassination of Lumumba.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. De Witte, Lumumba was a dazzling ray of hope for a successful postcolonial future in Africa, a man who might have led Congo, reluctantly granted independence by Belgium after a century of rapacious control, into a hopeful future. Mr. De Witte's thesis is that Lumumba's murder was not, as many have previously written, an internal Congolese affair, a kind of panicked overreaction among African factions fighting it out after the departure of the Belgians. Lumumba was murdered, in Mr. De Witte's account, by a kind of unholy alliance led by the Belgian government acting through well-paid Congolese stooges and enjoying the connivance of the American Central Intelligence Agency and the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Mr. De Witte's book, translated from the Flemish by Ann Wright and Renée Fenby, is an important and flawed examination of the persecution and murder of Lumumba. Mr. De Witte makes no pretense of being an impartial investigator. His book is full of a kind of impassioned boilerplate more common to the leftist intelligentsia in Europe than in the United States, phrases like ''the Western ruling classes'' and ''the fight for national liberation'' abound. At one point, after he has taken the reader through a gripping, minute-by-minute account of Lumumba's execution, Mr. De Witte laments:</p>
        <p>''Patrice Lumumba was not yet 36 years old, the same age as Robespierre, that other great defender of the modern nation state, when he died.'' To put Lumumba into the same category as the man who invented revolutionary terror seems at best tactically unwise; it does not inspire confidence in Mr. De Witte's political judgment.</p>
        <p>Still, whatever eccentric political ideas he may have, Mr. De Witte has written a compelling account of the tireless efforts by the West to eliminate Lumumba. When this book was published in Europe in 1999, it prompted the formation of a Belgian parliamentary inquiry into Lumumba's death. (Its findings are to be announced this year.) Mr. De Witte makes his case, and he has documentary evidence to make it stick.</p>
        <p>Lumumba was the first prime minister elected in Congo before a reluctant Belgium granted it independence in July 1960, but matters began to deteriorate almost immediately. Lumumba made an inflammatory speech at the independence ceremony, attacking Belgium for its years of colonialist exploitation and humiliation while King Baudouin stood nearby. Lumumba's attack was historically accurate but politically foolish. It aroused fears among Europeans that antiwhite vengeance would be a main theme of his regime.</p>
        <p>Within a couple of days, when the Congolese army revolted, beating European men and raping some women, Belgium intervened militarily, and though Belgian troops were soon displaced by a United Nations multinational force, Lumumba was soon dismissed by President Joseph Kasavubu. When he tried to escape house arrest in Leopoldville and join supporters in Stanleyville, he was arrested by troops controlled by the future dictator, Joseph Mubutu. A few months later, in the presence of several Belgian police and army officers, he was beaten, tortured and executed by a firing squad.</p>
        <p>It is a seedy story, and the essential fact of it is indisputable: that the legally elected prime minister of a newly independent country was murdered, to the evident satisfaction both of Belgium and the United States. Much of what Mr. De Witte says in his detailed reconstruction of the crime has been known for years, including the almost comic-opera plot concocted by the C.I.A. to have Lumumba assassinated by injecting poison into his toothpaste.</p>
        <p>Mr. De Witte mines the Belgian archives for a good deal of new information, especially on the role of ranking figures in the Belgian government in fomenting opposition to Lumumba among alternative Congolese leaders. Once Lumumba was arrested, Mr. De Witte's reconstruction of events says, Belgium pressed for what a senior Belgian official called his ''definitive elimination.'' Mr. De Witte and his translators maintain the original French phrase: ''élimination définitive.''</p>
        <p>But De Witte also slides quickly over the breakdown in order after the independence-day celebrations. In this book you won't read about the rape of European women, for example, or of Lumumba's inability to control the situation, or of his tendency to make inflammatory declarations. While Mr. De Witte meticulously describes Belgian economic interests in its former colony, he does not talk much about the Congo's powerful tribal and personal rivalries, which other commentators have stressed. You would almost think,  reading Mr. De Witte's account, that the murder of Lumumba was unusual in Africa at the time. In truth, throughout the continent, corrupt and brutal army officers of the Mobutu stripe were taking power from the Western-trained intellectuals that the departing colonial powers had left behind to run things.</p>
        <p>But it is also true that Congo was different in some ways, different because of the unusual cruelty of Belgian colonialism (grippingly recounted in Adam Hochschild's recent book ''King Leopold's Ghost'') and because of the exceptional brutality and corruption of the Mobutu regime after Lumumba's fall. Mr. De Witte's book, politically passionate as it is, is an unignorable effort to bring the West face to face with its culpability in this entire sad and sanguinary tale.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
