<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jewish Treasure Stays in Israel</title>
    <meta content="03ANTI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/03/arts/design/03ANTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illuminated Manuscripts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Israel Museum (Jerusalem)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jesselson, Erica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Manuscripts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Israel Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DC143CF930A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jewish Treasure Stays in Israel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Jewish Treasure Stays in Israel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column on First Nuremeberg Haggadah (c1449), Jewish illuminated manuscript that is being donated to Israel Museum in Jerusalem by New York collector Erica Jesselson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''It's like finding the Declaration of Independence in the attic,'' said Rabbi Jerry Schwarzbard, the librarian for special collections at the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan. He was explaining the excitement elicited by a manuscript that came up for auction in April at Sotheby's in Tel Aviv. The rare illuminated manuscript known as the First Nuremberg Haggadah was written and illustrated in about 1449 in Germany by a scribe artist known as Joel ben Simeon.</p>
        <p>''He was the Leonardo da Vinci of Jewish illustrators of the time,'' said James Snyder, the director of the Israel Museum in Jerusalem. ''This Haggadah is a patrimonial treasure, like the Mona Lisa. It has that standing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rare illuminated manuscript from about 1449 was bought at a Sotheby's auction in April and has been donated to the Israel Museum in Jerusalem</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''It's like finding the Declaration of Independence in the attic,'' said Rabbi Jerry Schwarzbard, the librarian for special collections at the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan. He was explaining the excitement elicited by a manuscript that came up for auction in April at Sotheby's in Tel Aviv. The rare illuminated manuscript known as the First Nuremberg Haggadah was written and illustrated in about 1449 in Germany by a scribe artist known as Joel ben Simeon.</p>
        <p>''He was the Leonardo da Vinci of Jewish illustrators of the time,'' said James Snyder, the director of the Israel Museum in Jerusalem. ''This Haggadah is a patrimonial treasure, like the Mona Lisa. It has that standing.''</p>
        <p>Erica Jesselson, a New York collector of Judaica and Jewish manuscripts, bought the Nuremberg Haggadah at the April sale for $1,017,750. (Its estimate had been $600,000 to $700,000.) It was the second most expensive manuscript ever sold in Israel. Today the Israel Museum is announcing that Ms. Jesselson and her family have donated the manuscript to the Israel Museum in honor of Teddy Kollek, a former mayor of Jerusalem, one of the founders of the museum and a friend of the Jesselson family for 50 years.</p>
        <p>The Haggadah is the Passover text recited at a Seder. It tells the story of the Jews' Exodus from Egypt, which occurred around the 13th century B.C., said Esta Kilstein, the specialist in charge of the Sotheby's sale. She said that the first written order for Passover eve  was in the Mishnah -- a collection of oral law, forming the basis of the Talmud and compiled in the early third century A.D. -- but that there were no surviving manuscripts. ''The earliest Haggadah as a separate manuscript dates to about the 10th century,'' Ms. Kilstein said.</p>
        <p>''We have all seen illuminated books from the 13th, 14th and 15th centuries,'' Ms. Jesselson said, ''but most Jewish books of the period from Germany and Poland were destroyed. Here is one by a famous Jewish scribe, the only one by him that was in private hands. My husband knew this book and I remember how gently he touched it when we saw it years ago. It is one of a kind.'' Her husband, Ludwig Jesselson, died in 1993.</p>
        <p>Daisy Raccah-Djivre, former chief curator of Judaica and Jewish Ethnography at the Israel Museum, said: ''Christians often burned Jewish texts. It is very special to have a manuscript from that time. Ben Simeon had to leave Germany -- most Jews were expelled from Germany by the end of the 15th century -- and he moved to Italy, bringing the tradition of illuminating Hebrew texts with him.''</p>
        <p>The parchment manuscript, handwritten in Ashkenazi Hebrew script in sepia ink, is dedicated to Rabbi Nathan ben Solomon. It is richly decorated, depicting dozens of biblical scenes and text illustrations with fine draftsmanship but also a certain naïve charm. It is embellished with gold and vibrant red, blue, green and yellow paint. Moses striking the rock, Adam and Eve, Noah and the Ark, Jonah and the whale, and several elaborate falconing and hunting scenes with dogs, deer and hares fill the pages.</p>
        <p>''Each page is like a painting,'' Ms. Jesselson said.</p>
        <p>Few works of Jewish art survive from the late Middle Ages in Europe, and even fewer are by known Jewish artists. Joel ben Simeon, sometimes called Feibush Ashkenazi, was active in Germany and Italy between 1440 and 1485. Fifteen of his manuscripts survive in public collections, including the British Library, the Vatican, the Library of Congress and the Jewish Theological Seminary.</p>
        <p>He was born in the Rhineland in the early 15th century and produced at least three illustrated manuscripts in Germany before moving to Italy about 1449. The Nuremberg Haggadah, which is signed but not dated, is thought to be his earliest surviving work.</p>
        <p>''Usually, the scribe is not the illuminator,'' Ms. Raccah-Djivre said. ''Ben Simeon did both. He was probably born in Cologne and traveled to fulfill personal orders. Jewish communities in Germany were very poor then. We think the Nuremberg Haggadah was done in Germany, even though no place is mentioned in the text, because once he leaves Germany, he points out in other texts that he came from Germany. His style also changed in Italy; it became more refined.''</p>
        <p>''A Haggadah done by Ben Simeon in Italy in 1454 is currently on display in ''Precious Possessions: Treasures From the Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary,'' at the seminary though Aug. 30.</p>
        <p>Sharon Liberman Mintz, curator of Jewish art at the seminary library, said: ''It was expensive to produce illuminated manuscripts. There were schools of Christian manuscript production in Paris, Oxford and elsewhere, but the demand wasn't there for Jewish scribes to work together in a workshop. Jews were not allowed in the Christian art guilds of Europe. When you commissioned a work from a Jewish scribe, you had to house and feed him. Most Jewish scribes were itinerant. They went from one patron to the next.''</p>
        <p>There may have been a shortage of Jewish artists. Pia Palladino, an assistant research curator of the Lehman Collection at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, said, ''Very often the illuminators who did 14th- and 15th-century Christian manuscripts also did Jewish texts; the technique employed doesn't vary.''</p>
        <p>Illuminated texts were highly prized by Jewish families, who passed them down from generation to generation. Haggadot are often marked by food and wine stains from the Seder. ''We also tend to have more Haggadot than other texts because it was a small book,'' Ms. Mintz said. ''A large Bible could take from 200 to 400 sheets of vellum.''</p>
        <p>Vellum was very expensive, according to Nellie Stavisky, the conservator of paper and parchment at the Jewish Theological Seminary library. ''It is a finer quality of parchment made from a young animal. An animal often yielded only one piece.'' Jewish artists had to buy vellum but they made their own paints. ''Colors came from grinding up precious stones, earth or plants,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Nuremberg Haggadah, which needs some conservation, retains its gold and vibrant colors. Mr. Jesselson, a native of Heidelberg, and Ms. Jesselson, a native of Vienna, knew the Nuremberg Haggadah because they had once seen it in the Schocken Library in Jerusalem. Shlomo Zalman Schocken, a German department store owner and publisher who moved from Berlin to Palestine in the 1930's, commissioned the Bauhaus architect Erich Mendelsohn to design a modern private library for his book collection and the Nuremberg Haggadah was in that library until Mr. Schocken's children consigned it to Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>''My late husband, Luddy, was determined to ensure that major manuscripts of Jewish heritage stay in Israel and lobbied the government to restrict their export,'' Ms. Jesselson said, ''Our gift fulfills Luddy's dreams for the destiny of this supremely important work.''</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
