<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peace Lobby</title>
    <meta content="FASHILT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Fashions of The Times Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="146" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/18/magazine/magazinespecial/18HILT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1416599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cairo (Egypt)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tel Aviv (Israel)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hilton International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilton, Conrad (1887-1979)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rechter, Ya'acov</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Tel Aviv</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt/Cairo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDD103AF93BA2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peace Lobby</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Peace Lobby</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Muschamp</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp article on Conrad Hilton's legendary Hilton International hotels, built in 1950's and 1960's, as major architectural statement on jet-age mobility; says high-style hotels in Middle Eastern cities were as much about diplomacy as hospitality, Cairo Hilton showcasing capitalism to newly-independent nation, and Tel Aviv and Jerusalem hotels 'explicitly Zionist in ambition'; Tel Aviv in particular, by Ya'acov Rechter, was experimental ground for first generation of Israeli architects to emigrate from Europe (special section, Fashions of The Times) (part 2 of 2-part section) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Effective immediately, the State, Justice, Treasury and Interior departments will be superceded by the Super Agency for All-American Style. As we all know, President Bush's restructuring of federal agencies is largely cosmetic. Therefore, we may as well let makeup artists and other professional image consultants take over the job. (See policy memos: ''Domestic Security -It's About the Eyes,'' ''Dull Lips Sink Ships,'' et al.)</p>
        <p>Given that the major conflicts threatening the world today are cultural, it is time to concede that politicians will never understand them. Designers, however, know what it takes to get along under trying circumstances. They know how to talk to people: clients, consumers and the press. Do not underestimate their skills in conflict resolution. They have saved many rocky marriages. They will not fail the community of nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conrad Hilton's high-style, midcentury Middle East hotels were as much about diplomacy as hospitality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Effective immediately, the State, Justice, Treasury and Interior departments will be superceded by the Super Agency for All-American Style. As we all know, President Bush's restructuring of federal agencies is largely cosmetic. Therefore, we may as well let makeup artists and other professional image consultants take over the job. (See policy memos: ''Domestic Security -It's About the Eyes,'' ''Dull Lips Sink Ships,'' et al.)</p>
        <p>Given that the major conflicts threatening the world today are cultural, it is time to concede that politicians will never understand them. Designers, however, know what it takes to get along under trying circumstances. They know how to talk to people: clients, consumers and the press. Do not underestimate their skills in conflict resolution. They have saved many rocky marriages. They will not fail the community of nations.</p>
        <p>Architects will not only design embassies but also occupy them. Interior, industrial, fashion and graphic designers will be our new consular corps. And all of us will look to the fountainhead (or is it the Fontainebleau?) of stylish international relations: the legendary Hilton International hotels.</p>
        <p>Constructed in the 1950's and 60's, Conrad Hilton's global empire was the world's first major architectural statement on the subject of jet-age mobility -- a transition from the International style of the 30's to today's monoculture, with its power to flatten cultural differences into global sameness. But the hotels made a good-faith effort to strike a reasonable balance between the homogenizing forces of modernity and the particulars of regional identity. Today, this effort may strike us as naïve. It consisted in many cases of upholstering harsh modern buildings with deluxe versions of ethnic ornamentation.</p>
        <p>Still, Hilton's ideological objectives were not sinister. When he began to build internationally, the United States had recently helped to win a just war. Our citizens and their leaders had lived through the Depression. Amid the postwar optimism and prosperity, few could imagine that the appetite for modernity's fruit might not be universally shared.</p>
        <p>I feel fortunate to be old enough to remember when modernity still felt clean, if not entirely new. Glad to have been young enough, also; too short in years to distinguish what was genuinely idealistic about the cold-war years from what was substantially a form of propaganda. When I was growing up in the 50's and early 60's, everything modern seemed worth running after. And when I look back at some of that era's architectural artifacts, I still find the distinction hard to discern. For a time, the ideals of democracy and of material prosperity were so tightly woven together that both could be easily transmitted in the same architectural code.</p>
        <p>Freedom, success and modernity were also embodied by Hilton himself. A native New Mexican, son of a small-town businessman, Hilton gained his first glimpse of the wide world while stationed in France during World War I, and on one level the International hotels were a boy's dream of a suitcase covered with exotic travel stickers: Athens, Rome, Istanbul. From this yearning was born the diffusion of the jet-set dream.</p>
        <p>And then along came Zsa Zsa. Hilton's marriage to the most glittering of the Gabor sisters symbolized his public embodiment of that dream. Zsa Zsa was an icon for the masses, and so was the self-styled ''Mr. Hotel.'' And for the price of a room, anyone could ascend to the stratosphere, at least for a night.</p>
        <p>From 1953 to 1966, Hilton constructed 16 luxury hotels in foreign cities. These are the subject of a brilliant study by Annabel Jane Wharton, published last year by the University of Chicago Press. Titled ''Building the Cold War,'' the book precisely decodes the ideology embodied by midcentury modern design.</p>
        <p>It is remarkable how much effort and intelligence went into the planning of these hotels. None, bear in mind, have joined the canon of great 20th-century masterworks. Some of them, however, should be included -- on aesthetic as well as sociological grounds, and also for the high degree of awareness with which they sought to coax architecture out of agonizing cultural conflicts. In light of the turmoil in the Middle East, Wharton's account of the design of the hotels in Cairo (1959), Tel Aviv (1965) and Jerusalem (1974) is particularly fascinating.</p>
        <p>The Nile Hilton in Cairo was a kind of West Berlin in miniature, an effort to showcase the advantages of capitalism in a country that had attained independence only seven years before. The hotel was designed by Welton Becket, a California architect best known for the fabulous Dorothy Chandler Pavilion in downtown Los Angeles, but who also produced buildings in styles as various as those that line the streets of Beverly Hills.</p>
        <p>Becket's talent for pastiche was extremely useful in creating a hotel that was essentially a high-rise billboard for the Western way of life. The Egyptian president Gamal Abdel Nasser, who sponsored the project, was eager to project a modern image for his young nation. His geopolitical loyalties, however, were divided. His young nation needed money. He was happy to accept Soviet support for the Aswan dam, but he was also eager for investment from capitalists. Hilton saw his hotel not just as a profitable investment, but also as a form of propaganda. ''In our current expansion,'' the hotelier wrote, ''Hilton Hotels International views itself as a medium for bettering the understanding of peoples by extending the best we have to offer in the American enterprise system to other countries.''</p>
        <p>As Wharton writes, the Hilton was sited to turn its back on Cairo, a medieval city of crowds and poverty. Instead, the windows and balconies of the best rooms framed postcard views of the pyramids, essentially erasing 4,000 years of Egyptian history from the tourist's experience (and obstructing Cairo's view of Egypt's own past in the process).</p>
        <p>The interior, which featured ersatz tomb reliefs and hieroglyphs, echoed this contraction of space and time between ancient Egypt and the modern West. From within and without, the views affirmed notions of a cultural mainstream flowing from the pharaohs to ourselves. The unsubtle message was that a common bond of tradition joined Egypt and the United States to a degree unmatched by the Soviet ''East.''</p>
        <p>The Tel Aviv and Jerusalem Hiltons embodied a different political agenda. Both were explicitly Zionist in ambition. Designed by Ya'acov Rechter, they were rooted in the intention to build a European country in an Eastern region. Nice work if you can get it, and Israel's architects had been getting it well before the country's creation in 1948.</p>
        <p>Tel Aviv, in particular, was an experimental ground for the first generation of architects to emigrate from Europe to Palestine. In the 1930's, it became the world's most complete urban realization of ideas developed at the Bauhaus under the direction of Walter Gropius.</p>
        <p>In hindsight, it is clear that the European origins of modern architecture would be grounds for conflict with local customs. But the architects of the time believed that modern architecture was inherently capable of transcending, if not precisely bridging, the gulfs that separated cultures.</p>
        <p>The ambition may have been utopian, but European architects had already succeeded in transforming utopian dreams into realized buildings. After World War II, they had produced the templates for social housing in the Netherlands, Germany, Italy, France, Britain and other nations. That aesthetic, conventionally associated with the Bauhaus, had also been embraced by wealthy patrons. Modern architecture had bridged the social classes, in other words. Why couldn't it narrow the gaps between cultural traditions?</p>
        <p>With structures of rough exposed concrete and sharply geometric balconies and windows, Rechter's Brutalist Hilton hotels reflected the influence of Le Corbusier and Louis Kahn. Glass was less conspicuous. Intended to attain greater harmony with the landscape and ancient building traditions, the concrete also conveyed the impression of fortresses under siege.</p>
        <p>Those who have actually stayed in a Hilton discover soon enough that the fortress appearance is deceptive. The function of the design is not to keep people out but to prevent those who are in from leaving. Good guests should stay within the grounds and spend their dollars there.</p>
        <p>I first encountered this strategy 30 years ago during a stay at what was then the Kahala Hilton in Honolulu. Situated in a compound outside Honolulu, the Kahala was surrounded by a golf course, gardens and artificial lagoons in which porpoises leapt and plunged in synchronized routines. There was a Polynesian floor show.</p>
        <p>Chandeliers made of beach glass hung in the huge lobby, which also came furnished with a hostess, an attractive woman dressed in a long flowered gown, a variation on the muumuu. Since this was my first visit to Hawaii, I wanted to see something besides the hotel -- something of Hawaii, in fact.</p>
        <p>''But this is Hawaii,'' the hostess said. ''This is the best of Hawaii.''</p>
        <p>''I mean, the real Hawaii.''</p>
        <p>''But this is the real Hawaii. We have everything here. Would you like to go to our luau? There is no other Hawaii.''</p>
        <p>I retreated, so confused that I would have believed the hostess had she continued further in this surreal vein: ''There is no real Hawaii. There is no Hawaii. * ''What idiot went to the Kahala Hilton for reality, anyhow? Or to Hawaii, for that matter? You want authenticity? Go home!</p>
        <p>Hawaii, the lady tried to tell me, is a state of mind. So are Istanbul, Athens, Cairo and the other cities that came to be dominated by Hilton's out-of-scale dream palaces. The emotional interior, the inner world, is the true foreign land. But this, of course, more nearly resembles the psychology of the prison than of the traditional traveler. Alcatraz would make a fine resort, too, if they let Philippe Starck do it over with billowing white curtains.</p>
        <p>And is it not true that boutique hotels are Hilton's postmodern equivalent? Hotels like the ones Starck has designed have become icons in the era of globalization. This era has intensified a struggle that has been going on since the end of World War II: a culture war between the creative classes clustered in older urban centers and the consumer-based lifestyle of the suburbs. Boutique hotels have become our embassies of urbanity. Forget the United Nations. What we need now is a League of Cities: a Secretariat of Cosmopolitan Style.</p>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp is the architecture critic of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herbert Muschamp is the architecture critic of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
