<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheering Tax Cuts, Fearing Deficits</title>
    <meta content="MB022517" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1460447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE UNION: THE NATIONAL MOOD -- THE CONSULTANT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D81139F93AA15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheering Tax Cuts, Fearing Deficits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <dateline>FAYETTEVILLE, Ga., Jan. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To gauge response to President Bush's State of the Union address last night, The New York Times spoke to Americans who may be affected by the plans he laid out.</p>
        <p>Raymond Cornelius, 43, a financial consultant at Salomon Smith Barney who voted for George Bush in 2000, sat up on his couch when he heard Mr. Bush promise new and faster tax cuts. And he burst into a wide grin when the president promoted private investment accounts for Social Security taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To gauge response to President Bush's State of the Union address last night, The New York Times spoke to Americans who may be affected by the plans he laid out.</p>
        <p>Raymond Cornelius, 43, a financial consultant at Salomon Smith Barney who voted for George Bush in 2000, sat up on his couch when he heard Mr. Bush promise new and faster tax cuts. And he burst into a wide grin when the president promoted private investment accounts for Social Security taxes.</p>
        <p>''Amen, brother!'' Mr. Cornelius said to his wife, Sabrina. ''He's preaching now.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cornelius said he remained unconvinced that all those tax cuts would really speed up the economy. He said eliminating the dividend tax, in particular, would probably do nothing at all to help in the short term, though as an investment adviser he supported the cut.</p>
        <p>''I'm still concerned how we're going to pay for it, because the stimulus package has to work quickly,'' Mr. Cornelius said. ''We have to fund it in the meantime, and we fund it through deficits. And how long can we wait? It seems like a Democrat got us out of debt, and a Republican is getting us into it again.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cornelius, 40, a human resources executive at Delta Airlines who voted for Al Gore, said, ''I was just thinking we'll just have to elect a Democrat president to get us out of all this mess.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's promise to put ''doctors, nurses and patients back in charge'' met with skepticism.</p>
        <p>''He's saying what we want to hear, but how's he going to follow through with that?'' Mr. Cornelius asked.</p>
        <p>He and his wife said they were thrilled to hear the president promote the development of hydrogen-powered automobiles, especially if it reduced dependence on foreign oil. They thought that his promise of $15 billion to fight AIDS in Africa was laudable, but they wondered whether the country could afford it.</p>
        <p>As the president turned to terrorism and Iraq, the Corneliuses looked at each other in surprise as Mr. Bush alluded to nameless terrorists who had been ''eliminated.''</p>
        <p>''Does that mean killed?'' their son, Barrett, 11, asked his parents, who said it did.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush promised to go it alone with Iraq, if necessary, the couple said they had little doubt what that meant.</p>
        <p>''It sounds like we're going to war,'' Mrs. Cornelius said, checking her watch to note the date.</p>
        <p>''I think this is the speech,'' her husband agreed. ''Walk softly and carry a big stick? How about thunder around and carry a big stick.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cornelius said, ''I hate for us to go to war, but I hate even worse walking around worrying when the next terrorist is going to strike.''</p>
        <p>DAVID M. HALBFINGER</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE UNION: THE NATIONAL MOOD -- THE CONSULTANT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
