<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sears Is Sued By Executive It Dismissed At Credit Unit</title>
    <meta content="Y29SEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/29/business/29SEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1460300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sears Roebuck and Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1D81039F93AA15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sears Is Sued By Executive It Dismissed At Credit Unit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sears Is Sued by Executive It Dismissed at Credit Unit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, which dismissed the president of its credit division in October shortly before announcing unexpected losses at the unit, is being sued by the executive, Kevin T. Keleghan, for defamation and breach of contract.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, filed in an Illinois state court in November and reported yesterday in The Chicago Tribune, says that Mr. Keleghan has not received the severance pay he was entitled to after signing a contract in September. It also accuses the chief executive of Sears, Alan J. Lacy, of defaming Mr. Keleghan when Mr. Lacy said he withheld information and otherwise ''wasn't forthcoming'' about problems at the credit division. Sears set aside an additional $222 million to cover unpaid debt from its credit card operations in the third quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck, which dismissed the president of its credit division shortly before announcing unexpected losses, is being sued by the executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, which dismissed the president of its credit division in October shortly before announcing unexpected losses at the unit, is being sued by the executive, Kevin T. Keleghan, for defamation and breach of contract.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, filed in an Illinois state court in November and reported yesterday in The Chicago Tribune, says that Mr. Keleghan has not received the severance pay he was entitled to after signing a contract in September. It also accuses the chief executive of Sears, Alan J. Lacy, of defaming Mr. Keleghan when Mr. Lacy said he withheld information and otherwise ''wasn't forthcoming'' about problems at the credit division. Sears set aside an additional $222 million to cover unpaid debt from its credit card operations in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Sears, which is seeking to have the claims dismissed, said Mr. Lacy's comments were ''protected expressions of opinion.'' In its response, filed on Jan. 17, the company accuses Mr. Keleghan of signing the severance agreement ''without disclosing to Sears facts'' that might have led to his dismissal.</p>
        <p>''They have probably been negotiating with him, to no avail,'' said Anita Boomstein, a credit executive in Manhattan who once worked with Mr. Keleghan. ''He is taking steps he feels are appropriate to protect his reputation.''</p>
        <p>The announcement on Oct. 17 about problems at the credit division, stemming largely from a campaign to move many Sears cardholders to Gold MasterCard accounts that offered more generous credit limits and check-writing privileges, came nearly two weeks after Mr. Keleghan left the company. It angered many analysts, who felt Sears should have detailed its credit problems sooner.</p>
        <p>Sears derives 60 percent of its income from its credit operations. About 37 percent of its credit card receivables come from MasterCard, and the rest from Sears cards. Since the Depression, credit cards have been an integral part of the Sears business, and the company says the cards help to drive sales of big-ticket items like washing machines and refrigerators.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Lacy said Mr. Keleghan had failed to give him information about the status of the money owed to Sears by cardholders. He later said that Mr. Keleghan ''was not forthcoming about what was happening in his business,'' and added: ''My statement that I had lost confidence in his credibility is an accurate statement, and it's as nice as I can phrase it.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts said that Mr. Lacy, who once managed the credit division, should have been aware of any problems. On Oct. 17, the share price of Sears stock plunged 32 percent, losing more than $10 a share in a single trading session.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, shares of Sears closed at $25.65, down $1.08.</p>
        <p>The company also confirmed yesterday that Anastasia D. Kelly, its general counsel, had resigned. A Sears spokeswoman said she did not know why Ms. Kelly was leaving or what her plans were. Another executive, Ronald Culp, who has spent 10 years at Sears in the public relations department, said last week that he would retire, the spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>''At this point, I would say that everybody is pretty weary,'' said Roz Bryant, a retail analyst for Morningstar in Chicago, ''and announcements like this don't help.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
