<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="599146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DD1E3CF932A05750C0A965958260" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-13  ISRAEL HARDENS ITS STAND  Israel sealed off the West Bank and Gaza Strip indefinitely, and Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin urged Israelis to stand firm in "an all-out war against terrorism." Two Israeli policemen were killed overnight in the worst violence in years.  A1  NEW BARRIER TO ARMS REDUCTION  The political unrest in Russia has stalled efforts to reduce nuclear arsenals in the United States and the former Soviet Union. In Ukraine, new fears of Russian nationalism have encouraged a vocal group of legislators who advocate keeping some weapons.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-13  ISRAEL HARDENS ITS STAND  Israel sealed off the West Bank and Gaza Strip indefinitely, and Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin urged Israelis to stand firm in "an all-out war against terrorism." Two Israeli policemen were killed overnight in the worst violence in years.  A1  NEW BARRIER TO ARMS REDUCTION  The political unrest in Russia has stalled efforts to reduce nuclear arsenals in the United States and the former Soviet Union. In Ukraine, new fears of Russian nationalism have encouraged a vocal group of legislators who advocate keeping some weapons.  A1</p>
        <p>TOUGH TALK FROM THE U.S.  Secretary of State Warren Christopher branded Iran an "international outlaw" because of what he called its support for international terrorism and its determination to develop nuclear weapons. He also threatened Libya with a global oil embargo because of its refusal to hand over two officials accused of the 1988 bombing of a Pan Am jet.  A3  ANOTHER RESIGNATION IN ITALY  Italy's Finance Minister resigned after being told he was under investigation for receiving stolen goods in the country's growing corruption scandal. Of the 24 ministers named by Prime Minister Giuliano Amato when he came to power last June, six have been implicated.  A3  DEATH SENTENCES IN BOSNIA  In Sarajevo, two men were sentenced to death by firing squad for a rampage of killing and rape while serving with Serbian nationalist forces in Bosnia. One defendant confessed to 35 killings and 16 rapes of Muslims; the other was accused of taking part in many attacks.  A6  U.S. WITHHOLDS ENDORSEMENT  The United States has rejected a plan for a Security Council resolution to give full support to the Bosnian peace plan drawn up by the two Balkan mediators, diplomats said. Britain, France and Spain want the Security Council to endorse the plan and to then threaten the Serbs with new sanctions unless they sign the accord within 15 days.  A6  INDIA CANCELS LOAN FOR A DAM  In a victory for environmental groups, the Indian Government canceled much of a $450 million World Bank loan for a vast irrigation and hydroelectric project because it cannot meet the bank's environmental and resettlement standards.  A5  QUARREL OVER ULSTER CONTINUES  Two days after a large demonstration in Dublin calling for peace in Northern Ireland, Dublin opposed a proposal to put a peace settlement to a referendum.  A7  UNCERTAINTY OVER NORTH KOREA  More than two weeks after North Korea pulled out of the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty, its neighbors still disagree sharply about whether to respond with harsh sanctions Concern is growing that a misstep could renew hostilities in one of the most heavily armed parts of the world.  A9  A RULING ON DEAD SEA SCROLLS  A Jerusalem court ruled that an Israeli professor had a copyright on his reconstruction of one of the Dead Sea Scrolls.  A12  France's new prime minister names a conservative Cabinet.  A8  Cairo Journal: For foreigners, the good life gives way to fear.  A4  National A14-21  CLINTON RETREATS ON LAND POLICY  President Clinton backed away from a major change in the way Federal land is managed after Western senators warned that they might oppose his economic program.  A1  BUDGET POLITICS: A CASE STUDY  Even as they embrace deficit reduction, lawmakers are fighting to save programs that benefit their districts. The intricacies of budget politics are most evident in the all-out effort by Texas and Louisiana to save the superconducting supercollider.  A20  HOUSE CUTS BACK, A LITTLE  Rejecting Republican demands for a deep reduction in staff, the House voted to cut spending on its committees this year by only 5 percent below the 1992 level.  A20  Lawmakers reacted coolly to the Pentagon's "holding budget." A20  House and Senate negotiators reached a pact on the deficit.  A20  B.C.C.I. TRIAL BEGINS  The state B.C.C.I. trial began in New York, and it became clear that one of the defendants, Clark M. Clifford, the hospitalized former Defense Secretary Presidential adviser, would be prosecuted in absentia.  A1  ON GUARD, DOCTORS  Americans underestimate the salaries of doctors and health-care executives and nevertheless think the salaries are too high, a poll found.  A21  WHERE SCIENCE AND LAW COLLIDE  The Supreme Court wrestled with the question of how judges should decide when a scientific theory or process is sound enough to be admitted as evidence.  A19  N.A.A.C.P. LOOKS INTO THE FOG  The N.A.A.C.P. is in transition, but to where, no one quite knows. The uncertainty shows in the group's tortuous search for a new leader.  A14  SCARCITY OF ABORTION DOCTORS  The recent shooting of an abortion doctor in Florida underscores the difficulty clinics face in finding doctors who will put up with the death threats, tedium and low pay of abortion practice.  A14  BIOLOGICAL PARENTS WIN BACK GIRL  A Michigan court ordered a state couple who raised a 2-year-old girl from infancy to return her to her biological parents in Iowa.  A17  BAN ON SPEAKING FEES IS LIFTED  Striking down a 1989 ethics law, a Federal appeals court said Government employees may accept payment for giving speeches.  A19  David Koresh met with a lawyer hired by his mother.  A18  A symbol of white supremacy is under attack in New Orleans.  A16  Education Page B8  Metro Digest B1  PROPOSALS FOR U.S. ATTORNEY  Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan recommended the appointment of the first woman and first black to be United States Attorneys in New York, and both candidates said they would put a greater emphasis than their predecessors on prosecuting civil rights cases.  A1  HAMPERED BY IMAGE  As Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield struggles with staggering financial losses -- more than $250 million in the last two years -- officials of the nonprofit health insurer maintain a decades-old tradition of high corporate living that belies the company's dire financial situation.  A1  Obituaries B9-10  RICHARD DIEBENKORN DIES  One of the premier postwar American painters, the California painter of lyrical abstractions was 70.  A1  Business Digest D1  Living Section C1-13  Sports B11-16  Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23  Editorials  The blame for Empire's mess.  The Oscars' neglect.  Teaching Mr. Murdoch.  Letters  Anna Quindlen: But not both.  John J. Mearsheimer: Shrink Bosnia to save it.  David Cohen: Notes on a Grecian yearn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
