<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada Moves to Strengthen Sexual Assault Law</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Law Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAMPBELL, KIM (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DA173BF932A15751C0A964958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada Moves to Strengthen Sexual Assault Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Feb. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While headlines were being made by the William Kennedy Smith and Mike Tyson rape trials in the United States, a case involving many of the same complex and controversial issues was unfolding in the quiet town of Kingston in eastern Ontario.</p>
        <p>Last December, as in the case of Mr. Smith, the Kingston trial ended in acquittal, angering some women's groups. They saw the outcome as further supporting their argument that Canadian rape laws do not adequately protect the rights of women. The previous August, Canada's Supreme Court voided some protections for accusers under the nation's rape-shield law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While headlines were being made by the William Kennedy Smith and Mike Tyson rape trials in the United States, a case involving many of the same complex and controversial issues was unfolding in the quiet town of Kingston in eastern Ontario.</p>
        <p>Last December, as in the case of Mr. Smith, the Kingston trial ended in acquittal, angering some women's groups. They saw the outcome as further supporting their argument that Canadian rape laws do not adequately protect the rights of women. The previous August, Canada's Supreme Court voided some protections for accusers under the nation's rape-shield law.</p>
        <p>The feeling over the issue has fueled an intense national debate about Canada's laws regarding sexual assault. It has also prompted Kim Campbell, the Minister of Justice who is the first woman to hold the post, to propose changes to the criminal code. They include an unusually restrictive definition of consensual sex. Such a definition is intended to make it easier to win convictions in rape cases.</p>
        <p>In the Kingston case, Robert VanOostrom, a 23-year-old graduate student in chemical engineering at Queen's University, was charged with sexually assaulting three female undergraduates. The women acknowledged having befriended Mr. VanOostrom, but they asserted that he had forced himself on them. Furor Over the Verdict</p>
        <p>Mr. VanOostrom's lawyer, Brian H. Greenspan, built a case around the contention that the women, carried away by rising anxieties about date rape that have swept Canadian campuses recently, had recast their relationships with the defendant to make consensual sex seem like rape.</p>
        <p>The defense created a furor. As Mr. VanOostrom left the courthouse after his acquittal, a crowd of women rocked his car, shouted "Guilty!" and spray-painted slogans, including "Stop Rape, Stop Rob," on the courthouse steps.</p>
        <p>The anger has been fueled nationwide by reports of cases in which men with a history of sexual violence and who were free on bail or parole have sexually attacked and killed women.  The uproar has been further stoked by recent statistics showing that people convicted of crimes in the least serious category of sexual offenses get lighter sentences, on average, than are given to people who have been convicted of burglary.</p>
        <p>The reported incidence of sexual assault in Canada has risen sharply. The Ministry of Justice said there were 29,111 cases in 1988, more than double the 12,848 cases recorded in 1982. Figures for that six-year span were the most recent for which statistics were widely available. Legislative Changes Sought</p>
        <p>Members of women's groups, criminologists, sociologists and others urging stronger measures were heartened in December when Minister Campbell proposed a package of legislative changes to the criminal code's provisions on rape. At the core of the new bill, the legal definition of sexual consent would have the effect of eliminating, or sharply narrowing, some of the pleas used by defendants who have won acquittal in rape cases.</p>
        <p>One major provision would require that defendants show that they took "all reasonable steps" to affirm an accuser's consent. Other provisions would restore protections for accusers under parts of the rape-shield law that were voided last August.</p>
        <p>In the United States, rape laws vary considerably by state, with the strictest laws still requiring a demonstration of a show of force, and the most liberal making it a crime to have sexual intercourse with a woman without her consent. But prosecutors in states with the most liberal laws said that as a practical matter it would be difficult to win a conviction in a case in which a woman had remained silent and had not resisted intercourse.</p>
        <p>In Canada, while the new bill awaits study by a parliamentary committee, a storm has broken over Ms. Campbell, a 44-year-old lawyer from Vancouver.</p>
        <p>Strong objections have been raised by groups representing criminal lawyers as well as by editorial writers and columnists. They have objected in particular to provisions that deal with drinking and drugs. For example, one provision stipulates that a defendant in a sexual assault trial could not claim to have had consent if the accuser in the case was "incapable of consenting to the activity by reason of intoxication or other condition."</p>
        <p>Ridiculing such provisions, Mr. Greenspan, the lawyer who won Mr. VanOostrom's acquittal and who is president of the Criminal Lawyers' Association of Ontario, said in an interview that Canadian men might have to travel with portable breathalyzers to be able to determine the sobriety of potential sexual partners.</p>
        <p>Critics have also focused on the bill's requirement that a defendant in a rape case demonstrate that he took "all reasonable steps" to ascertain that he had obtained his partner's consent. To critics like Mr. Greenspan, this is unrealistic in view of the inexplicit manner in which many men and women move toward having sex. He said it might mean that they would have to interrupt their passion to deal with the matter of consent.</p>
        <p>"In the end, I know of no way of doing that other than actively seeking a 'yes,' " Mr. Greenspan said.</p>
        <p>Another section of the bill has potentially far-reaching implications for executives, professors and others who have sexual relationships with people who work or study under their authority. As proposed, the section would not allow a defendant to argue that sex was consensual in cases in which his accuser is shown to have engaged in sexual activity "by reason of the accused's abuse of a position of trust or authority."</p>
        <p>For example, some criminal lawyers have said, the clause could open the way for malicious rape prosecutions by women who willingly engaged in sex with their bosses and were later spurned. In such instances, the lawyers said, the cases could turn on a assertion by a woman that she was afraid to refuse a man's advances, regardless of whether the prosecution was able to demonstrate that she was coerced.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell hastened the drafting of the new bill after the Court's decision last August to void part of the 1983 rape-shield law. In its ruling, the Court struck down a provision in the law that restricted evidence about an accuser's past sexual activities to matters involving previous sexual relations with the defendant. Delving Into Accuser's Past</p>
        <p>The Minister, who had strongly opposed allowing courts to delve into accusers' sexual histories, includedprovisions in the bill that would enforce the Court's ruling while limiting its repercussions.</p>
        <p>The bill offers strict guidelines for judges in determining which, if any, evidence about an accuser's past could be admitted at trial. Lawyers seeking to present evidence about an accuser's past would have to do so in a closed hearing with the jury absent. A defense move to introduce such evidence would have to deal with a specific instance of sexual activity, not a pattern of behavior.</p>
        <p>The bill also provides that an accuser cannot be compelled to appear or testify at the evidence hearing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
