<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Culpepper to Moss, and That's to Green's Credit in Minnesota</title>
    <meta content="26NFLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/26/sports/26NFLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Vikings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Culpepper, Daunte</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Minnesota Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4DF1F3AF935A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Culpepper to Moss, and That's to Green's Credit in Minnesota</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minnesota Vikings Coach Dennis Green was excoriated by news media when he decided to go with Daunte Culpepper as starting quarterback, but has been vindicated by excellent performance and winning record; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Minnesota quarterback Daunte Culpepper made the smart throw in the face of a blitz, as he has done so many times this season, this time against Dallas on Thanksgiving Day. It was the third quarter, the Vikings were in Cowboys territory and Culpepper, not wanting to take a sack, wisely threw the ball away.</p>
        <p>His only mistake: he missed a wide-open Randy Moss, who had gotten behind the secondary. On occasion, this happens, even to Hall of Fame throwers, let alone young ones like Culpepper. ''On that play, Daunte had a lot to think about,'' Minnesota's offensive coordinator, Sherman Lewis, said, ''and a lot of people in his face.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Minnesota quarterback Daunte Culpepper made the smart throw in the face of a blitz, as he has done so many times this season, this time against Dallas on Thanksgiving Day. It was the third quarter, the Vikings were in Cowboys territory and Culpepper, not wanting to take a sack, wisely threw the ball away.</p>
        <p>His only mistake: he missed a wide-open Randy Moss, who had gotten behind the secondary. On occasion, this happens, even to Hall of Fame throwers, let alone young ones like Culpepper. ''On that play, Daunte had a lot to think about,'' Minnesota's offensive coordinator, Sherman Lewis, said, ''and a lot of people in his face.''</p>
        <p>Moss was not so understanding. He blew up, screaming at Culpepper as he walked off the field. Culpepper snapped back and they  went at it for several minutes, jawing before a national television audience.</p>
        <p>Then, as quickly as the storm erupted, it became calm again, the two shaking hands and making up. And just to make sure there were no hard feelings, Culpepper later found Moss for a 36-yard touchdown.</p>
        <p>Maybe they should fight more often.</p>
        <p>On the surface, the chemistry between the two stars, one established in Moss, another on the rise in Culpepper, seems shaky. But that is not the case. They are actually extremely close. ''Like brothers,'' Vikings Coach Dennis Green said. ''I have four older brothers and you have disagreements.''</p>
        <p>Lewis said: ''Randy is an emotional player. About two to three minutes after he erupts, he calms down, and he's fine.''</p>
        <p>This is the core of the 10-2 Vikings, now perhaps the best team in football. They are a solid, passionate team, led by two unlikely players. Some teams refused to draft Moss two years ago because of off-the-field issues. And when Green turned over the reins of the offense to Culpepper this off-season, the coach was ripped by many in the news media as having lost his mind.</p>
        <p>It is safe to say Green has been thoroughly vindicated.</p>
        <p>''I don't worry about vindication,'' Green said. ''I'm totally at peace. We love coaching Randy and Daunte. We think we're the luckiest guys in the world. We have two players who we rated as the No. 1 player in each of their drafts. Randy Moss was our top-rated player in 1998. We had him rated ahead of Peyton Manning. And we had Culpepper No. 1 in 1999 and we were lucky enough to get him.''</p>
        <p>Culpepper was able to step in and perform at such a high level, despite this being only his second year in the league, because in addition to his talent, he has the benefit of working in Green's system.</p>
        <p>Over the last three years, Minnesota has a 35-9 regular-season record, the best of any team over that period. If the Vikings make the playoffs, which is a near certainty, then Culpepper would be the seventh Minnesota quarterback to lead his team to the postseason since 1992. Dallas and San Francisco are the only other teams to make seven playoff appearances in that span, and both did it with one quarterback at the helm in Troy Aikman and Steve Young.</p>
        <p>Green has gone to the playoffs with quarterbacks Sean Salisbury (a career backup), Jim McMahon (well beyond his prime), Brad Johnson (good but injury prone), Warren Moon (old), Randall Cunningham (out of football for more than a year) and Jeff George (a career knucklehead). Green's system is so quarterback-friendly, he could probably plug in almost any player and he would do well. Stick in a talent like Culpepper and you get this edition of the Vikings, who could win a championship.</p>
        <p>That is probably why Green could not understand all the heavy breathing by the news media about his decision to let Cunningham and George go and stick with Culpepper. Green has made that kind of tough decision about the quarterback, rather successfully, a number of times.</p>
        <p>Green's formula for success is simple. Combine a fast running back (Robert Smith) with a speedy vertical game (Culpepper, Moss and Cris Carter) and you get a lot of victories. While once-great franchises like Green Bay, San Francisco and the Cowboys have struggled under the salary cap, Green is a lock to win at least 10 games a season. Because of smart drafting and the development of young players like Culpepper, the Vikings have not suffered a drop-off.</p>
        <p>As for Culpepper and Moss, they said their highly visible dispute was well behind them.</p>
        <p>''That's just being the competitor that I am,'' Moss said of the argument. ''I think my whole team understands how I am and how I play. They blitzed, and I was open for the first down. It wasn't anything that we'll hold against one another. Daunte knows that I like to compete, and I know what I expect out of Daunte, and that's just the best.''</p>
        <p>Not From Quarterback U.</p>
        <p>''You know, sometimes the N.F.L. makes mistakes, it happens,'' St. Louis quarterback Kurt Warner said earlier this season. ''As great as this league is, there are people who make mistakes in judgments about players.''</p>
        <p>Warner was speaking of his own career. You know his story: Undrafted. Arena League. Grocery store clerk. Signed by the Rams and leads them to the Super Bowl, where he was the most valuable player.</p>
        <p>The league needs players like Warner, who come along and shake up the personnel status quo, forcing the league to say, ''How did we miss that guy?''</p>
        <p>Even though Warner's story is highly unusual, something interesting is happening across the N.F.L. Of all the division-leading teams, none of the starting quarterbacks is from a traditional football university.</p>
        <p>The Miami Dolphins lead the American Football Conference East and their quarterback is Jay Fiedler, who attended Dartmouth. In the Central, Tennessee is on top, led by Steve McNair, from Alcorn State. In the West, division-leading Oakland is quarterbacked by Rich Gannon, a graduate of Delaware, known as the Fighting Blue Hens.</p>
        <p>In the National Football Conference, the East is led by Philadelphia, where Donovan McNabb is at the helm. He went to Syracuse, known more for basketball than football. In the Central, if Minnesota reaches the Super Bowl, it will have done so primarily because of the steady play of Daunte Culpepper. His college? Central Florida. Finally there are the Rams in the West and Warner, who will return to the starting lineup from a broken hand as early as next week, and he attended Northern Iowa.</p>
        <p>Gannon has passed for 792 yards and seven touchdowns in his past three games. His 340 rushing yards leads A.F.C. quarterbacks. McNabb's four rushing touchdowns are the most by an Eagles quarterback since Randall Cunningham ran for five in 1992. This season, Warner and his backup, Trent Green, have combined for a 109.5 passer rating, 4,104 passing yards, a 66.1 completion percentage and 32 touchdown passes. Culpepper has a 96.7 passer rating.</p>
        <p>Teams often scout the major colleges to find quarterbacks, and rightfully so. That is normally where the best competition plays. But on occasion, a player like Warner shakes things up.</p>
        <p>A Lighter Wallet</p>
        <p>The terrible season of the 2-9 Cincinnati Bengals is costing the rookie Peter Warrick, who was used to winning championships while at Florida State, more than dents in his pride. It's costing him cash.</p>
        <p>Warrick has only 37 catches for 417 yards. The picture gets uglier when you look at his contract. If Warrick gets 801 receiving yards on the season, the team has to pay him a $500,000 bonus and increase his base salary $500,000 each of the next five seasons.</p>
        <p>To reach 801 yards Warrick needs to average 77 receiving yards the last five games. Considering the way the Bengals are playing, that probably will not happen.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
