<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Elegant, So Intelligent</title>
    <meta content="26KIRSCHT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirsch, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donoghue, Denis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Words Alone: The Poet T.S. Eliot (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DB153BF935A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Elegant, So Intelligent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Kirsch</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirsch, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Kirsch reviews book Words Alone: The Poet T.S. Eliot by Denis Donoghue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Words Alone</p>
        <p>The Poet T. S. Eliot.</p>
        <p>By Denis Donoghue.</p>
        <p>326 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Words Alone</p>
        <p>The Poet T. S. Eliot.</p>
        <p>By Denis Donoghue.</p>
        <p>326 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $26.95.</p>
        <p>T. S. ELIOT knew that his carefully constructed persona could be forbidding. He satirized himself, gently but tellingly, in a piece of light verse:</p>
        <p>How unpleasant to meet Mr. Eliot!</p>
        <p>With his features of clerical cut,</p>
        <p>And his brow so grim</p>
        <p>And his mouth so prim</p>
        <p>And his conversation, so nicely</p>
        <p>Restricted to What Precisely</p>
        <p>And If and Perhaps and But.</p>
        <p>But surely Eliot, for all his self-mockery, would be disturbed to see how truly unpleasant many readers now find him. The clerical features have hardened into the pinched visage of the reactionary, the anti-Semite, the emotional cripple, familiar from such works as Anthony Julius's ''T. S. Eliot, Anti-Semitism, and Literary Form'' and the play ''Tom and Viv.'' The moment is ripe for a return swing of the critical pendulum, a renewed respect for the great originality and beauty of his poetry, and a more sophisticated analysis of its shortcomings.</p>
        <p>Denis Donoghue's new book may help to begin that movement. Its title and subtitle, though simple enough, are practically a clarion call: the words and the poet are Donoghue's concern, the mind that created rather than the man who suffered. Probing, wide-ranging, sometimes unsatisfactory, ''Words Alone'' is always valuable for its respectful seriousness toward Eliot's poetry.</p>
        <p>The book is billed as an ''intellectual memoir,'' which is misleading; there is little here about Donoghue, an eminent critic and professor at New York University, or the circumstances in which he first read Eliot. If ''Words Alone'' differs from a standard critical study, it is in Donoghue's willingness to browse informally through his reading, to use his sources as inspiration rather than armor. Indeed, he can err on the other side: he is sometimes too casual, and does not always draw out his themes and topics with sufficient clarity.</p>
        <p>But Donoghue does offer at least two important insights into Eliot's verse. The first is a reply to the question that every reader of Eliot, even today, must often ask: ''What does it mean?'' So many passages have grown familiar in contour that we forget that their substance remains opaque. Donoghue skillfully deploys Eliot's literary criticism, especially the less-known early reviews, to argue that ''Eliot's genius took the form of the auditory more than the visual imagination'' -- or, in other words, that his ''language goes some distance toward giving words . . . independent life.'' This is one of many instances in which Eliot the critic -- who praised Dante for his lucidity of image, and roundly chastised Milton for his ''complication . . . dictated by a demand of verbal music'' -- disagrees with, and disguises, Eliot the poet. Donoghue insists on Eliot's affinities with Tennyson, Poe and Mallarme, which supplement (without canceling) his self-proclaimed allegiances to Dante, Donne and Laforgue.</p>
        <p>Donoghue's second major insight deals with the later religious poetry, and has to do with Eliot's ''examining local forces and conditions within the highest perspective'' -- that is, from a Christian perspective. Christianity played a delicate double role for Eliot, which Donoghue sensitively describes. ''The deepest quandary in Eliot's poetry,'' he writes, is ''his feeling, in part, that all the declared values of human life are somehow illusory and, in part, that nevertheless God so loved the world that He gave up for its redemption His beloved Son.'' The first of these ''parts'' is the first to appear in Eliot's life and verse: his disgust at mankind, both himself and other specimens. Much of ''The Waste Land'' is an expression of this feeling; so too are poems like ''Burbank With a Baedeker: Bleistein With a Cigar,'' with its hints of anti-Semitism.</p>
        <p>Christianity was a ''higher perspective'' in which this disgust could be redeemed, and transformed into love. Thus Eliot's Christianity is always ascetic, doubtful, not to say guilty: ''Love is the unfamiliar Name / Behind the hands that wove / The intolerable shirt of flame / Which human power cannot remove.'' And thus, too, it can seem an egoistic, unappealing form of religion, even a form of spiritual pride. It is because Eliot was aware of these ambiguities that his Christian poetry is genuine and moving, not just an exercise in nostalgia or willed devotion.</p>
        <p>UNFORTUNATELY, Donoghue sometimes allows his fine sense of these matters to be coarsened by controversy. His interventions in the debate over Eliot's anti-Semitism do not do justice to the complexity of the issue, and at moments are simply querulous. ''That he is accused of anti-Semitism,'' Donoghue writes, ''seems to me an injustice''; but that Eliot was, at least occasionally, anti-Semitic is impossible to deny. It is legitimate to argue that anti-Semitism was far from the center of Eliot's thought and art, that it was merely a common class prejudice or a questionable outgrowth of his theology. But Donoghue's peremptory anger at the charge leads him to lash out at those who ''attack Christianity and . . . deride any Christian's faith'' while claiming ''to be appalled by anti-Semitism'' -- and this equation misses the point. The intellectual revolt against Christianity in the West is a revolt from within, and is not stained with blood, as anti-Semitism has so terribly been. And Donoghue goes further:</p>
        <p>''I appreciate the fact that, since the Holocaust, Jews must be treated with particular tenderness. In American politics, Israel is treated as a special case; the sensibilities of its citizens are cherished beyond the consideration given to other people. But the convention by which exceptional tenderness is maintained toward those sensibilities should be questioned.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, this is motivated by impatience and a desire to vindicate Eliot's honor. But it is obtuse about the moral issues raised by the Holocaust, and does Donoghue little credit. To ascribe the West's wariness of anti-Semitism to a questionable ''tenderness'' toward Jews -- rather than to an eminently merited sense of guilt and self-scrutiny -- is myopic and wrongheaded. More to the point, it sheds no light on Eliot, whose anti-Semitic statements date from before World War II. In a book generally sane and penetrating, such blemishes stand out all the more clearly.</p>
        <p>Adam Kirsch is a poet and critic living in New York City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Adam Kirsch is a poet and critic living in New York City.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
