<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprinter in Balco Scandal Is Suspended</title>
    <meta content="11COLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/11/sports/othersports/11collins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Anti-Doping Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Court of Arbitration for Sport</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EEDE1E31F932A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprinter in Balco Scandal Is Suspended</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sprinter in Balco Scandal Is Suspended</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US sprinter Michelle Collins is suspended for eight years by United States Anti-Doping Agency after arbitrator determines she is guilty of doping despite lack of failed drug test; Collins was accused and suspended on basis of evidence gathered during Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative investigation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Anti-Doping Agency received an important validation yesterday in its attempt to punish athletes who were suspected of doping in the Balco steroids scandal but who had not failed a drug test.</p>
        <p>The sprinter Michelle Collins, 33, the 2003 world indoor champion at 200 meters, received an eight-year suspension yesterday after an arbitration panel declared that she was guilty beyond a reasonable doubt of using banned performance-enhancing substances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Anti-Doping Agency received an important validation when Michelle Collins, 33, received an eight-year suspension on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Anti-Doping Agency received an important validation yesterday in its attempt to punish athletes who were suspected of doping in the Balco steroids scandal but who had not failed a drug test.</p>
        <p>The sprinter Michelle Collins, 33, the 2003 world indoor champion at 200 meters, received an eight-year suspension yesterday after an arbitration panel declared that she was guilty beyond a reasonable doubt of using banned performance-enhancing substances.</p>
        <p>Collins never failed a drug test during her career. Rather, she was punished on the basis of what is called a nonanalytical positive. In Collins's case, the evidence against her was built on materials seized by federal authorities in a raid in Sept. 2003 of the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative. The evidence included e-mail messages between Collins and Victor Conte Jr., the Balco founder, in which Collins admitted using prohibited substances.</p>
        <p>The evidence also included the results of her blood and urine tests, taken in and out of competition by labs accredited by the International Olympic Committee and compared with test results apparently used by Balco-affiliated labs to monitor Collins's hormonal levels and the presence of illicit drugs.</p>
        <p>She became the 13th athlete punished in the Balco case, and the first who challenged evidence that did not include a positive drug test. The other 12 athletes failed drug tests, admitted to doping or retired without contesting charges against them.</p>
        <p>The ruling could have an impact on the case of the former Olympic champion Marion Jones. She has repeatedly denied using banned substances and faces no formal charges. But the evidence in her case is similar to the evidence in Collins's case, including blood and urine tests from Balco-affiliated labs and a calendar with coded letters that could be initials for illicit drugs. Jones's lawyers have said this evidence does not refer to her.</p>
        <p>Conte, who has been charged with distributing steroids and laundering money, said on the ABC program ''20/20'' last Friday that he had devised a doping program for Jones and had watched as she injected human growth hormone into her leg.</p>
        <p>The International Olympic Committee has begun investigating Conte's charge that Jones used banned performance-enhancing drugs in preparation for the 2000 Olympics in Sydney, Australia, where she won five medals.</p>
        <p>''For the last year and a half, U.S.A.D.A. has been committed to uncovering the truth regarding athletes and others who participated in the Balco drug conspiracy,'' Terry Madden, the chief executive of the anti-doping agency, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The decision involving Collins, which was made yesterday by a three-member panel of the American Arbitration Association, ''confirms that those who violate the rules will be sanctioned,'' Madden said.</p>
        <p>Collins could appeal to the Swiss-based international Court of Arbitration for Sport. Otherwise, an eight-year suspension is sure to end her career. Her lawyer, Brian Getz, said in a statement that Collins was disappointed and considering her options.</p>
        <p>The anti-doping agency had sought to use the standard of ''comfortable satisfaction'' in determining whether Collins had used banned substances. But the arbitration panel held the agency to the higher standard of ''beyond a reasonable doubt.''</p>
        <p>Even so, Collins was determined to have used THG, a designer steroid at the center of the Balco scandal; a steroid-based cream that served as a masking agent; and the endurance drug erythropoietin, or EPO, which is used by sprinters to train harder and recover more quickly from workouts.</p>
        <p>Among those testifying against Collins was the sprinter Kelli White, a former world champion who has admitted using similar substances and has agreed to assist the authorities. White was suspended from competition for two years.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
