<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tokyo Not Pleased by U.S. Proposals</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="614231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">QUOTAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALANCE OF PAYMENTS AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC1630F93AA35755C0A965958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tokyo Not Pleased by U.S. Proposals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japanese officials said today that they would reject proposals made by the United States regarding trade relations because the proposals included numerical targets for reduction of Japan's trade surplus and for increasing imports of specific products.</p>
        <p>American officials, at a briefing in Washington on Monday, said that although the proposal would set numerical benchmarks, there would be no automatic retaliation against Japan if the targets were not met. But if that was meant as a concession to Japan, it did not seem to have registered here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japanese officials said today that they would reject proposals made by the United States regarding trade relations because the proposals included numerical targets for reduction of Japan's trade surplus and for increasing imports of specific products.</p>
        <p>American officials, at a briefing in Washington on Monday, said that although the proposal would set numerical benchmarks, there would be no automatic retaliation against Japan if the targets were not met. But if that was meant as a concession to Japan, it did not seem to have registered here.</p>
        <p>"I think it is especially important that we make clear that the Japanese Government cannot accept this point," Foreign Minister Kabun Muto said at a news briefing today, reiterating Japan's oft-stated position that setting numerical targets would lead to "managed trade." No Promises Made</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Kiichi Miyazawa said it would be "unrealistic" for Japan to promise to reduce its trade surplus by a specific amount by a specific date, as called for in the American proposal. "Because it is a free economy, no one can control exports or imports," he said.</p>
        <p>Japanese bureaucrats were poring over the proposal they received this morning from the United States. They said the proposal consisted of a one-page outline devoid of many important details.</p>
        <p>A meeting of American and Japanese officials is scheduled for Friday in Washington to begin negotiations on establishing a framework for trade between the world's two largest economies. The goal is to reach a basic agreement before the summit meeting of the Group of Seven industrial nations in Tokyo in early July. Possible Compromises</p>
        <p>Whether Japan will relax its opposition once negotiations begin, as has happened on occasion in the past, remains to be seen. Some experts have said there may be room for Japan and the United States to agree on some broad policy goals. Japanese officials have, for instance, said that their nation's huge trade surplus was undesirable and should be reduced.</p>
        <p>The American proposal calls for Japan's current account surplus to be reduced to 1 to 2 percent of Japan's economic output in three years; it is now about 3 percent of output. It also calls for an increase in Japan's imports of manufactured goods by about a third. Benchmarks are also expected to be set for imports of specific products like autos.</p>
        <p>Tatsuya Terazawa, deputy director of the Americas division of the Ministry of International Trade and Industry, said Japan had not yet received any explanations from Washington about how the United States would enforce the numerical targets. Senior Clinton Administration officials said the proposals did not include automatic retaliation if the targets were not met. Because of a lack of information on this aspect, Mr. Terazawa said the ministry could not comment.</p>
        <p>Other officials said that it would be difficult to agree to any targets, even if they were nonbinding. Once a numerical target is mentioned, they said, it tends to take on a life of its own and becomes a source of friction.</p>
        <p>The semiconductor agreement between Japan and the United States set an expectation that foreign companies would achieve 20 percent of Japan's computer chip market, but specifically said the 20 percent was not a guarantee.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Japanese officials have repeatedly complained, the United States treated the number as a commitment by Japan and was considering imposing sanctions on Japan until the 20 percent goal was unexpectedly met late last year. Friction Over Autos</p>
        <p>Japanese automobile manufacturers agreed during President George Bush's trip here in 1992 to try to buy $19 billion worth of American auto parts by the fiscal year that ends in March 1995. Japanese officials have recently complained that the United States is regarding what had been a voluntary plan by the private sector as a Government-backed pledge.</p>
        <p>Others here say that it would be foolish for Japan to agree to targets that it cannot control. The trade surplus, for instance, is a result of actions by private companies and by other nations, not just Japan.</p>
        <p>"We are not in control of all of the variables," said one Foreign Ministry official. He said that the American trade proposal included a pledge that the United States would work to reduce the Federal budget deficit, but that the American Government did not set a specific target for itself.</p>
        <p>"There's an asymmetry already there," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
