<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>XM Radio Fans Can Record It If They Hear It</title>
    <meta content="25pogue" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/25/technology/25pogue.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060526T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1764259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="David Pogue"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/David Pogue</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DB113EF936A15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>XM Radio Fans Can Record It If They Hear It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">XM Radio Fans Can Record It if They Hear It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID POGUE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO be filed under Best Ideas of the Year: Imagine a tiny music player, smaller than an iPod, that's also an XM satellite radio receiver. When you hear a song you like -- even if it's halfway over -- one press of a button records it from the beginning.</p>
        <p>Meet the Samsung Helix (and its twin, the Pioneer Inno): a tiny, well-designed $400 radio that not only lets you enjoy satellite radio in the car, at home or when you're jogging, but also plays back your own MP3 files and up to 750 songs that you've recorded from the satellites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To be filed under "Best Ideas of the Year": the Samsung Helix and its twin, the Pioneer Inno, tiny music players that are also XM satellite radio receivers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO be filed under Best Ideas of the Year: Imagine a tiny music player, smaller than an iPod, that's also an XM satellite radio receiver. When you hear a song you like -- even if it's halfway over -- one press of a button records it from the beginning.</p>
        <p>Meet the Samsung Helix (and its twin, the Pioneer Inno): a tiny, well-designed $400 radio that not only lets you enjoy satellite radio in the car, at home or when you're jogging, but also plays back your own MP3 files and up to 750 songs that you've recorded from the satellites.</p>
        <p>Satellite radio now sends about 10 million music lovers into rapturous orbit every day. For $13 a month, you get about 70 nonstop music stations with no ads. The hosts are under no pressure to play all the hits, all the time; they can delve deeply into the catalog of deserving tracks in each channel's category, from Bluegrass to Broadway to Big Band. (Dozens of talk channels -- with some ads -- plus sports coverage and, on XM, dedicated traffic and weather stations round out the dial.)</p>
        <p>These rich offerings lead you to discover new favorite bands, genres and songs that you'd otherwise miss. The significance of the Helix is that, for the first time, it lets you immortalize those discoveries by pressing Record.</p>
        <p>Now, not everybody is happy about this feature of the Helix and its Pioneer sibling. XM, which was largely responsible for the design of both players, has been sued by the increasingly busy lawyers of the Recording Industry Association of America. They're calling the design of these players ''a tool for copyright infringement.''</p>
        <p>Truth is, on the pure silliness scale, the association's case ranks right up there with Monty Python. You've already paid to listen to these XM songs; all the Helix adds is the ability to time-shift and replay them, just as people have done with audiocassettes for decades. Once you record a song to the Helix's memory, that's where it stays. You can't burn it to a CD or transfer it to a computer; you can't move, copy or distribute it in any way.</p>
        <p>The clever part is that this musical lockdown doesn't affect you much. After all, in most cases, isn't the primary benefit of song portability to move your collection to a portable player? Dudes -- these songs are already on your portable player.</p>
        <p>If you do want to burn an XM song to a CD, you'll have to buy it online. That's what the Helix's Bookmark function is all about. When you hear a good song, you bookmark it on the player. Later, you can connect it to a Windows PC, fire up the Napster online music store, and buy the bookmarked songs for $1 each. Navigating Napster's service plans and software options is only slightly more fun than filling out a 1040 form, but the dedicated music aficionado will muddle through.</p>
        <p>THE Helix itself is an extremely slim, compact device (3.7 by 2.2 by 0.6 inches) with a 1.7-inch color screen. The entire front panel is clickable in four directions. You use the up/down buttons, for example, to scroll through lists of music, although without the variable-speed efficiency of the iPod's scroll dial.</p>
        <p>The center button, bearing the XM logo, opens the menus. It's also the button that you can hold down to record the current song.</p>
        <p>Admiring onlookers may comment that the Helix is like a TiVo for satellite radio -- and in many regards, they're right. Thanks to a memory buffer (10 minutes long, in the Helix's case), both gadgets can record a song/TV episode from the beginning, even if you hit Record partway through. That's huge.</p>
        <p>But also as on the TiVo, changing channels resets the buffer. If a song is halfway over when you tune into its channel, the part you missed is gone forever.</p>
        <p>The Helix also lets you program unattended recordings by time and channel, although that works only when it's on AC power. The player also offers a TiVo-like ''wish list'' feature: you plug in the name of a band or a song, and if that band or song ever comes on while you're listening to a different channel, the radio automatically tunes in and records it.</p>
        <p>In one critical way, though, the Helix is not like a TiVo: you can't pause a live broadcast. The Pause button does pause playback of recorded music. But when you're listening live, it only mutes or unmutes the sound. So much for putting Opie &amp; Anthony on hold while you take a phone call.</p>
        <p>The one gigabyte of memory can hold up to 25 hours of recorded radio, plus about eight hours of MP3 files -- songs copied from your CD collection, for example, or bought from any online music store except iTunes. The player arrives with its memory divided, 50-50, between XM recordings and your own files. If you're willing to wipe out the player's entire memory, you can also choose to dedicate its full memory to XM recordings.</p>
        <p>The Helix's docking cradle fulfills four functions. First, it's the sole means of recharging the Helix's battery. Second, it connects the Helix to your stereo so you can listen at home. Third, it contains the U.S.B. jack that, when connected to a Windows PC, lets you load the player with your own MP3 files. And finally, it accommodates the Helix's indoor-outdoor antenna, whose very long cord is designed to reach, for example, a window.</p>
        <p>The player fits into this cradle sideways. At that moment, the screen -- along with the assignments of the four directional buttons -- rotates by 90 degrees, which is a pointless but cool-looking effect.</p>
        <p>(If you want to use the Helix in your car, also budget $70 more for the mounting/charging/magnetic rooftop antenna kit.)</p>
        <p>Now, before you get all fired up, remember that any satellite receiver requires a clear view of the sky; unless you snake the external antenna over to a window, listening to live radio indoors or on the subway is essentially out of the question. (Those are excellent times to play back some of your recordings.) The Helix's stubby little antenna, however, is an especially dainty flower when it comes to sensitivity. Even covering it with your hand, slipping the device into your pocket, or facing the wrong way can be enough to introduce hissy static into the signal.</p>
        <p>The first portable satellite receiver, the Delphi MyFi, offered an external antenna that you could clip on your clothing. It made you look like a geek, but at least you could keep the radio in your pocket while jogging. Samsung offers a slightly better idea: a pair of $50 Belkin headphones whose external antenna is hidden in the headband.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the Helix's battery isn't great; it lasts 15 hours if you're just playing back songs or recordings, but only 5.5 hours if you're listening to live XM broadcasts. At least it's removable; if you're preparing for a three-day safari trek, buy a spare or two for $30 each.</p>
        <p>Speaking of hours: XM requires that the Helix spend eight hours of every month actually receiving XM broadcasts. That requirement is designed to prove that you're still a current subscriber, but it's a little creepy. (Similarly, all of your recordings disappear when you are no longer an XM subscriber.)</p>
        <p>Now, if $400 seems steep, there are less expensive alternatives. Samsung also offers the Nexus ($270 for the one-gigabyte model), which is just like the Helix except that it has a black-and-white screen and doesn't receive XM broadcasts itself. Instead, a receiver is built into the charging dock. The Nexus, in other words, is designed to record stuff at home that you'll listen to later. (In that regard, it's a lot like the Sirius S50, a $300 alternative for people who prefer Sirius's satellite radio to XM's.)</p>
        <p>Some of the Helix's drawbacks are inescapable facts of portable-receiver life: you can't have a fat battery in a thin device, and you can't receive satellite radio broadcasts unless the antenna can see the sky.</p>
        <p>What is in XM-Samsung's control, however, has been done expertly and beautifully. The menu system is easy to figure out, the features are complete and friendly, and the instruction booklet ought to get the Pulitzer Prize for user manuals. The recording industry's lawyers may not like the Samsung Helix, but the odds are very good that you will.</p>
        <p>David Pogue E-mail: Pogue@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 26, 2006, Friday  The David Pogue column in Business Day yesterday, about the Samsung Helix, a radio for XM satellite broadcasts that can also record, described a ''wish list'' feature incorrectly. While users can be alerted to a designated band or song playing on another channel, the radio will not automatically tune to that channel to record it; the user must do that manually. The column also incorrectly attributed a quotation about legal objections to lawyers for the Recording Industry Association of America, which is suing XM. They have not said the player is ''a tool for copyright infringement.'' That was the columnist's assessment of the recording industry's position.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 26, 2006, Friday</p>
        <p>The David Pogue column in Business Day yesterday, about the Samsung Helix, a radio for XM satellite broadcasts that can also record, described a ''wish list'' feature incorrectly. While users can be alerted to a designated band or song playing on another channel, the radio will not automatically tune to that channel to record it; the user must do that manually. The column also incorrectly attributed a quotation about legal objections to lawyers for the Recording Industry Association of America, which is suing XM. They have not said the player is ''a tool for copyright infringement.'' That was the columnist's assessment of the recording industry's position.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Pogue@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
