<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding an Extra Dimension, Color, to World War II</title>
    <meta content="12GARN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/12/arts/television/12GARN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garner, Dwight</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Perilous Fight, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World War II</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fussell, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DD1F3BF931A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding an Extra Dimension, Color, to World War II</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Adding an Extra Dimension, Color, to World War II</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DWIGHT GARNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garner, Dwight</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dwight Garner reviews new PBS documentary The Perilous Fight: America's World War II in Color (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the late 1980's, a decade before the Greatest Generation hysteria fully kicked into gear, the historian Paul Fussell, among others, was already issuing bitter complaints about how World War II ''has been sanitized and romanticized almost beyond recognition.'' Channel surfers who arrive late to the new PBS documentary ''The Perilious Fight: America's World War II in Color'' may initially feel that they've stumbled on the ultimate insult to the actualities of that war: has some blundering archivist actually thought to ''colorize'' hundreds of hours of battle scenes and other period film shots?</p>
        <p>Those channel surfers should, at least temporarily, hold their fire. Our collective memories of World War II may exist almost entirely in black and white, but as this documentary makes plain, the war was the first to be recorded extensively on color film; a good deal of that film has only recently been recovered. As American moviegoers were thrilling to the ripe color dreamscapes in ''The Wizard of Oz'' (1939), this young technology was about to be deployed on battle fronts across the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PBS documentary presents the most comprehensive collection to date of color film related to America's involvement in World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the late 1980's, a decade before the Greatest Generation hysteria fully kicked into gear, the historian Paul Fussell, among others, was already issuing bitter complaints about how World War II ''has been sanitized and romanticized almost beyond recognition.'' Channel surfers who arrive late to the new PBS documentary ''The Perilious Fight: America's World War II in Color'' may initially feel that they've stumbled on the ultimate insult to the actualities of that war: has some blundering archivist actually thought to ''colorize'' hundreds of hours of battle scenes and other period film shots?</p>
        <p>Those channel surfers should, at least temporarily, hold their fire. Our collective memories of World War II may exist almost entirely in black and white, but as this documentary makes plain, the war was the first to be recorded extensively on color film; a good deal of that film has only recently been recovered. As American moviegoers were thrilling to the ripe color dreamscapes in ''The Wizard of Oz'' (1939), this young technology was about to be deployed on battle fronts across the world.</p>
        <p>''The Perilous Fight'' is not the best World War II documentary ever made. (Martin Sheen's absurdly terse narration can make you wish he had Aaron Sorkin stenciling in his cue cards, as he does on ''The West Wing.'') It may not even be the best ''color'' documentary produced about the war. But ''The Perilous Fight,'' a four-hour series, which will run in two two-hour installments tonight and next Wednesday, does present the most comprehensive collection to date of color film related to America's involvement in World War II, and many of the scenes are stunning.</p>
        <p>Early in the documentary the primary colors -- notably the reds -- are the ones that hit you the hardest: the red of Nazi banners at the Berlin Olympics in 1936 and at rallies in 1937, the red of Hitler's swastika armbands, ''Jude'' painted in lurid red on the windows of Jewish-owned businesses in Vienna and the red of the congealing blood that trickles from countless bodies. The color may add nothing to our understanding of this war, but there is no denying its emotional immediacy.</p>
        <p>There are more shockingly vivid colors to come, notably the oranges of flame-throwers and of the explosions caused by kamikaze pilots slamming into American aircraft carriers. But as ''The Perilous Fight'' grinds onward, it's the smaller, more subtle moments that stick with you.</p>
        <p>As any devotee of the History Channel is aware, most war documentaries contain more secondary, or B-roll, shots and aftermath-of-battle scenes than actual war scenes; cameramen had as little interest in being shot to ribbons on the front lines as the average G.I. For every shot of tracer fire ripping through the trees at close range, there are usually three of soldiers shaving, playing cards or running through drills.</p>
        <p>That's the case here, too, but much of this documentary is haunting. The color scenes of young men, frequently taken from home movies, underlines the essential reality that they were very young men being sent into battle.</p>
        <p>''The Perilous Fight'' is far from just a homely assortment of B-roll filler, however. Part 1 of the series, ''Infamy'' (1919-42), in addition to scenes of Nazi rallies, includes some of the earliest color motion-picture images ever made, of a victory parade in Paris at the end of World War I. There is also film of the ruin at Pearl Harbor, shot by a unit working for the director John Ford.</p>
        <p>Part 2, ''Battlefronts'' (1942-44), brings wrenching scenes from German propaganda films of starving children in the Warsaw ghetto as well as scenes from America's Japanese internment camps.</p>
        <p>Part 3, ''Wrath'' (D-Day and V-E Day), features film of the seizure, a few days before D-Day, of a German U-boat that carried Enigma code machines. (The captured Germans stand on the decks, bearded and blinking like gerbils thrust into the light.) There are also scenes of bombing raids over Germany and of the liberation of Buchenwald, where German civilians are being forced to walk through the camp to witness its horrors. Part 4, ''Triumph'' (The Pacific, 1943-45), imparts a strong sense of the viciousness of the fighting there.</p>
        <p>Throughout ''The Perilous Fight,'' Mr. Sheen's narration is the glue that links together snippets from letters, journals and reports from war correspondents like Ernie Pyle and Martha Gellhorn. The role of black journalists is also emphasized, driving home that ''The Perilous Fight'' may be among the most politically and socially inclusive full-scale World War II documentaries yet produced. Close and repeated attention is paid not only to the black experience during the war -- there is a color training film of the black Tuskegee airmen -- but also to the experiences of women, Allied Jewish soldiers and the Japanese in America.</p>
        <p>Throughout the program viewers may have to fight a nagging sense that some of the scenes look too good, too vibrant to be true. They may be. In promotional material, the producers take pains to explain that none of the film has been colorized: that is, artificial colors haven't been digitally applied to black-and-white images. The film has, however, been ''color-graded,'' a process that ''restores the colors that were recorded on the film to their original hues.''</p>
        <p>For some viewers the line between colorization and color-grading might seem to be a thin one. Yet with war on the horizon again, viewers may want to fight the urge to fiddle with the contrast knobs on their sets. World War II in black-and-white documentaries can seem impossibly remote and antiquated. In color the terrors of this war seem, appropriately enough, to have been only yesterday.</p>
        <p>THE PERILOUS FIGHT  America's World War II in Color  On most PBS stations tonight  (check local listings)</p>
        <p>Produced and written by Martin Smith, Scott Pearson and Greg Palmer; David Boardman, associate producer; Mr. Smith, series producer; Adrian Wood, archive film producer; David Rabinovitch, Polly Bide and Alastair Waddington, executive producers; Martin Sheen, narrator. Produced by KCTS, Seattle; TWI, London; and Carlton Television, London.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
