<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On My Mind; Fighting A Former War</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="692676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLOMBIA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERU-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLOMBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D8133AF933A25755C0A962958260" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On My Mind; Fighting A Former War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. M. ROSENTHAL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States makes a specific military-technological commitment to two foreign Governments, allies in a struggle of life and death, many lives and deaths.</p>
        <p>A year after it goes into operation, the arrangement starts a legal dispute between sets of U.S. Government lawyers. So the U.S. breaks the commitment, snap, like that, without consulting in advance the countries Washington had talked into the deal. They happen to think it was working well and was exquisitely important.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States makes a specific military-technological commitment to two foreign Governments, allies in a struggle of life and death, many lives and deaths.</p>
        <p>A year after it goes into operation, the arrangement starts a legal dispute between sets of U.S. Government lawyers. So the U.S. breaks the commitment, snap, like that, without consulting in advance the countries Washington had talked into the deal. They happen to think it was working well and was exquisitely important.</p>
        <p>The commitment was to provide Colombia and Peru with information from American ground radar and Awacs intelligence planes to track drug planes as they flew to their bases in those countries.</p>
        <p>The State Department said the help was legal. Lawyers from Defense and some other agencies thought the U.S. could be sued by the families of the traffickers if the Colombians or Peruvians shot down their planes. They won.</p>
        <p>Colombians and Peruvians say they have been betrayed, and a State Department official has just flown down to see them. The South Americans say the radar information was essential not for shooting down planes but far more for discovering traffickers' distribution points and tracking guerrilla bands working as gunslingers for narcotics gangs. And they say that since the U.S. folded the radar screen the drug flights have increased.</p>
        <p>How could this happen without Congress going up in smoke, without President Clinton's advisers warning him away from another breach of word?</p>
        <p>One reason is that our partners were just South Americans. Americans get interested in Latin America when its name is Castro or we land troops. Name three living South American presidents. Two.</p>
        <p>Second, the struggle involved was the drug war, which does not grab government and journalistic trend-setters as much as it used to. It grabs the public all right, under the heading of crime.</p>
        <p>But Washington doesn't seem fired up. Maybe because the President doesn't. Mr. Clinton has approved a decent budget and does from time to time speak of narcotics. But in the whole Government, during a year's worth of poking around, I have not run into as much know-how and drive about drugs as in one meeting with three narcotics fighters from a therapy-and-job program for released prisoners. (Business people who realize how essential both are in the drug war should write to Father Peter Young, Altamont Program, 134 Franklin Street, Albany, N.Y. 12202.)</p>
        <p>Sorry -- the Clinton Administration does not want it called the drug war anymore. That news comes from Dr. Lee Brown, drug policy director. He was supposed to be top general in the struggle. But through no fault of his the new Clinton Administration downgraded the job before he was even appointed, to about captain.</p>
        <p>So, no more war, you hear? Reminds me of the time the Rockefeller government in New York State decided to grapple with the Mafia by banning the word in all statements. Terrific idea -- the Mafia loved it so much that they blocked the truck bays of The New York Times when the paper refused to go along.</p>
        <p>The former general was out of town and the people on his tiny staff would not say what he thought about breaking American commitments to our former partners in the former war.</p>
        <p>So let me tell them -- he will support it. He has echoed the Clinton Administration's decision to cut back on one of three basic strategies in the former war -- enforcement, therapy, interdiction. The Administration does not think interdiction is as important as do South Americans who live with drugs flying over their heads.</p>
        <p>South Americans had already spoken of their fears about the cutback in interception. Still, the Colombians and the Peruvians were startled that the radar tracking program was eliminated, snap, because some lawyers found it dicey, liability-wise -- startled, bitter, furious.</p>
        <p>Maybe, on a trip to South America some day, Mr. Clinton will explain why he permitted his Administration to behave so to nations we said were our partners. For a President who already has troubles about this promise-keeping business, it is a wound inflicted by himself, or the people supposed to guard his word and honor.</p>
        <p>Meantime, just think of how much money the U.S. would have saved if only General Eisenhower had lawyers to warn him of D-Day liability suits from German families.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
