<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Five Are Killed as Van Crashes Into Bus</title>
    <meta content="21CRAS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/nyregion/21CRAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Transit</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Crown Heights</location>
        <org class="online_producer">aid</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Porsche AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Medical Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1D61030F932A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Five Are Killed as Van Crashes Into Bus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minivan traveling at high speed crashes into New York City Transit bus in Crown Heights section of Brooklyn, killing five occupants of minivan; witnesses say van emitted hissing noise, possibly indicating faulty brakes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five people were killed last night when a minivan crashed at high speed into the side of a New York City Transit bus at the corner of Brooklyn Avenue and St. John's Place in Crown Heights, the police said.</p>
        <p>Several bus passengers were taken to nearby hospitals; their conditions could not be determined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five people were killed last night when a minivan crashed at high speed into the side of a New York City Transit bus at the corner of Brooklyn Avenue and St. John's Place in Crown Heights, the police said.</p>
        <p>Several bus passengers were taken to nearby hospitals; their conditions could not be determined.</p>
        <p>Although the police account of the accident remained sketchy late last night, witnesses on the scene of the collision, which occurred at 8:25 p.m. in front of 241 Brooklyn Avenue, said they saw a blue Dodge Caravan traveling south on Brooklyn Avenue at a high speed, and run two stop lights before striking the bus.</p>
        <p>The witnesses said the five people who died, all occupants of the minivan, were adults, although their ages could not be determined. One neighbor who was called to the scene to identify the victims. The neighbor, Nathan Perry, a corrections officer, rsaid the victims were all members of the family of James Stewart, who Mr. Perry said was in his 60's or early 70's and lived at 1247 President Street, about five blocks from the accident scene.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry, who lives near the Stewart home on President Street, said the other victims included two of Mr. Stewart's children, Lorraine and Melvin, and Lorraine's son, Tyrone, a college student in his 20's.  Mr. Perry said he was unable to identify the fifth victim.</p>
        <p>According to two other witnesses, the van emitted hissing sounds before the collision that may have indicated it had faulty brakes. The witnesses said the bus, which had a green light when it entered the intersection after making a routine passenger stop, was struck so hard on the rear of its passenger side that the van was left a crumpled wreck.</p>
        <p>''At the speed they were going, it had to be a brake problem,'' said Orwin John, 40, of Crown Heights, who said he had been startled to see the  Caravan hurtling down Brooklyn Avenue before it hit the bus. He used his cell phone to call the police, and said he tried to aid the victims in the van.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry said he was shocked that Mr. Stewart and his family would be traveling at an unsafe speed.</p>
        <p>A New York City Transit official who was at the accident scene last night, and who declined to be identified by name, said the actions of the bus driver would be investigated, but that there was no evidence that he had acted improperly.</p>
        <p>Another witness, Ambar Pacheco, 19, who lives on Brooklyn Avenue, said six passengers from the bus appeared to have been injured, two of them slightly. Of the others, she said tweo were carried to ambulances in stretchers with their necks in braces, and two limped.</p>
        <p>The Crown Heights collision occurred less than two hours after a fatal accident on Ocean Parkway at Avenue X. The police said a 15-year-old girl was killed when a Porsche jumped the curb, striking four pedestrians.</p>
        <p>The other three pedestrians, including a 15-year-old boy who was riding a scooter and two female members of the girl's family, ages 10 and 36, were taken to nearby hospitals and listed in stable condition last night.</p>
        <p>A Coney Island Hospital spokeswoman said the 36-year-old victim was treated for multiple fractures and transferred to Lutheran Medical Center. She said the 10-year-old remained in critical condition with head injuries.</p>
        <p>The driver of the Porsche and a passenger sustained minor injuries and were taken to Lutheran Medical Center, the police said.</p>
        <p>The accident occurred at 6:29 p.m. when, according to the authorities, the Porsche went out of control after making a sharp turn to avoid hitting another vehicle in the intersection.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
