<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Death Penalty Lawyers' Duty Is Taken Up by Supreme Court</title>
    <meta content="Y25COU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/25/politics/25COUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1475234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiggins, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1DC1230F936A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Death Penalty Lawyers' Duty Is Taken Up by Supreme Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Death Penalty Lawyers' Duty Is Taken Up by Supreme Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court hears arguments in case that could define constitutional duty of defense lawyers to search background of client facing death penalty in order to find evidence that may persuade jury to spare client's life; case is appeal on behalf of Maryland man, Kevin Wiggins, whose inexperienced lawyers did not reconstruct and present to jury details of serious abuse by his mother in early childhood and of both physical and sexual abuse while he was in care of foster families (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court heard arguments today in a case that could define the constitutional duty of defense lawyers to search the background of a client facing the death penalty in order to find evidence that may persuade a jury to spare the client's life.</p>
        <p>The case is an appeal on behalf of a Maryland man whose inexperienced lawyers did not reconstruct and present to the jury details of serious abuse by his mother in early childhood and of both physical and sexual abuse while he was in the care of foster families. Evidence of this kind is typically presented to juries in death penalty cases under Supreme Court precedents that permit the introduction of any potentially mitigating evidence at the trial's sentencing phase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court heard arguments in a case that could define the constitutional duty of defense lawyers to search the background of a client facing the death penalty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court heard arguments today in a case that could define the constitutional duty of defense lawyers to search the background of a client facing the death penalty in order to find evidence that may persuade a jury to spare the client's life.</p>
        <p>The case is an appeal on behalf of a Maryland man whose inexperienced lawyers did not reconstruct and present to the jury details of serious abuse by his mother in early childhood and of both physical and sexual abuse while he was in the care of foster families. Evidence of this kind is typically presented to juries in death penalty cases under Supreme Court precedents that permit the introduction of any potentially mitigating evidence at the trial's sentencing phase.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Kevin Wiggins, was convicted and sentenced to death in the murder of an elderly woman for whom he had performed chores.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Wiggins was found with the victim's car and credit cards, the evidence linking him to the murder was circumstantial. He waived the right to a jury trial, requesting a trial by a judge, who found him guilty. At the sentencing phase, which was before a jury, the public defenders who represented him concentrated on dissuading the jurors of his responsibility for the crime rather than trying to persuade them that his life story merited leniency.</p>
        <p>After the Maryland courts upheld the death sentence, the Federal District Court in Baltimore overturned it, granting a writ of habeas corpus on the ground that the lawyers' performance had fallen below the effective representation guaranteed by the Sixth Amendment.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, in Richmond, Va., overturned that decision. The appeals court held that the representation had not been below minimum standards because the lawyers had been aware at least to some degree of the facts of their client's childhood but had made a strategic, even if questionable, choice to steer the defense in a different direction.</p>
        <p>The case, Wiggins v. Smith, No. 02-311, has attracted wide attention because the standards for effective representation are surprisingly undeveloped. That has in turn caused considerable confusion about the rules for reviewing such cases under the tightened standards for habeas corpus that Congress imposed in a 1996 law, the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act.</p>
        <p>As the Supreme Court has interpreted that law, federal courts may not grant relief on a state prisoner's behalf unless the state courts have applied federal law in an objectively unreasonable way; with federal law unclear, it is unclear whether a state court's interpretation was reasonable.</p>
        <p>Arguing for Mr. Wiggins, Donald B. Verrilli Jr. told the justices today that it was ''completely clear that this was neglect,'' adding that the defense lawyers ''just dropped the ball'' in not offering ''the powerful mitigating case that could have been made to save this man's life.'' The deference owed to state court judgments should not amount to ''abdication,'' Mr. Verrilli said.</p>
        <p>Gary E. Bair, Maryland's solicitor general, said the lawyers had made a ''reasonable tactical decision'' not to present evidence that the jury could have interpreted as having made Mr. Wiggins more antisocial and prone to violence.</p>
        <p>The American Bar Association and the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers were among the groups filing briefs on behalf of Mr. Wiggins. The bar association said it was essential for death penalty defense lawyers to ''develop the individualized research necessary to humanize the client.''</p>
        <p>Former Attorney General Janet Reno filed a brief along with nine other current and former prosecutors, some of whom support the death penalty while others oppose it. The credibility of the criminal justice system is at stake in cases like this one, they said, adding, ''To the extent that the Fourth Circuit's decision suggests that inadequate performance in a death penalty case can be excused, we are concerned that it does not redound to the credit of the system.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department under Ms. Reno's successor, Attorney General John Ashcroft, entered the case on Maryland's side, calling the representation that Mr. Wiggins received ''eminently reasonable.'' Dan Himmelfarb, an assistant solicitor general, told the justices today that ''the Sixth Amendment imposed no obligation to present evidence or conduct a more extensive investigation'' beyond what Mr. Wiggins received.</p>
        <p>The Criminal Justice Legal Foundation, a victims' rights group based in California, also filed a brief on the state's behalf.</p>
        <p>''Bogus claims of ineffective assistance are now pandemic in capital litigation,'' the group said, urging the justices to curb that trend and to discount the arguments of the American Bar Association, which it called ''just one more interest group among many.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
