<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Salmon Are Thrown Away As Alaska Deals With Glut</title>
    <meta content="14SALM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="883381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salmon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish Farming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D61F3EF937A25753C1A960958260" item-length="1461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Salmon Are Thrown Away As Alaska Deals With Glut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>ANCHORAGE, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alaska is grappling with salmon so bounteous that millions of fish are being thrown away; experts say dumping amounts to one of biggest single incidents of wasting valuable fish species in modern times; glut was caused in part by huge surge of hatchery-bred fish that occurred when wild fish runs were also reaching a peak; buyers say prices are depressed because of enormous growth in farm-raised salmon in other countries; milions of dollars in below-market state loans were used to build hatcheries for fish that nobody now wants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a time when coastal communities in most of the United States are left with the spectral remains of once-abundant fish runs, Alaska this fall is grappling with the opposite problem: salmon so bounteous that millions of fish are being thrown away.</p>
        <p>Like a parable of nature primed beyond its limits, Alaska's attempt to maximize its salmon output has worked so well that it has produced a crisis. Fishermen complain about record low prices for their catch. Processors say the market has fallen. And food banks bemoan a missed opportunity to feed the hungry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a time when coastal communities in most of the United States are left with the spectral remains of once-abundant fish runs, Alaska this fall is grappling with the opposite problem: salmon so bounteous that millions of fish are being thrown away.</p>
        <p>Like a parable of nature primed beyond its limits, Alaska's attempt to maximize its salmon output has worked so well that it has produced a crisis. Fishermen complain about record low prices for their catch. Processors say the market has fallen. And food banks bemoan a missed opportunity to feed the hungry.</p>
        <p>''We have been more than successful, and now we're paying for it,'' said Carl Rosier, the former state Fish and Game Commissioner.</p>
        <p>About 2.5 million pink and chum salmon, reaching the end of their life cycles, have been scooped up near shore, ground up and then dumped at sea in the last three months.</p>
        <p>Experts say the dumping amounts to one of the biggest single incidents of wasting a valuable fish species in modern times.</p>
        <p>''It's not something we're proud of, or something we want to repeat,'' said Geron Bruce, a special assistant to the Fish and Game Commissioner. ''There were no buyers for the fish, and the food banks could not figure out a way to get them.''</p>
        <p>The glut was caused in part by a huge surge of hatchery-bred fish that occurred when the wild fish runs were also reaching a peak.</p>
        <p>Buyers say prices are depressed because of the enormous growth in farm-raised salmon from countries like Norway, Chile and Japan. But, beyond the swings of the global fish market, Alaska's disposal of its surfeit of salmon has left many biologists scratching their heads over what the state has created. Millions in below-market state loans were used to build hatcheries for fish that nobody seems to want.</p>
        <p>The waste of a valuable source of fresh protein has spurred plans to insure that it never happens again. One Alaska charity, One Heart Ministries in Anchorage, says it will use $3 million in pledged donations to begin a venture in the fish canning business. The organization plans to take all the available surplus next year, can it and distribute it to food banks across the United States.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be there next year for all the fish that they might have to dump,'' said Patrick Bradley, a longtime fisherman who is the manager of the fleet the ministry will use to collect the fish.</p>
        <p>Typically, the fish are caught using large nets placed near the mouths of rivers where the fish return to spawn.</p>
        <p>Alaskan fishermen caught about 186 million salmon a year in the five years that ended in 1995. By comparison, in the Pacific Northwest and Northern California, where more than $3 billion has been spent trying to restore vanquished Pacific salmon runs, a good year's commercial catch might total five million fish.</p>
        <p>''To think that we are throwing away this many fish at a time when food banks are full of people who need help and the lower 48 is suffering with lost fish runs is just mind-boggling,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''I don't think the public is going to put up with this anymore, either.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Tony Knowles tried to interest a number of charities and food banks in taking the excess fish this year. But he was told that it would be logistically difficult and too costly to catch, freeze, process and ship fish from distant Alaskan coastal villages to the rest of the country, according to Bob King, a spokesman for the Governor.</p>
        <p>Among the five species of Pacific salmon, chinook and coho are still fetching good prices, though they are down considerably from past years. The final spawning spurt of coho, also known as silver, is just occurring in Alaskan streams, during a week when most of the state is getting its first taste of winter snow. It is the last fish run of a season that begins in the spring with reds, or sockeye salmon.</p>
        <p>There is almost no market for the smaller species, like pink and chum, Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>''The bottom just fell out,'' he said. ''There were literally millions of these fish milling around hatcheries. We let everyone who wanted a salmon get one for free. But at one point, these fish would have caused a health hazard if we just let them rot on beaches near people's homes.''</p>
        <p>The Governor has called a major salmon conference for next month. All this week, fishermen, processors, state officials and hatchery operators have been meeting in sometimes angry sessions to figure out what went wrong and how to bring financial stability to the nation's biggest commercial salmon fishery.</p>
        <p>Many fishermen attribute the problem to the hatcheries, which produce fish from eggs and then harvest them two or three years after the young fish are released at sea. The hatcheries are usually near the shore at the mouths of rivers. The hatcheries were built over the last 20 years with low-cost state loans because of a fear that Alaska's natural wealth from the sea was dwindling. But then the number of fish born in the wild reached a record level, at the same time the millions of hatchery fish reached a peak.</p>
        <p>''They just went out and created too many fish, squeezing out the wild stock, and it's killing people like me,'' said Gail Stevens, who has been fishing for 25 years on the Nenana River, in the Alaskan interior. ''Ten or 15 years ago, we would get one dollar a pound for salmon. Now, most of my catch goes to dog-mushers for dog food, and we get 10 cents a pound.''</p>
        <p>Prices for the prime coho, sockeye and chinook salmon are also depressed this year, at least for fishermen. At the dock, buyers are paying fishermen $1.41 a pound for chinook and 41 cents a pound for coho.</p>
        <p>But in grocery stores, even in Alaska, those fish go for 5 and sometimes 10 times the price at the dock, leaving many fishermen to wonder why in a time of glut they cannot afford to buy their own product.</p>
        <p>The solution is not to close hatcheries or ask grocery stores and restaurants to change their pricing structures, state officials said, but to develop more markets for different kinds of Alaskan salmon. A number of processors have plans to market salmon loaf, salmon nuggets and salmon hot dogs.</p>
        <p>''That's the future -- adding value to the product and then selling to the world market,'' Mr. Rosier said. ''But it's one of those things where the government has to help.''</p>
        <p>The other end of the extreme, giving away fish, is not popular among Alaskan fishermen or cannery operators. At one time, the state upped the limit that people could take from 4 fish a day to more than 20.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who wanted a fish could literally pick one off the beach in places like Juneau,'' Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>In a world flush with farm salmon, Alaskans consider their wild fish the finest-tasting anywhere. But they have lost markets to farm-raised fish, which can be harvested at any time of the year. Alaskan wild fish have a limited season.</p>
        <p>It is against state law to ''wantonly waste'' fish or game. The hatcheries that dumped the fish this season were given an exemption to the law. Many of the hatcheries stripped the salmon of their roe, which is sold as a delicacy like caviar, before grinding and dumping the fish.</p>
        <p>The dumping angered Michael O'Callaghan, who runs a charity called Earth. In the last five years, he has distributed more than two million pounds of surplus chum salmon to Alaskans. This year, for the first time, he went to the lower 48 states, distributing more than 40,000 pounds in Washington State.</p>
        <p>''We moved 40,000 pounds of fish to hungry people, and it cost us just 3 cents a pound,'' Mr. O'Callaghan said at the salmon conference this week. He told the fishermen, ''Send us a check -- we'll move your fish for 3 cents a pound.''</p>
        <p>At that price, the fishermen said, most of them would soon be out of business, leaving the state with record salmon runs and no market.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
