<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton, in Detailed Interview, Calls His Health 'Very Good'</title>
    <meta content="14HEAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="883359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D81F3EF937A25753C1A960958260" item-length="2564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton, in Detailed Interview, Calls His Health 'Very Good'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Oct. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton gives first interview on his health, saying it is 'very good' and he has controlled his three chronic problems: hoarseness, allergies and weight; says he has never had a serious illness and pledges to tell public if he developed anything serious while in White House; says there is detailed written plan on how to activate 25th Amendment if he is ever disabled and Vice Pres Al Gore needs to assume duties of President; Dr E Connie Mariano, senior White House physician, says she would stake her professional reputation on statement that nothing is being hidden about Clinton's health; Clinton has refused to grant requests since 1992 for interview about his health; he has been under pressure from Bob Dole to give interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first interview about his health, President Clinton said that it was ''very good,'' that he had never had a serious illness and that he had controlled his three most pesky problems: hoarseness, allergies and weight. Sometimes, however, he misses comments in crowded areas because of a mild hearing loss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who is 50 years old, pledged in the interview, on Saturday, to tell the public if he developed any serious illness while in the White House. From the moment he took office, he has had ready a detailed written plan on how to activate the 25th Amendment if he is ever disabled and Vice President Al Gore needs to assume the duties of President. Mr. Clinton said he did not have a living will or other directive to guide his care if he developed an incapacitating illness, and details of the plan under the 25th Amendment are classified for security reasons. Dr. E. Connie Mariano, the senior White House physician, said the plan covered a variety of potentially disabling medical conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first interview about his health, President Clinton said that it was ''very good,'' that he had never had a serious illness and that he had controlled his three most pesky problems: hoarseness, allergies and weight. Sometimes, however, he misses comments in crowded areas because of a mild hearing loss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who is 50 years old, pledged in the interview, on Saturday, to tell the public if he developed any serious illness while in the White House. From the moment he took office, he has had ready a detailed written plan on how to activate the 25th Amendment if he is ever disabled and Vice President Al Gore needs to assume the duties of President. Mr. Clinton said he did not have a living will or other directive to guide his care if he developed an incapacitating illness, and details of the plan under the 25th Amendment are classified for security reasons. Dr. E. Connie Mariano, the senior White House physician, said the plan covered a variety of potentially disabling medical conditions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that he had been open about his health and that he had missed only one day of work, from a 24-hour bout of intestinal flu early in his term. The interview, at which Dr. Mariano was present, lasted about a half-hour aboard Air Force One en route to Denver. Mr. Clinton left from Denver today for New Mexico to continue a campaign swing that will end with the second debate on Wednesday in San Diego.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton ''is fit to re-enlist,'' said Dr. Mariano, a Navy general internist, using a standard military phrase to summarize her belief that there are no medical reasons why Mr. Clinton cannot serve a second term. Dr. Mariano spoke in a lengthy interview after Mr. Clinton's last checkup, on May 24, and in additional interviews this weekend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he had overcome the problem of hoarseness that hampered his 1992 campaign by drinking copious amounts of water, not eating late at night, raising the head of his bed and taking , Prilosec, or omeprazole, and occasional antacids. The aim is to reduce gastric reflux, a common condition in which stomach acid passes up the esophagus and may irritate the vocal cords.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton fights allergies with desensitization shots that he takes every week, a nonsedating antihistamine and decongestant drug, Claritin-D, and an anti-inflammatory steroid nasal spray, called Nasalide. An allergist has adjusted the shots to include substances prevalent in the Washington area that are most apt to trigger allergic reactions.</p>
        <p>''We catch him, usually after a run or a call to him upstairs, and say it is time for your shot,'' Dr. Mariano said. ''Then we sit and watch him to make sure he does not have a reaction to the shot.''</p>
        <p>The city of Washington is notorious  for aggravating allergies, and Mr. Clinton said he expected his to be more severe there than in Arkansas. But Mr. Clinton said: ''We are managing them reasonably well. They seem to be maybe a little worse in the spring, but not as bad in the fall as they were at home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's staff was first asked for permission to interview the President and his doctors about his health during the 1992 campaign, when he was having difficulty with his voice. Other Presidential candidates in that year and prior years, including Ronald Reagan, Michael S. Dukakis, George Bush and Paul E. Tsongas, had agreed to such interviews with this correspondent, a medical doctor.  Through spokesmen, Mr. Clinton refused, citing reasons of privacy.</p>
        <p>But in October 1992, after The New York Times said in an article that he had been one of the least forthcoming of any Presidential nominees in two decades about his health, his staff released some detailed information and allowed interviews with his doctors.</p>
        <p>Until now, Mr. Clinton had continued to refuse all requests for an interview on the subject. The issue of his refusal has come up from time to time, under prodding by news organizations and, most recently, the Dole campaign.</p>
        <p>Asked why he had not responded to repeated requests since 1992 for an interview about his health, Mr. Clinton said he had not been aware of them. ''I don't know; I can't say. I don't remember my staff saying anything about it one way or the other,'' Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>In October 1992, a spokeswoman, Avis LaVelle, said, ''We feel this is a privacy issue and that if he became President, his medical records would be open.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has been under pressure from his Republican challenger, Bob Dole, to give an interview and release his medical records. In July, Mr. Dole and his doctors spoke with this reporter about his health in an interview, and he has released copies of some medical records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has not released any copies of medical records. He said no previous President had made available ''actual copies'' of medical records and asserted that he had provided as much medical information as any predecessor. With this interview, Mr. Clinton appears to have done about as much to discuss his medical history as previous Presidents or Presidential candidates without serious medical problems.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mariano said she would stake her professional reputation on the statement that nothing is being hidden about Mr. Clinton's health. Dr. Mariano said she was well aware that in the past, other doctors in the White House had colluded with Presidents to keep secret their potentially fatal illnesses and other serious conditions. ''We are not going to repeat errors of the past,'' Dr. Mariano said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mariano also said that she planned to hold news conferences after future Presidential annual checkups at which the doctors who performed the examinations would answer questions. In the past, the White House press secretary has issued a brief statement summarizing the exam but has often been unable or unwilling to answer specific medical questions. Occasionally, the President's doctor has given interviews.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton appeared relaxed but serious as he sat in his Oval Office in the sky wearing a blue shirt and red tie. He often folded his arms and leaned forward on the desk as he answered all questions directly. He smiled often, occasionally introduced a note of humor and deferred a few questions to Dr. Mariano.</p>
        <p>He did not appear ruffled when he was asked if he ever took mood-altering drugs or had undergone psychological counseling. He answered no to both questions. The President said his press secretary, Michael D. McCurry, had been correct in saying that Mr. Clinton had never had a sexually transmitted disease.</p>
        <p>At his last physical, Mr. Clinton weighed 216 pounds, down from 226 in 1992. His cholesterol was 191, down from 202 in 1995. His triglycerides rose to 72 from 50; HDL was a stable 36; LDL dropped to 141 from 158; his lipid ratio was a tad high at 5.3. These are within the normal range for a 50-year-old man. A test for prostate cancer was normal, as were additional tests for thyroid, kidney, liver and other organs' function.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton performed very well on an exercise treadmill test. His doctors stopped it into stage 6, a very advanced stage, when he had reached more than 90 percent of his predicted maximum heart rate and his electrocardiogram was normal.</p>
        <p>Because of a history of heart disease on his mother's side, Mr. Clinton said, he had asked his doctors in Arkansas to perform treadmill tests nearly every year. He said he ''just wanted to know what kind of health I was in'' and ''if any problems were developing.'' But questions about Mr. Clinton's health arose in 1992 because such exercise tests are generally not recommended for healthy patients in their 40's unless there is a specific medical reason to do them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said in the interview he was unaware that the health insurance plan proposed by his Administration in 1993 but not enacted by Congress would probably not have covered the costs of such treadmill tests for a person, like himself, lacking risk factors for heart disease.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that in addition to Dr. Mariano, he had consulted two other doctors for medical problems: Dr. James Y. Suen, an ear, nose and throat specialist at the University of Arkansas in Little Rock, for hoarseness, and an allergist, Dr. Talal M. Nsouli, of the Georgetown University Medical Center in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said his doctors had originally attributed the hoarseness  to his allergies but then had gone on to ''discover it was reflux.'' In 1992, and occasionally since then, Mr. Clinton said, he has sought consultants' advice on caring for his voice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also watches what he eats and when. He said he always tried to have exercised before going to bed and avoided going to bed on a full stomach. He drinks as much as 100 ounces of water a day, especially when traveling, which is roughly double the normal consumption. For example, Mr. Clinton said that after awakening on Saturday, he ''drank a 17-ounce bottle of water just to get ready for the trip.''</p>
        <p>Since 1992, he has used a wedge to raise the head of his bed and ''no question, it helps.''</p>
        <p>Although some people avoid putting flowers on his table at receptions, Mr. Clinton said he was much more allergic to Christmas greenery than flowers. ''I have to be careful how much I am around the greenery at the White House, and we put up our Christmas tree late, like just a few days before Christmas'' and keep less greenery in the living quarters than downstairs, Mr. Clinton said. ''But I love it so we put it up, and I manage it the best I can.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is allergic to cat dander. His family cat, Socks, often sleeps outside the President's office but does not stay in the White House living quarters ''because the cat could tear up what's upstairs.'' Socks resides elsewhere in the White House and roams outside. Mr. Clinton said he usually had no allergic reaction if he played with Socks outdoors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said his eyes watered in reaction to smoke-filled rooms, a problem that occurs more often when he travels abroad, where smoking is more common than in the United States. He said his wife, Hillary, had always had a no-smoking policy in their homes, the Governor's Mansion and the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton smoked a pipe as a student at Oxford and in law school and an occasional cigar, but he gave that up because of an allergy to smoke. He never smoked cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Questions have been raised about Mr. Clinton becoming depressed in reaction to adverse events. On the days when he gets gloomy, Mr. Clinton said, he tries to ''get a little more sleep'' or slips out of the office for an hour or so, spending more time with his wife or his daughter, Chelsea, reading for pleasure, exercising or planting flowers. ''But I don't have to be blue to want to do that,'' Mr. Clinton said with a chuckle.</p>
        <p>When he lost the election for Governor of Arkansas in 1980, Mr. Clinton said, ''The way I handled it was by making up my mind to go on with my life.'' He went out the next day and bought a house, one he sold but wished he still owned, and he started looking for a job.</p>
        <p>After the Republicans gained control of Congress in the 1994 election, Mr. Clinton said, he analyzed what happened and how he should respond and focused on his re-election plans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he had never sought care from a psychiatrist, psychologist or counselor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he had first noticed a decline in his hearing in 1979 that apparently is due to damage from hunting and loud music. The high-frequency hearing loss, which is at frequencies of 3 to 8 kilohertz, seems to have progressed, but Mr. Clinton has no problem understanding normal conversations.</p>
        <p>''The only time it ever bothers me is when I'm in a crowd and someone is trying to talk to me, or I'm trying to speak,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''The background noise often seems to drown out the voices.''</p>
        <p>In 1990, Mr. Clinton tested negative for H.I.V., the AIDS virus, as part of an examination for a life insurance policy. He has not been tested again. As President, Mr. Clinton is Commander in Chief of the military, which rejects H.I.V.-positive recruits and requires active-duty personnel to have annual H.I.V. tests. Mr. Clinton said that he was unaware that he had not been tested again and that he was ''not in any kind of at-risk category -- there is nothing I've done that would indicate that I could have become positive'' for the AIDS virus.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mariano said, with Mr. Clinton's permission, she would include an H.I.V. test in future checkups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he had been tested for drugs when running for re-election as Governor of Arkansas in 1986. In preparing for a debate, Mr. Clinton said, he heard ''a rumor that my opponent was going to challenge me to take one, make some big deal of it.'' So Mr. Clinton said he and his campaign manager had been tested.  Mr. Clinton said that he and his manager had then challenged their opponents to do the same but that the opponent's campaign manager had declined to be tested. Dr. Mariano said Mr. Clinton had not had a urine test for drugs since then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton partly clarified a 4-year-old mystery about why Dr. Burton S. Lee 3d was dismissed as the senior White House doctor soon after Mr. Clinton took office. The dismissal occurred shortly after Dr. Lee refused to give Mr. Clinton an allergy shot. Dr. Lee, who was President Bush's personal physician, said he had been invited to stay on until Mr. Clinton chose his own doctor. Dr. Lee said that he had declined to give the allergy shot because the vial had come without sufficient labeling and checking and that he did not know Mr. Clinton's medical history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that he did not know about the allergy shot but that it had nothing to do with Dr. Lee's leaving. ''I just wanted my own doctor,'' Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mariano, who worked with Dr. Lee, said she had been on duty the day of the flap over the allergy shot. She said she had called Dr. Kelsy J. Caplinger, Mr. Clinton's allergist in Little Rock, to learn the contents of the vial. ''I felt good enough to say I trust it, and I administered the shot myself,'' Dr. Mariano said.</p>
        <p>In defending Mr. Clinton's right to privacy about his medical records, George J. Annas, a lawyer and ethicist at Boston University, has urged journalists to curb their curiosity about private medical information about Presidential candidates.</p>
        <p>Asked about such criticism, Mr. Clinton said that he did not regard the interview about his health as an invasion of his privacy and that ''the public has a right to know the condition of the President's health.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
