<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE NAMES</title>
    <meta content="28BOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/28/nyregion/28BOLD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1379385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface Names"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stephanopoulos, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pelosi, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ammon, R Theodore</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Fight, A (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Death to Smoochy (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Boldface Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4D8113BF93BA15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shaking Hands, Busting Groove</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Barron; With Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Clinton and his former aide George Stephanopoulos, who have not spoken for five years, cordially greet one another during encounter in Manhattan restaurant; photo; Clinton attends reception for Sarah Brady's book A Good Fight; Robin Williams, in departure from recent roles, is children's show host who goes bad in movie Death to Smoochy; Daniel Pelosi contends his relationship with slain investment banker R Theodore Ammon was cordial and friendly, denying any role in his death (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaking Hands, Busting Groove</p>
        <p>For the first time in five years -- since one moved to New York and wrote a scorching memoir about working for the other -- GEORGE STEPHANOPOULOS and his former boss, BILL CLINTON, shook hands yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in five years Bill Clinton and George Stephenopoulos shook hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shaking Hands, Busting Groove</p>
        <p>For the first time in five years -- since one moved to New York and wrote a scorching memoir about working for the other -- GEORGE STEPHANOPOULOS and his former boss, BILL CLINTON, shook hands yesterday.</p>
        <p>The encounter was a coincidence. Both had lunch dates in the same restaurant, Michael's, on West 55th Street. Once so close that they could finish each other's sentences, they had not seen each other in person since 1997. In recent years, other former White House aides say, Mr. Clinton and Mr. Stephanopoulos had been known to worry about bumping into each other around New York.</p>
        <p>As word of the handshake circulated yesterday, another former Clinton aide went so far as to say, ''It has the flavor of the return of the prodigal son.''</p>
        <p>Maybe, maybe not. Mr. Stephanopoulos was on the way to the men's room when he stopped at the table where Mr. Clinton was having lunch with ROBIN WILLIAMS; BILLY CRYSTAL; ANN RICHARDS, the former governor of Texas; DIANE SAWYER; and the host, JOE ARMSTRONG, an adviser to ABC News and a former publisher of New York and Rolling Stone. Mr. Clinton did not rise to shake Mr. Stephanopoulos's hand as they exchanged hellos. But a spokeswoman for the former president said later, ''He was glad to see him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has been listening to music by ''PUFF DADDY, or whatever they call him now.'' On Tuesday, Mr. Clinton said that his daughter, CHELSEA, had given him compact disks by nine performers, including SEAN COMBS, the rap impresario who announced last year that he wanted to be known as P. Diddy, not Puff Daddy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said his daughter had told him, ''You may not like these, but you have to try to understand it.''</p>
        <p>Listening did not turn him into a fan. He said he liked Jimi Hendrix, ''but he lost me when he started breaking his guitars.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said all this at a reception for SARAH BRADY'S book, ''A Good Fight.'' Her husband, JAMES BRADY, was RONALD REAGAN'S press secretary and was wounded in 1981 in an assassination attempt. For the reception, at the Jazz Standard Club in the Blue Smoke Restaurant on East 27th Street, the party planners had rented a saxophone, hoping Mr. Clinton would do some jamming. But no. People who attended the reception said the former president apparently did not realize the saxophone was clean and new. They heard him say, ''I can't use somebody else's mouthpiece.''</p>
        <p>When Mork Goes Bad</p>
        <p>When he was not hamming it up as only he can -- doing a veddy British accent for a BBC camera crew and improvising skits as he pranced up and down the red carpet -- ROBIN WILLIAMS talked Tuesday about his part in the new film ''Death to Smoochy.'' He was doing the prancing outside the Ziegfeld Theater before the premiere on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''Death to Smoochy'' is a departure from the roles he played in films like ''Patch Adams'' and ''Bicentennial Man.'' He plays an anti-Mr. Rogers, a children's show host who goes bad. Besides ''Smoochy,'' Mr. Williams goes bad in two other movies that will be coming out soon -- ''Insomnia'' and ''One Hour Photo.''</p>
        <p>Is he discovering his dark side?</p>
        <p>''Your inner evil,'' he said, and before you could say domestic diva he was imitating one: ''Find your inner villain. The anti-MARTHA STEWART. It's a bad thing.' ''</p>
        <p>New Twist in Mystery Killing</p>
        <p>DANIEL PELOSI, the handyman-turned-husband of GENEROSA AMMON, hinted that there is a new twist to the mystery surrounding his wife's previous husband, R. THEODORE AMMON, an investment banker who was found slain in East Hampton, N.Y., in October. In a statement faxed to reporters on Long Island, Mr. Pelosi described a ''two-sided handwritten document'' that had been found in the house where Mr. Ammon was killed.</p>
        <p>''It contains information which shows that it was written just before he died and that his wealth was $300 million more than he previously disclosed,'' Mr. Pelosi said in the statement. He said his lawyers were preparing to turn it over to ''responsible Suffolk County public officials.''</p>
        <p>He also said he had nothing to do with Mr. Ammon's death. ''My personal relationship with Ted was cordial and friendly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With Marian Burros</p>
        <p>Boldface Names</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
