<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Not-So-Dutiful Daughter</title>
    <meta content="23MASONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/23/books/review/23MASONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1537447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mason, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tan, Amy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Opposite of Fate, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Tan, Amy</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Opposite of Fate: A Book of Musings (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6DD1438F930A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Not-So-Dutiful Daughter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Opposite of Fate: A Not-So-Dutiful Daughter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Mason</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mason, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Mason reviews book The Opposite of Fate: A Book of Musings by Amy Tan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE OPPOSITE OF FATE</p>
        <p>A Book of Musings.</p>
        <p>By Amy Tan.</p>
        <p>398 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>G. P. Putnam's Sons. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this collection of autobiographical essays, Amy Tan reflects on a life spent challenging destiny.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE OPPOSITE OF FATE</p>
        <p>A Book of Musings.</p>
        <p>By Amy Tan.</p>
        <p>398 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>G. P. Putnam's Sons. $24.95.</p>
        <p>AMY TAN turned Ouija-board thug at 15, sabotaging its responses in order to advance her own interests. Her mother had begun pleading with the board for advice after Tan's father died: ''Amy treat me so bad. . . . What I should do -- send her Taiwan, school for bad girls?'' The Ouija board clearly had strong feelings on the subject. ''The planchette deftly scooted to the correct answer: No,'' drastically altering the fate of this dexterous daughter.</p>
        <p>The creative rewriting of their destinies is the trademark of many of Tan's characters in ''The Joy Luck Club'' and the three novels that followed. Now, in her first collection of essays, Tan reports on her own very American negotiations with the contract of Chinese fate -- from hammering out a détente with a depressive mother hellbent on raising an obedient daughter to, most recently, bucking the doctors who for years dismissed Tan's distressing neurological symptoms of advanced Lyme disease.</p>
        <p>Many of the essays in ''The Opposite of Fate'' are sharp and invigorating, like ''Mother Tongue,'' Tan's defense of the fierce, primal authority of her mother's ''broken'' English. Some are slight and a bit precious (her paean to singing with a rock band of writers). Others are droll self-snapshots: copping, for example, to a home armed with Chinese ''good luck charms . . . strategically placed mirrors, and heaven forgive me, New Age crystals.'' But it is Tan's excursions into past lives -- her family's and her own -- that make for the most fertile reading.</p>
        <p>In ''The CliffsNotes Version of My Life,'' she recounts a Northern California childhood pinned between two clashing ideologies: the God-will-provide-for-you faith of her Baptist minister father and the dictatorship of fate that ruled her mother. As a child, Tan was trained to appease two kinds of ghosts. Her father's Holy Ghost, she was told, ''sat at our dinner table and ate Chinese food. We laid out chopsticks and a bowl for our unseen guest at every meal.'' Her mother's old-country ghosts chose to stay in hiding. ''Yet they were there,'' Tan writes. ''I could sense them. My mother told me I could.''</p>
        <p>In these essays, most of which have appeared in national magazines, the motherland is less a geographical place than an alternative universe of fraught symbiosis, love and, for years, emotional captivity. It is ''a world,'' Tan writes, ''in which the mother . . . can make the girl see yin when it is yang. The girl sees that her mother, who is her ally, is also her adversary.'' As a result, Tan says, her childhood was shadowed by a ''sense of double jeopardy; realizing that my mother could both help me and hurt me, in the best and worst ways possible.''</p>
        <p>When Tan began to date, her mother offered this hardly reassuring advice: ''Don't ever let boy kiss you. You do, you can't stop. Then you have baby. You put baby in garbage can. Police find you, put you in jail, then you life over, better just kill youself.'' In truth, it was Tan's mother, Daisy, who wanted to kill herself, threatening to do so ''sometimes weekly, sometimes daily, whenever she was displeased with me or my father or my brothers, whenever she felt slighted by her friends, whenever the milk spilled or the rice burned.'' What Tan didn't learn for decades was that horrific memories stalked her mother daily. Daisy Tan's own mother, the young widow of a vice magistrate in China, had been raped by a rich man and forced to become his concubine. The shamed widow killed herself by swallowing a large dose of raw opium as her 9-year-old daughter looked on. Later in her life, when being tested for Alzheimer's disease, Daisy growled: ''Nothing wrong my memory. Depress 'cause can not forget.''</p>
        <p>The cunning willfulness of memory is a powerful refrain in this book. Tan considers how she, like her mother, became frozen in one frame of time, a slave to her own punishing recollections. In ''Scent,'' she relates how one whiff of a gardenia would plunge her into the ''unbearable grief'' of the year in her midteens when the living room was twice filled with funeral sprays after both her father and brother died of brain tumors. Now, she says, she is submerging those black memories into others of ''an earlier time, of happy expectations,'' when the scent of a gardenia meant ''prom nights and first kisses.''</p>
        <p>In describing how we edit and manipulate memory, Tan produces some of her strongest essays. ''Confessions'' recalls a violent standoff with her mother over Tan's first real boyfriend, a mangy deserter from the German Army, that ended with Tan's mother holding a meat cleaver to her daughter's neck. Having repressed the memory for 25 years, Tan suddenly remembers it and, with the older woman failing, nervously brings it up. ''Angry? Slap you?'' her mother laughs. ''No, no, no. You always good girl, never even need to spank, not even one time.'' ''How wonderful to hear her say what was never true,'' Tan remarks, ''yet now would be forever so.''</p>
        <p>Tan's novels swim with memories transfigured by the pulse of her imagination -- the sorcery of writing fiction that she says many academics ignore. Instead, they rope off her books under ''multicultural literature,'' scan them for sociology lessons and -- this really ticks her off -- imbue her with ''ethnic authority.'' ''Contrary to what some . . . assume,'' she snaps back in the riveting essay ''Required Reading and Other Dangerous Subjects,'' ''I am not an expert on China, Chinese culture, mah-jongg . . . racial tension, Tiananmen Square . . . Pacific Rim economics . . . or, I am sorry to say, Chinese cooking.'' The label she most prefers? ''American writer.''</p>
        <p>In Tan's case, ''American writer'' also entails the odd life of a literary celebrity. Some of these essays reveal how she relishes it; others spill out its less comfortable aspects: the Web fanzines that get their facts all wrong; the notes pressed into her hand at book signings by would-be collaborators. One read: ''Father hanged, mother murdered, uncle shot, baby son drowned, wife insane, me, almost died twice, all horrible ways. Want to write about me? Call me. Let's talk.''</p>
        <p>In the end, these essays ask, what does it take to construct and balance a life? For Tan, it requires engaging fate, ''both blind and blessed,'' with aggressive creativity and ducking from time to time into the big tent of fate's ''alternatives'': ''choice, chance, luck, faith, forgiveness, forgetting . . . the balm of love, a sturdy attitude . . . trolling for miracles, a plea to others to throw a lifeline'' -- the whole shebang anchored by stubborn hope.</p>
        <p>Deborah Mason is a writer and critic who lives in New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deborah Mason is a writer and critic who lives in New York.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
