<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When New World Plants Were a Wonder</title>
    <meta content="23CTYCUTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/23/garden/23ctycutt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1537646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Botanical Garden</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2D8123BF930A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When New World Plants Were a Wonder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When New World Plants Were a Marvel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the delights for a gardener in winter is having the time to wander into a great public library and find some quirky exhibition. The one I stumbled on most recently, ''America's Cornucopia: A Collector's View of American Botany and Horticulture,'' is at the LuEsther T. Mertz Library at the New York Botanical Garden, in the Bronx, through Feb. 16.</p>
        <p>Early this month, the exhibition whisked me back to the 1600's, when early colonists and European explorers were venturing into the wilderness, mapping its rivers and coastlines, and sending back seeds and specimens of strange and beautiful things, like poison ivy and Venus flytrap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the delights for a gardener in winter is having the time to wander into a great public library and find some quirky exhibition. The one I stumbled on most recently,</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the delights for a gardener in winter is having the time to wander into a great public library and find some quirky exhibition. The one I stumbled on most recently, ''America's Cornucopia: A Collector's View of American Botany and Horticulture,'' is at the LuEsther T. Mertz Library at the New York Botanical Garden, in the Bronx, through Feb. 16.</p>
        <p>Early this month, the exhibition whisked me back to the 1600's, when early colonists and European explorers were venturing into the wilderness, mapping its rivers and coastlines, and sending back seeds and specimens of strange and beautiful things, like poison ivy and Venus flytrap.</p>
        <p>Europe has no poison ivy or meat-eating plants, so these New World plants were a revelation, said David Andrews, the curator of the exhibition. An avid longtime collector, he drew from his thousands of volumes and ephemera -- items like nursery catalogs and colorful plant cards once carried by itinerant salesmen.</p>
        <p>We stared at a 1635 anonymous engraving of a poison ivy plant. At the time, wealthy Europeans were hooking up with intrepid explorers, who would send them rarities, be it squash seed or a carnivorous plant, to be used as a medium of exchange, a way of gaining access to dukes and kings, Mr. Andrews said. American novelties -- corn, squash, tobacco and beans -- were as valuable as gold.</p>
        <p>Among the treasures on display are a map drawn by the King George III's royal geographer and a diary kept by John Bartram, a Philadelphia Quaker who was hired to explore Florida between 1763 and 1765. The rivers were then so crowded with bellowing alligators that boats could hardly maneuver.</p>
        <p>The documentation of these first forays was published in Europe; Americans were too busy warring with the Indians and otherwise trying to survive to make books, Mr. Andrews said. But in the 1800's, that began to change. The exhibition reveals the evolution not only of American botany and horticulture, but also how the printing industry and the mass production of books democratized knowledge.</p>
        <p>Some of the other things I learned at the library were that the first botanists were doctors searching for cures. Dropsy, or edema, for example, was remedied by foxglove (digitalis), which reduced swelling of the legs and feet. So it was natural for American doctors to study plants in their spare time. Dr. William Darlington drew the plants that grew around his home in West Chester, Pa., publishing a book, ''Florula Cestrica,'' in 1826.</p>
        <p>Around the same time, John Torrey published his ''Catalogue of Plants, Growing Spontaneously Within 30 Miles of the City of New York.'' Mr. Torrey, considered the first professional botanist in America because he was paid to lecture at the College of Physicians and Surgeons, had a student, Asa Gray, who joined him in a lifelong project aimed at identifying and cataloging all the flora of North America. They drew from the findings of the government-sponsored Wilkes Expedition to Antarctica, the South and Central Pacific Ocean, and the Oregon coast between 1838 and 1842.</p>
        <p>Then came the heyday of the apple.</p>
        <p>In 1900, American orchards, centered around Rochester, N.Y., shipped apples all over the world, Mr. Andrews said, adding, ''I believe the amount of money made on apples was more than the profits of all the corporations in New York City.''</p>
        <p>Pomologists tried, mostly in vain, to identifythe varieties based on prints made by dipping apple halves in ink and stamping them on paper, like potato prints.</p>
        <p>Since farmers often forgot the names of the varieties sold by tree peddlers, not to mention the chance seedlings they let grow in the pasture, trying to sort their genealogy was no easy task.</p>
        <p>A catalog from 1834 has the words ''Red Swipe is our French Red Speckled'' scrawled on one page by William Robert Prince, whose father, William, founded the famous Prince Nursery in Flushing, N.Y., in 1737.</p>
        <p>But books like ''The American Fruit Culturist,'' published by John Jacob Thomas in 1846, began to clear up the confusion.</p>
        <p>BY the late 1800's, salesmen were crisscrossing the country with colorful plant cards, including cigar-smoking carrots. Farmers held on to the cards, waiting until spring for delivery of their orders. Mail-order nurseries outdid one another's claims. In 1906 H.W. Buckbee of Rockford, Ill., created a cover girl by topping a Buckbee Extra Early Large New Queen Cabbage with a gold crown and cross.</p>
        <p>There were little books for children, who were encouraged to learn the Latin names of flowers and insects. And as mass production drove down their cost, how-to books appeared on almost every aspect of gardening, from pruning to beekeeping.</p>
        <p>The sight of these texts made me long to reach into the glass cabinets and turn the pages -- to read firsthand, for example, what Bartram wrote when he was navigating a river thick with bellowing alligators.</p>
        <p>Eventually, I will able to do just that. Mr. Andrews has given his vast collection to the Botanical Garden library. Some of his books are already in the rare book room. When the exhibition ends in February, others will move there, too. They can't be checked out and the pages can't be copied, but you can sit and read all day, if you like.</p>
        <p>You can sign onto www.nybg.org/events/floshow.html for information on the exhibition.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
