<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Page Two; One Book, Two Very Different Covers</title>
    <meta content="23BIGP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031130T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1537658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krugman, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Great Unraveling, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DC133BF930A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="439" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Page Two; One Book, Two Very Different Covers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British publisher of New York Times columnist Paul Krugman's book The Great Unraveling uses cover with caricatures of Pres Bush and Vice Pres Dick Cheney; American publisher opts for staid cover; Republican National Committee holds British cover shows Krugman's attacks on administration are 'hate speech'; Times says it has no ties to British publisher and was not shown cover; Krugman calls cover possibly 'undignified'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAUL KRUGMAN, the liberal economist and columnist for The New York Times Op-Ed Page, has recently urged his fellow liberals to be less civil toward their conservative foes. The British publisher of his latest book, ''The Great Unraveling,'' however, may have taken Mr. Krugman's advice further than he intended.</p>
        <p>Unlike the relatively staid cover of the American edition published by W. W. Norton, the British book jacket bears caricatures of President Bush as Frankenstein-like and Vice President Dick Cheney with a Hitler mustache. A dark scrawl on the vice president's forehead reads, ''Got Oil?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAUL KRUGMAN, the liberal economist and columnist for The New York Times Op-Ed Page, has recently urged his fellow liberals to be less civil toward their conservative foes. The British publisher of his latest book, ''The Great Unraveling,'' however, may have taken Mr. Krugman's advice further than he intended.</p>
        <p>Unlike the relatively staid cover of the American edition published by W. W. Norton, the British book jacket bears caricatures of President Bush as Frankenstein-like and Vice President Dick Cheney with a Hitler mustache. A dark scrawl on the vice president's forehead reads, ''Got Oil?''</p>
        <p>Christine Iverson, a spokeswoman for the Republican National Committee, said the cover showed that Mr. Krugman's attacks on the administration had descended into ''hate speech.''</p>
        <p>''It is obvious that his feelings have clouded his objectivity and his ability to discuss the issues in a rational way,'' she said. ''The fact that they are using a much different cover here in the United States is proof that his tactics are offensive to mainstream Americans.''</p>
        <p>Stuart Proffitt, who published the British edition for the Allen Lane imprint of Penguin Press, said he chose the cover because it seemed appropriate to the book's potential readers in Britain, where Mr. Krugman's name is less known and Mr. Bush is less popular than in the United States.</p>
        <p>Catherine J. Mathis, a spokeswoman for The New York Times, said, ''The newspaper has no relationship to the British publisher -- we were never even shown the cover.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Krugman, for his part, said he did not remember seeing the cover until prepublication copies were sent to reviewers. ''I think it was intended to be ironic,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The cover images of Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney were borrowed from puppets carried by protesters outside the World Economic Forum in New York in 2002. Mr. Krugman said that he took part in the forum and does not share the protesters' views. He noted that his columns have defended free trade and argued that the administration's war in Iraq was not about oil.</p>
        <p>''It is a marketing thing, not a statement,'' he said. ''I should have taken a look at that and said, 'What are you doing marketing me as if I am Michael Moore? This is silly.' ''</p>
        <p>Incivility is one thing, he said, but the book cover ''may be undignified, which would be a reason to object.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 30, 2003, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the differing covers on the American and British editions of a book by Paul Krugman, the economist and Op-Ed columnist for The New York Times, Page, referred incorrectly to a caricature on the British version. According to groups that distribute the image, the drawing of Vice President Dick Cheney, with the words ''Got Oil'' on his forehead and a dark mustache, was intended to evoke the ''Got Milk'' advertising campaign, not to suggest a comparison with Hitler.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 30, 2003, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the differing covers on the American and British editions of a book by Paul Krugman, the economist and Op-Ed columnist for The New York Times, Page, referred incorrectly to a caricature on the British version. According to groups that distribute the image, the drawing of Vice President Dick Cheney, with the words ''Got Oil'' on his forehead and a dark mustache, was intended to evoke the ''Got Milk'' advertising campaign, not to suggest a comparison with Hitler.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
