<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FAMILY FARE</title>
    <meta content="19FAMI$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/19/arts/19FAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1409280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Family Fare"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mamet, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frog Prince, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/David Mamet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDC1039F93AA25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FAMILY FARE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trading a Crown for a Lily Pad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Family Fare column notes events suitable for families, including David Mamet's stage adaptation of Frog Prince at 78th Street Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trading a Crown For a Lily Pad</p>
        <p>''Contrast and balance,'' a prince says gravely, contemplating the flowers he has picked. Those qualities, he observes, are ''what we need in life (and art is a part of life).''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trading a Crown For a Lily Pad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trading a Crown For a Lily Pad</p>
        <p>''Contrast and balance,'' a prince says gravely, contemplating the flowers he has picked. Those qualities, he observes, are ''what we need in life (and art is a part of life).''</p>
        <p>David Mamet, author of the speech, has clearly taken the words to heart. A playwright whose characters may be more famous for hurling profanities than gathering posies, Mr. Mamet has balanced his own gritty art with the occasional foray into children's theater. But while his adaptation of ''The Frog Prince'' is certainly a contrast to much of his work, it is no less provocative and perhaps even more haunting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mamet's complex version departs from the black-and-white moral world of fairy tales to reveal a universe of gray. The prince, while arrogant, hardly seems to deserve being transformed into a frog for refusing to surrender the blossoms he has selected for his fiancée. And while the crone who requests them punishes him horribly, her curse is also a kind of blessing: he can now see things as they are, and be loved for who he really is.</p>
        <p>But knowledge comes with a terrible price: his betrothed proves false, his realm is ruined, and his faithful servant sacrifices his life.</p>
        <p>This is not to say, though, that children 5 and older will not love the bittersweet story.</p>
        <p>This is its third staging by the 78th Street Theater Lab under Eric Nightengale's direction, and the 50-minute production misses no opportunity for laughter, from the opening strains of the ''Masterpiece Theater'' theme song to the inventive physical comedy of Toby Wherry, who has consistently played the hapless prince.</p>
        <p>The delightful Karen Michelle Wright has also returned as the philosophical milkmaid, complemented with great sincerity by Jonathan Uffelman as the servant.</p>
        <p>And then, Mr. Mamet is still Mr. Mamet. When the prince says, ''Someday, I'm going to get that broad to kiss me, and then we're going to saddle up and blow this joint,'' you know that this is a royal he could smoke a cigar with.</p>
        <p>''The Frog Prince,'' Sundays at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m., through July 28 at the 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, Manhattan, (212) 873-9050. Tickets: $10. Reservations strongly advised.</p>
        <p>From Page to Stage</p>
        <p>Imagine a musical version of ''The Wizard of Oz'' that focused on the Scarecrow and the Tin Man rather than Dorothy. Or a ''Peter Pan'' in which Boris Karloff traded his Frankenstein scars and head screws for the plumed hat and curved claw of Captain Hook.</p>
        <p>These are just a couple of the productions documented in ''Children's Books in Performance,'' a new exhibition at the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts. Devoted to the other artistic lives that children's literature has enjoyed, the show ranges from a libretto and score for a 1730 comic opera ''Robin Hood'' to the film poster for ''Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone.''</p>
        <p>''I love this,'' said Barbara Cohen-Stratyner, the library's curator of exhibitions, pausing by the 19th-century patterns for a toy theater ''Cinderella.'' ''These are the ingredients for the coach and the footman,'' she said, pointing to tiny kitchen shelves holding a pumpkin and cages of rats.</p>
        <p>As well as capturing famous interpretations, the show offers surprises, including a newspaper photo of the future Queen Elizabeth II and her sister, Princess Margaret, costumed for a benefit staging of ''Aladdin'' during World War II.</p>
        <p>The show has its own performance aspects: tapes of radio plays, a film reel of animated stories and a free accompanying summer film series on Wednesdays. It even offers tables and crayons for the next generation of literary dreamers.</p>
        <p>''Children's Books in Performance,'' through Oct. 31 at the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-1630. Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 6 p.m.; Mondays and Thursdays, noon to 8 p.m. Free. Film series: (212) 621-0609.</p>
        <p>Play Time</p>
        <p>Some of the most tireless revelers in Manhattan playgrounds this summer aren't children. But they do zoom down slides, climb on monkey bars and yell at the top of their lungs.</p>
        <p>They're the members of the Faux-Real Theater Company, performing Hans Christian Andersen's tale ''The Tinderbox.'' Adapted by Carrie Dubois, the story is presented in circuslike style, with a ringmaster, tumbling, stilt-walking, a fire-breathing witch and a tinderbox that ignites.</p>
        <p>The sets are the playgrounds themselves: gazebos serve as rooms and ladders as castle towers. And all the children become eager extras.</p>
        <p>This version resembles ''Sleeping Beauty'': a witch (Constance Tarbox), outraged at not being invited to a princess's christening, curses the child, saying she will marry a common soldier. The princess's parents keep her locked up, but love, like curses, finds a way. The hero, who is (surprise!) a soldier (Alan Steffan Fessenden), obtains the witch's tinderbox, which gives him control over three enchanted dogs. But he's in trouble: witches like being duped about as much as they like being excluded from royal baptisms.</p>
        <p>Ms. DuBois, who also plays the princess, has spiced the tale with comic touches. And the troupe seems really magical: how else to explain its ability to earn children's rapt attention in the midst of a playground?</p>
        <p>''The Tinderbox,'' Fridays through Sundays at 6 p.m. through Aug. 4. This weekend: northeast playground of Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village. Free. Information and other locations: (212) 353-6935.</p>
        <p>Family Fare</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
