<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lemieux's 3 Goals Take Life Out of Isles</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="803962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PENGUINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DB1331F934A15753C1A963958260" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lemieux's 3 Goals Take Life Out of Isles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Finally showing some signs of life, the Islanders equaled their season high of four goals in a game with four in the second period alone tonight. And Wendel Clark responded to being benched Wednesday night with his first goal as an Islander.</p>
        <p>But Pittsburgh had Mario Lemieux on its side -- and that was more than enough. The big center, who missed last season with a bad back, scored goals Nos. 498, 499 and 500 of his National Hockey League career in achieving his 32d career hat trick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Finally showing some signs of life, the Islanders equaled their season high of four goals in a game with four in the second period alone tonight. And Wendel Clark responded to being benched Wednesday night with his first goal as an Islander.</p>
        <p>But Pittsburgh had Mario Lemieux on its side -- and that was more than enough. The big center, who missed last season with a bad back, scored goals Nos. 498, 499 and 500 of his National Hockey League career in achieving his 32d career hat trick.</p>
        <p>Lemieux's 500th, a wrist shot from the right circle that eluded Tommy Soderstrom with 2 minutes 48 seconds to play, also clinched for the Penguins a wild 7-5 victory before a half-full Nassau Coliseum and plunged the Islanders to 1-6-1 on the season, tying the worst start in team history.</p>
        <p>"Hey, he's the best there is," Islander Coach Mike Milbury said of Lemieux. "How do I argue that?"</p>
        <p>None necessary. Lemieux first erased a 4-3 Islander lead 19 seconds into the final period with his second goal of the game. He then set up Tomas Sandstrom's go-ahead one-timer off a face-off midway through the period. Big No. 66 finally deflected enough attention away from Soderstrom on the power play to enable Jaromir Jagr to score with less than eight minutes to play to make it 6-4.</p>
        <p>Clark temporarily answered back at 14:47, before Lemieux gave the Penguins a four-goal third period with his 500th in his 605th N.H.L. game. That's faster than anyone this side of Wayne Gretzky, who did it in 30 fewer games.</p>
        <p>"My back surprisingly is in great shape," Lemieux said afterward. "I didn't feel very good early in the game. I picked it up in the third. I knew I needed one more. It's important for me to score 500. It's a mark great players go out and achieve."</p>
        <p>The goal capped a contest that was almost like river hockey. Todd Bertuzzi called it a Ping-Pong game. Dennis Vaske likened it to a tennis match.</p>
        <p>The first sign of an Islander pulse came at even strength early in the second period. One minute 24 seconds in, Aleksandr Semak scored to cut the deficit to 2-1.</p>
        <p>The next breath was detected on the power play. After going 0 for 3 to drop to 4 for 34 on the season, the Islanders finally made something happen with the man advantage on Zigmund Palffy's one-time blast at 12:43.</p>
        <p>Palffy was not finished. At 17:01, the Slovak right wing took a pass just onside at the red line from Derek King, skated in on Tom Barrasso, deked him and beat him wide on a breakaway.</p>
        <p>All of a sudden, the Islanders had a 3-2 lead.</p>
        <p>A short-lived 3-2 lead. Sandstrom knocked home a rebound at the right post at 18:18 and it was tied at 3-3.</p>
        <p>Tied, that is, for exactly 10 seconds. Off the ensuing face-off, Bertuzzi backhanded a shot on goal flying down the right wing. Travis Green was flying, too -- toward the net. He deflected the puck past Barrasso as he crashed into him.</p>
        <p>Barrasso responded by punching Green in the head. The goal counted, though. And the Islanders had scored four times in 20 minutes -- more than they had scored in any previous game this season save the season-opener in Boston.</p>
        <p>But in the end, the Penguins had Lemieux. And Sandstrom. And Jagr. And another patented run-and-gun victory.</p>
        <p>Despite the significance of Lemieux's final goal, there was no official announcement over the Nassau Coliseum sound system.</p>
        <p>"I was waiting for it," he would later say.</p>
        <p>He need wait for 500 no more. SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The National Hockey League handed down an automatic three-game suspension to defenseman BRETT SEVERYN for his role in a brawl in Philadelphia on Wednesday night. . . . Defenseman CHRIS LUONGO was scratched from the lineup for the first time this season. Luongo was on the ice for all three Flyers goals on Wednesday night and is a minus-10 in seven games. . . . The Islanders played the final two periods with five defensemen after MATHIEU SCHNEIDER aggravated bruised ribs and did not return.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
