<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parcells and Johnson Keeping Decisions on Hold</title>
    <meta content="04JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/04/superbowl/04JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1260160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parcells, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Robert Wood Iv</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Groh, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DD1E3BF937A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parcells and Johnson Keeping Decisions on Hold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Future of New York Jets remains continuing mystery as Robert Wood Johnson, team's owner, and Bill Parcells, team's director of football operations, meet for three hours to discuss Parcell's future with team and vacancy left by resignation of coach Al Groh; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The future of the Jets remained a continuing mystery yesterday. Robert Wood Johnson, the team's owner, and Bill Parcells, the team's director of football operations, met for three hours at the team's complex on Long Island to discuss Parcells's future with the franchise and the vacancy left by Coach Al Groh's sudden resignation on Saturday.</p>
        <p>When the discussion was over, the Jets issued a four-paragraph statement that said nothing had been resolved and that talks between the two men would continue, with a definitive announcement about the team probably coming in the middle of next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The future of the Jets remained a continuing mystery yesterday. Robert Wood Johnson, the team's owner, and Bill Parcells, the team's director of football operations, met for three hours at the team's complex on Long Island to discuss Parcells's future with the franchise and the vacancy left by Coach Al Groh's sudden resignation on Saturday.</p>
        <p>When the discussion was over, the Jets issued a four-paragraph statement that said nothing had been resolved and that talks between the two men would continue, with a definitive announcement about the team probably coming in the middle of next week.</p>
        <p>The fact that the talks are continuing seems to indicate that Parcells will not leave the Jets entirely. Parcells, who reiterated his desire not to coach, is believed to be considering a move that will make him the president of the Jets, replacing Steve Gutman, who is mulling retirement. If Parcells accepts that job, he will no longer be in charge of the day-to-day football operation and he will probably hire a general manager. The general manager would then hire a coach, someone who could come from outside Parcells's immediate circle, unless Parcells were to hire someone like Jaguars Coach Tom Coughlin, a Parcells disciple who could assume both roles.</p>
        <p>If Parcells retains control of football operations, he would hand-pick Groh's successor, which would probably make the Jets' assistant head coach Maurice Carthon the leading candidate.</p>
        <p>The Jets have already lost out on a potential candidate for the coach and general manager's job. Marty Schottenheimer, a friend of Parcells, agreed yesterday to a deal to become the coach and general manager of the National Football League's other dysfunctional franchise, the Washington Redskins. The Redskins owner Daniel Snyder had also wanted to talk to Parcells, but when Snyder asked Johnson for permission to speak to Parcells, Parcells told Johnson that he was not interested.</p>
        <p>It is clear that the Jets are in no particular rush to restore normalcy to the team. According to the statement, Johnson and Parcells did not have time to finish their conversation yesterday and would continue to meet during the week. Mike Tannenbaum, the director of pro player development, was in and out of the meeting and Jay Cross, the Jets' stadium consultant, was also present for a time.</p>
        <p>The Jets said they would probably not make an announcement until the middle of next week.</p>
        <p>''They will continue to explore all possibilities before deciding the direction the franchise will take,'' the statement said.</p>
        <p>The Jets are used to this sort of unnerving institutional limbo. Last year, Bill Belichick resigned a day after replacing Parcells as coach. The Jets went three weeks without a coach before Groh was finally hired. The Jets did not have an owner for part of that time, either.</p>
        <p>This time, they do have an owner and Johnson's first mission is to resolve what job Parcells will have.</p>
        <p>By waiting, the pool of candidates for the Jets will likely expand, because other coaches who have not yet been fired or who have not yet resigned will become available. The Jets may also take a look at the group of highly regarded offensive and defensive coordinators whose teams remain in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Jets cannot talk to coaches whose teams are still in the playoffs, but they can let the other teams know they are interested in talking once the season is over. Among those possibilities are Marvin Lewis, the well-regarded defensive coordinator of the Baltimore Ravens and Chan Gailey, the offensive coordinator of the Dolphins who was once the head coach in Dallas.</p>
        <p>The slow pace of the Jets' progress may be in part because of the shock over Groh's resignation -- one person who spoke to officials at the Jets' complex on Tuesday described them as ''upside down about this thing'' -- and Parcells' undecided future. His contract expires Jan. 31, but even before Groh's departure he had indicated that he would return to the franchise. Earlier this week, The Boston Globe suggested that the job of director of football operations was more than Parcells had bargained for and that he was thinking of backing away before Groh's resignation. If Parcells is, in fact, thinking of scaling back his workload, then a move out of football operations seems likely.</p>
        <p>According to the statement, the Jets also seem to be looking at the overall structure of the team. Dick Haley, who runs the college draft, is believed to be considering retirement. The Jets could also create a position for pro player personnel director.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
