<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No New Powers Unless Palestinians Prevent Attacks, Israel Says</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="706908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GAZA STRIP</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST BANK</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PALESTINE LIBERATION ORGANIZATION (PLO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEDGES, CHRIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1D81E30F93BA2575BC0A962958260" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No New Powers Unless Palestinians Prevent Attacks, Israel Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEDGES, CHRIS</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Thursday, Aug. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Angered by recent attacks, Israeli officials warned on Wednesday that it would be impossible to broker further agreements on extending Palestinian self-rule in the West Bank and Gaza Strip unless Palestinian officials halted Islamic militant violence against Israelis.</p>
        <p>The latest violence, in which one Israeli was killed and eight were wounded in separate incidents in Gaza on Sunday, has led Israeli leaders to freeze plans for the withdrawal of Israeli troops from the strip and from parts of the West Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Angered by recent attacks, Israeli officials warned on Wednesday that it would be impossible to broker further agreements on extending Palestinian self-rule in the West Bank and Gaza Strip unless Palestinian officials halted Islamic militant violence against Israelis.</p>
        <p>The latest violence, in which one Israeli was killed and eight were wounded in separate incidents in Gaza on Sunday, has led Israeli leaders to freeze plans for the withdrawal of Israeli troops from the strip and from parts of the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Foreign Minister Shimon Peres told Palestine Liberation Organization officials at a meeting in Alexandria, Egypt, that the deteriorating security sitiuation was now threatening the peace agreement.</p>
        <p>"The Palestinian side and we also are struggling very hard so that this thing will not collapse," Mr. Peres said. Here in Jerusalem, Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin was quoted by the Israel radio as saying that the security steps taken so far by the Palestinians to bolster security were no more than a publicity stunt.</p>
        <p>At the meeting in Alexandria, which broke up early today, the two sides agreed nonetheless to complete negotiations on the handover of authority in the Gaza Strip and West Bank town of Jericho in five categories by Aug. 24. In a joint statement, they also confirmed that they still planned to extend Palestinian control to the education system by the beginning of the school year in September.</p>
        <p>The four other areas under negotiation are social affairs, taxation, education and tourism.</p>
        <p>As part of the agreement, Israel is to release 249 of the remaining 5,000 Palestinian prisoners in Israeli jails by Friday, the joint statement said. None of the prisoners scheduled for release are members of the Islamic militant group Hamas, which carried out the attacks in Gaza on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian Authority questioned 40 supporters of Hamas after the attacks. Five are still being held, although Israeli officials have privately raised doubts about whether they are responsible for the violence.</p>
        <p>To allay Israeli security concerns, Palestinian officials announced on Wednesday that they would open a campaign to confiscate illegal weapons in Gaza and Jericho.</p>
        <p>"We will start to collect arms because whoever wishes to own weapons must have a license," said Freih Abu Medeen, the Palestinian official in charge of justice in the self-rule areas. Several Islamic militant leaders said that the P.L.O. chairman, Yasir Arafat, had warned them on Tuesday not to carry weapons in public.</p>
        <p>Those leaders also reported that a senior Palestinian security officer in southern Gaza met with seven Hamas activists and told them that Palestinian police officers would take action against those who were armed or masked.</p>
        <p>The resurgence of attacks by Hamas, including a shootout between Islamic militants and Israeli police officers last Friday in East Jerusalem, has placed Mr. Arafat and his new leadership in a quandary.</p>
        <p>While Hamas opposes the peace accord with Israel and vows to seek Israel's destruction, it has managed to work with the P.L.O. as a partner in Gaza. But much of that relationship has been the result of Mr. Arafat's unwillingness to challenge the militant groups, which hold public rallies and parade in the streets with automatic weapons.</p>
        <p>In the attack in East Jerusalem on Friday, Hamas gunmen opened fire on a patrol car, wounding three police officers. The police later shot two Palestinians and captured a third.  Hamas leaders said the two attacks on Sunday in Gaza were carried out to avenge the deaths of the militants killed on Friday.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian police appealed to families of Hamas members to help them search for the people who took part in the attacks. The groups Islamic Holy War and Hamas accused Mr. Arafat of carrying out Israel's "dirty" work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
