<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Georgetown Survives Scare</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="319530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC1F30F930A15752C0A966958260" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Georgetown Survives Scare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A driving layup by Alonzo Mourning put Georgetown ahead with 18 seconds left and the Hoyas held on for a 70-69 victory over Villanova tonight in a Big East Conference game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A driving layup by Alonzo Mourning put Georgetown ahead with 18 seconds left and the Hoyas held on for a 70-69 victory over Villanova tonight in a Big East Conference game.</p>
        <p>A driving layup by Alonzo Mourning put Georgetown ahead with 18 seconds left and the Hoyas held on for a 70-69 victory over Villanova tonight in a Big East Conference game.</p>
        <p>With the Hoyas trailing by 69-68, Mourning took an inbounds pass, made the basket and was fouled. After he missed the free throw, Villanova got three final shots.</p>
        <p>A layup by Lance Miller didn't go in, and Georgetown knocked the ball out of bounds. Then, a jumper by Chris Walker was blocked by Mark Tillmon, and Walker missed a desperation attempt at the buzzer.</p>
        <p>Georgetown, a loser at Connecticut on Saturday, improved to 15-1 over all and 5-1 in the league, tied with St. John's for first place. Villanova (11-9, 3-4) has won its three conference games on road but has lost all four at home.</p>
        <p>The Wildcats rallied from a 5-point deficit with 1 minutes 9 seconds remaining to go ahead, 69-68, with 24 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Tillmon scored 26, including three 3-point shots, to lead Georgetown. Mourning had 19 points and Dwayne Bryant 14. Miller led Villanova with 16 points, and Walker scored 13, including three 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>Duke 109, William &amp; Mary 76</p>
        <p>WILLIAMSBURG, Va. (AP) -Phil Henderson scored 25 points and Duke shot 38-for-43 from the foul line.</p>
        <p>The Blue Devils (14-3) took an 11-9 lead five minutes into the game and steadily pulled away from the Indians (4-12). The game matched Coach Mike Krzyzewski of Duke against a former assistant, Chuck Swenson.</p>
        <p>Duke made 18 of 20 free throws in the first half and led by 47-30 at halftime. Bobby Hurley made consecutive 3-point baskets and Henderson dunked as Duke opened the second half with 8 points in a row.</p>
        <p>Arkansas 100, Houston 89</p>
        <p>FAYETTEVILLE, Ark. (AP) -Mario Credit and Ron Huery scored 21 points each as the Razorbacks won the Southwest Conference game. Arkansas (15-2, 7-0) never trailed after Todd Day's steal and layup made it 6-5 with less than three minutes gone. The Cougars are 12-6 and 3-3.</p>
        <p>La Salle 89, Loyola 69</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA (AP) - Lionel Simmons scored 36 points and sparked a second-half run as La Salle beat Loyola of Maryland in the Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference game.</p>
        <p>La Salle (13-1, 4-0) defeated Loyola for the 26th time in 27 games. Simmons scored in double figures for his 93d consecutive game. Kevin Green scored 22 points for Loyola (3-13, 1-5).</p>
        <p>N. Carolina 73, Wake Forest 61</p>
        <p>CHAPEL HILL, N.C. (AP) - North Carolina (14-6, 4-1 in the Atlantic Coast Conference) tied Kentucky as college basketball's winningest team as Rick Fox sparked a second-half run and led five Tar Heel players in double figures. Both Kentucky and North Carolina have won 1,472 games. The Wildcats, who did not play tonight, have lost 483 games while the Tar Heels have dropped 537. Wake Forest is 7-10 and 0-5.  Wisconsin 77, Minnesota 75 MADISON (AP) - Patrick Tompkins took an inbounds lob from Kurt Portmann and laid it in as time expired, giving Wisconsin a victory over Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Minnesota rallied from a 21-point deficit in the final 12 minutes, but got beaten at the buzzer. With one second left, Portmans threw an alley-oop pass from underneath the basket to Tompkins, who cut down the lane, caught the ball and scored.</p>
        <p>Willie Simms scored 22 points, Tim Locum had 20 and Danny Jones finished with 19 for Wisconsin (11-7 over all, 2-4 in the Big Ten). Willie Burton scored 24 points to lead Minnesota (12-4, 3-3). Wisconsin led by 38-25 at halftime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
