<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digital, Sun and Xerox Join To Make Better Printer Link</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="788292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTER PRINTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DIGITAL EQUIPMENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUN MICROSYSTEMS INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">XEROX CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Printers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D6133BF930A2575AC0A963958260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digital, Sun and Xerox Join To Make Better Printer Link</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to make computers and printers from different manufacturers more compatible and manageable, the Digital Equipment Corporation, the Sun Soft subsidiary of Sun Microsystems Inc. and the Xerox Corporation announced an alliance yesterday to develop software that would permit communications between various devices.</p>
        <p>The first shipments of the software, called Printxchange, are expected about the middle of next year and would be intended for machines using the Unix operating system. The software would be embedded in products made by the companies, so users would not have to purchase it separately.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to make computers and printers from different manufacturers more compatible and manageable, the Digital Equipment Corporation, the Sun Soft subsidiary of Sun Microsystems Inc. and the Xerox Corporation announced an alliance yesterday to develop software that would permit communications between various devices.</p>
        <p>The first shipments of the software, called Printxchange, are expected about the middle of next year and would be intended for machines using the Unix operating system. The software would be embedded in products made by the companies, so users would not have to purchase it separately.</p>
        <p>The three companies have equipped a laboratory in El Segundo, Calif., where the software would be tested on a variety of computers and printers, including machines made by Hewlett-Packard and Eastman Kodak, as well as those made by Xerox, D.E.C. and Sun.</p>
        <p>The alliance is also holding discussions with Novell Inc. to develop a link between Printxchange and Novell's Netware Distributed Print Services software.</p>
        <p>The companies in the alliance said obtaining printed copies of documents composed on personal computers or work stations had been a big problem in distributed computing. A user sending a document to a remote printer does not know if the machine has sufficient paper, is overwhelmed with work or is not operating.</p>
        <p>They said surveys by consultants found that the top complaint of systems administrators was difficulties with printing, and that many companies kept mainframe computers in operation solely to handle printing.</p>
        <p>The object of the new software is to "take the pain and misery out of printing," John A. Lopiano, head of Xerox's production systems division, said.</p>
        <p>Printxchange could be the basis for applications that would deliver a detailed status report immediately after a printing job was sent to a printer; it would also have a feature to forward a job to an alternate printer automatically to avoid delays, and would contain accounting features to report the cost of a job and charge the appropriate department.</p>
        <p>Research for the Printxchange system was originally conducted at the Massachussetts Institute of Technology. The system would have three modules: one to initiate print system requests, another to store data to be printed and one to control the printing devices. The companies have tested the various pieces of the system for compatability during the last 18 months.</p>
        <p>The alliance with a computer hardware and a software company was consistent with Xerox's strategy of linking closely with the computer industry without becoming part of it. It was also an demonstration of how large manufacturers are teaming with computer-based companies as they move into the digital age.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the Eastman Kodak Company announced a series of relationships with computer industry companies as it sought to develop electronic imaging devices to market along with its chemically based film.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
