<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Janzen Watches the Birdies Fall and Ties an Open Record</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="616212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="U.S. OPEN GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES OPEN (GOLF)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">&lt;DIAZ,&gt;JAIME</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANZEN, LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF133CF93AA25755C0A965958260" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Janzen Watches the Birdies Fall and Ties an Open Record</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAIME DIAZ,</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, N.J., June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a burst of birdies through the heart of Baltusrol's back nine, Lee Janzen shot his second consecutive 67 today to take a two-stroke lead in the 93d United States Open.</p>
        <p>Propelled by a hot 3-2-3 run on the 11th, 12th and 13th holes, the 28-year-old Janzen finished with a 36-hole total of six-under-par 134, two strokes better than Tom Watson and Payne Stewart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a burst of birdies through the heart of Baltusrol's back nine, Lee Janzen shot his second consecutive 67 today to take a two-stroke lead in the 93d United States Open.</p>
        <p>Propelled by a hot 3-2-3 run on the 11th, 12th and 13th holes, the 28-year-old Janzen finished with a 36-hole total of six-under-par 134, two strokes better than Tom Watson and Payne Stewart.</p>
        <p>The two former champions each shot 66 to tie at 136, while Corey Pavin and Nick Price were another stroke back at 137. Scott Hoch, the first-round co-leader, was at 138, and Fred Couples, Paul Azinger, Jeff Maggert, Billy Andrade, Bob Gilder and Mike Standly were at 139.</p>
        <p>Janzen's total tied the lowest two-round total ever achieved in the Open, a record that had been set by T. C. Chen (1985) and Jack Nicklaus (1980). Nicklaus's score came at Baltusrol, where he went on to set the 72-hole scoring record of eight-under 272.</p>
        <p>That record is probably the last thing on Janzen's mind. For one thing, the hardening and quickening of Baltusrol's greens is making it extremely difficult to put iron shots close to the pin, even with nearly windless conditions. Most of the contenders said that if no rain falls by Sunday, the record will survive.</p>
        <p>Janzen has also learned the hard way not to get ahead of himself in major championships. Two months ago, he was tied for the lead at the Masters after an opening 67, but fell back with rounds of 73, 76 and 77 to finish 39th.</p>
        <p>"After the first round, I didn't play the golf course the way I should have, which was one shot at a time," Janzen said of his experience at Augusta National. "I got too much into trying to make birdies, and I pretty much shot myself out of the tournament.</p>
        <p>"The U.S. Open is a little different. You know pars will get you a lot farther than anywhere else. I know a lot of things will happen to me before Sunday afternoon. I'm going to do my best to hang in there."</p>
        <p>Janzen may not be a household name, but he is definitely well known among his peers. Last year, in his third season on the PGA Tour, he won in Tucson, Ariz., and finished ninth on the money list with nearly $800,000 in earnings. This year he had another victory, at Phoenix; along with a third last week at the Buick Classic at Westchester, he is seventh on the money list with $516,990.</p>
        <p>The hard-working resident of Kissimmee, Fla., is known for having the kind of sound swing, solid temperment and textbook putting stroke that produce consistent golf. But it was with a flash of brilliance that he took the lead on Baltusrol's Lower Course.</p>
        <p>After pushing his drive onto the grassy bank of a bunker on the 428-yard 11th hole, Janzen hit a towering 3-iron from an uphill lie that traveled 218 yards to within 15 feet of the hole. When he made the putt, it changed him from a defensive to an offensive golfer.</p>
        <p>"I had been struggling, but that was a tremendous turnaround," said Janzen. "I was thinking birdie on every hole the rest of the way."</p>
        <p>He got a birdie on each of the next two holes, sinking a 20-footer on the 193-yard par-3 12th and a six-footer on the 401-yard 13th.</p>
        <p>From there, Janzen went back to steady pars, including a somewhat disappointing 5 on the 542-yard closing hole when he pushed his 4-wood second shot into a bunker. But it didn't take away the thrill of being atop the leader board.</p>
        <p>"Watson, Stewart and Nick Price have all won majors," said Janzen. "They've got the whole package with their games. They know what they've got to do and I know what I have to do. I have to go out and play my game and do my best. When my emotions start to take over and nerves get going, I have to stay patient and calm."</p>
        <p>Janzen's late run lowered the cut to four-over-par 144, which knocked out the 145 scorers: a list that includes Tom Kite, the defending champion; Bernhard Langer, the Masters champion, and Joey Sindelar, the first-round co-leader, who skied to a 79. Also missing the cut were Greg Norman, Seve Ballesteros and last week's winner at the Buick Classic, Vijay Singh, who was eliminated at the halfway point for the first time after 12 appearances on the PGA Tour over the last two seasons. Missouri Breaks</p>
        <p>While Janzen was giving the crowds at Baltusrol a view of a star of the future, Watson and Stewart, the two Missourians, were providing a blast from the past.</p>
        <p>Stewart's last victory was the 1991 United States Open at Hazeltine in Chaska, Minn., but he has consistently played well this year. He has nine top-10 finishes in 18 events, including two seconds and two thirds.</p>
        <p>The 43-year-old Watson, who won the Open in 1982, hasn't won on the PGA Tour since 1987. This year his best finish in 11 events is a tie for sixth at the Southwestern Bell Colonial in Fort Worth.</p>
        <p>Still, he views the Open as the greatest challenge in golf, and he played with a special verve today.</p>
        <p>Watson, who began the tournament Thursday by going four-over par on the first seven holes, again righted himself after stumbling early. After a par on the 470-yard par-4 first hole, Watson missed a putt of less than 4 feet for a par on the second. It was just the kind of miss that has been the bane of his game in recent years, and it infuriated him.</p>
        <p>"I yipped it and I got angry at myself," said Watson. "I've been fighting short putts all year. And I had a pretty solid talk with myself. I said, 'What in the heck am I doing this for? Here is the most important tournament and I'm not going to fail this time.' So I sucked it up."</p>
        <p>From that point, Watson didn't make another bogey. He birdied the 470-yard par-4 seventh with a driver, 6-iron and 20-foot putt, and then made three more, closing out his scoring on the 542-yard par-5 18th, where he used a wedge to get within 15 feet and eased the dowhill putt into the hole.</p>
        <p>Watson said he no longer feels frustrated at not being the same player he was in the late 1970's and early 80's, when he was the PGA Player of the Year six times and was clearly the best in the game.</p>
        <p>"It used to bug me because I put a tremendous amount of pressure on myself to live up to the performances of my past, but it just didn't happen," said Watson. "I still think I'm tournament tough and tournament ready. There's no reason I can't win the tournament as long as I play my best golf."</p>
        <p>Stewart, 36, feels the same way.</p>
        <p>"I have the belief in myself that I have the ability to do it because I have done it before," he said. "I want to get myself in that position again and see if I can deal with it."</p>
        <p>After a shaky opening 70 that ended with a disappointing bogey on the easy 18th, Stewart worked out some swing problems on the practice range. He termed the difference between his play Thursday and today "like night and day."</p>
        <p>"Today, I hit the ball like I've been playing all year," he said. "I feel comfortable with my golf game."</p>
        <p>Stewart has every right to be frustrated, especially after his loss at the Memorial in Ohio, where Paul Azinger holed a sand shot for a birdie on the 72d hole.</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>PAYNE STEWART, who played with JOHN DALY in the first two rounds, was decidedly unimpressed by the Wild Thing becoming the first player ever to hit the 630-yard par-5 17th hole in two. "What did he do?" asked Stewart with a straight face when asked about Daly's accomplishment. "I was paying attention to my golf game. I wasn't paying attention to John's golf game." . . . TOM WATSON found a key to his putting on the sixth green, when he did something that is almost never seen in professional golf. After holing out, he stayed on the green and hit several practice putts. Under the United States Golf Association's rules of competition, players are allowed to practice-putt on a green if they are not holding up play. After two-putting from 20 feet for a par, Watson asked the official assigned to the hole if he was within the rules to practice-putt. After being told that he was, Watson stroked about 10 six-footers, missing more than half of them.</p>
        <p>U.S. OPEN GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
