<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberal Bloggers Reaching Out To Major Media</title>
    <meta content="14BLOG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/14/technology/14blog.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1656964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Democrats.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fertik, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Post Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DB153CF937A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberal Bloggers Reaching Out To Major Media</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Liberal Bloggers Reaching Out to Major Media</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bloggers describing themselves as liberal or progressive are using telephone conference calls to share their ideas with newspaper and television journalists in effort to counter what they regard as much stronger influence of conservative pundits online; conference call is small development in complex relationship between bloggers and mainstream media, which largely ignored bloggers when they emerged but have begun to take note of their influence as online commentators assume roles in news stories; Bob Fertik, president of Democrats.com, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as online pundits criticize traditional news organizations as slow, biased and technologically challenged, a group of bloggers is trying to use old-fashioned telephone conference calls to share their ideas with newspaper and television journalists.</p>
        <p>The bloggers, who describe themselves as liberal or progressive, say the conference calls are intended to counter what they regard as the much stronger influence of conservative pundits online. Bob Fertik, president of Democrats.com, the host of the two calls so far, views them as a step toward getting their reports out to mainstream news organizations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of left-wing bloggers has started holding conference calls with news outlets to counter what they believe is the growing power of right-wing blogs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as online pundits criticize traditional news organizations as slow, biased and technologically challenged, a group of bloggers is trying to use old-fashioned telephone conference calls to share their ideas with newspaper and television journalists.</p>
        <p>The bloggers, who describe themselves as liberal or progressive, say the conference calls are intended to counter what they regard as the much stronger influence of conservative pundits online. Bob Fertik, president of Democrats.com, the host of the two calls so far, views them as a step toward getting their reports out to mainstream news organizations.</p>
        <p>While there is no way to know precisely who dialed in, reporters from news organizations including CBS, The Washington Post, Newsweek, MSNBC and The National Journal asked for a call-in number, according to one participant.</p>
        <p>''We hope to build a bridge,'' Mr. Fertik said, adding that different bloggers would be invited to share their reporting on each call. ''We hope that good credible stories that are broken on the Internet find their way into coverage in the mainstream media.''</p>
        <p>The conference call is a small development in the complex relationship between bloggers and the mainstream media. Traditional journalists largely ignored bloggers when they emerged, but have begun to take note of their influence as online commentators assumed roles in news stories like the flaws in the report by ''60 Minutes Wednesday'' on President Bush's National Guard service and the comments by the former CNN chief, Eason Jordan, about the military's treatment of journalists in Iraq.</p>
        <p>As more news emerges online, or what is reported offline becomes fodder for further investigation, the lines between those operating in the world of online news and commentary and those at the traditional media organizations have become more blurred and sometimes less confrontational. Some news organizations now credit blogs that originate stories, extending to them the treatment other media receive. Some bloggers, in turn, argue that they should receive all the legal privileges that traditional journalists often have, including the right to protect news sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fertik maintains that the blurring of boundaries has benefited left-wing bloggers less than their adversaries on the right, saying that reports posted on conservative blogs more easily make the jump to the main news media. ''The way we perceive it,'' he said, ''is that right-wing bloggers are able to invent stories, get them out on Drudge, get them on Rush Limbaugh, get them on Fox, and pretty soon that spills over into the mainstream media. We, the progressives, we don't have that kind of network to work with.''</p>
        <p>Some on the right disagree, arguing that the news reported by traditional media is tainted by liberal bias. ''We learned years ago that the mainstream media just weren't going to pay attention to us,'' said Kristinn Taylor of the Web site FreeRepublic.com.</p>
        <p>But bloggers on all sides agree that the left has made less effective use of the opportunities to organize and wield influence afforded by the Internet. The reasons, though, are more complex than they might appear. ''It's not just a story about the blogosphere,'' said Jack M. Balkin, a professor and director of the Information Society Project at Yale Law School. ''It's a story about the conservative social networks of which the blogosphere is a part. The important thing is the network -- and I mean the social network.''</p>
        <p>It is probably too early to tell how successful the conference calls have been, although Mr. Fertik said that the audio recording of the first call had been downloaded some 2,000 times. During the second call, held last Tuesday, Brad Friedman, who runs bradblog.com, discussed his investigation into accusations of rigged electronic voting machines -- a contentious subject that drew questions from listeners, mostly other bloggers.</p>
        <p>Some phoned from far away, including places in Canada, to take part in the call, which lasted more than an hour. Listeners asked if a figure in Mr. Friedman's inquiry had taken a lie-detector test and if any traditional news outlets had picked up the story.</p>
        <p>Will Femia, a producer at MSNBC.com who monitors blogging, said he was surprised by how well that call worked. ''It was a fascinating idea,'' he said, ''and I would also say that it's not a bad idea to try something like that. I know that the news producers that I've spoken with are still engaged in a learning curve on how to extract news from blogs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Femia, who sometimes presents ideas based on bloggers' postings, said he was not sure exactly how stories made the transition. ''I don't know what the tipping point is,'' he said, adding that some reporters clearly checked blogs for ideas.</p>
        <p>Another conservative Web site, younger than FreeRepublic.com, may offer the best lesson on how to gain influence, a lesson that would resonate with any aspiring journalist: tell a compelling, highly topical story.</p>
        <p>Powerlineblog.com was one of the first blogs to spread criticism of the documents used as evidence in the ''60 Minutes Wednesday'' segment, said Paul Mirengoff, a Washington lawyer and a member of the site. ''We put the question on our blog and then our readers started weighing in,'' he said, adding that because the topic was so sensational, it was inevitable that it would make it into the mainstream media.</p>
        <p>''That really spiked our readership,'' Mr. Mirengoff said, and established the site as a force to be reckoned with.</p>
        <p>But he disputed the idea that conservative bloggers had greater success in getting their stories spread by mainstream reporters. ''The left just thinks we're getting a free ride and the mainstream media are just eating out of our hand,'' he said. ''That's just not the case.''</p>
        <p>He added that he would be curious to see what happened with the conference call effort. ''It never would've occurred to me,'' he said. ''It seems a reasonable thing to do and if it works, we might copy it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Balkin said that building the influence of a particular Web site requires more than simply expressing conservative views online or taking on a broadcast journalist like Dan Rather. What matters is the willingness of like-minded people to establish links to that Web site, to drive more traffic there, and of yet other like-minded people in traditional news organizations, in talk radio and on television to draw on it.</p>
        <p>''It's a team effort,'' Mr. Taylor of FreeRepublic.com said. ''We feed off each other, because the radio hosts would have information that we didn't have and then we would post that.'' In the early days of FreeRepublic, meetings with politicians and other offline efforts helped get word of the site out, too.</p>
        <p>Right-leaning bloggers were unified by the presence of President Bill Clinton in the 1990's, Mr. Balkin said. That fueled their sense of commitment, he said, adding that while the war in Iraq might have a similar effect on the left now, that would take time.</p>
        <p>Asked what lessons liberal and progressive bloggers could learn from the experience of FreeRepublic, Mr. Taylor replied that while ''I'm loath to give them advice,'' they might have to outgrow the conspiracy-theory stage of blogging to produce reports that are credible and relevant to a wider audience.</p>
        <p>''In the old days of FreeRepublic,'' he said, ''we had all kinds of black helicopters'' and speculation about the effect of the Y2K problem. After the world did not end on Jan. 1, 2000, he said, ''We tried to be more realistic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
