<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Like Old Times at Duke: No. 1 in the A.C.C. and Seeded First in Its Regional</title>
    <meta content="14TOUR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/14/sports/ncaabasketball/14tourneys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1657053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: CONFERENCE TOURNAMENT FINALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgia Tech (Georgia Institute of Technology)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D7153CF937A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Like Old Times at Duke: No. 1 in the A.C.C. and Seeded First in Its Regional</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It's March, and Duke Believes. Opponents Beware.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Duke University defeats Georgia Tech University, 69-64, to win men's Atlantic Coast Conference tournament championship; other conference results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps it is true what they say about Duke, that this is not a vintage group of blue-chip Blue Devils.</p>
        <p>They may lack depth behind the scoring of the brilliant J.J. Redick and his sidekick at guard, Daniel Ewing, and the low-post power of center Shelden Williams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Duke is still Duke, which won another A.C.C. tournament title. Other winners Sunday: Illinois, Florida, Okahoma State, Southeastern Louisiana and Alabama A&amp;M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps it is true what they say about Duke, that this is not a vintage group of blue-chip Blue Devils.</p>
        <p>They may lack depth behind the scoring of the brilliant J.J. Redick and his sidekick at guard, Daniel Ewing, and the low-post power of center Shelden Williams.</p>
        <p>But what is not to like about a 25-5 record and an Atlantic Coast Conference tournament championship after Sunday's 69-64 victory over Georgia Tech at the MCI Center? Duke is still Duke, a talented team many love to hate and some learn to fear.</p>
        <p>Led by the veteran coach, Mike Krzyzewski, the Devils will open the N.C.A.A. tournament seeded No. 1 in the Austin Regional and will play Delaware State (19-13) on Friday in Charlotte.</p>
        <p>Georgia Tech (19-11) is seeded fifth in the Albuquerque Regional and will play George Washington (22-7) on Friday in Nashville.</p>
        <p>''You can expect a lot from us,'' Ewing said. ''We believe in ourselves. So far this year, we've just been building. We'll be a typical Duke team in the tournament.''</p>
        <p>In the final, Redick led Duke with 26 points, Ewing had 15 before fouling out with 4:32 left, and Williams was pivotal with 16 points, 13 rebounds and 6 blocked shots.</p>
        <p>Duke has won the tournament title in six of the last seven seasons.</p>
        <p>Tech guard Jarrett Jack sprained his ankle with 9:41 left, but he returned to score 7 of his team-best 19 points in helping the Yellow Jackets cut a 13-point Duke lead to 2 with 1 minute 27 seconds left. The Jackets held the Devils without a field goal for more than 11 minutes at the end. Will Bynum scored 14 for Tech, but he missed all seven 3-point attempts.</p>
        <p>Big Ten</p>
        <p>ILLINOIS 54, WISCONSIN 43 -- The top-ranked Illini (32-1) built a big lead, then dominated defensively to hold off No. 23 Wisconsin (22-8) in the Big Ten tournament final for their team-record 32nd victory.</p>
        <p>Illinois will play Fairleigh Dickinson (20-12) in the first round of the N.C.A.A. tournament Thursday in Indianapolis. The Badgers play Northern Iowa (21-10) in Oklahoma City on Friday. (AP)</p>
        <p>Southeastern</p>
        <p>FLORIDA 70, KENTUCKY 53 -- Matt Walsh had 26 points as the Gators (23-7) routed Kentucky for their first SEC tournament championship.</p>
        <p>The loss knocked the No. 4 Wildcats out of contention for a No. 1 seed in the N.C.A.A. tournament. Kentucky (25-5) is seeded second in the Austin Regional, and will play Eastern Kentucky (22-8) in the first round Thursday in Indianapolis. Florida plays Ohio (21-10) in Nashville on Friday. (AP)</p>
        <p>Big 12</p>
        <p>OKLAHOMA ST. 72, TEXAS TECH 68 -- John Lucas scored 19 points, including a free throw with 4.4 seconds left, and No. 10 Oklahoma State (24-6) earned its second straight Big 12 tournament championship.</p>
        <p>Oklahoma State will play Southeastern Louisiana (24-8), the Southland conference champion, in the first round of the N.C.A.A. tournament on Friday in Oklahoma City. Texas Tech (20-10) plays U.C.L.A. (18-10) on Thursday in Tucson. (AP)</p>
        <p>National Invitation Tournament</p>
        <p>40-TEAM FIELD CHOSEN -- Shunned by the N.C.A.A. tournament for the first time in 12 years, Maryland (16-12) is headed to the N.I.T.</p>
        <p>The Terrapins play Oral Roberts (25-7) on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Conference USA had five teams selected, the A.C.C. and Mid-American had four, and the Colonial Athletic Association had three. The Big East, Big 12, Pac-10, SEC and America East each had two.</p>
        <p>Eleven teams have at least 20 victories, down from 13 last year, and three have 15 victories. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: CONFERENCE TOURNAMENT FINALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
