<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Ex-Marine's Way to Build Self-Esteem</title>
    <meta content="19MARINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callahan, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Walter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confidence Course, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DF1138F93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Ex-Marine's Way to Build Self-Esteem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CALLAHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Callahan, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Walter Anderson, editor of Parade magazine and author of The Confidence Course, a book on developing self-esteem; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States Marine Corps calls the obstacle course for new recruits at Parris Island, S. C., a confidence course. This semantic distinction had a major impact on a resident here, Walter Anderson, when he went through Parris Island as a 17-year-old recruit in 1961.</p>
        <p>In the years since, Mr. Anderson, 52, has built a successful career as a newspaper reporter, magazine editor, author, college professor and public speaker. Currently the editor of Parade, a weekly magazine that appears in 340 newspapers around the country, Mr. Anderson has titled his latest book ''The Confidence Course.'' The book is scheduled to be published this month by HarperCollins and is based on a class Mr. Anderson has taught at the New School for Social Research in New York City since 1994.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States Marine Corps calls the obstacle course for new recruits at Parris Island, S. C., a confidence course. This semantic distinction had a major impact on a resident here, Walter Anderson, when he went through Parris Island as a 17-year-old recruit in 1961.</p>
        <p>In the years since, Mr. Anderson, 52, has built a successful career as a newspaper reporter, magazine editor, author, college professor and public speaker. Currently the editor of Parade, a weekly magazine that appears in 340 newspapers around the country, Mr. Anderson has titled his latest book ''The Confidence Course.'' The book is scheduled to be published this month by HarperCollins and is based on a class Mr. Anderson has taught at the New School for Social Research in New York City since 1994.</p>
        <p>''The most profound change that occurred in my life was enlisting in the Marine Corps and going to Parris Island,'' Mr. Anderson said in a recent interview in his home. A framed black-and-white photograph of the Marines raising the American flag on Iwo Jima hangs on the wall behind the desk in his study. ''It was in the Marines that I developed self-esteem. The purpose of their confidence course is not to present obstacles but to develop your confidence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson dropped out of high school at 16 to join the Marines and was told to come back when he reached 17. He grew up in an impoverished Mount Vernon neighborhood and in an abusive family environment. His father was a alcoholic. ''I lived with a burning rage,'' he said, describing his youth. ''I was a very angry adolescent. It took me years to overcome that anger.''</p>
        <p>During his five years in the Marines, he served in Vietnam and was promoted to sergeant by the time he was 21. He returned to Westchester after his discharge and took a job as a reporter for The Reporter Dispatch here. At 27, he became managing editor of the Westchester Rockland Newspapers. He returned to school while working in journalism, earning an associate degree from Westchester Community College and then graduating summa cum laude with a bachelor's degree from Mercy  College in Dobbs Ferry. He was valedictorian of his class at both colleges.</p>
        <p>He joined Parade in June 1977 and was named editor in 1980. During his tenure as editor, the magazine has increased its circulation from 21 million to 36 million. He has written three previous books and served as chairman of the board of Mercy College for eight years. He taught as an adjunct professor of psychology and sociology at Westchester Community College before joining the faculty at the New School. He has also been a host of a public television series, ''Read Together,'' which was meant to increase literacy among children</p>
        <p>In October 1995, President Clinton nominated him to serve on the United States National Commission on Libraries and Information Science. The Senate confirmed that nomination two months later.</p>
        <p>''I have to do more than one thing to keep a balance in my life,'' Mr. Anderson said. ''Folks ask me how I deal with stress. Well, I always do more than one thing.''</p>
        <p>But even as his career progressed, he still suffered from anxiety attacks and feelings of inferiority. The confidence-building course took him 10 years to develop. It is based on both his personal experiences and those of successful people he has met.</p>
        <p>''I have had an incredible opportunity that just about anybody on earth would love to take advantage of,'' he said. ''For the last 17 years, I've spent every day of my life with the smartest people in the world -- Nobel laureates, Pulitzer Prize winners, people who run nations, people who run great companies, artists. I've got a thicker head than most, but what they've told me starts to sink in.'' He lists the late Norman Vincent Peale and Elie Wiesel, a Nobel Peace Prize winner, as his mentors.</p>
        <p>When the course was first offered in 1994, it was expected to attract 10 to 12 students, but 54 showed up on the first night. His new book took two years to write and includes material from the class.</p>
        <p>''The reason I wrote the book is I've been asked over the years how I do this or that,'' he said. ''I realized that there are many books and articles written about reaching as high as you want in life. Family and friends tell us we can be anything we want. But nobody tells us how to do it. I wanted to create actual assignments people could do to increase their confidence.''</p>
        <p>The book is subtitled ''Seven Steps to Self-Fulfillment.'' These steps include accepting responsibility, believing in something big, practicing tolerance, being brave, loving someone, being ambitious and smiling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson said: ''The seven steps work because they begin with the most important. Who is responsible? I am responsible. Once you say these three words, you can not only  change your life, but there is a good chance you can change the world. You certainly can change the world around you once you realize that nobody else is responsible for your contentment, happiness and behavior.''</p>
        <p>Confidence, he said, is a learned attitude that can be increased. ''Nobody on earth escapes disappointment, loss and tragedy,'' he said. ''They occur in every life. The quality and character of our life is not determined by whether we experience these things, but by how we respond to them. The goal of this course is to climb the mountain of your choice -- and to enjoy the trek as well.''</p>
        <p>In his own life, that meant letting go of the anger he felt toward his father and finally forgiving him years after his death. Professionally, his toughest challenge was facing up to his fear of public speaking and humiliation. In 1992 he wrote and performed a one-man, one-night show, ''Talkin' Stuff'' at Ford's Theater in Washington, which benefited the Literacy Volunteers of America.</p>
        <p>''That was the highest mountain I ever had to climb,'' he said. ''It wasn't becoming editor of Parade, or The Reporter Dispatch, or writing my books. It was the moment when I stood on that stage and faced my greatest fear. I still get nervous when I speak in front of groups, but I learned how to use that energy. How to focus it. For the first time in my life in my 50's, I can truly say that I like me. It took me a long, long time before I could like myself.''</p>
        <p>He has received many professional honors over the years but is most proud of two: the 1994 Horatio Alger Award, which he was nominated for by Norman Vincent Peale, and the Tree of Life Award from the Jewish National Fund. That award was presented to him by Elie Wiesel in recognition of a plea he made on behalf of Soviet Jewry during a visit to the former Soviet Union in 1987.</p>
        <p>His said his greatest satisfaction in life has come from watching his  two children, Eric, 26, and Melinda, 22, grow up. He and his wife, Loretta, have been married for 30 years.</p>
        <p>After 17 years as editor of one of the nation's largest circulation magazines, he is not yet ready to step aside. ''My vision as editor is the same now as it was 17 years ago,'' he said. ''Human beings can transform themselves. We have a responsibility to make a better world. We will not leave people helpless. Americans will respond.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
