<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MEDICARE PANEL ADVISES A FREEZE ON HOSPITAL PAY</title>
    <meta content="19HEAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prospective Payment Assessment Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Hospital Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DF123BF93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MEDICARE PANEL ADVISES A FREEZE ON HOSPITAL PAY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prospective Payment Assessment Commission, a Federal advisory panel, recommends that Congress freeze Medicare payments to hospitals next year because hospitals have effectively controlled their costs and can maintain current level of care without additional funds; Medicare payments to hospitals totaled $84 billion last year, or 44 percent of all Medicare spending; recommendation offers Pres Clinton and Congress a relatively easy way to reduce Federal budget deficit and shore up Medicare trust; American Hospital Association spokeswoman complains that maintaining current level of hospital payments would effectively punish hospitals for improving their productivity, but Federal officials say that Medicare should share the benefits of such improvements and that hospitals can continue increasing productivity; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal advisory panel has decided to recommend that Congress freeze Medicare payments to hospitals next year. It would be the first time in the history of the program that hospitals have not received an increase.</p>
        <p>In approving the recommendation, the panel said that hospitals had effectively controlled their costs, so that existing Medicare payment rates were generally adequate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal advisory panel has decided to recommend that Congress freeze Medicare payments to hospitals next year. It would be the first time in the history of the program that hospitals have not received an increase.</p>
        <p>In approving the recommendation, the panel said that hospitals had effectively controlled their costs, so that existing Medicare payment rates were generally adequate.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the panel, Prof. Joseph P. Newhouse of Harvard, said in an interview that payment rates could be kept level next year without harming the quality of health care or access to care for beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>Medicare finances care for 38 million people who are elderly or disabled. Payments to hospitals totaled $84 billion last year, or 44 percent of all Medicare spending.</p>
        <p>The Federal advisory panel, the Prospective Payment Assessment Commission, voted this week to recommend a ''zero update'' -- no change -- in Medicare payment rates for hospitals. Congress pays close attention to the panel's advice, often providing less money but rarely more than it suggests.</p>
        <p>The unexpected recommendation offers President Clinton and Congress a relatively easy way to reduce the Federal budget deficit and shore up the Medicare trust fund that pays hospital bills.</p>
        <p>Carmela S. Coyle, a vice president of the American Hospital Association, said: ''We are surprised that the commission recommended no increase at all in Medicare payment amounts. It's unprecedented. Hospitals have become more efficient. We've kept down costs for two or three years in a row. There have been real cuts in the cost of treating Medicare patients. But how long can these cost reductions be sustained?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Coyle said hospitals were, in effect, being punished for having improved their productivity. Federal officials contend that Medicare should share the benefits of such improvements, and that hospitals can continue increasing productivity.</p>
        <p>Kenneth E. Raske, president of the Greater New York Hospital Association, said the Medicare proposal was ''the third stroke of a triple whammy'' adversely affecting hospital revenues. New York State recently lifted price controls on hospitals, forcing them to compete for patients by offering discounts to insurers. In addition, Mr. Raske said, New York has cut Medicaid payments to hospitals, and Gov. George E. Pataki is proposing deeper cuts.</p>
        <p>The recommendation from the Federal advisory panel coincides with new evidence showing how inflation has been squeezed from the health care industry.</p>
        <p>The cost of medical care, as measured by the Consumer Price Index, rose last year by just 3 percent, the smallest amount in three decades. The price index for all items increased 3.3 percent. It was the first time since 1980 that medical prices rose less than the overall index, which measures changes in the prices paid by consumers for a fixed market basket of goods and services.</p>
        <p>While the Government data show that medical prices are leveling off, some economists say they are actually declining.</p>
        <p>''For example,'' said Dahlia K. Remler, a health economist at Tulane University in New Orleans, ''the price you have to pay for extending your life after a heart attack is not rising as fast as the price of other goods in the economy like food, clothing and housing. In the last 15 years, the price of what we care about -- the price of having our health improved when we are sick -- has gone down in real terms.''</p>
        <p>Since 1984, hospitals have received a fixed amount of money for each Medicare patient they treat, regardless of how long the person stays in the hospital. Each Medicare patient is assigned to 1 of 495 categories, depending on the illness. Payments are set in advance for each category and can be updated annually.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office had assumed that payment rates would be increased 3 percent next year. Based on that figure, the panel's recommendation would save more than $2 billion in 1998. It would permanently lower the base for future increases, saving more than $11 billion over five years.</p>
        <p>The sum, while substantial, is a relatively small part of the savings that will be needed to guarantee the long-term solvency of Medicare.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, the commission has recommended increases averaging 3 percent a year, and Congress has approved increases averaging 2.6 percent a year.</p>
        <p>Stuart Guterman, deputy executive director of the commission, said: ''Hospital costs have been declining while Medicare payments have increased at a moderate rate. As a result, hospitals have found their Medicare business more profitable.''</p>
        <p>The hospital association boasted last year that ''increases in hospitals' costs of delivering care hit their lowest point in 40 years.'' One reason, the commission said, is that wages and benefits of hospital employees are growing more slowly than compensation in many other industries.</p>
        <p>Data collected by the Government show that hospital profit margins have, on the average, been rising for several years. But Mrs. Coyle said the data also showed that some hospitals were experiencing financial difficulties. Nineteen percent of hospitals lost money over all, she said, while 39 percent lost money on their Medicare business.</p>
        <p>Kay Ford, an economist at the Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics, said that the growing use of managed care had helped hold down health costs. Nearly three-fourths of workers with health insurance are in some type of managed care.</p>
        <p>Both H.M.O.'s and traditional insurance plans are negotiating with hospitals to get lower rates for their patients. Hardly anyone pays the full list price any more.</p>
        <p>Economists told Congress last month that the Consumer Price Index tends to overstate increases in the cost of living because it does not fully account for the development of new products, improvements in the quality of old products and other changes in the standard market basket of goods and services.</p>
        <p>Such changes are occurring throughout the health care industry. New drugs and devices and medical procedures are introduced every month. Employers, labor unions, H.M.O.'s and insurance companies are continually devising new ways to pay for services. Different people often pay different prices for the same service provided by the same doctor or hospital.</p>
        <p>The Bureau of Labor Statistics has data showing the prices of hospital rooms over the last 60 years. But the price index does not take account of the fact that the average length of hospital stays has declined in the last 15 years, especially for elderly patients.</p>
        <p>In addition, ''a hospital day today is very different from one 10 years ago in terms of the procedures a patient receives,'' said Dr. Mark McClellan, an economist and physician at Stanford University.</p>
        <p>David M. Cutler, an economist at Harvard, said that the services provided by doctors and hospitals today were worth more than those provided 10 or 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cutler, Dr. McClellan, Ms. Remler, and Mr. Newhouse recently studied the care of people who had suffered heart attacks. In a study published by the National Bureau of Economic Research, they found that while the ''use of more intensive procedures like bypass surgery and angioplasty has skyrocketed,'' prices have come down and patients are living longer.</p>
        <p>For these patients, they said, the cost of living in a literal sense -- the cost of prolonging life after a heart attack -- has declined.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
