<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suns Leave The Knicks Chilled And Hurting</title>
    <meta content="19KNIC$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO BASKETBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phoenix Suns</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7D8123BF93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suns Leave The Knicks Chilled And Hurting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phoenix Suns defeat New York Knicks 105-98 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tee times and the warm weather, things the Knicks had come to enjoy here, were suddenly a memory. Inside the America West Arena tonight, the reality of the situation was cold and, for a few moments, frightening.</p>
        <p>Chris Childs could not remember who hit him and John Starks was on his way to the hospital. The lone source of heat in the building came from the scorching hands of the Phoenix Suns. They ruined the Knicks' three-day trip to Arizona by unnerving them in the third quarter and holding them off in the fourth for a 105-98 victory before a loud home-town mob.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tee times and the warm weather, things the Knicks had come to enjoy here, were suddenly a memory. Inside the America West Arena tonight, the reality of the situation was cold and, for a few moments, frightening.</p>
        <p>Chris Childs could not remember who hit him and John Starks was on his way to the hospital. The lone source of heat in the building came from the scorching hands of the Phoenix Suns. They ruined the Knicks' three-day trip to Arizona by unnerving them in the third quarter and holding them off in the fourth for a 105-98 victory before a loud home-town mob.</p>
        <p>Neither Childs or Starks was seriously hurt, but the injuries they suffered contributed to a horrible night for the Knicks, who scored only one field goal the last 7 minutes 10 seconds of the game.</p>
        <p>Kevin Johnson leveled Starks in the third quarter as he was heading upcourt. Starks's collarbone was X-rayed and he was taken to the Barrow's Neurological Unit at St. Joseph's Medical Center in Phoenix as a precaution. The X-rays were negative, and Starks was diagnosed with a muscle strain of the neck and shoulder. He was listed as day-to-day and planned to return with the team.</p>
        <p>Childs suffered a mild concussion and a contusion of the left cheekbone when he was pulled down to the floor by John Williams in the second quarter. The injury appeared to happen afterward when Charles Oakley's foot hit his head.</p>
        <p>The Knicks had no problems with the plays by Johnson or Williams.</p>
        <p>''He was going for the steal and they just collided,'' Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy said of Johnson's collision with Starks. ''That's just basketball. We definitely have the talent to win and we just didn't get it done.''</p>
        <p>Cedric Ceballos crept sneakily along the baseline all game, finishing with 32 points. His lean-in improbable bank shot with 54.4 seconds left sealed the victory for Phoenix, which led only 97-92 at the time. Johnson and Wesley Person contributed 21 apiece for Phoenix, which improved to 14-25.</p>
        <p>Patrick Ewing led the Knicks with 28 points and Allan Houston added 19, but the Knicks (27-11) completely self-destructed in the final two quarters. They went from leading by 13 at halftime to trailing by nearly double figures in the final minutes.</p>
        <p>''Everything we did right in the first half we didn't do in the second half,'' Ewing said. ''We just didn't get it done. We didn't step up.''</p>
        <p>With Johnson orchestrating the running game, Phoenix energized its crowd by taking an 81-78 lead into the fourth quarter. The Knicks were outscored by 36-20 in the third quarter and had to work hard every possession in the final period to stay within striking distance.</p>
        <p>Starks was pulverized not once, but twice in the game. He was hammered as he drove to the basket at the end of the second quarter. He left the game shaken up with 27.8 seconds remaining in the half and walked straight toward the locker room. His left ribs were X-rayed at halftime, but the X-rays were negative and he returned with less than 9 minutes left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>He was charging down the floor when  he received a pass upcourt from Larry Johnson. But Kevin Johnson stepped in his path and his head and right shoulder hit the left side of Starks's body. The foul was whistled, but it was little consolation.</p>
        <p>Starks was writhing in pain, holding his  shoulder and squirming as he hit the ground. He lay there for a few minutes until the Knicks trainer Mike Saunders helped him off.</p>
        <p>Childs had his face accidentally stepped on during a scramble for the loose ball in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>''He just locked my arm and pulled me to the ground,'' Childs said of Williams's takedown. ''After that, someone hit me in the head. I don't remember. I just remember somebody asking me a lot of questions later.''</p>
        <p>Charlie Ward's performance was one of the lone bright spots. He had one of those second quarters of which Van Gundy could be proud. He ignited a lethargic team, threading no-look passes underneath to open teammates, took smart shots and made the game simple instead of trying to be spectacular.</p>
        <p>He had 9 assists in 16 minutes, including 2 to Buck Williams in a set offense for easy dunks. But he picked up his fourth foul with more than 8 minutes to play in the third quarter and his fifth with less than a minute left in the period. It changed the complexion of the game, as Kevin Johnson darted past Scott Brooks and anyone else who tried to stop him.</p>
        <p>''The time down here and the off-court activities didn't have anything to do with it,'' Van Gundy said. ''We just didn't get stops in the third quarter, that's all.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks return home for a Martin Luther King Day game against Washington before traveling to Chicago for their first meeting against the Bulls on Tuesday. . . . LARRY JOHNSON (6 points, 2 rebounds in 28 minutes) returned for the first time in five games. He said his left hamstring felt fine.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
