<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Duncan as Model, Suns Look to Regroup</title>
    <meta content="14spurs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/14/sports/basketball/14spurs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Phoenix Suns</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Duncan, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stoudemire, Amare</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D91231F937A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Duncan as Model, Suns Look to Regroup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Duncan as Model, Suns Look to Regroup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, May 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tim Duncan was spinning the Phoenix Suns on their heels, muscling his way to the basket and finishing his turnaround jump hooks with angles off the backboard that only he knows.</p>
        <p>Amare Stoudemire watched helplessly from the bench, saddled with fouls and frustration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In preparing for Game 4, the Suns realized that the toughness they lacked was less about bumps and bruises and more about sharp decision-making and mental fortitude.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tim Duncan was spinning the Phoenix Suns on their heels, muscling his way to the basket and finishing his turnaround jump hooks with angles off the backboard that only he knows.</p>
        <p>Amare Stoudemire watched helplessly from the bench, saddled with fouls and frustration.</p>
        <p>''It was vintage Tim Duncan,'' Stoudemire said Sunday, reflecting on Duncan's 33-point, 19-rebound performance a day earlier in Game 3. Duncan helped the Spurs to a 108-101 victory Saturday and a 2-1 series lead in the Western Conference semifinals. ''He uses the glass to perfection, and that gets them out of trouble. He's a great player.''</p>
        <p>Stoudemire, who missed last season recovering from microfracture knee surgery, was a first-team all-N.B.A. selection alongside Duncan. At 24, Stoudemire's talent seems boundless.</p>
        <p>But he has not been able to leap one hurdle. Stoudemire participated in the playoffs in 2003 and 2005 and ended up losing to Duncan's Spurs both times. The Spurs went on to win N.B.A. titles those seasons.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of another physical game Saturday, the Spurs could point to the bruise under Manu Ginóbili's left eye, which had turned red and yellow by Sunday, as proof of their mettle.</p>
        <p>But in preparing for Game 4, which will be Monday in San Antonio, the Suns looked inward. They realized that the toughness they lacked was less about bumps and bruises and more about sharp decision-making and mental fortitude in the face of a bad call or a bad play.</p>
        <p>''To be a champion, you have to acquire this, either by getting it in your gut or by failing,'' Suns Coach Mike D'Antoni said before practice. ''You have to be there, and then you have to get over the hump. And we're not over the hump.''</p>
        <p>The Suns missed shots, committed turnovers and had lapses at crucial times in Game 3. At the beginning of the third quarter, Stoudemire picked up his third foul while trying to block a shot by Duncan. Less than a minute later he committed his fourth, a needless offensive foul.</p>
        <p>He went to the bench and was not on the floor when Ginóbili scored all 10 points in a 10-3 run that essentially decided the game for the Spurs in the final two minutes of the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Stoudemire re-entered the game at the start of the fourth and picked up his fifth foul 19 seconds later.</p>
        <p>How can he stay aggressive and still stay in the game? Stoudemire looks to Duncan as an example.</p>
        <p>''First, stay out of foul trouble,'' Stoudemire said. ''Secondly, be yourself. That's what Timmy is doing, he's been himself. He's very poised, he takes his time, and that also comes with experience and knowing the game of basketball.</p>
        <p>''Me being a young player, only 24, I want to elevate my game and that starts with staying out of foul trouble.''</p>
        <p>Stoudemire said he was fine with everyone, including D'Antoni and the Suns' captain, Steve Nash, calling him young. Even if it seemed to suggest inexperience and impetuousness.</p>
        <p>''He's learning all the time,'' Nash said of Stoudemire.</p>
        <p>Nash said his team had to concentrate on playing a smart game as well as a physical one in Game 4.</p>
        <p>''Mental toughness encapsulates physical toughness,'' he said. ''I'd like to see us be great at both.''</p>
        <p>Stoudemire acknowledged Sunday that his physical instability last season still affected his mind-set.</p>
        <p>He said his memory of the injury caused his outburst after Game 2, when he called the Spurs dirty players. He focused particularly on Bruce Bowen, who he felt deliberately tried to injure him.</p>
        <p>''That's the reason why I had to speak about it,'' he said. ''I've been injured before and I know how it feels not to play for a year. I'm not scared at all. If it's done on purpose, it shouldn't be. But I'm over it.''</p>
        <p>The Spurs said his comments gave them extra motivation, and they certainly rallied the crowd. But Stoudemire still has confidence about his play in this series. In the 2005 Western Conference finals, he averaged 37 points in five games against the Spurs. Five months later, he signed a $73 million contract extension and had knee surgery.</p>
        <p>Duncan, too, experienced a drop-off from 2005, when he was named the most valuable player of the N.B.A. finals. He injured his right foot last season and was not himself when the Spurs lost in Game 7 to the Dallas Mavericks in the conference semifinals.</p>
        <p>''He's very different,'' San Antonio Coach Gregg Popovich said of Duncan, who reinvented himself with summer workouts last year.</p>
        <p>Spurs forward Robert Horry said: ''Now he's more mobile, he's blocking more shots, getting more rebounds. He's been the Tim of old.''</p>
        <p>Ginóbili said Duncan's presence brought a sense of tranquillity. ''He's so reliable, he's performing so good for long periods of time, he makes everybody feel more secure,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''He's the guy who makes this team going from a good one to a great one.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
