<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soviet Liberals Get Smart</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SESTANOVICH, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED71430F935A15751C0A967958260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soviet Liberals Get Smart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Sestanovich; Stephen Sestanovich is director of Soviet and East European studies at the Center for Strategic and International Studies.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SESTANOVICH, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soviet liberals are far from crushed. This was evident on Sunday, when Mikhail Gorbachev allowed Boris Yeltsin's supporters to rally in Moscow and demand Mr. Gorbachev's resignation. A few days earlier, Mr. Yeltsin had gone on national television to denounce him and make the same demand.</p>
        <p>Last month, after the Soviet leader allowed military units to go on a murderous rampage in Lithuania and Latvia, he pulled back from his threat to close down Baltic parliaments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soviet liberals are far from crushed. This was evident on Sunday, when Mikhail Gorbachev allowed Boris Yeltsin's supporters to rally in Moscow and demand Mr. Gorbachev's resignation. A few days earlier, Mr. Yeltsin had gone on national television to denounce him and make the same demand.</p>
        <p>Last month, after the Soviet leader allowed military units to go on a murderous rampage in Lithuania and Latvia, he pulled back from his threat to close down Baltic parliaments.</p>
        <p>What kind of crackdown is this, then? Clearly, one that is different from its predecessors in the Communist world. Mr. Gorbachev's campaign of repression has been carried out in the same slow motion he used as a reformer. His pace is not merely a style but a strategy: He tries never to give opponents a clear target, and if he meets unexpected resistance, he retreats to fight another day.</p>
        <p>The result is that liberals have a breathing space to regroup and many opportunities to challenge Mr. Gorbachev in the political season ahead. They are mobilizing supporters and trying to turn upcoming events such as the referendum March 17 on the future of the Union to their advantage.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Gorbachev has not arrested opponents does not mean he is not trying to weaken them. He has vigorously, but not wholly successfully, assaulted liberal strongholds in the media. When Izvestia's deputy editor was to be removed for criticizing him, the staff rallied and threatened to strike. And when the Russian republic's radio network was deprived of some frequencies, Yeltsin supporters accelerated plans to create an independent republic TV network.</p>
        <p>Yet salvaging the freedom to criticize, organize and agitate may be the easy half of the liberals' problem. The tougher half is to devise a strategy that enables them to shape the Soviet Union's future. Without it, they may end up cherishing their democratic ideals in isolation.</p>
        <p>The opposition is making progress in three crucial areas. The first concerns the structure of political institutions. The local, republic and national soviets or legislative councils (which gave the system its name) have never had any real power. When opposition candidates were elected to them last year, they acquired little control over anything. Now liberals are insisting that the soviets be junked. In their place, Gavriil Popov, chairman of the Moscow soviet, is pushing for a full overhaul of municipal government along Western lines.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Yeltsin proposes to create a popularly elected presidency of the Russian republic to replace his position as chairman of the republic's soviet. This is not just a gimmick to highlight Mr. Gorbachev's fear of facing the voters. Mr. Yeltsin wants to strengthen elected officials in dealing with the unelected party functionaries still trying to run the country.</p>
        <p>Second, liberals are moving to develop a distinctive approach to the ethnic crisis. They say no formula imposed from the top down will prove workable. To hold the country together means negotiating new political relations from the bottom up. At Mr. Yeltsin's initiative, the presidents of Russia, Kazakhstan, the Ukraine and Byelorussia have signed an economic agreement and are expanding it into a plan for political federation. It is likely to become a potent alternative to Mr. Gorbachev's Union treaty, which Mr. Yeltsin has derided as having no takers.</p>
        <p>Third, the opposition is rethinking its view of Mr. Gorbachev. They see that remaining undecided about the father of perestroika is to play his game of political ambiguity. Liberals risk irrelevance if they wait for him to define himself more clearly.</p>
        <p>The real significance of Mr. Yeltsin's TV attack on Mr. Gorbachev was that it cast him as the defender of the old order. Other important liberals agree that this is the only way they can influence events. Anatoly Sobchak, Leningrad's leader, argues that the vote on March 17 on preserving the Union must be turned into a vote against the Soviet President.</p>
        <p>A single thread runs through the opposition's developing strategy. Liberals who thought the politics of consensus would carry them forward are now learning the politics of polarization.</p>
        <p>The goal of this strategy is no longer to change Mr. Gorbachev's mind. Even those still drawn to the idea of a center-left coalition realize it can be revived only by pressure, not persuasion. In trying to build such pressure, the opposition has its best chance ever to win over reformers who have remained members of the party in the hope that they would be permitted to create within it a minority faction that espouses European-style social democracy. Stanislav Shatalin, author of the now-defunct "500 days" economic reform plan and still a Central Committee member, recently called this hope futile. Anyone trying to organize such a faction, he said, "will be immediately strangled."</p>
        <p>Another disillusioned Gorbachev supporter, Fyodor Burlatsky, chairman of the Soviet Parliament's human rights commission, says that "the revolution of the dilettantes is over." He has not yet decided which side he is on, and may never do so, but he acknowledges that the revolution will not be won by trying to be all things to all people. The emerging line of division in Soviet politics is between those who understand this and those who do not.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
