<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WAR IN THE GULF: The Exiles; Worries Dim Hopes as Kuwaiti Exiles Lose Touch With Resistance</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATROCITIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, JUDITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DD123DF935A15751C0A967958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WAR IN THE GULF: The Exiles; Worries Dim Hopes as Kuwaiti Exiles Lose Touch With Resistance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, JUDITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kuwaitis in exile marked their National Day yesterday with joy over what they see as their country's impending liberation. But there was deepening anxiety over atrocities that they say are taking place there.</p>
        <p>At the same time, conflicting, unverifiable reports of human rights abuses and destruction within the Kuwaiti capital prompted confusion and concern. The sense of foreboding was heightened when several Kuwaiti exile groups said they had lost contact with Kuwaitis opposing the Iraqi occupation in Kuwait City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kuwaitis in exile marked their National Day yesterday with joy over what they see as their country's impending liberation. But there was deepening anxiety over atrocities that they say are taking place there.</p>
        <p>At the same time, conflicting, unverifiable reports of human rights abuses and destruction within the Kuwaiti capital prompted confusion and concern. The sense of foreboding was heightened when several Kuwaiti exile groups said they had lost contact with Kuwaitis opposing the Iraqi occupation in Kuwait City.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for exile groups in Washington and southern France said they had received no direct communication for the past 48 hours from resistance groups that had supplied information from inside the occupied country.</p>
        <p>Kuwaiti exile groups said last night that they were still evaluating the Baghdad radio's announcement of an Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait and would not comment on it at this point.  Abuses Accelerate</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Free Kuwait Campaign, a London-based group, said it received its last message from inside Kuwait, via Saudi Arabia, just after 8 A.M. yesterday.</p>
        <p>"Everybody is happy in Kuwait," said the faxed message. "Everybody is expecting the allies in Kuwait City within coming days." But then the message became choppy, reporting "very very heavy bombardments."</p>
        <p>Kuwaiti exile groups, which vehemently oppose the Iraqi occupation, report that Iraqi soldiers have been killing and torturing hundreds of Kuwaiti men, raping Kuwaiti women and girls and deporting hundreds -- some say thousands -- of Kuwaiti men between the ages of 15 and 45. Such abuses increased, they say, shortly before the allied ground assault began.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for major human rights groups said that such reports were impossible to verify. Some of the claims about what is happening in Kuwait have apparently proved false -- for example, the assertion by Kuwaiti exiles that allied paratroopers had landed in Kuwait City on Sunday. But others are consistent with earlier reports from occupied Kuwait.  Reports Uncomfirmed</p>
        <p>Curt Goering, a spokesman for Amnesty International, the London-based human rights monitor, said that his organization did not have independent confirmation of the latest abuses. But an Amnesty report issued in December, based largely on interviews with Kuwaitis who fled the Iraqi occupation, said Iraqi forces had tortured and killed hundreds of people in Kuwait, sometimes gouging out eyes or cutting off tongues, ears or genitals. In addition, Amnesty said, Iraq had taken several thousand people prisoner and had let 300 premature babies die after stealing their incubators.</p>
        <p>Andrew Whitley, director of Middle East Watch, a independent human rights group based in New York, expressed frustration at the inability to verify reports of atrocities in Kuwait. Mr. Whitley, whose group reported in November that about 1,000 Kuwaitis had been killed and 5,000 people detained under occupation, expressed some skepticism over recent atrocity charges, given that they came mainly from Kuwaiti exile groups and were made soon after the United States bombed an underground installation in Baghdad in an attack that Iraq said caused hundreds of civilian deaths.</p>
        <p>"We have to raise questions about the self-interested nature of the sources and the timing of their announcements," Mr. Whitley said in an interview. "But at the same time, the charges are consistent with previous Iraqi practices inside Kuwait, and I would not be surprised to see that they were true."</p>
        <p>Passengers in the first, 12-car convoy of war refugees from Kuwait who arrived at the Jordanian border yesterday said they saw no evidence of the widescale atrocities alleged by Kuwaiti exile groups and some American officials; they left last Friday, before the start of the allied ground offensive. Ghazi Hijazi, a businessman in the convoy, said: "Iraqi troops are treating people well. They are not bothering them." Discrepancies Cited</p>
        <p>Kuwaiti exile groups dismissed such descriptions, saying they came mostly from Jordanians of Palestinian origin, many of whom have been sympathetic to Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>Discrepancies in estimates of Iraqi abuses in Kuwait -- by Kuwaitis and their supporters and by independent human-rights groups -- have given rise to charges and counter-charges about accuracy and motivation. Iraq has repeatedly denied committing atrocities in Kuwait. But it has also refused to permit journalists or human rights monitors to visit Kuwait to conduct unsupervised interviews and assessments.</p>
        <p>In a reflection of the confusion over reports from Kuwait, exile groups denied a Reuters report from Nice saying that cholera had broken out inside Kuwait City. But groups in London and Washington confirmed reports that five of the emirate's luxurious hotels -- the S.A.S., Hyatt Regency, International, Sheraton, and the Al-Masila -- had been blown up by Iraqi soldiers.</p>
        <p>Hassan al-Ebraheem, president of Citizens for a Free Kuwait, a Kuwaiti exile group in Washington, said that because communications with the resistance had always been sporadic at best, he was hopeful that the men and women fighting inside Kuwait had not been arrested or killed. But a member of the group in France, who spoke on condition that he not be identified, said he feared for the worst, adding that the day the ground war began, Kuwaitis had sent out at least three messages before contact stopped.</p>
        <p>Anxiety among exile groups is growing. "It's difficult to describe what I feel," said Da'ad Abdullah, of the London-based Association for a Free Kuwait. "We know we can rebuild the banks and factories they have destroyed. But how will we rebuild the human beings, those who are still alive but have been so badly scarred?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
