<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WAR IN THE GULF: The Troops; New G.I.'s Shake Off Vietnam Ghost</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY PERSONNEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIFNER, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA123DF935A15751C0A967958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WAR IN THE GULF: The Troops; New G.I.'s Shake Off Vietnam Ghost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIFNER, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>IN IRAQ, Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the 101st Airborne Division flew into battle at dawn on Sunday, the ghost of Vietnam hovered alongside their helicopters.</p>
        <p>Time after time as the air assault division counted out the last days before it attacked deep behind Iraqi lines, senior officers and noncoms who had fought in that flawed conflict brought up Vietnam in conversations as a memory they sought to expunge. For the younger soldiers of the new professional Army, Vietnam was a childhood memory they feared but could barely understand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the 101st Airborne Division flew into battle at dawn on Sunday, the ghost of Vietnam hovered alongside their helicopters.</p>
        <p>Time after time as the air assault division counted out the last days before it attacked deep behind Iraqi lines, senior officers and noncoms who had fought in that flawed conflict brought up Vietnam in conversations as a memory they sought to expunge. For the younger soldiers of the new professional Army, Vietnam was a childhood memory they feared but could barely understand.</p>
        <p>"This is a chance to put the Vietnam stigma behind me," said First Sgt. Don Leftwich, who served as a Marine rifleman in Vietnam. "And my troops will never have to put up with it."</p>
        <p>That war in the jungles of Indochina was one marked by drugs, racial division and infighting among the troops. There was indiscipline, tales of "fragging" -- killing -- disliked officers with hand grenades rolled into their tents. There were also protests at home, political uncertainty, the shame of My Lai and ultimately ignominious withdrawal.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the Persian Gulf war is one where wholesome-looking young men and women treasure sacks full of mail sent to "any soldier" and write back to their correspondents at elementary schools, arbor societies and church groups.  'Ethics, Always' as a Value</p>
        <p>It is also a war in which high-technology firepower stretched in an awesome array across the desert is being unleashed against Saddam Hussein by business-like officers who briskly use words like "lethality" and "violence."</p>
        <p>Maj. Gen. J. H. Binford Peay 3d, the gray-haired, soft-spoken division commander of the 101st, distributes inspirational diagrams to his troops, stressing discipline, leadership and the unit's rich history and lists of values, including "ethics, always."</p>
        <p>"Of course if I did this in Vietnam, particularly my second tour, I would have been laughed out of town," General Peay, a Virginia Military Institute graduate, said with a small smile.</p>
        <p>Among the keys to the differences that will be tested as the new Army goes into battle, officers and soldiers here say, are a more educated, dedicated professional corps of senior sergeants -- the backbone of the Army -- the fact that the troops are volunteers rather than reluctant draftees, and the vocal support they are receiving from home.</p>
        <p>When Charles A. Robinson was a young squad leader in Vietnam, he never even knew the name of his company's first sergeant, let alone saw him.  'We Care for the Soldiers'</p>
        <p>Now the sergeant major of the Second Brigade -- the ranking noncommissioned officer -- he is looked up to as one of the new breed of professional sergeants trained to see to what the Army calls standards.</p>
        <p>"In Vietnam, you never saw the senior sergeants," he said. "That's what will make this war different. We live with the soldiers. We carry out the standards. We care for the soldiers. Simply said, but there's a lot to it."</p>
        <p>Sergeant Major Robinson, who said without embarrassment that he was in the infantry because of "patriotism," spoke of the differences on a dusty afternoon along with three other senior sergeants gathered in the tent. Their Vietnam-era experiences were similar, and all praised the quality of the new soldiers.</p>
        <p>"By and large, these guys are terrific," Sergeant Major Robinson said. "All our guys are high school graduates. They all want to be here to do the job. They're doing what they chose to do, and that is the main difference. Back in '66 in Vietnam, it was a different attitude."</p>
        <p>Lieut. Col. Harlan Lawson, an artillery battery commander who served in Vietnam, said: "The biggest difference is these guys are interested in the big picture. They listen to the radio; they want to discuss politics. I don't hear the griping you'd hear in Vietnam."</p>
        <p>Capt. Scott Ross, of the Flying Tigers Attack Helicopter Battalion assigned to the 101st Airborne, is the son of a military family. "My dad told me stories about Vietnam, how he'd landed in San Francisco and been spit on," he said. "It's always been my fear that the American people wouldn't support us. But now, school kids write us and everything. I'm pen pals with a second-grader from Georgia. Some of their questions are neat."  900 Women in the 101st</p>
        <p>Among the 17,000 soldiers in the 101st Airborne are nearly 900 women, some of whom like First Lieut. Cynthia Dubots will be flying troops into combat on giant Chinook helicopters and evacuating the wounded.</p>
        <p>"I cannot believe I'm here involved in a war," said Lieutenant Dubots, a helicopter platoon commander who earned her commission through R.O.T.C. at Cornell -- where students shunned the program in the 60's and armed black students once took over the Student Union building -- and wears paratrooper and airborne assault qualification badges along with her pilot's wings.</p>
        <p>"I'm scared to death about flying across that border, so is everybody," she said. "We've all talked about it. I know when everybody gets in the cockpit, they're going to have that scared feeling in their gut. But I'm just as qualified as anyone else."</p>
        <p>Tucked away among the 101st "Screaming Eagles" is a field-grade officer who confided only on the strictest of secrecy that he had demonstrated against the Vietnam War at the 1968 Democratic Convention in Chicago.</p>
        <p>"Those were different times," he said. "And I'm a different person."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
