<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bahia Makes Room for A Candomble Pantheon</title>
    <meta content="14REP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEED6113BF937A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bahia Makes Room for A Candomble Pantheon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <dateline>SALVADOR, Brazil</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A CENTURY ago, the African-rooted religion of Candomble was an unspoken secret in Bahia and its capital, Salvador. Today, the former mystery is a matter of public pride, and now it has its own monument. Eight towering statues of orixas, the deities of Candomble, were dedicated in April in the Dique do Tororo, a lake in the center of downtown Salvador.</p>
        <p>The statues, by the sculptor Tatti Moreno, are more than 22 feet tall and weigh 2 tons each. By night, they are illuminated and appear to float above the water in a circle as if they are dancing, around a lighted fountain. They are monuments to Brazil's African heritage, which remains strongest in the state of Bahia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A CENTURY ago, the African-rooted religion of Candomble was an unspoken secret in Bahia and its capital, Salvador. Today, the former mystery is a matter of public pride, and now it has its own monument. Eight towering statues of orixas, the deities of Candomble, were dedicated in April in the Dique do Tororo, a lake in the center of downtown Salvador.</p>
        <p>The statues, by the sculptor Tatti Moreno, are more than 22 feet tall and weigh 2 tons each. By night, they are illuminated and appear to float above the water in a circle as if they are dancing, around a lighted fountain. They are monuments to Brazil's African heritage, which remains strongest in the state of Bahia.</p>
        <p>Candomble is the Brazilian relative of voodoo in Haiti and santeria in the Spanish-speaking Caribbean. The tradition is a New World resurgence of a Yoruba religion that arrived with African slaves. When Salvador, with its superb natural harbor, was Brazil's capital and major trading center under the the Portuguese empire, Brazil was the largest importer of slaves in the Americas. Descendants of those slaves make Bahia the state with Brazil's highest percentage of African-Brazilians.</p>
        <p>The orixas of Candomble are worshiped as powerful, capricious beings, each with its own constellation of attributes. They are associated with natural phenomena, with colors, with occupations and with days of the week. In Candomble ceremonies, drumming and chanting help carry believers into a trance where they are taken over by the spirit of an orixa. The rhythms and the tradition of drumming have filtered into Brazilian popular music.</p>
        <p>Colonial overseers tried to stamp out candomble, which survived, in part, by continuing to worship the African deities in the guise of Christian saints. The Virgin Mary, for instance, is equated with Iemanja, the goddess of the sea, who also wears white; the aged Omolu is matched to Lazarus.</p>
        <p>Earlier this century, the police still raided Candomble ceremonies, and until 1976, candomble celebrants were required to obtain permits from the police vice squad. Yet today, Salvador is estimated to have at least twice as many Candomble houses as it does churches, and it has churches everywhere. In a country that is 90 percent Roman Catholic, many of the faithful attend both Candomble ceremonies and Catholic Mass.</p>
        <p>Candomble believers long ago designated the Dique do Tororo a sacred site for Oxum, the goddess who rules lakes. On a secular level, the lake has lately been reclaimed by the city from years of pollution and neglect. The orixa statues are part of a rehabilitation that includes new plantings and playgrounds around the lake's perimeter.</p>
        <p>From the shore, the orixas look like women in long wigwam-sized skirts; actually, they are male and female deities wearing African robes. It's well worth taking along  binoculars to see them more clearly.</p>
        <p>Made of fiberglass resin over conical iron frames, with elaborately textured robes and crowns painted in their traditional colors, the orixas carry the symbols of their godhood. Xango, the deity of fire, thunder and drums, holds a two-bladed axe, and Ogum, the patron of people who work with their hands, carries a carpenter's saw, hammer and drill. The orixas' faces are black, brown and tan, and their features are African, Indian and European, reflecting the mixture of worshipers that Mr. Moreno sees at Candomble services.</p>
        <p>As a combination of public and religious art, the orixas involved a certain amount of diplomacy. There was a brief controversy when a Protestant evangelical church, which had planned to acquire a building on the lake shore, objected to the prospect of having African deities on its doorstep. Eventually, the church decided to move.</p>
        <p>Now, eight orixas command the lake; four remaining deities in the pantheon, whose attributes prevent them from living on the water, have been built to stand in other sites around Salvador, still to be chosen.</p>
        <p>For the exact arrangement of the orixas in the lake, Mr. Moreno consulted the many Candomble houses nearby, and knowing the lore of the orixas, he was cautious. ''Some of them simply shouldn't be next to each other,'' he said. ''If they are, they will fight.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
