<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Future Shock</title>
    <meta content="14HITTLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DC103BF937A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Future Shock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Hitt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COLD NEW WORLD</p>
        <p>Growing Up in a Harder Country.</p>
        <p>By William Finnegan.</p>
        <p>421 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COLD NEW WORLD</p>
        <p>Growing Up in a Harder Country.</p>
        <p>By William Finnegan.</p>
        <p>421 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $26.</p>
        <p>Mindy, the protagonist of one of the four nonfiction reports in William Finnegan's ''Cold New World,'' is a teen-ager living in a Los Angeles suburb so down on its luck that the abandoned tract houses are routinely used by Hollywood directors when they need to blow up something big. Mindy is looking for an ideology, a set of beliefs, a religion -- something that might make sense of her condition in contemporary America. She settles on Mormonism, Finnegan tells us.</p>
        <p>Then he deploys a narrative tactic that he uses to great effect throughout the book. He drops in a few deadpan sentences that plunge the story into one of the uncommon worlds he explores with the determination of Stanley on his search for Livingstone. ''Actually,'' Finnegan writes, ''before Mindy became a Mormon, she had wanted to become Jewish. But that had turned out to be too much work. Becoming a Mormon was relatively easy. All this was before Mindy got addicted to crystal methamphetamine and became a Nazi, in the ninth grade.''</p>
        <p>Mindy becomes Finnegan's native bearer, as he calls her, leading him to a scary remote crossroads in our bustling economy, Antelope Valley, Calif., where ''widespread white insecurity and downward mobility intersected with significant black and Latino upward mobility.''</p>
        <p>In another story in the book, Finnegan uses the same tactic to introduce a onetime box folder in New Haven named Terry: ''He started fingering a pile of not-yet-folded pizza boxes. 'I love these things,' he said dreamily. 'I got really good at folding boxes at Kevin's Seafood. The better you fold 'em, the more you can do.' At Kevin's, Terry was earning about $50 a week. Then a friend of a friend offered him work that paid $1,000 a week.'' So Terry becomes a drug dealer, and Finnegan's guide to America's crack economy.</p>
        <p>Each part of ''Cold New World'' latches on to small figures caught up in forces larger than they are and far beyond their comprehension. Finnegan describes a high-tech drug assault in a tiny East Texas town, Operation White Tornado, that deployed 200 agents and found only five ounces of cocaine. The raid managed to sweep many financially independent blacks into the pen for long unforgiving stretches, and Finnegan points out that it was supported by some whites who ''simply didn't like the idea of blacks' getting uppity -- a prejudice that 'drugs' covered nicely.''</p>
        <p>Yet another section of the book, and my favorite, concerns the troubles of a Mexican-American tough named Juan. It reads like a novella, and the contradictions at play in this story alone are worth the price of the book. No illiterate street punk, Juan is smart and clever, like his girlfriend, but he lacks her ambition and so breaks up with her. His ethnic pride is so convoluted that he mocks all things Mexican; he claims to loathe the food. Juan is not from a broken home. He has two parents, long married, hard-working, decent to the core. He's in trouble with the local gangs, but it's because he refuses to join one. Lost in his parents' adopted land, he exhausts his talents on fighting and drinking.</p>
        <p>Finnegan's ability to plumb his characters' complexities is due to his documentary style. He settles upon a character and a place, and then he just keeps coming back for more and more visits, sometimes for years. Minor problems arise from such long-term reporting. Terry's story is so old that there is a creakiness to the slang -- as when Terry boasts that he's ''livin' large'' and looking ''dope.'' But Finnegan's hanging-around technique yields riches among the kind of people that most reporters would strenuously avoid. His stories do not concern a trial of the century, a perfect storm or the ascent of a tall mountain. Instead, they are about powerless people left battered and grounded by an economy that may be richly rewarding the educated, but is cruelly punishing many others.</p>
        <p>Finnegan ranges widely in the lives of his subjects. In the case of Mindy, we meet her mom, her friends, several boyfriends, pen pals, her mom's boyfriend and her mom's boyfriend's son. We also meet Mindy's enemies, particularly Heather, the ''Aryan Mother'' who threatens to kill her for befriending Darius, a skinhead of color.</p>
        <p>Professors of journalistic ethics might object, but Finnegan becomes personally involved in the lives of these people without too much hand wringing. In a moment of unintended comedy, he finds himself chauffeuring nine assorted skinheads to a rave in his rental car. After they arrive, a fight breaks out and one of Finnegan's passengers bolts toward the rental, reaches under the seat and retrieves a knife. Finnegan later lectures the boy, expressing his anger that he and his car were used to transport weapons.</p>
        <p>The cumulative effect is to create an unusual kind of sympathy for the characters he describes. It's not the stereotypical liberal sense of pity. Rather, Finnegan convincingly connects the wayward events in these people's lives to the messages and forces they detect around them -- whether from a fractured home, a school tracking system that subtly winnows out the losers from the gifted or just the plain despair inherent in what Finnegan calls our national religion of ''liberal consumerism.''</p>
        <p>We see how and why these people make their wretched choices and the seeming inevitability of it all: it's not that their dreams reach beyond the grasp of their capabilities, it's that they don't dream at all. The pipelines of opportunity leading out of the lower end of our economy are being shut off, Finnegan says. He offers statistics revealing that per-pupil spending in California's once-celebrated educational system -- seventh in the nation in the mid-1960's -- has plummeted in three decades to 47th. Fairly half the state's 2,150 public libraries were closed in that time. Given recent tuition hikes and enrollment cuts, and the cancellation of affirmative action programs, the state's colleges and universities have evolved into economic aeries for the privileged children of the upper-middle-class taxpayer. Since 1970, Finnegan reports, the poverty rate in California among children doubled while ''poverty among the state's elderly was nearly wiped out.'' And California is just leading the way for the nation. ''It is clearly no coincidence,'' he continues, ''that the 1996 budget of the Children's Defense Fund, the leading national lobby for children's interests, was $15 million while the equivalent lobby for the elderly, the American Association of Retired Persons, in the same year spent $449 million.''</p>
        <p>Although the four sections of Finnegan's book are seemingly unrelated, there is a larger structure at work here. The first account, about Terry's drug dealing, really concerns a cunning youth making an end run around the limits he senses blocking him. His story is not nearly as unsettling as Juan's, with his mysterious absence of faith in his own talent and future -- mysterious in that it appears to have no origin and no end.</p>
        <p>But by the time you get to the last story -- to Mindy and the dark lives of skinheads, boneheads, heshers, punks, Goths and tweakers -- the future has turned truly bleak and frightening. Theirs is a world where the only input comes from Jerry Springer, crude comic books and word of mouth. They are practically medieval in the way that they let the forces of superstition and rumor guide the day-to-day events of their lives. They spend their afternoons spinning out increasingly more paranoid racial theories to explain their own economic imprisonment.</p>
        <p>Glimpsing Mindy's world actually makes the reader yearn for the comfort of Terry's rational, if corrupt, decision to become a crack dealer. His motives belong to the familiar sphere of liberal consumerism. He can be reasoned with, possibly persuaded to take some other work. After all, he's just trying to make a living.  Jack Hitt is a writer at large for GQ magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jack Hitt is a writer at large for GQ magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
