<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 MacArthur Fellows Are Adding Value to the World of Money</title>
    <meta content="MITCHELL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="EARNING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DA163DF937A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 MacArthur Fellows Are Adding Value to the World of Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY year since 1981, it has been a cross between a Pulitzer and a lottery: the fellowship program of the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, which awards sizable, no-strings-attached grants to a diverse group of creative thinkers.</p>
        <p>To choose recipients, the foundation uses a confidential group of nominators and a selection committee. Earlier this month, the foundation announced 29 such fellows -- distributing grants, to be paid over five years, that ranged from $220,000 to $375,000, depending on the recipient's age.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY year since 1981, it has been a cross between a Pulitzer and a lottery: the fellowship program of the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, which awards sizable, no-strings-attached grants to a diverse group of creative thinkers.</p>
        <p>To choose recipients, the foundation uses a confidential group of nominators and a selection committee. Earlier this month, the foundation announced 29 such fellows -- distributing grants, to be paid over five years, that ranged from $220,000 to $375,000, depending on the recipient's age.</p>
        <p>Among the winners were three whose work involves innovative perspectives on money matters: a rancher who has taken steps to preserve his Southwestern way of life; a geographer who studies how labor and political issues help mold a cultural landscape, and an economist who aims to apply the ideals of feminism and the left to calculations of productivity.</p>
        <p>Don Mitchell  'People's Geography Of the United States'</p>
        <p>''Mansfield Park,'' by Jane Austen, contains a passage of special significance to Don Mitchell, 36, a cultural geographer at Syracuse University who has just won a $235,000 grant for his work on how human activity influences the natural landscape.</p>
        <p>In the book, when Mr. Rushworth vows to improve his home at Southerton Court but wonders who will help, Miss Bertram chimes in: ''Your best friend upon such an occasion would be Mr. Repton, I imagine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Repton was Humphrey Repton, a famous English landscape gardener who lived at the turn of the 18th century and laid out the gardens and parks surrounding many great country houses.</p>
        <p>''Repton is a fascinating figure who illustrates how human aesthetic sense and wealth can be part of the process of constructing the space we live in,'' Mr. Mitchell said last week in a phone conversation from Scotland where he was visiting the parents of his wife, Susan Millar, who is also a geography professor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell's specialty is the influence of political conflict on the landscape. In ''The Lie of the Land: Migrant Workers and the Californian Landscape'' (University of Minnesota Press, 1996), he explored how the endless struggles between big farming interests and migrant workers shaped the state's agricultural landscape.</p>
        <p>''The way the land looks today is the result of these debates and arguments,'' he said in the phone interview.</p>
        <p>As an example, he pointed to the labor camps built for migrant workers in California's central valley after the strikes of 1933 and 1934 because authorities feared a social explosion if the farmers failed to improve conditions for their help. ''You only find decent living and washing facilities where the workers were militant,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As other examples of the way social or political conflicts can shape a landscape, Mr. Mitchell cites Tompkins Square Park in Manhattan's East Village and the People's Park near the campus of the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Both parks, he said, are products of long political battles among various interests, including city and university bureaucrats, local residents, environmentalists and advocates of the rights of homeless people.</p>
        <p>In New York, a result has been a space that now serves the needs of local residents, while in Berkeley the university constructed a park where it had originally planned to build dormitories.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell, born in Walnut Creek, Calif., came to Syracuse University in 1997 from the University of Colorado in Boulder, where he had taught since gaining a doctorate in geography from Rutgers University in 1992.</p>
        <p>He said he had no firm idea yet how he would spend his award: ''I'm not an entrepreneur. I like teaching.''</p>
        <p>But he would like to assemble a team of geographers and historians to write what he calls ''a people's geography of the United States,'' which would chart the development of Americans' ''social relationship with their landscape.''</p>
        <p>PAUL LEWIS</p>
        <p>EARNING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
