<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vintage Musicals in Revival</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="110799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW AMSTERDAM THEATER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERN, JEROME</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HASSENFELD, MARJORIE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DC103EF93AA25752C0A96E948260" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vintage Musicals in Revival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When a 29-piece orchestra strikes up the overture to Jerome Kern's 1920 show ''Sally'' tomorrow evening at the Academy Theater, the sound of music will herald the revitalization of the New Amsterdam Theater Company, the only theater organization in New York devoted full time to the concert restoration of vintage</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When a 29-piece orchestra strikes up the overture to Jerome Kern's 1920 show ''Sally'' tomorrow evening at the Academy Theater, the sound of music will herald the revitalization of the New Amsterdam Theater Company, the only theater organization in New York devoted full time to the concert restoration of vintage</p>
        <p>When a 29-piece orchestra strikes up the overture to Jerome Kern's 1920 show ''Sally'' tomorrow evening at the Academy Theater, the sound of music will herald the revitalization of the New Amsterdam Theater Company, the only theater organization in New York devoted full time to the concert restoration of vintage American musicals.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the company's future seemed anything but rosy. Last January, Bill Tynes, the New Amsterdam's visionary young founder and director, died of AIDS at age 30. His illness had already forced the company to cancel the third and final production of its 1986 season, a revival of the 1934 Howard Dietz-Arthur Schwartz show ''Revenge With Music,'' and the New Amsterdam's 1987 season was called off.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1981 at a benefit cocktail party in the Algonquin Hotel, the New Amsterdam company had presented concert restorations of shows ranging from Victor Herbert's 1912 operetta ''Sweethearts'' to ''Jubilee,'' the 1935 saucy satire of cafe society by Cole Porter and Moss Hart. In five years, the subscription list for the company's Town Hall concerts expanded from 250 to more than 1,500. Each restoration has featured well-known Broadway performers singing classic scores accompanied by a full orchestra, with the librettos trimmed and delivered as staged readings.</p>
        <p>What finally enabled the company to survive was a combination of the generosity of key members of the board, the patience of subscribers and the dedication of Marjorie E. Hassenfeld, who succeeded Mr. Tynes as the company's executive director. Helped By Fund-Raising Event</p>
        <p>''Last January, it looked like we were at the point of closing down,'' Ms. Hassenfeld recalled in an interview last week. ''But through the generosity of board members like Richard C. Norton and Dina Merrill and an emergency grant from the Lamb's Foundation, we were able to mount a fund-raising gala at Alice Tully Hall last May.''</p>
        <p>The gala, in which more than 15 stars, among them Laurie Beechman, Kitty Carlisle Hart, Judy Kaye and Dina Merrill donated their talents to an evening of highlights from future New Amsterdam productions, helped to erase the company's $22,000 deficit. More important, it reassured nervous subscribers that the New Amsterdam was alive and kicking. And for its new season its subscription list has grown to 2,000 and its annual operating budget to $400,000, double that of two years ago.</p>
        <p>''Replacing Bill is not an easy task, since he had so many different talents,'' said Ms. Hassenfeld, who joined the New Amsterdam nearly three years ago as its producing director after having worked for 15 years on and Off Broadway as a stage manager. Under her guidance, the New Amsterdam has moved its shows from Town Hall to the more intimate 1,138-seat Academy Theater, further west on 43d Street, between Broadway and Eighth Avenue. Formerly the New Apollo, the theater had been dark for some eight years until last fall, when the comedian Redd Foxx appeared there briefly. In its agreement with the Academy Theater management, the New Amsterdam is operating at a special nonprofit rate that is considerably less expensive than its Town Hall arrangement.</p>
        <p>''The Academy is much more like a real residence for us,'' Ms. Hassenfeld said. ''For every show, we'll have access to the theater both day and night, during the entire week around its run. And the theater allows us more flexibility to experiment with increasing production values.''</p>
        <p>One of the high points of ''Sally'' is a ballet with music by Victor Herbert that has been fully staged for this revival. Rodgers, Hart and Gershwin</p>
        <p>''Sally'' is the first of three shows to be presented by the New Amsterdam this season. Scheduled for March is ''I'd Rather Be Right,'' the Rodgers and Hart show about President Franklin D. Roosevelt, with a book by George S. Kaufman and Moss Hart. In May, the 1926 Gershwin show ''Oh, Kay!'' will arrive. Instead of two or three performances as in past years, all three shows will have five.</p>
        <p>''Sally,'' with a run of 570 performances starting in 1920, was the longest running Kern musical before ''Show Boat.'' Produced by Florenz Ziegfeld Jr., it is an elaborate Cinderella story about a dishwasher who is invited by a disguised exiled European peer to impersonate a famous ballerina at a fancy-dress ball. The most famous song in the show, which was originally a vehicle for Marilyn Miller, is ''Look for the Silver Lining.'' In this concert revival, directed by James Brennan, the leads are played by Christina Saffran and Don Correia. There will be five performances -tomorrow, Friday, Saturday and Sunday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2.</p>
        <p>Having a base that is more stable and flexible than Town Hall means more possibilities for the New Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>''I would like to begin to create different types of seasons,'' Ms. Hassenfeld said. ''Bill chose most of the material from the 20's and 30's because he loved period operettas so much. I would like to expand a little bit. We're looking into the possibility of a Harold Arlen season and have also talked with the Kurt Weill Foundation about ''Lady in the Dark,'' which is currently being restored. I'd also like to find a way to record these shows properly, perhaps in live concert form. We're also slowly developing a stable core ensemble of performers and musicians. Perhaps one day we'll become a real resident company with a full fall-through-spring concert season.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
