<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING ON A COAST PAYS OFF, U.S. SAYS</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="173217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA1031F932A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING ON A COAST PAYS OFF, U.S. SAYS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Regional disparities in personal incomes widened in 1987, as residents of coastal states continued to earn more than residents in most other areas, the Government reports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Regional disparities in personal incomes widened in 1987, as residents of coastal states continued to earn more than residents in most other areas, the Government reports.</p>
        <p>Regional disparities in personal incomes widened in 1987, as residents of coastal states continued to earn more than residents in most other areas, the Government reports.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department said Thursday that all 10 of the states with the highest average personal incomes last year were on the nation's coasts. Eight of them are along the Atlantic. The others are Alaska and California.</p>
        <p>Connecticut ranked No. 1, with residents earning $21,266 for every adult and child last year, an increase of 8.8 percent over 1986.</p>
        <p>For the nation as a whole, incomes rose 6 percent to an average of $15,481 last year, the best overall increase since a similar 6 percent gain in 1985. Incomes rose 5.1 percent in 1986. Seven of the 10 states with the lowest incomes were in the South. Mississippi was last with a per capita income of $10,292, an increase of 6.5 percent over the previous year. Figures Put to Political Use</p>
        <p>The new figures, revised from a report issued four months ago, confirmed other studies that have shown wide geographic differences in how the country has responded to the current economic expansion.</p>
        <p>While Republicans hoping to hold onto the White House are emphasizing the peacetime economic expansion, Democrats have charged that President Reagan's economic policies have turned the United States into a ''bicoastal economy'' at the expense of a midsection facing hard times in agriculture, oil and declining smokestack industries.</p>
        <p>In contrast with most recovery periods, regional differences have widened rather than narrowed, the report said.</p>
        <p>The Southwest and Rocky Mountain regions were farther behind the average national income in 1987 than they were in 1982 at the depths of the recession, while New England and the Mid-Atlantic regions were farther ahead. 'Unusual Economic Expansion'</p>
        <p>This was the first recovery period since 1958-1960 in which regional disparities have widened instead of narrowed, said Rudolph DePass, a Commerce Department analyst.</p>
        <p>''This has been a somewhat unusual economic expansion,'' he said. ''Regions like New England have benefited from rapid growth in high-tech industries and relatively slow increases in population, while the Southwest and Rocky Mountain states have been hit by a slump in the oil industry.''</p>
        <p>New England was the top-earning region in 1982, with incomes 9 percent above the national average. By 1987, it had increased its lead with incomes now 20 percent above the national average. The Mid-Atlantic region, which had incomes 10 percent above the national average in 1982, had incomes 14 percent higher last year.</p>
        <p>By contrast, incomes in the Southwest and Rocky Mountain regions fell to 12 percent below the national average in 1987, as against 4 percent or less in 1982. Southeast Last in Income</p>
        <p>This drop put these two regions close to the Southeast, which still came in last with incomes 13 percent below the national average. The Southeast was 14 percent below in 1982.</p>
        <p>The Great Lakes region was unchanged, with incomes still 2 percent below the national average in 1987. The West had incomes 11 percent higher than the national average last year, as against 12 percent higher in 1982.</p>
        <p>The report released Thursday was based on revised figures that showed incomes overall grew at a stronger pace than estimated when the original report was released in April. At that time, the Government said national per capita incomes rose 4.8 percent, barely ahead of the 4.4 percent rise in consumer prices last year.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mississippi, states with the lowest incomes were West Virginia, with an average of $11,020; followed by Utah, Louisiana, Arkansas, Idaho, New Mexico, Alabama, South Carolina and Kentucky.  THE RICHEST STATES  Per capita income in each state in 1987 and the percent change from 1986.</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Conn.</p>
        <p>$21,266</p>
        <p>+8.8%</p>
        <p>N.J.</p>
        <p>20,352</p>
        <p>+8.3</p>
        <p>Mass.</p>
        <p>19,142</p>
        <p>+8.5</p>
        <p>Alaska</p>
        <p>18,230</p>
        <p>-0.8</p>
        <p>Md.</p>
        <p>18,124</p>
        <p>+7.0</p>
        <p>N.Y.</p>
        <p>18,004</p>
        <p>+7.0</p>
        <p>Calif.</p>
        <p>17,821</p>
        <p>+6.1</p>
        <p>N.H.</p>
        <p>17,529</p>
        <p>+6.9</p>
        <p>Del.</p>
        <p>16,696</p>
        <p>+7.7</p>
        <p>Va.</p>
        <p>16,517</p>
        <p>+7.1</p>
        <p>Source: Associated Press</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
