<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At WNYC, Independence Has Its Price</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVATIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNYC FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNYC (RADIO STATION)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DB1039F936A35754C0A960958260" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At WNYC, Independence Has Its Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL things considered, the two WNYC radio stations got off to a fine start flying solo this week, their first days of independence from their old master, the New York City government.</p>
        <p>Of course, one could always debate who had been liberated from whom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL things considered, the two WNYC radio stations got off to a fine start flying solo this week, their first days of independence from their old master, the New York City government.</p>
        <p>Of course, one could always debate who had been liberated from whom.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration was more than delighted to unload New York's leading public-radio outlet, which until July 1 had been municipal property for  74 years. By selling the AM and FM stations for $20 million to the nonprofit WNYC Foundation, the ever-broke city picked up spare change and the Mayor followed through on his belief that democracies should not be broadcasters, a conviction that, while honestly come by, seemed to confuse WNYC with Radio Havana.</p>
        <p>Well, people at the stations said yesterday, the feeling is mutual: It's good to be rid of the municipal yoke.</p>
        <p>On the Fourth of July, the talk in the radio booth was of independence, WNYC's as well as the country's, whose birthday was observed with listeners invited by Brian Lehrer, the host of a public affairs program, to call in with suggestions for amending the Constitution. (Don't worry. None of the ideas are likely to be enacted soon.)</p>
        <p>In trumpeting their independence, the broadcasters bore mental scars from days when mayors could not resist occasionally seizing the microphones for their own agendas, a droit du seigneur considered intrusive regardless of who exercised it. It made no difference whether it was Edward I. Koch insisting that men arrested for patronizing prostitutes be pilloried in the "John Hour" or Rudolph W. Giuliani suggesting that air time be given to the noted philosopher Curtis Sliwa.</p>
        <p>RICHARD HINCHLIFFE, the director of WNYC's news operation, recalled that when he started at the station in 1985, "there were commissioners who felt they could just waltz up here and go on the air -- and some of them did." That sort of imposition has not been a problem in recent years, he added. But Laura Sydell, one of his three reporters, said the complete break from City Hall should make things only better.</p>
        <p>"If you know that the City of New York is your boss, there may unconsciously  be some sort of self-censorship," she said. "I breathe a sigh of relief now that that dark cloud is no longer hanging over us."</p>
        <p>But one person's cloud is another's relief from a pounding sun. Editorial freedom may also mean the freedom to starve to death by degrees, for the stations must rattle the cup harder than ever among their corporate sponsors and 800,000 listeners to climb out of a new multimillion-dollar hole.</p>
        <p>"It's a staggering set of challenges," Peter H. Darrow, the WNYC Foundation chairman, said. "When you're part of the city, there's a safety net there. When  you can't pay a bill, well, the city will pay it for you. That's not there for us now."</p>
        <p>Gone is an annual city subsidy of $1 million to help cover the $8 million radio budget. Gone is an additional $500,000 worth of free services like city-paid mail delivery. Gone are profits from WNYC-TV, which died this week and was reincarnated as WBIS+, a channel created by ITT Corporation and Dow Jones &amp;  Company and operating on a license bought from the city for $207 million.</p>
        <p>On top of all that, the foundation has a new expense. It must come up with $3.3 million in each of the next six years to pay the $20 million purchase price.</p>
        <p>IN many respects, it was a bargain sale. Some in fact have criticized Mr. Giuliani for not offering the stations to commercial interests, saying he could  have got twice as much that way. Instead, the Mayor kept the price down, and allowed the radio studios to stay in the Municipal Building rent-free for now. That made it easier for WNYC to continue as a public-broadcast operation providing a blend of classical music and news analysis -- no small contribution in this shock-jock age, when many think that 22 hyperthyroidic minutes of bulletins and traffic reports truly gives them the world.</p>
        <p>So for believers in quality broadcasting, a lot rides on the question of whether WNYC can make it on its own. Probably it can. Its listeners tend to be more affluent than most and its high-powered board of directors knows how to shake corporate money trees. It already has pledges of $7 million toward the $20 million purchase.</p>
        <p>But the lesson of independence, one that goes at least as far back as 1776, is that nothing is guaranteed. "This independence is a long-term blessing but a  short-term curse," said Laura Walker, the WNYC president. "Getting through the next few years is going to be tough."</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
