<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holding Action in Hanoi</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIETNAM</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIETNAM</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0DC1039F936A35754C0A960958260" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holding Action in Hanoi</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vietnam's Communist Party ducked all the hard questions about its country's future this week. Instead of dealing with an aging leadership and the tensions produced by the development of a market economy in an authoritarian state, the Communists did some tinkering and left the difficult decisions for another day.</p>
        <p>Top party and government leaders, though already well into their 70's, had their terms extended by the Party Congress. The debate between reformers who advocate further economic liberalization and conservatives who fear that will undermine party political control produced an unsatisfying and untenable commitment to more reforms and tightened controls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vietnam's Communist Party ducked all the hard questions about its country's future this week. Instead of dealing with an aging leadership and the tensions produced by the development of a market economy in an authoritarian state, the Communists did some tinkering and left the difficult decisions for another day.</p>
        <p>Top party and government leaders, though already well into their 70's, had their terms extended by the Party Congress. The debate between reformers who advocate further economic liberalization and conservatives who fear that will undermine party political control produced an unsatisfying and untenable commitment to more reforms and tightened controls.</p>
        <p>These nondecisions may have helped preserve internal party unity. Prime Minister Vo Van Kiet, 73, is a southerner and a strong advocate of reform. The Communist Party General Secretary, Do Muoi, 79, is a moderate, and President Le  Duc Anh, 75, is a retired general and a voice for party and military traditionalists. But a prolonged failure to resolve policy and succession issues could prove costly to Vietnam's long-term economic prospects.</p>
        <p>Just a year ago, Vietnam was among the hottest of emerging markets for American and other foreign investors. A decade of accelerating economic reforms  had unleashed the energies of some 75 million people located at the heart of the booming Southeast Asian region. President Clinton had normalized diplomatic relations between Washington and Hanoi. Growth rates were high and government officials seemed eager to recruit new foreign investors, especially Americans.</p>
        <p>Many of those positive factors remain, but there has been some disenchantment. Newly arriving investors have encountered frustrating licensing  restrictions, uncooperative local joint-venture partners, politically motivated  campaigns against foreign advertising, occasional instances of police harassment and widespread corruption.</p>
        <p>Some of the difficulties are caused by greed. But others reflect the continuing tug-of-war between reformers and more restrictive elements of the Vietnamese regime. Foreign capital in Southeast Asia is highly mobile. Vietnam's so far impressive ability to attract and hold on to capital depends on its ability to address these problems swiftly and satisfactorily.</p>
        <p>Instead the Party Congress emphasized unity over clarity. Unity has always been something of an obsession among Vietnamese Communists and has probably helped them survive into a post-Communist era. Nurturing the current economic boom will require something more. The issues avoided this week cannot be put off much longer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
