<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Middle-Aged Romance Amid Dreaming Spires</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="596455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TNT (CABLE NETWORK)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FOREIGN AFFAIRS (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA163CF934A25750C0A965958260" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Middle-Aged Romance Amid Dreaming Spires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every few months on television, there comes along a movie that is usually described as the kind of movie not being made anymore. A good example is "Foreign Affairs," to be shown tonight at 8, 10 and midnight on TNT. The list of those likely to enjoy this film begins with Anglophiles, hopeless romantics and those who never again want to watch Michael Douglas playing a psychopath.</p>
        <p>Adapted by Chris Bryant from an Alison Lurie novel, "Foreign Affairs" is directed by Jim O'Brien, a Briton best known here for overseeing half the 16 hours of "The Jewel in the Crown." That mini-series was about the English colonialists in India. This movie is about three Americans in England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every few months on television, there comes along a movie that is usually described as the kind of movie not being made anymore. A good example is "Foreign Affairs," to be shown tonight at 8, 10 and midnight on TNT. The list of those likely to enjoy this film begins with Anglophiles, hopeless romantics and those who never again want to watch Michael Douglas playing a psychopath.</p>
        <p>Adapted by Chris Bryant from an Alison Lurie novel, "Foreign Affairs" is directed by Jim O'Brien, a Briton best known here for overseeing half the 16 hours of "The Jewel in the Crown." That mini-series was about the English colonialists in India. This movie is about three Americans in England.</p>
        <p>Vinnie Miner, played by Joanne Woodward, is a prim, fussy New England college teacher going on a research sabbatical and glad to have along as a companion a young colleague, Fred Turner (Eric Stoltz), who's working on his own academic project. On the crowded flight to London, Vinnie, smartly prepared with a proper book and her own plastic containers of nutritionally correct food, finds herself sitting next to a huge hulk of a man named Chuck Mumpson, a sewage engineer, portrayed by Brian Dennehy. He is from Oklahoma and is setting out to trace his ancestral roots in England. Chuck is uninhibitedly gruff. Vinnie is horrified.</p>
        <p>A tourist map isn't needed to figure out where "Foreign Affairs" is headed. There are a couple of detours, most notably Fred's passionate affair with an older woman, a flamboyant actress whom Stephanie Beacham ("The Colbys") embodies with a vengeance. And the always wily Ian Richardson ("House of Cards"), looking more than ever like a reincarnation of Wilfred Hyde-White, is on hand as Edwin, Vinnie's very wealthy and very gay old friend, given to saying things like, "Call me when you get in, and I'll put something naughty on the video." When detecting nothing available for himself, Edwin isn't beyond playing Cupid.</p>
        <p>But this movie is mostly about divorced Vinnie and about-to-be-divorced Chuck, totally mismatched and clearly fated for each other. Here we have a middle-aged romance, not one of Hollywood's favorite situations. More important, here we have two middle-aged actors confidently demonstrating how gifted they are. Ms. Woodward can shift Vinnie from mean to compassionate with a single, momentary glance. Mr. Dennehy takes Chuck from brash to shattered in the course of sinking into an easy chair. We are, obviously, in the midst of professional grace.</p>
        <p>With a bit of luck, and vision, "Foreign Affairs" could turn out to a harbinger of the kinds of movies finally being made again.  Foreign Affairs  TNT, tonight at 8; repeated at 10 and midnight. Directed by Jim O'Brien; written by Chris Bryant, based on the novel by Alison Lurie; director of photography, Michael Coulter; editor, Susan B. Browdy; costumes by Amy Roberts; music by Cynthia Millar; production designer, Stuart Walker; produced by Patricia Clifford for Turner Network Television; Ted Field and Jeffrey Taylor, executive producers. Vinnie Miner . . . Joanne Woodward Chuck Mumpson . . . Brian Dennehy Fred Turner . . . Eric Stoltz Rosemary Radley . . . Stephanie Beacham Edwin . . . Ian Richardson David Hewson . . . Robert Hands</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
