<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Loss Can't Dampen Nets' Success</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="596477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PORTLAND TRAIL BLAZERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Portland Trail Blazers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D9173FF934A25750C0A965958260" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Loss Can't Dampen Nets' Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore., March 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once, the Nets might have been satisfied with splitting their four-game trip against Pacific Division teams. But not now, not after going 3-1 and solidifying the idea that they are one of the top teams in the National Basketball Association. These Nets won't be able to surprise teams anymore.</p>
        <p>They believe in themselves, but do many people believe in them? Other teams do, as the league's elite now talk about New Jersey with respect. The only nonbelievers seem to be Nets fans -- or lack of them -- because Byrne Meadowlands Arena still often resembles a tomb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once, the Nets might have been satisfied with splitting their four-game trip against Pacific Division teams. But not now, not after going 3-1 and solidifying the idea that they are one of the top teams in the National Basketball Association. These Nets won't be able to surprise teams anymore.</p>
        <p>They believe in themselves, but do many people believe in them? Other teams do, as the league's elite now talk about New Jersey with respect. The only nonbelievers seem to be Nets fans -- or lack of them -- because Byrne Meadowlands Arena still often resembles a tomb.</p>
        <p>Maybe this successful trip will change that. The Nets beat the Los Angeles Clippers and Golden State, and their centerpiece victory was a 31-point thrashing of the Phoenix Suns, the league's best team.</p>
        <p>The only stumbling block was a 110-94 loss to the Portland Trail Blazers on Monday night. The Nets were simply overwhelmed during an intense Portland spurt late in the second half, when the Trail Blazers did something not many teams can do: overpower New Jersey on the boards.</p>
        <p>Portland spent the middle of the game struggling, and it looked as if New Jersey might sneak away with yet another victory. It led, 61-52, with 8 minutes 14 seconds left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Then Portland Coach Rick Adelman put Jerome Kersey in for Kevin Duckworth, and Cliff Robinson in for Tracy Murray. Portland woke up and took control of the boards and the game.</p>
        <p>Kersey, who has spent a lot of time recently on the bench, finished with a season-high 13 rebounds, and was a big reason the Trail Blazers scored 9 straight points to tie the score and eventually went on a 24-9 bombardment over the last eight minutes.</p>
        <p>Rebounding and defense -- two things Coach Chuck Daly says can make or break a team -- were the Nets' problems on Monday. Portland dominated the Nets -- the league's top rebounding team -- with a 53-40 advantage on the boards.</p>
        <p>"I can't say enough about the group that came in when we were 9 down," said Adelman. "Jerome was just incredible. He just picked up everything and then Cliff came in, and that group got very active defensively. That's what turned it around."  27 Minutes for Kersey</p>
        <p>Kersey played 27 minutes, tying the most he has played since being benched on Feb. 26.</p>
        <p>"This is the first game I've had extended minutes since I stopped starting," Kersey said. "It's been a long time. In my mind, I'm still searching for exactly what I can do, but I've tried to play hard and hustle. I think the way I played this game is what they want the bench players to do."</p>
        <p>It was a tough loss for the Nets, but over all they aren't complaining. Few observers expected them to lose just one game on the trip. And now many look at the thrashing of Phoenix and the recent consistent play, and have even bigger expectations for the Nets.</p>
        <p>"We've improved, but we still have room for more improvement," said Brendan Suhr, a Nets assistant. "We told them if we're going to go anywhere in the playoffs, they had to raise their level of defense. If you really become good defensively that is your offense."  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
