<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Districts Assailed on Travel Expenses</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="668106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCHOOL ADMINISTRATION AND COMMUNITY ROLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOARD OF EDUCATION (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D91238F932A25751C0A962958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Districts Assailed on Travel Expenses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New York City Council panel yesterday accused local school districts of excessive spending on meals, conferences and out-of-town travel for school board members in such vacation resorts as Las Vegas, Honolulu and St. Thomas. In some cases, the report said, the meals and trips came while money for classes was being cut.</p>
        <p>But officials of the central Board of Education and the president of one board that was criticized disputed some findings in the report, which was released yesterday by the Council's Finance Committee. They said the Council had misinterpreted budget records.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A New York City Council panel yesterday accused local school districts of excessive spending on meals, conferences and out-of-town travel for school board members in such vacation resorts as Las Vegas, Honolulu and St. Thomas. In some cases, the report said, the meals and trips came while money for classes was being cut.</p>
        <p>But officials of the central Board of Education and the president of one board that was criticized disputed some findings in the report, which was released yesterday by the Council's Finance Committee. They said the Council had misinterpreted budget records.</p>
        <p>The school officials said that some of the retreats and trips were paid for through state and Federal funds earmarked for teaching conferences. They also said that many conventions mentioned in the report were attended not by school board members, but by teachers and administrators. The total spent by board members is much less, officials said, though they said it was impossible to provide the figures yesterday.</p>
        <p>"It's a little misleading," said a spokesman for the central board, Robert Terte. "The money listed as being spent for travel is not solely by board members." Vacation Paradises</p>
        <p>Even so, the report painted a picture of board members from some of the city's poorest districts traveling on tax-financed trips to vacation paradises to attend conventions, while money was being taken from the operating budget for classes and used for administration. The report was released at a raucous City Hall hearing yesterday, in which Council members yelled at each other and at school officials.</p>
        <p>Local school districts spent about $2.2 million on travel, conferences and meals for officials and board members in the fiscal year that ended June 30. That was a 36 percent increase over the previous year, despite cuts in the education budget, according to the study. Its findings were reported in Newsday yesterday.</p>
        <p>The poorest districts in the Bronx and Upper Manhattan spent the most on out-of-town conferences. District 7 -- which includes Mott Haven, Port Morris and parts of Melrose in the South Bronx -- led the city's 32 districts in spending for travel and meals, with expenses of $323,536, the report said.</p>
        <p>Included in that total were at least 16 out-of-town conferences attended by local board members in places like Las Vegas, Nev.; Puerto Rico; Orlando, Fla., Honolulu and St. Thomas in the Virgin Islands. In each trip, all expenses were paid for two board members and several staff members. At the same time, the district borrowed $35,000 from its classroom budget to cover administrative costs, and its 15,000 students were using outdated textbooks, the report said. 'Unequivocally Excessive'</p>
        <p>"That's excessive," said the Finance Committee Chairman, Herbert E. Berman, who commissioned the report. "That's absolutely, unequivocally excessive."</p>
        <p>The Superintendent of District 7, Pedro Crespo, did not return telephone calls left at his office yesterday. Neither did his two deputies, Joliana Kokason and Richard Topps. None of the nine members of the District 7 board could be reached.</p>
        <p>The next highest amount spent on travel was reported in District 6 in Washington Heights, which totaled $213,000, including $10,329 at the Harrison, N.Y., Conference Center. The report also criticized as excessive the travel expenses of three other Bronx districts: $144,000 in District 8, $132,000 in District 9 and $134,000 in District 10.</p>
        <p>The president of the District 6 board, Robert Jackson, defended the board's spending. In testy exchanges with Mr. Berman, Mr. Jackson said his board members had spent only $206 on travel in the last fiscal year, and that most of the $213,000 listed in the report had been for training teachers and administrators, which he said the district preferred to do in New Jersey or upstate New York because lodging was cheaper there than in Manhattan. He also said that much of the travel budget came from state and Federal grants for that purpose, not from local taxes.</p>
        <p>"I was livid when I saw the report," he said.</p>
        <p>Responding to the study, the Schools Chancellor, Ramon C. Cortines, is considering putting a cap on travel expenses and requiring local boards to vote on such trips in public sessions and to report what happened on the trips at public hearings, his spokesman, Mr. Terte, said. The Chancellor is also looking into limiting the total a local board can take from instructional budget for administration, Mr. Terte said.</p>
        <p>"He's concerned about the appearance that money is being spent for travel which might be better spent in the classroom," Mr. Terte said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
