<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tar Heels Fight Off Maryland's Challenge</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="668124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1D81238F932A25751C0A962958260" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tar Heels Fight Off Maryland's Challenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>North Carolina 95, Maryland 89</p>
        <p>Derrick Phelps scored 9 of his 21 points in the final 2 minutes 12 seconds last night as No. 1 North Carolina held off a furious second-half rally by Maryland for a 95-89 victory in Chapel Hill, N.C.</p>
        <p>The triumph gave the Tar Heels 20 victories for the 24th straight season and moved Carolina (20-3, 8-2 in the Atlantic Coast Conference) back into a first-place tie with No. 2 Duke. It also gave Dean Smith 27 20-victory seasons in his 33 years as coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>North Carolina 95, Maryland 89</p>
        <p>Derrick Phelps scored 9 of his 21 points in the final 2 minutes 12 seconds last night as No. 1 North Carolina held off a furious second-half rally by Maryland for a 95-89 victory in Chapel Hill, N.C.</p>
        <p>The triumph gave the Tar Heels 20 victories for the 24th straight season and moved Carolina (20-3, 8-2 in the Atlantic Coast Conference) back into a first-place tie with No. 2 Duke. It also gave Dean Smith 27 20-victory seasons in his 33 years as coach.</p>
        <p>Maryland (12-7, 5-5), which was in a first-place A.C.C. tie with Duke two weeks ago, has lost four in a row -- all league games.</p>
        <p>Louisville 65, South Florida 50</p>
        <p>Clifford Rozier scored 25 points and keyed a 17-6 run down the stretch as No. 7 Louisville pulled away to a 65-50 victory over South Florida in Tampa, Fla. The victory was the ninth straight for the Cardinals (19-2, 8-1 Metro Conference), who were playing their first game since Coach Denny Crum was elected to the Basketball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Temple 51, Duquesne 49</p>
        <p>Eddie Jones scored 24 points and Jason Ivey hit a short bank shot with six seconds left last night to give No. 8 Temple (17-3, 10-2 Atlantic 10 Conference) the victory in Philadelphia. Duquesne tied the game with 15 seconds left on a jumper by Kenya Hunter. Rick Brunson then found Ivey for the short shot and the victory.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts 70 Rhode Island 64</p>
        <p>Derek Kellogg scored 13 points, 7 of them in the final two minutes, and Lou Roe overcame an early injury to add 11 points, as No. 13 Massachusetts outlasted Rhode Island, 70-64, last night to remain undefeated in the Atlantic 10. Mike Williams, Marcus Camby and Dana Dingle each had 9 points for the Minutemen (18-4, 9-0). It was Williams's first appearance since being cleared to play by cardiac specialists after he collapsed during a game at Cincinnati on Jan. 27.</p>
        <p>Arizona 77, Stanford 60</p>
        <p>Khalid Reeves scored 33 points and had six 3-pointers as No. 16 Arizona held host Stanford to its fewest points of the season. Rebounding from last Saturday's 74-69 loss at Washington, Arizona claimed a 13th straight win over Stanford, which lost for just the second time in 11 home games this season. The other loss was to then-No. 1 U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>U.C.L.A. 79, Washington 76</p>
        <p>Tynus Edney scored 22 points, including six free throws in the final three minutes, and Shon Tarver added 20 points as No. 9 U.C.L.A. rallied in the last four minutes to beat Washington in Los Angeles.  Marquette 61, Cincinnati 60</p>
        <p>Jim McIlvaine blocked 8 shots, scored 18 points and hit 2 free throws that gave visiting Marquette the victory, snapping a five-game losing streak to Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Iona 74, Niagara 63</p>
        <p>Mikkel Larsen scored 22 points and Greg Barr added 21 as Iona snapped a five-game losing streak with the victory over Niagara in a Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference game at Niagara Falls, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Fairleigh Dickinson 83 Long Island U. 79</p>
        <p>Tanner Robinson's 3-point play with 19 seconds left gave visiting Fairleigh Dickinson a 2-point lead and Dave Freeman added two free throws as the Knights (11-10, 7-6 Northeast Conference) won.  BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
