<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Help for Families on the Edge</title>
    <meta content="26SUN2$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E5DF133AF935A15752C0A961958260" item-length="367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Help for Families on the Edge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial hails contributions to New York Times Neediest Cases Fund (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City has been splintering ever further into separate worlds of rich and poor as economic trends deepen the divisions and government social programs are cut back. Last week, The New York Times Neediest Cases appeal found heartening evidence that some well-off citizens are trying to bridge the gap. At a time when Wall Street is enjoying its biggest boom in years, employees from seven leading Wall Street firms came forward with substantial contributions that put the fund over the $4 million mark. That is the highest figure, at this point in the appeal, since 1992, but it is still well below that year's total of more than $5 million.</p>
        <p>Cynicism grips many New Yorkers, who have come to feel that private giving cannot make much of a difference. The people who run the seven charities that receive contributions from the Neediest Cases Fund speak of ''compassion fatigue.'' But the money raised by the fund is desperately needed. More families are showing up at food pantries and emergency shelters. Rising unemployment and layoffs of unskilled workers are throwing more families into crisis, raising doubts about their ability to stay together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City has been splintering ever further into separate worlds of rich and poor as economic trends deepen the divisions and government social programs are cut back. Last week, The New York Times Neediest Cases appeal found heartening evidence that some well-off citizens are trying to bridge the gap. At a time when Wall Street is enjoying its biggest boom in years, employees from seven leading Wall Street firms came forward with substantial contributions that put the fund over the $4 million mark. That is the highest figure, at this point in the appeal, since 1992, but it is still well below that year's total of more than $5 million.</p>
        <p>Cynicism grips many New Yorkers, who have come to feel that private giving cannot make much of a difference. The people who run the seven charities that receive contributions from the Neediest Cases Fund speak of ''compassion fatigue.'' But the money raised by the fund is desperately needed. More families are showing up at food pantries and emergency shelters. Rising unemployment and layoffs of unskilled workers are throwing more families into crisis, raising doubts about their ability to stay together.</p>
        <p>With New York City hard pressed to operate its own system of foster care for more than 40,000 children, private charity is essential for the tens of thousands of children who have not yet fallen into the system but are holding on by the barest of threads. Among these families, illness or loss of a job or an eviction can create a crisis. Money contributed to the Neediest Cases Fund can make the difference by providing a poor family with a crib, warm winter blankets, transportation to a health clinic or shoes so that children can go to school.</p>
        <p>The charities supported by the Times drive need more than just money. Volunteer help can provide a crucial boost to counseling and mentoring programs for young people and others. Monetary contributions, still critically needed, are tax-deductible to the extent permitted by law. Checks should be made payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund and mailed to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
