<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Visual Lesson in the Evolution of Prints</title>
    <meta content="26ART.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ART" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zimmerli Art Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D7163AF935A15752C0A961958260" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Visual Lesson in the Evolution of Prints</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews exhibit of prints at Zimmerli Art Museum at Rutgers University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a game of free association, art aficionados might respond to ''Rutgers'' with ''prints.'' The Zimmerli Art Museum at the university has more than 50,000 of them from all eras and constantly mounts shows approaching prints from various angles. Currently, it's back to basics with ''Four Centuries of Prints.''</p>
        <p>The Zimmerli's specialization was charted by Dennis Cate, the only director the museum has ever had. He arrived on the Rutgers campus 25 years ago with a specialty in turn-of the-century French graphic art, which became the core of the collection. Now, the Mason Gross School for the Arts at Rutgers houses the Center for Innovative Print and Paper. The Zimmerli is also showing work created at the center by three American Indian artists, Jaune Quick-to-See Smith, James Lavadour and Truman Lowe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a game of free association, art aficionados might respond to ''Rutgers'' with ''prints.'' The Zimmerli Art Museum at the university has more than 50,000 of them from all eras and constantly mounts shows approaching prints from various angles. Currently, it's back to basics with ''Four Centuries of Prints.''</p>
        <p>The Zimmerli's specialization was charted by Dennis Cate, the only director the museum has ever had. He arrived on the Rutgers campus 25 years ago with a specialty in turn-of the-century French graphic art, which became the core of the collection. Now, the Mason Gross School for the Arts at Rutgers houses the Center for Innovative Print and Paper. The Zimmerli is also showing work created at the center by three American Indian artists, Jaune Quick-to-See Smith, James Lavadour and Truman Lowe.</p>
        <p>''Four Centuries of Prints'' focuses on print processes. The title seems to indicate an exhaustive display, but Trudy Hansen, the Zimmerli's curator of prints, makes her points with a manageable number of works, many of them by artists who are household names like Durer, Rembrandt and Whistler.</p>
        <p>An information sheet defines four major print categories: relief, intaglio, surface, and stencil, or screenprint. In conversation, Ms. Hansen made them even more approachable by using the formula ''over, under, around and through.''</p>
        <p>All prints involve a matrix, a plate or a block. In relief, the ''over'' process, paper is placed over, say, an inked block of wood and picks up the ink from what hasn't been cut away. Etchings and engravings are the primary representatives of intaglio. (The name means incision.) Lines are cut into or scratched on a metal plate; ink fills the grooves (and hence is under the surface), while the plate's surface is wiped clean. With great pressure, a printing press transfers ink to damp paper.</p>
        <p>Lithography, drawing on a stone with a greasy crayon, is ''around'' because it's based on the fact that ink is attracted to oil and avoids water. The lithography stone is kept wet, and the wet areas stay blank while the crayon marks attract ink, which is applied to the stone with a roller and sticks to the greasy image. In stencil or screenprint, a matrix or metal mesh of silk is stretched on a frame. The image is an area that ink can be forced through, while the rest of the matrix is blocked so that ink cannot pass.</p>
        <p>''People's eyes tend to glaze over when you discuss these processes, but yet they're fascinated by them,'' said Ms. Hansen, who, as overseer of the Zimmerli's Archives for Printmaking Studios, has a network of two dozen presses that donate a print from each edition they produce, and sometimes plates or blocks as well. ''In painting, everyone knows what the artist does. But in the end, I want the viewer to be knocked out by the images themselves.''</p>
        <p>She leads off the show with a punchy comparison. A manuscript with stiff figures whose shapes were crudely cut from wood precedes Durer, the master of engraving. He had been to Italy and seen the limpid naturalness that Renaissance art was ushering in, and he wanted to capture it in prints.</p>
        <p>Durer made forays into etching as well. The difference between etching and engraving is that an engraver digs the line into the metal itself, while in etching the plate is coated with a resin ground and the drawing tool moves with greater ease.</p>
        <p>''The whole evolution in prints has been toward greater freedom,'' Ms. Hansen said. Freedom also meant that artists would appropriate the work of others. ''Rubens had a stable of engravers who copied his paintings, and they weren't careful about limiting editions, the way it is today. An image would be printed until the plate wore out.''</p>
        <p>A large etching of Roman ruins by Piranesi is included to show that travel views were a major avenue for printmakers in the 17th century. But then the exhibition pauses at Rembrandt, the master of etching. The examples, including a self-portrait of the artist at his window and another print of the shepherds adoring the baby Jesus, are very dark. ''Students in printmaking classes are always told to wipe the plate clean, but Rembrandt would ignore that and would constantly build up rich tonalities,'' Ms. Hansen said.</p>
        <p>These nuances eventually gave way to the aquatint, associated with Goya, and the mezzotint. Both involve the creation of a surface that is densely pitted to hold ink, but the aquatint plate is coated with resin. By burnishing the pits, the artist can achieve lighter or darker tones. In mezzotints the entire surface of an uncoated plate is roughened by a sharp-toothed tool called a rocker. Laborious rocking followed by burnishing and scraping can be rewarded with luxurious, velvety blacks, well illustrated here by two works by the early 19th-century English artist John Martin.</p>
        <p>The Martin works anticipate the Romantic movement of the 19th century, a movement that coincided with the invention and development of lithography. Because it can accommodate all types of drawing, the spectrum of works in the show can range from a circular image by Delacroix of a devil flying over Paris to topical political commentary by Daumier. At the end of the century, artists were becoming acquainted with the possibilities of color lithography, but they tended to use it sparingly, as highlights in mostly black-and-white compositions.</p>
        <p>It took the commercial world to nudge artistic print makers into bold color, but when it caught on it was like an explosion. Thanks to Mr. Cate, a specialization within the Zimmerli's overall specialization in prints turn-of-the-century French and Belgian posters. The show closes with these examples of the lithographic process, some of them outsized, hung floor to ceiling in imitation of a pioneering poster exhibition in Nantes, France, in 1898.</p>
        <p>The four centuries of the show's title do not include the 20th, and the fourth category, screenprint, is not covered. Ms. Hansen is already thinking ahead to the next century and has accepted a donation of a computer print by Dorothy Krause, dominated by the face of an elderly woman who is musing on her past with an erotic image from the Kama Sutra hovering behind her.</p>
        <p>Remarking on clarity and seamlessness of its complex image, Ms. Hansen recalled, ''Computer prints of a few years ago were done on slick computer paper, and you could see the pixels.'' Some museumgoers may be seeing a recapitulation of the gawky woodcut's rapid move into supple engraving.</p>
        <p>FOUR CENTURIES OF PRINTS</p>
        <p>Zimmerli Art Museum  Rutgers University, George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick</p>
        <p>Selections from the permanent collection, with an introduction to the history and basic methods of print production. With ''Recent Acquisitions to the Rutgers Archives for Printmaking Studios.'' Through Feb. 16. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>(908) 932-7237.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
