<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long, Winding Road for Rison</title>
    <meta content="26RHOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Bay Packers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rison, Andre</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D9123AF935A15752C0A961958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long, Winding Road for Rison</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden, in Sports of The Times, profiles Andre Rison, wide receiver who has been an offensive spark for Green Bay Packers since being claimed off waivers in November; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDRE RISON carries his own camera now. Unlike fellow players filming Super Bowl moments, Rison's rationale is, as usual, a little different. He understands that the news media form the image; he wants more control of the vehicle.</p>
        <p>Rison has been invented and reinvented more than any other impact player in this evening's Super Bowl. He has gone from misfit to clubhouse lawyer to renegade leader. With Green Bay, Rison is a born-again good guy. Rison has essentially gone from being one of the best receivers no one has seen to being the spark plug who will occupy center stage as the Packers face the New England Patriots in Super Bowl XXXI.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDRE RISON carries his own camera now. Unlike fellow players filming Super Bowl moments, Rison's rationale is, as usual, a little different. He understands that the news media form the image; he wants more control of the vehicle.</p>
        <p>Rison has been invented and reinvented more than any other impact player in this evening's Super Bowl. He has gone from misfit to clubhouse lawyer to renegade leader. With Green Bay, Rison is a born-again good guy. Rison has essentially gone from being one of the best receivers no one has seen to being the spark plug who will occupy center stage as the Packers face the New England Patriots in Super Bowl XXXI.</p>
        <p>''I think when you have a player who's a winner but he's in the wrong spot, sometimes he tends to stick out like a sore thumb,'' he said. ''He wants to win so bad, so sometimes he might make a comment that gets taken out of context. Then it snowballs and that becomes his 'personality.' ''</p>
        <p>Rison sees himself as the offensive counterpart of his good friend Deion Sanders, who now plays for Dallas. Rison and Sanders did time together with the Atlanta Falcons.</p>
        <p>''When Deion was in Atlanta, he was portrayed as the worst football player living -- outside of me,'' Rison said. ''He was the bad boy, and I fell in the same category because I was right there with him. We were stirring things up in Atlanta because we wanted to show what we had to offer. But we were putting up 2 wins and 14 losses, so what we said was negative. When you're 14-2 and 13-3, it's positive.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Rison, the lingering image of his Atlanta days is a June 1994 incident in which his girlfriend at the time, Lisa (Left Eye) Lopes, gathered his athletic-shoe collection in a bathtub and set it on fire. The subsequent blaze destroyed Rison's house. In many ways, the blaze was a purge that challenged Rison's greatest attribute: his confidence.</p>
        <p>The man who once said he was as good as Jerry Rice -- and proved it -- went from Atlanta to Cleveland to Baltimore to Jacksonville as a nomad for hire.</p>
        <p>''I would go to believing in myself again and get ready to play ball, then something would come in the way and take it away,'' Rison said.</p>
        <p>Rison made the Pro Bowl four times as a Falcon but was dumped after one season by the Browns. The Baltimore Ravens, who signed him to a five-year, $17 million contract, released him in a salary move. The Jaguars signed him the day before training camp started last year, then released him in November for what Coach Tom Coughlin described as a lack of performance.</p>
        <p>With Jacksonville, Rison taught wide receivers a trick he called ''late hands.'' In the move, a receiver acts as if the ball were not coming to him, then at the last minute puts his hands up and catches it. He said he also taught the Jaguars about winning. As he tells it, his influence on the team was too strong and he was released. The Packers claimed him off waivers.</p>
        <p>So now Rison has been rehabilitated and resurrected. Gone to Green and Gold Heaven, where cheeseheads and Packers reign and everything is cool. Make that cold.</p>
        <p>Rison received a call from Sanders the other day. The two laughed and reflected on the long journey.</p>
        <p>''He said, 'Man, I'm just laughing; I'm so happy for you, me and my family are so happy for you,' '' Rison said. ''Deion told me, 'Before you went to Cleveland and they stripped you of your confidence, you believed that you were the best -- and you were the best. Couldn't nobody stop you -- can't nobody stop you now -- but me.' ''</p>
        <p>As a matter of fact, a year and a half ago, Sanders told the 49ers that they needed to get Rison.</p>
        <p>''I'm not out here committing crimes; I'm not out here going to jail,'' Rison said. ''I want to play football and I like to win. I would like the ball to be thrown my way a couple times. Am I a criminal for that?''</p>
        <p>In Green Bay, Rison has had no need to complain about the team's attitude or effort.</p>
        <p>''But if we were playing bad and we were struggling, I'm quite sure I'd say something,'' he said. ''But then, it would be taken in a different context; I'd be showing leadership.''</p>
        <p>Rison looked at the camera and pointed across the room.</p>
        <p>''The main thing I focused on when I came to Green Bay was proving to the world that I can play this game and I can play it how it's supposed to be played,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''All I know is that Andre Rison has made it to the Super Bowl.''</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
