<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding a Twist to Winter Soups</title>
    <meta content="WCFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FOOD" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soups</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodgson, Moira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDE143AF935A15752C0A961958260" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding a Twist to Winter Soups</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hodgson, Moira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moira Hodgson article on making winter soups; recipes; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYONE is familiar with the classic winter soups made from split peas or white or black beans. But these dishes can be given an interesting twist by adding unexpected ingredients. The bland creaminess of white beans goes well with shellfish like mussels or clams. Black bean soup, one of my favorites, makes an elegant first course perked up with oven-dried tomatoes, which add a pleasing acidity, along with creme fraiche and coriander.</p>
        <p>Alice Waters, chef of Chez Panisse in Berkeley, Calif., makes it with roasted green tomatillos. Joyce Goldstein, a chef and teacher whose  Mediterranean restaurant Square One in San Francisco influenced a generation of chefs, suggests adding lemon to a legume soup if it seems flat. A split-pea soup can be brightened with a little chopped spinach and paprika. In Turkey, where her version of a recipe below comes from, small bowls of plain yogurt are served on the side. She also advises that soup absorbs salt as it sits, so seasoning should be adjusted at serving time. As soup sits, it also thickens. So stock or water should be added when it is reheated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYONE is familiar with the classic winter soups made from split peas or white or black beans. But these dishes can be given an interesting twist by adding unexpected ingredients. The bland creaminess of white beans goes well with shellfish like mussels or clams. Black bean soup, one of my favorites, makes an elegant first course perked up with oven-dried tomatoes, which add a pleasing acidity, along with creme fraiche and coriander.</p>
        <p>Alice Waters, chef of Chez Panisse in Berkeley, Calif., makes it with roasted green tomatillos. Joyce Goldstein, a chef and teacher whose  Mediterranean restaurant Square One in San Francisco influenced a generation of chefs, suggests adding lemon to a legume soup if it seems flat. A split-pea soup can be brightened with a little chopped spinach and paprika. In Turkey, where her version of a recipe below comes from, small bowls of plain yogurt are served on the side. She also advises that soup absorbs salt as it sits, so seasoning should be adjusted at serving time. As soup sits, it also thickens. So stock or water should be added when it is reheated.</p>
        <p>How long to cook beans depends on when they were harvested. They are best soaked overnight, but they can also be covered with water, brought to a boil and allowed to sit for an hour or so instead. This will insure that they cook evenly. They should be picked over first and small stones or discolored beans removed. Salt should not be added until halfway through cooking to prevent the beans from becoming tough.</p>
        <p>French bread, with salad and cheese to follow, and a simple red wine go well with these dishes.</p>
        <p>Black-Bean Soup With Dried Tomatoes  Total time: Soaking overnight; 2 to 3 hours cooking</p>
        <p>1pound black beans</p>
        <p>Water to cover</p>
        <p>2pounds plum tomatoes</p>
        <p>Olive oil</p>
        <p>Coarse sea salt</p>
        <p>1onion chopped</p>
        <p>1carrot chopped</p>
        <p>2stalks celery chopped</p>
        <p>3cloves garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1green chili pepper, minced</p>
        <p>1/2teaspoon cumin</p>
        <p>Freshly ground pepper to taste</p>
        <p>8tablespoons creme fraiche</p>
        <p>8teaspoons chopped fresh coriander.</p>
        <p>1. Cover the beans with water and soak them overnight. Preheat the oven to 375 degrees. Cut the tomatoes in half and put them on oiled baking sheets. Season them with salt and roast them about two hours, or until they are dried and wrinkled. When they have cooled, cut them in thin strips and set them aside.</p>
        <p>2. Drain the beans and put them in a pot with the onion, carrot, celery, garlic and chili pepper. Add three quarts cold water and bring to boil. Turn down the heat and simmer gently for an hour. Add cumin, salt and pepper to taste and continue cooking until the beans are tender.</p>
        <p>3. Puree the beans in a blender or put them through a food mill. Pour the soup into eight bowls and garnish each bowl with a spoonful of creme fraiche, a spoonful of chopped tomatoes and a teaspoon of chopped coriander.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Turkish Split-Pea Soup With Mint and Paprika  Total time: Overnight soaking; 1 hour cooking</p>
        <p>8ounces split peas</p>
        <p>2tablespoons unsalted butter</p>
        <p>1onion thinly sliced</p>
        <p>1carrot peeled and thinly sliced</p>
        <p>1bay leaf</p>
        <p>5to 6 cups chicken stock</p>
        <p>1/2pound spinach washed and chopped</p>
        <p>3teaspoons Hungarian paprika</p>
        <p>Milk for thinning</p>
        <p>1teaspoon coarse sea salt</p>
        <p>Freshly ground pepper to taste</p>
        <p>3tablespoons chopped mint to garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Cover the split peas with cold water. Soak for a few hours or overnight. Drain.</p>
        <p>2. Melt the butter in a saucepan over moderate heat. Cook the onion until soft and translucent, about 10 minutes. Add the split peas, carrot, bay leaf and stock to cover and bring to boil. Simmer gently, covered until the peas are very soft. If the mixture seems dry, add more stock or water as needed.</p>
        <p>3. Remove the bay leaf. Add the chopped spinach and two teaspoons of the paprika and simmer until the spinach wilts.</p>
        <p>4. Puree the soup in a blender or food processor. Add the milk, water or stock to thin. Season to taste with salt and pepper. Serve hot, sprinkle with chopped mint and remaining paprika.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: Adapted from ''Kitchen Conversation'' by Joyce Goldstein (William Morrow and Co. Ltd.)</p>
        <p>White-Bean Soup With Shellfish and Pesto  Total time: Soaking overnight; 2 to 3 hours cooking</p>
        <p>1cup white beans</p>
        <p>1onion</p>
        <p>2cloves garlic</p>
        <p>1bay leaf</p>
        <p>1teaspoon of coarse sea salt</p>
        <p>2tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>2cups chopped onions</p>
        <p>Pinch of hot pepper</p>
        <p>1clove garlic, minced</p>
        <p>2cups tomatoes, diced, peeled and seeded</p>
        <p>2pounds mussels or clams, well scrubbed</p>
        <p>1cup white wine or as needed</p>
        <p>Fish stock or water as needed</p>
        <p>4tablespoons pesto sauce.</p>
        <p>1. Soak the beans overnight with water to cover and drain. Alternatively, cover the beans with four cups cold water and bring to a boil. Simmer for two minutes. Cover and let sit for an hour. Drain and put in a saucepan with cold water to cover by about two inches. Add the whole onion, garlic and bay leaf and bring to a boil. Reduce heat and simmer for an hour. Add salt and continue cooking until beans are tender. Remove the onion, garlic and bay leaf and set the beans aside with the liquid.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the olive oil in a saucepan and add the chopped onions. Cook over moderate heat for 10 minutes, add the minced garlic and a pinch of hot pepper, if you like, and cook a moment longer. Add the tomatoes and the white beans with their liquid and simmer for two minutes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. Put the shellfish in a pan with an inch or two of white wine. Bring to boil, cover the pan and steam until the shellfish open. Remove the shellfish to a bowl. Strain the pan juices and add them to the soup. Remove the mussels or clams from their shells and discard the shells. Heat the beans and add the shellfish. Adjust seasoning and thin with stock or water if needed. Serve with a dollop of pesto in each bowl.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: Adapted from ''Kitchen Conversations'' by Joyce Goldstein (William Morrow and Co. Inc.)</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
