<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="03QNA.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/03/travel/03QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1252000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cormier, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EED8163DF930A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ray Cormier</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cormier, Ray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel Q&amp;A column on Buddhist pilgrimage to India, thoroughbred horse farms in Japan and getting married in Paris (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Buddhist Pilgrimage</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>I am a Buddhist and would like to make a pilgrimage to India to visit the major sites associated with the life of Buddha. Are there companies or agents offering such tours? -- Mark Metta Silber, Budd Lake, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Buddhist Pilgrimage</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>I am a Buddhist and would like to make a pilgrimage to India to visit the major sites associated with the life of Buddha. Are there companies or agents offering such tours? -- Mark Metta Silber, Budd Lake, N.J.</p>
        <p>A.  The India Government Tourist Office, 1270 Avenue of the Americas, Suite 1808, New York, N.Y. 10020, (800) 953-9399, fax (212) 582-3274, can provide a list of such agents. A spokesman, Gowri Shanka, suggested two in New York.</p>
        <p>One, Pollina Tours and Travel, 143-04 Cherry Avenue, Flushing, Queens 11355, (718) 321-7873, fax (718) 886-9282, has had a pilgrimage tour, In the Footsteps of Lord Buddha, for five years. It lasts 13 days and with international and domestic air fares, first-class hotels, chauffeured transportation between sites, and English-speaking guides, costs $2,999 each for  double occupancy. Food, beverages and other expenses are extra.</p>
        <p>The itinerary includes visits to Sarnath, the site of Buddha's first sermon; a sunrise cruise on the Ganges in Varanasi; a stop at Bodh Gaya, the site of the Bodhi tree, where Buddha attained enlightenment; a visit to Kushinagar, where he died, and one to Lumbini, in southern Nepal, where he was born as  Siddhartha Gautama.</p>
        <p>Another New York agency, UVI Holidays, 82 Wall Street, New York, N.Y. 10048, (212) 425-1518 or 1531, fax (212) 425-1528, www.uviusa.com, does not have a standard tour, but Joe Thomas, the president, said he would customize one. He outlined a 12-day trip similar to Pollina's that would cost $925 a person, double occupancy, without meals or air fare.</p>
        <p>A British company, Soul of India, offers a pilgrimage tour Feb. 11 to 29. It includes a visit to Katmandu, Nepal, and an optional flight over  Mount Everest ($75). The basic cost from New Delhi (without air fare) is $1,855 at $1.45 to the pound. Kenneth Wilson, the director, says it also can be arranged at any time for two people or more. Soul of India Tours, 6 Westland Road, Wolverhampton, WV3 9NY, United Kingdom; (44-1902) 561-485; www.soulofindia.com.</p>
        <p>Japanese Thoroughbreds</p>
        <p>Q.  I am interested in visiting thoroughbred farms in Hokkaido in March. Are any open to the public?  -- J. H., Hayward, Calif.</p>
        <p>A.  Hokkaido, Japan's large northern island, is among the nation's most rural areas. The island, which includes Sapporo, site of the 1972 Winter Olympics, has become the breeding center for the Japan's horse racing industry.</p>
        <p>According to Marian Goldberg of the Japan National Tourist Organization, there are 125 horse farms in Hokkaido open to visitors (Shadai, the stables of Fusao Sekiguchi, who won the Kentucky Derby this year with Fusaichi Pegasus, is one of a number closed to the public). The farms are in three areas of the southern part of the island, each of which has a racehorse information center -- the Iburi, Hokkaido and Tokachi centers.</p>
        <p>These can provide farms' opening hours and seasons, information on lodging and transportation, and tips for visiting the farms. (Note that many farms close in the foaling season, February and March, and for severe winter weather.)</p>
        <p>These centers are sponsored by the racehorse association, not the tourist office, but they encourage visitors. Unfortunately, their staffs are not likely to speak English nor is there a volunteer guide organization on Hokkaido. So, unless you speak Japanese, you will probably want to hire a guide or interpreter. Here are the centers' phone numbers: Hokkaido, (81-14) 643-2121; Tokachi, (81-15) 554-4341; Iburi, (81-14) 485-2009.</p>
        <p>You can fly from Narita Airport in Tokyo to Shin Chitose Airport, 25 miles south of Sapporo. There is at least one flight a day (two on Tuesday, Thursday and Saturday) each way. Hokkaido is one area of Japan where renting a car can make sense, but if you are going to drive, you must get an International Driver's license from AAA.</p>
        <p>The farm closest to Sapporo is Northern Horse Park, 114-7 Misawa, Tomakomai, Hokkaido; phone (81-144) 58-2116. The farm is open to visitors daily from noon to 3 p.m. It's just a short drive to the farm from the airport, and the park operates a free shuttle bus linking the two.</p>
        <p>The region with the largest number of horse farms is near Shizunai, which is reachable by rail on the JR Hokkaido Hidaka Line.</p>
        <p>For travel information, including help finding guides, contact the Japan tourist organization, 1 Rockefeller Plaza, Suite 1250, New York, N.Y. 10020, (212) 757-5640, fax (212) 307-6754; or closer to you, at 360 Post Street, Suite 601, San Francisco, Calif. 94108, (415) 989-7140, fax (415) 398-5461; or see its Web site, www .japantravelinfo.com.</p>
        <p>Marrying in Paris</p>
        <p>Q.  How would a couple go about being married in Paris? -- K. Murphy, Baton Rouge, La.</p>
        <p>A.  A well-publicized law enacted last year gave legal status in France to unmarried couples, but changed nothing about getting a marriage license, according to the French Consulate in New York. So France remains a poor choice for eloping, since at least one party must have lived in same town or arrondissement at least 40 days before a civil ceremony, including 10 days for the publication of marriage banns. And a civil authority must perform a wedding before any religious ceremony can take place.</p>
        <p>To apply for a marriage license in Paris, first go with your passports to the mairie, or town hall, in the arrondissement one party is living in. You will also need a number of other documents, including these:</p>
        <p>* A medical certificate for each of you with blood-test results. These must be submitted before the banns can be published and be dated no more than two months before then. Americans can be examined in the United States by a doctor approved by the French Consulate.</p>
        <p>* A birth certificate translated into French and affidavits by the couple stating, if applicable, how a previous marriage was terminated.</p>
        <p>* A document (certificat de coutume) by an approved lawyer stating that each party is free to marry in France and that the marriage will be recognized in the United States.</p>
        <p>A list of authorized translators and doctors is available from consulates in the United States. One is at 934 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10021; (212) 606-3689, fax (212) 606-3620; www.franceconsulatny.org.</p>
        <p>Marriage information is also available at the Web site for the American Embassy to France, www .amb-usa.fr. Click on American Citizen Services, then Guide for U.S. Citizens Residing in France.</p>
        <p>RAY CORMIER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
