<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>East Meets West in the Evolution of an Austrian Sushi Chef</title>
    <meta content="03SUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1252209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER EAST SIDE -- CITYPEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D7113DF930A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>East Meets West in the Evolution of an Austrian Sushi Chef</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GENIA GOULD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The more conservative Japanese diners at Ikeno Hana, a Japanese restaurant on Lexington Avenue near 72nd Street, are visibly disturbed when they see the sushi chef. But the younger patrons are pleasantly surprised.</p>
        <p>They are impressed as they watch the chef expertly cut raw fish and confidently mold rice in the palms of his hands. They are not concerned  that the sushi chef, William Schropp, is not only one of the few non-Japanese in his field but also an Austrian trained in French cuisine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The more conservative Japanese diners at Ikeno Hana, a Japanese restaurant on Lexington Avenue near 72nd Street, are visibly disturbed when they see the sushi chef. But the younger patrons are pleasantly surprised.</p>
        <p>They are impressed as they watch the chef expertly cut raw fish and confidently mold rice in the palms of his hands. They are not concerned  that the sushi chef, William Schropp, is not only one of the few non-Japanese in his field but also an Austrian trained in French cuisine.</p>
        <p>''He has natural movements,'' said Yasuko Nagasawa, an art historian from Japan who has lived in the United States for years and recently dined at the restaurant. ''If I didn't see his face, I wouldn't know that he wasn't Japanese.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schropp, 33, half Austrian and half Danish, began his career at 15, training as a chef at French restaurants in the Austrian Alps. In 1988, he went to Manhattan and got a job at Odeon.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago he became captivated by the art of Japanese sushi.</p>
        <p>''I kind of tripped into it,'' said Mr. Schropp, who lives in the East Village. A sturdily built man with strong forearms and a brown buzz cut hidden under his chef's hat, he began his latest culinary journey when he was helping with the opening of Match, a restaurant in SoHo, where the menu included sushi.</p>
        <p>But when opening day arrived, the owners realized that in all the confusion, no sushi chef had been hired. So Mr. Schropp jumped in, making basic rolls the way he had learned at Nosmo King, a Manhattan restaurant where he had worked.</p>
        <p>For a few days, he relied on his smattering of previous experience, along with a few basic concepts and a little improvisation. ''I was able to pull it out of the hat,'' said Mr. Schropp, who had always liked sushi and paid attention to what the chefs were doing at sushi bars.</p>
        <p>When the owners of Match finally hired two real sushi chefs, Mr. Schropp decided to stay and become their apprentice. One attraction was getting out of the kitchen and into a more pleasant environment.</p>
        <p>''It's not hot,'' he said. ''It's not greasy. You don't get burned. You get instant feedback from people.</p>
        <p>''When you're in the kitchen, you never get thanks. You just get attitude from the waiters.''</p>
        <p>After perfecting his skills at Mika, a sushi restaurant, he moved five years ago to Ikeno Hana, where he has amassed a devoted following. Eve Strausman, a patron who lives nearby, always requests that he make her sushi. ''I never really thought about the fact that he wasn't Japanese,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Schropp sometimes encounters resistance on the part of Japanese diners.</p>
        <p>''Because they see I'm a white guy doing the sushi, they judge me,'' he said. But, he said, he cares much more about the opinion of a master chef who trained in Japan decades ago. ''If he says, 'Good job,' that's what matters to me,'' Mr. Schropp said.</p>
        <p>GENIA GOULD</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER EAST SIDE -- CITYPEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
