<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.E. Offers an Active Role In the Hudson PCB Cleanup</title>
    <meta content="10GE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/10/nyregion/10GE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1382835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dredges and Dredging</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pcb (Polychlorinated Biphenyls)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Superfund</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1DB113DF933A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.E. Offers an Active Role In the Hudson PCB Cleanup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.E. Offers an Active Role in the Hudson PCB Cleanup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Electric offers to take on much of Hudson River cleanup work; company, which spilled tons of PCB's from its upstate factories, files notice with Environmental Protection Agency that it will negotiate with government in good faith about removing chemicals, including collecting sediment samples, designing dredging plan and then performing dredging; says it will leave to government job of finding site for mud that will be removed; cost is expected to reach about $460 million; company takes conciliatory tone, but also files suit challenging constitutionality of Superfund law, under which EPA can unilaterally order cleanup (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Electric Company, which spent millions of dollars arguing that dredging the Hudson River to remove its industrial pollution would be environmentally disastrous, has quietly signaled that it may now be ready to participate in the cleanup -- and in fact may take on much of the work itself.</p>
        <p>The company, which spilled and discharged tons of polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, from its factories north of Albany, said in a filing late Monday with the federal Environmental Protection Agency that it would negotiate with the government in ''good faith'' about removing the chemicals, which have been linked to cancer in humans and other problems in fish and wildlife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Electric Company, which spent millions of dollars arguing that dredging the Hudson River to remove its industrial pollution would be environmentally disastrous, has quietly signaled that it may now be readyto participate in the cleanup  and in fact may take on much of the work itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The General Electric Company, which spent millions of dollars arguing that dredging the Hudson River to remove its industrial pollution would be environmentally disastrous, has quietly signaled that it may now be ready to participate in the cleanup -- and in fact may take on much of the work itself.</p>
        <p>The company, which spilled and discharged tons of polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, from its factories north of Albany, said in a filing late Monday with the federal Environmental Protection Agency that it would negotiate with the government in ''good faith'' about removing the chemicals, which have been linked to cancer in humans and other problems in fish and wildlife.</p>
        <p>More specifically, the company offered to collect more than 25,000 sediment samples on the river beginning this summer, design the scope of the dredging plan over the next three years and then ''perform or fund'' the actual dredging after that.</p>
        <p>G.E. said it would not perform tasks that it feels are more appropriately the province of the government -- especially finding a site for the thousands of tons of mud that will be dug from the river over the life of the project and building a plant to remove water from the mud.</p>
        <p>After years of combative language, defiant posturing and harsh criticism of the E.P.A. and its goals, the company's tone was conciliatory and accommodating.</p>
        <p>''G.E. will work constructively with E.P.A. on this project and our offer reflects that commitment,'' said Stephen D. Ramsey, G.E.'s vice president for corporate environmental programs. ''This is a major step toward what we hope will be a cooperative relationship for ensuring the implementation of the dredging project.''</p>
        <p>The E.P.A.'s office in New York issued a statement yesterday saying that it would ''not be productive to comment on G.E.'s response at this time,'' but the agency said that discussions were being held with the company and that further information and clarification had been requested.</p>
        <p>The filing itself was not unexpected. The E.P.A. issued an order in December that the river would be dredged at a cost of $460 million, paid for by G.E., and a failure by the company to respond in writing could have triggered further financial penalties. The filing came at the close of business on the last day of the company's deadline.</p>
        <p>But government and company officials said that G.E.'s response would nonetheless be the beginning of what could be concrete discussion -- as opposed to the polemics that have characterized much of the debate about the river in recent years -- about who might do what and how it might be done.</p>
        <p>Under federal pollution laws, the government could do the dredging work itself and bill G.E., or the company could agree to do the work, or some other division of labor could be negotiated.</p>
        <p>General Electric has not given up the field of battle entirely. The company filed a lawsuit in Federal District Court in Washington in late 2000, challenging the constitutionality of the so-called Superfund law, which Congress passed in 1980, and is the legal foundation of the E.P.A.'s ability to order unilaterally that pollution be cleaned up in places like the Hudson.</p>
        <p>The suit does not address the particulars of PCB's, but focuses on whether cleanup orders in general violate G.E.'s right to due process. Oral arguments were held in February, during the same period in which the company was preparing its response to the dredging order.</p>
        <p>General Electric manufactured capacitors and other components using PCB's at its factories in Hudson Falls and Fort Edward, about an hour north of Albany. The government banned PCB's in 1977, but by then decades of leaks, spills and permitted drainage of the chemicals had made the Hudson one of the nation's most PCB-contaminated rivers. In 1984, a 200-mile stretch of the river from Hudson Falls to the Battery in New York City was added to the government's Superfund priority cleanup list.</p>
        <p>Under the government's plan, 2.65 million cubic yards of river sediment would be dredged up along a 40-mile stretch south of the factories, with the goal of removing 150,000 pounds of the oily yellow chemicals, which are concentrated in a series of ''hot spots'' on the river's bottom. The E.P.A. said it planned a three-year design phase for the project, followed by five years of actual dredging.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
