<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conflict Takes Toll on Jewish and Arab Families in the City</title>
    <meta content="10RETU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/10/nyregion/10RETU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1382850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ramallah (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Magnes, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Magnes, Rafi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Habiby-Browne, Emira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">West Bank</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Arab-American Family Support Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharon, Ariel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DA113DF933A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conflict Takes Toll on Jewish and Arab Families in the City</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conflict Takes Toll on Jewish and Arab Families in the City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turmoil in Middle East preoccupies New Yorkers that have family there; Israelis Liz and Rafi Magnes came to New York when peace process stalled, but are worried about three daughters still living there; photo of Emira Habiby-Browne who is unable to bury her mother in Ramallah because of fighting (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Emira Habiby-Browne learned last week that her mother had slipped into a coma in an East Jerusalem hospital, the news was all the more painful because she knew the dying woman's paramount wish was to be buried in Ramallah.</p>
        <p>But Ramallah, a West Bank city, is a war zone, its Palestinian residents are confined to their houses and Israeli tanks and soldiers patrol the streets. There was a blockade on the city and a ban on funerals. The Palestinian dead were piled up in morgues or placed in makeshift mass graves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conflict in the West Bank has reached across the ocean to affect relatives in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Emira Habiby-Browne learned last week that her mother had slipped into a coma in an East Jerusalem hospital, the news was all the more painful because she knew the dying woman's paramount wish was to be buried in Ramallah.</p>
        <p>But Ramallah, a West Bank city, is a war zone, its Palestinian residents are confined to their houses and Israeli tanks and soldiers patrol the streets. There was a blockade on the city and a ban on funerals. The Palestinian dead were piled up in morgues or placed in makeshift mass graves.</p>
        <p>''My father is buried in Ramallah,'' said Mrs. Habiby-Browne, as she rushed through last-minute phone calls and chores at her Brooklyn office before heading to the airport last Friday. ''Each time my mother was here visiting, she'd say: 'I want to go back. I want to be in Palestine. I want to be near your father.' And now she's dying and we can't even bury her where she wants.''</p>
        <p>Every day, the bloodshed in the Middle East also preoccupies Liz and Rafi Magnes, an Israeli couple who left their country out of frustration with its rightward drift and lack of progress toward peace with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>But they have three daughters living in Israel, including one who works as a waitress a block from a restaurant destroyed by a Palestinian suicide bomber last month. The Magneses never thought they would hear themselves say it, but they would like their children to leave Israel.</p>
        <p>''We had a good life but a hard life there,'' said Ms. Magnes, a concert pianist who now teaches music to children and adults in the Bronx. ''But we see people becoming less tolerant in all of Israeli society. So I say to myself, I don't want my children to live in a culture that is so destructive, so sad and so hard. I wouldn't care if they leave and have a life somewhere else.''</p>
        <p>This is what war does, even from far away. The abstract becomes personal. The battlefield is as familiar as a childhood home. Pain leaps distances. And ordinary people think about changing their lives -- or they have their lives changed for them.</p>
        <p>While the Arab-Israeli conflict has always figured large in the politics of New York, the relentlessly rising death toll from both Palestinian suicide bombers and Israel's military operations has deeply wounded countless Arab and Jewish families in the city.</p>
        <p>''Everything that happens in the Middle East spills over to here,'' said Mrs. Habiby-Browne, the executive director of the Arab-American Family Support Center in Brooklyn. ''We all have families and connections there, and there's just so much pain I can't find words to express it.''</p>
        <p>For Arabs living in New York, the latest Israeli offensive against Palestinian refugee camps and towns, accompanied by army-enforced curfews and roadblocks, hit hard. Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel said the attacks were aimed at destroying an infrastructure of terrorism that sustained Palestinian suicide bombers. But the ramifications -- intimate and frightening -- are felt in every Palestinian family.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Habiby-Browne's mother died on Sunday. As family members feared, the Israeli Army did not permit them to take her to Ramallah for burial. They buried her instead in Arab East Jerusalem, hoping that they might soon move her body to rest next to her husband's grave, as she had so fervently wished.</p>
        <p>''I don't think people have any conception of what Palestinians are going through,'' Mrs. Habiby-Browne said. ''It hurts me that people don't understand that I want to have the right to feel a connection. At least I'm in an office environment where I can say what I feel and not be considered un-American or unpatriotic.''</p>
        <p>No doubt many Arab-Americans feel more angry than she with Israel, as surely many Jewish and Israeli-Americans feel more anger for Palestinians than the Magnes family. But for the Magneses, longtime leftists who long to see Israel withdraw from the West Bank and Gaza Strip, the recent violence is mostly disheartening as a reminder of how far the two sides have traveled away from the dream of peaceful coexistence.</p>
        <p>''We left originally for a year because Rafi said the country was making him ill,'' Ms. Magnes said. In 1998, the couple went to Cairo, where they spent three months learning Arabic, and then to New York City in hopes of eventually seeing a concrete peace settlement take hold in Israel. The year away from home became two and then three. ''We left and we didn't leave,'' Ms. Magnes said. ''But we have the luxury of leaving. Think about those who don't.''</p>
        <p>She and her husband said they do not torment themselves worrying about where their daughters are at any given moment, when a bomb might explode in Israel. They worry more, they said, about whether the young women can lead productive lives, free from the draining effects of hatred and isolation, in such an atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''I talked the other day with a friend in Israel and he said, 'My son has become a right-winger,' '' said Mr. Magnes, shaking his head in disbelief. ''He said his son now says, 'They're killing us, so we should kill them.' ''</p>
        <p>The parents' immediate focus is on their daughter Dina, who has been visiting them in New York since March 23 and is scheduled to return to Tel Aviv on April 20. They would like her to stay in the United States. ''It's not easy to leave,'' Dina, 30, said this week. ''You feel it's your responsibility to be there. What if all the people who think like me leave? Then the state has no hope of existence.''</p>
        <p>She is a fashion designer who returned to Israel just two years ago after working in the United States. Unlike her parents, she believed peace with the Palestinians and neighboring Arab countries might be at hand. ''When I moved back, I thought I could have a thriving business,'' the younger Ms. Magnes added. ''I would sell clothes to all the Arab world and go skiing in Lebanon and do whatever a normal person in Europe does -- get on a train and go visit another country.''</p>
        <p>For the foreseeable future, her father said, that dream has to be put away along with those of many other Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take a long time to rebuild any kind of trust after this war,'' Mr. Magnes said. ''The economy will go down. The suicide bombings will come back. And there will be plenty of people to do harm but not enough to do good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
