<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Loans Discriminate, Study Shows</title>
    <meta content="Y13LOA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Fair Housing Alliance</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Housing Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Macarthur, John D and Catherine T, Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dedman, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreclosures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDC1430F930A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Loans Discriminate, Study Shows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL DEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dedman, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Fair Housing Alliance study finds that realtors and lenders steer unqualified minority home buyers to Federal Housing Administration mortgage loans, which are especially profitable for lenders, with the result that black and Hispanic neighborhoods in Chicago area are pockmarked with foreclosed homes; finds percentage of FHA loans does not decline in middle-income and upper-income minority neighborhoods, as it does for whites, but increases; MacArthur Foundation financed study (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Racial discrimination and abuse by lenders of a Federal mortgage program are helping to create pockets of blight in black and Hispanic neighborhoods, according to a study of lending in the Chicago area.</p>
        <p>The study, by the Chicago Fair Housing Alliance, an advocacy group, contends that lenders and real estate agents direct a disproportionate number of minority buyers to Federal Housing Administration loans. Since the loans are especially profitable for lenders, unqualified home buyers are given the loans and minority neighborhoods are pockmarked with the foreclosed homes of buyers who should never have been approved for the mortgage, the study concluded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Racial discrimination and abuse by lenders of a Federal mortgage program are helping to create pockets of blight in black and Hispanic neighborhoods, according to a study of lending in the Chicago area.</p>
        <p>The study, by the Chicago Fair Housing Alliance, an advocacy group, contends that lenders and real estate agents direct a disproportionate number of minority buyers to Federal Housing Administration loans. Since the loans are especially profitable for lenders, unqualified home buyers are given the loans and minority neighborhoods are pockmarked with the foreclosed homes of buyers who should never have been approved for the mortgage, the study concluded.</p>
        <p>''Were any private mortgage lending or mortgage insurance institutions engaged in activities with such clearly differential impacts for white and minority communities, HUD and the Department of Justice would surely file suit for discrimination under the Fair Housing Act,'' said Calvin Bradford, a fair-housing researcher who wrote the study, which was financed by the MacArthur Foundation. The study is to be released on Wednesday at a hearing of a House housing subcommittee, where the study's author and others will testify.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Federal Department of Housing and Urban Development, which enforces fair housing laws and oversees the F.H.A., said that the study's portrayal of the agency was ''rather extreme,'' but agreed that elements of the program ''require additional improvement and reform.''</p>
        <p>The F.H.A. was created in the Great Depression to assist homebuyers who could not qualify for conventional mortgages. While F.H.A. loans allow buyers with less money for a downpayment to buy a home, the interest rates are usually higher than those for conventional loans.</p>
        <p>Nationally, African-American and Hispanic homebuyers received F.H.A. loans more than twice as often as white homebuyers, which might be expected because minority home buyers have, on average, lower incomes and worse credit ratings.</p>
        <p>But the researchers found a surprising pattern: As they looked at middle-income and upper-income minority neighborhoods, the percentage of F.H.A. loans did not decline, as it did for whites, but increased. Even high-income black neighborhoods had higher rates of F.H.A. lending -- 67 percent -- than low-income white neighborhoods -- 32 percent.</p>
        <p>Steering by real estate agents explains part of this pattern. In tests of more than 50 real estate firms, agents steered minority buyers to minority neighborhoods, when the buyers had expressed no preference. Many agents also steered minority buyers to lenders that specialized in F.H.A. loans.</p>
        <p>This occurred although, in every case, the minority ''testers'' had higher incomes and were more credit-worthy than the white testers.</p>
        <p>The study found that Housing Department policies discouraged lenders from caring whether they were making sound loans. The fees that F.H.A. pays to lenders are twice as high as those for conventional loans. And by guaranteeing full repayment of mortgages, F.H.A. reduces a lender's incentive to make sound loans, the fair housing group contends.</p>
        <p>''You have people being steered to F.H.A. who don't need it,'' Mr. Bradford said, ''and at the low end of that market, people are being given F.H.A. loans who don't qualify, who shouldn't really have gotten any loan. We all want more minorities to receive loans. But HUD has never faced the side effects of its programs.''</p>
        <p>A HUD spokeswoman, Karen Hinton, said that Housing Secretary Andrew M. Cuomo has toughened enforcement since he took office in 1997 and that the department has tightened its standards. Ms. Hinton also said that the high fees for lenders and the loan guarantees are necessary to induce lenders to make the loans. But she denied that they induced lenders to overuse F.H.A.</p>
        <p>She agreed with one contention of the Chicago group: that the department could do more to push conventional lenders to lend to minorities.</p>
        <p>In general, Ms. Hinton agreed that steering is a problem. ''But it's not a problem with F.H.A.'s policy,'' she said. ''That's lenders breaking the law. They see a minority person walk in the door and say, 'I'm not going to make a conventional loan to them.' We're doing everything possible to send a message to the lending committee that they're not going to get away with it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
