<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; An Animal Nativity Of Puppets</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="580241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BREAD AND PUPPET THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NATIVITY 1992 (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D81E30F932A35752C0A965958260" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; An Animal Nativity Of Puppets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 30 years, the Bread and Puppet Theater has been enlightening audiences about timeless political issues. Peter Schumann's anniversary show, "Nativity 1992," at Theater for the New City, is one of the troupe's more playful efforts. This animal fable is an exemplar of performance folk art. It reaffirms the fact that Bread and Puppet is entertaining as well as uplifting. This time the message comes in a bright holiday wrapping.</p>
        <p>Played on and around a small two-level proscenium stage, an expandable puppet theater, the show frequently catches the audience off guard as actors dressed as puppets remove their outer masks, change their postures and transform themselves into startlingly different creatures. Beginning with four bulbous-headed peasants marching for Greenpeace, "Nativity 1992" never moves too far from social consciousness yet remains lighthearted when touching matters of portent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For 30 years, the Bread and Puppet Theater has been enlightening audiences about timeless political issues. Peter Schumann's anniversary show, "Nativity 1992," at Theater for the New City, is one of the troupe's more playful efforts. This animal fable is an exemplar of performance folk art. It reaffirms the fact that Bread and Puppet is entertaining as well as uplifting. This time the message comes in a bright holiday wrapping.</p>
        <p>Played on and around a small two-level proscenium stage, an expandable puppet theater, the show frequently catches the audience off guard as actors dressed as puppets remove their outer masks, change their postures and transform themselves into startlingly different creatures. Beginning with four bulbous-headed peasants marching for Greenpeace, "Nativity 1992" never moves too far from social consciousness yet remains lighthearted when touching matters of portent.</p>
        <p>Following the cue "And God created the heavens," the curtain parts to reveal two angels (actors wearing deer heads) sitting in the clouds and playing percussion and accordion. Together they leap into tympanic melody. After a heavy week of creating, the show's God takes a deep breath and announces: "That's it. I'm tired," and steps aside to let the animals cavort.</p>
        <p>A long slinky tiger throws off its skin to reveal himself as a monolithic King Herod, "the man in charge" and the villain of this piece. The three white sheep he is badgering respond to his officiousness by standing tall. They turn into militant soldiers, then return to their original sheepish shape.</p>
        <p>As the narrative loops in and out of the Nativity story, taking time for commentary, the costumes are their own panoply. By having his puppetized actors hold additional masks, Mr. Schumann increases the size of his cast. There are only eight actors onstage, but they stand in for triple that number. One actor becomes three kings and three others clone themselves into a multitude that might have strayed from one of the company's mournful canvases like "The Gray Lady Cantata." In such a fashion, the show evokes Bread and Puppet new and old.</p>
        <p>The company carries with it a sense of its history as well as a feeling for the political moment. Watching the troupe, one is aware of the talented directors and puppeteers who have derived inspiration from its work, people like Julie Taymor, Theodora Skipitares and Janie Geiser. Each of them has gone in a distinct and highly individualized direction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumann is the progenitor. He is also the head of a company that constantly replenishes itself. As demonstrated in this seasonal show, Bread and Puppet retains its youthful exuberance and its zest for activism through performance. Bread and Puppet Theater 'Nativity 1992' Written, directed and designed by Peter Schumann. Presented by the Theater for the New City, Bartenieff-Field. At 155 First Avenue, near Ninth Street, East Village. WITH: Pedro Adorno, Emily Anderson, Mary Curtin, Michael Dennison, Pati Hernandez, Jackie O'Halloran, Michael Romanyshyn and Cathy Vigo.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
