<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reds Crunch Braves for Fifth in a Row</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="344039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL LEAGUE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE1039F935A25757C0A966958260" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reds Crunch Braves for Fifth in a Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Cincinnati won its fifth straight game under its new manager, Lou Piniella, as Eric Davis and Chris Sabo each hit three-run homers today to pace the unbeaten Reds to a 13-6 victory over the Atlanta Braves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Cincinnati won its fifth straight game under its new manager, Lou Piniella, as Eric Davis and Chris Sabo each hit three-run homers today to pace the unbeaten Reds to a 13-6 victory over the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>Cincinnati won its fifth straight game under its new manager, Lou Piniella, as Eric Davis and Chris Sabo each hit three-run homers today to pace the unbeaten Reds to a 13-6 victory over the Atlanta Braves.</p>
        <p>It is the Reds' best start since 1980 when they were 8-0.</p>
        <p>Cincinnati scored four times after two outs in the seventh, chasing Tom Glavine (0-2) on consecutive singles by Sabo, Billy Hatcher and Barry Larkin for a run.</p>
        <p>Davis hit a 2-0 pitch from the reliever Dwayne Henry over the center-field fence, his first home run of the year, to erase a 4-3 deficit.</p>
        <p>The Reds blew the game open with seven runs in the ninth inning off three relievers. Larkin and Mariano Duncan each had run-scoring singles, Paul O'Neill hit a two-run single and Sabo capped the scoring with a three-run homer off Mike Stanton.</p>
        <p>Sabo, who hit 6 homers and drove in 29 runs all of last season, has 3 homers and 6 r.b.i. in his first five games.</p>
        <p>Tim Birtsas (1-0), who pitched one and a third hitless innings in relief of Rick Mahler, got the victory. Phillies 4 Cardinals 0 PHILADELPHIA (AP) - Dennis Cook allowed seven hits in eight and two-thirds innings and Len Dykstra had four hits and scored three runs as Philadelphia won.</p>
        <p>Cook (1-0) gave up a leadoff single in the ninth inning to Willie McGee and left with two outs when Terry Pendleton doubled, sending McGee to third. McGee was the first runner to reach third against Cook in the game.</p>
        <p>Roger McDowell walked Ozzie Smith to load the bases, but got the pinch-hitter Denny Walling on a groundout to the mound for his second save.</p>
        <p>Dykstra, who led off four times with hits, scored his first run in the first when he doubled and scored on John Kruk's one-out single.</p>
        <p>After the Phillies scored again in the second, Dykstra singled in the third and scored on Von Hayes's sacrifice fly to left.</p>
        <p>Dykstra led off the fifth with a single, moved to third on a single by Kruk and scored on Ricky Jordan's fielder's choice to make it 4-0. Dodgers 5 Astros 4 HOUSTON (AP) - Juan Samuel doubled off Charley Kerfeld and scored the tie-breaking run on the reliever's wild pitch with one out in the 10th inning as Los Angeles sent Houston to its fifth loss in six games.</p>
        <p>After Samuel doubled, Willie Randolph sacrificed him to third. Kerfeld (0-2) threw a 1-2 pitch to Hubie Brooks that got by the catcher Craig Biggio and allowed Samuel to score.</p>
        <p>Jay Howell (1-0) pitched two innings in his first appearance of the season for the victory.</p>
        <p>Randolph tied the score at 4-4 when he hit a homer with one out in the eighth inning off the reliever Danny Darwin. Randolph, who hit his first home run last season on Aug. 20, had three hits and drove in three runs.</p>
        <p>Tim Belcher, the Dodger starter, pitched six innings and allowed eight hits. Pirates 4 Cubs 3 PITTSBURGH (AP) - Sid Bream sat out the first seven innings for Pittsburgh, but he hit a run-scoring single in the 10th inning off Les Lancaster. Bream is still recovering from reconstructive knee surgery.</p>
        <p>It was the first run against Chicago's bullpen in 20Y innings this season. Bobby Bonilla earlier hit a three-run homer for the Pirates.</p>
        <p>The Cubs, who held the Pirates to eight hits and one run in the first two games of the series, were trying for their second three-game sweep in Pittsburgh since June 1957.</p>
        <p>With the score tied at 3-3, Andy Van Slyke, in a 1-for-17 slump, singled to center to start the 10th against Lancaster, who had worked a scoreless eighth and ninth. John Cangelosi popped out trying to bunt but Lancaster walked R. J. Reynolds.</p>
        <p>Bream, who entered the game in the eighth as a pinch-hitter, then bounced a single up the middle, scoring Van Slyke for the winning run. Padres 4 Giants 3 SAN FRANCISCO (AP) - Benito Santiago hit a two-run homer with one out in the ninth inning off the reliever Steve Bedrosian to spur San Diego to a three-game sweep of the defending National League champions.</p>
        <p>It was the Padres' fifth straight victory and marked the first time the Giants were swept in a three-game series at Candlestick Park since May 25-27, 1987.</p>
        <p>Bedrosian (0-1) was making his 1990 debut. He missed the first five games to be with his family after his son was diagnosed as having leukemia.</p>
        <p>Joe Carter opened the San Diego ninth with a double down the left-field line. One out later, Santiago hit a 0-2 pitch over the left-field fence for his first home run of the season.</p>
        <p>Greg Harris (2-0) pitched the final three innings for the victory, retiring all nine batters he faced.</p>
        <p>Will Clark's first home run of the season, a two-run shot in the sixth inning, gave the Giants a 3-2 lead. Clark has eight r.b.i. in his first six games.</p>
        <p>Rick Reuschel retired the first 14 batters before the Padres tied the score in the fifth inning. He pitched eight innings, allowing seven hits, before Bedrosian relieved.</p>
        <p>The Padres have won five of their first seven games, while the Giants have dropped four of six.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
