<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Newark Dream</title>
    <meta content="14NJVAILS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1627106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN MYTHOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golway, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDA1F3CF937A25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Newark Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY GOLWAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Golway, Terry</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Vailsburg neighborhood of Newark, NJ, once center of political influence in city; neighborhood is holding several reunions to celebrate its 100th anniversary of incorporation into greater Newark; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES the mention of a single word can conjure not just memories, but smells and sounds and sights and stories of a time that only the foolish would regard as long gone.</p>
        <p>For thousands of Jews who lived in Newark during and immediately after World War II, that one word is Weequahic. Immortalized in Philip Roth's novels --most recently ''The Plot Against America'' -- Weequahic occupies a place in the nation's literary imagination as well as in the memories of those who strolled along Chancellor Avenue in the 40's, 50's and 60's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES the mention of a single word can conjure not just memories, but smells and sounds and sights and stories of a time that only the foolish would regard as long gone.</p>
        <p>For thousands of Jews who lived in Newark during and immediately after World War II, that one word is Weequahic. Immortalized in Philip Roth's novels --most recently ''The Plot Against America'' -- Weequahic occupies a place in the nation's literary imagination as well as in the memories of those who strolled along Chancellor Avenue in the 40's, 50's and 60's.</p>
        <p>Yet a few miles northwest of Roth Country, in another part of Newark, the children and grandchildren of Catholic immigrants were playing their own parts in the drama known as the American Century. Their neighborhood was Vailsburg, in the westernmost part of Newark -- the only part of the city that jumps the artificial boundary known as the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>What Weequahic was to the Jews of Mr. Roth's generation, Vailsburg was to a mixture of Irish, Italian, German and Ukrainian immigrants and their children. Many of them had fled other parts of the city -- the Irish from Down Neck, the Italians from the 14th Ward. The breadwinners were police and firemen, operating engineers, brewery workers, Board of Education employees and, in the brick homes along Eastern Parkway, doctors, lawyers and dentists.</p>
        <p>Vailsburg was also home to Newark's governing elite, beginning with a prominent lawyer who went on to become a Supreme Court Justice, William Brennan, the son of an Irish immigrant and labor union organizer. Mayors like Vince Murphy and Leo Carlin and Hugh Addonizio lived in Vailsburg, along with countless members of the City Council and chairmen of the Essex County Democratic Party. Two future Democratic state chairmen, Ray Durkin and Thomas Giblin, grew up within shouting distance of each other.</p>
        <p>And most were parishioners of Sacred Heart Roman Catholic Church on South Orange Avenue.</p>
        <p>''That church was the locus of life in Vailsburg,'' said State Supreme Court Justice James Zazzali, a Rumson resident who was born in the neighborhood in 1937 and lived there until his marriage in 1967. ''It was a classic immigrant church, and was the largest church in the city at the time.''</p>
        <p>In those years before the race riots of 1967, Vailsburg was the political capital of Newark, its influence felt in Newark City Hall as well as the State House in Trenton.</p>
        <p>''It was very much a political culture,'' said Brendan O'Flaherty of Maplewood, a professor of economics and of international and public affairs at Columbia University who lived in Vailsburg from 1958 to 1994. ''It was the political hub of the city.''</p>
        <p>Over the years Vailsburg's political influence has waned, but its influence over its exiles has not. In less than two weeks, on Nov. 23, former Vailsburg residents will gather at Cryan's Beef and Ale House in South Orange -- a bar with its own Vailsburg roots -- for an annual reunion. That is in addition to the Vailsburg reunions held every winter by the Giblin Association, run by Mr. Giblin's family, and the Cryan Association, run by the tavern-owning family.</p>
        <p>The reunions this year will have a special significance, because Vailsburg is celebrating the 100th anniversary of its incorporation into greater Newark. It has existed as an independent town for 10 years, but was swallowed in the age of urban consolidation, the same impulse that led to the creation of greater New York in 1898 with the addition of Brooklyn, Queens and Staten Island.</p>
        <p>To commemorate the anniversary, Professor O'Flaherty and Ed Lewinson, a retired history professor at Seton Hall University, will give a talk on the neighborhood's history at Cryan's on Monday.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Roth's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel ''American Pastoral,'' the chapter on life in Weequahic during the post-war years is entitled, ''Paradise Remembered.'' That might well serve as the subtitle for the Vailsburg reunions coming up. ''It was very family-oriented,'' said Eileen Smith, a 65-year-old West Orange resident who attended Sacred Heart School and lived in Vailsburg's Ivy Hill Apartments in the 1960's. ''My parents never had a car. We walked everywhere, and it was safe. You could take a bus downtown and come back at night without having to worry about crime.''</p>
        <p>But it was not necessary to take a bus downtown, unless the excitement of Broad and Market Streets simply was irresistible. With two movie theaters, the Stanley and the Mayfair, a butcher, a clutch of 5-and-10-cent stores and a noteworthy collection of bars along South Orange Avenue, Vailsburg was a self-contained neighborhood.</p>
        <p>And then there was that other form of entertainment.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Smith served as vice president of one of the neighborhood's most active community organizations, the Young Democrats of Vailsburg. The president of the group at the time was Ray Durkin, who would go on to be chairman the Essex County Democrats and the state Democratic Party. Today, the 68-year-old Mr. Durkin remains a potent force in state politics.</p>
        <p>''But of all the titles I've had,'' he said, ''the one I valued most was president of the Young Democrats of Vailsburg. Everybody wanted that.''</p>
        <p>As late as the late 1950's and early 60's, life in Vailsburg -- with a population of 35,000, about the same as today -- seemed unchanged, even as highways like the Parkway and Interstates 78 and 280 opened up broad swaths of the state. Sacred Heart parish grew so big that a new parish, Immaculate Heart of Mary, was founded in the late 1950's on the Maplewood-Newark-Irvington border. Sacred Heart itself built a new school to relieve overcrowding.</p>
        <p>And then the riots erupted in 1967. It would take some time for the residual effects of the violence to cross the Parkway, but by the mid-1970's flight was under way. It was more than just a reaction to urban disorder. ''Jobs were leaving the city,'' Mr. Giblin noted. And people followed.</p>
        <p>By the early 1980's, Sacred Heart ''was a shell of what it had once been in terms of numbers,'' said Drew Bauman, a Maplewood lawyer who served the parish as a priest from the late 1970's to 1982.</p>
        <p>Still, the school somehow stayed open, and today the parish's current pastor is a young priest named Andrew Prachar, who grew up in Vailsburg and said he was inspired by people like Mr. Bauman. Father Prachar's assignment these days is in many ways more difficult that his predecessors -- he is fighting not only changes in the neighborhood, but changes in society as well. Sacred Heart no longer is the locus of Vailsburg, and the rich would-be patrons are scattered throughout the state.</p>
        <p>Still, the exiles do come back on occasion. Sometimes they return in a coffin for a funeral service in the old neighborhood. Other times, they help out at functions sponsored by the Unified Vailsburg Service Organization, which helps the community's poor. Or they turn out for reunions in the huge Sacred Heart school cafeteria.</p>
        <p>They are decades removed from the neighborhood, but not really. ''Growing up in Vailsburg really was a wonderful experience,'' said Justice Zazzali, ''and so many people who are products of the Vailsburg experience really regret that that their children didn't have that city experience.''</p>
        <p>But you can be sure that they have heard the stories.</p>
        <p>URBAN MYTHOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
