<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Program to Fix Up the Eyesore on the Block</title>
    <meta content="13PROP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="About Real Estate" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="About Real Estate"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Neighborhood Housing Services (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greater New York Savings Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing Preservation and Development Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">About Real Estate (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DA163AF930A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Program to Fix Up the Eyesore on the Block</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In $11 million project begun by Neighborhood Housing Services, 47 rundown houses on otherwise well-tended blocks in New York City's boroughs will be restored and sold at or just below market value; Greater New York Savings Bank will provide $8 million for construction, guaranteed by Federal mortgage insurance program; money will be repaid when houses are sold; city's Department of Housing Preservation and Development will make up difference between sales price and greater cost of rehabilitation, which city agency expects to be about $3 million (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a block of historic brownstones, their cast-iron balustrades freshly painted, their front gardens beautifully manicured, the house at 198 McDonough Street in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn stands out.</p>
        <p>It is the only house that appears to be falling apart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a block of historic brownstones, their cast-iron balustrades freshly painted, their front gardens beautifully manicured, the house at 198 McDonough Street in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn stands out.</p>
        <p>It is the only house that appears to be falling apart.</p>
        <p>Its brownstone veneer has given way on the ground floor, leaving only sloppily mortared bricks, underpinnings never meant to be seen. The first-floor windows are stoppered with plywood; the windows on the upper floors, with cinder blocks. Unlike the magnificent mahogany doors of its neighbors, the door of this house is a roll-down metal gate.</p>
        <p>The rundown house in the midst of well-kept neighbors is a familiar picture -- but one that an unusual new program is setting out to change. In an $11 million project begun by Neighborhood Housing Services, a nonprofit housing organization, 47 houses in the same predicament as the one at 198 McDonough Street -- the only derelict, city-owned house in an otherwise well-tended block -- are to be restored and sold at or just below market value.</p>
        <p>The Greater New York Savings Bank will provide $8 million for the construction, guaranteed by a Federal mortgage insurance program. The money will be repaid when the houses -- in Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx -- are sold. The city's Department of Housing Preservation and Development will make up the difference between the sales price and the greater cost of the rehabilitation, which the city agency expects to be about $3 million.</p>
        <p>The bank will also offer mortgages to the ultimate buyers, who, under the program, must be first-time home buyers. Under the bank's plan, buyers may be able to qualify with  lower assets and income than usual -- although they must have acceptable credit histories and be able to show they can make the monthly payments. Purchasers will also be able to buy the houses with as little as 2 percent down, versus the more normal 10 to 20 percent down payment -- a sum that Jeanne Lutfy, a senior vice president at the bank, called ''the biggest obstacle to owning a home.''</p>
        <p>Closing costs, too, will be lower because in most cases the mortgage held by Neighborhood Housing Services will simply be transferred to the new private buyers, without the normal appraisal and other fees. Under the special program, closing costs will average $2,000 to $2,500, compared with 6 percent of the purchase price of the house in more typical transactions. Real estate taxes on the house will be phased in over six years; the first year the new homeowner will pay taxes on only the land.</p>
        <p>When it is finished, the grand house on McDonough Street, in the midst of the Stuyvesant Heights Historic District, will have cost $216,017 to fix up into a three-family dwelling.  Under the program, new owners commit to live in their homes -- or at least part of them; they are able to rent out apartments -- for at least six years. If they leave before then, at least part of their profit must go to repay the city's contribution.</p>
        <p>The appraised market value of the house is $185,000. And, as an added attraction, Neighborhood Housing Services -- which has bought this and the rest of the houses from the city for $1 apiece -- will sell it for $170,000.</p>
        <p>Homeworks, as it is called, is a new program for Neighborhood Housing Services, whose core business, according to David Beer, director of housing development, consists of making loans for repairs to owner-occupied one- to four-family houses, especially when the owners are considered ''unbankable,'' a description Mr. Beer defined as unable to obtain credit. Neighborhood Housing Services also renders technical assistance; a construction staff oversees the work.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, the agency renovated 54 houses for first-time buyers, but those buyers had to have low and moderate incomes; under the new program, there are no income limits.</p>
        <p>The money for the new rehabilitations will come from the Federal Department of Housing and Urban Development's Mortgage Insurance Program, called the 203(k) program. While the little-used loan guarantee program has been around since the 80's, the Federal Government just streamlined its processing procedures,</p>
        <p>''Before, the 203(k) program was a mess, and it's still perceived to be difficult,'' Ms. Lutfy said. ''That's why banks have shied away from it.'' But for the buyer, there are some substantial savings, she said.</p>
        <p>The 47 houses include 19 in Bedford-Stuyvesant, with the rest scattered throughout neighborhoods in Queens and the Bronx: in East Elmhurst, Corona, Rego Park and Sunnyside in Queens, and Belmont, Soundview, Williamsbridge, Morris Heights and University Heights in the Bronx. The vacant houses will be gut renovated: New electrical and plumbing systems -- along with new kitchen cabinets, appliances, hardwood floors, tile and new sheetrock walls -- will be installed.</p>
        <p>If the houses are historic, their facades will be restored carefully, according to Mr. Beer. ''Brownstone will be restored, cornices will be restored or replaced with similarly designed fiberglass,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''What we aim to do with this new program,'' he said, ''is to fill in that gaptooth effect on the block -- and we know the neighbors will be grateful.''</p>
        <p>About Real Estate</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
