<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Bar; A top Russian judge, in limbo, testifies to the perils and promise of law back home.</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Law Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="653582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGOLICK, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AMETISTO, ERNEST (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGOLICK, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AMETISTO, ERNEST (JUDGE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB133FF930A35751C1A965958260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Bar; A top Russian judge, in limbo, testifies to the perils and promise of law back home.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Margolick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARGOLICK, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting in a New York hotel room recently, Judge Ernest Ametistov of the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation took a break from what he called "an absolutely crazy day," filled with speeches, reunions and conversations with the curious.</p>
        <p>But the craziness Judge Ametistov found in Manhattan hardly compares to what he has seen in Moscow over the last two years. Russia, he said, finds itself in a "battle between Communism and democracy, slavery and freedom, the past and the future," and his court, the nation's highest, has been caught in the crossfire. After the jurisprudential Chernobyl that was the Soviet Union, the first buds of law sprouted through the ashes, only to wither as Russia's President, Boris N. Yeltsin, wrestled with its Parliament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting in a New York hotel room recently, Judge Ernest Ametistov of the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation took a break from what he called "an absolutely crazy day," filled with speeches, reunions and conversations with the curious.</p>
        <p>But the craziness Judge Ametistov found in Manhattan hardly compares to what he has seen in Moscow over the last two years. Russia, he said, finds itself in a "battle between Communism and democracy, slavery and freedom, the past and the future," and his court, the nation's highest, has been caught in the crossfire. After the jurisprudential Chernobyl that was the Soviet Union, the first buds of law sprouted through the ashes, only to wither as Russia's President, Boris N. Yeltsin, wrestled with its Parliament.</p>
        <p>Whenever the battle between Mr. Yeltsin and his enemies -- notably Vice President Aleksandr Rutskoi and Ruslan Khasbulatov, the chairman of the Congress of People's Deputies -- reached his court, Judge Ametistov invariably voted with Mr. Yeltsin. That made him a dissenter, one of four on the 13-member panel.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Yeltsin became fed up with the majority, headed by the court's chairman, Valery Zorkin. Proclaiming that the court had degenerated into a "tool of political struggle of great danger for the state," he suspended it on Oct. 7 until the adoption of a new constitution, to be voted on in a referendum next week. Judge Ametistov (pronounced ah-met-TEE-stov) thus sits on a court in limbo. That left him with enough time on his hands to visit New York, New Haven, Detroit and Chicago in mid-November.</p>
        <p>In speeches to the New York City bar association and to the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, in visits to the law schools of Columbia and Yale, and in a conversation with a reporter, the 59-year-old judge offered a mixed verdict on Russian-style justice.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, he described a nation that has yet to learn even the rudiments of law -- where, he conceded, the creation of a court like his was "probably premature." Amazingly enough, he and his brethren were selected (by the Russian Parliament) after five-minute interviews.</p>
        <p>Traveling in Austria at the time, Judge Ametistov missed the perfunctory process altogether; he learned of his appointment only when his mother congratulated him upon his return. "It was a kind of parody," he said, puffing on a Marlboro Light and speaking in English, having learned it in the Soviet era by reading novels like "Goodbye, Columbus" and "The Godfather" as well as bootlegged translations of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Joseph Brodsky and Andrei Sakharov.</p>
        <p>Once in place, the new court had to parse a dated and internally contradictory Brezhnev-era "constitution of developed socialism." Judge Ametistov maintained that his colleagues, far from mediating disputes between the executive and legislature, used that constitution to thwart Mr. Yeltsin, often without holding a hearing. By creating a purportedly legal basis for the occupation of the Russian Parliament, he said, they bear responsibility for the bloodshed that followed.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he noted, the very existence of the court, along with its work in nonpolitical cases, represents a giant leap forward in a nation where constitutional rule, judicial review and individuals' rights are largely alien.</p>
        <p>"The court and law in Russia were not tools for protecting people but for suppressing them," Judge Ametistov said. "But in the last years, the situation has changed. More and more people now come to the court to protect themselves."</p>
        <p>Even as the tanks rolled in Moscow last October, he noted, both sides claimed constitutional support for their positions. "It's the first time in the history of my country when the sides in civil conflict referred to a legal document," he said.</p>
        <p>Judge Ametistov, an authority on international law and human rights, first came to the United States in 1990; his mission was to study the American legal system and the lessons it offered Russian reformers. (His book on the subject was published recently in Moscow by the Lawyers Committee.) He subsequently helped draft the proposed new constitution of the Russian Federation.</p>
        <p>He made many friends in American human rights organizations.  They praise him as a bona fide democrat, referring to him by the familiar "Ernest Mikhailovich." He in turn has kind words for America's beleaguered lawyers. He singled out the Lawyers Committee and the American Bar Association, whose role in screening candidates for the Federal judiciary, he said, is something the Russian bar groups should emulate.</p>
        <p>In a move reminiscent of Franklin D. Roosevelt's star-crossed Court-packing plan, the reconstituted constitutional court will increase by six slots -- just enough, should his selections be ratified, for Mr. Yeltsin to fashion a bare majority. Judge Ametistov could well become the court's chairman, though he does not savor the prospect. "My character is dissident," he said.</p>
        <p>One way or another, Judge Ametistov will have to sit once more with Judge Zorkin and others whose hands, he believes, are stained with Russian blood. "For me personally and my colleagues, it will be very difficult to work with them," he lamented.</p>
        <p>But Judge Ametistov said he was convinced that more than a few incumbent judges, and a few years, stand between Russia and the rule of law. "Unfortunately, everything depends not on the law or the legal system but on individuals," he said. "It will be possible, but only after one or two generations of lawyers, when the Old Guard and their pupils leave."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
