<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="653639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAND PALAIS (PARIS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAND PALAIS (PARIS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARIS (FRANCE)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL GALLERY OF ART (WASHINGTON, DC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRISTIE'S</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL GALLERY OF ART (WASHINGTON, DC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRISTIE'S</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOODNER, IAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURGE, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOURY, ELIZABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOODNER, IAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURGE, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOURY, ELIZABETH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NATIONAL GALLERY OF ART (WASHINGTON, DC)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHRISTIE'S</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61730F930A35751C1A965958260" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grand Palais Ferme</p>
        <p>The Paris architect Jean Loup Roubert is at work repairing the Grand Palais, which closed less than two weeks ago after it was declared structurally unsound. The giant glass-domed exhibition center in Paris just off the Champs-Elysees has traditionally shown everything from fine art to cars.</p>
        <p>After a rivet head fell in June, netting was strung from the ceiling of the main dome; a subsequent study found the turn-of-the-century building had structural weaknesses. When it closed, spokesmen for the Grand Palais said about 20 shows scheduled to be held there in the next year would be canceled. Two shows were forced to close early: "Les Nabis," an exhibition of works by the group of painters that included Pierre Bonnard, Edouard Vuillard, Maurice Denis and Felix Vallotton, which was to run through Jan. 3, and "The Soul in the Body: Arts and Sciences 1793-1993," which was to close on Jan. 24. Together, the shows had been drawing about 2,500 visitors a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grand Palais Ferme</p>
        <p>The Paris architect Jean Loup Roubert is at work repairing the Grand Palais, which closed less than two weeks ago after it was declared structurally unsound. The giant glass-domed exhibition center in Paris just off the Champs-Elysees has traditionally shown everything from fine art to cars.</p>
        <p>After a rivet head fell in June, netting was strung from the ceiling of the main dome; a subsequent study found the turn-of-the-century building had structural weaknesses. When it closed, spokesmen for the Grand Palais said about 20 shows scheduled to be held there in the next year would be canceled. Two shows were forced to close early: "Les Nabis," an exhibition of works by the group of painters that included Pierre Bonnard, Edouard Vuillard, Maurice Denis and Felix Vallotton, which was to run through Jan. 3, and "The Soul in the Body: Arts and Sciences 1793-1993," which was to close on Jan. 24. Together, the shows had been drawing about 2,500 visitors a day.</p>
        <p>Most art exhibitions are not held in the central core of the building, where the worst physical problems are, but in side galleries. But the obstacle here is the need for an alternative emergency exit; the present exit leads right back into the unsafe central core.</p>
        <p>Grand Palais spokesmen said the main portion of the building would be closed for 18 months. All fairs and shows scheduled for that part of the building, including a major art fair and a book show, must find alternative locations. But two scheduled exhibitions, "The Sun and the North Star," which opens on March 18, and "The Origins of Impressionism," on April 2, are to go ahead as planned. Drawings Donated</p>
        <p>The number of drawings given to the National Gallery of Art in Washington from the collection of Ian Woodner, the New York and Washington real-estate developer, who died three years ago, keeps growing. This week, the museum announced it had been given nine drawings by Old Masters including Durer, Raphael, Van Dyck, Rembrandt, Tiepolo, Ingres and Goya, bringing the total to 32. The latest ones will go on view at the gallery starting Sunday.</p>
        <p>"Drawings have been a weak link here, and this is a real shot in the arm," said Andrew Robison, the National Gallery's Mellon senior curator. "Seen together, they are a constellation of Mr. Woodner's distinctive taste for the Renaissance."</p>
        <p>The collector, who was on the Trustee's Council, began buying drawings in the mid-1950's and spent four decades building his collection of 1,000 Old Masters and 19th- and 20th-century works.</p>
        <p>The latest gift was not exactly a surprise. The gallery had had discussions with Mr. Woodner about his collection since the 1970's. Two years ago, Dian and Andrea Woodner, the collector's daughters, along with the Ian Woodner Family Foundation, sold the gallery two drawings. One was by Cellini, the other by Vasari, and the cost was estimated to be millions of dollars. Since then, the Woodner family and foundation have donated 32 drawings to the museum.</p>
        <p>In addition, 109 works from the collection are on loan to the Gallery with the hope that they will eventually be donated, the museum said.</p>
        <p>"This gift shows the continuing support of the Woodner family," Mr. Robison said. "They have chosen to give some of the collection's very best." The latest group includes Durer's "Virgin Annunciate" (circa 1492), the earliest drawing in the gallery's collection and the earliest Durer drawing in the United States; two works by Raphael, "Eight Apostles" (1514-16) and "A Marble Horse on the Quirinal Hill" (1516-17), and Van Dyck's "Mystic Marriage of St. Catherine" (1616-18). Changes at Christie's</p>
        <p>Last week, Sotheby's announced major management news: that Michael L. Ainslie would step down as its president and chief executive and Diana D. Brooks, who heads Sotheby's auctions worldwide, would take his place. This week, it's Christie's turn.</p>
        <p>Changes at the auction house have been announced on both sides of the Atlantic. In New York, Christopher Burge, who has been Christie's president for North and South America for eight years, will become chairman of Christie's in America in January. Taking his place is David Tyler, Christie's group finance director in London.</p>
        <p>"It's a way of relieving Mr. Burge of day-to-day operations and making him our ambassador to America with a focus on what he does best: business-getting," said Christopher Davidge, Christie's managing director worldwide. Daniel P. Davison, who has been Christie's chairman since 1990, is to retire at the end of the year.</p>
        <p>In London, several other appointments were announced. John Lumley, who has been in Christie's paintings department for more than 20 years, will head its 19th- and 20th-century pictures department. That job had previously been part of Mr. Burge's responsibilities. Koury Closing</p>
        <p>Although business has picked up for many contemporary-art galleries, it's still not strong enough to keep everyone happy. On Dec. 18, Elizabeth Koury will close her three-year-old gallery at 89 Greene Street in SoHo, known for artists like Nicole Eisenman, Cheryl Donegan, Charles Long, Stephen Ellis and John Zonnser. "I want people to see this as a positive move," Ms. Koury said. "After 10 years of public support, I need a change. Of course, the reality of the times has assisted."</p>
        <p>Ms. Koury, who was a co-founder of International With Monument, the East Village gallery that launched the careers of artists including Jeff Koons and Peter Halley in the late 1980's, said she intended to represent several artists privately and organize shows. "I'd still like to have a public image but just be more independent," she said.</p>
        <p>Conversely, Stuart Feld of Hirschl &amp; Adler is determined to become more involved. At the end of the year, he is moving Hirschl &amp; Adler Modern from 420 West Broadway in SoHo to the second floor of his main Manhattan gallery at 21 East 70th Street.</p>
        <p>"This is not a financial decision; it's a global business move," Mr. Feld said. "We're in an era of consolidation, and I'd like to get more involved with this side of the business, which is hard to do when it's in SoHo. Hirschl &amp; Adler Modern's presence here will add a fresh flavor."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
