<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EUROPEANS OFFER $144 MILLION AID TO PALESTINIANS</title>
    <meta content="28mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/28/international/middleeast/28mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1743215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfensohn, James D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5D81631F93BA15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EUROPEANS OFFER $144 MILLION AID TO PALESTINIANS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europeans Offer $144 Million Aid to Palestinians</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER; James Kanter contributed reporting from Brussels for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After receiving a dire warning that the Palestinian Authority was so short of money that it might collapse in two weeks, the European Union on Monday offered $144 million in aid to the Palestinians before a Hamas government takes power.</p>
        <p>The Europeans acted in partial response to a letter from James D. Wolfensohn, the special Middle East envoy of the so-called Quartet made up of the United States, the European Union, Russia and the United Nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.N.'s Middle East envoy warned that the Palestinian Authority could collapse "within two weeks" without funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After receiving a dire warning that the Palestinian Authority was so short of money that it might collapse in two weeks, the European Union on Monday offered $144 million in aid to the Palestinians before a Hamas government takes power.</p>
        <p>The Europeans acted in partial response to a letter from James D. Wolfensohn, the special Middle East envoy of the so-called Quartet made up of the United States, the European Union, Russia and the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfensohn warned in a letter dated Saturday that ''unless a solution is found, we may be facing the financial collapse of the P.A. within two weeks,'' referring to the Palestinian Authority. The money from the European Union will not solve the Palestinian money crunch for very long, especially since most of it is not in cash, but it will ease the burden of repayments to suppliers.</p>
        <p>A large Israeli oil company, Dor Alon, said Monday that it could no longer supply fuel oil and natural gas to the Palestinians because a check for some $35 million from the Palestinian Authority bounced last week. The European money will presumably ensure the flow of energy to the Palestinians in a chilly, wet winter.</p>
        <p>The acting Palestinian finance minister, Jihad al-Wazir, said there was an immediate need for ''$60-80 million next week to begin to pay wages,'' Mr. Wolfensohn wrote in the letter to Quartet foreign ministers, warning of ''wide-ranging consequences'' for ''security and stability for both the Palestininians and the Israelis.''</p>
        <p>The Palestinian Authority's financial situation has worsened, said Mr. Wolfensohn, the former president of the World Bank. With estimated internal tax revenues of $35 million a month, and the loss of Israeli-collected tax and customs receipts of some $50 million a month, the Authority faces a monthly deficit of $130 million a month.</p>
        <p>For February and March, the period before a Hamas government is likely to take over, Mr. Wolfensohn said, the Authority may need as much as $360 million in new money. He said the Authority had to make loan repayments, pay arrears to private suppliers of energy and other goods, and meet the Bush administration's demand that it return $50 million provided last year for infrastructure improvements and used as collateral for bank loans.</p>
        <p>Israeli public companies supply electricity and water to the Palestinians, deducting the cost from the customs and tax revenues the Israelis collect for the Palestinian Authority. Israel is now withholding the revenues because of the victory of Hamas in the legislative elections last month.</p>
        <p>Israel argues that the recent swearing in of the legislature means that Hamas now controls the Authority, but the United States and the rest of the Quartet insist that President Mahmoud Abbas is still running a caretaker government that must be supported, and that any cutoff of financing should not take place until Hamas forms a government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfensohn has been asked to help the Authority get through February and March. Matters will only get worse once Hamas is considered to have formed a government by the Quartet and more funds are cut off. But the Quartet is arguing about when that date will be, with the European Union and the United Nations now saying it is important to wait to see what the new government's program is before cutting aid.</p>
        <p>Benita Ferrero-Waldner, the European Union's external relations commissioner, emphasized on Monday that European aid was not going to Hamas. After a Hamas-led government is sworn in, she said, ''we have to see what will be the program of the government.''</p>
        <p>''We have to give them time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the interim, she said, the Europeans, like the Americans, are ''supporting the caretaker government and trying to do everything to give Mahmoud Abbas our full support.''</p>
        <p>Of the $144 million the Europeans pledged on Monday, about $47.4 million will pay energy bills that the Palestinians owe Israeli companies, $75.9 million will be channeled through the United Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestinian refugees and $20.7 million is cash -- direct budget support to help pay salaries.</p>
        <p>The Quartet and Israel agree that relief aid to the Palestinians should continue, including money spent by United Nations organizations. The amount of money channeled through such organizations is likely to increase, but that will not pay the 135,000 or so Palestinians dependent on salaries from the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfensohn, diplomats say, is arguing that he should try to get the Palestinian Authority through to June, when the Group of 8 industrial nations are to meet. But the United States and Israel fear that such a long period would allow Hamas to establish itself.</p>
        <p>Israel and other countries are examining how money might be given to the Palestinians without going through the Authority. Perhaps, the diplomats say, a new international structure can be built with the help of the World Bank to disburse the money directly, with international auditing to try to ensure that none of it goes to the security forces.</p>
        <p>In the interim, the Saudis have promised but not yet delivered $20 million for February, the Norwegians have promised another $10 million and Qatar has delivered $14 million, which has already gone to repay loans taken in January in anticipation of the donation. Iran has made vague promises to help Hamas with financing once it takes power.</p>
        <p>Diplomats are also considering how, within the World Bank's regulations, to allow the payment of a frozen $60 million, which was withheld in December because the Palestinian Authority, even before the victory of Hamas, broke promises of fiscal responsibility by raising salaries against international advice.</p>
        <p>But the Wolfensohn letter notes that given the Palestinian failure to keep their promises, perhaps only $30 million will be disbursed. Compared with the monthly requirement, the amounts are small.</p>
        <p>''If we do not want to see rising tension leading to violence and chaos,'' Mr. Wolfensohn wrote, ''we will have to develop urgently a convincing strategy addressing the P.A.'s financial and developmental needs not only in the short-term of the next few weeks but also in a longer time frame.'' That includes the revenues withheld by Israel, he said, adding, ''It cannot be in Israel's interests to have a sharp deterioration of the economic and humanitarian situation next door.''</p>
        <p>But a senior Israeli official said Monday that Israel could not stand by while a group it considered terrorist and sworn to its destruction consolidated power next door, and that neighboring countries like Egypt and Jordan were also extremely nervous. ''We need to keep the pressure on Hamas and not give any discounts,'' the official said. ''The U.S. is with us, that pressure is very important now.''</p>
        <p>''We take Hamas too seriously to think they will change in the short or medium run,'' the official said. ''It will take a lot of pressure to force them to change.''</p>
        <p>The European Union is the largest donor to the Palestinians, but like the United States it lists Hamas as a terrorist organization and is reviewing its aid once Hamas takes power.</p>
        <p>In Israel, an official from the office of Acting Prime Minister Ehud Olmert stepped back from remarks on Sunday by Foreign Minister Tzipi Livni, saying that Mr. Abbas was ''no longer relevant.'' But the official also said Israel had no intention of holding peace talks with him, because he was viewed as powerless to fulfill any agreement with Hamas controlling the government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
