<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="786271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LONG ISLAND SLAVIC FESTIVAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SMITHTOWN (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FESTIVAL SHIPPING AND TOURIST ENTERPRISES</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D9133BF930A3575AC0A963958260" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE KETCHAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'This Is a Football'</p>
        <p>AT their Football 101 clinic for the women of Long Island, the New York Jets handed out T-shirts. Jeanette Teitelbaum of Central Islip quickly grabbed an extra-extra-large. For herself. Mrs. Teitelbaum was eight months pregnant. "I'm having a planned 'section,' " she said of the upcoming delivery. "It's planned around the Jets schedule."</p>
        <p>It's hard to find the words, she said, to describe how devoted a fan her husband, Ken, is. "He wears New Yorks Jets underwear," she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'This Is a Football'</p>
        <p>AT their Football 101 clinic for the women of Long Island, the New York Jets handed out T-shirts. Jeanette Teitelbaum of Central Islip quickly grabbed an extra-extra-large. For herself. Mrs. Teitelbaum was eight months pregnant. "I'm having a planned 'section,' " she said of the upcoming delivery. "It's planned around the Jets schedule."</p>
        <p>It's hard to find the words, she said, to describe how devoted a fan her husband, Ken, is. "He wears New Yorks Jets underwear," she said.</p>
        <p>The Jets have been part of the Teitelbaums' lives since their life together started. "We planned the wedding for an away game date," she said. "Two television sets were set up in the reception. On the top of the wedding cake I had them put a bride and a football player."</p>
        <p>When Mr. Teitelbaum found out that the Jets were having a seminar to teach women the fundamentals of football, he signed up his wife. "He wants me to learn more about the game," Mrs. Teitelbaum said, "so I can watch it on TV while he takes our son to the home games."</p>
        <p>Ever the devoted spouse, there was Mrs. Teitelbaum trying to find a comfortable position in a Long Island Marriott ballroom chair as the Jets quarterback, Boomer Esiason of Manhasset; the coach, Rich Kotite; and the president, Steve Gutman, discussed the intricacies of football, although not too intricately. "Hi," Mr. Esiason said to the 300 women gathered. "I'm the quarterback. I'm going to tell you about touchdowns. They're worth six points. Why? I have no idea."</p>
        <p>A few women giggled. "You don't know how basic to make the clinic," the moderator, Doug Miller of the Jets, had said earlier. "I'm going to start with 'This is the football,' and 'This is the field.' "</p>
        <p>At the moment the women were learning "This is the coach." Mr. Kotite had stepped to the mike. "I'm a Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, boy," he told them. "I feel like the prodigal son coming home. We all have the same accents in this room."</p>
        <p>And the same strong opinions. Mr. Kotite started his talk by showing the players' equipment and discussing the complexities of the game. "We've become so specialized," he said, "we have people who just play on third down." But the women didn't want to talk about the game. They wanted to talk about the team.</p>
        <p>"Why do you do so well in the beginning of the season and so bad the second half?" asked Pam Donnelly of Franklin Square. "When are the New York Jets going to play in New York?" Betty Paulik of Freeport asked. "Right on!" Mike Desepoli of Nesconset shouted. Mr. Desepoli, a season ticket-holder for 31 years, was one of about 20 men who had sneaked into the free seminar. "My wife couldn't make it," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Esiason's spouse did make it. Cheryl Esiason spoke to the crowd about being a football wife rather than a football widow. Mr. Esiason smiled at her. "Football players score points by touchdowns, safeties and field goals," he said. "When we come home we take the kids away from our harried wives. That's another way we score points." The women cheered. A Pinch? No, a Ton</p>
        <p>When cooking for 70,000, measuring ingredients can prove a challenge. A crane probably would have been the kitchen utensil of choice for Doris Boruch of East Northport as she helped mix 3 1/2 tons of cabbage, 1,500 pounds of beef and pork, 800 pounds of rice and onions and 240 quarts of tomato soup into 30,000 stuffed cabbages, or holupki.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Boruch and her compatriots in cooking figured one stuffed cabbage for about every two people. (And you thought you had a problem deciding how many ears of corn to cook for six.)</p>
        <p>Each year the cooks of the Byzantine Catholic Church of the Resurrection in Smithtown seem to come up with the right numbers for their Long Island Slavic Festival. All right, there was the year they ran out of kielbasa. "We rushed people into the city," Bob Greene, a church member, said. "They brought it back in their cars. For weeks we had Cadillacs smelling of kielbasa."</p>
        <p>This weekend through Monday, there should be more than enough at the event, which is held on the church grounds. All the food served is home- cooked, or rather church-cooked, because there is no stove big enough in the homes of the 300 church families. So they cook in the church basement and then store it all in the church freezers. Anna and Joseph Tkach of Kings Park were making 50 pounds of Hungarian goulash. "I've been cooking since May," Mrs. Tkach said.</p>
        <p>Doesn't she get tired of all that food? "We don't eat it," Mrs. Tkach said, "We just cook it." Father Dan Bitsko, the pastor, does take a few samples. "I watch over all the cooking," he said. "I make sure -- I can't say that everything's kosher -- but I make sure everything is blessed."</p>
        <p>Although there are many new Slavic countries, the festival features old Slavic dishes. The cooks attempted to spell a few, like pompushki and golumpki. "We don't care if we know how to spell it," Maryann Moroz Kibrizzi of Smithtown said, "as long as people know how to eat it."</p>
        <p>With no vendors the church families divide the tasks. Rita Holodick of Centereach is in charge of the cleaner-uppers. Doing the dishes for 70,000 would not seem a popular task. "We have somebody who likes to do them," Mrs. Boruch said. "We work as a family."</p>
        <p>A frugal family, that is. Several ingredients have to be imported, such as the Hungarian paprika. "It's expensive," Kristine Melvin of Smithtown said "So we use Price Club oregano." Here and There</p>
        <p>The Town of Hempstead's Hurricane Preparedness Conference had to be called off because of Hurricane Felix. The town had invited 150 hurricane experts to a two-day conference on what to do in case of a hurricane. But since it was hurricane season the experts were too busy doing what needed to be done to talk about it. . . . Amy Fisher just turned 21. That means Ms. Fisher, formerly of Merrick, is now "legal." . . . Seeing professional tennis players up close and personal has always been a draw at the Hamlet Cup tennis tournament in Commack. This year there was an added dimension. Organizers invited Steffi Graf, the No. 1 player in the women's game, to play an exhibition match at the all-male tournament. After the match Ms. Graf's four male guards accompanied her to the club's ladies locker room. But they had to stay out as she walked in, followed by numerous female fans wanting to use the restroom. Putting on lipstick over and over were Lynn Ricca of Smithtown and her sister-in-law, Arlene Ricca. "My daughter wanted to get her autograph," Lynn Ricca said, "and I'm the one who's seeing her in a towel." Mrs. Ricca is no stranger to close proximity to celebrities. "I was standing next to Lou Holtz of Notre Dame once," she recalled, "and I got his autograph. After, he said, 'You've got a real problem with this pencil.' I had given him my eyeliner."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
