<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'War and Peace' in 20 Minutes? If You Care What It Says, Read</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="786410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">READING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOOD, EVELYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D6123DF930A3575AC0A963958260" item-length="368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'War and Peace' in 20 Minutes? If You Care What It Says, Read</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your Aug. 30 obituary of Evelyn Wood neglects to mention that her approach to reading has long since been discredited by serious investigators. Study after study demonstrates that although people can skim at extremely high rates (as much as 100,000 words a minute), they gain substantially no comprehension in the process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your Aug. 30 obituary of Evelyn Wood neglects to mention that her approach to reading has long since been discredited by serious investigators. Study after study demonstrates that although people can skim at extremely high rates (as much as 100,000 words a minute), they gain substantially no comprehension in the process.</p>
        <p>Indeed the researcher Ray Carver concluded that "one must read every word in order to understand the content of written material."</p>
        <p>During the past two decades I have worked with hundreds of literate people who "learned" the Wood and related methods either as adolescents or in adulthood. Not one still uses the techniques. Why? Because failure must result from any method that assumes that reading is primarily a visual task, that one can "take in whole pages at a single glance," that hand movement plays a central role in the reading task, that "subvocalization" is a bad thing, to be suppressed, or that the approach to reading remains independent of the content of the material to be read or the purposes of reading.</p>
        <p>The most efficient techniques grow from a structural analysis of the material and a careful reading of only selected portions, followed by a slow and precise reading of the most vital works. Authors follow conventions when they write, and each discipline adheres to predictable structural and locational conventions.</p>
        <p>By knowing the conventions and structures in the field, readers can attain superb comprehension quickly.</p>
        <p>The most trenchant critiques of "speed reading" emerge, directly or indirectly, from the strongest readers. The writer Stanley Elkin, for example, called reading "fine, precise, detailed work, the infinitely small motor managements of diamond cutters and safecrackers that we do in our heads."</p>
        <p>And Woody Allen quipped, "I took a speed reading course where you run your finger down the middle of the page and was able to read 'War and Peace' in twenty minutes. It's about Russia."</p>
        <p>If you want to know if "it's about Russia," speed right through, but if you care what it says, you must read. PHYLLIS MINDELL  Pittsford, N.Y., Aug. 30, 1995 The writer is an international communications consultant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
