<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="786314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DD133AF930A3575AC0A963958260" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">HUBERT B. HERRING</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ADVERTISING Calvin Klein Zips Up Calvin Klein admit that he's gone too far? Don't be silly. That's the very definition of a Calvin Klein ad -- going too far. Yet sure enough, last week his company said it would scrap, as soon as possible, some jeans ads that had raised cries that they skirted dangerously close to child pornography. Not that it admitted any excess -- no, the ads had been "misunderstood." Calvin Klein ads aren't "that much more erotic than Marky Mark" with his pants down, one consultant said, suggesting that the latest ones were pulled because "these are more conservative times." But a critic for Advertising Age said this retreat might put a damper on ads aimed at "shocking a million people to impress nine."</p>
        <p>As an alternative, there's Prison Blues Clothing, made by inmates in Oregon. "Buy some," the catalog urges, "so if the fashion police knock on your door, you won't have to flush your old clothes down the toilet." Your old clothes, presumably, being your Calvins. MERGERS One Nation, One Bank? It's coming. You can feel it. One nation, one humongous bank. Its name? How about Citi-Chem-Union-BofA-BNY-NBD-PNC-ATM-PDQ? Like snapping Pac-Banks addled by this drought, bankers have been madly buying one another all summer. First Fidelity and First Union, Midlantic and PNC, First Chicago and NBD -- oh, why go on. And for the grand, pre-Labor Day finale, Chase and Chemical linked up, sidling past Citibank to create the nation's biggest bank. Rah-rah, Wall Street said, as investors salivated over all the juicy cost cuts on the way. But those cuts will have a human face: of the banks' 75,000 jobs, 12,000 will vanish, and a third of those will be in the New York area, already bleeding from past losses of bank jobs. And in poor neighborhoods, "cost cuts" often mean just one thing: no more local bank -- though the banks did vow that no branch would close if there's no other nearby.  MORE MERGERS High-Impact Media Aerobics And don't think for a second that media companies will be left behind in this huge-is-best stampede. Disney and ABC team up to create a giant? Well, Time Warner can top that -- no problem. Last week it said it would buy Turner Broadcasting -- if, that is, the mighty Ted Turner agrees to bend his knee to another master, as vice chairman of the new powerhouse. Money might ease the pain: he's worth, on paper, some $600 million more than he was a week ago. There are other hurdles, though. For one thing, John Malone has to be made happy, because his company, Tele-Communications, owns 21 percent of Turner. And the head of HBO, Michael Fuchs, is apparently concerned about Mr. Turner's ascendance. So many egos, so few media giants.  THE DONALD Tees of Gold, Naturally Coming: Trump, the golf course. No, no, make that: Trump, the Golf Course. That's right, Donald Trump, who never tires of buying and selling choice pieces of this unworthy planet, is buying a 14-bedroom Mount Kisco chateau and plans to turn it into a playground for golfers -- those who can afford it, anyway. Can you afford it? Since you asked, forget it. For your first swing, this one will reportedly charge you -- brace yourself -- more than $250,000. That's clearly a bargain, though, when you consider that a typical golf club -- one with an entrance fee that's merely astronomical -- has 400 to 500 members. No such un-Rolexed masses here -- Mr. Trump is said to plan a limit of about 75. COMMUNICATIONS The Day the Numbers Died So, you thought you could have all those modems and pagers and faxes and pocket phones and toys yet undreamed of -- and not, sooner or later, pay the price? Face it: even Bill Gates can't add to life's 10 digits. (If we'd only had, say, 14 fingers, we'd surely have a 14-digit number system -- and just imagine how many possible phone numbers.) But it's a decimal world, alas, and it's running out of those phone numbers. Just last week, Connecticut -- for so long a rustic, one-area-code island in the clanging stream -- suffered the indignity of having an 860 added to its 203. No, there's no "0" or "1" in the middle of 860 -- we're out of those. And by 2025, experts say, we'll need four-digit area codes. But given the pace at which we're inventing gadgets, it'll probably be a lot sooner.  WORK Incredible Shrinking Fridays It's over, folks. No more four-day workweeks. Labor Day means what it says. Don't deny it, now. All summer a lot of people have been sneaking off earlier and earlier on Fridays -- you know, beating the traffic, then beating the people beating the traffic, and on and on in a cascading waterfall that, in some circles, pretty much wiped out Fridays. Can capitalism survive this insidious assault? Oh, yes, the would-be overachievers always insist that even on the beach or in the wild, they've got cellular phones blazing in both hands, like some bizarre latter-day cowboys. And, alas, some of them do. PHYSICS What Goes Up Goes Up If stock prices rise long enough, that proves they'll never fall. Don't believe that bit of revisionist physics? Well, a lot of people clearly do, because in July investors poured more money than ever before into mutual funds that invest in American stocks -- $12.4 billion more than they took out. And that, remember, comes with the stock market somehow hanging on at its lofty levels. But a word of caution, from a fund executive: "The excitement is always highest just before the roller coaster goes over the top." He added, in a plea to investors dreaming of untold riches, that he hoped they "realize that stocks do go down as well as up." What an odd notion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ADVERTISING Calvin Klein Zips Up Calvin Klein admit that he's gone too far? Don't be silly. That's the very definition of a Calvin Klein ad -- going too far. Yet sure enough, last week his company said it would scrap, as soon as possible, some jeans ads that had raised cries that they skirted dangerously close to child pornography. Not that it admitted any excess -- no, the ads had been "misunderstood." Calvin Klein ads aren't "that much more erotic than Marky Mark" with his pants down, one consultant said, suggesting that the latest ones were pulled because "these are more conservative times." But a critic for Advertising Age said this retreat might put a damper on ads aimed at "shocking a million people to impress nine."</p>
        <p>As an alternative, there's Prison Blues Clothing, made by inmates in Oregon. "Buy some," the catalog urges, "so if the fashion police knock on your door, you won't have to flush your old clothes down the toilet." Your old clothes, presumably, being your Calvins. MERGERS One Nation, One Bank? It's coming. You can feel it. One nation, one humongous bank. Its name? How about Citi-Chem-Union-BofA-BNY-NBD-PNC-ATM-PDQ? Like snapping Pac-Banks addled by this drought, bankers have been madly buying one another all summer. First Fidelity and First Union, Midlantic and PNC, First Chicago and NBD -- oh, why go on. And for the grand, pre-Labor Day finale, Chase and Chemical linked up, sidling past Citibank to create the nation's biggest bank. Rah-rah, Wall Street said, as investors salivated over all the juicy cost cuts on the way. But those cuts will have a human face: of the banks' 75,000 jobs, 12,000 will vanish, and a third of those will be in the New York area, already bleeding from past losses of bank jobs. And in poor neighborhoods, "cost cuts" often mean just one thing: no more local bank -- though the banks did vow that no branch would close if there's no other nearby.  MORE MERGERS High-Impact Media Aerobics And don't think for a second that media companies will be left behind in this huge-is-best stampede. Disney and ABC team up to create a giant? Well, Time Warner can top that -- no problem. Last week it said it would buy Turner Broadcasting -- if, that is, the mighty Ted Turner agrees to bend his knee to another master, as vice chairman of the new powerhouse. Money might ease the pain: he's worth, on paper, some $600 million more than he was a week ago. There are other hurdles, though. For one thing, John Malone has to be made happy, because his company, Tele-Communications, owns 21 percent of Turner. And the head of HBO, Michael Fuchs, is apparently concerned about Mr. Turner's ascendance. So many egos, so few media giants.  THE DONALD Tees of Gold, Naturally Coming: Trump, the golf course. No, no, make that: Trump, the Golf Course. That's right, Donald Trump, who never tires of buying and selling choice pieces of this unworthy planet, is buying a 14-bedroom Mount Kisco chateau and plans to turn it into a playground for golfers -- those who can afford it, anyway. Can you afford it? Since you asked, forget it. For your first swing, this one will reportedly charge you -- brace yourself -- more than $250,000. That's clearly a bargain, though, when you consider that a typical golf club -- one with an entrance fee that's merely astronomical -- has 400 to 500 members. No such un-Rolexed masses here -- Mr. Trump is said to plan a limit of about 75. COMMUNICATIONS The Day the Numbers Died So, you thought you could have all those modems and pagers and faxes and pocket phones and toys yet undreamed of -- and not, sooner or later, pay the price? Face it: even Bill Gates can't add to life's 10 digits. (If we'd only had, say, 14 fingers, we'd surely have a 14-digit number system -- and just imagine how many possible phone numbers.) But it's a decimal world, alas, and it's running out of those phone numbers. Just last week, Connecticut -- for so long a rustic, one-area-code island in the clanging stream -- suffered the indignity of having an 860 added to its 203. No, there's no "0" or "1" in the middle of 860 -- we're out of those. And by 2025, experts say, we'll need four-digit area codes. But given the pace at which we're inventing gadgets, it'll probably be a lot sooner.  WORK Incredible Shrinking Fridays It's over, folks. No more four-day workweeks. Labor Day means what it says. Don't deny it, now. All summer a lot of people have been sneaking off earlier and earlier on Fridays -- you know, beating the traffic, then beating the people beating the traffic, and on and on in a cascading waterfall that, in some circles, pretty much wiped out Fridays. Can capitalism survive this insidious assault? Oh, yes, the would-be overachievers always insist that even on the beach or in the wild, they've got cellular phones blazing in both hands, like some bizarre latter-day cowboys. And, alas, some of them do. PHYSICS What Goes Up Goes Up If stock prices rise long enough, that proves they'll never fall. Don't believe that bit of revisionist physics? Well, a lot of people clearly do, because in July investors poured more money than ever before into mutual funds that invest in American stocks -- $12.4 billion more than they took out. And that, remember, comes with the stock market somehow hanging on at its lofty levels. But a word of caution, from a fund executive: "The excitement is always highest just before the roller coaster goes over the top." He added, in a plea to investors dreaming of untold riches, that he hoped they "realize that stocks do go down as well as up." What an odd notion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
