<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is B.I.D. Plan One Too Many?</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="786250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RED HOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RED HOOK (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D91F38F930A3575AC0A963958260" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is B.I.D. Plan One Too Many?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wally Shapiro, who has run a Red Hook warehouse for 41 years, supports a plan to create a business improvement district that would levy fees on businesses to pay for private security, sanitation and marketing. "The B.I.D. would give us services the city is supposed to supply, but doesn't have money to adequately provide," he said as he walked past the stacks of carpets, tungsten and potpourri he stores.</p>
        <p>Damian Lubrano, who has watched the staff of his Barge Autobody shop on Coffey Street dwindle to 6 from 22, questioned what he would get for his money. "We have a good Sanitation Department and a good Police Department and they have always worked with us," said Mr. Lubrano, who was born and raised in Red Hook. "What business owner wants a new tax?"</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wally Shapiro, who has run a Red Hook warehouse for 41 years, supports a plan to create a business improvement district that would levy fees on businesses to pay for private security, sanitation and marketing. "The B.I.D. would give us services the city is supposed to supply, but doesn't have money to adequately provide," he said as he walked past the stacks of carpets, tungsten and potpourri he stores.</p>
        <p>Damian Lubrano, who has watched the staff of his Barge Autobody shop on Coffey Street dwindle to 6 from 22, questioned what he would get for his money. "We have a good Sanitation Department and a good Police Department and they have always worked with us," said Mr. Lubrano, who was born and raised in Red Hook. "What business owner wants a new tax?"</p>
        <p>The plan for a Red Hook Business Improvement District has exposed tensions between businesses and residents over how to share their isolated peninsula on the far side of the Gowanus Expressway.</p>
        <p>It is not the only plan in the works for Red Hook. Noting that the neighborhood's population fell to 11,000 from 21,000 since 1950 as it lost waterfront jobs and industries, Community Board 6 released a broad urban renewal plan last year calling for new housing, a new high school, a waterfront museum and other economic development.</p>
        <p>While the two plans are not mutually exclusive, disputes have arisen between businesses and residents over the sites of truck routes, new housing and the new high school. The City Planning Commission, which received the urban renewal plan enthusiastically this year, delayed its vote to give businesses a chance to weigh in on the proposals.</p>
        <p>"I think a lot of people would like the businesses to go away and leave them with a nice waterfront community without trucks, without workmen sitting outside eating lunch," said Bette Stoltz, the executive director of the South Brooklyn Development Corporation, a business group that created the B.I.D. proposal with a grant from the state's Urban Development Corporation. "They would rather have an espresso place than a ball-bearing manufacturer."</p>
        <p>Unlike many of the city's 33 business improvement districts, the one in Red Hook would focus on industrial businesses like manufacturers, warehouses, bakeries and distributors. A main retail strip, along Van Brunt Street, would be excluded. Ms. Stoltz said that stores there were reluctant to join the district and that many would have trouble paying the fee.</p>
        <p>Supporters of both plans have held several meetings this summer to try to resolve their differences. "In a general sense, the plan and the B.I.D. are complementary documents," said Craig Hammerman, the district manager for Community Board 6. "They seek to accomplish the same goal: a stronger community, one that would be less impacted by a national recession." M.C.  BUDGET A B.I.D.'s Bottom Line The proposed Business Improvement District for Red Hook would include approximately 230 industrial businesses. Each would be assessed dues based on the size and value of its properties. This is what the dues would go toward:</p>
        <p>Security $68,250 (increase private security patrol to 84 hours/week from 44)</p>
        <p>Administration $52,100 (salary for 3 part-time staff members to run district and write grant proposals) Sanitation and Maintenance $37,500 (clean illegally dumped trash, remove graffiti) Marketing and Promotion $35,400 (banners, landscaped public spaces and brochures) Contingency $16,750 (miscellaneous expenses and to cover members behind in their dues) Total $210,000 (Source: South Brooklyn Local Development Corp.)  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RED HOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
