<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Timorese Vote in Prelude to Nationhood</title>
    <meta content="Y31TIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/31/international/asia/31TIMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Timor</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Timor</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDE1330F932A0575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Timorese Vote in Prelude to Nationhood</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Timorese Vote in Prelude to Nationhood</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>BANGKOK, Thailand, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>East Timorese election draws huge turnout in party-like atmosphere as residents take crucial step in establishing self rule after 25 years of Indonesian occupation and two years of United Nations administration; election will create 88-member Assembly that is to draw up new constitution and prepare for full independent nationhood next year; photo ()</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was the day the people of East Timor had been waiting for. After 25 years of Indonesian occupation and two years of United Nations administration, they voted today for a government of their own.</p>
        <p>The turnout was huge and peaceful, officials said. People stood for hours in the hot sun to elect an 88-member Assembly that is to draw up a new constitution and prepare for full independent nationhood next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 25 years of Indonesian occupation and two years of United Nations administration, the people of East Timor were gleeful at getting a government of their own</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was the day the people of East Timor had been waiting for. After 25 years of Indonesian occupation and two years of United Nations administration, they voted today for a government of their own.</p>
        <p>The turnout was huge and peaceful, officials said. People stood for hours in the hot sun to elect an 88-member Assembly that is to draw up a new constitution and prepare for full independent nationhood next year.</p>
        <p>Apart from a brief, fractious interlude in 1975 when their Portuguese overlords withdrew, it will be the first time that East Timor has ruled itself since the Portuguese arrived 400 years ago.</p>
        <p>A presidential election is likely early next year and José Alexandre Gusmão, the highly popular independence leader, is widely expected to be chosen to take on the difficult task of building, from the ground up, the world's newest nation.</p>
        <p>''This ballot shows the maturity of our people, their willingness to go through the democratic system, their willingness to avoid violence,'' Mr. Gusmão said today.</p>
        <p>The United Nations said more than 90 percent of the 425,000 eligible voters chose from among 16 parties. Unofficial results were expected early next week, with official results to be announced on Sept. 10. The Fretilin Party, which led the independence struggle against Indonesia, was expected to win the most assembly seats.</p>
        <p>''I'm very happy today,'' said Ivete de Oliveira, 26, who heads a women's rights office, speaking by telephone from the capital, Dili. ''This is the first time for us. We are choosing our own leaders. This is what we have been waiting for for 25 years.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Oliveira, who observed the vote in several towns and villages, said the atmosphere was ''like a party.''</p>
        <p>People began lining up at polling places long before dawn, she said, many walking for hours from their homes in the mountains, many wearing their Sunday best and bringing picnics of holiday food.</p>
        <p>Some of them, particularly old women, did not know what they were voting for, Ms. Oliveira said, but they were excited just to be voting.</p>
        <p>Today was also the anniversary of one of the most intense and courageous days in East Timor's history.  On Aug. 30, 1999, nearly 98 percent of East Timor's voters defied threats and cast their ballots in a referendum on independence. Many emerged to vote from hiding places in the hills despite a determined campaign of violence and intimidation orchestrated by the Indonesian military and carried out by local militias.</p>
        <p>When almost 90 percent of the voters chose independence, the militias went on a coordinated rampage, killing as many as 1,000 people, deporting more than 200,000 to neighboring Indonesia and destroying 80 percent of the territory's buildings. Some 50,000 people remain under the control of the militias in camps in the Indonesian territory of West Timor.</p>
        <p>Election observers said there was some residual fear among voters today, given the lingering trauma of that earlier vote. But security was heavy and people were mostly reassured.</p>
        <p>''I am very happy but not surprised to report that all is well and the election is taking place in a calm and peaceful atmosphere,'' said Carlos Valenzuela, the chief electoral officer for the United Nations, which is administering the election.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Oliveira asked voters what they hoped for for their country, she said, ''most said they want peace, and then they want their leaders to have good relations and not to fight each other.''</p>
        <p>''They want prices to go down and they want to have a better education for their children,'' she said. ''They want transportation not only in the city but going to the villages so they can come to the city to buy and sell. These things, and also health care, these are the things people hope for in the future.''</p>
        <p>For the new government, providing those basic services will be a major challenge. Most of East Timor remains in ruins, with much of its work force unemployed.</p>
        <p>The United Nations administrator for East Timor, Sergio Vieira de Mello, said his caretaker government was likely to cede sovereignty to the East Timorese after the presidential election, which is expected in the first part of next year.</p>
        <p>But he said a considerable administrative and security presence would probably remain to aid the new government.</p>
        <p>When José Ramos Horta, who won a Nobel Peace Prize in 1996 for his pro-independence campaign, arrived at a polling place to cast his vote, he was overcome with the emotion of the day, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>''My work for 24 years is done.'' he said. ''People have come in freedom and without violence to vote today.''</p>
        <p>When a crowd caught sight of Mr. Gusmão and began chanting his nom de guerre, ''Viva Xanana!'' he shouted back: ''Do not say that. Say instead, 'Viva freedom and liberty!' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
