<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scofflaws Give Communities A New Line Item</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="529308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCOFFLAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDA153FF934A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scofflaws Give Communities A New Line Item</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST fall New Britain paid $1,875 for five Denver boots, devices that immobilize illegally parked cars until their owners pay outstanding parking tickets. "We had more than $60,000 in unpaid tickets, and we had to do something," said the supervisor of the New Britain Police Department's traffic division, Sgt. Joseph S. Rizzo.</p>
        <p>It proved to be a good investment: New Britain got back more than half the cost of the boots the first day, snaring two of the city's worst scofflaws, who owed $1,000 between them. Since then, the boots have brought in more than $15,000, Sgt. Rizzo said. As tax collections fall and municipal expenses rise, towns are looking at all sources of revenues, and parking ticket receipts are getting increasing attention. Across the state, officials are using a variety of methods to collect unpaid parking tickets, which can amount to hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST fall New Britain paid $1,875 for five Denver boots, devices that immobilize illegally parked cars until their owners pay outstanding parking tickets. "We had more than $60,000 in unpaid tickets, and we had to do something," said the supervisor of the New Britain Police Department's traffic division, Sgt. Joseph S. Rizzo.</p>
        <p>It proved to be a good investment: New Britain got back more than half the cost of the boots the first day, snaring two of the city's worst scofflaws, who owed $1,000 between them. Since then, the boots have brought in more than $15,000, Sgt. Rizzo said. As tax collections fall and municipal expenses rise, towns are looking at all sources of revenues, and parking ticket receipts are getting increasing attention. Across the state, officials are using a variety of methods to collect unpaid parking tickets, which can amount to hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>Besides the boot, which is used in at least a dozen cities and towns, municipalities are employing collection agencies, installing computer systems to more readily identify scofflaws, or impounding the vehicles of those with unpaid fines.</p>
        <p>Some towns are starting to use a law to block parking-ticket scofflaws from registering their cars, and adopting ordinances to double or triple the fines after a certain number of days.</p>
        <p>Towns are also going after more parking-ticket revenue by raising the fines so it is no longer practical to park in a no-parking zone. Bridgeport, a financially beleaguered city, hired six meter attendants this year to patrol the downtown district; they were looking for drivers parking 20 minutes in a 15-minute zone, parking too far from the curb or parking in a loading zone.</p>
        <p>Police say that even in these times, people are willing to risk a ticket if it means saving a few steps. Some tickets are put on vehicles parked just a few feet from garages, where people could have parked legally and a lot less expensively. The Collector of Revenues in Mansfield, Pamela V. Wells, said that the number of tickets issued in that town, primarily on the University of Connecticut campus, had been climbing sharply, from 30,000 in 1990 to 35,000 last year. The Town Council decided it was due in part to an old fine schedule -- tickets were all $10, with no late penalties. So they raised the levies, depending on the offense, to as much as $25, and instituted a $5 charge if the tickets were not paid in 21 days. Still, the town expects to issue about 30,000 tickets this year, based on the trend so far, Ms. Wells said.</p>
        <p>The boot, which has been around for the last 10 years, is becoming one of the most popular methods of cracking down on scofflaws.</p>
        <p>In Greenwich, one of the first towns to employ the device, a traffic technician, Scott T. McConnell, said that a list of scofflaws was updated every two weeks and given to police officers. "Most of the tickets are given out in the central business district, to people who are there on a regular basis," Mr. McConnell said. "They have to come to work, and if they're on that list they're going to be spotted sooner or later."</p>
        <p>Mr. McConnell said it was not unusual to snare people with $500 or $600 worth of parking tickets. "We have five boots, and they're used pretty steadily," he said.</p>
        <p>In New Britain the new boots are being deployed with a more sophisticated method of tracking scofflaws: hand-held computers that get updated daily. "We catch up with people a lot quicker," Sergeant Rizzo said. "If someone makes the scofflaw list on a Wednesday night patrol, we know about it by Thursday morning, and the next ticket he gets, he gets the boot."</p>
        <p>The computers also print out tickets, Sergeant Rizzo said, which speeds up the process considerably. "We can tag a whole line of cars in 40 seconds -- zip, zip, zip," he said. "We're getting real high-tech."</p>
        <p>Sergeant Rizzo said that the police were also concerned about a $5 ticket for overtime parking in a one-hour zone being cheaper than paying $8 for a parking garage for the day. As a result the police asked for, and got, a city ordinance that allows for multiple ticketing: after one hour the car gets its first ticket, after two hours it gets its second, and so on. "If you get five tickets in a restricted area, that's $50, but after 10 days it's $150," Sergeant Rizzo said. "It can add up to some real money pretty quickly."  'Question of Image'</p>
        <p>Parking violators aside, not everyone likes the boot. The parking enforcement administrator for the City of New Haven, Charles A. Wailonis, said that he has some boots but does not use them. "It's a question of image," he said. "Driving down the street and seeing a car with a boot on it doesn't translate into, 'Welcome to New Haven.' "</p>
        <p>Even in New Haven, which has $506,000 of unpaid tickets from people who owe at least $150 each in fines, scofflaws do not get off any easier.  When their cars are spotted they are towed to an impoundment area where they are held until the owner pays the fines as well as towing and storage charges. Mr. Wailonis said New Haven was impounding 40 to 60 cars a week. "A year ago we were probably impounding about 30 percent fewer cars than we are right now," Mr. Wailonis said. "Some of it is the fact that more people are not paying their parking tickets, probably because of the economy," he said.</p>
        <p>But it is also because those who hand out the tickets have been given radios that allow them to call for a tow truck.</p>
        <p>Last month the city also began using a different towing company each day rather than a different one for each call. "That allows them to beef up their staff on their day, and keep a couple of trucks right in the downtown, ready to go," Mr. Wailonis said. "That's cut way down on our response time."</p>
        <p>Mr. Wailonis also said that New Haven has started to take advantage of a law that allows the state's five largest cities to block scofflaws from registering their cars. In January it sent a list of 300 scofflaws to the State Department of Motor Vehicles. On April 28 it sent 375 more names. The registrations on those cars, including vehicles owned by people from out of town, cannot be renewed until the parking fines are paid.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wells said Mansfield and other smaller towns were lobbying for the same power. She said it could have a particular effect in a college town like Mansfield. "A lot of these cars are driven to campus by the student but registered to the mom or dad, and when the notice of the tickets comes home the student is told to take care of it," Ms. Wells said. "If all of a sudden they can't renew their registration, that will certainly get some action."</p>
        <p>The Tax Collector for Bristol, Esmonde J. Phelan, said that that city collects about $20,000 a year in parking fines, but he is not sure how many scofflaws there are because the records have never been computerized. "I'd like to say we're collecting two out of every three tickets that we're giving out, but I'm not sure the collection rate is that good," Mr. Phelan said.</p>
        <p>A project to computerize those records by June has been delayed because of personnel cuts, Mr. Phelan said, "but there's no question we have to computerize that list if we want to maximize our collections.</p>
        <p>"There's no question the process of computerizing the records would pay for itself in short order," he said. "And, as long as there's a need to give a parking ticket, we should have a vehicle to collect it. Otherwise, it's not fair to the people who pay their fines on time."</p>
        <p>In Waterbury, the Deputy Police Superintendent, Richard J. White, said the city recently doubled the price of a parking ticket, and imposed late fees for the first time -- though they offered scofflaws amnesty for a month. The program was so successful that one scofflaw called from his new home in the Middle West to settle a bill of several hundred dollars, Mr. White said.</p>
        <p>"There was a little criticism that we shouldn't give them the chance to pay at the old rate," Mr. White said. "But the fact is, 100 percent of nothing is still nothing."</p>
        <p>Mr. White said Waterbury has also started to take advantage of the law that allows it to block scofflaws from registering their car. "We'd like to get some boots, but with times the way they are we can't afford the investment," he said. "I think we'll accomplish just as much as we did if we impounded the car this way but it's a longer process. The registration period in Connecticut is two years, so if you've just registered your car you're in the clear for two years, but we're going to get you eventually."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
