<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coaster With a Message: Your Table Is Ready</title>
    <meta content="26HOWW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1499813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HOW IT WORKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/How It Works</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DC113BF936A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coaster With a Message: Your Table Is Ready</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY SELINGO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S early on a Wednesday night and the wait for a table at Jaleo, a popular Washington tapas restaurant, is 20 minutes and growing. Along the bar, customers line up three deep for pitchers of sangria.</p>
        <p>Almost to the beat of the flamenco music in the background, red lights flash on top of the bar. It's not a light show, but rather a signal that the next table is ready for the lucky person holding the pulsating light.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S early on a Wednesday night and the wait for a table at Jaleo, a popular Washington tapas restaurant, is 20 minutes and growing. Along the bar, customers line up three deep for pitchers of sangria.</p>
        <p>Almost to the beat of the flamenco music in the background, red lights flash on top of the bar. It's not a light show, but rather a signal that the next table is ready for the lucky person holding the pulsating light.</p>
        <p>Once only a mainstay of casual restaurants like TGI Friday's and Olive Garden, paging systems are being used more widely as restaurants look for better ways to move diners in and out quickly. Table turnover is important: Half of a typical restaurant's revenue is generated on Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>''Restaurants don't want you to get frustrated so that you go to a competitor down the street,'' said David Stokoe, president of JTech Communications, a manufacturer of paging systems for restaurants. ''It creates a bond between the customer and the restaurant, and allows people to move around instead of gathering around the hostess waiting for their name to be called out.''</p>
        <p>Ken Lovegreen, the founder of Long Range Systems, another company that makes pagers, developed one of the most popular versions, a coaster pager, in the early 1990's. He had the idea at a restaurant where a hostess was handing out bulky pagers that many customers fumbled and dropped.</p>
        <p>''I thought, why not have something that can double as a coaster at the bar and lights up when the table is ready?'' said Mr. Lovegreen, who recently designed a lobster-shaped pager for seafood restaurants and a sombrero for Mexican restaurants.</p>
        <p>The water-resistant stackable coaster pager has been popular. Long Range Systems, for example, sells about 100,000 of the devices a year. A typical system, which includes a transmitter, a charger and 40 pagers, costs about $3,000.</p>
        <p>While the pagers are capable of being reached up to two miles from their base, most restaurants buy systems with a much smaller range -- usually around 1,000 feet -- in the hope that customers will remain nearby and perhaps spend money at the bar while they wait.</p>
        <p>The limited range also reduces the time it takes to seat customers and keeps them from wandering to another restaurant.</p>
        <p>When waiting customers decide to go elsewhere, they sometimes forget to return the pager, which costs about $80 to replace. Jaleo loses ''a few pagers a month, especially in the summer,'' said Antoni Yalemos, the director of operations. It's a particular problem at Jaleo's suburban outpost in Bethesda, Md., which is situated in a busy strip of restaurants and shops.</p>
        <p>Mon Ami Gabi, a French bistro a few doors from Jaleo in Bethesda, is experimenting with a paging system that uses a customer's cellphone, partly as a way of reducing the number of lost pagers, said Matt Lourick, the restaurant's general manager. When a customer's table is ready, the paging device calls his cellphone and plays a recorded message.</p>
        <p>''Customers love the option,'' Mr. Lourick said. About a quarter of his guests use it, he said, and so far, no one has been hesitant to give a phone number. ''This way they can go browse at Barnes &amp; Noble across the street without worrying about losing their table,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Lovegreen of Long Range Systems predicts that cellphone technology will eventually make its way into more restaurants, Mr. Stokoe of JTech questions whether a typical customer would be willing to give his phone number to a stranger. Moreover, ''restaurants don't want you to be 14 miles away when your table is ready,'' Mr. Stokoe said. ''They want you to be 14 feet away.''</p>
        <p>The two companies are now entangled in a legal battle over the wait-list pagers. Long Range Systems filed a lawsuit against JTech in May alleging that the company infringed on patents for the coaster pager and the cellphone device. The case is pending.</p>
        <p>HOW IT WORKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
