<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuji Agrees to Buy Rest of Subaru in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUBARU OF AMERICA INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FUJI HEAVY INDUSTRIES LTD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JUDGE, PAUL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91630F937A35756C0A966958260" item-length="404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuji Agrees to Buy Rest of Subaru in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL C. JUDGE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JUDGE, PAUL C</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Fuji Heavy Industries Ltd., the Japanese maker of Subaru cars, said today that it had agreed to buy the half of Subaru of America Inc. it did not own in a deal valued at $412.2 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Fuji Heavy Industries Ltd., the Japanese maker of Subaru cars, said today that it had agreed to buy the half of Subaru of America Inc. it did not own in a deal valued at $412.2 million.</p>
        <p>Fuji Heavy Industries Ltd., the Japanese maker of Subaru cars, said today that it had agreed to buy the half of Subaru of America Inc. it did not own in a deal valued at $412.2 million.</p>
        <p>The acquisition will give Fuji full control over the marketing and distribution of Subaru cars in the United States. Subaru of America, based in Cherry Hill, N.J., has shared responsibility for developing new products and marketing them in this country.</p>
        <p>A committee of Subaru of America directors not affiliated with Fuji has recommended that the $8.50-a-share offer be accepted, according to a statement issued jointly by the companies.</p>
        <p>A Fuji spokeswoman said the company did not plan any management changes at Subaru of America, which is the only publicly held affiliate of a Japanese car maker in this country.</p>
        <p>Fuji's offer is sweeter for non-Fuji shareholders than the $6-a-share bid by the Japanese auto maker in January. The companies plan to raise the additional $2.50 a share through selling Subaru's portfolio of automobile leases, which the company holds on cars bought by customers through its dealerships. Subaru said in its 1989 annual report that the auto leases were worth $120 million.</p>
        <p>The company's shares were the third most active on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, rising by $1.625 each, or by 25.5 percent, to $8, on a volume of more than 4.8 million shares.</p>
        <p>Subaru was one of the first auto makers to offer a four-wheel-drive vehicle, which sold well in the United States. But the company was slow to develop new products, analysts say, and lost market share to competitors in the four-wheel-drive category.</p>
        <p>In the year that ended last Oct. 31, Subaru had a net loss of $42.4 million, on sales of $1.7 billion, compared with a $57.9 million loss, on sales of $1.7 billion a year earlier. The company has 48.5 million shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>Subaru officials said the company would call its annual shareholders meeting, delayed since February, sometime in the third quarter of the year. The shareholders will be asked at the meeting to vote on the proposed sale to Fuji, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Fuji's offer to buy the rest of Subaru comes despite recent financial troubles for the parent company. Fuji said in March that it would post a loss for 1989 of 23 billion yen, or about $145.6 million, after saying only a few weeks earlier that its losses would total 3 billion yen, or about $18.9 million.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
