<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newark's New Image Buoys Mayor on Eve of Election</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19900509T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAYORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, SHARPE (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD1631F937A35756C0A966958260" item-length="1477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newark's New Image Buoys Mayor on Eve of Election</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Every city has its symbol, and Newark's may still be the 1967 riots that scorched the city and left 23 people dead. But Sharpe James, a believer in the strength of symbols, has spent as much time over his four years as mayor trying to change that image as he has trying to solve the most serious problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Every city has its symbol, and Newark's may still be the 1967 riots that scorched the city and left 23 people dead. But Sharpe James, a believer in the strength of symbols, has spent as much time over his four years as mayor trying to change that image as he has trying to solve the most serious problems.</p>
        <p>Every city has its symbol, and Newark's may still be the 1967 riots that scorched the city and left 23 people dead. But Sharpe James, a believer in the strength of symbols, has spent as much time over his four years as mayor trying to change that image as he has trying to solve the most serious problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. James spent $100,000 to install 775 nylon banners printed with flags or civic messages on downtown lampposts. Changing the banners every six months costs $30,000. He knows the banners may not help the 100,000 residents on public assistance nor shelter the 16,000 homeless people nor reduce the 50 percent high-school dropout rate. But he said he believed they were absolutely necessary.</p>
        <p>''What they are is like the eagle somebody puts over a garage,'' he said. ''It just says: 'I live here. I care.' ''</p>
        <p>Bond Rating Upgraded to BBB+</p>
        <p>As Mr. James approaches the election next Tuesday unopposed for a second term, business and community leaders give him high marks for image building and say there is substance behind the symbols.</p>
        <p>The state's largest home builder is putting up 1,100 residences in the Central Ward. For the first time in 20 years the city's bond rating has been upgraded, to BBB+ from BBB, saving the city millions in interest.</p>
        <p>Business leaders say the plans of Blue Cross-Blue Shield of New Jersey to move 2,500 workers from the suburbs to a new office tower downtown show that Newark is bouncing back.</p>
        <p>No one, not even Mr. James, believes all the problems have been solved. Crime and drug abuse are still out of control. Much of the housing is substandard, and rents are still climbing. Schools are old and often wild, and children born here have a 1-in-5 chance of dying before reaching their first birthday. Still, using his energy and the talents of newly hired employees, as well as big corporations, Mr. James has managed to keep many of the promises he made in 1986, when he turned out his solidly entrenched predecessor, Kenneth A. Gibson, the first black mayor of a major Northeastern city. Mr. James has gained national attention as a second-generation black mayor in a city where members of minority groups are no longer satisfied just to have one of their own in City Hall. Having severely criticized Mr. Gibson in the campaign, Mr. James has had to deliver a combination of economic development, municipal services and fiscal accountability downtown and in the neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>In a city that once seemed to have lost hope, many of Mr. James's initiatives have been symbolic, like the banners on Broad Street, the newly organized mounted police, the hundreds of new trees and a new law that requires security gates on downtown stores to be open meshed, so the city does not appear to be under seige.</p>
        <p>Residents and community leaders said the biggest change in this city of 315,000, founded in 1666 by a band of Puritans searching for a heaven-on-earth, may be a can-do attitude, personified by the Mayor's unstoppable image.</p>
        <p>''He has uplifted the spirit of the city,'' E. James Ferland, chairman of the Public Service Electric and Gas Company, which has its headquarters in Newark, said at a recent gathering of executives at the newly refurbished Newark Museum. ''He has changed the way Newark thinks about itself and the way others think about Newark.''</p>
        <p>Much of the turnabout is a spillover from the state's economic vigor of the 80's. Newark was late in reaping the benefits of that expansion, but now it remains active while the suburbs have grown quieter.</p>
        <p>Richard W. Roper, director of the program for New Jersey affairs at the Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs at Princeton University, said Mr. James's personal energy and enthusiasm for leadership suited Newark's needs in the mid-80's in much the same way that the low-key style of Mr. Gibson fit the need for calm in the contentious days of the 1970's.</p>
        <p>There are other differences between the two men that reflect their contrasting styles and differing challenges.</p>
        <p>Changes in Circumstances</p>
        <p>''Gibson focused at the beginning on direct delivery of social and human services,'' Mr. Roper said. But as the 80's began, the Federal assistance supporting such programs evaporated, and ''it was clear that by Gibson's third-term economic development was what he should have been attempting to secure for the community.''</p>
        <p>The people of Newark had observed Mr. James from 1970 to 1986 as a maverick City Council member, with independent ideas and humorous barbs as his trademark, but lacking a clear agenda. By the time he took over at City Hall, the people were demanding safe streets and affordable housing and they wanted them at once.</p>
        <p>''Ken Gibson was a hero,'' Mr. James said in a recent interview. ''I'm supposed to be a miracle worker.''</p>
        <p>Mr. James spends as much time in the streets as in City Hall and said he felt the impatience keenly. ''I got elected by criticizing an entrenched black leader,'' he said. ''The day I took over, the people wanted me to solve all the problems.''</p>
        <p>Administrator From Atlanta</p>
        <p>His first priority was to avoid the mistakes of other black mayors who, after winning City Hall, had rewarded supporters by giving them jobs without regard to ability.</p>
        <p>Mr. James conducted a national search for staff members. His most important appointment was Richard A. Monteilh as business administrator. Mr. Monteilh was administrative and financial officer of Atlanta and had earned a national reputation for an efficient, responsible style.</p>
        <p>Mr. James and Mr. Monteilh began by hiring the accounting firm of Coopers &amp; Lybrand to study management; 700 recommendations came out of the study. The most important dealt with improving the 80 percent rate for collecting taxes, water bills, parking tickets and other fees. The city became tough, putting liens on properties, turning off water and towing scofflaws' cars. The collection rate is up to 95 percent, and revenues have risen $30 million.</p>
        <p>Conflict With School Board</p>
        <p>Although many lots remain, more than $3 billion in commercial development has been completed or proposed since 1986, and 2,000 houses and apartments have been built. The city also won state support for a proposed $200 million performing-arts center.</p>
        <p>Despite the general smoothness of his first term, Mr. James has had setbacks. He has engaged in a running battle with the Board of Education over patronage, accountability and its $421 million budget. By comparison, the city budget is $346 million. Last week voters approved a budget for the next school year despite his opposition.</p>
        <p>Jump in Infant Mortality</p>
        <p>Poverty and unemployment rates remain significantly higher than the state average, the incidence of AIDS is among the highest of any major city in the nation, and recently there has been a troubling rise in infant mortality, which jumped from 15.5 percent in 1987 to 19.3 percent in 1988, according to the latest available figures. The state average is 9.8 percent.</p>
        <p>City officials said drug abuse, in particular crack, is at the root of many of those problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. James also fought for control of the Housing Authority. This year he won the power to appoint its members, but he has been stymied in his plan to demolish most of the hellish high-rise projects until the units to be destroyed are replaced one for one.</p>
        <p>Critics fault the Mayor for being too eager to promote the city and offer tax abatements to developers. ''If the city is going to give abatements and land, it should get something more in return,'' said Victor DeLuca, executive director of the Ironbound Community Corporation and a candidate for councilman-at-large. Mr. James said it was the abatements that kept developers interested in Newark when they abandoned the suburbs.</p>
        <p>Impatience With Small Details</p>
        <p>In an interview at City Hall, Mr. James said he had grown more cooperative in four years and he conceded one longstanding fault, an impatience with the small details of government.</p>
        <p>''I hate meetings just for meetings' sake,'' he said. ''I'm a problem solver. I'm not a numbers person. I don't sit down and play with slide rules and calculators. I have a hard time reading my telephone bill.''</p>
        <p>Though he professes to not being a fiscal expert, Mr. James said the two accomplishments he is proudest of are the upgrading of the bond rating and keeping administrative budget increases to below 4 percent every year.</p>
        <p>In his next term he plans to focus on adding police officers, building rental housing and improving schools.</p>
        <p>Bettering the image also remains high on his list, even if many of the efforts are purely symbolic. He recently decided not to replace his 1986 Lincoln with a new car. But he did have the license plates changed, from NWK 86 to NWK 90.</p>
        <p>''If you can't buy a new suit, you buy new shoes,'' he said. ''Putting 90 on there makes it feel new.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 9, 1990, Wednesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about Sharpe James's first term as Mayor of Newark misstated the infant mortality rates for Newark and New Jersey. In 1988, the last year for which figures are available, the city's rate was 19.3 per 1,000 births, and the state's was 9.8 per 1,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 9, 1990, Wednesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on Friday about Sharpe James's first term as Mayor of Newark misstated the infant mortality rates for Newark and New Jersey. In 1988, the last year for which figures are available, the city's rate was 19.3 per 1,000 births, and the state's was 9.8 per 1,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
