<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Did President Send Lewinsky a Signal With His Necktie?</title>
    <meta content="19NECK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE ATTIRE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DD153DF93AA2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Did President Send Lewinsky a Signal With His Necktie?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON VAN NATTA Jr. and JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Clinton strode into the Rose Garden on Aug. 6, his jazzy gold and navy necktie stood out sharply against his white shirt and sent a jolt through certain lawyers around town.</p>
        <p>They were not clotheshorses struck by a rare Washington fashion statement. They were prosecutors in the office of Kenneth W. Starr, wondering if the President might have dressed to obstruct justice -- by sending a secret signal to Monica S. Lewinsky as she testified before the grand jury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When President Clinton strode into the Rose Garden on Aug. 6, his jazzy gold and navy necktie stood out sharply against his white shirt and sent a jolt through certain lawyers around town.</p>
        <p>They were not clotheshorses struck by a rare Washington fashion statement. They were prosecutors in the office of Kenneth W. Starr, wondering if the President might have dressed to obstruct justice -- by sending a secret signal to Monica S. Lewinsky as she testified before the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky, the former intern at the center of the investigation into sex and lies at the White House, had said in her debriefings with prosecutors in recent weeks that she had given Mr. Clinton the Zegna tie on his 50th birthday, in August 1996.</p>
        <p>According to what Ms. Lewinsky told a close friend, Ms. Lewinsky told the President that because they would not be able to see each other every day, ''when I see you wearing this tie I'll know that I am close to your heart.''</p>
        <p>On the day of her testimony, Mr. Clinton was inveighing against handguns in a televised ceremony. Prosecutors apparently wondered, Was the tie a sign, a  plea for solidarity?</p>
        <p>If it was, it did not work. Ms. Lewinsky did not learn of Mr. Clinton's choice of neckties until she turned on the television that evening and saw a clip of him in the Rose Garden, her friends said.</p>
        <p>That day, she had contradicted her sworn affidavit, testifying that she and the President had had an affair in the White House.</p>
        <p>The necktie was evidently covered by a subpoena sent to the White House for gifts and other evidence by prosecutors for Mr. Starr. But apparently it was not turned over by Mr. Clinton at that time.</p>
        <p>Clothing has become something of a leitmotif in Mr. Starr's investigation. He has pursued a great deal of circumstantial evidence in his investigation of Mr. Clinton, including gifts like a T-shirt that the President gave her. One of Mr. Starr's potentially strongest pieces of evidence is a navy blue dress that Ms. Lewinsky turned over to prosecutors. They are having it tested to determine whether it bears stains from a sexual encounter with the President.</p>
        <p>On Monday, during more than four hours of testimony at the White House, prosecutors asked Mr. Clinton why he chose to wear that particular tie on that particular day, one Clinton adviser said. He described the inquiry into neckwear as an example of how the Starr investigation had gone rambling along irrelevant and peculiar byways. ''The obstruction of justice stuff was kind of goofy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The President was said to have smiled at the question and expressed some bafflement. Perry Mason-style, the prosecutors then pulled out a photograph of the tie. Mr. Clinton was said to have indicated that it was possible she had given it to him but that he certainly was not trying to communicate anything by wearing it. The exchange was said to have provided a rare light moment in a grueling session.</p>
        <p>But the tie has meant a lot to Ms. Lewinsky, who has looked at television reports to see if the President was wearing it. Ms. Lewinsky had noticed that Mr. Clinton had worn the tie she had given him on three occasions in recent months: on the day he left for his trip to China, the day he returned from China and several days later, in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky had given Mr. Clinton six ties in their 18-month relationship, which began in November 1995.</p>
        <p>In his Monday night speech, Mr. Clinton contradicted his previous denials and acknowledged he had had a relationship with Ms. Lewinsky that was ''not appropriate'' and ''wrong.'' That night, Ms. Lewinsky's friends were dismayed that he seemed to send her no signals whatsoever.</p>
        <p>He wore a patterned blue tie, of undetermined provenance.</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE ATTIRE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
