<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home-Style Cuisine Acts Like a Magnet</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="432313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MILFORD (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PURELY COUNTRY (MILFORD, CONN, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB173AF937A15750C0A967958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home-Style Cuisine Acts Like a Magnet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PURELY COUNTRY is a label that evokes homey, natural, nostalgic images. A restaurant with such a name is like a magnet for people who eat out a lot and crave a sense of the homemade -- or at least home style, judging by the crowds that fill Purely Country restaurant in the center of Milford.</p>
        <p>Stepping over the threshold of this former luncheonette, our first emotion was dismay. A long counter, with globe lights of differing sizes, ceiling fans and a narrow passageway past tables for two to the rear, where tables flank the aisle, evoked a sense of uncomfortable crowding. But once ensconced at a table, with a dot-matrix-printed menu in hand, reassurance crept back. The menu is intriguing, with inventive touches. And the fact that it changes weekly also suggests a degree of creativity -- or at least ambition -- in the kitchen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PURELY COUNTRY is a label that evokes homey, natural, nostalgic images. A restaurant with such a name is like a magnet for people who eat out a lot and crave a sense of the homemade -- or at least home style, judging by the crowds that fill Purely Country restaurant in the center of Milford.</p>
        <p>Stepping over the threshold of this former luncheonette, our first emotion was dismay. A long counter, with globe lights of differing sizes, ceiling fans and a narrow passageway past tables for two to the rear, where tables flank the aisle, evoked a sense of uncomfortable crowding. But once ensconced at a table, with a dot-matrix-printed menu in hand, reassurance crept back. The menu is intriguing, with inventive touches. And the fact that it changes weekly also suggests a degree of creativity -- or at least ambition -- in the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Of four starters we sampled one evening, two were successful, a third passable and only one a disappointment. One of the three was a real knockout: Finnish carrot-potato pancakes with pear sauce on one side and a dab of sour cream on the other. The fresh pear sauce and sour cream complemented the two medium-size hot pancakes beautifully, with all the flavors resonating in synchronization.</p>
        <p>Another concept that worked was mushroom caps stuffed with a congenial mixture of chopped eggplant, mozzarella and roasted red peppers. Chilled sesame noodles with teriyaki chicken had more eye appeal than flavor, with the noodles on one side of the plate and small slices of chicken breast fanned out on the other. It was a fresh-tasting dish, though there was minimal evidence of teriyaki or sesame flavor. The last starter, to be erased as quickly as possible, was tortellini creole soup, a disaster that tasted like unadulterated canned tomatoes with flabby pieces of plain pasta (not stuffed tortellini) adrift in it.</p>
        <p>Culinary adventurousness was further demonstrated in several entrees. Roast duck (a well-crisped half) was served with a tabouleh and a tantalizing orange sauce that was called Persian and included onions, garlic and nutmeg. Almost as winsome was chicken Manchamantel, chicken breast in a fresh-tasting sauce of roasted tomatoes, pineapple, banana, pear and lime juice.</p>
        <p>Added sparkle came with a scoop of sweet pea guacamole. The consistency was the same as the usual mashed avocado variety, but the peas made a pleasing taste change, marrying easily with cilantro, lemon juice and the other guacamole ingredients.</p>
        <p>Beef medallions Olivier were juicy and tender, enhanced by artichoke hearts and black olives in a succulent brown sauce accented by Madeira and bacon. Cornmeal-crusted catfish, served with a fresh remoulade, also deserved high praise for light, fresh, crisp and well-peppered flavor.</p>
        <p>Desserts, like the dense brown bread served at the start of the meal, are made on the premises. A special prize was the orange-chocolate torte, a fudgy, rich chocolate slab with a hint of Triple Sec and with kumquat slices on top and scattered throughout the cake -- a superb combination.</p>
        <p>Also mouthwatering was pear-ginger pie, served warm, with a dollop of soft, fresh-whipped cream. The crust was crisp and full of flavor. Four mint-chocolate meringues were well-flavored, if a mite dry. A Bing cherry rose spice cake had rose leaves on top to add flavor, but alas the cake was stale.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner for four cost $87.45 before tax, tip and drinks. Prices on the serviceable wine list were good, but the number of whites was disproportionately large, and many vintages listed were out of stock.</p>
        <p>A word should be added about portions: There has been a restaurant trend in recent years to monstrously large appetizer servings (usually at prices to match), making it difficult for the diner of average appetite to polish off a similarly large entree as well. Purely Country has returned to the original meaning of the word appetizer, with adequate but not gargantuan portions, and most of the prices reflect this. All in all, the modest-looking restaurant has much to take pride in, and with a new chef in residence, it promises to get better and better. Purely Country</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>89 River Street, Milford (diagonally across from Town Hall). 877-7141.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: A former luncheonette, with counter and tables, floral wallpaper, mismatched chairs.</p>
        <p>Service: Friendly, helpful and prompt.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Finnish carrot-potato pancakes, stuffed mushrooms, beef medallions Olivier, roast duck with Persian orange sauce, chicken Manchamantel, cornmeal-crusted catfish, pear-ginger pie, orange chocolate torte.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch entrees $5.95 to $6.95, dinner entrees $12.95 to $17.25.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: Mastercard and Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: Breakfast 8:30 to 11 A.M. Monday through Friday, lunch 11:30 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. Monday through Friday, dinner 6 to 10 P.M. Thursday, Friday and Saturday (Sundays after April 1), brunch (after April 1) 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Not accepted at lunch, strongly recommended at dinner.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Ground-level access. Ratings: Poor Satisfactory Good Very Good Excellent Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings are based on the reviewer's reaction to food and price in relation to comparable establishments.</p>
        <p>The Times Restaurant Line offers capsule reviews by cuisine, price and location (in New York City and suburbs), published in the last 18 months. Touch-line telephones only: 1-900-988-0101 (75 cents a minute).</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
