<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chess</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC113FF937A35755C0A967958260" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chess</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BYRNE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is sometimes possible to unsettle a solid positional player by hyperaggressive tactics, but two questions have to be answered before trying this: how sound is your action? And how strong is the opponent? If he is one of the highest-rated players in the world, second thoughts are in order.</p>
        <p>In the first round of the Fifth Verenigde Spaarbank Tournament in Amsterdam on May 2, Viktor Korchnoi failed the quiz by trying too unreliable an attack against too tough an adversary. The erstwhile challenger for the world championship, who now lives in Switzerland, chose a wild, flimsy onslaught against the Soviet grandmaster Valery Salov, who repulsed it smartly nd won when Korchnoi blundered a piece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is sometimes possible to unsettle a solid positional player by hyperaggressive tactics, but two questions have to be answered before trying this: how sound is your action? And how strong is the opponent? If he is one of the highest-rated players in the world, second thoughts are in order.</p>
        <p>In the first round of the Fifth Verenigde Spaarbank Tournament in Amsterdam on May 2, Viktor Korchnoi failed the quiz by trying too unreliable an attack against too tough an adversary. The erstwhile challenger for the world championship, who now lives in Switzerland, chose a wild, flimsy onslaught against the Soviet grandmaster Valery Salov, who repulsed it smartly nd won when Korchnoi blundered a piece.</p>
        <p>Salov went on to tie for first place with the British grandmaster Nigel Short.FINAL STANDINGS</p>
        <p>Player</p>
        <p>Pts.</p>
        <p>Salov</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Short</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Karpov</p>
        <p>5 1/2</p>
        <p>Kasparov</p>
        <p>5 1/2</p>
        <p>Korchnoi</p>
        <p>4 1/2</p>
        <p>Hjartarson</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Timman</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Gurevich, M.</p>
        <p>3 1/2</p>
        <p>Ljubojevic</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Van der Wiel</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>This was the second tournament in succession in which Gary Kasparov, who is accustomed to winning everything in sight, was denied first prize.</p>
        <p>The sequence that ends in 4 cd came in this game from a Slav Defense setup against an English Opening, but in the openings books, starved for space, it is listed as a Caro-Kann Defense, which is its more usual origin. Black can play 4 . . . Qd5 5 Nc3 Qd6 6 d4 Nf6 7 Nge2 e6 8 g3 Be7 9 Bg2 O-O 10 O-O Rd8, although it seems that most players are not entirely happy with Black's lack of development. The move 4 . . . Nf6, used by Salov here, postpones the recapture of the pawn in favor of quick mobilization.</p>
        <p>The purpose of 5 Qa4 is to force an interposition at d7 and thus block Black's attack on the d5 pawn. White will then try to hang on to the material sacrificed.</p>
        <p>On 6 . . . g6, the preferred method for White has been considered 7 g3, but after 7 . . . Bg7 8 Bg2 O-O 9 Nge2, Black can offer a potent gambit with 9 . . . e6!? 10 de?! (both 10 d6 and 10 Nf4 are safer) Nc5 11 ef Rf7 12 Qc4 Nd3 13 Kf1 Bf5.</p>
        <p>Instead, the hyperaggressive move Korchnoi selected, 7 g4, though it drives the black king knight out on a limb after 7 . . . Bg7 8 g5 Nh5, represents an appreciable loosening of the white pawn position. Of course, on 9 Nge2 O-O 10 Ng3, Black must allow 11 Nh5 gh because 10 . . . Ng3? 11 hg would open the h file for a mating attack by White.</p>
        <p>But meanwhile Black has at his disposal the thematic gambit with 10 . . . e6!? that makes White's aggression look wobbly in view of his lack of development. After 11 Nh5 gh, Korchnoi declined to open more lines for Black with 12 de Nc5. All this had appeared before, in a Gurevic-Rytov game in the Soviet Union in 1967, which had continued with 12 Qh4 Ne5 13 Bg2 Ng6, yielding Black powerful attacking chances. Could Korchnoi have supposed that his divergence with 12 d4 Nb6 13 Qd1 ed 14 Qh5 would have amounted to a real improvement?</p>
        <p>On 15 . . . Re8, Korchnoi's king would not have been safe on the queenside after 16 O-O-O Rc8 17 Bd3 Qd7. For example, 18 Kb1 Bd3 19 Rd3 Qf5 20 Qe2 Bd4! is very unpleasant. But after 16 Bb5 Re6 17 O-O Nc4 18 Bc4 dc, Salov's pressure was palpable.</p>
        <p>After 20 f4, Salov's 20 . . . b5! threatened 21 . . . b4 followed by the capture of the d5 pawn or the b2 pawn or both. The white position would have been crumbling. But at this point, Korchnoi blundered with 21 Nb5?, and after the fork 21 . . . Qe8 revealed that he had to drop a piece, he gave up with 13 minutes remaining on his clock.</p>
        <p>CARO KANN DEFENSE</p>
        <p>White</p>
        <p>Black</p>
        <p>Korchnoi</p>
        <p>Salov</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>c4</p>
        <p>c6</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>e4</p>
        <p>d5</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>ed</p>
        <p>cd</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>cd</p>
        <p>Nf6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Qa4</p>
        <p>Nbd7</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Nc3</p>
        <p>g6</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>g4</p>
        <p>Bg7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>g5</p>
        <p>Nh5</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Nfe2</p>
        <p>O-O</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Ng3</p>
        <p>e6</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Nh5</p>
        <p>gh</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>d4</p>
        <p>Nb6</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Qd1</p>
        <p>ed</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Qh5</p>
        <p>Bf5</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>Be3</p>
        <p>Re8</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Bb5</p>
        <p>Re6</p>
        <p>17</p>
        <p>O-O</p>
        <p>Nc4</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>Bc4</p>
        <p>dc</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>d5</p>
        <p>Rg6</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>f4</p>
        <p>b5</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Nb5</p>
        <p>Qe8</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Resigns</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
