<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Health Care of America's Children</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO (NBC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">C EVERETT KOOP, MD (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHILDREN AT RISK (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB123DF937A35755C0A967958260" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Health Care of America's Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. C. Everett Koop, the former United States Surgeon General, begins a painfully timely series at 10 tonight on NBC . "Children at Risk," the first of his five hourlong reports, calls attention to the millions of families that cannot obtain health insurance and to the effects of spotty medical care on children in rural areas and the inner cities.</p>
        <p>NBC, whose recent record of documentaries has not been impressive, made a wise decision in going to the MacNeil/Lehrer production company for "C. Everett Koop, M.D." In the next few weeks, Dr. Koop will look at preventive health care, at the problems of adolescents and the elderly and at ideas for providing decent health care for everyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. C. Everett Koop, the former United States Surgeon General, begins a painfully timely series at 10 tonight on NBC . "Children at Risk," the first of his five hourlong reports, calls attention to the millions of families that cannot obtain health insurance and to the effects of spotty medical care on children in rural areas and the inner cities.</p>
        <p>NBC, whose recent record of documentaries has not been impressive, made a wise decision in going to the MacNeil/Lehrer production company for "C. Everett Koop, M.D." In the next few weeks, Dr. Koop will look at preventive health care, at the problems of adolescents and the elderly and at ideas for providing decent health care for everyone.</p>
        <p>Throughout rural America, Dr. Koop notes, hospitals are closing and doctors are departing. People are left to rely on small understaffed clinics or distant hospitals. A Kentucky mother tells him that her family's take-home pay of $168 a week is barely enough to cover the rent, with nothing left for illness. The doctor, a hands-on reporter, gives a child an immunization shot at a clinic in West Virginia that may have to shut down.</p>
        <p>In Pennsylvania, he talks to a sales clerk, who is among the 37 million Americans without health insurance. This man's asthmatic son needs a degree of attention that the family cannot afford. "I've been a working stiff all my life," the father says. "I don't want anything for nothing." He speaks for many. The program notes that many strikes in recent years have been caused by workers' fear of having their health benefits reduced or eliminated. A woman with a chronically ill child says, "We're being wiped out."</p>
        <p>In Harlem, where he delivered babies in 1940, Dr. Koop describes the consequences of "poverty and all that goes with it." One thing that goes with it is a mortality rate for black babies that is 40 to 50 percent higher than that of white babies. These days, one in five children born at Harlem Hospital has been exposed to drugs in the womb. A doctor there says, "We are losing an entire generation of children."</p>
        <p>Tonight's hour starts with a few provocative questions from Dr. Daniel Callahan, the director of the Hastings Center in Briarcliff Manor, N.Y., a nonprofit research and educational organization involved in the study of ethics in medicine, the environment and biotechnology. About the high bills for high-tech equipment, he asks, "How much progress can we afford?" He faces the unpleasant reality that the nation may have to choose between basic child care and heroic efforts to save the dying. Like all the doctors and nurses interviewed here, Dr. Koop refuses to make such choices, and he concludes with pleas for more and better care of every sort. But Dr. Callahan's questions sound a dark and unresolved note in this troubling program.</p>
        <p>C. Everett Koop, M.D.Children at Risk Produced by Judy Reemstsma, Mort Silverstein, Kathy Sulkes, Ed Gray and Steve Brand for MacNeil/Lehrer Productions; Phil Burton, executive producer. At 10 tonight on NBC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
