<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Beleaguered Tarkanian Takes His Case To Regents</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NEVADA (LAS VEGAS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TARKANIAN, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE1F3AF937A35755C0A967958260" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Beleaguered Tarkanian Takes His Case To Regents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The University of Nevada Board of Regents held a closed-door meeting in Las Vegas yesterday with basketball coach Jerry Tarkanian, and when the five-hour session had ended, the coach emerged with his job intact, but his status uncertain.</p>
        <p>Tarkanian said he was pleased with the regents' response to his explanation of the latest troubles of his U.N.L.V. basketball team. It was Tarkanian who sought yesterday's session with the board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The University of Nevada Board of Regents held a closed-door meeting in Las Vegas yesterday with basketball coach Jerry Tarkanian, and when the five-hour session had ended, the coach emerged with his job intact, but his status uncertain.</p>
        <p>Tarkanian said he was pleased with the regents' response to his explanation of the latest troubles of his U.N.L.V. basketball team. It was Tarkanian who sought yesterday's session with the board.</p>
        <p>"The regents were very attentive, they listened to what I had to say, they gave me an opportunity to go through everything," Tarkanian told The Associated Press as he left the meeting. "I was very pleased. It was an excellent meeting."</p>
        <p>There are two years remaining on Tarkanian's contract. Regent June Whitley said no vote was taken on the contract, adding that the board is prohibited from taking a vote in executive session.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lonnie Hammagren, one of the nine regents, said he had emerged from the meeting in better spirits. "Tireder, but better," he said, adding that "before, all I knew was what I read in the newspaper, and now I've been briefed."</p>
        <p>The meeting went longer than necessary, he said, because "everybody talked too much." Troublesome Photos</p>
        <p>The special session of the regents was convened in response to the publication last week of photographs showing three players from the 1990 championship team -- David Butler, Anderson Hunt and Moses Scurry -- relaxing at the home of Richard Perry, who has twice been convicted of sports bribery. The photos were taken before the 1989-90 season.</p>
        <p>The pictures have raised new questions about the integrity of the U.N.L.V. basketball program. The team has been placed on probation by the National Collegiate Athletic Association for recruiting violations dating to the mid-1970's, and is the subject of a separate N.C.A.A. investigation that is now under way.</p>
        <p>Before yesterday's meeting of the regents, eight former U.N.L.V. players, including two -- Sidney Green and Armon Gilliam -- now in the National Basketball Association, said at a news conference that Tarkanian had warned them to stay away from gamblers. Three other players, from the 1990-91 team -- Larry Johnson, Stacey Augmon and Greg Anthony -- sent letters of support for Tarkanian.</p>
        <p>"He told us to stay away from Perry or our basketball careers would be over," said David Rice, who played on last year's team. "He said Perry was a dangerous person to be around." School President at Meeting</p>
        <p>Robert Maxson, the U.N.L.V. president, attended the closed meeting along with Dennis Finfrock, the U.N.L.V. athletic director, and attorneys for the university.</p>
        <p>The Board of Regents is an elected body. It hires the university president to carry out its policies.</p>
        <p>The photos, showing the three players in a hot tub with Perry and playing basketball with him, were published May 26 in The Las Vegas Review-Journal. The photos may have been the most damaging blow yet for Tarkanian, whose popularity in Nevada has been weakening in the face of continuing battles with the N.C.A.A.</p>
        <p>Although the board informally discussed convening yesterday's meeting, a formal request actually came from Tarkanian, who sought the session through Joseph Foley, a friend and member of the board.</p>
        <p>Personnel sessions are not uncommon, but it is rare for the regents to discuss a mid-level employee, such as Tarkanian.  Tarkanian Cites Warnings</p>
        <p>Tarkanian maintains that Perry had nothing to do with the U.N.L.V. program. He said he warned his players to stay away from Perry and that he asked Perry to stay away from the players.</p>
        <p>Tarkanian, who is paid $203,976 a year by U.N.L.V., has tenure at the university and a contract clause that says he cannot be fired unless he knowingly commits a major N.C.A.A. infraction.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
