<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Purchasers Report Dip in Growth Rate</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="133284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PURCHASING MANAGEMENT, NATIONAL ASSN OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EICHENWALD, KURT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD9123AF937A35757C0A96E948260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Purchasers Report Dip in Growth Rate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EICHENWALD, KURT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The economy continued to expand in March but the rate of growth slowed for the third month in a row, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report scheduled for release today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The economy continued to expand in March but the rate of growth slowed for the third month in a row, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report scheduled for release today.</p>
        <p>The economy continued to expand in March but the rate of growth slowed for the third month in a row, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report scheduled for release today.</p>
        <p>But the report contained some signs that the economy would be more vigorous in the second quarter. The growth rate in new orders increased considerably in March, and, in a sign that the trade deficit will drop, more of the member companies reported higher orders for exports.</p>
        <p>Although the growth in production remained strong, inventories declined sharply and vendor deliveries were slow, according to the report. Prices increased, but at a significantly slower rate than in the last five months. When considering normal seasonal variations, employment declined slightly as well, the report said. Sign of 'Continued Improvement'</p>
        <p>''The economy completed the first quarter with moderate if not substantial growth,'' said Robert J. Bretz, chairman of the purchasing group's business survey committee. ''The healthy increase in new orders, particularly export orders, signals continued improvement in the economy in the second quarter.''</p>
        <p>The report, which has been issued nearly every month since 1931, is based on surveys of managers at more than 250 companies in 21 industries. Economists consider its findings an early statistical indicator of the previous month's economic performance.</p>
        <p>The association's composite index, reflecting March's slowdown in the growth rate, declined to 53.3 percent, from 54.9 percent in February and 57.4 percent in January. In December, before the slide in the growth rate began, the index stood at 61.8 percent.</p>
        <p>An index reading above 50 percent indicates that the economy is generally expanding, while a level below 50 percent implies a contraction.</p>
        <p>March was the 20th consecutive month that the index, which is seasonally adjusted, exceeded 50 percent. But it was the lowest figure since 54.7 percent was reported for April 1987. New Orders Rise Again</p>
        <p>New orders rose for the 15th consecutive month, with a rate of growth of 24 percent, exceeding the 18 percent rate in February. Thirty-two percent of the purchasers reported a jump in orders, and 8 percent reported a decline. The rest reported no change.</p>
        <p>The report said these figures indicate a strong rise in production for April. It also said that, with 41 percent of the exporting companies reporting growth in export orders, the trade deficit should decline.</p>
        <p>Production also expanded for the 15th consecutive month. Although the growth was described as ''healthy,'' the rate was lower than in February. Twenty-nine percent of the managers reported stronger production in March, while 10 percent said production was off. In February, 32 percent said production was stronger while 9 percent said it had declined.</p>
        <p>For the 18th consecutive month, more purchasers - 23 percent - reported that vendor deliveries had slowed. Only 5 percent said that deliveries were faster. But the figures marked an improvement over February, when 26 percent reported a slowing of deliveries. The lower rate of slowing in March reflected the slowdown in production, the report said. Sharp Decline in Inventories</p>
        <p>Inventories declined sharply in March after growing modestly in the previous two months. The net drop of 13 percent is the largest since July 1987. Ten percent of the purchasers reported that inventories were higher, while 23 percent reported that they had fallen. ''These data should convince skeptics that manufacturers are definitely not building inventories,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>March was also the eighth consecutive month that employment grew. Sixteen percent of the producers reported more people employed, while 11 percent said employment had fallen. But the report said that, accounting for normal seasonal increases, employment should be viewed as in decline.</p>
        <p>At the same time, prices continued to rise at a slower pace than in the previous month. The difference between the 55 percent of the producers who reported higher prices and the 3 percent who reported drops was the smallest since September 1987.</p>
        <p>The report said prices rose for corrugated shipping containers, paper products, caustic soda, aluminum and plastic products, as well as for brass, steel, polyethylene and methanol. Among the products lower in price were fuel oil, diesel fuel, natural gas and chlorine.</p>
        <p>Shortages were reported in a range of goods that included aluminum, nickel, steel, printing paper, caustic soda and methanol.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
