<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haiti Legislature Declares the Presidency Vacant</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="479200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORGANIZATION OF AMERICAN STATES (OAS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA113EF93BA35753C1A967958260" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haiti Legislature Declares the Presidency Vacant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti, Oct. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under pressure from belligerent soldiers, Haiti's legislature tonight voted to apply a constitutional article that declares the presidency vacant and clear the way for the naming of a provisional leader who would be required to call new elections within 90 days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under pressure from belligerent soldiers, Haiti's legislature tonight voted to apply a constitutional article that declares the presidency vacant and clear the way for the naming of a provisional leader who would be required to call new elections within 90 days.</p>
        <p>The decision was announced during a visit by a delegation from the Organization of American States, which returned to Haiti this afternoon to demand the reinstatement of President Jean-Bertrand Aristide, exiled in a military coup last Monday. The army accused Father Aristide of violating the constitution and seeking to create a separate armed unit as his own political tool.</p>
        <p>Parliament's decision came shortly before 6 P.M., before the President of the National Assembly had returned from an airport meeting with the O.A.S. delegation.</p>
        <p>Asked why the decision had been made in such haste, one senator said: "The declaration had already been decided upon. We had to do it this way because the army was angry. They wanted it done right away."  Violence at the Airport</p>
        <p>More than 100 armed soldiers milled about the Parliament building. While the legislators were voting, a group of soldiers became violent at Haiti's international airport, beating and arresting the Mayor of Port-au-Prince, Evans Paul, and forcing the cancellation of a trip by a group of politicians who were traveling to Venezuela to negotiate Father Aristide's return.</p>
        <p>Father Aristide flew to Caracas, Venezuela, from Washington on Sunday night and met with the Venezuelan leader, Carlos Andres Perez. He flew to Kingston, Jamaica, today and met with the Jamaican Prime Minister, Michael Manley.</p>
        <p>Soldiers at the Haitian airport beat on passing cars, saying, "We want a President today!" and "We want the country!" said one witness who had just arrived from Miami. He said at least one shot was fired at the airport.</p>
        <p>Other soldiers surrounded a second-floor meeting room where members of the O.A.S. team, including Bernard W. Aronson, Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs, were discussing the country's crisis with Haitian officials. The delegation left the country shortly afterward.  Broadcasts Are Halted</p>
        <p>With the exception of Government programming, consisting of music punctuated by announcements of Parliament's action, all Haitian radio and television stations stopped broadcasting this evening. As night fell, automatic-weapons fire could be heard often around the city.</p>
        <p>A Government radio announcement said there was no possibility of Father Aristide's return as President and attributed the gunfire around Parliament to the special military unit created by Father Aristide, even though Government soldiers in uniform were seen in the area.</p>
        <p>The decision by Parliament, if applied, would call for the naming of Joseph Nerette, the senior justice on Haiti's Supreme Court, to serve temporarily as President.</p>
        <p>The decision, made while soldiers nervously patrolled the streets after rumors circulated this afternoon of President Aristide's impending return, places Haiti on a collision course with Western Hemisphere nations that have vowed to enforce economic sanctions against the country until the ousted President is returned to office.</p>
        <p>"We have come down with an extremely clear mandate that Aristide must be restored," said Carlos Iturralde, the Bolivian Foreign Minister who is chairman of the O.A.S. delegation, several hours before Parliament's decision was announced. "We want to make it clear that our position is very serious, that economic sanctions are there to stay and soon there will be a lack of oil." Fears of Foreign Intervention</p>
        <p>Referring to the Haitian legislature's proposal to name a provisional President who would conduct elections within 90 days, Mr. Iturralde said, before the O.A.S. meeting began, "We cannot allow the presidency to be declared vacant."</p>
        <p>After several days with little vocal support for Father Aristide among politicians not already tied to him, leaders of two political groupings said they were traveling to Venezuela tonight to meet with the President to help seek a way for his return.</p>
        <p>Victor Benoit, a leader of Konakom, a left-of-center political organization that had backed Father Aristide's candidacy for President before distancing itself from him after he was elected, said he was seeking to avoid foreign military intervention in Haiti or the total isolation of the country.</p>
        <p>With sentiment in the army strongly against Father Aristide's return and strong momentum in Parliament for an interim solution to the country's power vacuum, another O.A.S. official called the situation "very delicate and potentially very deadly."</p>
        <p>Father Aristide, responding to strong concerns both in Haiti and abroad over his the reality of commitment to human rights, issued a statement denouncing violence and pledging respect for his country's institutions. His remarks included an explicit disavowal of "Pere Lebrun," the street-corner lynchings with burning tires that he has been widely seen as condoning in previous speeches.</p>
        <p>"The three powers in our Constitution will have to mutually respect each other and respect the Constitution," the statement said. "As President of the republic, we condemn once again all forms of violence, all forms of violence from whatever source: Pere Lebrun or repressive violence."</p>
        <p>Experts in Haitian military affairs expressed concern that any effort to bring about the return of Father Aristide quickly would provoke a violent reaction among ordinary soldiers, whom they described as being nearly unanimous in their opposition to the exiled President.</p>
        <p>"The high command is in command insofar as there is no question of Aristide returning," one expert said. "They have no choice." Soldiers' Banter</p>
        <p>Soldiers were talking extemporaneously on the Government-controlled radio during the night.</p>
        <p>One soldier who said that he was "a little drunk" proclaimed: "There's no going back now." He asked the news media to "open their doors so that people can express their happiness" about the legislature's decision to vacate the presidency.</p>
        <p>Several neighborhoods in the capital continued to report sporadic incidents of nighttime violence by heavily armed men, apparently undisciplined soldiers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
