<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 White House Aides Appear Before Starr's Grand Jury</title>
    <meta content="Y27STA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1005316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Marsha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernreich, Nancy V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D7173BF934A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 White House Aides Appear Before Starr's Grand Jury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marsha Scott and Nancy Hernreich, two mid-level White House aides, are brought before Federal grand jury, apparently in effort to learn more about Monica S Lewinsky's job history at White House and her visits with Pres Clinton; this is second grand jury appearance for both women; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors brought two mid-level White House aides before a Federal grand jury today, apparently in an effort to learn more about Monica S. Lewinsky's job history at the White House and her visits with President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Marsha Scott, chief of staff in the White House personnel office, spent the morning before the grand jury, her second appearance at the Federal courthouse here in a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prosecutors brought two mid-level White House aides before a Federal grand jury today, apparently in an effort to learn more about Monica S. Lewinsky's job history at the White House and her visits with President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Marsha Scott, chief of staff in the White House personnel office, spent the morning before the grand jury, her second appearance at the Federal courthouse here in a week.</p>
        <p>She was followed by Nancy Hernreich, chief of Oval Office operations, who sits just outside the President's office and oversees his daily schedule. Ms. Hernreich too had previously appeared before the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Both women declined to comment about their testimony, given behind closed doors in accordance with grand jury secrecy.</p>
        <p>Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, is trying to compile a list of Ms. Lewinsky's visits with the President and to establish whether she and Mr. Clinton were alone together in the Oval Office and, if so, how often, according to witnesses who have been before the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr is also taking testimony from officials who can describe Ms. Lewinsky's duties at the White House and explain why she was transferred to a low-level job at the Pentagon in April 1996.</p>
        <p>The independent counsel is investigating accusations that Mr. Clinton had a sexual relationship with Ms. Lewinsky and then instructed her and others to deny it in sworn statements made for Paula Corbin Jones's lawsuit against him. Mr. Clinton has adamantly denied the accusations.</p>
        <p>Among the evidence newly sought by Mr. Starr are records from Ms. Jones's lawyers regarding four women whom they have tried to link to Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Donovan Campbell, Ms. Jones's chief lawyer, said today that he had received a subpoena from the independent counsel demanding depositions and other records he had from the four women. The Jones legal team has tried to establish a pattern of Mr. Clinton's engaging in extramarital relations with numerous women and then using job offers or other inducements to win their silence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell said Mr. Starr was seeking information about Dolly Kyle Browing, Beth Coulson, Marilyn Jo Jenkins and Juanita Broaddrick. In his deposition in the Jones suit, Mr. Clinton denied having had sex with any of the first three women; no mention of Ms. Broaddrick appears in any of the sections of the President's deposition that have been made public.</p>
        <p>White House officials and Mr. Clinton's private lawyers have complained that Mr. Starr and Ms. Jones's team appear to be cooperating in an investigation of the President's private life.</p>
        <p>''Ken Starr has decided to hijack the Paula Jones suit, and they have become mirror images of one another,'' said Rahm Emanuel, senior adviser to the President. ''That's what Ken Starr's $40 million and four-year investigation has come to.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell said there had been no ''collusion'' with the independent counsel. ''We never did that,'' he said in a telephone interview from his office in Dallas. ''We have never shared information with Judge Starr except in response to lawful subpoenas he has served to our office.''</p>
        <p>Officials of the independent counsel's office have also repeatedly denied collusion.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Lewinsky inquiry, the independent counsel is investigating Mr. Clinton's business dealings in Arkansas in the so-called Whitewater affair.</p>
        <p>Some witnesses before the Whitewater grand jury in Little Rock, Ark.,  have reported in recent days that they were asked about documents found in a briefcase discovered last year at the home of Vincent W. Foster Jr., deputy White House counsel and former law partner of Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foster committed suicide in July 1993. The briefcase found at his home contained a duplicate set of billing records that detail Mrs. Clinton's work for Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan, a now-defunct Arkansas thrift organization at the center of the Whitewater inquiry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr once sought the originals of the billing records. They were never found, but a copy of some of them appeared mysteriously in the White House residence two years after they had been subpoenaed.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Starr's inquiry proceeded today, Representative Henry J. Hyde, the Illinois Republican who heads the House Judiciary Committee, said he had hired an experienced Federal prosecutor as chief investigative counsel for the committee.</p>
        <p>The new investigator, David P. Schippers, 67, will direct a wide-ranging look by the committee into the operations of the Justice Department, Mr. Hyde said. Mr. Schippers will be paid from a new $1.3 million allocation set aside for the committee from a House reserve fund.</p>
        <p>Democrats complained that the hiring of Mr. Schippers was a thinly disguised effort to beef up the Republican committee staff in anticipation of an impeachment inquiry.</p>
        <p>''Tens of millions of dollars have been spent to investigate the Clinton Administration -- an unprecedented amount,'' complained Representative John Conyers Jr. of Michigan, the committee's ranking Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schippers, a defense lawyer, is former head of the Justice Department's organized crime and racketeering section in Chicago. He is a  Democrat, a committee aide said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
