<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="27SPAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1005171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DA163BF934A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="5645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS  Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. On permanent display are costumes, set pieces, filming equipment and other items relating to film, television and video. Exhibitions include ''Behind the Screen,'' a permanent display with more than 1,000 artifacts that illustrate the production, marketing and exhibition of moving images. Daily screenings include classic shorts, shown in Tut's Fever Movie Palace: Through April 3, ''Cops'' (1922), with Buster Keaton. Screening times: 1, 2:30 and 4 P.M. ''True Stories: The Films of Barbara Kopple,'' four documentaries from the Academy Award-winning filmmaker will be screened tomorrow and Sunday. Tomorrow at 2 P.M., ''Harlan County, U.S.A.'' (1977), focusing on the tension between Kentucky coal miners and their bosses, and at 5 P.M., ''American Dream'' (1989), a look at labor's weakening position at a Minnesota meat-packing company. On Sunday at 1:30 P.M., ''Fallen Champ: The Untold Story of Mike Tyson'' (1993), chronicling the heavyweight champion's rise and fall; at 4:30 P.M., Ms. Kopple will be on hand for a ''Pinewood Dialogue,'' where she will preview her new ''Wild Man Blues'' (1997), a candid look at Woody Allen and Soon-Yi Previn during Mr. Allen's European jazz tour. Tickets for the ''Pinewood Dialogue'' and the screening will be $20. Also, ''Computer Space '98,'' a continuing exhibition of classic arcade games and contemporary home-entertainment software that visitors can play. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. All activities are free with museum admission unless indicated otherwise: $8; the elderly and students, $5; ages 5 to 18, $4; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS  Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. On permanent display are costumes, set pieces, filming equipment and other items relating to film, television and video. Exhibitions include ''Behind the Screen,'' a permanent display with more than 1,000 artifacts that illustrate the production, marketing and exhibition of moving images. Daily screenings include classic shorts, shown in Tut's Fever Movie Palace: Through April 3, ''Cops'' (1922), with Buster Keaton. Screening times: 1, 2:30 and 4 P.M. ''True Stories: The Films of Barbara Kopple,'' four documentaries from the Academy Award-winning filmmaker will be screened tomorrow and Sunday. Tomorrow at 2 P.M., ''Harlan County, U.S.A.'' (1977), focusing on the tension between Kentucky coal miners and their bosses, and at 5 P.M., ''American Dream'' (1989), a look at labor's weakening position at a Minnesota meat-packing company. On Sunday at 1:30 P.M., ''Fallen Champ: The Untold Story of Mike Tyson'' (1993), chronicling the heavyweight champion's rise and fall; at 4:30 P.M., Ms. Kopple will be on hand for a ''Pinewood Dialogue,'' where she will preview her new ''Wild Man Blues'' (1997), a candid look at Woody Allen and Soon-Yi Previn during Mr. Allen's European jazz tour. Tickets for the ''Pinewood Dialogue'' and the screening will be $20. Also, ''Computer Space '98,'' a continuing exhibition of classic arcade games and contemporary home-entertainment software that visitors can play. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. All activities are free with museum admission unless indicated otherwise: $8; the elderly and students, $5; ages 5 to 18, $4; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West at 79th Street. ''Sacred Mountains of the World,'' an exhibition of photographs exploring the cultural, religious and symbolic significance of some of the world's most famous mountains. Through March 31. Other exhibitions include ''The Nature of Diamonds,'' which explores all aspects of the mineral, from its geological origins to its popularity as an adornment to its modern uses in technology and research. Through April 26. ''Africa: Explorations and Expeditions,'' featuring firsthand accounts of European and American exploration from the 18th century on, as depicted in selections from the museum's rare-book collection. Through Sept. 30. Permanent displays include the dinosaur and fossil halls and the Imax films ''Cosmic Voyage,'' ''Whales'' and the recently opened ''Titanica,'' which chronicles the construction, sinking, exploration and excavation of the Titanic. In the Imax Theater on Fridays and Saturdays at 9 P.M., ''Led Zeppelin in 3-D'' and ''Pink Floyd's 'Dark Side of the Moon' '' in 3-D. Tickets: $9. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 5:45 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 8:45 P.M. Suggested admission: $8; students and the elderly, $6; children 12 and under, $4.50. A combination ticket including museum admission and one film: $12; students and the elderly, $8.50; children 12 and under, $6.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100; to buy tickets by phone: (212) 769-5200.  AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Washington Heights. The society has the most extensive coin collection in North America; its library is open to the public. A retrospective of the work of Helder Batista of Portugal, including sculpture, graphics and medals from the artist's collection, will be on view through April 19. On permanent display is ''American Numismatic Design, 1892-1922,'' which includes all coins issued during this period. Also on view is ''The World of Coins,'' a history from 600 B.C. to the present. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. Information: (212) 234-3130.  INTREPID SEA-AIR-SPACE MUSEUM, Pier 86, West 46th Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. A converted World War II aircraft carrier with two full decks of displays, including four themed halls: United States Navy Hall, Pioneer Hall, Technologies Hall and Intrepid Hall. ''The Spanish-American War'' is an exhibition featuring pieces of ships that fought in the war, models, photographs and nautical charts. Through July 1999. ''Proudly We Serve,'' an exhibition about the service of black veterans, with photographs, uniforms, artifacts and models, is on view through February 1999. Also on view is a 1950's French naval fighter jet, the Etendard IV-M, given to the museum by the French Government. Visitors can feel what it's like to fly a tactical mission over the Persian Gulf by using a flight simulator, which recreates five minutes aboard an F-18 Hornet fighter jet. A ride on the simulator is $5; $3 for school groups. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; closed Mondays and Tuesdays. Admission: $10; the elderly, veterans, reservists and ages 12 to 17, $7.50; ages 6 to 11, $5; 5 and under, $1; under 2, free; wheelchair patrons, half price. Information: (212) 245-0072.  THE MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST, 18 First Place (West Street and Battery Place), Battery Park City. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videotapes and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. Exhibitions include ''Life a Century Ago,'' featuring memorabilia from Jewish rituals and celebrations in Europe in the early 1900's, ''War Against the Jews,'' detailing the years 1933 to 1945 and ''Jewish Renewal,'' focusing on life after the Holocaust. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursdays, 9 A.M. to 8 P.M.; Fridays and the eves of Jewish holidays, 9 A.M. to 2 P.M.; closed on Saturdays and Jewish holidays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; 5 and under, free. A limited number of same-day tickets are available at the museum; because of heavy attendance, tickets should be purchased in advance through Ticketmaster: (212) 307-4007. Information: (212) 968-1800.  MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52d Street, Manhattan. A collection of taped radio and television broadcasts as well as exhibitions of other media, including drawings, posters and photographs. The exhibition ''Worlds Without End: The Art and History of the Soap Opera'' ends on Sunday and includes screenings, seminars and a gallery display. Through Sunday a compilation of highlights from parodies, including ''Bob and Ray: 'Mary Backstayge, Noble Wife' ''; ''As the Stomach Turns,'' from ''The Carol Burnett Show,'' and ''SCTV Network 90: The Days of the Week,'' will be screened: today at 1 and 7 P.M.; tomorrow and Sunday at 1 P.M. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 P.M.; Thursdays, noon to 8 P.M. On Fridays, the theater is open until 9 P.M.; closed Mondays and holidays. Admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; 12 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.  NEW YORK CITY FIRE MUSEUM, 278 Spring Street, SoHo. In a renovated 1904 firehouse is a collection of fire-related art and artifacts from the 18th century to the present, including a firetruck, hose wagons, hats, toys, paintings and hand-drawn pumpers. Also, an exhibition, ''Fire Marks: Emblems of Insurance,'' features a selection of 18th- and 19th-century British and American fire marks from the museum's collection. Insurance agencies would give bonuses to firefighters when they rescued the premises of a policyholder. The decorative emblems were used to distinguish policyholders from the uninsured. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Suggested admission: $4 for adults; $2 for students and the elderly; $1 for children under 12. Information: (212) 691-1303.  NEW YORK TRANSIT MUSEUM, Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn. ''Steel, Stone and Backbone,'' a display tracing the construction of the subway system from 1900 to 1925, with photographs, construction tools, films and other objects; ''Ceramic Ornamentation,'' a look at the mosaics, tiles and terra cotta used to adorn subway stations from 1904 to the present and ''Here to There: Signs for Moving Around Underground,'' a display of more than 100 subway signs, continuing. Also on view are 19 restored subway cars dating from 1903 to 1960. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.; closed Mondays and holidays. Admission: $3; the elderly and ages 6 to 17, $1.50; 5 and under, free. On Wednesday from 12 to 4 P.M., admission is free for the elderly. Information: (718) 243-8601.  SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM AND MARKETPLACE, South and Fulton Streets, lower Manhattan. The 19th-century port district has restaurants, shops and bars. The museum has three gallery spaces, a children's crafts center and a boat-building center. Tomorrow and Sunday at 2 P.M., ''Maritime Mosaics,'' where participants can learn about dinner in 19th-century New York and make a mosaic with foods based on those traditionally eaten in lower Manhattan. Current exhibitions include ''By Appointment to the King: Becken of Cowes, Marine Photographers,'' yachting images. Also, a permanent exhibition: ''Traveling in Style: 20th-Century Ocean Liners.'' Museum hours: Wednesdays through Sunday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; stores in the marketplace: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M.; Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission to museum: $6; the elderly, $5; students, $4; children 12 and under, $3. Information: the museum, (212) 748-8600; the marketplace, (212) 732-7678.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>''RUN FOR THE RAIN FOREST 5K,'' Central Park. Sunday at 10 A.M. There will also be a ''Run for the Rain Forest'' race tomorrow at 9:15 A.M. for youngsters 2 to 12 years old (distances vary from one block to one mile). Both sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Admission fee for the 5K race, $15; $10 for members; $9 for junior and senior members of the club. Admission fee for the the youngsters' race, $6; $4 for members. Information: (212) 860-4455.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''WORLD OF FINANCE,'' lower Manhattan. A tour of the financial center, inside and out, with stops at the New York Stock Exchange and Trinity Church (the burial place of notable financial figures). Every Friday at 9:30 A.M., leaving from 14 Wall Street. Sponsored by Heritage Trails. Fee, $15; $10 for students and the elderly; a prix-fixe breakfast is available for an additional $10. Reservations: (212) 269-1500, extension 207.  ''BROOKLYN BRIDGE TO BROOKLYN HEIGHTS.'' A walking tour across the Brooklyn Bridge and through the city's first suburb, concentrating on the history, architecture and people of the area. Stops include the Plymouth Church, Walt Whitman's childhood home, the A. A. Low Mansion and the Brooklyn Historical Society. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. on the front steps of City Hall. Fee, $9; students and the elderly, $7. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Information: (212) 439-1090.  ''GREENWICH VILLAGE PAST AND PRESENT.'' A historical walk devoted to the lives of the writers and artists who have worked and lived in the area. Meets tomorrow at 2 P.M at the Washington Square Arch. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Information: (212) 969-8262.  ''THE IMMIGRANT, RADICAL AND NOTORIOUS WOMEN OF WASHINGTON SQUARE.'' A three-hour walking tour through Washington Square that celebrates Women's History Month, with stops at the site of Margaret Sanger's clinic, the location of Edith Wharton's ''Pen and Brush Club'' and the salon of Mable Dodge. Meets tomorrow and Sunday at 1 P.M. at the Washington Square Arch. Fee, $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.  ''RAGTIME ERA NEW YORK,'' Manhattan. A walk through 19th-century New York's most exclusive areas, including Gramercy Park and Ladies Mile, the favorite 1890's shopping area, and stops at the homes of Samuel Tilden, Edwin Booth and Peter Cooper. Tomorrow and Sunday at noon. Fee, $12. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Information: (212) 465-3331.  ''TERRIFIC TURTLE BAY,'' Manhattan. A stroll of the elegant neighborhood in the East 40's, passing through the United Nations headquarters, the Tudor City historic district and Turtle Bay Gardens. Tomorrow at 11 A.M. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information: (212) 265-2663.  ''VICTORIAN NEW YORK,'' Manhattan. A tour that explores 1890's and early 1900's New York, with stops that include the Flatiron Building and sites associated with Teddy Roosevelt, Emma Goldman and Stanford White. Tomorrow and Sunday at 2:30 P.M. Fee, $12. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Information: (212) 465-3331.  EAST OF SOHO. A walk spotlighting diverse and distinguished architectural landmarks, including works associated with James Boardus, Calvert Vaux and Steven Holl. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. at the southwest corner of Lafayette and White Streets. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee, $15; $12 for members of the society. Information: (212) 935-3960.  ''GREENWICH VILLAGE: NEW YORK'S LEFT BANK.'' A tour of the streets that have been home to such writers and artists as Eugene O'Neill, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Edgar Allan Poe and Edward Hopper. Meets tomorrow and Sunday at noon at the Washington Square Arch. Sponsored by Mainly Manhattan Tours. Fee, $10. Information: (212) 755-6199.  ROOSEVELT ISLAND. A two-mile walking tour, at an easy pace, of the planned community in the middle of the East River, in which visitors will see historic landmarks as well as the latest additions. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. at the tramway base in Manhattan at 60th Street and Second Avenue. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Fee, $3 for nonmembers. Tramway fare is 1.50; the fare for the elderly is free. Membership fee, $7; $5 for the elderly and anyone under 17. Information: (718) 998-3973.  ''CHINATOWN,'' Manhattan. A tour of the largest Chinatown in the Western Hemisphere. Stops include a Buddhist temple, Confucius Plaza and the Kim Lau Memorial. Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. at the southwest corner of Broadway and Canal Street. Fee, $10. Sponsored by I'll Take Manhattan Tours. Information: (732) 270-5277.  BRIDGE WALK. A stroll across the cantilevered Queensboro Bridge, connecting Queens with Manhattan, just before its 89th birthday. Sunday at 3 P.M. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. 3 P.M. Reservations: (212) 265-2663.  ''CHELSEA: LADIES' MILE TOUR.'' A tour of Chelsea, both known as a favorite 1890's shopping area and the home of radical political activities. Stops include the sites of the first two Madison Square Gardens, Margaret Sanger's clinic and the locale of Malcolm X's famous speech to the Socialists Workers' Party Forum. Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. in front of the Chelsea Hotel, 222 West 23d Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Radical Walking Tours. Information: (718) 492-0069.  ''EAST VILLAGE.'' The tour will combine the history of German, Ukrainian and Jewish immigrants with that of labor activism. Stops include the Fillmore East, Labor Lyceum and sites associated with Peter Stuyvesant and Margaret Sanger. Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. at the cube sculpture at Astor Place. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Fee, $9; $7 for students and the elderly. Information: (212)  439-1090.  ''EAST VILLAGE TALES AND TAVERNS.'' A tour of four of the area's historic taverns. Meets tomorrow at 6 P.M. at the Astor Place I.R.T. subway kiosk. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Fee, $10 (does not include cost of refreshments.) Information: (212) 969-8262.  FLUSHING-FORT TOTTEN, Queens. The tour, which covers about four miles, goes through Flushing, Bayside and Whitestone, Queens. Meets Sunday at 11 A.M. at Caldors, on Roosevelt Avenue, off Main Street. Take the No. 7 subway to Main Street (the last stop), Flushing. Bring lunch and water. Dinner in Flushing is optional. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Fee, $3 for nonmembers. Membership fee, $7; $5 for the elderly and those under 17. Information: (718) 361-2585, call evenings before 10:30 P.M.  ''SOHO-TRIBECA GHOSTS.'' A walk in search of ghosts amid the historic buildings. Meets tomorrow at 2 P.M. at Old St. Patrick's Cathedral, Mott Street, between Prince and Houston Streets. Sponsored by Street Smarts New York. Fee, $10. Information: (212) 969-8262.  ''CENTRAL PARK,'' a walking tour of Manhattan's largest grassy playground, designed by Olmsted and Vaux. Stops include the site of Seneca Village, Strawberry Fields and the Ramble. Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. at the northwest corner of 66th Street and Central Park West. Fee, $9; students and the elderly, $7. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Information: (212) 439-1090.  ''HAUNTED GREENWICH VILLAGE.'' A tour of some of the area's ''haunted'' spots, including the cobblestoned Washington Mews, the Jefferson Market Courthouse Library and the homes of Aaron Burr and Washington Irving. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Tomorrow at 3:30 P.M. Fee: $5. Information and meeting place: (212) 265-2663.  ''MILLIONAIRES' ROW,'' Manhattan. A tour of Fifth Avenue, in midtown, past the Plaza Hotel and the former residences of the Rockefellers, Vanderbilts and Hearsts. Tomorrow at 1 P.M. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Fee, $5. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 265-2663.  STUDIOS OF GREENPOINT, BROOKLYN. A look at the private and public studios of Greenpoint's artists. The historian David Steinberg will lead a tour of the growing art scene in this ethnic community, the second-largest Polish population in the country. Sunday at 10:30 A.M. Sponsored by the 92d Street Y. Fee, $25. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 996-1100.  ''NEW YORK IN BRONZE: THE CITY'S HISTORY IN STATUARY, lower Manhattan. The urban historian Marvin Gelfand will lead a tour through New York's public spaces, pointing out statues in Union Square and Gramercy Park of famous historical figures busy New Yorkers barely notice. Sunday at 1 P.M. Sponsored by the 92d Street Y. Fee, $15. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 996-1100.  ''SPRING WALK THROUGH UPPER CENTRAL PARK.'' A walking tour through Central Park's north end, visiting the Conservatory Garden, the Ravine, the North Woods, the Loch and other sites. Sunday at 1 P.M. Sponsored by the 92d Street Y. Fee, $15. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 996-1100.  ''STUYVESANT AND GRAMERCY PARKS HISTORIC DISTRICTS.'' A tour focusing on the historical and architectural elements of the neighborhoods. Highlights include Stuyvesant Town, the Players Club, St. George's Church and the site of the first apartment house in New York. Sunday at 2 P.M., meeting at the northeast corner of East 14th Street and First Avenue. Sponsored by New York City Cultural Walking Tours. Fee, $10. Information: (212) 979-2388.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
