<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="27TRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1005328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4D7173BF934A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Named David J. McGowan public address announcer.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Acquired P Marty Weymouth from the Seattle Mariners for RHP Jim Bullinger.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Fired Bob Cluck pitching coach. Named Rick Peterson pitching coach. Optioned RHP Ariel Prieto to Edmonton of the PCL.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Claimed RHP Jose Paniagua off waivers from the Tampa Bay Devils Rays. Assigned INF Aaron Holbert outright to Tacoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Released RHP Carey Paige, RHP Alan Meinershagen and OF Scott Bullett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Named David J. McGowan public address announcer.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Acquired P Marty Weymouth from the Seattle Mariners for RHP Jim Bullinger.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Fired Bob Cluck pitching coach. Named Rick Peterson pitching coach. Optioned RHP Ariel Prieto to Edmonton of the PCL.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Claimed RHP Jose Paniagua off waivers from the Tampa Bay Devils Rays. Assigned INF Aaron Holbert outright to Tacoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Released RHP Carey Paige, RHP Alan Meinershagen and OF Scott Bullett.</p>
        <p>National League  CHICAGO CUBS--Optioned INF Jason Hardtke to Iowa of the PCL. Assigned RHP Dave Stevens to their minor-league complex. Placed OF Robin Jennings on the 15-day disabled list.  FLORIDA MARLINS--Assigned RHP Hector Ramirez and LHP Jesus Martinez outright to Charlotte of the International League. Sent Martinez to Indianapolis of the International League to complete the March 21 trade with the Cincinnati Reds for INF-OF Eric Owens.  METS--Optioned C Todd Pratt to Norfolk of the International League. Assigned INF Shawn Gilbert to their minor-league complex. Voided the contract of INF Chad Fonville due to a pre-existing injury.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  SACRAMENTO KINGS--Suspended C Olden Polynice for two games and fined him an undisclosed amount for conduct detrimental to the team.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  DETROIT LIONS--Re-signed LB Ben Hanks and S Ryan Stewart. Signed LB Phillip Ward.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS--Traded QB Paul Justin to the Cincinnati Bengals for an undisclosed draft pick.  SEATTLE SEAHAWKS--Named Winston Moss defensive quality control coach.  HOCKEY  National Hockey League  DALLAS STARS--Activated LW Dave Reid and D Sergei Zubov in the injured reserve list.  DETROIT RED WINGS--Assigned C Sylvain Cloutier and D Duane Joyce to Detroit of the IHL. Assigned D Tim Murray and LW Rob Pattison to Adirondack of the AHL.  DEVILS--Assigned RW Bobby House to Syracuse of the AHL.  ISLANDERS--Assigned D Jeff Libby to Kentucky of the AHL.  PHILADELPHIA FLYERS--Returned RW John Druce to Philadelphia of the AHL.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Assigned LW Jocelyn Lemieux to Rochester of the AHL.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Assigned C Serge Aubin to Hershey of the AHL.  SAN JOSE SHARKS--Assigned G Jamie Ram to Utah of the IHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS--Returned G Corey Hirsch to Syracuse of the AHL.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BOWLING GREEN--Named Tim Beckman secondary coach.  COASTAL CAROLINA--Announced the resignation of Michael Hopkins, men's basketball coach.  C.W. POST--Named Brian Hughes offensive coordinator-athletic department business manager, Frank Limanni running backs coach, Ten Tsirigotis wide receiver coach and Mike Henning quarterbacks coach.  WESTCHESTER CC--Announced the retirement of Ralph Arietta, men's basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
