<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shareholder Sues John Hancock Over Executive Pay Levels</title>
    <meta content="Y29INSU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/29/business/29INSU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1492564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">John Hancock Financial Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landy, Aaron E Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Alessandro, David F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Syron, Richard F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">John Hancock Financial Services Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDB1E31F93AA15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shareholder Sues John Hancock Over Executive Pay Levels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shareholder Sues John Hancock Over Executive Pay Levels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Hancock Financial Services' shareholder Aaron E Landy Jr files civil suit in federal court over compensation of company's chief executive David F D'Alessandro and other senior executives, seeking return to John Hancock of much of $42.3 million they received; pay package of D'Alessandro rose to $21.7 million in 2002, up from $8.2 million in 2001; suit contends executives improperly profited from Hancock's conversion in early 2000 from ownership by policyholders to ownership by shareholders, and from more than doubling of its share price; Richard F Syron, head of Hancock's compensation committee, says rapid growth in share price in first year was significantly important in determining executive pay in 2002; lawsuit also accuses Hancock of fraud and deception by failing to state in reports to Securities and Exchange Commission that executive pay was at least partly based on company's first-year performance as publicly traded company (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A shareholder of John Hancock Financial Services filed a civil suit in federal court yesterday over the compensation of the company's chief executive and other senior executives, seeking the return to John Hancock of much of the $42.3 million they received.</p>
        <p>The pay package of the chief executive, David F. D'Alessandro, rose to $21.7 million in 2002, up from $8.2 million in 2001. It has been criticized by Wall Street analysts and executive compensation experts as out of line with the company's performance in a year when the stock price fell 32 percent and earnings dropped 15 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A shareholder of John Hancock Financial Services filed a civil suit over the compensation of the company's chief executive and other senior executives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A shareholder of John Hancock Financial Services filed a civil suit in federal court yesterday over the compensation of the company's chief executive and other senior executives, seeking the return to John Hancock of much of the $42.3 million they received.</p>
        <p>The pay package of the chief executive, David F. D'Alessandro, rose to $21.7 million in 2002, up from $8.2 million in 2001. It has been criticized by Wall Street analysts and executive compensation experts as out of line with the company's performance in a year when the stock price fell 32 percent and earnings dropped 15 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Alessandro's pay was by far the highest of any chief executive of a life insurance company last year, more than two and a half times that of the chief executives of MetLife and Prudential Financial, each with twice the stock market value of John Hancock. Four other John Hancock executives received what analysts have called exceptionally high pay.</p>
        <p>The company, based in Boston, characterized the lawsuit as frivolous and said it expected to prevail.</p>
        <p>The suit, filed in Federal District Court in Boston by Aaron E. Landy Jr., a small shareholder in Southlake, Tex., contends that the executives improperly profited from John Hancock's conversion in early 2000 from ownership by policyholders to ownership by shareholders, and from the more than doubling of its share price. Mr. Landy is represented by Jason Adkins, a persistent critic of John Hancock.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts and other states prohibit executives from receiving stock and stock options in the first year after a mutual insurer becomes a publicly traded company. The intent of the laws is to reduce the ability of executives to profit, at least initially, from the decision to convert.</p>
        <p>In a conference call with investors on May 2, Mr. D'Alessandro noted that John Hancock executives could not be compensated during the first year for their work in the conversion and for any rise then in share prices, but he said there was no bar to rewarding them retroactively.</p>
        <p>Richard F. Syron, the head of John Hancock's compensation committee, has said that the rapid growth in the share price in the first year ''was significantly important'' in determining executive pay in 2002.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit also accuses John Hancock of fraud and deception by failing to state in reports to the Securities and Exchange Commission that the executive pay was at least partly based on the company's first-year performance as a publicly traded company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
