<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quarterbacks at Helm in Ivy League</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="475823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDF153FF930A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quarterbacks at Helm in Ivy League</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of the Ivy League's seven new quarterbacks making their first starts, three came through impressively Saturday; two others certainly met expectations, and there might be some doubt about the last two.</p>
        <p>Princeton's Chad Roghair and Harvard's Mike Giardi were best in leading their teams to victories, the Tigers over Cornell, 18-0, and the Crimson over Columbia, 21-16.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of the Ivy League's seven new quarterbacks making their first starts, three came through impressively Saturday; two others certainly met expectations, and there might be some doubt about the last two.</p>
        <p>Princeton's Chad Roghair and Harvard's Mike Giardi were best in leading their teams to victories, the Tigers over Cornell, 18-0, and the Crimson over Columbia, 21-16.</p>
        <p>Brown's Jeff Barrett worked the hardest, trying 49 passes against Yale and completing 27 for 285 yards. But three were intercepted as the Bulldogs prevailed, 36-20.</p>
        <p>Nick Crawford directed Yale's modified I-bone offense which was more interested in running than passing.</p>
        <p>Chris Kouri, the captain who has moved from fullback to tailback, had 161 of Yale's 382 rushing yards and Crawford gained 60 while completing only 2 of 7 pass attempts.</p>
        <p>Another first-time senior starter, John Tribolet of Columbia, was 19 for 40 for 246 yards, no interceptions and two touchdowns against Harvard.  Making History</p>
        <p>The Crimson's Giardi, the first sophomore ever to start a season at quarterback in Coach Joe Restic's 20 years at Cambridge, had similar passing figures: 12 of 24 for 174 yards, two touchdowns and no interceptions. "He did a great job," Restic said.</p>
        <p>Dartmouth's Matt Brzica, the Ivy's only holdover starting quarterback, ran a ball-control offense that gained 215 yards rushing in a 21-15 victory over Penn. Brzica had three completed passes for a modest 54 yards.</p>
        <p>Penn's offense gained only 214 yards against the Green as the Quaker passer, Fitz McKinnon, had 9 completions in 21 attempts and two interceptions. Cornell's Sean Andreas also had an unimpressive debut as the Big Red gained only 187 yards against Princeton, 67 by passing.</p>
        <p>The Tigers' Roghair had the best day of all the Ivy newcomers with 21 completions of 28 pass attempts for 179 yards and two touchdowns. Like Crawford, Tribolet and Andreas, Roghair is a senior who seldom played in the two previous seasons.</p>
        <p>Quarterback Glenn Kempa of Lehigh, a Patriot League team, had a big game as the Engineers achieved a rare victory over a Yankee Conference team, Connecticut, 35-19.</p>
        <p>Holy Cross, another Patriot League team, also won from a Yankee Conference foe, Boston University, 27-23. This was the Crusaders' 11th straight victory and they trailed at halftime, 17-7, as they had a week ago against Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Patriot League teams are now 3-1 against Yankee Conference foes this season.</p>
        <p>Hofstra found out how good a Division I-AA team can be when the Flying Dutchmen lost, 48-28, to New Hampshire, the Yankee Conference preseason favorite.</p>
        <p>The Flying Dutchmen were in trouble early when their starting quarterback, freshman Michael Doto, was knocked out of the contest with a separted shoulder. His successor, George Beisel, tried to sustain the Hofstra passing game with 48 attempts and 19 completions good for 268 yards and two touchdowns.</p>
        <p>The Wildcats gained 610 yards in total offense, 433 by passing, and the defense had seven sacks of Hofstra quarterbacks.</p>
        <p>Bucknell held Fordham to minus 29 yards rushing and forced six turnovers in a 21-14 victory. For the Rams, star linebacker Mark Blazejewski had a memorable performance with 21 tackles, 11 unassisted.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
