<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Tracking the Path of the Perfect Pitch With 3-D Graphics</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="441689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THREE-DIMENSIONAL DEVICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SPORTSIGHT INC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Three-Dimensional Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D7113FF93BA15757C0A967958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Tracking the Path of the Perfect Pitch With 3-D Graphics</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does the famous rising fast ball actually exist? Tommy Lasorda, the Los Angeles Dodgers manager, believes that it does. Not all baseball aficionados agree. After all, the idea that a pitcher can hurl a blazingly fast pitch that will defy gravity and not drop as fast as it should is a little hard for some people to swallow.</p>
        <p>But a new three-dimensional computer graphics system developed by Sportsight Inc. of Irvine, Calif., has cast a new light on the question. Sportsight's system, which the company calls Supervision, works like this: Two video cameras are placed behind and to each side of home plate. The cameras between them capture 60 images a second of every pitch thrown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Does the famous rising fast ball actually exist? Tommy Lasorda, the Los Angeles Dodgers manager, believes that it does. Not all baseball aficionados agree. After all, the idea that a pitcher can hurl a blazingly fast pitch that will defy gravity and not drop as fast as it should is a little hard for some people to swallow.</p>
        <p>But a new three-dimensional computer graphics system developed by Sportsight Inc. of Irvine, Calif., has cast a new light on the question. Sportsight's system, which the company calls Supervision, works like this: Two video cameras are placed behind and to each side of home plate. The cameras between them capture 60 images a second of every pitch thrown.</p>
        <p>The video information is then fed into a series of computers that calculate the baseball's trajectory, speed, lateral movement and other data. This information is next sent to a Silicon Graphics work station, which renders a 3-D image a few seconds later. The pitcher, his coach or a television sportscaster at a game -- and the viewers -- can see what kind of pitch was thrown, where it "broke" if it was a curve, where it passed in relation to the batter and his strike zone -- even how well the umpire called the pitch.</p>
        <p>"It's an exercise in ballistics, like tracking a missile as it moves through space," said Donald Johnston, executive vice president of Sportsight, a start-up company that began working on the system three years ago.</p>
        <p>Once the visual data about the pitch is captured, the Sportsight system can manipulate the image in a variety of ways. It can show the pitch from the pitcher's point of view or from that of the catcher. Grids the computer places along the side of the image help quantify just how much the pitch deviated vertically or laterally from its desired path.</p>
        <p>"I can even place the viewer in a ridiculous place, like looking up from home plate," Mr. Johnston said.</p>
        <p>The basic Sportsight system costs from $200,000 to $400,000, which is likely to restrict the market to professional sports teams and television networks. The technology can also be used to superimpose the computer analysis of the pitch on an image of the pitcher throwing the pitch in a new variant on instant replay.</p>
        <p>Sportsight executives say the system uses computer memory efficiently -- all the pitches thrown by a pitcher during a season could easily be stored in a data base. That means that a coach using the system could quickly review every pitch a certain player threw last season, for example.</p>
        <p>Baseball enthusiasts who have seen the system point out the eventual possibilities: the opposing team in the dugout studying its own 3-D data base of the pitchers it is facing; a manager making decisions about trading a pitcher after studying the pitches of a game or a season; fans -- and outraged managers -- passing instant judgment on an umpire's call. Imagine a giant screen at the stadium delivering an analysis of each pitch for all the fans to see seconds after it was thrown.</p>
        <p>Promoting its new technology through a brochure aimed at team owners and stadium managers, Sportsight says, "Your pitcher can see just where he needs to pitch each batter. Supervision becomes your secret weapon!" Such bombast, if acted upon by major league owners, might lead to a 3-D video technology arms race.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Dodgers have been testing the system for the last year, Mr. Johnston said, and it was the team's experiments that brought up the question of Mr. Lasorda's belief in the rising fast ball.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday the Sportsvision system was on as the Dodgers beat the San Francisco Giants 7-1 behind Tim Belcher's five-hit pitching. "Belcher threw several rising fastballs, more than we have ever seen," Mr. Johnston said. While he had not yet analyzed how Giants batters fared against the pitches, Mr. Johnston said it was his impression that they frequently led to pop-up flies.</p>
        <p>"I think they definitely helped him win the game," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
