<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Squeeze Play; Hussein's Ouster Is U.S. Goal, But at What Cost to the Iraqis?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="441692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D61E3FF93BA15757C0A967958260" item-length="1630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Squeeze Play; Hussein's Ouster Is U.S. Goal, But at What Cost to the Iraqis?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States intelligence community this month completed its first full assessment of war damage in Iraq, and the numbers were sobering: $30 billion to rebuild the infrastructure of roads, bridges, power plants and oil installations; five years to repair the electrical grid; months to get water purification plants working; shortages of chlorine and grain, depleted livestock and acute shortages of medicine.</p>
        <p>The question for the Bush Administration is what should Saddam Hussein be allowed to do about it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States intelligence community this month completed its first full assessment of war damage in Iraq, and the numbers were sobering: $30 billion to rebuild the infrastructure of roads, bridges, power plants and oil installations; five years to repair the electrical grid; months to get water purification plants working; shortages of chlorine and grain, depleted livestock and acute shortages of medicine.</p>
        <p>The question for the Bush Administration is what should Saddam Hussein be allowed to do about it?</p>
        <p>After nine months of trade sanctions and economic blockade, the United States and its allies still exert absolute control over the levers of Iraq's economy. Two months after the shooting stopped, Mr. Hussein has not been allowed to sell a single barrel of oil, his principal source of national income.</p>
        <p>While a long and meticulous inspection program goes ahead to verify that Iraq has destroyed its weapons of mass destruction, Washington and its allies will retain enormous power over Iraq's 18 million people, many of whom are refugees in their own land, many of whom are hungry, sick or traumatized by war.</p>
        <p>Therein lies the quandary for the Bush Administration -- how tightly to squeeze Iraq, and when to let up. This next step may determine the long-term survival of the man Mr. Bush has been able to defeat in every way except one: Mr. Hussein remains in power in Baghdad. If not victory, as Milton's dark angel said, it is yet revenge.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, the initial inclination in the White House is to tighten the screws, using as justification Mr. Hussein's repression of the Kurds in northern Iraq and his disingenuous accounting of the ballistic missiles, chemical weapons and nuclear materials he is hiding.</p>
        <p>President Bush reaffirmed on Friday his central postwar policy goal. "There will not be normal relations with this man as long as I'm President of the United States," he declared, adding that "it's only terror that's keeping him in power" and "we want him out of there." Tighter or Looser?</p>
        <p>The critical question for United States policy will be whether to undertake a controlled strangulation of Iraq's economy as part of a strategy to topple Mr. Hussein, or a loosening of the noose that allows Mr. Hussein to rescue his people from the deprivation and destruction of the war. Strangulation inevitably brings more human suffering and will prevent Iraq from making a down payment on reparations to Kuwait, whose civilian and oil economies suffered untold billions in damage from the Iraqi occupation. Strangulation would also prolong the damage being done to the economies of Jordan and Turkey, which had strong trading ties with Baghdad before the war.</p>
        <p>But allowing Iraq to open the valves of its formidable oil industry would only strengthen Mr. Hussein as the leader who can still deliver at home. It would also allow him to fulfill his obligation to pay war damages in Kuwait and perhaps launch him once again into the Arab political arena he still aspires to dominate.</p>
        <p>There were strong indications at week's end that Mr. Bush and his senior advisers were getting ready to calibrate their postwar campaign. "My impression is that they are at the thinking stage and not at the clear formulation stage," said one senior analyst who participates in the interagency groups that feed options to Mr. Bush and his senior national security aides.</p>
        <p>In another indication, a senior Administration official was asked whether the United States would look favorably on Iraqi requests to export oil. The official said that would depend upon a lot of things, "Such as first of all, there will be a big difference in approach to it whether Saddam Hussein is in power or not."</p>
        <p>Whatever course Mr. Bush takes, constructing and then managing a postwar strategy for Iraq will be complicated and full of risks.</p>
        <p>"It's not clear to me how long this population can hold out with these sanctions," said one government specialist on Iraq. "They still seem to be eating, but we need to get electricity going for water purification, they need chlorine and simple things you could give them." He added that because of the threat of cholera and other diseases, "They need vaccines and medicines massively and immediately."</p>
        <p>Without elaborating on where Administration policy was going, one senior adviser said, "Oh, we're not going to let Iraqis starve."</p>
        <p>Still, no one in the Administration foresaw the scale or intensity of the Kurdish crisis, which has left thousands dead.</p>
        <p>Even if the ropes were taken off Iraq's economy, intelligence estimates say the country's oil revenues would not be able to cover the reconstruction bills or pay down the $80 billion in foreign debts piled up over the last decade. By the end of the current decade, Baghdad's shortfall is forecast at between $100 billion and $170 billion. Just to pay the interest on its debt this year, Iraq needs $8 billion.</p>
        <p>One Central Intelligence Agency estimate says that with minimal investment, Iraq could be exporting 1 million barrels a day within three months. And, the study adds, with a $1.5 billion investment to repair bomb-damaged pumps, Iraq could be shipping 2.7 million barrels a day of crude oil to the world markets by the end of 1992, assuming the West cooperates by selling Baghdad the oil-sector equipment and spare parts it desperately needs. Diagnosing His Strength</p>
        <p>In contemplating a long-term pressure campaign to drive Mr. Hussein from power, one part of Mr. Bush's calculus must be whether any amount of pressure can dislodge the Iraqi leader from his seat as absolute ruler in a totalitarian police state.</p>
        <p>Last month, a special intelligence assessment suggested that Mr. Hussein's regime was "diseased" and he was not likely to last more than 6 to 12 months. But in the ensuing weeks the intelligence community has altered its view, based on the observation that the Iraqi Army has remained loyal to Mr. Hussein and that violent insurrection that flared in the north and south never made it to the capital.</p>
        <p>In an important respect, the spontaneous uprising in the predominantly Shiite Muslim south and the northern Kurdish provinces may have only served to reinforce Mr. Hussein's appeal as a strong central figure able to prevent ethnic and regional pressures from splitting the nation apart. To the Sunni Muslim minority that has run Iraq in this century, Mr. Hussein still is the only thing standing between them and the anarchy of disintegration; the only thing holding together the unruly ethnic and religious warren on the fertile and oil-rich land of Mesopotamia.</p>
        <p>To be sure, many Iraqis would prefer a change at the top, but taking on Mr. Hussein's security apparatus has long been regarded as a suicidal proposition.</p>
        <p>From the moment the war ended and Mr. Bush opposed an initial Iraqi request to sell oil to buy food and medicine, there was every indication that Mr. Hussein sensed Washington's pressure game and has maneuvered to counter it. After five days of secret negotiations in Baghdad last week, Mr. Hussein struck a tentative accord with Kurdish guerrilla leaders to end the state of war in the north and to cooperate in bringing 2 million Kurdish refugees back from the borders with Iran and Turkey under new security guarantees.</p>
        <p>Whether the pact survives the scrutiny of the Kurdish community, it demonstrated Mr. Hussein's focus on dividing his internal opposition as the first step in his political recovery at home. His next step will be to divide the international coalition that effectively controls his economy.</p>
        <p>Iraq's export pipelines through Saudi Arabia and Turkey are the key to his economic recovery. Saudi Arabia, whose ruling family has dedicated itself to Mr. Hussein's downfall, has the least interest in rushing to reopen the valves on the oil terminal it allowed Iraq to establish on its Red Sea coast in 1989.</p>
        <p>But Turkey continues to suffer the effects of lost trade with Iraq. Aside from the hefty pipeline fees it once earned, Turkey misses the lucrative market Iraq provided for its exports and the barter payments that arrived in the form of 4,000 tanker trucks carrying Iraqi crude oil for Eastern Turkey's refineries.</p>
        <p>Jordan also would suffer from an extended embargo against Iraq. Bereft of friends among the oil-rich Arab gulf states that fought Iraq while Jordan stayed on the fence, King Hussein's severe economic problems will only intensify in coming months.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration, having decided that the Jordanian monarch was too important a strategic player in the region to abandon during the war, could end up contributing to Jordan's economic collapse by insisting on keeping Iraq's borders sealed against trade. Without the trade revenue, Baghdad cannot make payments to Jordan on the pile of debts left over from the Iran-Iraq war, nor will Jordanian farmers and exporters be able to ship goods to their traditional overland markets in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hussein will focus his diplomatic energies at the United Nations Security Council, where China, the Soviet Union and many non-aligned nations may balk at an economic campaign that smacks too heavily of retribution or nation tampering.</p>
        <p>Most Iraq specialists who have watched Mr. Bush over the last nine months instinctively believe that a harsh pressure campaign is ahead and they are gearing up to be alert for the telltale signs of human catastrophe, such as epidemics and starvation, that will require what one analyst called "humanitarian adjustments" along the way.</p>
        <p>But for now, from Baghdad to Basra and from Mosul to Kirkuk, it seems clear that it will be a long time before Iraq's war-weary population returns to the living standard to which it was accustomed -- at least as long as Mr. Hussein rules.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
