<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Return Complete, Seles Takes Title</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUSTRALIAN OPEN (TENNIS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SELES, MONICA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUBER, ANKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER MONICA SELES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DF1639F934A15752C0A960958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Return Complete, Seles Takes Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER MONICA SELES;</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, Saturday, Jan. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The record book will show that Monica Seles won the Australian Open in 1991,  1992, 1993 and 1996. What the record book will not show is that Seles actually won it four times in a row.</p>
        <p>The only reason for Seles's two-year absence from the Flinders Park honor roll was a knife attack in Hamburg, Germany, in April 1993. The objective of that attack was to knock Seles out of the No. 1 spot in the rankings. It achieved that end and more, but it would ultimately not end Seles's run as a champion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The record book will show that Monica Seles won the Australian Open in 1991,  1992, 1993 and 1996. What the record book will not show is that Seles actually won it four times in a row.</p>
        <p>The only reason for Seles's two-year absence from the Flinders Park honor roll was a knife attack in Hamburg, Germany, in April 1993. The objective of that attack was to knock Seles out of the No. 1 spot in the rankings. It achieved that end and more, but it would ultimately not end Seles's run as a champion.</p>
        <p>Her 6-4, 6-1 victory over Germany's Anke Huber in today's Australian Open final was her first Grand Slam title since her comeback. It was also her first Grand Slam title as an American citizen.</p>
        <p>Seles, the No.-1 seeded player, won today by swinging freely and grunting freely from the baseline, just as she did before she was forced from the game. She won it by inexorably breaking down her more inexperienced opponent's game and exploiting her minor weaknesses, particularly her erratic forehand.</p>
        <p>Huber, a German who was seeded eighth and was playing in her first Grand Slam final, came out slugging and held her own through the first set. But she was unable to sustain that level of excellence long enough to seriously threaten Seles's ability to win her ninth Grand Slam title.</p>
        <p>"I left this tournament in 1993 with unbelievable memories and the hardest thing for me when I was away was not being able to defend my title here," Seles  told the crowd after the match. "Since 1991, I played so well here. I love the tournament and Melbourne. It brings out great tennis in me. To be back here holding up this trophy again means a lot to me."</p>
        <p>In four appearances at this tournament, Seles is 28-0. And though there were  actually more banners supporting Huber hanging inside Center Court, there was no question that this was a popular victory. After Huber's final forehand floated wide, the applause was long and warm. Seles put her hand to her racquet strings  and applauded the crowd.</p>
        <p>"Welcome back to the winner's circle in Grand Slam tournaments," said Geoff Pollard, the president of Tennis Australia just before he gave Seles the silver  cup that goes to the victor.</p>
        <p>Seles very nearly won the first Grand Slam tournament of her comeback, but she ultimately lost in three sets in last year's United States Open final to Steffi Graf. She did not play again in 1995, missing the end of the season with  lingering tendinitis in her knee and an ankle injury. But though she flew to Australia in less than peak condition, she shrugged off various aches and pains, including a very sore left shoulder in her narrow semifinal victory over  Chanda Rubin.</p>
        <p>Today, her serve still did not appear in top form, but she was more solid from the baseline than against Rubin.</p>
        <p>"The whole two weeks I think she played great tennis again," Huber said.</p>
        <p>Huber led early in the first set, breaking Seles in the fifth game, which Seles lost at love, double-faulting on break point. But in the next game, Seles  played tennis more typical of her career, pushing Huber to nine deuces on her serve and finally breaking back when Huber knocked a wide forehand into the tape.</p>
        <p>From then on, the pattern was set. Seles would hold with relative ease, and Huber would struggle to hold at all as Seles stepped inside the baseline and began smacking her returns with increasing confidence.</p>
        <p>Serving at 4-5, Huber saved one set point when Seles shanked a backhand, throwing her head back and shouting at the cloudy sky. But on the next set point, Huber showed that her nerves are still fragile, hitting the tape with her forehand as she stared at a relatively open court.</p>
        <p>All that remained was for Seles to tighten her grip in the second set and then grip the microphone at the awards ceremony.</p>
        <p>"I'd like to thank my family for being there always," she said, looking at her father, Karolj, and her mother, Esther, in the stands.</p>
        <p>Seles kept her composure, but Karolj was in tears.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
