<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts World: Many Tiny Economic Stars</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="639031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PORT AUTHORITY OF NY AND NJ</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REDBURN, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF1239F935A35753C1A965958260" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts World: Many Tiny Economic Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM REDBURN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REDBURN, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For all the acknowledged importance of Broadway theater, Woody Allen's movies or a blockbuster show at the Museum of Modern Art, a new study by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey has found that the arts in New York exert their greatest economic impact through a myriad of far smaller and more obscure enterprises and organizations.</p>
        <p>According to the comprehensive, yearlong research project, the arts and other cultural activities have grown substantially in importance over the last decade. They now pump at least $9.8 billion a year into the New York metropolitan area and, directly and indirectly, support more than 107,000 jobs. The arts directly employ some 41,000, appreciably more than the 36,000 employed in advertising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For all the acknowledged importance of Broadway theater, Woody Allen's movies or a blockbuster show at the Museum of Modern Art, a new study by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey has found that the arts in New York exert their greatest economic impact through a myriad of far smaller and more obscure enterprises and organizations.</p>
        <p>According to the comprehensive, yearlong research project, the arts and other cultural activities have grown substantially in importance over the last decade. They now pump at least $9.8 billion a year into the New York metropolitan area and, directly and indirectly, support more than 107,000 jobs. The arts directly employ some 41,000, appreciably more than the 36,000 employed in advertising.</p>
        <p>"This sector of the regional economy has grown even as the region itself has suffered through difficult times," the study found.</p>
        <p>Within the New York-New Jersey region that the Port Authority serves, the arts remain largely concentrated in the city. It accounted for 91 percent of the direct jobs and 93 percent of total expenditures by cultural institutions. A Broad Reach</p>
        <p>The authors argue that the very diversity of New York's extensive cultural complex has helped it thrive: "stimulating it to grow some 14 percent in real terms over the 10 years. In many ways it was the creativity of the institutions themselves that allowed them to prosper, increasing their revenues from operations and concessions sales to fuel their growth."</p>
        <p>While giant institutions like the Metropolitan Museum of Art and Lincoln Center are highly visible, the authors concluded that the strength of the cultural community rests on thousands of individuals and organizations who make toe shoes for ballet dancers, build stage sets for dramatic productions, devise lighting for television commercials and produce buffets for movie crews.</p>
        <p>"Today the cultural world extends far beyond Madison Avenue and SoHo art galleries and is not just those museums and institutions within a mile of Central Park," said Mitchell Moss, director of the Urban Research Center at New York University and an adviser to the study group.</p>
        <p>The sponsors of the report -- which include the business-supported New York City Partnership and the Partnership for New Jersey -- intend to use the findings to lobby for additional backing for the arts from public agencies. While the City of New York, after a round of cuts in 1991, has largely maintained its arts budget, state and Federal support for cultural activities has fallen sharply since the late 1980's as the recession has carved a deep hole out of government tax revenues. Theater-in-Meadowlands</p>
        <p>But louder voices are also clamoring for Albany's attention. Local leaders of the arts complain that Gov. Mario M. Cuomo largely ignores the contribution of cultural activities, but bends over backward to respond to the threat by George M. Steinbrenner 3d, principal owner of the New York Yankees, to move his baseball team out of the Bronx. The Governor has suggested building a $500 million stadium in Manhattan if that is necessary to prevent the Yankees from leaving for the Meadowlands in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>"Twice as many people go to theater, dance, museums and concerts as all the sports combined in New York," declared Martin E. Segal, chairman of the New York International Festival of the Arts. "The Governor is charming, intelligent, a marvelous orator, but he doesn't go to the cultural attractions of the city." Gerald Schoenfeld, president of the Shubert Organization, which owns 16 Broadway theaters, said: "Unfortunately, we can't exactly pick up and move, but what you do see is that nobody has built a new theater in New York for a very long time."</p>
        <p>Vincent Tese, director of the state's Urban Development Corporation, replied: "I don't think that keeping the Yankees is counterproductive to the state's involvement in the arts. I understand there is frustration that the arts got cut back in the recession, like everything else. That should improve as the economy recovers. But the important thing to remember is that we need to maintain a critical mass of all types of entertainment and culture."</p>
        <p>Another state official joked, "When Lincoln Center says they are going to move to New Jersey, we'll pay attention."</p>
        <p>The study found that visitors to New York for the City's cultural offerings generated an estimated $2.3 billion a year in economic activity, up by 13 percent in real terms from 1982.</p>
        <p>The report was supported by foundations, business groups and arts organizations and it is the first installment of a larger $650,000 study of the impact of tourism and the arts.</p>
        <p>To some extent, the rosy health of the arts in New York today may serve to undermine its advocates' case for greater government support. Since most cultural institutions have managed to survive and even expand on their own despite recent public austerity, state officials argue that other recipients have greater needs.</p>
        <p>But supporters of the arts contend that that is a short-sighted view. Investment in cultural activities pays big dividends, they say.</p>
        <p>Lawrence P. Goldman, president of the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, is leading the effort to build a large $200 million to $250 million cultural complex, similar in scale to Lincoln Center, in downtown Newark. At least 625 new construction jobs will be created directly in the initial phase, and Mr. Goldman said he hoped to attract as many as 650,000 visitors a year once the center is completed, providing permanent employment at the center for more than 470 people. The ripple effect would help support 6,700 jobs in Newark, according to an economic analysis of the project.</p>
        <p>"An arts center is not something that is in the exclusive province of the culturally elite," Mr. Goldman said. "People in Newark and other central cities also need things to be proud of." 'Part of the Infrastructure'</p>
        <p>While most of the money to expand such institutions as the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Guggenheim Museum was raised privately during the Wall Street boom of the 1980's, government funds also helped fuel what Randall Bourscheidt, president of the Alliance for the Arts, a nonprofit organization that represents a wide range of local cultural institutions, called "the greatest period of building cultural institutions in this region since the 19th century." He said that the decadelong investment of $1.5 billion, which followed years of public and private neglect, "is now an unequaled part of the infrastructure of the city, just like bridges, roads and mass transit."</p>
        <p>As in the broader society, though, New York's 80's business boom and subsequent bust helped widen the gap between the cultural haves and have-nots.</p>
        <p>Private art collecting soared, helping boost the economic impact of roughly 500 major art galleries and auction houses by 48 percent from 1982 to 1992, to a total of $840 million in payrolls and purchases. That measure excludes the value of art bought and sold.</p>
        <p>With the nonprofit sector, which includes nearly 1,400 institutions -- museums, dance companies, orchestras and numerous other arts organizations -- growth was concentrated in prominent large institutions. In recent years some smaller nonprofit groups have been forced to close and others have shrunk.</p>
        <p>"An across-the-board cut may look equitable on the surface, but when you recognize that smaller institutions are more dependent on public dollars, they suffer more," said Kinshasha Holman Conwill, director of the Studio Museum of Harlem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
