<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets See The Good And Bad In Reyes</title>
    <meta content="28METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/28/sports/28METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1500485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reyes, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D8163AF93BA15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets See The Good And Bad In Reyes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Weigh the Good and Bad in Reyes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets shortstop Jose Reyes impresses team with his sheer talent and drive, and makes team uneasy when blunders reveal his youth and inexperience (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>José Reyes said he thought about a double when he saw that his ground ball would go slightly to the left of second base and into left-center field, forcing Yankees center fielder Hideki Matsui to chase it. Reyes sped down the first-base line and kept going to second, surprising Matsui, who casually threw the ball in as Reyes slid in safely headfirst.</p>
        <p>''That kid, I give him credit,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said. ''He just left home plate and it was going to be a double for him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rookie shortstop José Reyes has provided the Mets with a jolt since his promotion, even if it has short-circuited at times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>José Reyes said he thought about a double when he saw that his ground ball would go slightly to the left of second base and into left-center field, forcing Yankees center fielder Hideki Matsui to chase it. Reyes sped down the first-base line and kept going to second, surprising Matsui, who casually threw the ball in as Reyes slid in safely headfirst.</p>
        <p>''That kid, I give him credit,'' Yankees Manager Joe Torre said. ''He just left home plate and it was going to be a double for him.''</p>
        <p>That kind of double, which Reyes hit in the second inning of the Yankees' 6-4 victory last night, has not been seen around the Mets for years, probably not since Roger Cedeño, Rickey Henderson and Melvin Mora were motoring for the Mets in 1999. Reyes, a 20-year-old rookie shortstop, has provided the team with a jolt since his promotion June 10, even if his play has short-circuited at times.</p>
        <p>Reyes's hustle led to a Mets run, but later he was caught stealing and dropped a throw from second baseman Roberto Alomar in the seventh inning as he was readying to turn a double play. It was his sixth error in 16 games with the Mets and his fourth in five games this week, and the game became a summation of his brief major league career.</p>
        <p>''You're going to see some mistakes like young guys do, but he's going to make some great plays,'' Alomar said. ''He's got great range, great arm. He's got good instincts of the game. The only thing I think is he sometimes tries to be too quick. Maybe he doesn't know how strong his arm is. I think he needs to catch the ball first and not rush, especially in double-play situations. That's why he's made the errors so far.''</p>
        <p>Reyes can dazzle and disappoint, and the Mets must weigh how much he can take before his confidence breaks. That decision will be made Monday, when Rey Sanchez, the starting shortstop earlier in the season, is expected to be activated from a rehabilitation assignment.</p>
        <p>The Mets have indicated that they will keep Reyes, allowing him to learn the speed of the major league game, something he cannot do at Class AAA Norfolk.</p>
        <p>Reyes, who increased his average to .226 by going 2 for 4 last night, has appeared resolute through a trying week, and Manager Art Howe said everyone could live with the inconsistency as long as Reyes remained that way. Reyes also has 15 runs batted in and 9 runs scored.</p>
        <p>''When you bring up a kid like that, and he's our top prospect right now, you have to leave him out there,'' Alomar said. ''We're not contending right now, so now's a good time to leave him over here and hopefully he'll get to know the game.''</p>
        <p>In the seventh, Ruben Sierra was running from first base when Alomar fielded Matsui's grounder in the second-base hole and made a flip throw to Reyes, who had already cleared the bag. Alomar said he had no choice because he had backed up on the play, and Reyes defended Alomar, saying, ''That's a good throw.''</p>
        <p>As Sierra slid into the bag, the ball hit off the fingers of Reyes' glove. The Yankees loaded the bases that inning, and Howe used a pitching change to tell Reyes he needed to take his time on double plays. Alomar explained in Spanish to keep his glove up and Reyes nodded.</p>
        <p>''You got to get one before you get two,'' Howe said. ''He was rushing.''</p>
        <p>All four of Reyes's errors this week have come on potential double-play balls.</p>
        <p>Before last night, Reyes's haste had come mostly on grounders to his right. He would go to his right to field a hard-hit grounder, reach over with his glove and the ball would scoot off the webbing for an error.</p>
        <p>Matt Galante, the Mets' infield coach, said learning in the major leagues could be valuable and detrimental. Galante has watched videotape with Reyes and hit extra ground balls to him, but perhaps the best reason to keep Reyes with the Mets is that he will experience things that cannot be replicated in practice or in the minor leagues.</p>
        <p>''You hate to lose games, but if that's what it takes to get better, you have to do it,'' Galante said. ''If he's not here, he's going to go through the same thing next year.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
