<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>911 Operator Mishandled Boaters' Call, Kelly Says</title>
    <meta content="28BRON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/28/nyregion/28BRON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1460177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emergency Telephone Numbers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">City Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santora, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Badillo, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertenbaker, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Raymond W (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guarino, Max</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Melnikov, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emergency Telephone Numbers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D81339F93BA15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>911 Operator Mishandled Boaters' Call, Kelly Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">911 Operator Mishandled Boaters' Call, Kelly Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Operator who took 911 call from one of four teenagers on small boat who disappeared in icy waters off Bronx failed to properly classify call, delaying police response by 14 hours; officials stress that even if call had been handled properly, chances of finding boys would have been remote; Police Comr Raymond Kelly calls operator's actions clear violation of procedure; 12-second distress call was received 30 minutes after boys were last seen and call was logged, but police were not notified, delaying start of search until next day when families reported boys as missing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 911 operator failed to properly classify a desperate cellphone call from one of the four teenagers who disappeared in the icy waters off the Bronx on Friday night, an error that delayed a police response for 14 hours, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The operator and a supervisor made a record of the call, the officials said, but they did not relay it to the Police Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 911 operator failed to properly classify a desperate cellphone call from one of the four teenagers who disappeared in the icy waters off the Bronx on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 911 operator failed to properly classify a desperate cellphone call from one of the four teenagers who disappeared in the icy waters off the Bronx on Friday night, an error that delayed a police response for 14 hours, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The operator and a supervisor made a record of the call, the officials said, but they did not relay it to the Police Department.</p>
        <p>Police officials stressed that even if a search for the small boat sinking in the dark had immediately begun, the chances of finding it would have been remote. Nevertheless, Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said the failure of the operator and her supervisor to enter the call into a computer as a water emergency was a clear violation of procedure.</p>
        <p>''A procedure was put in last September that says in the case of water rescues, you should put the location for our Harbor Unit, which is in the 72nd Precinct in Brooklyn,'' into the dispatching system, Mr. Kelly said, ''and that would have brought about a notification to the Special Operations Division and they would have been able to dispatch some of their resources,'' like boats and planes.</p>
        <p>The 911 operator, who was not identified, received a 12-second call at 9:58 p.m. on Friday -- a half-hour after the boys were last seen, leaving a party on City Island carrying oars -- from the cellphone of Henry Badillo, 17, one of the missing boys. While the police did not release a transcript of the call to 911, at the request of family members, Mr. Kelly gave a basic description of what was said: ''We are taking on water . . . on the Long Island Sound . . . near City I. . . .''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said: ''The operator tries to put the Long Island Sound location into the computer system three times. It doesn't accept it.'' After alerting her supervisor, who listened to the tape, they made a notation that the call had been received, but they did not notify the police.</p>
        <p>The search did not begin until noon on Saturday, after the parents of the boys -- Mr. Badillo and Charles Wertenbaker, 16, both of the Bronx, and Andrew Melnikov, 16, and Max Guarino, 17, both of Manhattan -- notified the authorities that their sons were missing.</p>
        <p>For the past three days and into last night, police helicopters, harbor launches and Coast Guard rescue ships have conducted one of the most extensive air-sea searches in the region in years. The search area covered 60 square miles of water around City Island.</p>
        <p>People involved in the search were hopeful that yesterday's clear weather might have enabled them to find the eight-foot fiberglass rowboat, which could easily blend in with ice and snow. But as the sun set, there was little news. Investigators found a tennis shoe on the docks of the South Minneford Marina, and they were checking to see if it belonged to one of the boys.</p>
        <p>A small aluminum boat was found floating in Eastchester Bay over the weekend, but a rescue worker said searchers did not know whether it was the boat the boys were in.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kelly said he did not want to speculate on what might have happened had the search been started immediately after the 911 call was received, he said the closest police boat was underneath the Triborough Bridge, and was about a half-hour away. An airborne rescue team, with scuba divers aboard, from Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn, ''would have taken, at best, 20 minutes to get to the scene,'' the commissioner added.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, the water temperature was 33 degrees and the air temperature was in the teens. Mr. Kelly said it was his understanding that a person could survive for only about 15 minutes in the water in such conditions.</p>
        <p>As far as the more specific information in the 911 call, Mr. Kelly said that only ''near City I'' -- not City Island -- was heard on the tape. He said it was not reasonable to expect the operator to have made the connection to City Island, and he said that the quality of the sound during the call was poor.</p>
        <p>In addition to citing the operator's failure to follow procedure, Mr. Kelly said that the city was working on enhancing the 911 system so operators could get the general location of any cellphone caller. But he said the Police Department had not received the money from the state to enhance its system.</p>
        <p>A monthly surcharge is added to the bills of cellphone customers in the state to support the handling of emergency calls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said the technology existed to make the desired enhancements, but added, ''We are waiting for funding from the state to enable us to do that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
