<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Room-Service Treat at $25,000 (Piano Included)</title>
    <meta content="08PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/08/nyregion/08PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">BOBBY SHORT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cafe Carlyle (Manhattan)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Short, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sutton Place</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mead</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Las Vegas</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Denver</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Rosewood</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Danville</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Cafe Carlyle</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Beatles</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Three Stooges</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Landmarks Conservancy</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Library of Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ellington, Duke</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2D9163BF93BA35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Room-Service Treat at $25,000 (Piano Included)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives profile of singer/pianist Bobby Short, entertainer in his 34th year at Cafe Carlyle in New York City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOBBY SHORT lowers his famous voice, his improbable, inimitable liquid sandpaper voice, as if the gleaming black Bechstein grand that dominates his living room might overhear. ''Let's sit and talk in the library,'' he suggests, his raspy, conspiratorial whisper calculated to charm. ''Sometimes I like to get away from the piano,'' Mr. Short says with a let's-play-hooky grin.</p>
        <p>And that's not the only off-duty heresy. He's even traded his trademark tuxedo (a Cafe Carlyle uniform five nights per week) for jeans (black, not blue; fitted, not baggy). Mr. Short wears, and sings, nothing that's not bespoke. ''My most current song -- Sondheim's 'Losing My Mind' from 'Follies' -- is from 1970, which is just terrible!'' he screeches, not meaning it. ''At least the show's revival is current. But there's nothing wrong with old songs. I think people sometimes forget I'm an old man. I stay where I belong.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOBBY SHORT lowers his famous voice, his improbable, inimitable liquid sandpaper voice, as if the gleaming black Bechstein grand that dominates his living room might overhear. ''Let's sit and talk in the library,'' he suggests, his raspy, conspiratorial whisper calculated to charm. ''Sometimes I like to get away from the piano,'' Mr. Short says with a let's-play-hooky grin.</p>
        <p>And that's not the only off-duty heresy. He's even traded his trademark tuxedo (a Cafe Carlyle uniform five nights per week) for jeans (black, not blue; fitted, not baggy). Mr. Short wears, and sings, nothing that's not bespoke. ''My most current song -- Sondheim's 'Losing My Mind' from 'Follies' -- is from 1970, which is just terrible!'' he screeches, not meaning it. ''At least the show's revival is current. But there's nothing wrong with old songs. I think people sometimes forget I'm an old man. I stay where I belong.''</p>
        <p>Off we sneak to the library under the watchful glare of Mr. Short's companion and taskmaster, Chili, a 14-year-old Dalmatian with a hoarse bark -- he takes after his master -- who just happens to match the apartment's color scheme. As does Mr. Short.</p>
        <p>In his custom-made white shirt and monogrammed slippers (the RWS is shorthand for his never-used longhand name, Robert Waltrip Short), he exudes urbanity, and every room is a show-stopper (the living room boasts a wall-sized Richard Serra) in this Nick-and-Nora-Charles-swank condominium on the doorstep of Sutton Place. He has been here 17 years, is still house-proud. To enter the foyer, where a black-and-white cowhide reclines underfoot and crystal stemware lights the sideboard, is to imagine the congenial clink of ice cubes merging with Noel Coward-ish chitchat. (Mr. Short, and his Bechstein, entertain regularly.)</p>
        <p>''This is where the cocktail crowd stands -- and refuses to leave,'' says Mr. Short, who takes few cocktails but plenty of naps during this, his 34th season at the Cafe Carlyle, where he's been chanteur-in-residence since a two-week engagement finagled by his friend Ahmet Ertegun in 1968. The Carlyle's owner was desperate for a fill-in pianist; Mr. Short, his species endangered by the Beatles and other cabaret killers, was desperate for a paying gig, especially one at the elegant room that seduced him when he first saw it in 1956. He and his portfolio of Porter-Gershwin standards went over so swimmingly that he was soon booked full-time, THREE shows a night. Grueling!</p>
        <p>''I told the management it had the most glamorous indentured servant in New York,'' recalls Mr. Short, his double-entendre intended. Throughout his career -- he hit the road at 12, occasionally sharing the bill with vaudeville start-ups like the Three Stooges -- Mr. Short encountered the racial divide in all its permutations. The first of his two memoirs is, appropriately, titled ''Black and White Baby'' (Dodd Mead, 1971). In Las Vegas and St. Louis, he was welcome onstage, but the instant his act ended, the welcome mat retracted. In Denver, he was castigated for singing ballads written by whites. ''A young man told me, 'How dare you insult your race by not singing the blues!' '' he recalls. ''I still get feedback about that. I'm a 76-year-old black man living in a white society; I've gone through the medley. I'd like to think my legacy includes having done something positive to help eliminate the problems between races. I never let racism into the core of me.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Short, a three-time Grammy nominee, is 76 -- in 1994, he was named a Living Landmark by New York's Landmarks Conservancy; last year, the Library of Congress designated him a National Living Legend -- you can't tell by looking at him. His face is unlined. His hair and eyebrows are all pepper, no salt. Never a sylph, he works out with a trainer. He avoids his beloved red wine because it triggers allergies. He eats steamed vegetables for lunch. He is religious about his 4 p.m. nap. He gets to bed -- alone, he winks -- by midnight. He says he owes it to his audience to look the part (his idea of suave is equal portions Duke Ellington and Fred Astaire) as well as sing it.</p>
        <p>''I've lived long enough to know that whatever you've done wrong during the day comes back to haunt you onstage at night,'' he notes.</p>
        <p>These days Mr. Short performs two shows nightly at the Cafe Carlyle; the tariff is $60, the clientele is mostly tourists. He foresees a time when two shows will be too much, but not yet. The new management, Rosewood Hotels &amp; Resorts, has expanded Mr. Short's duties by making him the centerpiece of their $25,000 Short en Suite package. If the promotion (no takers yet) makes him feel like a glorified room service adjunct, he's not letting on.</p>
        <p>IT'S a lusciously romantic notion,'' he gushes. ''For $25,000, Mr. Short will creep up to your suite and knock out two or three tunes! Everything first class! I just hope I measure up.'' The thought of it gets him laughing. Coughing.</p>
        <p>It does beat warbling for $2 or $3 in tips in Danville, Ill., as he did when he was 8 and handed most of the money over to help with Depression-era household expenses. Mr. Short was raised with five siblings (he recently adopted the son of his deceased brother). His Methodist mother was a domestic. He barely knew his absentee father, who died in a mining accident when he was 11. He learned to play the upright piano in the parlor by ear, same as his uncle and grandfather. He never learned to read or write music. So far, that hasn't mattered one whit.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
