<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Man Who Freed the Banks</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITIBANK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEMANN, NICHOLAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZWEIG, PHILLIP L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WRISTON, WALTER WALTER BIGELOWWRISTON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WRISTON (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D61539F931A25756C0A960958260" item-length="1537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Man Who Freed the Banks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nicholas Lemann</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEMANN, NICHOLAS;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wriston Walter Wriston, Citibank, and the Rise and Fall of American Financial Supremacy. By Phillip L. Zweig. 952 pp. New York: Crown Publishers. $40.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wriston Walter Wriston, Citibank, and the Rise and Fall of American Financial Supremacy. By Phillip L. Zweig. 952 pp. New York: Crown Publishers. $40.</p>
        <p>Banking is one of the handful of subjects that have generated intense controversy almost continuously through American history. It's tempting to think of all the many fights over it as having been ideological, pitting labor against capital, government against business, the little people against the rich. Judging from Phillip L. Zweig's new book, that's what Walter Wriston, an ardent  conservative Republican, might think.</p>
        <p>A more accurate model is of never-ending internecine warfare among conservative business interests that would divide much more cleanly into aggressive and traditional camps than into right- and left-wing ones. Mr. Wriston joined National City Bank, as it was then called, in 1946 and became its chief executive officer in 1967. During the early years of his career, banking was still operating in the shadow of 1929, its buccaneering element thoroughly disgraced and disabled by regulation. What big banks did was acquire money cheaply in the form of deposits and then lend it out at a modest profit to corporations. The sociology of banking was as unadventurous as the function: National City Bank's chairman and president were both scions of families long connected with the institution.</p>
        <p>What Walter Wriston did in his 17-year reign was to make Citicorp the nation's leading banking company while transforming what it did. He represents the triumph of the aggressive tendency. A wide range of banking innovations -- as familiar as automatic teller machines, credit cards and money-market checking and as exotic (to nonbankers) as the Eurodollar market, swaps, holding companies and cross-border loans -- became standard procedure while he was running the company. Longstanding government bars to interstate banking, investment banking  by commercial banks and high interest rates on deposits deteriorated under relentless pressure from Citicorp, among others. The big losers from this have been not so much ordinary people as the many second-tier big shots, like local bank presidents, who had been the main beneficiaries of the slow, careful system that Mr. Wriston helped destroy. Citicorp's effect on banking was a part of the  larger trend toward increasing ruthless marketplace efficiency in American society.</p>
        <p>The notion that Mr. Wriston was the exemplary figure and Citicorp the exemplary institution in a banking revolution is indisputable. The problem in Mr. Zweig's book is with the literary use of Mr. Wriston as subject of a biography.</p>
        <p>Words like tough, cold, withdrawn and controlled come to people's minds as they describe Walter Wriston to Mr. Zweig. One Citi executive calls him "a dill  pickle." Like many very successful people, he seems to have focused entirely on  the one thing he does extremely well. Although he had very little free time, he  would spend hours of what there was of it, according to Mr. Zweig, arguing "arcane accounting rules" with his wife. Citicorp has been involved in every conceivable world crisis, but Mr. Wriston's own life has been relatively unadventurous: he had one employer, the bank, and one home, Manhattan. When his  biggest loan customer during the years of his rise, Aristotle Onassis, offered him a much higher-paying job, he turned it down to climb the company ladder. He  had the chance to be Secretary of the Treasury in 1968 and again in 1974, but both times said no because the President hadn't asked him personally. His views, as described here, are strongly held but not so complicated or subtle as to reward detailed exploration: he believes the free market is good and government  interference in it is bad.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Zweig is resolutely uninterested in psychological speculation. The first words Walter Wriston ever spoke to his first wife were a proposal of marriage; then, Mr. Zweig says, it took her five years to get him to speak to her at breakfast. Nuggets like this appear regularly in "Wriston," but are let pass with no comment.</p>
        <p>As a result, the book is at its heart less a biography than a company history, a genre in which it is far more difficult to engage readers without some relation to the company (or one of its competitors). Mr. Zweig, an editor at Business Week and the author of "Belly-Up: The Collapse of the Penn Square Bank," is an enormously energetic and careful reporter who must surely know more about Citicorp than any journalist has ever known about any bank. He has poured  heart and soul into this book, spending seven years on it and turning in (he says in the acknowledgments) a 2,000-page manuscript. What he hasn't done is master the biographer's craft of shaping a narrative by pruning the inessential  and presenting the subject's life as a series of dramatic incidents that are first set up and then resolved. Shorter than "War and Peace" but longer than "Anna Karenina," "Wriston" covers too much ground, has too many characters and adopts its hero's perspective without getting inside his head.</p>
        <p>Walter Wriston's view is that he modernized Citicorp, transforming it from a  conclave of preppies lolling in the shade of government regulation into a dynamic, democratic institution. This is partly true, but Mr. Zweig accepts it at face value, although, on his own evidence, even in the Wriston era Citicorp wasn't exactly Stuyvesant High School. Mr. Wriston's father, Henry Wriston, the  president of Brown University, was a friend of the chairman of the bank's executive committee; his handpicked successor, John Reed, was the son of an executive of an important bank customer, the Armour meat company. Most Citi executives who appear in "Wriston" seem to be white male Protestants who live in Greenwich. (One of the few exceptions, Lawrence Small, is "a Jewish kid from the Bronx who could have passed for a WASP.")</p>
        <p>Whenever the bank comes under political attack, Mr. Zweig tends to portray the attackers in the way that Mr. Wriston saw them -- as self-interested or impractical or ideological. Representative Wright Patman, the venerable Texas populist, "contributed . . . to the weakening of the American banking system." "Six of the most frightening words in the English language" are "Ralph Nader is  on the line." Unionization, a horror the bank has always successfully beaten back, is to Mr. Zweig the same thing as "union rule." On the other hand, Mr. Wriston dislikes Wall Street and regards investment bankers as morally suspect:  where he stands, it seems, is where he sits, in commercial banking. But Mr. Zweig elevates the automatic prejudices of someone in Mr. Wriston's position to  the status of a philosophy.</p>
        <p>As long as Mr. Wriston gets to be the great reformer of banking, whose enemies are the enemies of progress, the most telling criticism of him remains a little obscure, though the evidence for it is amply present in Mr. Zweig's prodigiously detailed reporting. Mr. Wriston wanted Citicorp to behave less like a quasi-public utility and more like a corporation; therefore he was more focused on earnings than on the traditional key statistic in banking, total assets. Mr. Zweig reports that Mr. Wriston's goal was for profit increases of 15 percent a year. What this inevitably did was to push the bank's culture toward excesses. Mr. Zweig provides us with many of these, from bribes of foreign officials, to large sums of money simply disappearing, to the booking of transactions in offices other than where they took place, to Asian drug running.</p>
        <p>But the overriding excess was bad loans. All over the world, booms have attracted Citi bankers in search of heavy loan volume and high yields. Chief among the crunches that Citi got caught in was the debt crisis in Latin America, which Mr. Wriston, by encouraging headlong lending there, did much to create. The savings-and-loan crisis, which he personally had nothing to do with, is another notorious example of what can happen when his view that financial institutions should be unshackled obtains. Three years after Mr. Wriston's retirement, John Reed set aside $3 billion to cover loan losses in Latin America -- "the total of the bank's earnings for the last four years of Wriston's watch," as Mr. Zweig notes -- and the company failed to pay a quarterly dividend for the first time since 1813. Four years later, another enormous loan portfolio went sour, this time in commercial real estate. The bank almost went under.</p>
        <p>There was a time, before the New Deal, when banks in such straits would lose  their deposits in a great stampede of withdrawals, then collapse. Today, at least if the bank is as big as Citicorp, that doesn't happen; governments, our own and those of debtor nations, step in, and if there's a bill it is footed by  taxpayers. The paradox of the bold and daring banking industry that Walter Wriston built is that it is so essentially incautious that it has to perform over a net.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Lemann is the national correspondent for The Atlantic Monthly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nicholas Lemann is the national correspondent for The Atlantic Monthly.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
