<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beef Prices for Ranchers Are at a 10-Year Low</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="850241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATTLE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDD1239F931A25756C0A960958260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beef Prices for Ranchers Are at a 10-Year Low</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>SIMLA, Colo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the barbecue season unfolds across America, the low-priced steaks sizzling on backyard grills are the despair of producers at the opposite end of the food  chain, the nation's ranchers.</p>
        <p>"We cut costs down to the point where isn't anything left to cut," said Glenn Benjamin, whose broad-brimmed cowboy hat failed to conceal a furrowed brow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the barbecue season unfolds across America, the low-priced steaks sizzling on backyard grills are the despair of producers at the opposite end of the food  chain, the nation's ranchers.</p>
        <p>"We cut costs down to the point where isn't anything left to cut," said Glenn Benjamin, whose broad-brimmed cowboy hat failed to conceal a furrowed brow.</p>
        <p>While his younger brother, Lee, weighed yearling heifers and steers before hauling them to summer grazing land, the rancher listed the cost-cutting measures taken at his family's 7,700-acre ranch here: no summer hired help, no tagging of calves and no anti-fever shots for calves before they are shipped to  feedlots this fall.</p>
        <p>With prices paid to ranchers at a 10-year low, "prices are lower than costs of production for 95 percent of cow-calf producers," estimated Chuck Lambert, economist for the National Cattlemen's Beef Association, a Denver-based group that represents 250,000 cattle ranchers.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, beef sales are the largest revenue source for agriculture. Here,  in the wide open spaces of America's cattle country, rock-bottom beef prices are rippling through local economies: ranchers are postponing bank payments and purchases of tractors, pickup trucks and fencing lumber.</p>
        <p>"Bankers are starting to sweat," said Jim Taylor, a ranch real-estate broker  in Billings, Mont.</p>
        <p>In the Southwest -- Arizona, New Mexico, Oklahoma and Texas -- drought has compounded the effect of low prices. There, farmers are selling off their herds, keeping prices low through the summer and eroding the tax base of ranching counties.</p>
        <p>"In some rural counties, livestock taxes account for half of the taxes," said Al Schneberger, executive director of the New Mexico Cattlegrowers Association,  a private group. "Herd liquidations hurt schools, roads, libraries, ambulance services."</p>
        <p>"I've been talking to people who remember the 1930's -- the Government coming out paying $8 a head, digging a hole and shooting the cow," said Mr. Schneberger, a rancher from Albuquerque. "I wonder if we are not so far away from that now."</p>
        <p>Historically, beef prices have followed 10-year cycles of price dips and rises.</p>
        <p>Overproduction, the past culprit for collapsing prices, is at work today. Beef production through the third week in April was 24 percent higher than during the same period in 1993, a recent peak price year, according to the beef association.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Americans are grilling far fewer steaks than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>In 1976 annual per capita beef consumption peaked at 94.5 pounds. In the 1990's, it has stagnated at around 66 pounds. It is unclear whether Britain's mad cow disease will have any effect on the consumption of American beef.</p>
        <p>Ranchers like to attribute today's plunging beef prices to floods of cattle from Mexico and Canada, price gouging by supermarkets and monopolistic prices by meatpacking companies.</p>
        <p>But last year, imports accounted for just 2.2 percent of the 104 million cattle in the nation's herds. In the first quarter of this year, imports were 19 percent lower than in the same period of 1993.</p>
        <p>Ranchers complain that while they face foreclosures, IBP Inc., the world's largest meatpacker, has nearly tripled its profits since 1993, reaching $256 million in 1995. Next month, a committee appointed by Agriculture Secretary Dan  Glickman is to report on the meatpacking industry, where IBP and three other companies hold 82 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>But defenders of the meatpackers -- and they are few in barbed-wire country -- note that the big four slaughterhouse companies enjoyed the same market share in 1993, when prices were at a peak. A large part of the profits, those defenders add, stem from record beef production levels, which keep processing plants operating near capacity.</p>
        <p>As for grocery stores, retail prices have gradually been bumped downward and  are expected to stay low during the summer, the nation's peak beef-eating season.</p>
        <p>In tribute to the barbecue culture, beef sales during Memorial Day weekend are 25 percent higher than daily averages for the rest of the year.</p>
        <p>But low cattle prices are not the only cloud over the Benjamin ranch, an 80-year-old homestead in bare, mustard-colored plains 60 miles southeast of Denver.</p>
        <p>"Feedcake went up 50 percent in six months, from $150 a ton in October to $220 a ton now," Ileta Benjamin, the ranch owner, said, as her two sons, Glenn and Lee, herded the balky yearlings into a weighing stall.</p>
        <p>The nation's cattle business is the largest single user of grain, largely corn in the shape of cakes or pellets for winter feed. But last year's drought created a corn shortage, pushing corn prices up to a 20-year high this spring.</p>
        <p>This year's corn crop is expected to bounce back to normal, swelling by 27 percent over last year's level, to 9.4 billion bushels, according to the Department of Agriculture.</p>
        <p>To ease the squeeze in an election year, President Clinton announced measures on April 30 to allow ranchers this summer to graze cattle and to cut hay on land previously set aside under a Federal soil conservation program. With more grass  available, ranchers will be able to reduce corn purchases.</p>
        <p>As money from the ranch has dwindled, Lee Benjamin now gets most income from  a job appraising farmland and a part-time job his wife has started in Denver.</p>
        <p>"The only way for a person to get into ranching today is to inherit it or marry it," Lee Benjamin said glumly from the dusty cab of a battered pickup.</p>
        <p>In a business affected by dozens of variables, economists see two bright spots that may speed ranching's recovery from its cyclical trough.</p>
        <p>This year's corn crop is expected to be strong. And beef exports are expected to grow.</p>
        <p>Once dismissed as negligible, United States beef exports increased sevenfold  in value in 15 years. In 1995, they added up to $3.3 billion, about 11 percent of the wholesale value of domestic beef production.</p>
        <p>Although sales to Mexico fell by half last year, strong sales to Russia and South Korea helped American beef exports post an overall increase of 18 percent.</p>
        <p>Ileta Benjamin is hedging her bets about ranching's recovery.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, four men worked full time running this ranch, which averages  about 400 head of mixed-breed cattle.</p>
        <p>Today, the same operation is run by Mrs. Benjamin and the ranch manager, Bob  Blake. Her sons give occasional help.</p>
        <p>"Two years ago, I told the hired men that they were taking the gravy off my income," the 67-year-old ranch owner recalled. "Today, I'm doing what the hired  men used to do -- branding, fencing, opening the gates."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
