<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newark Flight Paths Change, but All Isn't Quiet Below</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="850080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE GREAT OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWARK INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT (NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAGUARDIA AIRPORT (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL AVIATION ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHEN, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DE1239F931A25756C0A960958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newark Flight Paths Change, but All Isn't Quiet Below</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHEN, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Frank Stanski rides his bicycle down rustic, sleepy roads in western New Jersey, he usually hears things like crickets and frogs, the wind in the trees and the crackle of bubbling tar. But in the last couple of weeks, he has had to  adjust to a new, more frequent sound: airplanes.</p>
        <p>"Now the birds have competition," said Mr. Stanski, who lives in Montgomery Township, Somerset County, and is president of the Princeton Free Wheelers Bicycle Club. "The airplane noise gives you a sense that technology and the metropolitan area are encroaching on the environment."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Frank Stanski rides his bicycle down rustic, sleepy roads in western New Jersey, he usually hears things like crickets and frogs, the wind in the trees and the crackle of bubbling tar. But in the last couple of weeks, he has had to  adjust to a new, more frequent sound: airplanes.</p>
        <p>"Now the birds have competition," said Mr. Stanski, who lives in Montgomery Township, Somerset County, and is president of the Princeton Free Wheelers Bicycle Club. "The airplane noise gives you a sense that technology and the metropolitan area are encroaching on the environment."</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, the Federal Aviation Administration changed the flight patterns of westbound planes from Newark International Airport, in part to appease Union County residents who had complained for years about the roar of climbing jets over their neighborhoods. But now people on the ground are complaining that the new routes may only have shifted the problem elsewhere, to  Hunterdon, Somerset and Mercer Counties and even parts of Union.</p>
        <p>"You feel like you're in a condo in West Windsor instead of this house in the middle of the countryside," said Barbara Conklin of Kingwood Township, Hunterdon County, who has heard planes whizzing overhead more frequently, sometimes at three-minute intervals. "It's not enough to rattle the china in my house, but we're talking about annoyance of the nth degree. And my bet is that as the weather gets warmer, people will start noticing the planes more."</p>
        <p>Noise pollution is a highly subjective issue, and some Hunterdon residents say they have not noticed any difference. But because the air space over the New York metropolitan area is the busiest in the world, the Federal Government's handling of the crescendo of complaints from New Jersey has attracted nationwide attention and could set precedents for similar noise disputes in Denver, Seattle, Chicago and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>"No matter what you do in the New York-New Jersey area, it's probably going to hit somebody hard, so that's why you've seen a lot of counties and groups who are interested in using political process very aggressively," said Charlotte S.  Garvey, editor of Noise Regulation Report, a biweekly newsletter in Silver Spring, Md., that focuses on airplane noise issues. "There might be some parallel in watching how the F.A.A. handles this and how the F.A.A. will resolve other regional air-traffic crowding issues."</p>
        <p>For its part, the F.A.A. is monitoring Newark's 340 daily westbound flights (220 of which are jets) for things like wind, noise levels, attitude and location. And it plans a public meeting in June to discuss the data.</p>
        <p>"We think it's going very well, but it's been kind of a mixed bag so far," said John Walker, manager of air traffic for the agency's eastern region, about  the reaction to the new routes. "However, I think it's important that we made this one change, because it gives us the opportunity to insure that the relationship between us and the citizens' groups grows."</p>
        <p>It has been a long, often stormy relationship. In 1987, the aviation agency adopted the Expanded East Coast Plan, which spread air traffic over the central  and northern parts of New Jersey to make the skies less crowded. But the new routes enraged many residents of Union County and other suburban areas who were  not used to the noise.</p>
        <p>More than $6 million worth of studies, 30 public hearings, and 2,800 formal responses to citizens' comments later, the agency last year approved a proposal  to consolidate three flight paths across Union County into two, with one route shifted south and the other nudged north. The plan also rerouted eastbound flights to La Guardia Airport about 10 miles south, over Raritan Bay.</p>
        <p>But the new routes did not satisfy the most vocal anti-noise group, the New Jersey Coalition Against Aircraft Noise, based in Scotch Plains. It championed an ocean route that would have required westbound flights to head east from Newark, then make a U-turn over Raritan Bay and head west. The plan was designed by Glenn A. Bales, an aviation consultant who was a former project manager of the F.A.A.'s 1987 East Coast Plan and now is an aviation consultant in Colorado.</p>
        <p>But the agency rejected Mr. Bales's route, saying it was too costly and dangerous. It costs $35 extra per minute to keep a plane in the air; multiply that by perhaps 30 minutes for the extra U-turn, and then by several planes, and the total starts to pile up, said Mr. Walker of the F.A.A.</p>
        <p>Floyd Evans, a retired pilot who now lives in Flemington (and says he hasn't  been troubled by any additional noise in recent weeks), says the new plan is about as good as it gets -- that living in the New York metropolitan area requires a tacit acceptance of airplane noise. And besides, airplane engines are getting quieter.</p>
        <p>But that hasn't stopped the calls to the F.A.A. and elected officials. Coni Betzendahl of Annandale, executive director of a new citizens' group, Aircraft Irritates Hunterdon, Too, recites a litany of complaints it has received: residents who say they feel there are highways overhead; real estate brokers who say potential buyers have expressed concern about the noise; hunters and fishermen who say the noise scares the wildlife.</p>
        <p>Even some people for whom the plan was supposed to offer relief have not been satisfied. "We all waited for April 25, and I can't believe what happened: it was just nose to tail again for hours on end," said Pauline Arkoulakis, a resident of Scotch Plains. "I thought it was a mistake.</p>
        <p>"It's been eight or nine years, and you get weary of it all. You go to meetings, you make statements, you send in written statements and you look forward to the day when you think you're going to get some relief -- and then, it's a disappointment."</p>
        <p>THE GREAT OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
