<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. to Sell Saudis $20 Billion in Arms; Weapons Deal Is Largest in History</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="384064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS SALES ABROAD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIDDLE EAST-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERSIAN GULF</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DB173AF936A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. to Sell Saudis $20 Billion in Arms; Weapons Deal Is Largest in History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the single largest arms sale ever, the United States has agreed to sell Saudi Arabia about $20 billion in advanced weapons and technical support over several years, the Pentagon said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the single largest arms sale ever, the United States has agreed to sell Saudi Arabia about $20 billion in advanced weapons and technical support over several years, the Pentagon said today.</p>
        <p>In the single largest arms sale ever, the United States has agreed to sell Saudi Arabia about $20 billion in advanced weapons and technical support over several years, the Pentagon said today.</p>
        <p>The sale expands by billions of dollars previously announced arms sales to Riyadh and reflects the Bush Administration's eagerness to use the Persian Gulf crisis as an opportunity to sell the Saudis weapons they have sought for years.</p>
        <p>Last week, Administration officials said the United States was planning to sell Saudi Arabia hundreds of advanced tanks and armored vehicles and thousands of trucks as part of an $8 billion package.</p>
        <p>Today's disclosure, however, broadens that deal to include F-15 fighter planes, Patriot ground-to-air missiles, Apache anti-tank helicopters and possibly mobile missile launchers. Also included are spare parts, training and maintenance of the equipment.</p>
        <p>Windfall for Weapons Makers</p>
        <p>The sale - to be paid for in cash by the Saudis - represents a windfall for American military contractors, who until the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait had gloomily anticipated cuts in Pentagon spending.</p>
        <p>''This could be called the defense industry relief act of 1990,'' said a senior Congressional aide, who expressed amazement at the magnitude of the sale. Even Pentagon officials privately expressed surprise at the scale of the arms sale, which is expected to meet little resistance in Congress.</p>
        <p>In addition, Congressional officials said that the agreement calls for building new airfields, barracks and other support structures. A shortage of available airfields has forced the United States to station fighter and transport planes in several adjacent gulf countries.</p>
        <p>''This is basically the Saudis' wish list,'' an official familiar with the details of the arms deal said.</p>
        <p>Congressional supporters of Israel, the United States' chief ally in the Middle East, have in the past stymied or reduced the size of arms deals to Arab countries. But the specter of Iraqi troops attacking the American-led international force in Saudi Arabia has muted even Israel's staunchest supporters on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>No Time to Argue</p>
        <p>''This isn't the climate to be challenging these sales,'' said Representative Lawrence J. Smith, Democrat of Florida, who has opposed arms transfers to Arab countries in the past.</p>
        <p>The sale of Awacs early-warning radar planes to the Saudis in 1981, which introduced the advanced aircraft into the politically charged Middle East, touched off a bruising battle between Congress and the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>A Pentagon official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said that Congress would be officially notified of the sale on Monday or Tuesday. Lawmakers would then have 30 days to reject the agreement.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon official said that the arms and other equipment and services would be delivered in several installments over the next few years. The first shipment could be made within the next few weeks, the official said.</p>
        <p>Details of the weapons shipments to Saudi Arabia were first reported by the Cable News Network on Thursday.</p>
        <p>British Transaction Recalled</p>
        <p>The size of shipments disclosed today would dwarf the previously largest arms transaction, a 1988 agreement by the British to send the Saudis more than $10 billion in weapons, including 48 Tornado aircraft.</p>
        <p>The arms sales are not likely to end with the Saudis. Defense Minister Moshe Arens of Israel is scheduled to meet with Defense Secretary Dick Cheney at the Pentagon on Monday.</p>
        <p>Congressional officials and American Jewish groups said they expected Mr. Arens to press Washington for more sophisticated arms to maintain Israel's qualitative military edge.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have said they have agreed in principle to supply Israel with hundreds of millions of dollars in weapons, including Patriot ground-to-air missiles, but American and Israeli officials are still negotiating details.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Saudis, who always pay cash for their purchases, Administration officials are scrambling to devise financing for any deals with the Israelis.</p>
        <p>More Oil Money, Too</p>
        <p>Since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, the Saudis have gone on a spending spree for new weapons, aided by the billions of dollars in oil revenue from the rise of in petroleum prices and production.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, President Bush invoked emergency powers to send 24 F-15 planes, 150 M-60 tanks and 200 Stinger anti-aircraft missiles for $2.2 billion. Under this special authority, the 30-day Congressional review period required by the Arms Export Control Act was waived.</p>
        <p>The package disclosed today includes 24 additional F-15 air-to-air fighters; as many as 48 Apache helicopters, 385 M-1A2 tanks, 400 to 500 M-2 Bradley armed personnel carriers, and thousands of trucks and jeeps.</p>
        <p>''It's a monster sale,'' said Representative Mel Levine, Democrat of California, who is a frequent critic of American arms sales to Arab countries. ''With something of this magnitude, you're talking about everything but the kitchen sink.''</p>
        <p>Taken together, the immediate and longer-term arms shipments are likely to reshape the Saudi armored forces and nearly double their existing fleet of F15's, a top fighter plane.</p>
        <p>''What you're seeing is a commitment by the Saudis to a larger standing military if they're going to operate all this stuff,'' said Joel L. Johnson, a vice president with the Aerospace Industries Association.</p>
        <p>CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
