<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lucas Will Be Around the Jets, Somewhere, if Not Everywhere</title>
    <meta content="08JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1000690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucas, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DA1730F93BA35750C0A96E958260" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lucas Will Be Around the Jets, Somewhere, if Not Everywhere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets prepare for start of voluntary off-season workout program; quarterback Ray Lucas comments on uncertainty about his role (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Jets prepare for the start of their voluntary off-season workout program tomorrow, Ray Lucas could be the only quarterback who knows what his role will be. He knows he won't be the starter.</p>
        <p>But Lucas wants to be. He used to be a pretty good quarterback for Rutgers. And in his biggest shot at being a National Football League quarterback -- last season's finale against the Lions -- he almost provided the score that could have put the team in the playoffs. Almost.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Jets prepare for the start of their voluntary off-season workout program tomorrow, Ray Lucas could be the only quarterback who knows what his role will be. He knows he won't be the starter.</p>
        <p>But Lucas wants to be. He used to be a pretty good quarterback for Rutgers. And in his biggest shot at being a National Football League quarterback -- last season's finale against the Lions -- he almost provided the score that could have put the team in the playoffs. Almost.</p>
        <p>Now Lucas begins the off-season adventure to turn him into a regular passer. It coincides with the start of the 40-session conditioning program, where quarterback Neil O'Donnell could be the only absentee except for injured players.</p>
        <p>Lucas will also start working with the new quarterback coach, Dan Henning. But Lucas is not giving up the role that got him here.</p>
        <p>''Coach Parcells told me he wants me to compete for the quarterback's job,'' Lucas said recently. ''But I hope he doesn't want to take me off the special teams.''</p>
        <p>Of course, no one -- not even Bill Parcells -- knows the name of the Jets' starting quarterback. The Jets have given O'Donnell a $2.75 million advance on his salary, but they want to renegotiate it downward. And while the plan is to bulk up Glenn Foley, Parcells is concerned about Foley's ability to stand up to a full season of pounding.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, O'Donnell's agent, Leigh Steinberg, said the quarterback asked Parcells to be excused from the workout. His wish was granted.</p>
        <p>What could be the only known quarterback quantity on the Jets is that Lucas is being groomed in some sort of backup role. He has been told he will play in exhibition games this summer.</p>
        <p>The 25-year-old Lucas, entering his third N.F.L. season, is going to attend the meetings with the quarterbacks, whoever they are. He will be tutored privately by Henning, but Lucas will also be going to meetings with the special teams.</p>
        <p>''I coached against him in 1994 and 1995,'' recalled Henning, who was the Boston College coach then. ''I remember Ray from college. He was pretty good. He was probably the top quarterback in the Big East. I remember him mostly in a shotgun, to be honest. But I remember him.''</p>
        <p>Parcells returned Lucas to quarterback last season after he starred in practice. Lucas mirrored Jeff Blake for the game with the Bengals, and the season before, when he played for the Parcells-coached Patriots, he had mirrored Kordell Stewart for the playoff game against the Steelers.</p>
        <p>Lucas did not even get into a Jets game until Week 12. And then he scampered 15 yards. Against the Lions, Lucas threw his first N.F.L. pass when he came in on a third-and-1, and he connected with Keyshawn Johnson. It led to a field goal.</p>
        <p>Lucas soon came in again on a third-and-1 and, on the option, ran for 17 yards. Later, with the Jets leading by 10-6, he entered near midfield on a first down and completed a 19-yarder to Kyle Brady, scrambled for another 11 yards and connected with a short pass to Wayne Chrebet.</p>
        <p>But Lucas's perfect passing record was halted when he tried to force the ball to Fred Baxter. It was intercepted by Ron Rice.</p>
        <p>''The only person who said something to me after that game was Keyshawn,'' Lucas said. ''He said: 'You played pretty well. You're not perfect.' ''</p>
        <p>And after arriving recently, after having been the offensive coordinator with the Bills, Henning told Lucas, ''If there's a shadow of a doubt, you don't do it.''</p>
        <p>Lucas set a Rutgers passing record with 43 career touchdowns. But as a free agent at the Patriots' camp in 1996, Parcells did not know what to do with him. The first day he was a defensive back, the second day a wide receiver, the third a quarterback.</p>
        <p>Lucas said: ''I went to practice and Coach Parcells said, 'Well, son' -- and he paused for two seconds; it seemed like an hour -- and he said, 'We want to keep you if you want to stay.' And I said, 'What does that mean?' '' It meant Parcells liked him, and on the roster he was a wide receiver.</p>
        <p>Henning said he has yet to work with any of the Jets' quarterbacks. But he will now start working with the quarterbacks in the enclosed bubble at camp in Hempstead, N.Y. Twenty-two years ago, Henning also worked with a young Jets quarterback when Richard Todd joined the team as Joe Namath's heir apparent. Since then, Henning went on to Super Bowl seasons as a Redskins' assistant and became a head coach in San Diego and Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Henning is not specific about what he will try to teach Lucas. Indeed, the coach sounds almost modest, as if he's the new kid on the block, and not Lucas.</p>
        <p>He said he knows this about Lucas, though: ''It's to his credit that he was able to make it in this league as a non-quarterback. He had to be tough. Then he had to have some athletic skills. For him to catch the eye of coaches in this league, and Bill in particular, well, he must have demonstrated a toughness.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
