<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Song of the Earth</title>
    <meta content="08ROCKWET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1000390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockwell, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mahler, Gustav (1860-1911)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mahler (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE1E3EF93BA35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Song of the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Rockwell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rockwell, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Rockwell reviews book Mahler by Jonathan Carr; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAHLER</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Carr.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 272 pp. Woodstock, N.Y.:</p>
        <p>The Overlook Press. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAHLER</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Carr.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 272 pp. Woodstock, N.Y.:</p>
        <p>The Overlook Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>They used to say that except for Jesus Christ (or maybe it was Napoleon), nobody was the subject of more books than Richard Wagner. After a few decades of relative neglect, however, Gustav Mahler must be catching up to his erstwhile idol. Even if that claim comes close to Mahlerian hyperbole, it reflects the centrality to our time of a musician once better known as a conductor than as a composer. Jonathan Carr's deft little summary of the literature makes that amply clear, yet aside from the basics -- Henri Louis de la Grange's compulsively detailed multivolume biography, Donald Mitchell's searching musical analyses and Alma Mahler's still-controversial memoir and (bluntly edited) collections of letters -- he limits himself largely to his own, highly selective personal favorites.</p>
        <p>After all that tonnage of Mahlermania, what are we to make of this slim, almost chatty volume? Carr is a foreign correspondent by trade, apparently -- to judge from the cursory biographical information on this book and the tone of his prose -- untrained in musicology. He writes as an enthusiastic amateur for enthusiastic amateurs or for readers who, having been touched by Mahler's music, might want to know more.</p>
        <p>Carr is British, and his country's tradition of the gentleman musicologist has been a long and honorable one. Even Andrew Porter, who has done more than anyone in recent decades to introduce musicological rigor to journalistic criticism, is himself not a musicologist by formal training. The British musical amateur (the word, after all, originally meant a ''lover'' or ''devotee'' of an art) sharing his love for other amateurs is perhaps akin to the relative conservatism of 20th-century British composition. Not for most Britons those wild flights into the positivist empyrean, so beloved of tough-guy academic serialists and fearsome parsers of musical syntax.</p>
        <p>What Carr offers here is an intelligent, solidly based, up-to-date account of Mahler's life interleaved with non-technical but still perceptive musical insights. I must confess that at first I found his approach, or more precisely his tone, simplistic -- with his earnest explanations of all things musical and nonmusical and his dogged translations of German titles perhaps best rendered in English in the first place. But the sensible lucidity of his writing convinces on its own terms. Carr is, above all, balanced. (Which does not mean that in his perceptive essay on recommended recordings he always prefers the safe over the ecstatic. Just sometimes.) The last line of his introduction, after sketching contradictory views of Mahler -- saint, devil, idealist, careerist, healthy, sickly, optimistic, death-obsessed, guilt-ridden Jew, quasi-Buddhistic converted Roman Catholic -- asks, ''Which of them is the real Mahler?'' But of course he never fully resolves the contradictions, and quite properly so; instead he juggles all of them in the air, the way Mahler himself seems to embrace all possibilities in his music.</p>
        <p>Mahler's life, in roughest outline, goes like this: A musically gifted German-speaking Jew, born in Bohemia, gains entrance to the Vienna Conservatory and climbs rapidly up the ladder as an opera conductor, from the smallest posts (Laibach) to the most prestigious (Vienna Court Opera and Philharmonic, Metropolitan Opera and New York Philharmonic). On the way he establishes himself as a symphonic conductor, although never with the success he enjoyed in the opera house. He has many affairs, although the strength of his libido and the skill of his amatory technique remain in doubt. He woos and wins the fairest damsel in Vienna. And oh yes, working almost exclusively in the summers between musical seasons, he composes enough music to claim posthumously a firm place in the pantheon.</p>
        <p>Mahler won devoted admirers, and their legion has only grown since his death in 1911. Like all devotees (''amateurs''), they seem to see in Mahler some aspect of themselves. Thus he became the death-driven forebear of all the agony of the 20th century. He became the archetypal Jewish composer, both for the Nazis and for his latter-day champions (many of them Jewish), who seem unfazed by their hero's seeming indifference to his own tradition and his seemingly calculated conversion to Catholicism. He became a hero for rigorous modernists (Schoenberg) and, with his collages of music grand and banal, high and low, for post-modernists as well. His anxieties and a four-hour walk in the woods with Sigmund Freud opened the doors to post-Freudian analysis of his music. And his technical sophistication (despite his own laments that he should have paid more attention in his Vienna counterpoint class) made him fair game for the positivist parsers.</p>
        <p>Carr maneuvers carefully through all this, alert to the latest discoveries and interpretations and generally fair-minded in his judgments. He is also sweetly willing to dally by the roadside of his tale to explore a point that catches his fancy (just when Mahler first met Alma, or the proper tempo for the Adagietto of the Fifth Symphony). To those with a feminist bent, he may seem a little hard on Alma, who in Mahler literature is either a trivial, heartless coquette or, less frequently, a martyr in a world of egomaniacal men. Carr debunks the image of Mahler as wasted and morbid, seeing buoyant optimism up to the end (which came from a heart already weakened by bacterial infection that could have been dispatched by penicillin a few years later).</p>
        <p>On the whole, Carr's musical descriptions seem apt, and in them he makes another balanced compromise between formalist abstraction and crude life-art parallels. Only very occasionally, and rather endearingly, does the amateur fan emerge: ''No Mahler score, perhaps no score at all, better repays prolonged scrutiny,'' he enthuses about ''Das Lied von der Erde''; so much for ''Tristan und Isolde,'' so much for Bach. And only occasionally can one flush him out in an actual error: Hans Gregor, who succeeded Felix Weingartner as director of the Vienna Opera in 1911, is unfairly dismissed as ''no musician but (evidently more important) a canny businessman''; he was also a noted stage director.</p>
        <p>But by and large Carr knows what tale he's telling and he tells it well. He is good on the posthumous Mahler, too, putting Leonard Bernstein's immense contribution to the Mahler legacy in proper perspective and recognizing the crucial role of the long-playing record in establishing Mahler as a mainstream composer. One wishes the main text, before Carr gets to a consideration of the literature and the recordings, ended more eloquently. Throughout, his prose style remains stubbornly British in its tone and idioms, eschewing Continental rhetoric, let alone central European angst, in favor of good common sense.</p>
        <p>But there is nothing wrong with good sense, especially in an introduction to a complex and contradictory composer. Minor grumbles aside, Carr has written a valuable book, even a valuable addition to the swelling Mahler bibliography. It will be less necessary for the specialist than for the amateur. But it is smart enough not to insult the expert, and that smartness and an amateur's passion infuse what could otherwise have been a dutiful run-through. This is a book that does its own tradition, that of the purveyor of enlightened, gentlemanly insights, proud.  John Rockwell is the editor of the Arts and Leisure section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Rockwell is the editor of the Arts and Leisure section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
