<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators Keep Gay Nominee for Luxembourg Post in Limbo</title>
    <meta content="08AMBA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1000680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Luxembourg</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shenon, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hormel, James C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Luxembourg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Luxembourg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DC1730F93BA35750C0A96E958260" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators Keep Gay Nominee for Luxembourg Post in Limbo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shenon, Philip</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton's nomination last year of James C Hormel, who is gay, to be ambassador to Luxembourg appears hopelessly stalled on Capitol Hill; Hormel is 65-year-old philanthropist and heir to Hormel meat-processing fortune; group of conservative Senate Republicans has placed hold on his nomination, and Sen Trent Lott, Senate majority leader, says he has no plans to bring nomination to vote (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the State Department announced last year that James C. Hormel, who is gay, had been nominated to be an ambassador, there was jubilation here, and not just among the city's homosexuals.</p>
        <p>George P. Shultz, who returned to San Francisco after serving as President Ronald Reagan's Secretary of State, said Mr. Hormel would be a ''wonderful representative of our country'' to Luxembourg, the European duchy where he was being posted. Don Fisher, founder of the Gap, the retailing giant, described Mr. Hormel as a ''paragon of ethics.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the State Department announced last year that James C. Hormel, who is gay, had been nominated to be an ambassador, there was jubilation here, and not just among the city's homosexuals.</p>
        <p>George P. Shultz, who returned to San Francisco after serving as President Ronald Reagan's Secretary of State, said Mr. Hormel would be a ''wonderful representative of our country'' to Luxembourg, the European duchy where he was being posted. Don Fisher, founder of the Gap, the retailing giant, described Mr. Hormel as a ''paragon of ethics.''</p>
        <p>''It would be a loss to our country to not have someone of his stellar character representing us abroad,'' Mr. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>But the nomination of the 65-year-old philanthropist and heir to the Hormel meat-processing fortune appears hopelessly stalled on Capitol Hill. A group of conservative Senate Republicans has placed a hold on his nomination, and Senator Trent Lott, the Senate majority leader, has said he has no plans to bring the nomination to a vote.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Hormel seems to be an amiable, congenial individual, and I'm sure he's done a lot of good things,'' said Senator Tim Hutchinson, an Arkansas Republican who put a hold on the nomination after learning of Mr. Hormel's involvement in several gay rights groups. ''But he's very much got an agenda.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hormel's philanthropy reaches beyond the issue of gay rights. He supports charities for breast-cancer victims and the homeless. He is a director of the San Francisco Symphony and the Chamber of Commerce. He is a key benefactor of Swarthmore College, his alma mater, and the University of Chicago Law School, where he financed a program to encourage students to enter public-interest law.</p>
        <p>San Franciscans who know Mr. Hormel as a civic leader are indignant at the Senate's treatment of a favorite son of this famously tolerant city. ''I think it's a travesty that a handful of Senators are blocking this body from voting for a qualified nominee,'' said Senator Dianne Feinstein, a California Democrat and a former Mayor of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The Administration has vowed to press ahead with the nomination. In a speech here recently, President Clinton praised Mr. Hormel and urged Senators to put aside any prejudice. ''I have just one question,'' the President said. ''Will he or will he not be a good ambassador?''</p>
        <p>Traditional Values, a religious group based in Anaheim, Calif., is organizing the campaign against Mr. Hormel. Its executive director, Andrea Sheldon, said that Mr. Hormel was the Administration's ''homosexual poster boy'' and that he was being given the post in Luxembourg so the Administration ''could fill its quota of homosexuals.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sheldon has given several Senators a three-inch-thick binder filled with photocopies of sexually graphic material from the James C. Hormel Gay and Lesbian Center, which was set up at the San Francisco Public Library in 1996 with a $500,000 donation from Mr. Hormel. Most of the collection is duplicated in the Library of Congress. In a letter, Mr. Hormel said he did not play a role in the selection of books or magazines for the center, and the San Francisco library confirms this.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hormel answered some of his critics in a letter to Senator Gordon H. Smith, an Oregon Republican and member of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. ''I will not use, nor do I think it is appropriate to use, the office of the ambassador to advocate any personal views I may hold on any issue,'' Mr. Hormel said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
