<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Afghans Mark Year of Slowly Growing Stability</title>
    <meta content="25AFGH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/25/international/asia/25AFGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: KARZAI'S PROGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karzai, Hamid (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rabbani, Burhanuddin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Karzai, Hamid</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDA133CF936A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Afghans Mark Year of Slowly Growing Stability</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Afghans Mark Year of Slowly Growing Stability</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>KABUL, Afghanistan, Dec. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Afghanistan has achieved degree of stability in year since Hamid Karzai began governing, even if it is not yet united country with functioning multiethnic army; Karzai acknowledges some failures of his government, namely security and disarmament, and vows to tackle those issues more energetically in year ahead; Burhanuddin Rabbani, former president who last year opposed Karzai's presidency, now voices unreserved support for him and central government; American forces based in country now contemplate moving from combat operations toward development activities, deploying larger teams of civil affairs officers in 8 to 10 provincial centers to give boost to economic development; American officials say battle against Taliban and Al Qaeda is drawing to end and effort to win peace and help government establish its control countrywide is new target; economic condition of country remain precarious; regional warlords continue to flex enormous power, but Karzai is intent on winning them over by persuasion rather than force of arms (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a year ago that Hamid Karzai took over the business of governing Afghanistan, a ruin of a country he and his government inherited after the collapse of the Taliban and have tried to guide through its first year relatively free of war in two decades.</p>
        <p>A united Afghanistan with a functioning multiethnic army remains a desire, not a reality. Yet despite violent incidents -- a narrow escape from assassination, the killing of two of his ministers and continued clashes among rival warlords in the provinces -- Mr. Karzai is looking stronger now that under his stewardship the country has found a degree of stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite violent incidents, Hamid Karzai is looking stronger now that his stewardship of Afghanistan has found a degree of stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a year ago that Hamid Karzai took over the business of governing Afghanistan, a ruin of a country he and his government inherited after the collapse of the Taliban and have tried to guide through its first year relatively free of war in two decades.</p>
        <p>A united Afghanistan with a functioning multiethnic army remains a desire, not a reality. Yet despite violent incidents -- a narrow escape from assassination, the killing of two of his ministers and continued clashes among rival warlords in the provinces -- Mr. Karzai is looking stronger now that under his stewardship the country has found a degree of stability.</p>
        <p>That was underscored today when a former president, Burhanuddin Rabbani, who last year opposed the United Nations plan to make Mr. Karzai president, voiced unreserved support for him and the central government at a ceremony marking their first year in office.</p>
        <p>Speaking to an audience of high-level government officials at the ceremony, Mr. Karzai acknowledged some failures of his government, namely security and disarmament, and vowed to tackle those issues more energetically in the next year.</p>
        <p>In a sign of progress made, American forces based in Afghanistan have been contemplating moving from combat operations toward development activities, deploying larger teams of civil affairs officers in 8 to 10 provincial centers to give a boost to economic development.</p>
        <p>The battle against the Taliban and Al Qaeda has been drawing to an end, and the effort to win the peace and help the government establish its control countrywide is the new target, American military officials and diplomats have said.</p>
        <p>Rocket and grenade attacks against American forces -- and recently suicide bomber attacks -- have continued and even increased in recent weeks. Yet they remain small in scale, and any concerted organized opposition to the presence of about 9,000 United States troops has failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>The economic situation in the country remains precarious, however. Of the population of 20 million, nearly two million are recently returned refugees struggling to find a way to survive their first winter back.</p>
        <p>Some 1.3 million people will be relying on food aid this winter, the World Food Program says, and more than half a million displaced people are considered vulnerable and in need of shelter and relief assistance, according to the United Nations refugee agency.</p>
        <p>Although several nations pledged more than $4.5 billion in aid this year, not all of that money has arrived. The United States gave about $588 million this year, and expects to contribute a similar amount to the roughly $2 billion pledged by various nations for 2003, the State Department says.</p>
        <p>Regional leaders continue to flex enormous power, running their own armies, collecting their own taxes and customs and to some extent running their own foreign policy. Armed clashes have continued, as regional commanders seek to consolidate their local power or defeat rivals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karzai, determined to avoid further bloodshed for his exhausted and traumatized people, has chosen to win over the warlords by persuasion -- a tactic that so far has won at least their verbal support for his government.</p>
        <p>The list Mr. Karzai gave today of his government's undeniable achievements and the cheering he received from police and military officers who filled the auditorium spoke for themselves.</p>
        <p>Among those achievements is Mr. Karzai's success in binding together a disparate cabinet that includes veterans of the guerrilla war against the Soviets, Western-educated Afghans who returned after 20 years abroad and representatives of ethnic groups that had been fighting one another.</p>
        <p>In a striking gesture of support, his defense minister, Marshal Muhammad Qasim Fahim, warned regional commanders in his speech today that they must give up some of their power and bow to the authority of the central government. It was the strongest sign yet of the Marshal Fahim's readiness to move against the powerful warlords, several of whom are his own supporters and source of power.</p>
        <p>Marshal Fahim, probably the most powerful man in Afghanistan thanks to his control of the bulk of the country's heavy weaponry and men under arms, has been slow to dismantle the forces loyal to him and make way for the civilian authorities.</p>
        <p>The president signed a decree this month to create a multiethnic, regionally diverse national army, which envisions disarmament and demobilization of the various armed militias that fought the Taliban.</p>
        <p>Trying to separate political and military powers, Mr. Karzai further ordered military commanders to relinquish political positions and regional leaders or governors to give up their military positions.</p>
        <p>Marshal Fahim has been involved in creating the plan for the national army, but his commitment to real change remains to be tested. Without his cooperation, Mr. Karzai's decrees are worth little, since his practical power does not stretch much beyond the capital.</p>
        <p>But in his comments today, Marshall Fahim called for sacrifices in order to create a strong central government.</p>
        <p>''We should have a powerful central government according to the wishes of our people, and to achieve this aim, we should make some sacrifices,'' he said. ''We should give up some positions. It is very necessary that we come under the command of the central government, so let's put an end to local military power bases.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Karzai, as often before, promised constitutional reform and preparations in the coming year for Afghanistan's first democratic elections in more than 20 years. ''You will have the right to choose whomever you want,'' he told the audience.</p>
        <p>Speaking in the hall where he was inaugurated on Dec. 22 last year, Mr. Karzai noted with typical understatement that there was still fighting between different groups in some areas, ''and in this point, we have not been completely successful.''</p>
        <p>Disarmament started in some provinces in the last month, but it needs to move faster, he said.</p>
        <p>''Although the general security situation is good, sometimes theft, robbery and killing occurs,'' he said. ''Sometimes it is carried out by people who are linked to authority figures working in the government.''</p>
        <p>In his frank look back over the last year, Mr. Karzai remembered particular low moments -- the killing of over 40 civilians in Deh Rawud, in southern Afghanistan on July 1, during a raid by American-led forces hunting for terrorists; the car bomb that killed 30 men and women in central Kabul on Sept. 5 (on the same day, there was an attempt on Mr. Karzai's life in Kandahar); the assassination of his vice president, Haji Abdul Qadir, on July 6; and the killing of two students in demonstrations in Kabul last month, for which he blamed ill-trained policemen.</p>
        <p>But he also talked of moments of joy and optimism, when during visits to the provinces he encountered ordinary and poor people who had given him their support.</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: KARZAI'S PROGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
