<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Crafts and Cookies, Girl Scouts Are Prospering</title>
    <meta content="25SCOU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/25/nyregion/25SCOU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atheism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Girl Scouts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boy Scouts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atheism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Girl Scouts</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Boy Scouts of America</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DA133CF936A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Crafts and Cookies, Girl Scouts Are Prospering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beyond Crafts and Cookies, Girl Scouts Are Prospering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>LARCHMONT, N.Y., Dec. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Girl Scouts are prospering locally and nationally, with membership at 20-year high of 2.8 million; are increasingly retaining girls as they enter their teenage years, dropout point in past, by shedding somewhat square image and offering rugged adventures, internships and travel opportunities; have also steered clear of controversies about sexual orientation and religion that have dogged Boy Scouts; badges earned by scouts today can reflect implicitly feminist message and awareness of contemporary issues as well as traditional values; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a chilly cabin here, the ambitious young suburbanites brainstormed a few weeks back on ways to relieve stress. The solutions were the usual: bubble baths by candlelight, yoga, relaxing music, setting limits.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing wrong with being busy,'' said Vickie Hage, an architect in Mamaroneck, helping the fourth graders in Girl Scout Troop 1839 work on their ''Stress Less'' merit badge. ''It's much better to be busy than to not be busy. But you don't want to be so busy that it makes you cry or it makes you nervous or it makes you mean to your mom.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the Boy Scouts have stumbled from one controversy to another, membership in the Girl Scouts has hit a 20-year high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a chilly cabin here, the ambitious young suburbanites brainstormed a few weeks back on ways to relieve stress. The solutions were the usual: bubble baths by candlelight, yoga, relaxing music, setting limits.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing wrong with being busy,'' said Vickie Hage, an architect in Mamaroneck, helping the fourth graders in Girl Scout Troop 1839 work on their ''Stress Less'' merit badge. ''It's much better to be busy than to not be busy. But you don't want to be so busy that it makes you cry or it makes you nervous or it makes you mean to your mom.''</p>
        <p>Being a child in these high-stress, full-scheduled times is not what it used to be, and, as the Stress Less badge introduced a year ago indicates, neither are the Girl Scouts. In fact, while the Boy Scouts have stumbled from one controversy to another, Girl Scouts locally and nationally are prospering. National membership in the Girl Scouts of the U.S.A. has hit a 20-year high of 2.8 million, with 11 percent of all available girls signed on as scouts.</p>
        <p>The organization is increasingly retaining girls as they enter their teenage years, a traditional dropout point. It has done so, in part, by shedding the somewhat square image associated with scouting. It has also done so by offering rugged adventures like mountain climbing, as well as internships and travel opportunities. One troop here in Westchester County recently went to Kenya.</p>
        <p>But the Girl Scouts have also steered clear of the commotion surrounding sexual orientation and religion that has dogged the Boy Scouts of America in recent years. The Boy Scouts' position on homosexuality -- that gay members are not welcome -- has cost that organization financing and members. And troop leaders say the Girl Scouts, traditionally known for the three C's of crafts, cookies and camping, have evolved into a thoroughly modern organization. It has formed an implicitly feminist message by plugging into contemporary issues and trends, while maintaining its traditional values.</p>
        <p>In Westchester and Putnam Counties, for instance, the number of Boy Scouts has fallen to 9,500 from 13,000 in the last 10 years, a 27 percent decline. During the same period, membership in the Westchester-Putnam chapter of the Girl Scouts has risen by 24 percent, to 16,500 from 13,300.</p>
        <p>Even the Brownies, who are in the first through the third grades, are exposed to a range of not-so-girlish subjects. Yes, there are still badges in puppets and dolls and manners. But in the last several years, badges have been added in careers, ''penny power,'' computer smarts, space exploration and math fun.</p>
        <p>Years ago, there was a badge for 10- to 17-year-olds called matron housekeeper, which instructed girls in using a vacuum cleaner and identifying cuts of meat. Its counterpart today is a Ms. Fix-It badge, for junior Girl Scouts, ages 9 to 11. To earn the badge, girls need to be able to repair a leaky toilet and replace a broken window pane, among other things.</p>
        <p>''If you define feminism as a girl being strong-minded and independent and making decisions for herself, then yes, it's feminism,'' said Mary T. Stroock, chief executive of Girl Scouts of Westchester Putnam Inc. ''But I don't think that's necessarily feminism. I think it's just life now.''</p>
        <p>An example of how the organization has tried to stay current was the creation of a Girl Scout Research Institute three years ago at its headquarters in Manhattan. The institute conducts its own research and pulls together existing studies to help Girl Scouts of the U.S.A. plan for the future. One study, Teens Before Their Time, looked at the pressures on girls to act and look older than they are.</p>
        <p>Other research has shown the extent to which the older girls in scouting are particularly interested in career development. Harriet Fier, a filmmaker who leads a Girl Scout troop in Chappaqua, says that as the girls reach middle school and high school, there is a career component to almost everything they do.</p>
        <p>At a recent Girl Scout event devoted to games ranging from Monopoly to Twister, a counselor had set up a table nearby. ''The girls talked to her about how to turn your interest in games into a career,'' Ms. Fier said. ''No matter what they do there is an element that takes it further from the moment and gets the girls to think about this as something they can do as an adult.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fier's own family illustrates the shifting fortunes of the Girl Scouts and Boy Scouts in Westchester and Putnam. Her 12-year-old daughter, Laura Mantell, has been active in Girl Scouts since kindergarten. Her son, Will, left the Boy Scouts two years ago, at age 8, when the Boy Scouts' decision to exclude gays was making front-page headlines.</p>
        <p>Jack L. Sears, scout executive of the Westchester-Putnam Council of Boy Scouts of America, attributes the decline in membership less to any opposition over the group's policies than to a loss of financing. Responding to the Boy Scouts' position on homosexuality, the United Way of Westchester and Putnam stopped its annual contribution of $150,000; corporate support has also eroded.</p>
        <p>''If we had the financial resources to get the message out, we would have a lot more members joining,'' Mr. Sears said. ''If we want to embrace diversity, we have to embrace the right to associate.''</p>
        <p>For its part, the Girl Scouts do not prohibit lesbians from becoming members or leaders. Whether heterosexual or homosexual, members and leaders may not promote a particular sexual orientation or display any sexual behavior.</p>
        <p>As for religion, a member can substitute her own word for God in the Girl Scout promise. If a girl were an atheist but was still comfortable reciting the Girl Scout promise, the organization ''would not conduct an inquisition about what was behind that,'' said Sharon Woods Hussey, senior vice president of membership, program and research for Girls Scouts of the U.S.A.</p>
        <p>In November, the Boy Scouts ejected an Eagle Scout after he proclaimed himself an atheist. Even some Boy Scout leaders in Westchester wish their organization acted more like the Girl Scouts with regard to a scout's sexual orientation or religion.</p>
        <p>''Both of those issues were poorly handled and the Girl Scouts, to their credit, took a very different view and very different position,'' said Dr. William H. Flank, a professor of chemistry and environmental science at Pace University and a scoutmaster in Chappaqua. ''They don't discriminate, period, and I wish the B.S.A. would do the same.''</p>
        <p>The Girl Scouts' national organization has analyzed ZIP codes to make sure they are attracting girls from all socioeconomic backgrounds and has studied its existing membership rolls with an eye toward racial and ethnic diversity.</p>
        <p>There is a new push to attract Hispanic girls, who are not participating at the same rate as white and African-American girls. Similarly, the Girl Scouts have just started an initiative to introduce scouting to girls living in housing projects.</p>
        <p>The Girl Scouts reached their peak of popularity nationally during the baby-boom years of 1947 to 1955, when 12.5 percent of American girls were involved. Through the 1970's and mid-1980's, the ''market share,'' as Girl Scout officials put it, dipped to 10 percent. But it has since picked up and has hovered around 11 percent in recent years.</p>
        <p>The organization was founded in 1912 by Juliette Gordon Low, who believed all girls should be given the opportunity to develop physically, mentally and spiritually. From the start, the Girl Scouts sought to get girls out of their isolated home environments and into community service and the open air.</p>
        <p>Community service and the great outdoors still figure prominently in Girl Scouts. Recently, a troop in Briarcliff Manor was frantically looking for a way to pay a $1,500 shipping charge for a wheelchair and holiday gifts for a 6-year-old girl in Ecuador who can neither walk nor talk. The girl is related to the housekeeper of the troop leader, Diane Newman Kahn. The troop decided to use the money they had raised selling cookies to buy a high-tech, collapsible wheelchair for the Ecuadorean girl, whose family cannot afford one.</p>
        <p>Troop 1366, farther north in Putnam County, was getting ready for the annual Klondike Derby, a survival exercise scheduled to take place in January at the Girl Scouts' own 100-acre Rock Hill Camp.</p>
        <p>At a recent troop meeting, the girls practiced building fires outdoors and erecting a shelter, using only a tarp and trees. They will also have to demonstrate their orienteering skills and knowledge of first aid, as well as their ability to signal for help using S O S flags.</p>
        <p>With two daughters in Girl Scouts, Liz Rau leads two troops: 1366 and 2177. Both are preparing for the Klondike. Ms. Rau was a Girl Scout herself years ago; she left at the start of ninth grade. ''I quit because of the stigma of being in Girl Scouts,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her own daughters, Theresa, 13, and Patricia, 15, have no plans to leave. Patricia is admittedly a bit self-conscious about being a Girl Scout now that she is 15. But she is determined to remain in scouting through the end of high school, and she has set two goals: to take an overseas trip with her troop, and to earn the Gold Award, the equivalent of the boys' Eagle Scout honor.</p>
        <p>As for the lingering social stigma, Patricia said she did not broadcast the fact of her participation. But the Girl Scouts' main fund-raising vehicle, those iconic cookies, have made her popular in school, at least among the boys.</p>
        <p>''It's not cool,'' she said of the Girl Scouts, ''but it's accepted. Guys know you have cookies, and guys like food.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
