<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daring to Dream of Eradicating Poverty</title>
    <meta content="01GORD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illiteracy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordimer, Nadine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illiteracy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D61038F932A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daring to Dream of Eradicating Poverty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nadine Gordimer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordimer, Nadine</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nadine Gordimer Op-Ed article says her appointment as Goodwill Ambassador for UN Development Program's 'Decade for the Eradication of Poverty'; observes that cultural deprivation is also form of poverty, and that illiteracy is 'crime against humanity' (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What's the definition of an honor you can't refuse?</p>
        <p>For me, an appointment as Goodwill Ambassador for the United Nations Development Program's ''Decade for the Eradication of Poverty.'' This is a great honor; it's also an imperative disguised as an honor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What's the definition of an honor you can't refuse?</p>
        <p>For me, an appointment as Goodwill Ambassador for the United Nations Development Program's ''Decade for the Eradication of Poverty.'' This is a great honor; it's also an imperative disguised as an honor.</p>
        <p>It asserts something very important: that an individual can contribute, in one way or another, to the fight against poverty in our world of paradox, where plenty and dire need exist side by side.</p>
        <p>National governments and their policies have the primary responsibility in breaking through this paradox. International aid organizations, trade agreements, the World Bank, the International Monetary Fund, the European Union and other economic forces have perhaps equal, or even overriding responsibility. For if our much-vaunted globalization has meaning beyond technical miracles, it is the globalization of poverty.</p>
        <p>''The poor are always with us''; yes, the poor were always with us, but now we are with them. We come face to face with the victims of pandemic ethnic conflicts and multinational manipulative greed on television and the Internet, from the starving in the Sudan to the quarter of a million refugees in Guinea-Bissau to those poverty-stricken by civil strife in Eastern Europe, as well as in the rural villages, squatter camps and streets in our own countries where the homeless sleep.</p>
        <p>It is on this scale -- global poverty, the world's 1.3 billion poor -- that the the United Nations Development Program has the audacity to institute a program, with a time frame, to eradicate poverty in a world of plenty.</p>
        <p>Eradicate is a strong word, a bold ambition. Hubris? But I believe that nothing begins to take off without the drive of idealism.</p>
        <p>Poverty is an octopus whose tentacles reach out from under the rock of indifference to engage us all. Only if that grasp is responded to will that ancient adage, ''The poor are always with us,'' have the possibility to be disproved. Poverty is not ''in the nature of things.'' Poverty is not inevitable in the world today. There are the resources -- food, shelter, work, skills, training -- and means to make them available to all.</p>
        <p>I begin by realizing that we must revise preconceptions. People think of need firstly -- and rightly -- in terms of empty stomachs. But there are many forms of poverty, and they are interdependent. You surely cannot take up one without the other -- homelessness without employment, employment without education and training, health without food and shelter.</p>
        <p>Not generally recognized as such, cultural deprivation is also a form of poverty. I believe that illiteracy is a crime against humanity, for we are the only creatures who have the Word, and therefore implicit in our human condition is the right to read and write, and to create and enjoy the texts of the imagination.</p>
        <p>In my own country, a national poverty summit convened by church leaders and civic organizations has just published its report. Its findings are an indication, along with our Government's recent poverty and inequality report, of the poverty that is still with us.</p>
        <p>There are achievements to record. Lack of clean water is poverty; this basic need is being addressed vigorously by our Minister of Water Affairs, Kader Asmal. The deprivation of our land rights is poverty; in our country, where under apartheid people were stripped of their land and property, the Minister of Agriculture and Land Affairs, Derek Hanekom, and the Land Commission are wrestling with the problems of restoration of these rights to communities and individuals.</p>
        <p>The Growth, Employment and Redistribution program, known as GEAR, is the Government's basic, comprehensive reorganization strategy of our country of haves and have-nots. But nongovernmental organizations, often regarded only as bit players on someone else's stage, are now vital to the transformation. Their initiatives open to every individual the chance to contribute their personal energies -- whether you can teach someone to read or, as I saw a student group doing, whether you volunteer to dig the pit for a latrine at a rural school.</p>
        <p>A coalition of nongovernmental organizations has a journal that airs frank debate on issues affecting poverty, from the World Bank's loan conditions to controversy over the Growth, Employment and Redistribution program.</p>
        <p>This exchange is essential if we are to discard, everywhere, once and for all, the cop-out of charity: handouts that salve the conscience and perpetuate the problem.</p>
        <p>The widely publicized testimony of poor people at recent hearings around South Africa has bluntly established an incontestable principle of learning from them what they need to free themselves from poverty by their own efforts.</p>
        <p>The United Nations Development Program has successfully proved this policy internationally. In the last year, men and women from the United States, South America, Vietnam and South Africa have reported on their United Nations-assisted projects -- from fish farming in Vietnam to catering in New Jersey to soil conservation in El Salvador. Capacity-building projects like these are the scaffolding of dedication to material and spiritual reconstruction of people's damaged and unrealized lives.</p>
        <p>Nadine Gordimer was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1991.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nadine Gordimer was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1991.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
