<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irabu Sticks Around to Beat Seattle</title>
    <meta content="01YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7D91138F932A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irabu Sticks Around to Beat Seattle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>irabu sticks around to beat seattle**New York Yankees defeat Seattle Mariners, 5-4 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An hour before he was scheduled to pitch tonight, Hideki Irabu rested on a couch in the visitors' clubhouse, watching the Atlanta Braves and the St. Louis Cardinals on television as his interpreter, George Rose, picked at a buffet.</p>
        <p>Neither man had any idea if he would be employed by the Yankees at night's end. Irabu, who teammates said was hurt and distracted by the idea that the team had dangled him in trade discussions, beat the Mariners, 5-3. Irabu became the Yankees' fourth pitcher with 10 or more victories, joining David Cone (15), Andy Pettitte (13) and David Wells (12). Jorge Posada hit two home runs for the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An hour before he was scheduled to pitch tonight, Hideki Irabu rested on a couch in the visitors' clubhouse, watching the Atlanta Braves and the St. Louis Cardinals on television as his interpreter, George Rose, picked at a buffet.</p>
        <p>Neither man had any idea if he would be employed by the Yankees at night's end. Irabu, who teammates said was hurt and distracted by the idea that the team had dangled him in trade discussions, beat the Mariners, 5-3. Irabu became the Yankees' fourth pitcher with 10 or more victories, joining David Cone (15), Andy Pettitte (13) and David Wells (12). Jorge Posada hit two home runs for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are 76-27, the second-best 103-game record in this century, behind the 1902 Pittsburgh Pirates. They have won three of their first four games on this 10-game West Coast trip.</p>
        <p>According to baseball officials, Irabu was part of an offer to the Seattle Mariners for Randy Johnson, and Irabu could have only impressed the Mariners executives with his performance tonight.</p>
        <p>Irabu, his fastball buzzing and his off-speed pitches baffling, struck out four in the first four innings, giving up just two hits.</p>
        <p>Facing the Seattle left-hander Jeff Fassero in tonight's game, Yankees Manager Joe Torre decided to go with a lineup composed entirely of right-handed hitters.</p>
        <p>First baseman Tino Martinez and right fielder Paul O'Neill were given the night off, replaced by Luis Sojo and Shane Spencer, respectively.</p>
        <p>In the second inning, the Yankees' Chad Curtis doubled when his line drive short-hopped the wall in left-center field.</p>
        <p>One out later, Spencer hit a double off the wall in right-center, scoring Curtis (Spencer later hit a single, giving him two hits against the left-hander -- or one more hit than Dale Sveum, whom Spencer replaced on the roster, had in 12 at-bats agains lefties).</p>
        <p>Irabu struck out Shane Monahan in the third inning, and Jorge Posada, the Yankees' catcher, moved toward the dugout, three up, three down. Except that Monahan was the second out of the inning, and Posada sheepishly returned to his position.</p>
        <p>No wonder he was eager to get back to the dugout. Batting in the next half-inning, Posada slammed his 12th home run of the year off Seattle's Jeff Fassero, who offered a poorly thrown curveball with an 0-2 count.</p>
        <p>Two batters later, Scott Brosius lifted a home run into the stands into right-center field, becoming the 10th Yankees player to hit 10 or more home runs this season.</p>
        <p>Curtis singled home Tim Raines in the fifth, giving the Yankees a 4-1 lead. Edgar Martinez and David Segui slugged back-to-back homers off Irabu in the bottom of the sixth, shaving Irabu's advantage to one run.</p>
        <p>But Posada blasted his second home run of the game in the eighth, the Yankees' third solo homer.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CHILI DAVIS, making his second injury rehabilitation start with Class AA Norwich, was 1 for 4 . . . DARREN HOLMES, the Yankees' reliever, is bothered by a sore lower back, but he will probably be available this weekend.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
