<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson Is Shipped To Astros</title>
    <meta content="01BASE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Astros</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D91138F932A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson Is Shipped To Astros</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seattle Mariners give up waiting for New York Yankees decision and trade pitcher Randy Johnson to Houston Astros just before deadline for trades without waivers; list of some of day's trades (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees did not get Randy Johnson last night, but they didn't have to get the dominating pitcher to keep him from the Cleveland Indians. That is because the Seattle Mariners traded Johnson to the Houston Astros.</p>
        <p>In a stunning development just before the midnight deadline for trades without waivers, the Mariners quit waiting for the Yankees or the Indians to say yes to the package of players they wanted and instead shipped him to the other league and the first-place team that has the smallest lead among the National League's three division leaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees did not get Randy Johnson last night, but they didn't have to get the dominating pitcher to keep him from the Cleveland Indians. That is because the Seattle Mariners traded Johnson to the Houston Astros.</p>
        <p>In a stunning development just before the midnight deadline for trades without waivers, the Mariners quit waiting for the Yankees or the Indians to say yes to the package of players they wanted and instead shipped him to the other league and the first-place team that has the smallest lead among the National League's three division leaders.</p>
        <p>Instead of an established starting pitcher, an outfielder and a second baseman whom the Mariners had sought, the Astros gave up two minor league players and a player to be named. The minor leaguers are Freddy Garcia, a right-handed pitcher, who spent all of last season in the Astros' system after they selected him in the minor league draft, and Carlos Guillen, an infielder who like Garcia is a Venezuelan.</p>
        <p>Johnson, 34, began his major league career in the National League with the Montreal Expos but has been a member of the Mariners since they traded for him in 1989. He was on the trading block because the Mariners decided last winter they were not going to give him a contract extension at the kind of money he sought.</p>
        <p>At different times yesterday, various baseball officials and lawyers said Johnson was there for the Yankees' plucking if the Yankees said yes to the package of players the Mariners asked for. But the Yankees declined to take that step.</p>
        <p>All along, the Yankees' interest seemed to be fueled by their desire to keep Johnson away from the Indians, who they believe will be their prime competition for the American League pennant once they reach October and the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Astros have never been so aggressive, but they apparently decided Johnson could be the equalizer for them with the Atlanta Braves, who are always the team to beat in the N.L. playoffs. The Astros lead the Chicago Cubs in the N.L. Central by three and a half games. The Braves have a 15-game lead in the East and San Diego has a 13-game bulge in the West.</p>
        <p>''We identified all along our primary need was a No. 1 starter, and we got one of the dominating starters in the game,'' Gerry Hunsicker, the Astros' general manager, said. ''It's been a long night, and I didn't think we had much of a chance, but we were able to pull it off.''</p>
        <p>The Johnson trade was the most awaited on a day that was filled with trades.</p>
        <p>The Texas Rangers, scratching and clawing their way through the American League West race, were the busiest club, creating half a new infield and swapping starting pitchers. But the Montreal Expos and the Los Angeles Dodgers executed the biggest transaction, a seven-player deal that makes teammates of the Guerrero brothers, Wilton and Vladimir.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers, intent on winning the National League wild-card race, acquired Carlos Perez, the Expos' best pitcher, for their starting rotation and Mark Grudzielanek to shore up their weakened infield. The Expos gained Wilton Guerrero, a second baseman-outfielder, who at 23 is 16 months older than Vladimir, the Expos' hard-hitting right fielder, and three minor league prospects.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers, who also got a minor leaguer, will keep Grudzielanek in his regular shortstop role now because Jose Vizcaino is on the disabled list with a sprained ankle. However, Grudzielanek, who has a .276 batting average this season, could eventually wind up at second base. Perez, who has a 7-10 record, will go directly into the starting rotation, perhaps as soon as tonight against the Mets.</p>
        <p>The Rangers, who were one game behind Anaheim when they made their trades, acquired pitcher Todd Stottlemyre and shortstop Royce Clayton from St. Louis for pitcher Darren Oliver and third baseman Fernando Tatis. The Rangers also obtained third baseman Todd Zeile from Florida for two minor league players. They then released shortstop Kevin Elster.</p>
        <p>The Rangers had talked with Toronto about Juan Guzman for their rotation but preferred Stottlemyre, so the Blue Jays sent Guzman to Baltimore for two young players.</p>
        <p>In what was basically a swap of center fielders, the San Francisco Giants tried to improve themselves for the remainder of the N.L. wild-card race. The Giants, who recently added Joe Carter to their outfield, got Ellis Burks from Colorado for Darryl Hamilton. Burks, with 16 home runs to one for Hamilton, hits with more power, which is what the Giants were seeking.</p>
        <p>The trade with the Cardinals made sense to the Rangers because they were looking to improve their starting pitching and their defense at short. Oliver, a left-hander, had been a disappointment with a 6-7 record and 6.53 earned run average, and Elster had lost a lot of range at short.</p>
        <p>General Manager Doug Melvin, who two weeks ago acquired Esteban Loaiza from Pittsburgh for the starting rotation, was especially pleased to add Stottlemyre, a 33-year-old right-hander, who has a 9-9 record and 3.51 e.r.a.</p>
        <p>''If you look at Todd's track record and competitiveness, we feel he's going to help our ball club,'' Melvin said on a conference call. ''We feel when you go down to the last 45, 50 games, it's important to have someone with that kind of attitude. It's almost an arrogance, and it's good to have down the stretch.''</p>
        <p>Melvin, operating out of a hotel room in Toronto, where the Rangers had played the night before, said he had juggled the hotel phone and his cell phone, talking to two general managers at the same time. Dave Dombrowski, the Marlins' general manager, was on the cell phone and Walt Jocketty of St. Louis was on the hotel phone.</p>
        <p>''I had to make sure I could do both deals,'' Melvin said. ''I couldn't give up Tatis without getting Zeile.''</p>
        <p>Tatis, who at 23 is nine years younger than Zeile, is a better defensive player but does not hit as well as Zeile.</p>
        <p>With the Zeile trade and others, the Marlins' payroll, which they slashed from $53 million as World Series champions at the end of last season to $33 million at the start of this one, now is about $14 million.</p>
        <p>Guzman, who in recent starts has been a much better pitcher than his  6-12 season record would indicate, did not cost the Orioles significant major league talent.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
