<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 150-Mile Voyage by Canal</title>
    <meta content="11ERIE$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND EXCURSION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Erie Canal (NYS)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cayuga-Seneca Canal (NYS)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Lakes</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Canals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E1D91E3EF932A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="2400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 150-Mile Voyage by Canal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weekend Excursion article by Elisabeth Bumiller on voyage along the Erie and Cayuga-Seneca Canals in upstate New York; describes family trip, piloting rented boat six miles an hour along historic artery that connected Great Lakes to Hudson River and the Atlantic Ocean in 1825; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Lock 25, Lock 25, Lock 25. This is the vessel Onondaga requesting westbound passage. Over.''</p>
        <p>I felt silly, but what fun it was. Anyone traveling on the Erie Canal in upstate New York must call ahead by two-way radio to the laconic men and women operating the locks. Lock-tenders, as they're unofficially called, report that canal amateurs tend to get overexcited by the radio, as if reliving a childhood fantasy about navigating a battleship. ''It's new to them,'' said Joe Pidgeon, the lock-tender of the bucolic Lock 25 near Savannah, N.Y. ''You can tell when they pull up to the lock, because they keep chirping.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Lock 25, Lock 25, Lock 25. This is the vessel Onondaga requesting westbound passage. Over.''</p>
        <p>I felt silly, but what fun it was. Anyone traveling on the Erie Canal in upstate New York must call ahead by two-way radio to the laconic men and women operating the locks. Lock-tenders, as they're unofficially called, report that canal amateurs tend to get overexcited by the radio, as if reliving a childhood fantasy about navigating a battleship. ''It's new to them,'' said Joe Pidgeon, the lock-tender of the bucolic Lock 25 near Savannah, N.Y. ''You can tell when they pull up to the lock, because they keep chirping.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, my family and I piloted our own rented boat -- the 10-ton, 34-foot, very personable Onondaga -- for nearly 150 miles on the Erie and Cayuga-Seneca Canals. Over five days we went from just north of Syracuse to Seneca Falls to the edge of Rochester and back. (Different kinds of boats are available for weekends.)</p>
        <p>We traveled at six miles an hour, ate and slept on the Onondaga, and saw wilderness, sleepy courthouses and one wastewater treatment plant. Not every sight was exquisite. But the clock slowed down, and distances seemed much farther, just as they had in an earlier century. Although we've lived in India and Japan, and have trekked in Nepal, this turned out to be one of the most exotic things we have ever done.</p>
        <p>The magic of the canal is not so much its remote stretches of beauty, but the sensation it offers of traveling along an artery of history. To float down the Erie Canal is to have an intimate connection with the way it was built to be used. Many of the small towns we passed had remnants of the 19th-century mills that drove the industrial revolution and used the canal to ship their goods. We were right down in the water, where the power was.</p>
        <p>For years I have wanted to go to Seneca Falls, the site of the first women's rights convention. To arrive there for the first time by water -- to tie up our boat just below Wesleyan Chapel, where in 1848 Elizabeth Cady Stanton read the ''Declaration of Sentiments,'' demanding that women be given the vote -- made the journey  more personal and gave the town a lost-in-time feel (at least until a group of 20th-century teen-agers turned up to drink in the park right outside our boat).</p>
        <p>The 340-mile-long Erie, finished in 1825, was America's greatest canal. Before the railroads and highways, it connected the Great Lakes to the Atlantic Ocean as the crucial route for shipping the crops and products of the Western states to the East. It did nothing less than transform New York City into a commercial superpower. Philadelphia had been the nation's chief seaport, but two decades after the canal was finished New York was supreme.</p>
        <p>DeWitt Clinton, the New York City Mayor and then New York Governor who spent a political career promoting the canal's creation -- his dream was at first derided as ''Clinton's Ditch'' -- is today a visionary for what he imagined the canal would do for New York. ''The city will, in the course of time, become the granary of the world,'' he once wrote, ''the emporium of commerce, the seat of manufactures, the focus of great moneyed operations.''</p>
        <p>Our adventure began at 7 A.M. on Saturday. The four of us -- my husband, me and our two children, ages 8 and 4 -- drove the five hours from our home in Westchester County to Cold Springs Harbour Marina near the northern edge of Onondaga Lake, just above Syracuse. After loading up with groceries, we boarded our boat for an orientation by Carl Peterson, 17, of Mid-Lakes Navigation, the largest and oldest boat rental company on the Erie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson showed us around the barge, from the diesel engine to the head and shower, then told us it was time to cast off. I put the children in life jackets and undid the lines while my husband, Steve Weisman, took the tiller under Mr. Peterson's eye.</p>
        <p>Steve has had some experience with boats, but not with a 10-ton barge; the Onondaga, though easy to handle, took practice. Amazingly, Mid-Lakes rents to complete novices, but it heartily recommends that you take out $1 million in liability insurance. We did that, through Mid-Lakes, for $75.</p>
        <p>While Steve practiced his turns in the canal, I unpacked and looked over our new home. The boat was a marvel. A decade ago, Mid-Lakes began building what it calls Lockmasters, modeled on 19th-century European canal boats, for recreational use on the Erie. The Onondaga, one of the newest Lockmasters, had a steel hull, with a metal exterior painted a pleasing red, gold and forest green.</p>
        <p>Inside it looked like a floating Adirondack cabin with light-pine paneled walls and braided rugs.</p>
        <p>There was a double bed, a sofa that turned into bunk beds for the children at night and a small dining table with cushioned benches up in the bow. In the kitchen was a two-burner stove, an oven, a sink and a small refrigerator and freezer.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Wiles Wing manages the nine Mid-Lakes Lockmasters, and she is a woman after my own heart. The Onondaga was not only immaculate but obsessively well equipped, from a potato peeler to a portable propane grill to a corkscrew to salt and pepper shakers. There were even two bicycles strapped to the top deck.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson helped us through the first lock, No. 24, in Baldwinsville. It wasn't that easy; while Steve steered the boat through the gates and along the cement wall, I stood in the bow and grabbed for one of the lines hanging from the top of the lock. (The lines were covered with the most fantastic green slime I have ever seen. Ms. Wing thoughtfully supplied rubber gloves.)</p>
        <p>Steve, in the stern, grabbed for a line, too. We held the Onondaga parallel to the wall as the gates closed and millions of gallons of water filled the lock. In minutes we were lifted up 11 feet. Then the gates in front of us opened, and out we glided. The locks, 36 in all, are necessary because of the 568-foot rise in the canal as it stretches west from the Hudson River to Lake Erie.</p>
        <p>We tied up alongside a cemetery in Baldwinsville, said goodbye to Mr. Peterson, grilled some salmon for dinner, then went to bed and slapped miserably at mosquitoes all night. We bought a can of Raid the next day, and it saved us for the rest of the trip.</p>
        <p>We cast off on Sunday at 10 A.M., marveling at the blue herons, the red-tipped maple leaves and the labor of the 19th-century workers, many Irish immigrants who fought malarial mosquitoes as they dug the canal through the Montezuma Marsh, now the Montezuma National Wildlife Refuge. We were not in the original Erie Canal, but the enlarged Erie built after 1905, parallel to the first, which made use of existing rivers and lakes. Even at that time, railroads had cut heavily into the canal's traffic, and by the 1950's, the opening of the St. Lawrence Seaway and the New York State Thruway made it obsolete.</p>
        <p>Today the focus is on tourism. In a five-year plan, millions of dollars in Federal and state money is being spent to improve the canal's locks, moorings and bike paths. In 1992, the legislature created the Canal Recreationway Commission and renamed all four interconnected canals in the state -- the Erie, the Cayuga-Seneca, the Champlain and the Oswego -- as the New York State Canal System.</p>
        <p>We arrived in Seneca Falls by 6 P.M., and on Monday morning toured Wesleyan Chapel and Stanton's home, where a park ranger, Richard Pardee, told us that Stanton considered Seneca Falls an ''awful, mud-rutted town.'' I thought it was better than that, but no doubt things have improved. By 2 P.M. we were back on the water, headed west.</p>
        <p>The days fell into a nice pattern. We would cast off around 8 A.M., eat breakfast and lunch while under way, then anchor on a quiet stretch in the hot afternoons for a swim. The water was murky, a little creepy, but cold. I never saw anybody else swim in the canal, except for a teen-age boy who jumped in 60 feet from the top of a railroad bridge, screaming at the top of his lungs. (It was a stunt, and he survived.)</p>
        <p>My husband was happy because he discovered he could read while he drove the boat, although only half a page at a time; I navigated from the detailed charts supplied by Mid-Lakes. I also became an avid reader of the Onondaga's logbooks, which Mid-Lakes encourages boaters to keep. Most log entries were about restaurants and birds spotted along the way, but a few were soulful reflections from boaters who suddenly had found time to think.</p>
        <p>''Met lovely old man in Clyde,'' wrote a woman from Skaneateles, N.Y., last year. ''Must have been 85+ -- working his 5x10 store after 63 years!! He's lonesome &amp; wants to talk but can tell he doesn't want to be inappropriate. We buy some stuff and linger -- hard to pull away. Hope we see him again -- he's a really lovely human being. Working to stay alive, psychologically -- more power to him. . . . Testimony to the human spirit, like the canal.''</p>
        <p>We stayed Monday night in Lyons, and by Tuesday reached Fairport, an affluent suburb of Rochester. We looked over the Fairport Historical Museum, went on a walking tour of some 19th-century Greek revival and Italianate homes, had dinner at the Green Tavern and went to bed in a thunderstorm.</p>
        <p>Fairport has revitalized its canal front, and it's spiffy, but it also felt like an upscale mall. It would be awful if every canal waterfront looked the same way.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday morning we turned back toward home, reaching Lock  No. 25, and Mr. Pidgeon, its lock-tender, by dinner time. It was six more hours to Cold Springs Harbour Marina, so we decided to stay overnight. The lock was pretty, and surrounded by woods.</p>
        <p>''You can tie up anywhere you want,'' said Mr. Pidgeon, who was cutting the grass. He also plants flowers at the lock, and polishes to a burnished gleam the lock's brass and copper switches and contacts, circa 1915.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pidgeon, 38, who lives nearby, said he loved meeting boaters, and once offered his office for the night to a 70-ish man who was navigating the canal by canoe, in a driving rain. Mr. Pidgeon's 13-year-old son sometimes goes fishing near the lock for trout and bass.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pidgeon, a former electrician who brings an eloquence to his job,  said he considered himself less an employee of the state and more a ''guardian'' of a fine museum.</p>
        <p>''How's that saying go?'' he said. ''Once you find a job you love, you never work another day in your life.''</p>
        <p>Early the next morning, a beautiful mist rose up from the canal. We were sad to head home.</p>
        <p>''Lock 25, Lock 25, Lock 25. This is the vessel Onondaga requesting eastbound passage. Over.''</p>
        <p>Boats and Restaurants (No Mules)</p>
        <p>Here is information on taking an excursion on the Erie and Cayuga-Seneca Canals:</p>
        <p>Renting a Boat</p>
        <p>MID-LAKES NAVIGATION COMPANY has drive-your-own canal boats, from 33 to 41 feet, sleeping four to eight people. They are available into October, at $1,600 to $2,200 a week. Mid-Lakes will not rent boats for weekends, but offers two- and three-day canal cruises on the Emita II, a passenger boat with a captain and crew. Guests stay in hotels at night but are served meals on the boat. Fall 1998 cruises are full, but Mid-Lakes is booking for 1999. Rates start at $287 per person, including lodging, for a two-day cruise. Box 61, 11 Jordan Street, Skaneateles, N.Y.  13152, (800) 545-4318.</p>
        <p>CANAL PRINCESS CHARTERS, offers drive-your-own houseboats, sleeping a family of six or two couples. They are available this fall on the western Erie Canal, starting at $400 for two days. Box 421, Tonawanda, N.Y. 14151. Information: (716) 693-2752.</p>
        <p>ERIE CANAL CRUISE LINES offers drive-your-own canal boats, all 42 feet long, sleeping up to six. They are available on the Erie Canal starting June 1999 for three days (Saturday to Wednesday or Wednesday to Saturday), at $1,495, and one week, at $2,495. Boats are also available weekly this fall on the Intracoastal Waterway, which runs from New York to Sanford, Fla., with several stops between. A one-week rental is $1,795 and includes a captain. 714 Union Street, Suite 907, Manchester, N.H. 03104, (800) 962-1771.</p>
        <p>COLLAR CITY CHARTERS has drive-your-own canal boats, available weekly this fall on the Champlain Canal. May through October. Weekly rate, $2,000, which includes fuel, linens, locking fee and lessons. Troy Town Dock and Marina, 427 River Street, Troy, N.Y. 12180, (800) 830-5341.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>GREEN TAVERN, 1 Water Street, Fairport, N.Y., (716) 377-9888. Casual.</p>
        <p>LOCK 24, 33 Water Street, Baldwinsville, N.Y., (315) 635-2794. Casual, very friendly.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE TAVERN, 72 Geneva Street, Lyons, N.Y., (315) 946-6542. Old family restaurant since the turn of the century. Boaters recommend the Alaskan King crab.</p>
        <p>RICHARDSON'S CANAL HOUSE, 1474 Marsh Road, Pittsford, N.Y., (716) 248-5000. No jeans or children. Pre-fixe dinner: $35 per person.</p>
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>FAIRPORT HISTORICAL MUSEUM, 18 Perrin Street, Fairport, N.Y., (716) 223-3989. Open Sundays and Tuesdays, 2 to 4 P.M.,  and Thursdays, 7 to 9 P.M. Has Fairport walking tour map. Free admission.</p>
        <p>WOMEN'S RIGHTS NATIONAL HISTORICAL PARK, 136 Fall Street, Seneca Falls, N.Y., (315) 568-2991. Includes the visitor center, Wesleyan Chapel, Declaration Park and the Elizabeth Cady Stanton home. Open daily, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $3; free for those 16 and younger.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND EXCURSION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
