<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beware The Bald Barber</title>
    <meta content="11SLAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PUPPET FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Festival of Puppet Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Ginger (Puppet Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DF1F3EF932A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beware The Bald Barber</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews Slap Head: Demon Barber, performed at International Festival of Puppet Theater by Welsh group Green Ginger, using life-size puppets, masked actors and slides; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever hear of intro-hair disorder?</p>
        <p>You soon will if you make your way to P.S. 122. There, a most talented threesome from Wales called Green Ginger is injecting the International Festival of Puppet Theater with the merry and the macabre through Sept. 26 in its version of the Sweeney Todd story, ''Slap Head: Demon Barber.''</p>
        <p>With life-size puppets, masked actors and slides, to list only a few of its ingredients, this psychologically astute, caustically comic hourlong drama tells of poor Dibden Todd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever hear of intro-hair disorder?</p>
        <p>You soon will if you make your way to P.S. 122. There, a most talented threesome from Wales called Green Ginger is injecting the International Festival of Puppet Theater with the merry and the macabre through Sept. 26 in its version of the Sweeney Todd story, ''Slap Head: Demon Barber.''</p>
        <p>With life-size puppets, masked actors and slides, to list only a few of its ingredients, this psychologically astute, caustically comic hourlong drama tells of poor Dibden Todd.</p>
        <p>It is Todd, you see, who is afflicted with intro-hair disorder practically from the moment he is brought, buck-toothed and bespectacled, into the world by Dr. Tobias Sproat.</p>
        <p>Todd grows up bulb-headed, bald and unloved, which, as everybody knows, is the prelude to serial crime. From infancy, he plays second fiddle to the family dog, Truffles; there is no clown at his 14th birthday party because -- for reasons the audience will learn later -- last year's clown is still in the hospital. Todd is definitely weird and is only going to become weirder. He and hair, or the lack of it, are -- no pun intended -- inextricably tangled.</p>
        <p>From a medical standpoint, as Dr. Sproat explains to the accompaniment of a humorously inept slide show at the outset of ''Slap Head,''  Todd is suffering from intro-hair disorder, which causes his hair to grow inside his skull, eventually choking the central nervous system and leading (after various other afflictions) to madness.</p>
        <p>At that point, ''Slap Head'' introduces the nerdy Todd as a baby in a carriage and proceeds through his unhappy life: finishing second to Truffles as his mother's choice for the last candy; being slapped in the head by his schoolteacher for his stupidity, and having trouble learning the names of the handful of tools of barbering, a profession to which he is ineluctably and rather unhealthily drawn.</p>
        <p>But eventually he is apprenticed to Jeremiah Potter, and by the end of the evening, after an unfortunate accident with scissors that leaves him a hunted man, Todd has rented the barber's shop from the widowed Libby Potter and is working in the guise of a French tonsorial artist.</p>
        <p>Directed by Kevin Brooking, the gifted members of Green Ginger -- Dik Downey, Terry Lee, Chris Pirie -- people the stage with such vivid characters that in contrast to many similar shows, the focus becomes not the artful means by which they work, but the absorbing tale they tell.</p>
        <p>Todd's world includes not only his middle-class parents (who can barely remember him after he has moved in with the Potters) but also the rain-soaked local news vendor, the horsehair-wigged judge whom Todd terrifies, Dr. Sproat, the schoolteacher, Truffles, the birthday clown and the intrusive police constable, Inch of the Yard.</p>
        <p>Add to Green Ginger's sharp humor some atmospheric lighting and well-chosen sound effects (including appropriate opera), and scarcely an opportunity is missed in this splendidly acted, eerie, funny and touching show.</p>
        <p>PUPPET FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
