<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health: Medical Technology; Test Device Raises Hope of Keeping Organs Alive Longer for Transplant</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="154203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSPLANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA, UNIVERSITY OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D91339F935A25755C0A96E948260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health: Medical Technology; Test Device Raises Hope of Keeping Organs Alive Longer for Transplant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A team of California scientists has invented a device that may pave the way for vastly extending the time that human hearts, livers, kidneys and other transplantable organs can be kept alive once they are removed from human donors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A team of California scientists has invented a device that may pave the way for vastly extending the time that human hearts, livers, kidneys and other transplantable organs can be kept alive once they are removed from human donors.</p>
        <p>A team of California scientists has invented a device that may pave the way for vastly extending the time that human hearts, livers, kidneys and other transplantable organs can be kept alive once they are removed from human donors.</p>
        <p>The apparatus has been tested with the hearts of sheep, pigs and dogs, and the hearts have been kept slowly beating for up to 24 hours inside a portable container about the size of a television set. Although the hearts have not yet been transplanted into other animals to prove that they are viable, the researchers say they are confident that the hearts are kept alive and healthy by the device.</p>
        <p>The prototype, described at a news conference at the University of California at Irvine on Tuesday, was developed by Dr. Ralph E. Purdy, an associate professor of pharmacology at the university; James G. Martindale, a businessman from Laguna Beach; Dr. George L. Stupecky, a surgeon from Huntington Beach, and Ronny G. Tidwell, a staff research associate in surgery at the university's medical center.</p>
        <p>With current technology, human organs begin to deteriorate 4 to 36 hours after they are removed from the donors, often making it difficult or impossible to reach needy patients with organs that become available in distant cities. A Different Approach</p>
        <p>Dr. Purdy noted that donor hearts are currently flushed with an ice-cold solution that stops muscle activity and preserves tissues. Placed on ice for transport, heart tissues begin to deteriorate, suffering irreversible damage after about four hours.</p>
        <p>''We decided to look at the problem differently,'' Mr. Martindale said. ''Instead of asking how can we get the heart from point A to point B as quickly as possible, I asked, 'How can we maintain a functioning, beating heart outside the body?' ''</p>
        <p>Because the California researchers conducted their research independently and have not yet published scientific articles about the apparatus, this week's announcement surprised leading experts in transplant medicine and medical ethics.</p>
        <p>''If these fellows are correct and it is applicable to humans, it would be a real step forward,'' said Dr. Claude L'Enfant, director of the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute. ''The logistics of organ transplantation are a tremendous problem.''</p>
        <p>Arthur Caplan, director of the Center for Biomedical Ethics at the University of Minnesota, also remarked, ''The major obstacle to doing more transplants is the fragility of heart in terms of storage and transportation.'' He added that if the apparatus proved worthwhile, ''it would revolutionize heart transplantation.'' Patent Is Awaited</p>
        <p>Dr. Purdy said he was preparing scientific papers on the animal experiments and would submit them to journals as soon as a patent for the device was approved, possibly by the end of this year. The patent application has been submitted jointly with the University of California.</p>
        <p>The apparatus pumps a blood substitute through the heart while maintaining electrical, chemical and physical environments with the help of a computer. It could prove useful in many areas of medical research, Dr. Purdy said. It may be possible to test new drugs and medical procedures directly on human hearts, livers, kidneys and even brains that are kept viable in portable containers, he said.</p>
        <p>''We began with hearts because the need is there,'' Mr. Martindale said. ''But the system will work for other organs. We are raising the possibility of organ banking. Our primary objective is to not have any misses between donor and recipient.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Martindale, who has no formal scientific training, said he got the idea for the apparatus about three years ago.</p>
        <p>The apparatus is about the size of a 24-inch television set, Dr. Purdy said. An animal heart is placed into the container and is immediately perfused with a blood substitute also developed by the research team.</p>
        <p>''We sought to create an environment inside the device that mimics the environment inside the chest wall,'' Dr. Purdy said. Blood flow, temperature, pressure and oxygen balance are monitored, as are a variety of chemical factors including acidity, potassium and the concentration of blood sugars.</p>
        <p>Electrical activity between tissues, heart chambers and from where the heart branches out to other organs is independently monitored and waste products are automatically removed. Up to 20 special sensors monitor each function and feed the information into a computer that automatically corrects the system, Dr. Purdy said.</p>
        <p>The heart is cooled to about 45 or 50 degrees Fahrenheit, he said, which slows the heart rate to about 10 beats a minute. At this rate the heart preserves energy stores but does not suffer from the loss of oxygen, he said. Extending Viability of Organs</p>
        <p>''As we made corrections in the system, we learned more about the heart,'' Dr. Purdy said. ''These are preliminary experiments and we have much more to learn. But I am confident that we can extend the viability of human hearts out to 72 hours. We may be able to extend the viability of livers and kidneys out to a week.''</p>
        <p>Citing ethical concerns, the researchers said they had decided voluntarily to hold off further animal experiments and to refrain from starting experiments with human hearts until Federal guidelines are established. There are currently no Federal rules for using viable human organs in research or organ transplantation, Dr. Purdy noted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martindale said he had two ''nightmares'' concerning possible abuses of the apparatus. One is that a black market for hearts, livers or other organs might evolve because organs can be preserved longer and shipped across international borders.</p>
        <p>A second potential problem involves issues of ownership. If a family donates a viable heart for transplant, Mr. Martindale said, but the heart ends up beating in a laboratory somewhere for drug testing, the family would have a right to be upset. But, he said, if the heart advances drug research, does the family of the deceased have a right to share in the profits?</p>
        <p>''It is important that Congress move quickly and that the larger community gets involved,'' Dr. Purdy agreed. ''It is one thing to generate the technology, and quite another to determine how it is used.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
