<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coins</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="53" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Pastimes Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="482939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUMISMATICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LUNDY (GB)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, JED</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARMAN, MARTIN (?-1954)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC103AF934A15753C1A967958260" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jed Stevenson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, JED</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes a king's got to do what a king's got to do. So thought Martin Coles Harman, "king" of Lundy Island and lord of its domain, all one and a half square miles of it.</p>
        <p>Lundy is mostly rock, 3 miles long and 12 miles off the northern coast of Devonshire, England. Nominally, it lies within Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes a king's got to do what a king's got to do. So thought Martin Coles Harman, "king" of Lundy Island and lord of its domain, all one and a half square miles of it.</p>
        <p>Lundy is mostly rock, 3 miles long and 12 miles off the northern coast of Devonshire, England. Nominally, it lies within Britain.</p>
        <p>For years, Lundy supported a tiny population that did some farming, collected puffin feathers and relied mainly on salvaging the hundreds of ships that foundered in its shoals. Modern navigational systems reduced that livelihood.</p>
        <p>The first owner of Lundy was the Rev. William Hudson Heaven, who bought it in 1835.</p>
        <p>Under his family's ownership, a church was built, a telegraph cable to the mainland was added, and two lighthouses were erected.</p>
        <p>Naturally, Lundy became known as the kingdom of Heaven, although it was not quite large enough for even one Elysian field.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heaven's family sold it in 1916 to Augustus Christie, who in turn sold it to Martin Harman in 1925.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman had dropped out of school at age 16 and apprenticed himself to the Lazard Freres banking house in London.</p>
        <p>He rose quickly, and after he saw Lundy Island at the age of 18, he vowed to buy it one day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman seems to have been a benevolent ruler of his few subjects. He landscaped the island, bringing in shrubs, trees, birds and animals, and he apparently loved walking though his realm, which became more a nature preserve than a kingdom.</p>
        <p>All was well in the former kingdom of Heaven.</p>
        <p>In 1929, Mr. Harman decided that Lundy needed its own coins, so he ordered 100,000 coins from a private mint in Birmingham. The coins were in two denominations, the puffin and the half-puffin. Mr. Harman's bust was on the obverse, and on the reverse was the puffin, the sea bird whose rookeries dotted the island.</p>
        <p>Issuing coinage has always been the right of the sovereign. Mr. Harman felt that he was, in fact, sovereign of Lundy. But King George VI believed that if the sun never set on the British Empire, surely Lundy must fall within Britain's domain. The King's officers took Mr. Harman to court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman replied that while Lundy was surely "a little kingdom within the British Empire," it was not a part of England itself. Mr. Harman believed Lundy should be treated like any other regal state that allied itself with Britain, like, for instance, India.</p>
        <p>He noted that Lundy enjoyed no services, no free education, no pensions, unemployment insurance or anything else from England. It paid no income taxes, tithes or land taxes to England, "which we call the adjacent island," he said. He also noted that everyone on the island worked for him, except for two lighthouse keepers, but that the lights were on offshore rocks and the keepers' passage on the island was at his whim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman may have prejudiced his case by insisting that he was the legal sovereign of Lundy and had all sovereign rights, not just that of coinage. He lost. He paid the court costs and a $:5 fine. He appealed and lost again. The puffin was demonetized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harman was later convicted of fraud and served a prison term for misappropriating funds from a holding company that owned several Japanese companies. He died in 1954 and forgave all his debtors. He left an estate of $:4,719. In 1969 the island was bought by a British millionaire and donated to the public.</p>
        <p>Today, the Lundy puffins are numismatic curiosities that appear at auction from time to time, reminding all that in the kingdom of Heaven -- no matter how small -- any man could be king.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
