<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TAIWAN SETS PLAN TO REBUILD NATION</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIPLOMATIC RECOGNITION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TAIWAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WUDUNN, SHERYL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DD1F30F934A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TAIWAN SETS PLAN TO REBUILD NATION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL WuDUNN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WUDUNN, SHERYL</byline>
      <dateline>TAIPEI, Taiwan</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, Taiwan wants to modernize its concrete skylines and cracking sewers, but unlike them, Taiwan not only has the dreams but also the money -- $72 billion in official foreign exchange reserves, more than any other country.</p>
        <p>And so it has embarked on a bold program to lift itself into the upper ranks of developed nations, planning to spend more than $300 billion for new railroads and highways, a subway system, power plants, refineries, schools, housing, medical facilities, water treatment plants and sewage systems. The six- year construction program -- which will cost more than three times as much as rebuilding Kuwait -- has prompted a contest among American and other foreign contractors for some of the biggest plums of the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, Taiwan wants to modernize its concrete skylines and cracking sewers, but unlike them, Taiwan not only has the dreams but also the money -- $72 billion in official foreign exchange reserves, more than any other country.</p>
        <p>And so it has embarked on a bold program to lift itself into the upper ranks of developed nations, planning to spend more than $300 billion for new railroads and highways, a subway system, power plants, refineries, schools, housing, medical facilities, water treatment plants and sewage systems. The six- year construction program -- which will cost more than three times as much as rebuilding Kuwait -- has prompted a contest among American and other foreign contractors for some of the biggest plums of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The 779 projects involved in the plan were announced by Prime Minister Hau Pei-tsun this summer. The magnitude of the proposals stunned many business people. 'A Gigantic Project'</p>
        <p>"This is a gigantic project and will be Premier Hau's legacy," said James F. O'Hearn, president of the American Chamber of Commerce in Taipei. "There aren't too many six-year plans around the world where countries have the money, capability, intent and the wherewithal to make them happen."</p>
        <p>American executives estimate that Taiwan will spend $50 billion to $70 billion on foreign purchases over the next six years. Japanese and European companies are expected to be among the major bidders, but American companies have historically won a large number of contracts there. Although the United States has no diplomatic relations with Taiwan, in 1990 American companies received 34 percent of Taiwan's major contracts, worth about $650 million, many of them part of the six-year plan.</p>
        <p>American companies are likely to be strong bidders to provide engineering expertise and equipment for incineration, pollution control, oil refining, transportation and communications.</p>
        <p>The General Electric Company and the Westinghouse Electric Corporation have built all three of Taiwan's nuclear power plants and are strong contenders to build the fourth, which is part of the plan. Companies like Combustion Engineering Inc., Ebasco Services Inc. and Sargent &amp; Lundy that have supplied equipment for the other plants are also likely to vie for contracts. Rapid Transit Contracts</p>
        <p>American companies have also won leading roles in Taipei's effort to build the initial phase of its first rapid- transit system. The Union Railcar Partnership, of Yonkers, won a $170 million contract for the rail cars; the General Railway Signal Company, of Rochester, received a $100 million contract for signaling equipment, and a consortium that included Bechtel Group Inc. won a large share of $200 million worth of engineering consulting business. "We have tremendous interest in it," said a representative of an American company bidding on contracts. "There are big, big dollars."</p>
        <p>But American companies will be locked out of the main contract for a high-speed railway system, partly because the United States does not have such a system. Instead, companies from Japan, France and Germany will compete.</p>
        <p>Purchases of American equipment and technology should help reduce the United States' trade deficit with Taiwan, which declined only slightly in 1990, to $11.9 billion -- the second highest deficit, after Japan. Taiwan, which had a total trade volume last year of $122 billion, is clearly mindful of the impact that contracts can have on its trade balances with other nations. Last year, Taiwan had an overall surplus of $12.5 billion. Because Taiwan has a trade deficit with Japan, it has opened bidding in some cases only to American and European companies. Wealth, but Little Gloss</p>
        <p>Despite its astounding economic development of the last few decades and its enormous wealth today, Taiwan's appearance is dull. Mercedes- Benz and Porsche automobiles fill the streets of Taipei, but scarcely move during rush hour because of the poorly designed traffic system.</p>
        <p>The reasons for such disparities have much to do with Taiwan's history. The Nationalist Chinese regime that fled here in 1949, after its defeat on the mainland, saw the island as a base and temporary refuge, and always intended to return to the mainland. Only in the last few years, as the older generation has died off, have Government leaders seemed to reconcile themselves to the notion that Taiwan is their home, and well worth modernizing.</p>
        <p>Taipei is planning to finance most of the projects through its normal annual revenue sources, and economic planning officials say the Government can pay all but one-eighth, or about $38 billion, of the costs without dipping significantly into its foreign exchange reserves. To cover the shortfall, Taiwan says it will probably issue bonds and encourage the private sector to invest in some projects. Diplomacy May Benefit</p>
        <p>The Government's goals in announcing such a huge program are in part diplomatic. Officials are trying to entice government delegations from countries, including the United States, that no longer have diplomatic relations with Taiwan.</p>
        <p>In August, the American Chamber of Commerce in Taipei sent a letter to President Bush calling on him to lift a ban on visits by Cabinet-level officials to Taiwan. The chamber fears that visits by European delegations will encourage the Government to award many contracts to European, rather than American, companies.</p>
        <p>Taiwan's leaders respond coyly to suggestions that they are using the plan to reduce their diplomatic isolation.</p>
        <p>"If people have the kind of assumption we are using this economic strength to upgrade our political relations with other countries, this is wrong," John H. Chang, a vice foreign minister, said in an interview. "The only purpose and goal of the six-year plan is to upgrade the quality of life on this island. If at the same time we can help further develop relations with other countries, why not?"  Skeptics See a '12-Year Plan'</p>
        <p>Critics of Taiwan's plans point out that past large-scale projects have encountered delays. Now the Government will face squabbles over eminent domain as it tries to purchase land from people who may not want to sell at Government prices. It will be a tall order merely to assemble the needed labor and materials in six years.</p>
        <p>Some business executives are skeptical that the projects will be completed on schedule and mockingly refer to the program as the "12-year plan." It has also been criticized for its scale and for the packaging of old, continuing projects with new ones to attract greater attention from the foreign business community.</p>
        <p>About 60 percent of the projects are already in planning or construction, some for several years.  Growing Wealth</p>
        <p>For some time, Taiwan has successfully relied on labor-intensive industries to create wealth. After years of rapid economic growth, per capita income is about $8,000. While that leaves Taiwan well behind the United States' figure of $20,900, South Korea is at only $4,400 and China is at $350, according to the World Bank. Now, Taiwan authorities hope the economy will grow by 7 percent a year so that per capita income will reach $14,000 by 1996.</p>
        <p>The spending plan is the clearest sign of Taiwan's recognition that it must upgrade its technology and move into more sophisticated industries if it wants to increase its wealth. Thus, the plan also includes money to improve manufacturing processes, enhance research and development in many industries, including agriculture and electronics, and expand Taiwan's airports and airplane fleet.</p>
        <p>Besides spurring economic growth in the next decade, the plan is a means of gaining foreign expertise, technology and equipment to build a base for growth in the next generation. "It is something desperately needed," said Liang Chang, president of the Shearson-Global Financial Services Company. "This is a chance to show how to build a country."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
