<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making a Closet Bigger and Better</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE133CF934A15753C1A967958260" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making a Closet Bigger and Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMODELING a closet to provide additional space or better organization usually calls for replacing the standard single shelf and clothes pole with compartments and multiple poles of varying lengths and heights.</p>
        <p>To make a closet more convenient overall, it should have adequate lighting, an appropriate door and maybe even cedar paneling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMODELING a closet to provide additional space or better organization usually calls for replacing the standard single shelf and clothes pole with compartments and multiple poles of varying lengths and heights.</p>
        <p>To make a closet more convenient overall, it should have adequate lighting, an appropriate door and maybe even cedar paneling.</p>
        <p>Before adding a closet light, check with the building inspector to learn whether amateurs can perform electrical work and what regulations apply.</p>
        <p>Generally, codes permit surface-mounted and recessed fixtures for incandescent and fluorescent lighting, but fixtures for incandescents have to enclose the bulb or bulbs completely. Hanging fixtures and those with pull chains or other overhead switches are not allowed.</p>
        <p>Most codes also specify lighting locations. They are relative to the storage area, which is usually defined as extending 24 inches out from the back wall when measured from the floor to the highest clothes pole or 6 feet, whichever is higher.</p>
        <p>Above that, the storage area extends 12 inches from the back wall, unless the shelves there are wider than that. The full width of the space above the shelves is considered storage area.</p>
        <p>Surface-mounted incandescent and fluorescent fixtures can be installed on the wall above a door, provided that with incandescent fixtures there is a distance of at least 12 inches between the bulb and the storage area, and with fluorescents, which produce less heat, the distance is at least six inches.</p>
        <p>Fully recessed and enclosed incandescent and fluorescent fixtures can be installed on the wall or ceiling, as long as there are at least six inches between the fixture's surface and the storage area.</p>
        <p>By using surface wiring and a code-approved surface-mounted fixture, you can install a light without having to open finished construction. Otherwise, when you have chosen a light and mounting location, cut into the wall or ceiling at that spot and install an outlet box to which the fixture can be fastened.</p>
        <p>Mount the box on a strip of 1 x 3 lumber or on an adjustable metal bar installed between a pair of wall studs or ceiling joists. Then open another hole for a switch box for the light. A convenient spot is about 48 inches from the floor on the inside or outside of one of the closet walls, preferably close to the doorway.</p>
        <p>Use electrician's fish tape to route electric cable -- nonmetalic-sheathed 14-gauge two-conductor is acceptable -- between the outlet box and the switch-box opening. You will have to open the wall further to drill holes for the cable to pass through wall studs separating the two locations. Consider making these openings inside the closet.</p>
        <p>Another strategy is to open a narrow horizontal channel in the wall and notch the studs with a chisel to accept the cable. Before patching the wall, cover the notches with metal plates. In both cases, it may be possible to route some of the cable behind doorway molding.</p>
        <p>Choose a nearby wall receptacle or other outlet as a power source and shut off the current supplying it. Next, fish electric cable from the outlet to the switch-box opening.</p>
        <p>Install the switch box and then the fixture, bulbs and switch, but check the wiring connections before restoring the power.</p>
        <p>If you plan to modify the present closet door, wiring a light will probably be easier if you combine the two projects. Bifold and accordion doors save space while providing maximum accessibilty. For covering a wide opening, sliding doors, also called bypass doors, are another possiblity. Their disadvantage is that only half the closet space is accessible when the door is open.</p>
        <p>Where there is limited room for a swinging door, but you want to preserve a closet's wide front wall and standard-width doorway, consider a pocket door.</p>
        <p>All the doors mentioned are available as kits that include mounting hardware and instructions. Bifold, accordion and sliding doors are installed by attaching a metal track across the top of the doorway. Hardware may also have to be installed against one side and on the floor.</p>
        <p>Installing a pocket door usually requires demolishing part of the front wall to alter the framing and install the track and pocket hardware. The wall then has to be rebuilt to enclose the door when it is retracted.</p>
        <p>Paneling the inside of a closet with aromatic red cedar will protect the closet's contents from moths. Cedar closet lining comes either in tongue-and-groove strips of solid lumber that is usually about three-eighths of an inch thick, 4 inches wide and 3 1/2 feet long or in 4 x 8-foot sheets moade from cedar chips.</p>
        <p>Sheets typically are a quarter-inch thick. Although less attractive than strips, they provide the same degree of protection, cost less and are easier to install.</p>
        <p>For maximum moth protection, line both the closet's ceiling and walls. If the surfaces are smooth and plumb, lining can be attached directly with panel nails, construction adhesive or both. To line uneven surfaces, attach a grid of wood or plywood strips called furring and fasten the lining to them.</p>
        <p>With strips or sheets, start by covering the ceiling and then move to the walls. If adhesive is used, strips can be attached parallel or perpendicular to joists and studs. When nails are used, strips have be oriented perpendicular to the framing or furring.</p>
        <p>Do not apply sealer or other finish to the lining. To revive the aroma of lining, sand the surface lightly with fine-grit sandpaper.  HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
