<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2nd Officer Describes Beating of Man Who Died in Custody</title>
    <meta content="21ORAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/21/nyregion/21ORAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Carpinteri, Paul (Police Officer)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Orange (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tortorella, Anthony (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Brian S (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faison, Earl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carnegie, Joyce (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Thomas (Former Police Lieutenant)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garth, Andrew (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Payton, Tyrone (Police Officer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0D6163AF932A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2nd Officer Describes Beating of Man Who Died in Custody</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Nov. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police Officer Anthony Tortorella testifies in Federal District Court that he saw Officer Brian Smith spray pepper gas directly into face Earl Faison while Faison was handcuffed and lying on floor; testimony comes in trial of five members of Orange (NJ) Police Department charged with federal civil rights violations in connection Faison's death in police custody; Faison had been picked up during investigation of 1999 shooting death of Officer Joyce Carnegie (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Orange police officer, echoing his partner's testimony a week ago, said in Federal District Court today that he saw another officer spray pepper gas directly into the face of a handcuffed man who was lying on the floor of police headquarters and who later died in police custody.</p>
        <p>The officer, Anthony Tortorella, who said the man was not resisting when he was sprayed, testified in the third week of the trial of five members of the Orange Police Department charged with federal civil rights violations in connection with the beating and abuse of Earl Faison, a 27-year-old East Orange man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Orange police officer, echoing his partner's testimony a week ago, said in Federal District Court today that he saw another officer spray pepper gas directly into the face of a handcuffed man who was lying on the floor of police headquarters and who later died in police custody.</p>
        <p>The officer, Anthony Tortorella, who said the man was not resisting when he was sprayed, testified in the third week of the trial of five members of the Orange Police Department charged with federal civil rights violations in connection with the beating and abuse of Earl Faison, a 27-year-old East Orange man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Faison was picked up during the investigation of the April 8, 1999, shooting death of Officer Joyce Carnegie. Police now say Mr. Faison played no role in the shooting.</p>
        <p>Officer Tortorella and his partner, Officer Keith Jackson, who testified last week that he had seen Mr. Faison sprayed, were the second support team of officers to arrive on the scene of Mr. Faison's arrest. Both were also present when Mr. Faison was brought into the station minutes later.</p>
        <p>Officer Tortorella, a 10-year veteran of the department, said he saw Officer Brian Smith, one of the defendants, spray the gas into Mr. Faison's face as he lay handcuffed on the floor of a stairwell. ''He leaned over his face with a can of Mace and squirted it in the face area,'' he said, adding later that it was actually pepper spray.</p>
        <p>Other officers, including Officer Smith's brother Lt. Thomas Smith, who is also a defendant, stood by watching, he said. Asked by an assistant United States attorney, Luis Valentin, whether Mr. Faison appeared to be struggling or resisting before he was sprayed, Officer Tortorella said, ''No.'' He added that neither he nor any of the others in the stairwell had tried to help Mr. Faison.</p>
        <p>His testimony echoed most of what Officer Jackson has said about events in the stairwell. Like Officer Jackson, Officer Tortorella said he had lied to investigators at first in an effort to protect other officers. He decided to tell the truth after Officer Jackson confided that he could no longer lie, he said.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to get involved because once I started talking I had to tell the truth against other cops,'' he said, speaking in a clipped and unemotional voice. ''But my brother is a cop, my father is a retired cop from Orange, my nephew is a cop, and I just wanted to tell the truth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Faison, who suffered from asthma, was the first of three men to be wrongly arrested in the investigation of the slaying of Officer Carnegie. All three were later cleared, and one of them has said in a civil suit that he was beaten by arresting officers. Eventually, a fourth man, Condell Woodson, 27, pleaded guilty in the case and was sentenced to life in prison.</p>
        <p>The ripple effects of the mistake-riddled case attracted the attention of federal authorities and the state attorney general's office. Eventually it played a role in the forced resignation of the Essex County prosecutor, Patricia Hurt, who had led the investigation into Officer Carnegie's death and had presided over the arrests of the three innocent men.</p>
        <p>Officer Tortorella's testimony did not corroborate his partner's earlier account of seeing Lieutenant Smith and another defendant, Officer Andrew Garth, punching Mr. Faison as they threw him like a ''rag doll'' into the back of a patrol car.</p>
        <p>Officer Jackson testified last week that he had grabbed the lieutenant by the belt and had pulled him off the suspect so forcefully that they had both fallen to the ground. Officer Tortorella said he had seen his partner pulling Lieutenant Smith by the belt and falling with him to the curb.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Smith's lawyer, Michael Chertoff, seemed to make some headway in an attempt to find inconsistencies in the two officers' accounts, as well as conflicts with Officer Tortorella's interviews and grand jury testimony. But the importance of the differences was unclear.</p>
        <p>In one case, Mr. Chertoff showed that Officer Tortorella had differed with his partner about what they were wearing that night and whether the flashing patrol car lights had hampered their view of some events.</p>
        <p>He also emphasized that in earlier statements, Officer Tortorella had described differently the timing of when he had looked toward the car where Lieutenant Smith and the suspect were.</p>
        <p>Earlier, in the cross-examination of another prosecution witness, John Bennett, 34, a tow truck driver who happened upon Mr. Faison being arrested, defense lawyers tried unsuccessfully to dislodge him from his statement that two other officers had punched Mr. Faison as he lay on the ground before Officers Tortorella and Jackson arrived. Those officers, Tyrone Payton, 34, and Paul Carpinteri, 36, are also defendants.</p>
        <p>In the face of defense efforts to suggest that prosecutors had coached Mr. Bennett in how to describe events, Mr. Valentin highlighted his witness's consistent use of the same words to describe events.</p>
        <p>The cross-examination of Officer Tortorella is scheduled to continue before Judge John C. Lifland on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
