<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Help A Phone Call Away</title>
    <meta content="08WE911" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1670793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7D81730F93BA35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Help A Phone Call Away</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARIN RUBENSTEIN</byline>
      <dateline>HAWTHORNE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WOMAN called to report an accident. In the background were sounds of weeping and gagging. She had stopped to help a young woman whose car had crashed into a telephone pole. The victim was moaning that she was sick to her stomach. The caller reported that the airbag had activated but the victim seemed uninjured.</p>
        <p>''She's just shooken up,'' the good Samaritan said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WOMAN called to report an accident. In the background were sounds of weeping and gagging. She had stopped to help a young woman whose car had crashed into a telephone pole. The victim was moaning that she was sick to her stomach. The caller reported that the airbag had activated but the victim seemed uninjured.</p>
        <p>''She's just shooken up,'' the good Samaritan said.</p>
        <p>Right then a man called to report an incident, insisting that he was northbound on I-287, a roadway that goes east-west, which made it difficult to pinpoint where he was. The operator was about to locate him on her computer, using a map and global positioning technology to find his cellphone, with a tiny blue icon at the relevant site. But she found out the matter had already been called in, so she ended the call, with thanks.</p>
        <p>A woman was on the line from Mount Vernon, sobbing. She stammered out that ''three guys just jumped me'' -- that they had stolen something from her shop and that she needed an ambulance.</p>
        <p>It was a messy, snowy night in early spring, ''a night of P.D.A.A.'s all over the place,'' in the words of Nile Clarke, an operator at the high-tech cellphone 911 center here, who was using a shorthand for the jargon phrase ''Property Damage Auto Accidents.'' Cars were spinning, they were hitting phone poles, they were sliding off the road from the Taconic Parkway to the Thruway to I-84.</p>
        <p>As a trigger of accidents and incidents, a moderate to heavy storm is outranked only by traffic-churning holidays like Memorial Day, the imminent one at the moment. And because cellphones travel with people wherever they go, the Hawthorne center gets 60-percent-plus of Westchester's distress calls. In 3 8-hour shifts a day, in groups of 3 or so, the center's 22 operators field at least 40,000 calls a month -- which works out to about 1,300 calls a day, or more than 400 calls per shift.</p>
        <p>Given that volume, two facts about Westchester's 911 emergency service are surprising: It did not exist in any form at all until 1991; and until last August, its cellphone-specific service consisted of a temporary trailer, two civilian employees and a phone with caller ID.</p>
        <p>One of those employees is William E. Mackey, who says there is no comparison between the old days and life at the new Hudson Valley Transportation Management Center. Back then, he remembered, ''we were averaging 36,000 calls a month, and it was almost impossible for one person to keep up.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, trying to help a caller resuscitate a cardiac patient while also handling car accidents, Mr. Mackey said, ''I had three phones in my ears.''</p>
        <p>''We had no idea where people were calling from,'' he said. ''We had to do detective work to find out where they were.''</p>
        <p>Drivers wouldn't know if they were on Route 9W, which is west of the Hudson, or Route 9, on the east side. ''They'd say, 'I can see a bridge and I can see water.'''</p>
        <p>The county was ''obviously behind the times,'' said Stephen Seitz, a spokesman for the National Emergency Number Association in Arlington, Va., explaining that in many regions of the country, 911 has been in use since the late 1970's or early 1980's.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Seitz seemed less than concerned, that might be because lost time has been made up. August was the turning point; since then, the ultra-high-tech center here has been offering what is called Phase Two service, meaning that the call registers a phone number and a location.</p>
        <p>Fewer than half of communities nationwide have this enhanced technology. (A Phase Zero call offers no information at all; a Phase One call registers a phone number and a general location, triangulated from several cell towers.)</p>
        <p>THE thousands of cellular calls to 911 in Hawthorne contain bits and pieces of tragedies, stories of mishaps, accidents, and troubles, many of them never fully resolved -- tales without conclusions.</p>
        <p>And the only early witnesses to the mayhem are invisible, anonymous. Most are young women -- 15 of 22 in the group -- and many are minorities. There are also several middle-age men, some of them former police officers. Nearly all are earnest and empathic about their work. They don't joke about 911.</p>
        <p>The first thing they want to know is where you are -- not what happened or how upset you are or whose fault it was, which is mostly what greets their ears at the outset. To help find you, they can look at aerial flyover photographer views of any location in Westchester; they can also consult detailed maps of your location, which will reveal the tiny blue cellphone that stands for you.</p>
        <p>Only after that does anyone want to know the problem in question. Were you in a car accident, or was it a fire? Is someone drowning, or having a heart attack?</p>
        <p>Their challenge is to assess your call and route it to the correct agency -- a significant test when a voice is sobbing into the headphone and they have about a hundred public-safety agencies to choose from. These include 48 police departments, several emergency medical services, some fire departments, a few towing companies, the Connecticut State Police, even the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>The 911 worker may resemble the old-fashioned switchboard operator, but now the console, phone cords and sockets have been replaced with three computer screens, three computer mice, two keyboards, a telephone and a police radio.</p>
        <p>On the upper left-hand corner of the 911 operator's main screen is a drawing of a face silhouetted in red. When a 911 call comes in, the face starts to blink, as an alarm begins to blare. To answer and make them stop, the operator can use the mouse to click on the blinking face, or just touch the screen.</p>
        <p>Down its right side are small boxes that represent incoming cellular providers: Cingular, Nextel, Sprint, and Verizon. (Since the merger of AT&amp;T and Cingular, incoming lines are now labeled Cingular only.)</p>
        <p>The operators need a yogi-like composure and patience, a pleasant speaking voice, the ability to pick words out of static and garble, and a strong back.</p>
        <p>Anissa Smith, 28, of Wappingers Falls has most of these attributes, especially the imperturbability. She has been a 911 operator since the center opened last summer; not counting the veteran Mr. Mackey, she's already an old-timer.</p>
        <p>''I try to keep an even tone,'' she said, ''even when I don't know what to expect.'' If people hear a steady voice, she added, they tend to calm down.</p>
        <p>When training new employees, Ms. Smith said, ''I tell them to listen carefully and try not to get excited.'' Otherwise, they, too, will end up in a panic.</p>
        <p>A large redhead who would probably have maintained her composure on the Titanic, Ms. Smith does own to having had the occasional nightmare about her work. A vivid one concerned an armed robbery; she had it the night after taking a call from a store owner who was being held at gunpoint.</p>
        <p>The biggest help to her in her job, she says: her $800 ergonomic office chair.</p>
        <p>''We're sitting for long periods of time and we need to be comfortable and to have mobility,'' she said. In this chair, she can scoot effortlessly from screen to screen and back again, over and over.</p>
        <p>Called the Concorde 24 Hour, the chair is modeled after the seats in the defunct supersonic airline of the same name. Every emergency operator has one.</p>
        <p>As for the calls, sometimes they are full of static, or the person doesn't make much sense. But she has learned to hear what is difficult to hear.</p>
        <p>''At first it's hard to understand,'' she said, ''but one day it all clicks, then you understand everything.''</p>
        <p>What she hates is when she gets a call and can't hear anyone, just background noise of the bad sort like crying and yelling, and then the call is disconnected. She never knows what really happened, or whether she could have helped.</p>
        <p>There are, of course, the annoyances, most frequent among them calls from babies. Parents often give young children old cellphones to play with, not realizing that if the child hits a ''1'' or a ''9,'' the telephone may automatically dial 911. The operator is left listening to everything going on in the car, or the kitchen, or the backyard.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I say, 'Is your mom there?''' Ms. Smith said. But it rarely works.</p>
        <p>She is tolerant of silly calls -- from people who dial 911 when they need driving directions, or when their power fails at home, or when they lock their keys in the car. Once, during a snowstorm several months ago, a New Rochelle woman called to exclaim, ''I've just seen a fox in my backyard!''</p>
        <p>She even tolerates what are known in the industry as ''butt calls,'' generated unwittingly by people who tuck their cellphones into their back pockets and sit down on them. Depending on their angle of repose, the phone may auto-dial 911.</p>
        <p>''You end up hearing someone's conversation for a very long time,'' Mr. Seitz said.</p>
        <p>The only calls that really get to her are the pranks, most of which are made by children. They call to belch into the phone, or to report that ''When I turn on my stove, it's, like, blowing up.''</p>
        <p>''It's best not to entertain them,'' Ms. Smith said, ''because they'll keep calling back.'' But they can't be ignored because there may really be something wrong and ''we have to treat every call like it's a real call.''</p>
        <p>Most children probably don't realize that their phone numbers and locations show up on the operator's screen. Sometimes, when Ms. Smith has had enough, she said, she puts ''the fear of God in them,'' threatening to dispatch a state trooper to alert their parents.</p>
        <p>At that, even hardened pranksters tend to confess.</p>
        <p>The worst call that Ms. Clarke ever got was a ''nerve-racking prank.'' Working the night shift, Ms. Clarke, 24, heard a woman screaming for help, yelling that a man was hitting her. It turned out she was a teenager having a little fun at 911's expense.</p>
        <p>''Someone could have been killing her, that's what goes through your mind,'' said Ms. Clarke, who had long sparkly fingernails, dangly heart-shaped red earrings and a fake red flower in her hair. ''It was so scary, it was crazy.''</p>
        <p>She did not express embarrassment about having been fooled by a teenager. Her main concern at the time: ''I'm just glad nobody was hurt.''</p>
        <p>SHE says repetition is the secret to her success at soothing hysterical callers. ''We say the same things twice, like 'Calm down, try to relax, and I'm trying to help you.'''</p>
        <p>The call she feels proudest of is the one made one day by a little girl, who said in a whisper that her brother and some friends were doing drugs in the house and that she was scared. Ms. Clarke stayed on the phone with her a long time, until the police arrived at the house.</p>
        <p>Proud of her work in emergency services, Ms. Clarke has her own telephone headset, labeled ''NILE.'' She keeps it in a special case and takes it home with her after every shift. She commutes from Poughkeepsie, where she attends Dutchess Community College and is a communications major with her own monthly public-access show on Channel 23. She needs to take two more classes, she said, to earn her associate degree.</p>
        <p>''You definitely want to be the 911 call that helped,'' she said, ''not the one that messed up.''</p>
        <p>ANTHONY CORONA, who worked as a police officer in the South Bronx for 20 years, is a heavyset man with thinning hair who sees similarities between his work here and his career on the beat. In some ways, though, this job is more frustrating.</p>
        <p>''As a cop, you're finishing the job the dispatcher gives you, so there's a conclusion,'' he said. "These days, sometimes, it's frustrating not knowing how it turns out.''</p>
        <p>On occasion, Mr. Corona, 42, likes to regale his fellow operators with stories about the bad old days, like the time that two new district attorneys were riding along with him. They entered an apartment building that had become a heroin dealers' hangout, cornering an armed suspect in a closet. The man's accomplice had tried to rappel out the window using antenna wire. His death in a five-story fall had prompted the neighbors to call 911, Mr. Corona said. They reported that police officers had pushed the fleeing man out the window.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, he is the one getting that questionable 911 call.</p>
        <p>''As a 911 operator, I'm speaking to someone on the phone who may have been stabbed or shot,'' he said. After such a call, ''there's an adrenaline rush, and then you're answering a 911 call about a dog barking in the backyard.''</p>
        <p>Eating dinner one evening in the call center's break room -- a canteen equipped with a full, modern kitchen and a ceiling-mounted television set -- Mr. Corona recalled one high point in his new line of work: his pride in saving a potential suicide victim.</p>
        <p>''A call came in from Peekskill, and a female was crying on the phone,'' he said. ''But she said, 'Forget it,' and hung up. I called her back and she said her brother was driving to the Bear Mountain Bridge to commit suicide.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corona dispatched the call to several agencies and made sure that state troopers began a search for the man.</p>
        <p>''The Carmel police found him on Route 6,'' Mr. Corona said. The man was still distraught, but he was alive.</p>
        <p>One if by Land, Two if by Cell</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY uses one central call center for all emergencies, but Westchester uses two separate systems for directing 911 calls -- one for landline calls and another for cellular calls.</p>
        <p>Those originating from landline telephones are automatically routed to the nearest police department by a switching station in White Plains. If that station were damaged, the service could rely on a backup in Nyack, across the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>''We're much more diversified than New York City,'' said John R. Elliott, director of 911 for the county. ''It would be very difficult to lose 911 in Westchester, because we have more routes and paths.''</p>
        <p>Westchester's landline 911 switching station can handle 250 to 300 calls at once, Mr. Elliott said. Each call is routed to one of 39 public-safety answering points, including local and state police departments, as well as to the Westchester County Police, he said.</p>
        <p>Calls to 911 from Voice Over Internet Protocol, the Internet telephone system, are included among landline calls and are sorted at the White Plains station, Mr. Elliott said.</p>
        <p>As long as the callers' computers remain stationary, in their home, the call will be correctly located. But if the Voice Over customer takes the laptop computer to, say, Kansas, and has to dial 911 from the computer's phone, that caller will still be connected to the local Westchester police department nearest the home address. Which may not be particularly useful in Kansas.</p>
        <p>This situation has not yet reached the problem stage, but Mr. Elliott said that it soon would, with ever more people signing up for telephone service via the Internet.</p>
        <p>But for now, the majority of callers in distress use cellphones. (Cellphone calls per month: 40,000; landline calls per month: 25,000.)</p>
        <p>And although Westchester was very late in coming to 911 technology for landline telephones, it is now in the technological vanguard for cellular service.</p>
        <p>As mandated by the Federal Communications Commission, the majority of the calls coming in to 911 are now Phase Two, which means they register a phone number and a location. With a few exceptions, the agency is requiring all cellphone manufacturers to equip their phones with global positioning chips by the end of this year. With that new generation of phones, all emergency services can gain in speed and precision.</p>
        <p>CARIN RUBENSTEIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
