<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Park, Not New Players, Draws Fans</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="752280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COORS FIELD (DENVER)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DENVER (COLO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLORADO ROCKIES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Denver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D7143FF932A35757C0A963958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Park, Not New Players, Draws Fans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everywhere around Coors Field, there were baseball fans clad in purple and black hustling to get inside the splendid new stadium. They arrived early to gawk at the Camden Yards look-a-like and to peek at the replacement players who would be the first to grace it. Maybe the first and last replacement players.</p>
        <p>With United States District Judge Sonia Sotomayor having granted an injunction to the National Labor Relations Board in New York earlier today that restored baseball's prestrike contract conditions, there was a very good possibility the major league players would be returning to work soon and the replacement players would vanish. So today's exhibition game, inside a facility that cost $215.5 million to build, had a chance to be a collector's item of sorts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everywhere around Coors Field, there were baseball fans clad in purple and black hustling to get inside the splendid new stadium. They arrived early to gawk at the Camden Yards look-a-like and to peek at the replacement players who would be the first to grace it. Maybe the first and last replacement players.</p>
        <p>With United States District Judge Sonia Sotomayor having granted an injunction to the National Labor Relations Board in New York earlier today that restored baseball's prestrike contract conditions, there was a very good possibility the major league players would be returning to work soon and the replacement players would vanish. So today's exhibition game, inside a facility that cost $215.5 million to build, had a chance to be a collector's item of sorts.</p>
        <p>A bizarre slice of baseball history in an already frustrating chapter was taking place as the Rockies opposed the Yankees, replacement style.</p>
        <p>Most of the 47,563 fans conceded they were attracted to 20th Street and Blake Street by the new field, not by the new players. But others conceded that baseball is baseball and they will support whoever happens to jog onto the field wearing a Rockies uniform.</p>
        <p>The game was 2,686 spectators short of a sellout and provided the Yankees with 28,756 more fans in one contest than they had attracted in 14 spring games at Fort Lauderdale Stadium.</p>
        <p>Despite the festive atmosphere, the play bothered at least one Hall of Fame member.</p>
        <p>"I'd be a star in this league," said 48-year old Reggie Jackson, who guessed he had watched two innings. "That don't look too good. It's difficult to look at it. It's kind of sad to see."</p>
        <p>As the Yankees wobbled through today's game with six hits and a 4-1 defeat, Manager Buck Showalter and George Steinbrenner, the owner, were privately hoping the experiment with these substitute players would finally wilt. Steinbrenner and Jerry McMorris, the Rockies' owner, will attend the owner's meeting in Chicago Sunday afternoon that might finally sort things out regarding the 1995 season.</p>
        <p>Although Steinbrenner said the Yankees have contingency plans for different scenarios, including one for assembling their major leaguers in Florida, he would not discuss them. He did not expect a settlement this weekend; he did say the next five days would be pivotal.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner also discovered first-hand that the security is stringent at Coors Field, after an attendant prevented him from walking onto the field because he did not have the proper credential. The attendant, Shannon Smith, who described herself as a Yankee fan, said she knew who Steinbrenner was and still denied him access. She said the Yankee owner was patient while the pass was fetched and then later kissed her on the cheek.</p>
        <p>"This is as nice as any of the new stadiums," marveled Steinbrenner, perhaps wondering how a facility like Coors Field would look in New Jersey. "And it's been done in a classy way."</p>
        <p>The mirth did not continue after the game. Steinbrenner convened at least his second meeting of the day with Showalter. The replacement Yankees crowded around a television set for strike-related news and groaned when they were called the replacement Yankees.</p>
        <p>Showalter conceded that he was staring ahead, too.</p>
        <p>"You try to be fair to the players here and the organization in trying to make this team competitive in a couple of days," Showalter said. "Certainly we think about the players who are on strike and how this trip could have been different. We could have been coming in here champions of our division, the league or who knows what. But I don't dwell on it."</p>
        <p>If the replacement Yankees conclude their careers this weekend, they will remember their debuts at Coors Field. The brick facade and steel awnings are reminiscent of Camden Yards in Baltimore. The concourse along the outfield is similar to that of Jacobs Field in Cleveland and the right field bleachers, brick wall behind the plate and left field stands could have been swiped from Wrigley Field in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Coors Field is bigger than all three of those stadiums and should be a pitcher's ball park.</p>
        <p>Already, it is a fans' ball park. Jim Winkler waited on line for three hours beginning at 5 A.M. Wednesday to buy three tickets after season ticket holders had returned about 2,500. With his Rockies cap in place and a smile on his face, Winkler looked happier than his 13-year-old son, David, and 11-year-old daughter, Lena.</p>
        <p>"I originally thought I would walk out because I've been disgusted a bit by the strike," Winkler said. "But these guys got to do what they got to do and that is make millions. I got to do what I got to do and that is take my kids to a ball game."</p>
        <p>Winkler claimed that cheering for unknowns was routine for the Rockie fans because most of the players were unknowns when the team began playing as an expansion franchise two years ago. Showalter does not agree. He would rather see big names, not no-names.</p>
        <p>"We've had so many sways of emotions as far as this is concerned," Showalter said. "Let's hope it's coming to a head."</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
