<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peronists Shun a Rally Honoring Their Founder</title>
    <meta content="18ARGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="884043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buenos Aires (Argentina)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peron, Juan Domingo (1895-1974)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menem, Carlos Saul (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina/Buenos Aires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DE1031F93BA25753C1A960958260" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peronists Shun a Rally Honoring Their Founder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>BUENOS AIRES, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plaza de Mayo in Buenos Aires, where masses of Argentines have gathered in past to honor Juan de Peron, is empty of Peronists on anniversary of night in 1945 when Government freed popular young colonel; photo; few Peronists are in mood to cheer at time of record unemployment, when their leader, Pres Carlos Saul Menem, has erased decades-old laws guaranteeing jobs (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On this day in past years, masses of Argentines filled the Plaza de Mayo across from the presidential palace to celebrate the events of a night more than five decades ago. On that night, a multitude of workers gathered here to demand that the military Government release Juan Domingo Peron.</p>
        <p>The young colonel, who was in charge of labor issues for that Government, had taken up the people's cause, and when the people's widely popular hero was imprisoned, they came out to support him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On this day in past years, masses of Argentines filled the Plaza de Mayo across from the presidential palace to celebrate the events of a night more than five decades ago. On that night, a multitude of workers gathered here to demand that the military Government release Juan Domingo Peron.</p>
        <p>The young colonel, who was in charge of labor issues for that Government, had taken up the people's cause, and when the people's widely popular hero was imprisoned, they came out to support him.</p>
        <p>That night in 1945, the Government, fearing riots in the plaza, gave in and freed him.</p>
        <p>That was the first demonstration of the power of Peronism, which led to Peron's election as President the same year and the empowerment of Argentina's working class. The anniversary has seldom passed without great fanfare.</p>
        <p>But the Plaza de Mayo was silent today. Few Peronists felt like cheering in an Argentina of record unemployment and increasing poverty, where their leader, President Carlos Saul Menem, has erased decades-old labor laws that guaranteed the jobs of many voters.</p>
        <p>Today the Peronists are in disarray. The party's long-term strategy of extreme nationalism is being abandoned, in an effort to update the economy while seeking to establish a common ideology for its widely varied members.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason for any true Peronist to celebrate today when you look at what Menem has done to this country,'' said Celia Benavides, 50, a seamstress, who placed flowers at Peron's tomb in the Chacarita Cemetery in western Buenos Aires. ''Poor General Peron. He's probably turning over in his grave in disgust at what Menem is doing.''</p>
        <p>Since his election in 1989, Mr. Menem has dismantled many state-owned enterprises and undone much of the cradle-to-grave employment protection that was Peron's legacy. Many in the party see Mr. Menem's actions as an unfortunate but necessary betrayal of Peronist-populist ideas.</p>
        <p>President Menem, who last year became the first incumbent since Peron to win a second term, brought stability to a country suffering from runaway inflation by restructuring the economy, selling Government-owned businesses and attracting foreign investment.</p>
        <p>But in the process, thousands of Argentines who worked for inefficient private and state-owned businesses lost their jobs and, without the skills to find new ones, swelled the ranks of the unemployed. Joblessness now stands at 17 percent, and the country is in a deep recession.</p>
        <p>Senator Eduardo Vaca, President of the Peronist Party, said: ''We believe that this 17th of October, more than a day of remembrance, should be a day of reflection, especially on the employment problem, which is a symbol of Peronism. That is why we are going to work today, and not celebrating. We need to find ways to solve unemployment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vaca said that most Peronists saw Mr. Menem's reforms as necessary but were asking whether they had been enacted too quickly and what effect they would have on the party in congressional elections next year.</p>
        <p>''To enact these reforms,'' Mr. Vaca said, ''we were forced to take a strong change of direction and make alliances with groups that were not characteristic of Peronism, like the industrial and financial sectors. Often we didn't fully assess what the impact of these changes might be.''</p>
        <p>Trade unions, the traditional core of Peronist support, have responded to Mr. Menem's labor law reforms with nationwide strikes that have twice brought the country to a standstill.</p>
        <p>Juan Manuel Palacios, leader of the Passenger Transportation Union, which represents transit workers, said that if Mr. Menem pushed ahead with the changes, organized labor would re-evaluate its long-term support.</p>
        <p>The party leadership, too, has been divided, as traditionalists like Eduardo Duhalde, Governor of Buenos Aires, reject the economic changes and proclaim themselves as representing the original Peronist interests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duhalde, who served as Vice President during Mr. Menem's first term, has said he plans to run for the presidency in 1999.</p>
        <p>Although the Peronists have enjoyed a majority in the Congress for the last six years, they face a struggle retaining control, as public discontent over Mr. Menem's actions continues to grow.</p>
        <p>His popularity, which rarely fell below 50 percent in the past, has plummeted to the mid-teens. Still, he has reasserted his support for the reforms. ''If the unions hold a 48-hour strike, a 48-day strike, or a 48-month strike,'' he said, ''I will not change course.''</p>
        <p>The party's image has also been hurt recently by two major scandals involving people close to Mr. Menem and members of his Cabinet. The former Finance Minister, Domingo Cavallo, who was the architect of Mr. Menem's economic overhaul, accused the justice and interior ministers this week of covering up corruption and manipulating judges. And Mr. Menem's close friends, the soccer star Diego Maradona and his agent, are embroiled in a drug scandal.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Peronists' main rivals, the Radicals, appear to be making a comeback after winning the municipal elections in Buenos Aires. The Radicals are currently in discussions with the leftist Frepaso to strike an alliance in preparation for the elections next year.</p>
        <p>Peronism of the past raised the living standards in Argentina, helping to create the largest middle class in Latin America. But it shut the country off from the rest of the world, flirted with fascism and created the state and private monopolies that stifled the country's competitiveness.</p>
        <p>Peron ruled from 1946 to 1955 with the help of his second wife, Eva, until his Government fell in a coup. He returned to office in 1973 until his death less than a year later. His third wife and vice president, Maria Estela Peron, was overthrown in 1976 at a time of hyperinflation, strikes and leftist violence.</p>
        <p>''Peronism as we knew it is dead,'' said Mariano Plotkin, a professor of Latin American history at Colby College, who is visiting Argentina. ''But Peronism as a political movement is still alive and well. However, what we will continue to see in this party is an identification with the populist struggle of the past even though the Peronists have now moved beyond that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
