<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Dark The Other Games Begin</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NIGHTCLUBS AND CABARETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTA (GA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0D81E39F931A35755C0A960958260" item-length="2512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Dark The Other Games Begin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jon Pareles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEORGIA has been the cradle of some of America's most influential popular music, from soul to alternative rock to hip-hop: the roll-call includes Little Richard, James Brown, the Allman Brothers, R.E.M. and Arrested Development. As the cultural hub of the New South, Atlanta is a place where down-home Americana  rubs shoulders with the latest in communications technology. Many of its homegrown rock bands are close to blues, soul and country roots, while its recording studios have become a center for easygoing, seductive hip-hop and rhythm-and-blues. And with a sizable student population and a thriving middle class, Atlanta provides audiences for obscure local bands as well as national touring acts, in settings ranging from intimate, smoky basement hangouts to grand, scenic amphitheaters.</p>
        <p>Clubs are scattered around Atlanta and its suburbs, and serious club-hopping  requires a car, but there are a few areas where clubs are clustered. Little Five Points -- Atlanta's answer to St. Mark's Place in the East Village in Manhattan  -- has a handful of punky rock clubs. Discos and bars are grouped on two parts of Peachtree Street, with a frat-party atmosphere in Buckhead (near East Paces Ferry Road) and more up-to-the-minute dance music in midtown (around 10th Street).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEORGIA has been the cradle of some of America's most influential popular music, from soul to alternative rock to hip-hop: the roll-call includes Little Richard, James Brown, the Allman Brothers, R.E.M. and Arrested Development. As the cultural hub of the New South, Atlanta is a place where down-home Americana  rubs shoulders with the latest in communications technology. Many of its homegrown rock bands are close to blues, soul and country roots, while its recording studios have become a center for easygoing, seductive hip-hop and rhythm-and-blues. And with a sizable student population and a thriving middle class, Atlanta provides audiences for obscure local bands as well as national touring acts, in settings ranging from intimate, smoky basement hangouts to grand, scenic amphitheaters.</p>
        <p>Clubs are scattered around Atlanta and its suburbs, and serious club-hopping  requires a car, but there are a few areas where clubs are clustered. Little Five Points -- Atlanta's answer to St. Mark's Place in the East Village in Manhattan  -- has a handful of punky rock clubs. Discos and bars are grouped on two parts of Peachtree Street, with a frat-party atmosphere in Buckhead (near East Paces Ferry Road) and more up-to-the-minute dance music in midtown (around 10th Street).</p>
        <p>Admission prices are low by New York standards -- less than $10 for live music at many places, $15 or less for dance clubs -- and most clubs have friendly hosts and room enough for a pool table or two. Naturally, weekends are  most active, but more often than not the weekend starts on Wednesday. Live bands generally perform between 9 P.M. and midnight, but Atlantans stay up later, even during the week; dance clubs start hopping after 11 P.M. and usually stay open until 4 A.M. The free alternative weekly, Creative Loafing, has extensive music listings, and is available at many stores and clubs. Here are some of the  city's most congenial night spots.</p>
        <p>Dancing</p>
        <p>Tongue and Groove, 3055 Peachtree Road; (404) 261-2325. At night, the center  of the Buckhead section is an all-out party zone: a music lover's nightmare of singles bars, extra-large drink specials, karaoke belters and cover bands playing sloppy Allman Brothers tunes, some on open-air decks. Parking is scarce; groups of tipsy, giggling 20-somethings toddle along the sidewalks, shouting 1970's disco hits from the last place they visited. At one club, a sign warns of dire consequences from a new fad drug, gamma hydro butyric acid. The Tongue and  Groove, though situated amid the frenzy, is the upscale alternative: a dance and conversation club for people old enough to have voted in the last Presidential election or two.</p>
        <p>Inside, past a picky doorman, women wear little black designer dresses and most men wear jackets, though not necessarily ties; athletic shoes aren't allowed. In the conversation room, large surreal paintings and contraption-like  sculptures hang on the walls above long, curving banquettes and mirrors that allow unobtrusive people-watching. A bartender discusses the merits of various wines by the glass ($6.75 to $9.75); a cigarette girl kneels to clip the cigar of a man seated in an armchair. In the velvet-roped VIP area, a man sits talking into a cellular phone with an ice bucket at his elbow.</p>
        <p>The dance room, decorated as a kind of Art Brut basement, has a sushi bar and loud but not earsplitting recorded music, which varies with the night of the week and ranges from cool jazz to 70's disco to current hits.</p>
        <p>The Masquerade, 695 North Avenue, N.E.; (404) 577-8178. The building is a century old: an imposing, blocklong Romanesque stone structure that looms after  dark like a castle. It used to be a mill making excelsior (wood shavings used for stuffing or packing), and spoked wheels from the old machinery hang overhead. The Masquerade has three operations drawing different crowds. On the first floor is Hell, a sunken, dungeonlike space with chains on the walls and the flashing lights of a dance club; it presents 1980's music on Thursdays and current house and techno on weekends. Across the hall is a bar, Purgatory, with  pool tables and video games. And up the rough-hewn wooden stairs is Heaven, where live bands play punk and alternative rock in a huge room with a high ceiling and a tall stage. There are, logically, separate admissions for Heaven and Hell (Purgatory is free). On the same site is the Masquerade Music Park, which presents occasional large outdoor rock shows in the early evenings. Other  clubs for current dance music include Oxygen, 3065 Peachtree Street, N.E., (404) 816-6522, and the primarily gay Backstreet, 845 Peachtree Street, N.E., (404) 873-1986, and Otherside, 1924 Piedmont Road, N.E., (404) 875-5238.</p>
        <p>Johnny's Hideaway, 3371 Roswell Road; (404) 233-8026. Nostalgia extends back  to the 1930's at this Atlanta institution. Gray-haired couples and singles and some casually untrendy younger people dance to big-band selections played by a disk jockey, who also adds rock-and-roll oldies as the night goes on. Johnny Esposito is at the door to greet the regulars, and there are plenty of them, sipping mixed drinks and dining on bar food, from nachos and Buffalo wings to steak. On the walls are photos of vintage movie stars like Humphrey Bogart; red-velvet swivel chairs surround a patio-sized dance floor with mirrored balls  overhead. Video screens show dapper big-band performers or the club's own promotional clips.  The regulars greet each other, catch up on small talk and await the right song. When the disk jockey cues up Frank Sinatra singing, "I've  Got a Crush on You," the dance floor fills up fast.</p>
        <p>Rock</p>
        <p>Star Community Bar, 437 Moreland Avenue, N.E.; (404) 681-9018. From the sign  that spells out ELVIS in white lights to the Christmas twinklers over the bar to the silvery Mylar strips that are the stage backdrop, the Star Community Bar revels in kitschy Americana. It books bands in search of the perfect twang who play rowdy updates of surf rock and rockabilly, 1960's pop rock and blues. The crowd, in its 20's and 30's, dresses to match the music, in thrift-shop leopard  prints, cowboy shirts with the sleeves torn off and cocktail dresses that reveal tattoos.</p>
        <p>Cotton Club, 1021 Peachtree Street, N.E.; (404) 874-1993. Alternative-rock bands building national reputations make their Atlanta stop at the Cotton Club,  a big, open dance hall that holds more than 1,000 people. A wide stage built against the long wall of the rectangular room gives bands ample space to jump around, facing an audience on a broad level surface suitable for moshing. Around the edges, tiers with barstools and standing room offer a good view even when the place is packed, and the sound is hefty but precise.</p>
        <p>The Point, 420 Moreland Avenue, N.E.; (404) 659-3522. Atlanta's answer to CBGB, New York's punk citadel, is this scruffy, black-walled club, where bands on the middle rungs of the collegiate-rock circuit share bills with local rock groups. A cozy, publike bar is connected to the back of the club but separated from the music. Pierced and shaved punks hang around a small plaza behind the club until showtime, then crowd in close to the stage. It's strictly no-frills.</p>
        <p>Red Light Cafe, 553 Amsterdam Avenue, N.E.; (404) 874-7828. A loft space has  been turned into an outsized living room, complete with sofas and a shelf full of board games -- a clubhouse for slightly arty slackers. It's a coffeehouse, not a bar, with a dinner menu including sandwiches, salad and pasta. Local bands and some touring college-radio favorites perform for an audience that looks relieved that finals are over.</p>
        <p>Blues and Soul</p>
        <p>Blind Willie's, 828 North Highland Avenue, N.E.; (404) 873-2583. Mardi Gras beads hang over the bar, the jukebox has rare singles by Lightnin' Hopkins and Willie Dixon, the kitchen serves casual Cajun food and the people on stage belt  out straightforward Chicago and Southern blues until long after midnight. The club books local bands and some touring performers, and there's no pretension; it's the kind of place where a blues mama will pull a college student on stage and give him lessons in hip-shaking.</p>
        <p>Lou's Blues Revue, 736 Ponce de Leon Avenue; (404) 249-7311. This is Blind Willie's competition: a yellow shed tacked next to a mini-mall with the performer's tour van parked outside. It books blues singers with albums on independent labels, who work a circuit from the Midwest to the Deep South to New York City. Inside is a mini-Hard Rock Cafe, slightly too glossy, with guitars in display cases, saxophone-shaped beer taps and rock memorabilia on the walls. Lou Vandora, the owner, sometimes sits in on guitar during the late sets.</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Catfish Station, 618 Ponce de Leon Avenue; (404) 875-5687. Jazz, soul, funk, hip-hop and, on occasion, African bands perform at this genteel restaurant, where catfish is the specialty. It has a weekly Wednesday night showcase for unsigned hip-hop and rhythm-and-blues performers. A high, theater-sized stage sits at one end of a loftlike room filled with well-dressed couples and singles  at tables; a raised bar at the other end serves people who aren't dining. The decor is stylized industrial, with giant asterisks of ventilator ducts overhead. On a recent stopover, a band played easygoing pop-jazz at a volume that didn't preclude conversation. Although the entire clientele was black, a white visitor was treated with hospitality. "Come back and bring your friends," said the host.</p>
        <p>Dante's Down the Hatch, at Underground Atlanta; (404) 577-1800. In Underground Atlanta, a sunless, theme-park re-creation of the downtown of yore,  Dante's offers theme overload. Its two-story basement, where a well that dates back to 1810 and an old factory's steam engine are still visible, has been turned into a recreated frigate with upper and lower decks. There, from 7:30 P.M. to 11:30 (12:30 A.M. Friday and Saturday), a skillful, light-fingered jazz  trio plays standards and blues, while families, tourists and dating couples poke forks into fondue. The anteroom, decorated as a wharf, features classical or folk guitar players, and a moat around the ship holds a live crocodile or two. "After 9 P.M.," a sign warns, "No shorts. No yukky T-shirts." Unusual as it is,  Dante's has cloned itself, complete with crocodile, for a second, freestanding branch in Buckhead at 3380 Peachtree Road, N.E.; (404) 266-1600. Paul Mitchell,  the pianist who has been playing at Dante's for more than two decades, is now stationed in Buckhead.</p>
        <p>Yin Yang Cafe, 64 Third Street, N.E., near Spring Street; (404) 607-0682. The club is on a desolate dead end just a few feet from a highway, but inside the mood is urbane and cosmopolitan. In a brick-walled room under a changing display of paintings, an ambitious kitchen serves Mediterranean and Asian-inflected dishes in the early evenings. Local jazz groups or cool acid jazz disk jockeys take over around 9:30 or 10 P.M.</p>
        <p>Outside Atlanta</p>
        <p>40 Watt, 285 West Washington Street, Athens; (706) 549-7871. After the Olympic soccer games in Athens, about 60 miles north of Atlanta, rock fans may want to visit a historic spot. The 40 Watt Club is the University of Georgia hangout that nurtured groups like the B-52's and R.E.M., proving that a modest college-town scene could turn into a rock vanguard. The club shares a building with the Pain and Wonder tattoo parlor, and its street door opens directly into  a simple squarish room, with a bar along one wall, a cigarette machine on the other, and quilts hanging from the ceiling. Before making their next stop at the Cotton Club or the Point, touring rock bands soak up the unpretentious party spirit.</p>
        <p>Concerts</p>
        <p>Chastain Park Amphitheater, Powers Ferry Road and Stella Drive; (404) 733-5000. Major touring acts, most of them with audiences over 30, perform at this 7,000-seat amphitheater in a city park. Atlantans arrive like a bourgeois expeditionary force, carrying provisions from pasta salads to barbecue. "Onward, Jeeves," a woman at a recent show urged her companion, who was hefting a picnic  hamper, a padded wine-bottle carrier and a folding table. The rows are wide enough to accommodate those tables, and at their seats, the couple set up a spread complete with a tablecloth and a Chastain tradition: a candle in its holder. Patrons tend to chat through the opening act, and sometimes the headliner; an 85-decibel maximum aids conversation, though sound grows anemic in the back rows. But with the candles burning, the concerts have a fireside warmth. During the Olympics, shows include Peter, Paul and Mary (July 20); a blues night featuring Koko Taylor and Charles Brown (July 24); Mary Chapin Carpenter (July 26 and 27); Etta James (July 31); the Gipsy Kings (Aug. 2) and Patti Labelle (Aug. 3). Tickets range from $17 for lawn seats to $40.50 for box  seats.</p>
        <p>The Fox Theater, 660 Peachtree Street, N.E., (404) 881 2100. On the National  Register of Historic Places, the Fox Theater is a treat for its architecture alone. A former movie house and Shriners temple that is now used for live music  and theater, it's a grand architectural fantasy, designed as an imaginary Moorish palace. The wooden beams, the canopied ceiling and the stone parapets are all made of painted plaster; stars twinkle overhead in its blue ceiling. And it's relatively intimate, with the front row of the mezzanine only 30 feet from  the stage. Performers scheduled to appear during the Olympics include Alison Krauss on July 18, Luther Vandross on July 22, Kenny G on July 25, Vince Gill on July 26, Jerry Seinfeld on July 27 and 28 and Tony Bennett on July 29. Tickets,  from $50 to $125, are sold through Ticketmaster at (404) 249-6400.</p>
        <p>Variety Playhouse, 1099 Euclid Avenue, N.E.; (404) 524-7354. Formerly a porn  house, the Variety Playhouse now presents concerts in an ambiance between theater and cabaret. It's an unadorned box that holds 800 seats or 1,000 standees and its clear acoustics enhance concerts by singer-songwriters, pop-jazz groups and an occasional comedian or neo-hippie dance band. Usually it  has theater seating, steeply raked for good sightlines; tickets generally range  from $8 to $20, depending on the act. On the sides are tables and chairs, and there's a steady traffic during shows between the theater and the snack bar, which sells wine, beer and cappuccino. Quiet passages are sometimes punctuated by beer bottles hitting the floor.</p>
        <p>JON PARELES is the chief popular-music critic of TheNew York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JON PARELES is the chief popular-music critic of TheNew York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
