<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNET AND WORLD WIDE WEB</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROMM, DIANE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSLEAH, RAHEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D71E39F931A35755C0A960958260" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE KETCHAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bugs to Go, Hold the Mayo</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bugs to Go, Hold the Mayo</p>
        <p>ON the bottom shelf of Steve Restmeyer's refrigerator in Yaphank is the standard suburban fare -- yogurt, mustard and praying mantis. Mr. Restmeyer keeps bugs in his refrigerator because he makes a living from them. Like the "she" who "sells seashells by the seashore," he sells bugs by the blossoms. They are good bugs, he said, that eat the bad bugs, which makes for a natural way of controlling pests. "The key is knowing what is a pest," he said.</p>
        <p>His wife, Jacki, has learned to accept ladybugs, wasps and praying mantises  that share space with the leftover lasagna. "The only problem," she said, "is after you go to the supermarket. You come home and you're missing shelf space."</p>
        <p>The bugs don't remain in the fridge. Mr. Restmeyer keeps them there temporarily to "slow their metabolism," he said. "When they are in the dormant stage their need for food is low." Which means a lower overhead for the bugman and his company, Eco-Logical Organic Landscaping.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Restmeyer releases his bugs, they head for the nearest chow. At the  home of Debbie and Stewart Gormal of Fort Salonga, it was a cluster of white flowers. Mr. Restmeyer released hundreds of ladybugs there. "They like to eat aphids and mites," he said. At first they didn't seem to want to leave their keeper. Dozens crawled on his arms, legs and into his shoes. But slowly they began to fly away -- to the flowers, to a tree and, yes, to a neighbor's yard. Most, however, would stay on the property, Mr. Restmeyer said.</p>
        <p>"They stay here because they know this is a safe place," Mrs. Gormal added. She hired Mr. Restmeyer because he was an organic landscaper. "I was brought up  in Vermont," she said. "No one I knew used pesticides."</p>
        <p>When she learned that Mr. Restmeyer visits prospective customers at night "to see what bugs they have" she was hooked. After three springs with him, she isn't sure which bugs in her yard are imported or which came there naturally.</p>
        <p>Like that butterfly. "He's invited," Mr. Restmeyer said. So, too, were the birds. "I supply birdhouses," he said. "From sunrise to sunset you have two adults' scavenging your property for bugs." The other day he also supplied several hundred wasps.</p>
        <p>"Wasps are the tigers and lions of the insect world," he said. He placed a swatch containing trichogramma, or tiny wasps, on a branch of the Gormals' maple tree. "They feast on the eggs of the gypsy moths," he said.</p>
        <p>Through the years Mr. Restmeyer has learned what bugs eat other bugs. "I started in premed in college," he said. "But for my health I quit and decided to follow what I wanted to do." That was ecology. "I didn't want to be Mr. Pesticide," he said. "I'm like a holistic healer for your yard."</p>
        <p>He always has loved bugs, he said. "I never did any bug torture as a child. I collected plants as a teen-ager. I was somewhat of a hermit."</p>
        <p>Today he seems well adjusted as he travels the Island delivering bugs to backyards. He doesn't breed the bugs. "The mail carrier delivers them," he said. "They come in packages marked 'Live Insects.' "</p>
        <p>Among those are the praying mantises. Hundreds were in an egg case that he placed in a boxwood bush. "They will emerge in August," he said. "They are very  territorial and they can cannibalize. You may have heard how the female eats the head off of the male after they have sex."</p>
        <p>Praying mantises are good insects, because they eat flies and beetles. "They  also stalk bees," he said, "which we don't want them to do."</p>
        <p>Next month, the Restmeyers' refrigerator will hold nematodes. It will be a full house, what with the spiders' roaming in the basement. "I keep spiders down there to control the termites," Mr. Restmeyer said.</p>
        <p>But that's not the only roaming plan he has developed. "I'm working on a project to put quail in people's backyards to control ticks," he said. "The quail will eat the ticks. But hawks and owls like to eat the quail." That plan still has a few, ah, bugs, to work out.</p>
        <p>Drive-Over Dining</p>
        <p>In the past fund-raising dinners have come in two varieties. Organizations can rent a hotel ballroom, have the food catered and charge appropriately. Or they rent the ballroom and have a "Taste of," where restaurants and wineries supply the food and drink, which means more profits for the nonprofit.</p>
        <p>Now the Circle of Friends for the St. Charles Hospice in Port Jefferson has come up with an even more frugal idea. For a fund-raising dinner next Saturday,  they are supplying neither the hall nor the food. They persuaded nearby residents, including prominent ones, to open their homes and allow strangers to  dine with them. The resident-hosts are doing the shopping and cooking.  The hospice is reaping the rewards.</p>
        <p>"We have 13 homeowners' participating," Marianne Gillan of the hospice said.  Among the homeowners are two judges, Alfred Tisch, who with his wife will serve  a northern Italian dinner, and Lawrence Bracken, who with his wife will serve duck. A former president of the State University at Stony Brook, Dr. John H. Marburger 3d, and his wife plan on concocting a south-of-the-border seafood dinner for eight. And a former Congressman, George Hochbrueckner, and his wife will serve a Greek feast. In some houses wives will cook. In others the husbands.</p>
        <p>For $100 a person, guests can choose at whose house they wish to dine. "You have to list a first, second and third choice," said Ms. Gillan, who can be called at 474-4040.</p>
        <p>There have been some interesting sign-ups. "It seems all the physicians want  to eat with a judge," she said. What if some hosts are more popular than others? "We'll never tell," she said.</p>
        <p>After dinner everyone heads to Theater Three for "The Buddy Holly Story" and  dessert. Who does the dishes? "The automatic dishwasher, I guess," Ms. Gillan said. "Everybody can just leave the dishes on soak."</p>
        <p>Odds and the End</p>
        <p>Marty Simon of Hewlett always wanted to sing in Carnegie Hall. Last week he made it. He rented the hall. Before a crowd that almost reached the rafters -- Mr. Simon has many friends -- he sang "My Way" and "If I Ruled the World." The owner of an insurance company in Lynbrook, Mr. Simon hired as his opening acts the New York University Glee Club and Freddie Roman, and he gave the proceeds from ticket sales to Brookdale Hospital. The crowd gave him a standing ovation.  . . . Other singers with an interesting venue include Aretha Franklin and the Allman Brothers. Ms. Franklin is scheduled to perform on Aug. 19 at the Back at  the Ranch concert in Montauk. The Allman Brothers, who were at the ranch in 1993, will appear at the All for the Sea concert at Southampton College on July  22. Got it? . . . One thing that lawyers on Long Island don't always get is a will. According to an advertisement in The Suffolk Lawyer, the newspaper of the  Suffolk County Bar Association, many lawyers are too busy drafting wills to do their own. So several lawyers are offering to prepare simple wills for other lawyers free. Yes, free, the ad says to any cynical lawyer who may read it. "No  Cost! No Fee! No Kidding!" And no last names. For those interested the ad says,  "Call Arnold, Floyd, Mary or John."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
