<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Y to the Olympics</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HARTFORD (CONN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTA (GA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAVANAUGH, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAY-BEY, LAWRENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Hartford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D71E39F931A35755C0A960958260" item-length="2212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Y to the Olympics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CAVANAUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CAVANAUGH, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Lawrence Clay-Bey walked into the old Y Center at the Stowe Village housing project in Hartford's North End four years ago, the veteran boxing trainer Francisco Zayas saw, as he recalled it, "a fat guy with a gut."</p>
        <p>At 275 pounds on a 6-foot 2-inch frame, Clay-Bey fit that description. "He asked if he could work out a little bit, and I said 'sure,'," Zayas recollected. "And he looked like a guy who needed to work out a lot."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Lawrence Clay-Bey walked into the old Y Center at the Stowe Village housing project in Hartford's North End four years ago, the veteran boxing trainer Francisco Zayas saw, as he recalled it, "a fat guy with a gut."</p>
        <p>At 275 pounds on a 6-foot 2-inch frame, Clay-Bey fit that description. "He asked if he could work out a little bit, and I said 'sure,'," Zayas recollected. "And he looked like a guy who needed to work out a lot."</p>
        <p>The Y Center, which was sponsored by the Hartford Housing Authority, was essentially a youth center for aspiring boxers and it was equipped with a ring,  punching bags and other accouterments of the sport. Clay-Bey became a regular visitor after that, working out on the speed and heavy bags and, eventually, sparring with some amateur boxers who trained at the Center.</p>
        <p>"Right off the bat, I saw it -- that he had talent as a fighter," said Zayas, who has been a boxing trainer for 20 years. "About two weeks after he came in, I put him in the ring with a fighter who was training for the Golden Gloves tournament, and Clay-Bey knocked him out. And the kid he knocked out was a pretty good fighter."</p>
        <p>At the time, in 1992, Lawrence Clay-Bey was a 26-year-old father of three children, a correction officer in Cheshire who wanted to lose some weight but had absolutely no aspirations of becoming a boxer. Today, at the advanced age of 30 for an amateur boxer, he is the superheavyweight on the United States Olympic boxing team currently in training for this summer's Olympics in Atlanta and is ranked third in the world among amateur boxers in his weight class. Moreover, he is the reigning United States amateur champion in the superheavyweight division  and has beaten the top-ranked superheavyweight in the world, Alexei Zezin of Russia. "It's amazing, isn't it?," asked Zayas rhetorically. "It's a once-in-a-lifetime experience."</p>
        <p>It's also one of the most unusual happenings in the history of the United States Olympic boxing team since it first competed in the 1904 Summer Games in St. Louis. Even Clay-Bey, the reluctant warrior, is incredulous. "All I wanted to do was lose some weight when I went into the Y Center gym," he said. "And here I am, four years later, representing my country in the Olympics. I find it  hard to believe."</p>
        <p>To say that Lawrence Clay-Bey's rise in the world of boxing has been meteoric would be an understatment. Most amateur boxers in the United States begin their  careers in their middle teens. And those who are successful usually turn professional by the time they are 20 or 21. Indeed, about half of the boxers on  the United States team are still in their teens. A 30-year-old amateur in the country is a rarity. "I've checked, and I can't find any record of a fighter in  his 30's on any U.S. team in the past," said Steve Ross, a spokesman for U.S.A.  Boxing, the governing body for the American boxing team.</p>
        <p>Historically, the Olympics have been a stepping stone for many prominent American boxers. Six Olympic gold medal winners -- Floyd Patterson, Michael Spinks, Muhammad Ali, Leon Spinks, George Foreman and Joe Frazier -- went on to  become heavyweight champions of the world, and many other Olympic champions have also won world titles. But despite those precedents and his success and continuing improvement as a fighter, Clay-Bey says he has no desire to turn pro, even if he wins the gold medal in his division, which is certainly a possibility. "I've already accomplished far more than I ever thought was possible," says Clay-Bey, "and after the Olympics I'd like to get out and go back to my job as a prison guard."</p>
        <p>But the personable Clay-Bey, who has won 47 amateur fights and lost only 7, has left the door to pro boxing open, aware that Olympic boxing champions can command large purses if they turn professional. "If I was fortunate to get an offer that only a fool would turn down, I guess I'd have to consider it. After all, it could mean a lot to my family financially. And even if I don't turn pro, I might consider offers for endorsements or maybe to do television commentary."</p>
        <p>The coach of the United States team, Al Mitchell, thinks that a professional  offer might be forthcoming if Clay-Bey does well in the Olympics. "Lawrence is a late bloomer and there's no telling how far he could go as a pro," Mitchell said.</p>
        <p>Actually, Clay-Bey was ready to give up boxing so that he could spend more time at his job as a correction officer at the John R. Manson Youth Institution  in Cheshire and with his family at their home in Bloomfield. "After I won my first U.S. championship and the World Championship Challenge" -- where he beat Lezin, then and now the top-ranked amateur superheavyweight in the world -- "in  1995, I told myself that was going to be my last year," he said in a telephone interview from Portland, Ore., where he has been in training. "I had achieved all of my goals in boxing and I knew I'd be a longshot to win the Olympic trials this year."</p>
        <p>But he changed his mind, for which Mitchell, his coach, and the rest of the United States team is grateful. And this year, after winning his second straight United States amateur championship, Clay-Bey won both the Olympic team trials and the subsequent Olympic team boxoff, which earned him the designation as the  American superheavyweight (201 pounds and over) in the Olympic Games in Atlanta. To win the latter event, he had to avenge a loss to Joe Mesi of Tonawanda, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Clay-Bey outpointed Mesi in the champions' bracket of the Olympic Team Trials in Oakland, Calif. in early April. But then at the Olympic team boxoffs in Augusta two weeks later, Mesi won a three-round decision over Clay-Bey. That meant they would meet each other again the following day, with the winner becoming the superheavyweight-designate at the Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>Clay-Bey's wife, Valerie, and their three children as well as his mother, Marva Clay-Bey and several other in-laws and relatives -- 10 in all -- saw him lose, after driving from Hartford to Augusta.</p>
        <p>"I had dominated him in Oakland, but I did not fight a smart fight the second time around, and he beat me fair and square," Clay-Bey said. "My two sons were crying after I lost, but my daughter, Jania, who is 4, and had never seen my fight before, was running around excitedly, saying 'my Daddy's going to knock him out tomorrow.' "</p>
        <p>Jania, whose brothers are Jerelle, 11, and Jarin, 6, turned out to be correct. The next day, Clay-Bey dispatched Mesi with a right hook in the first round while boxing as a southpaw, which he does occasionally, although he is right handed.</p>
        <p>That night, the Clay-Bey entourage, including the boxer, began a 15-hour trip by car and van back to Hartford. "We drove all night, but no one minded," said Clay-Bey who drove the car all the way back.</p>
        <p>Following a one-week rest at home, Clay-Bey flew to Oregon to begin training  for the Olympics, which will be held in Atlanta from July 19 to Aug. 4, and for  two pre-Olympic meets against Germany and Russia.</p>
        <p>For a big man (he now weighs around 250 pounds), Clay-Bey is nimble in the ring. "He could be faster, but it seems that the bigger he is, the better he fights," said Mitchell, his Olympic team coach. "He's a good puncher with both hands, but he needs more defense. For one thing, he tends to drop his hands."</p>
        <p>Zayas, his trainer in Hartford, said, "Lawrence has phenomenal hand speed, and he's a good boxer."</p>
        <p>It was Zayas who taught Clay-Bey the fundamentals of boxing -- first at Stowe Village and later at the Bellevue Square Boys Club in Hartford -- and guided him to early boxing successes in New England Golden Gloves competition."Lawrence had raw, natural talent, but I refined it," Zayas said.</p>
        <p>Within a month after Clay-Bey had begun to spar at the Center Y, Zayas had entered him into a regional Golden Gloves tournament in Lowell, Mass., where he won his first two fights before losing. Then in both 1993 and 1994 he reached the second round of the National Golden Gloves, the second time after he had won the New England championship.</p>
        <p>Finally, in 1995, Clay-Bey achieved his big breakthrough, earning the bronze  medal in the world championships in Berlin, winning his first United States amateur title and capturing the World Championship Challenge.</p>
        <p>"All of a sudden, I started beating everybody, mostly by knockouts," said Clay-Bey, who played football and basketball at Weaver High School in Hartford and attended Greater Hartford Community College for a year, where he met his wife.</p>
        <p>All the while, Clay-Bey continued to work full time as a guard at the Manson  Youth Institute in Cheshire, where the inmates range in age from 16 to 21. There he is assigned to the restrictive housing unit; its inmates are confined to the  unit because of assaults on guards or other misbehavior within the prison.</p>
        <p>"Lawrence does a fabulous job," the warden, Robert Ronne, said. "He has an excellent rapport with the inmates and he has their respect because he consistently and uniformly enforces the rules. In him, they see a man who came out of a tough neighborhood like most of them, and who exemplifies balance in his life as a family man, a good worker and a successful boxer. And because of his success as a fighter, he's given all of the staff members a huge boost in morale."</p>
        <p>Clay-Bey concedes that his success as a boxer has helped him in dealing with  the inmates. "Like many of them, I went through some tough times growing up in the North End of Hartford," said Clay-Bey, who has been on a leave of absence since early April to train for the Olympics. "I got involved with a gang for a while, but then I saw a lot of my friends get incarcerated and a few of them get killed. So I began to look for an alternate route in life and I found it by hanging out with my cousins and getting involved in sports."</p>
        <p>"Now, when I come back to Cheshire after a tournament, they view me as a celebrity-type person and they root for me when I fight. A lot of them grew up the same neighborhood as I did, and they can look at me and say, 'Look what he did. And how he gets a check for bing in here while we're doing is time.' "</p>
        <p>Clay-Bey's wife, Valerie, is as surprised as her husband at his success as a  boxer. "I know he had no intention of becoming a boxer; he just wanted to lose weight," said Mrs. Clay-Bey. "And I don't particularly like the idea because I think boxing is a brutal sport, and though I go to some of his fights, I can barely stand to watch. He's so laid back it's hard to believe this has happened."</p>
        <p>His mother, Marva Clay-Bey, also has qualms about her son being a boxer. "My  husband, James, who died two years ago, was a semipro fighter when we got married, but I told him I would only marry him if he quit boxing and he did, even though he won a New England championship," said Mrs. Clay-Bey who lives in  Hartford and has three other children. "It's a rough sport and I just hope Lawrence doesn't get hurt.</p>
        <p>Despite their misgivings about boxing, both Clay-Bey's wife and mother will be in Atlanta to watch him box in the Olympics. So, too, will other members of the family, although, as of now, Clay-Bey only has two tickets for the boxing program, which will go to his wife and mother.</p>
        <p>"For him, this is all a fun thing; he's not in it for the glory," Al Mitchell, his coach, said. "But we're certainly glad we have him because of his  maturity and leadership. All of the other boxers look up to him, and not just because he's bigger than they are."</p>
        <p>And Steve Ross of U.S.A. Boxing, added: "Lawrence is so nice that it's unreal. He's a real gentleman, and he's very good for our team because he settles everyone down. We're lucky and happy that he made the team."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
