<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexican Drug Dealer Pushes Speed, Helping Set Off an Epidemic in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="818540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHAMPHETAMINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMUGGLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COCAINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEROIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARIJUANA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DILLON, SAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AMEZCUA, JESUS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Methamphetamines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Methamphetamines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EED71539F934A15751C1A963958260" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexican Drug Dealer Pushes Speed, Helping Set Off an Epidemic in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DILLON, SAM</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Dec. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like hundreds of other brash young Mexican narcotics wholesalers working the  California market, Jesus Amezcua did well in cocaine, well enough to shuttle between Tijuana suppliers and his Los Angeles clients in a $50,000 BMW. Then in  1993 the Americans brought a Federal indictment against him.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Amezcua evaded arrest, and adopted a shrewd business strategy that American and Mexican officials say has carried him to the front ranks of Mexican traffickers. Retreating to safety south of the border, Mr. Amezcua shifted from  cocaine to a drug then surging in popularity across the American West, and now sweeping east: methamphetamine, or speed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like hundreds of other brash young Mexican narcotics wholesalers working the  California market, Jesus Amezcua did well in cocaine, well enough to shuttle between Tijuana suppliers and his Los Angeles clients in a $50,000 BMW. Then in  1993 the Americans brought a Federal indictment against him.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Amezcua evaded arrest, and adopted a shrewd business strategy that American and Mexican officials say has carried him to the front ranks of Mexican traffickers. Retreating to safety south of the border, Mr. Amezcua shifted from  cocaine to a drug then surging in popularity across the American West, and now sweeping east: methamphetamine, or speed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amezcua got into speed at just the right moment. As lawmakers in the United States were clamping down on the "precursor" chemicals used to make methamphetamine, he and his brothers started importing vast quantities of them to Mexico from the Middle East and Asia. He began cooking up methamphetamine in  laboratories throughout the Sierra Madre in Mexico and peddling it in the United States through his seasoned cocaine sales force.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Amezcua's business boomed, other traffickers imitated him. Elbowing aside the American motorcycle gangs who once dominated production and trafficking, the Mexican drug mafias have in recent years flooded the Western United States with methamphetamine.</p>
        <p>The result is a new drug epidemic, with cheap speed displacing crack in many  Western cities. The average price nationally for a gram of methamphetamine dropped by 20 percent over three years, to as low as $40 from $50.</p>
        <p>A wave of overdoses and grotesque methamphetamine-related violence has followed; in Arizona in July, for example, a speed freak hacked off his son's head with a hunting knife.</p>
        <p>"The Mexican traffickers who flooded the U.S. with marijuana and heroin in the 1970's and 1980's and cocaine in the 1990's threaten to overwhelm us with methamphetamine now," Thomas A. Constantine, administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, told Congress recently.</p>
        <p>Their complete control over methamphetamine production and trafficking has added to the power Mexican traffickers have accumulated in cocaine, marijuana and heroin commerce at a time when the Cali cocaine cartel in Colombia has been  badly disrupted. That has strengthened the view among American and Mexican anti-drug officials that power in the hemispheric drug trade is shifting from Colombia to Mexico.</p>
        <p>"We believe that the major drug gangs operating out of Mexico pose the largest threat currently," Mr. Constantine said.</p>
        <p>Methamphetamine, which engulfs those who snort or inject it with temporary energy and euphoria, has been in use in the United States since the mid-1960's, especially among college students. But now, with production soaring  in Mexican-run labs south and north of the border, abuse has spread widely as prices have plunged.</p>
        <p>On the streets of Western American cities, single doses of crack and methamphetamine are both about $5, law enforcement officials said, but while crack's intoxication lasts as little as 45 minutes, methamphetamine keeps pulsing for six or eight hours.</p>
        <p>"Methamphetamine has hit us like a wave in the last two years," said Richard  Canas, the D.E.A.'s agent-in-charge in Phoenix. "In the inner cities, that's all we're seeing. We're inundated with it."</p>
        <p>Although this year the Mexican police seized five tons of ephedrine, one of methamphetamine's main ingredients, commerce in precursor chemicals has not been specifically outlawed, allowing bathtub production of synthetic drugs to spread. But this month the Government offered its first major response when Attorney General Antonio Lozano sent the Mexican Congress a bill that would for the first time impose tough sentences -- up to 15 years imprisonment -- for those who traffic in precursors, including ephedrine and hydriodic acid and red phosphorous, two other ingreditents of methamphetamine. A Mexican official said the bill, if approved in its current form, would give the police an important tool, but lawmakers may water it down before voting on it next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amezcua's skill at orchestrating industrial shipments of ephedrine to Mexico helped spur his spectacular comeback after drug agents in 1993 arrested his chief lieutenants in a buy-and-bust sting in Chula Vista, Calif. The United  States prosecutors and agents who watched Mr. Amezcua then say they saw little about him to suggest that he would become a world-class trafficker -- except overweening ambition.</p>
        <p>"He was sassy and arrogant," said William V. Gallo, the assistant United States attorney in San Diego who helped indict Mr. Amezcua. "He had the BMW, the braggadocio, the gold jewelry. He was a young guy looking to come up in the drug world."</p>
        <p>Mr. Amezcua's brother Luis was also indicted in California in 1993, on murder charges, and the two brothers both moved back to Mexico and dropped from sight,  for a while. But they caught investigators' attention again a year later when customs officials seized two spectacular loads of ephedrine at the Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport. The first, 120 barrels ordered from Madras, India,  and routed to Mexico through Switzerland, drew suspicion because of its sheer size.</p>
        <p>While law enforcement officials were still investigating, about 80 more barrels of ephedrine arrived at the airport. D.E.A. officials found that Mr. Amezcua had arranged purchase of the second load in Pakistan, routing it to Guadalajara via the United Arab Emirates. The two loads, which together weighed  nearly six tons, set off alarms throughout law enforcement agencies; hundreds of tons of ephedrine were being shipped to Mexico from chemical companies all over  the world.</p>
        <p>"We've tied the Amezcuas with 170 metric tons of ephedrine that we've seized  or been able to issue stop orders so that the loads were never sent," Harold D.  Wankel, the D.E.A.'s operations chief, said in a phone interview from the agency's headquarters in Virginia. "They are out there acquiring huge quantities."</p>
        <p>The Amezcuas and other Mexican traffickers have imported ephedrine to Mexico  not only from Pakistan and India but also from Thailand, China, the Czech Republic and other European countries, Mr. Wankel said.</p>
        <p>Investigators say Mr. Amezcua and his relatives have set up bases in the border cities of Tijuana and Mexicali, in Guadalajara, and in the mountainous areas of the western states of Jalisco, Colima and Michoacan, where so many methamphetamine labs are operating that the police at highway checkpoints have several times in recent months arrested peasants transporting sacks of methamphetamine or barrels of ephedrine in pickup trucks as routinely as though  it were cattle feed.</p>
        <p>In one roadside bust in Michoacan in April, the police seized 700 pounds of ephedrine and arrested six men -- including Mr. Amezcua's cousin, Roberto Amezcua del Toro -- who led them to two nearby methamphetamine laboratories.</p>
        <p>Also last spring, drug-sniffing dogs in Las Cruces, N.M., began barking at a  truck, leading to a search by Border Patrol agents that yielded 693 pounds of methamphetamine, one of the largest seizures of speed on record in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wankel said his agency traced that load, too, to Mr. Amezcua. It was headed for distribution through a Mexican-controlled network that is expanding fast throughout the United States. Phil Jordan, director of the D.E.A.'s El Paso intelligence center, said one Mexican sales organization that started in California is now distributing the drug in 25 states, including New York and Florida.</p>
        <p>"The networking these Mexican traffickers have done in methamphetamine is incredible," Mr. Jordan said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
