<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day's Work in Georgia: Shevardnadze Dodges a Coup and Ends a War</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDEPENDENCE MOVEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GEORGIA (GEORGIAN REPUBLIC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA (RUSSIAN FEDERATION)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH OSSETIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AZERBAIJAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARMENIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NAGORNO-KARABAKH</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GAMSAKHURDIA, ZVIAD K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHEVARDNADZE, EDUARD A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Armenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Georgia (Georgian Republic)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Armenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D8153FF936A15755C0A964958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day's Work in Georgia: Shevardnadze Dodges a Coup and Ends a War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only hours after the leader of Georgia, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, survived an apparent coup attempt, he and President Boris N. Yeltsin signed an agreement today to end the fighting in the rebellious Georgian province of South Ossetia.</p>
        <p>Immediately after the signing, Mr. Yeltsin flew off to Turkey for a meeting in which ethnic fighting between Azerbaijanis and Armenians is expected to be the dominant issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only hours after the leader of Georgia, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, survived an apparent coup attempt, he and President Boris N. Yeltsin signed an agreement today to end the fighting in the rebellious Georgian province of South Ossetia.</p>
        <p>Immediately after the signing, Mr. Yeltsin flew off to Turkey for a meeting in which ethnic fighting between Azerbaijanis and Armenians is expected to be the dominant issue.</p>
        <p>Only on Tuesday, Mr. Yeltsin had met with President Leonid M. Kravchuk of Ukraine to quell some of the disputes that had set the two most powerful former Soviet republics increasingly at odds.</p>
        <p>The rapid-fire sequence of events amounted to a concerted campaign by Mr. Yeltsin and leaders of other former Soviet republics to quash various conflicts threatening to engulf other states, including Russia and Ukraine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shevardnadze's dramatic day underscored the instability of many of the newly independent republics, especially those in the Caucasus region. Meeting Unavoidably Delayed</p>
        <p>Mr. Shevardnadze, the former Soviet Foreign Minister, returned to his native Georgia early this year after the breakup of the Soviet Union and became chairman of Georgia's governing State Council in March. He was scheduled to meet with Mr. Yeltsin at the Black Sea resort of Sochi to seek ways of ending the bitter struggle in South Ossetia, a province in Georgia whose Ossetian majority is seeking to reunite with the Russian province of North Ossetia.</p>
        <p>But at about 3 this morning, more than 100 supporters of the deposed former President, Zviad K. Gamsakhurdia, whose exact whereabouts have been unknown since he was ousted in sharp fighting last January, seized the television and radio center in Tbilisi.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Gamsakhurdia's top lieutenants, Walter Shurgaya, went on the air at 6 A.M. and urged people to gather outside the television center and demand the return of the deposed president. Several hours later, troops loyal to Mr. Shevardnadze surrounded the rebels, and after a brief fight reoccupied the television center and took the pro-Gamsakhurdia forces captive. Officials reported four people were killed in the clash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gamsakhurdia has reportedly taken refuge in the nearby Chechen republic -- itself a Russian province that has declared independence -- since he was deposed. Ousted by a coalition of pro-democracy movements after his administration turned increasingly autocratic, he has refused to cede his claim to power as the only leader chosen in free elections. An Appeal to the Crowd</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Shevardnadze subsequently told reporters in Sochi that Mr. Shevardnadze himself was present when the television tower was retaken. When the fighting ended, they said, he turned to the crowd that had gathered and declared that the rebels had intended to block his meeting with Mr. Yeltsin. The crowd shouted back that he must go through with the meeting, the aides said.</p>
        <p>"The failure of the meeting was among the main aims of their subversive plan," Mr. Shevardnadze said in a subsequent statement. "But that plan was shortlived. Our determination to build a democratic and humane state, well ordered and highly organized, remains intact."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shevardnadze arrived in Sochi this afternoon, several hours later than planned. After meeting for about four hours with Mr. Yeltsin and the leaders of North and South Ossetia, he and Mr. Yeltsin announced an agreement to end the conflict.</p>
        <p>"We have signed an agreement on the principles of regulating the Georgian-Ossetian conflict, which includes everything, a cease-fire, mutual cooperation and so on," Mr. Yeltsin told reporters.</p>
        <p>He said a peacekeeping force was being formed to separate the warring sides along the South Ossetian border. No further details were announced.  Yeltsin Flies to Istanbul</p>
        <p>Immediately after the signing, Mr. Yeltsin left for Istanbul. Vice President Aleksandr Rutskoi stayed behind with Mr. Shevardnadze and the Ossetian leaders to draft a full statement on the accord.</p>
        <p>It was difficult to assess whether a cease-fire would last or would even take hold. The Ossetian conflict, like many other ethnic wars that have erupted with the collapse of the Soviet Union, has proved highly resistant to reason and mediation.</p>
        <p>Tskhinvali, the capital of South Ossetia, has been left in ruins, with more than 80 percent of its housing reportedly destroyed.</p>
        <p>The meeting in Turkey to which Mr. Yeltsin flew is officially portrayed as a conference on economic cooperation among countries of the Black Sea basin. The participants are Turkey, Russia, Ukraine, Greece, Romania, Georgia, Azerbaijan and Armenia.</p>
        <p>But the presence of President Levon Ter-Petrosyan of Armenia and Abulfaz Elchibei, the newly elected President of Azerbaijan, has raised expectations that the conference will provide a venue for multilateral peace talks on the oldest and most intractable of the post-Soviet ethnic conflicts. Previous efforts to bring the Armenian and Azerbaijani leaders together have failed.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Coup Called 'Final Attempt'</p>
        <p>TBILISI, Georgia, June 24 (Special to The New York Times) -- Prime Minister Tenguiz Sigua said today the brief seizure of the television station by forces loyal to the ousted former president represented the "final attempt" by the rebels to restore Mr. Gamsakhurdia to power.</p>
        <p>The failed coup was the strongest challenge yet to Mr. Shevardnadze. The Government said that two of the four people killed in fighting around the television station were members of the Georgian National Guard, and that 29 other people were wounded, including four civilians.</p>
        <p>Officials also reported that 29 National Guardsmen had been arrested for having joined the rebel side.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sigua said the attack would not derail plans to hold elections in Georgia on Oct. 11.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
