<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Congressman Sets the Pace on the Road to Hartford</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="709420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JUDSON, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROWLAND, JOHN G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4D81638F932A0575BC0A962958260" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Congressman Sets the Pace on the Road to Hartford</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JUDSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JUDSON, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>WESTPORT, Conn., Aug. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John G. Rowland has been traveling across Connecticut for months now, hammering away at the four issues that he says residents want their next governor to address: jobs, crime, education and welfare.</p>
        <p>His message is relentless. Mr. Rowland, a 37-year-old Republican who narrowly lost the 1990 election to Lowell P. Weicker Jr., is far and away the best-known candidate this time, and he wants very much to shape the race while he can.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John G. Rowland has been traveling across Connecticut for months now, hammering away at the four issues that he says residents want their next governor to address: jobs, crime, education and welfare.</p>
        <p>His message is relentless. Mr. Rowland, a 37-year-old Republican who narrowly lost the 1990 election to Lowell P. Weicker Jr., is far and away the best-known candidate this time, and he wants very much to shape the race while he can.</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, all the candidates want more jobs, less crime, better schools, fairer welfare. But Mr. Rowland has most bluntly addressed the state's fragile frame of mind after years of economic trauma in its homes and gang shootings in its cities.</p>
        <p>"The wrong people are afraid," he says. Working people fear for their jobs and their safety, he says, while criminals fear nothing. A Conservative Reputation</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland, who earned a reputation as Connecticut's most conservative Congressman while he represented the Fifth District, which includes Waterbury, from 1985 to 1991, has prescriptions. He says he would revitalize the state's economy by cutting state spending enough to allow the three-year-old personal income tax to be phased out.</p>
        <p>He would make prisons places to fear, rather than "Club Meds," and would require life sentences for felons convicted of two violent crimes. Welfare recipients would have to work or undergo job training. Parents would be allowed to choose their children's schools, while the schools and their teachers would be given the means to restore order to classrooms.</p>
        <p>The problems city schools face in educating poor children "may not have as much to do with adversity as it does with discipline," Mr. Rowland said at a campaign stop in this wealthy suburb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland, who is leading not only in the polls but also in fund-raising, with more than $1 million so far, is waging his campaign almost like an incumbent. When he schedules an event, it carries the weight of a fact-finding mission, as when he toured the East Side of Bridgeport with a police escort this month, or of an official call for action, as when he met with the Legislature's Public Safety Committee immediately after a prison riot in July. An Unusual Election</p>
        <p>Speaking before Republican town committees, Rotary clubs and other groups, he slips in just on time, or a few minutes late, so that he has everyone's attention the moment he arrives. But he rarely seems in a hurry. Outside a Super Stop &amp; Shop on the Post Road here, he finds few shoppers but many campaign volunteers, and he takes the time to shake hands and chat, making sure that everyone who showed up for him is noticed and thanked.</p>
        <p>On television, meanwhile, he has begun broadcasting his first ad, vowing to make "our neighborhoods and schools safe from violent crime."</p>
        <p>As the early front-runner, Mr. Rowland is finding his toughness and his demands for personal and governmental accountability turned back upon him by his opponents, who are many in this unusual election year. Both Democrats and Republicans have primaries, and even though Mr. Weicker is not running for re-election, his party, A Connecticut Party, is again making the general election a three-way contest.</p>
        <p>Suggesting that Mr. Rowland's high standing in the polls is left over from his exposure four years ago, the opponents say his insistence on sticking to the four issues is an attempt to hide his record.</p>
        <p>Secretary of the State Pauline R. Kezer, challenging Mr. Rowland in a Republican primary on Sept. 13, has attacked him as someone whose experience is as a legislator in Washington, not as an executive in Hartford, who after his defeat in 1990 parlayed his Capitol experience into highly paid consulting work for the state's largest military contractors as they laid off thousands of Connecticut workers. A Sense of Discontent</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland earned $392,406 in 1992 and $361,743 in 1993, including income from his family's insurance agency as well as from consulting for United Technologies, Electric Boat and other corporations.</p>
        <p>Other opponents are concerned that Mr. Rowland will succeed in tapping the discontent that has run through the state since the income tax, which has a top rate of 4.5 percent, was imposed in 1991 in the midst of a real-estate collapse and layoffs in Connecticut's defense, banking and insurance industries.</p>
        <p>"He gives an irresponsible expression to people's anger," said Roy Ochiogrosso, press secretary for State Comptroller William E. Curry Jr., who is facing State Senator John B. Larson in the Democratic primary. "He's very good at hitting the hot-button issues."</p>
        <p>Richard Slawsky, Mr. Rowland's press secretary, responded: "Sooner or later somebody decides that they're behind and what they have to do is attack the front-runner. Bill Curry's in a primary with John Larson, and what does he do? He challenges John Rowland to a debate."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland has said he will soon release a plan for phasing out the personal income tax, over five years.  Eliminating the tax would eliminate $2.6 billion a year, more than 40 percent of the state's tax revenue. Connecticut has an annual budget of about $9 billion. The Fear-of-Crime Rate</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kezer said she would reduce the income tax but that it cannot be eliminated without raising other taxes. Senator Larson has pledged a 25 percent income-tax cut for middle-income families, while Mr. Curry has called for the state to finance a billion-dollar cut in local property taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland's favorite talking point so far has been crime, and his favorite target has been the state's Prison Commissioner, Larry R. Meachum, whom he says coddles inmates with futile policies that try to rehabilitate criminals rather than punish them.</p>
        <p>"The prospect of going to prison in and of itself should be a deterrent," Mr. Rowland said in a detailed anti-crime package he released last week.  In it, he called for life in prison for career criminals, making all felons serve more time before parole and cutting prison costs by contracting with other states to take Connecticut inmates.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in the State Capitol, Mr. Rowland conceded what his charts and graphs omitted, that Connecticut's crime rate has been dropping since its peak in 1990, when crime was hardly mentioned in the gubernatorial campaign.</p>
        <p>A recent voter poll by Quinnipiac College, however, found that 84 percent of those surveyed believed that crime was increasing. Nearly as many said the court system and prisons were not treating criminals harshly enough. The survey of 602 registered voters was conducted from Aug. 8 to Aug. 16. It had a sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>"The sense of fear that people have in this state, especially in the cities, especially at night, is at an all-time high," Mr. Rowland said. "And that fear, regardless of what the stats show in the last year or two or whatever period of time we want to use, that fear has really hurt the quality of life."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
