<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Rush a Bad Crime Bill</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="638090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HABEAS CORPUS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIDEN, JOSEPH R JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D91E31F931A35753C1A965958260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Rush a Bad Crime Bill</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a dangerous section in the new crime bill being promoted by Senator Joseph Biden and the Clinton Administration. Its title calls it a "reform," but it would lock in court rulings that have watered down the laws under which state court prisoners get their cases reviewed by Federal courts. This section of the bill has to do with the body of law built around the concept of habeas corpus -- literally "you (might) have the body."</p>
        <p>When a prisoner secures a writ of habeas corpus from a Federal court, the state authorities must show that the prisoner received a fair trial and that they are therefore authorized to "have the body" in prison. This body of law has ancient roots. It was intended to curb the power of monarchs to keep citizens under arrest and in custody. Yet Mr. Biden sees no necessity for debate over the habeas corpus section of the crime bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a dangerous section in the new crime bill being promoted by Senator Joseph Biden and the Clinton Administration. Its title calls it a "reform," but it would lock in court rulings that have watered down the laws under which state court prisoners get their cases reviewed by Federal courts. This section of the bill has to do with the body of law built around the concept of habeas corpus -- literally "you (might) have the body."</p>
        <p>When a prisoner secures a writ of habeas corpus from a Federal court, the state authorities must show that the prisoner received a fair trial and that they are therefore authorized to "have the body" in prison. This body of law has ancient roots. It was intended to curb the power of monarchs to keep citizens under arrest and in custody. Yet Mr. Biden sees no necessity for debate over the habeas corpus section of the crime bill.</p>
        <p>Why? "The prosecutors," he says, "now support this." But it's hardly surprising that prosecutors like a bill that makes it easier to keep the prisoners they convict from appealing to the Federal courts. As chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee, Mr. Biden has a higher duty than making prosecutors happy. He has to protect the constitutional and civil rights of all citizens, including the poor, the powerless and the jailed.</p>
        <p>A society that limits the rights of such citizens will in time erode those of the more fortunate. Mr. Biden is lackadaisically cooperating in institutionalizing the limitations placed on valuable rights by the Supreme Court justices appointed by Presidents Reagan and Bush.</p>
        <p>For decades inmates of state prisons have filed appeals under the concept of habeas corpus. Often they have won Federal court review of their claims that their convictions were illegal or unconstitutional, even after the Supreme Court, which can hear only a tiny fraction of the cases that come before it, has refused to hear their cases on direct appeal.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court has been chipping away at this valuable form of Federal justice. In the guise of interpreting habeas corpus it has invented special technical rules blocking court access, especially for death row inmates. The Court has thrown out petitions because of lawyers' technical mistakes and rejected petitions on the often specious grounds that considering them would involve a "new rule" of constitutional law beyond anything decided in the inmate's original state case.</p>
        <p>Congress needs to tell the high court justices not to mangle the habeas corpus statute with their own contrivances. Instead, the Biden-Administration bill only tinkers, cutting off review if the case entails a "new standard" of constitutional law. But "new rule" and "new standard" mean the same thing. The Supreme Court would likely construe the change as a Congressional ratification of its rulings and a green light for more rulings like them.</p>
        <p>Chairman Biden is not only proud of this provision but asserts that the crime bill is ready for the Senate floor. Opponents must now make their case in the House, if its Judiciary Committee will hold hearings. Shabby lawmaking can only encourage Chief Justice William Rehnquist and the Court's current majority to continue to take liberties with the existing statute. If justice is to be done, the debate has only begun.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
