<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Errors in Timing: Start of Fall and of Spades</title>
    <meta content="22card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/22/crosswords/bridge/22card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1704024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alder, Phillip</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDF1730F931A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Errors in Timing: Start of Fall and of Spades</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Errors in Timing: Start of Fall and of Spades</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phillip Alder bridge column on deal played during Long Island Fall Regional bridge tournament; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Island Fall Regional took place last week in Smithtown. Yes, somebody should explain the seasons to the organizers, since fall does not officially start until 10:23 p.m. tonight. Maybe they expected an autumnal feel to the air, but that didn't happen either.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday was the Stratified Swiss Teams. Flight A was won by Simon Erlich and Glenn Milgrim of Forest Hills, Queens; and Jeff Rothstein and Chris Willenken of New York. Milgrim profited from a defensive error on the diagramed deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Stratified Swiss Teams, Flight A was won by Simon Erlich and Glenn Milgrim of Forest Hills, Queens; Milgrim profited from a defensive error on the diagramed deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Long Island Fall Regional took place last week in Smithtown. Yes, somebody should explain the seasons to the organizers, since fall does not officially start until 10:23 p.m. tonight. Maybe they expected an autumnal feel to the air, but that didn't happen either.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday was the Stratified Swiss Teams. Flight A was won by Simon Erlich and Glenn Milgrim of Forest Hills, Queens; and Jeff Rothstein and Chris Willenken of New York. Milgrim profited from a defensive error on the diagramed deal.</p>
        <p>If Milgrim had overcalled two hearts on the first round, it would have been an intermediate jump overcall, showing a good six-card suit and some 14-16 high-card points. So his actual sequence suggested a slightly better hand in playing-trick terms. (With more in high cards, he would have started with a takeout double.) Therefore North might have bid three no-trump, a contract that would have cruised home.</p>
        <p>Against four hearts, West led the higher of his two diamonds. Declarer hoped to take seven hearts, one diamond and two clubs, but that would presumably require taking two club finesses and he had only one dummy entry -- gnash.</p>
        <p>South took the first trick with dummy's diamond ace and immediately played a club to his jack. West, after winning with the queen, could have defeated the contract by shifting to a spade, but he was not sure who held the spade ace, so he continued ''safely'' with a second diamond. South ruffed in his hand and started to run all his hearts, producing this end position:</p>
        <p>On the final trump, the diamond queen was thrown from the dummy, but what could East discard?</p>
        <p>If he throws the spade jack, South plays a spade to East's ace and pitches a spade on the diamond king, getting East to lead away from his club holding at Trick 12 and giving declarer the 10 tricks listed earlier.</p>
        <p>If East jettisons the spade ace, declarer merely plays a spade toward the queen.</p>
        <p>So East released the diamond king. But now a spade to East's jack caught him in the same Trick 12 club endplay.</p>
        <p>Instead of finding an extra dummy entry, South used East to take the second club finesse.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
