<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mother Learns Some Vital Lessons About Caring</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="60" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="FOR GIVERS AND RECEIVERS, CHANGING LIVE WITH NEEDIEST FUND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK TIMES NEEDIEST CASES FUND</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARDSON, LYNDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DF1538F935A35751C1A964958260" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mother Learns Some Vital Lessons About Caring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICHARDSON, LYNDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Angela P. struck her 2-year-old son so hard that he fell against the wall, she knew it was time to get help. She did not know why she hated her child so much, she said, only that her anger had flared even more with her own mother's recent death.</p>
        <p>Angela said that even the slightest irritation prompted her rage, like the time her son's voice rose in a sing-song whine or when he playfully dismantled furniture in their cramped apartment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Angela P. struck her 2-year-old son so hard that he fell against the wall, she knew it was time to get help. She did not know why she hated her child so much, she said, only that her anger had flared even more with her own mother's recent death.</p>
        <p>Angela said that even the slightest irritation prompted her rage, like the time her son's voice rose in a sing-song whine or when he playfully dismantled furniture in their cramped apartment.</p>
        <p>The 24-year-old mother did not understand why her son and 20-month-old daughter needed so much nurturing. When she was a little girl, often no one was there for her.</p>
        <p>Angela sought help and found hope at the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service, one of the seven charities aided by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund. With counseling, she is now using lessons from a painful past to make a bright future for her children.</p>
        <p>Angela seemed 24 going on 50 when she showed up at the bureau's East New York Family Center a year ago, said her social worker, Lisandra Ramirez.</p>
        <p>"It was like a heaviness hung over her," Ms. Ramirez said. "She felt like her life was over. She was at the end of the rope." Conflicting Feelings</p>
        <p>Angela felt frightened at her feelings toward her children, overwhelmed by motherhood and pained by conflicting feelings about her childhood of abandonment. "She wasn't able to have patience with her kids because nobody was there for her when she was little," Ms. Ramirez said. "It's painful for her. She can't quite connect what she didn't have when she was little. Angela wanted her kids to be independent but also to need her."</p>
        <p>Once a week, Angela now comes to the Brooklyn bureau's family center to talk to Ms. Ramirez, who coaches her on being a parent. "She helps me clear my mind when I'm bothered," Angela said approvingly. Her two children are enrolled in day care. She is enrolled as a freshman at Long Island University and is gaining self-esteem.</p>
        <p>The shadow of Angela's mother still looms large. Angela said she chose respiratory therapy as her major because she was curious about the mysterious tubes and machines that briefly kept her mother alive.</p>
        <p>After her mother's death, it was five months before Angela was able to shed a tear or talk about what life was like with her.</p>
        <p>She told her social worker that she had felt that her mother would come back somehow, that she simply had taken off again for another trip without her.</p>
        <p>That feeling stemmed from growing up with a single mother who often deserted her children for great lengths of time. Angela said that it was not out of the ordinary for her and her little sisters to be left alone for weeks.</p>
        <p>She said she thought her mother had instilled in her "a sense of responsibility and a sense of independence at a very young age."</p>
        <p>While her mother was away, she said, a relative or neighbor would occasionally check on them. "It was no big deal," she said with a shrug of her shoulders.</p>
        <p>She said her mother would visit relatives in Panama and Costa Rica in trips that sometimes would coincide with the carnival season there. One time, Angela said, her mother left the children alone for eight months.</p>
        <p>And another time, an uncle who considered himself a "father figure" sold all of their belongings and rented out their apartment, she said. The uncle shipped the children off to a grandmother in Baltimore for "a summer vacation" that lasted a year.</p>
        <p>Angela said she had not considered her childhood one of neglect. When her mother was around, Angela said, she was a stern disciplinarian who was quick with a belt or a stick.</p>
        <p>Like her mother, Angela is raising her children single-handedly. But she is determined to do a better job. With help from Ms. Ramirez, she is learning to be patient. She also is feeling some of the quiet joys of motherhood, like the times her son struggles to read to her from a Walt Disney book.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn bureau helped Angela to move her family out of a small apartment that she shared with one sister. She now lives in a two-bedroom apartment in the Starrett City housing complex in Brooklyn. The children's room has stuffed animals for her daughter and toy trucks and cars for her son.</p>
        <p>"I had a little bumpy road, but I'm trying to get myself back in order," she said. "It's coming true for me, slowly and surely."  FOR GIVERS AND RECEIVERS, CHANGING LIVE WITH NEEDIEST FUND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
