<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;Buffett's new shares probably won't deter the copycats.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19960514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BERKSHIRE HATHAWAY INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABELSON, REED WARREN E BUFFETT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DE1E39F93BA35756C0A960958260" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;Buffett's new shares probably won't deter the copycats.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Reed Abelson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ABELSON, REED WARREN E BUFFETT;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE mania surrounding the legendary investor Warren E. Buffett and his company, Berkshire Hathaway Inc., has spawned its own growth industry.</p>
        <p>Because a single share of Berkshire Hathaway stock is now $34,900, making it  the most expensive stock in the world, creative financiers have devised numerous ways to capitalize on the inability of most small investors to buy the  shares. They have written books explaining Mr. Buffett's investment style, created a mutual fund claiming to be modeled after that style and developed investment unit trusts that allow smaller investors to buy a piece of Mr. Buffett's action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE mania surrounding the legendary investor Warren E. Buffett and his company, Berkshire Hathaway Inc., has spawned its own growth industry.</p>
        <p>Because a single share of Berkshire Hathaway stock is now $34,900, making it  the most expensive stock in the world, creative financiers have devised numerous ways to capitalize on the inability of most small investors to buy the  shares. They have written books explaining Mr. Buffett's investment style, created a mutual fund claiming to be modeled after that style and developed investment unit trusts that allow smaller investors to buy a piece of Mr. Buffett's action.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Buffett has never been one to spurn growth. In fact, the offering this week of what might be called Berkshire junior shares -- shares equal to one-thirtieth the value of the existing stock -- seems to be an effort to take advantage of this exploitation as well as to discourage it.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Buffett himself says he would not buy the Berkshire junior stock, the company will, of course, end up pocketing the proceeds, which are estimated  to be a not-too-shabby $400 million or so. And no one can fault the company and  its underwriters for not doing their very best to make sure that everybody who wants the shares can get them. They are expected to be priced at the end of today at around $1,200 each.</p>
        <p>To that end, Mr. Buffett and the company's underwriter, Salomon Brothers, have lined up an impressive array of investment bankers, which is remarkable only for the few firms it may exclude. Among the dozens of bankers involved are Goldman, Sachs, Janney Montgomery Scott, Merrill Lynch and Morgan Stanley. Even discount brokerage firms like Fidelity and Charles Schwab, which typically  do not participate in equity offerings, have joined in. It is the first time Fidelity has been involved in a stock underwriting, and one of the rare times for Schwab.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett has made it abundantly clear, whenever he can, writing in the annual report and prospectus or talking to shareholders, that he will not be a buyer of the shares at current prices. The company, which has more than $1 billion in cash and short-term government securities, does not need to raise the capital and has indicated that it has no immediate plans to spend the money.</p>
        <p>Whether that will effectively stop small investors from rushing to buy the shares is another matter, of course. Robert Stovall, the president of Stovall/21st Advisors, said he thought investors would just want to own the shares, just as they longed to belong to an exclusive country club.</p>
        <p>So why did Mr. Buffett and the company's shareholders vote on Monday in favor of the offering? To discourage the development of investment unit vehicles that  buy its stocks or stocks that the company owns as way of offering small investors a chance to participate in the company's historic gains, which have been an astonishing 28 percent a year for the last decade. "Berkshire intends to provide a direct, low-cost means of investment in Berkshire so superior to the investments offered by the unit trust promoters that their products will be rendered unmarketable," the prospectus said.</p>
        <p>But the competition may be hard to kill. By offering the shares valued at one-thirtieth of the stock and therefore presumably well over $1,000 each, Mr. Buffett seems to have failed to offer investors the very lowest-priced way of investing in Berkshire Hathaway.</p>
        <p>Nike Securities, which has already raised $60 million in its Market Leaders Growth Trust that mirrors Mr. Buffett's investments, requires a minimum investment of $1,000. But investors can buy as little as $250 in units for their retirement accounts. And Sam Katz, the managing partner of Five Sigma Investment Partners in Bala-Cynwyd, Pa., plans to allow investors a $500 minimum in his proposed Berkshire lookalike. "A lot of people can't afford the price of a $1,000 stock," he said.</p>
        <p>Investors have to pay hefty sales charges for the Market Leaders Growth Trust, which amount to 4.5 percent by the end of the first year. Mr. Katz plans  to set a sales charge of 2.75 percent. While that's more than the $10 investors may pay in commissions for the new Berkshire junior share, the new class offers them less in the way of voting and conversion rights.</p>
        <p>Even if Mr. Buffett's aim is to save small investors from these promoters, that does not make his new class of shares a buy. Their biggest selling point may be only that their commission is lower and there is a stock certificate with Berkshire Hathaway's name on it.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 14, 1996, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Market Place column in Business Day on Wednesday, about an offering of junior shares of Berkshire Hathaway, referred incorrectly to a payment of $10 for each share. It represented a concession paid to the selling group by Berkshire Hathaway; it was not a commission paid by investors when they bought shares through the offering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 14, 1996, Tuesday&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;    The Market Place column in Business Day on Wednesday, about an offering of junior shares of Berkshire Hathaway, referred incorrectly to a payment of $10 for each share. It represented a concession paid to the selling group by Berkshire Hathaway; it was not a commission paid by investors when they bought shares through the offering.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
