<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Samaranch Says China Is Losing Votes for 2008</title>
    <meta content="15SWIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2008)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Samaranch, Juan Antonio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3DB1E39F936A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Samaranch Says China Is Losing Votes for 2008</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International Olympic Committee president Juan Antonio Samaranch says that China, in wake of second doping scandal at world swimming championships, has jeopardized its chances should it decide to bid on 2008 Summer Olympic Games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wake of a second doping scandal at the world swimming championships, China has jeopardized its chances should it decide to bid on the 2008 Summer Games, the president of the International Olympic Committee said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Four Chinese swimmers were suspended yesterday for testing positive for the banned diuretic triamterene at the world championships in Perth, Australia. Diuretics are considered masking agents for performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the wake of a second doping scandal at the world swimming championships, China has jeopardized its chances should it decide to bid on the 2008 Summer Games, the president of the International Olympic Committee said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Four Chinese swimmers were suspended yesterday for testing positive for the banned diuretic triamterene at the world championships in Perth, Australia. Diuretics are considered masking agents for performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>If Chinese officials bid on the 2008 Games, ''they will maybe be in trouble,'' Juan Antonio Samaranch, president of the I.O.C., told a group of reporters in New York yesterday. In the past, Samaranch has said that he believed China's efforts to control drug use were genuine and that he believed Chinese athletes to be clean. He made no such comments yesterday. ''It is clear that after the news we got this morning, if China is today a candidate to organize the Olympic Games, many I.O.C. members will not be in favor,'' Samaranch said.</p>
        <p>China has not yet said whether it will bid on the 2008 Summer Games, which will be awarded in 2001. Athens has been awarded the 2004 Summer Olympics. Many believed that a Chinese bid for 2008 would become the favorite. But it is clear after repeated swimming scandals that the I.O.C.'s current mood is not favorable to Beijing, which lost to Sydney, Australia, as the host city for the 2000 Summer Games.</p>
        <p>Don Talbot, the Australian national swim coach, called for all Chinese swimmers to be banned from further competition at the current world championship. However, the I.O.C.'s top medical official said that banning an entire team or country would unfairly harm innocent athletes.</p>
        <p>Yesterday in Perth, it was announced that three female swimmers, Wang Luna, Cai Huijue and Zhang Yi, and one male swimmer, Wang Wei, had tested positive for triamterene on Jan. 8 during an unannounced pre-competition drug test. The four have been suspended pending a review of their urine samples.</p>
        <p>Jon Urbancek, an American coach, told The Associated Press that members of the Chinese team had refused a drug test on Jan. 7, but submitted a day later upon the demand of FINA, swimming's world governing body.</p>
        <p>''During the night, they'd obviously given these kids a masking agent,'' Urbancek told A.P.</p>
        <p>The Agence France-Presse news agency reported that all four suspended swimmers were from the same club in Shanghai. It was in Shanghai at the Chinese National Games last October that female swimmers set two world records and recorded the best times of 1997 in 8 of 13 individual events.</p>
        <p>Bans from all international competition, including the Olympics, were also announced yesterday against the Chinese swimmer Yuan Yuan and her coach, Zhou Zhewen, who were caught bringing 13 vials of human growth hormone into Australia before the swim championships began. Yuan received a four-year ban while her coach faces a 15-year ban. Human growth hormone, or H.G.H., is banned as a performance-enhancing drug, but the I.O.C. does not yet have a reliable test to detect its use. A Danish pharmaceutical group said yesterday that it produced the growth hormone Yuan and Zhou tried to take into the competition, and that the drugs had been sold to a state-owned import company in China for use in hospitals, A.P. reported.</p>
        <p>Suspicions about Chinese swimmers grew after Chinese women won 12 of 16 gold medals at the 1994 world swimming championships in Rome. Two months later, seven Chinese swimmers, including two world champions, tested positive for a muscle-building steroid.</p>
        <p>Approximately two dozen Chinese swimmers have now tested positive for banned substances since 1990, prompting widespread belief among other swimming powers of systematic drug use. Chinese officials have denied the accusations.</p>
        <p>Talbot, the Australian coach, said yesterday that Chinese officials who said that drug use was not widespread were ''bloody liars.'' In calling for expulsion of Chinese swimmers from the world championships, he said, ''They deny it when they are accused of it, and when they have the evidence in their face, they still deny it.''</p>
        <p>Prince Alexandre de Merode of Belgium, the I.O.C.'s chief medical officer, said yesterday in New York that, in general, ''exclusion is not a solution.'' To exclude a nation or a team from an event is a delicate issue he said, because ''who suffers are the other athletes, the innocent.''</p>
        <p>Anita DeFrantz of the United States, the first woman elected as vice president of the I.O.C., also said she did not believe it was fair to suspend the entire Chinese team. It is difficult controlling drug use by athletes in a country with five times the population of the United States, she said. DeFrantz added that she believed only 10 percent of all athletes in Olympic-related sports use performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>Samaranch congratulated FINA for its drug-testing program. Olympic-type drug testing, with its random, unannounced testing procedures, is far more ambitious than the methods used by professional sports leagues in the United States.</p>
        <p>''They are doing what they have to do,'' Samaranch said of FINA officials. ''If all sports organizations in the world acted as FINA does, maybe this problem of doping can disappear.''</p>
        <p>SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
