<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Diva Returns In a Storm Of Gospel And Glitz</title>
    <meta content="15LABE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labelle, Patti</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D81139F936A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Diva Returns In a Storm Of Gospel And Glitz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews concert by Patti LaBelle at St James Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commotion started before the crowd had even settled in for Patti LaBelle's performance at the St. James Theater on Tuesday. People strained to see, then burst into applause as the Rev. Al Sharpton proceeded to his third-row seat. The crowd went wilder still when the songwriters and performers Nick Ashford and Valerie Simpson took their places near Mr. Sharpton.</p>
        <p>Only then did the evening's true star appear, behind a scrim, singing the inspirational schlock classic ''I Believe.'' The scrim rose and Ms. LaBelle let forth a signature glass-shattering high note. Fans raised their arms in exaltation. Patti LaBelle's return to Broadway was an event before it began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The commotion started before the crowd had even settled in for Patti LaBelle's performance at the St. James Theater on Tuesday. People strained to see, then burst into applause as the Rev. Al Sharpton proceeded to his third-row seat. The crowd went wilder still when the songwriters and performers Nick Ashford and Valerie Simpson took their places near Mr. Sharpton.</p>
        <p>Only then did the evening's true star appear, behind a scrim, singing the inspirational schlock classic ''I Believe.'' The scrim rose and Ms. LaBelle let forth a signature glass-shattering high note. Fans raised their arms in exaltation. Patti LaBelle's return to Broadway was an event before it began.</p>
        <p>Ms. LaBelle, like the luminaries in her audience, is admired as a true representative of African-American taste and culture. During her many transformations, from girl-group singer to disco queen (when she drew a large gay audience) to mellow balladeer, she has melded the fervor of gospel, campy theatrics and slick sentimentalism to attract both soul music traditionalists and lovers of dramatic pop.</p>
        <p>Surrounded by lavish good-luck bouquets, sipping from a wineglass perched on a grand piano and admiring herself in a hand mirror, Ms. LaBelle exuded the noblesse oblige of a legendary diva still earning Grammy nominations after 30 years in show business. She simultaneously reveled in earthiness. ''I'm not holding my stomach in any longer,'' she declared, shimmying in a tantalizing red minidress. ''Thin ain't in!''</p>
        <p>A youthful fan threw a small bottle of Tabasco sauce onstage and begged her for a five-minute meeting. She agreed. ''I couldn't resist,'' she smirked. Later, three more men were invited up -- one a towering drag queen in an outfit seemingly designed by Halston for Martian resort wear. He did a can-can. ''Tomorrow I'll wear my short dress,'' remarked Ms. LaBelle, then clad in a gold brocade gown. ''I've got to compete with boyfriend!''</p>
        <p>Where did music fit into this extravagant tribute to Ms. LaBelle's flamboyant self? It flowed like a river beneath the glitz, sometimes trickling out, at other times flooding over. Ms. LaBelle's able-bodied band, directed by James (Budd) Ellison and featuring the vocal interplay of Charles Buie, John Stanley and Anthony Williams, built a solid bed of grooves over which Ms. LaBelle improvised in the gospel tradition.</p>
        <p>She made medleys of songs from throughout her long career and offered versions of hits by other artists  including Aretha Franklin and Eric Clapton, and her much requested take on ''Somewhere Over the Rainbow.''</p>
        <p>After a final cluster of high notes, Ms. LaBelle exited with the Tabasco bottle tucked into her bodice. The young man was waiting. She surely would give him some some useful tips on making his soul glitter.  POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
