<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Monday Night Testosterone</title>
    <meta content="15THU3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fox Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Espn (Cable TV Network)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DD1E39F936A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Monday Night Testosterone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial questions decisions by ABC, CBS, Fox and ESPN to pay $18 billion over eight years for right to televise National Football League games; cites view of television and advertising executives that football is television's only reliable mechanism for attracting younger male viewers (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The numbers are certainly astonishing, but the first word that pops to mind is not ''Wow!'' but ''Why?'' Four networks -- ABC, CBS, Fox and ESPN -- have agreed to pay the National Football League $18 billion over eight years, about double the current price, for the right to televise professional football. That works out to something like $35 million per game, including the playoffs.</p>
        <p>As in football, there were winners and losers. CBS, which sat morosely on the sidelines for four years, outbid NBC for the rights to broadcast games played by the N.F.L.'s American Conference. NBC then challenged ABC for the Monday night games and lost. NBC will now ride the bench. Even so, its avid pursuit of the Monday night franchise suggested that, like the other networks, it regards football as an investment of talismanic importance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The numbers are certainly astonishing, but the first word that pops to mind is not ''Wow!'' but ''Why?'' Four networks -- ABC, CBS, Fox and ESPN -- have agreed to pay the National Football League $18 billion over eight years, about double the current price, for the right to televise professional football. That works out to something like $35 million per game, including the playoffs.</p>
        <p>As in football, there were winners and losers. CBS, which sat morosely on the sidelines for four years, outbid NBC for the rights to broadcast games played by the N.F.L.'s American Conference. NBC then challenged ABC for the Monday night games and lost. NBC will now ride the bench. Even so, its avid pursuit of the Monday night franchise suggested that, like the other networks, it regards football as an investment of talismanic importance.</p>
        <p>The answer to why they feel that way cannot lie in the ratings. ABC's popular Monday night game has actually shown a slight decline since the 1980's. The real answers seem to have more to do with horseback guesses about demographics and with  pride, tradition and morale. Don Hewitt, the producer of ''60 Minutes,'' the CBS show that was often delayed by football games in the days when CBS televised football games, put the matter succinctly: ''I think it's like restoring a piece of the CBS logo.''</p>
        <p>That sounds almost like a matter of manhood, and to hear other CBS people tell it, the network's decision to return to football, whatever the cost, had plenty to do with manhood, or at least men. Our favorite quote on this score came from Michael Jordan, the chairman of CBS: ''The CBS brand skews older, and therefore our revenue per eyeballs is somewhat less than our competition.''</p>
        <p>Somewhere in that mediaspeak lies a core belief shared by TV executives and advertisers alike -- football is television's only reliable mechanism for attracting a large, steady audience of younger male viewers. Furthermore, according to media analysts, a network that loses its men on Sundays cannot get them to watch other programs during the rest of the week, which means that it winds up with an audience of older women who spend less.</p>
        <p>That does not sound completely logical. But that is what the networks believe and that is why, when all is said and done, they bid so high.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
