<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Veneration Gap: Stones and Spice an Odd Mix</title>
    <meta content="15FANS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Madison Square Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Spice Girls (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Planet Hollywood</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rolling Stones (Rock Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DE1F39F936A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Veneration Gap: Stones and Spice an Odd Mix</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scenes outside Planet Hollywood restaurant in midtown Manhattan where music group Spice Girls was attending private screening and outside Madison Square Garden where Rolling Stones were performing in concert; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lana Donnelly was happy last night. Brenna Senno was not.</p>
        <p>Lana, 10, persuaded her mother, Linda, 43, to drive from Valley Stream on Long Island to Manhattan and stand behind police barricades at Planet Hollywood for hours with a thousand other screaming, prepubescent strangers to await the arrival of the Spice Girls, the British singing sensation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lana Donnelly was happy last night. Brenna Senno was not.</p>
        <p>Lana, 10, persuaded her mother, Linda, 43, to drive from Valley Stream on Long Island to Manhattan and stand behind police barricades at Planet Hollywood for hours with a thousand other screaming, prepubescent strangers to await the arrival of the Spice Girls, the British singing sensation.</p>
        <p>''I love them! They're the best!'' Lana blurted, to the bemused grin of Mrs. Donnelly.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Donnelly would have been envious of Denese Senno, 37, mother of 11-year-old Brenna. Like Mrs. Donnelly, Ms. Senno is a rabid Rolling Stones fan. But unlike Mrs. Donnelly, Ms. Senno coerced her children, Brenna -- a huge Spice Girls fan -- and Joseph, 13, to travel from New Rochelle, N.Y., to see the Rolling Stones perform at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''It's like going to a Broadway play or some other cultural experience,'' Ms. Senno said. ''It's something that I think they can appreciate when they grow up.''</p>
        <p>In terms of musical styles, the Spice Girls -- five young, provocatively dressed pop singers -- and the Rolling Stones -- four not-that-young men who are rock 'n' roll's equivalent of Been There, Done That -- could not be further apart.</p>
        <p>And yet, that the two were in New York last night was, in some minds, an odd coincidence and an occasion for rumination. In a way, the hysteria surrounding Planet Hollywood at West 57th Street was no different from the hysteria that surrounded groups like the Rolling Stones and the Beatles when they first arrived in America. But this time, the people who had screamed in the 1960's were watching their children scream.</p>
        <p>''Being a groupie in the 1960's, I understand the commotion,'' said Betsy Pfeffer, 40, of Riverdale, who had daughters Jillian, 11, and Allison, 9, in tow, primed for a Spice Girls sighting. ''When I was their age, it was the Monkees and the Beatles.''</p>
        <p>Officially, the Spice Girls were in town to attend a celebrities-only screening of their coming movie, ''Spiceworld.'' But the event had been hyped as a British invasion of the female variety and a chance for the group's mostly young, female fans to practice idolatry.</p>
        <p>They came in droves -- about 1,000 by the police's count and 6,000 by the promoter's ticker -- to wait in 32-degree weather for the event, which was scheduled to begin at 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>''If I can get an autograph, I'll die happy!'' yelled Melanie Ann Diaz, 14, of the Bronx, waiting since 2:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>''Me, too!'' said Delia McNicholas, 10, of Brooklyn. ''Tomorrow, I'm going to have laryngitis, and I don't care!''</p>
        <p>It was a raucous scene, as the police tried to keep order and fans jaywalked to gain better vantage points across the street. Traffic snarled to one lane in each direction. Promoters played the Spice Girl's huge hit, ''Wannabe,'' over and over. At 6:45 P.M., the stars arrived, atop a double-decker bus.</p>
        <p>Instant cameras exploded like a mirror ball at a discotheque. Pandemonium.</p>
        <p>About 10 minutes later, after the Spice Girls mounted a stage in front of the restaurant and said, ''We love New York,'' it was over.</p>
        <p>Twenty-four blocks away at Madison Square Garden, traffic was no worse than usual. There were no screams of glee, only the drone of vendors yelling, ''Programs here,'' the whispers of scalpers saying, ''Tickets?'' and the smell of marijuana.</p>
        <p>The crowd was diverse in age and background. Pat Malicher of New Providence, N.J., last attended a Stones concert in 1970, when she was 19. This time, she shepherded her daughter, Jennifer, 18, to her maiden Stones concert. Jennifer was excited. And there was no way -- just no way -- she would have gone to the Spice Girls extravaganza. ''I think they're poseurs,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Other fans offered responses akin to a veteran ballplayer paying a backhanded compliment to a rookie.</p>
        <p>''I remember being totally insane about the Beatles,'' said Martha Weinroth, 47, of Wilton, Conn. ''I can understand being idiotic about these things. But there's an amazing transformation that adolescent girls go through.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
