<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Look for the Spark That Led to the Shootings</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="655120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="DEATH ON THE L.I.R.R."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOOTINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOOTINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GARDEN CITY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND RAIL ROAD CO (LIRR)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND RAIL ROAD CO (LIRR)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RABINOWITZ, JONATHAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERGUSON, COLIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RABINOWITZ, JONATHAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERGUSON, COLIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND RAIL ROAD CO (LIRR) 
LONG ISLAND RAIL ROAD CO</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA1F31F933A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Look for the Spark That Led to the Shootings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN RABINOVITZ,</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, L.I., Dec. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after an angry gunman opened fire on a crowded railroad car, investigators are still looking into the question that continues to trouble almost everyone: why the suspect, Colin Ferguson, after years of simmering rage, apparently decided to vent his wrath on the 5:33 train to Hicksville.</p>
        <p>"He had the gun in possession since April of this year, and we don't know what triggered this," said Mel Kenny, assistant chief of detectives of the Nassau Police. "We would like to know why, and are trying to adequately cover what prompted this behavior -- if there were any particular or cumulative events in recent weeks that might have pushed him over the edge."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days after an angry gunman opened fire on a crowded railroad car, investigators are still looking into the question that continues to trouble almost everyone: why the suspect, Colin Ferguson, after years of simmering rage, apparently decided to vent his wrath on the 5:33 train to Hicksville.</p>
        <p>"He had the gun in possession since April of this year, and we don't know what triggered this," said Mel Kenny, assistant chief of detectives of the Nassau Police. "We would like to know why, and are trying to adequately cover what prompted this behavior -- if there were any particular or cumulative events in recent weeks that might have pushed him over the edge."</p>
        <p>Referring to the shooting that left 5 dead and 20 wounded as a "planned execution," Chief Kenny stressed that the crime had to be placed against the background of Mr. Ferguson's skewed world view. "He had a number of problems in his life, and every problem he was involved in he attached some racial motivation to the person and institution he was dealing with, regardless of their race. It does not translate into black and white racism." A History of Troubles</p>
        <p>As the investigation continued, more information about Mr. Ferguson's past continued to filter out, from his apparently troubled marriage, to his difficulties as a student and employee, to his continuing battle with the workers' compensation agency. And the case began to be transformed into a political lightning rod that has become the latest focal point for continuing debates about race, the death penalty and gun control.</p>
        <p>The police today interviewed Mr. Ferguson's former wife, Audrey M. Warren, who they said lives in Nassau County. According to Richard Fiero, chief of detectives, Mr. Ferguson married her in Queens on May 13, 1986, and they were divorced in Nassau on May 18, 1988. He declined to further comment on why the marriage ended, and would not discuss the interview with the woman, other than to say that it "assisted the investigation."</p>
        <p>Ms. Warren asked the police to refer all inquiries about her to Christoper W. Critelli, a lawyer in Garden City who has a general practice with a specialty in family law. This afternoon, Mr. Critelli refused to answer any questions, saying he had not yet been retained by Mr. Ferguson's former wife and that reporters should call on Friday. Focus on Compensation Board</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferguson's frustration with the Workers' Compensation Board was one area of inquiry.</p>
        <p>The Workers' Compensation Board issued a chronology of Mr. Ferguson's contacts with the agency. The agency approved a settlement of $26,250 in September 1992 for injuries to his head, back and neck suffered on the job at Ademco Security Group several years earlier. This year, Mr. Ferguson apparently asked for the case to be reopened because he believed he needed more money and needed assistance to receive more medical treatment.</p>
        <p>A law-enforcement official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said today that Mr. Ferguson had talked with agency officials the day of the shooting, but he added that this was not unusual. "He often called them three times a day and made threats," the official said.</p>
        <p>Barbara Patton, the chairman of the State Workers' Compensation Board, often rode the train where the shootings occurred. But the police, however, were skeptical about any link to her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Patton has said that she knew of no confrontation between Mr. Ferguson and an agency employee on Monday. And as a resident of Garden City, she saw an eerie coincidence in the shooting taking place as the train pulled into a station in that village. "I could have easily been on that train," she said. "I can't tell you the number of times my husband has picked me up at that stop."</p>
        <p>Chief Kenny said the police did not believe Ms. Patton was Mr. Ferguson's target, and he added that there was no reason to believe that he knew Ms. Patton's commuting habits or even her name and position.</p>
        <p>Colin Moore, a Brooklyn lawyer, recalled today that Mr. Ferguson contacted him in 1991 after Mr. Ferguson was expelled from Adelphi University, saying he thought it was because of racism. Mr. Moore described his client as a neatly dressed man who was lucid and articulate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore, who first provided his account in an article in Newsday today, said Mr. Ferguson called again four months ago and said he had seen Mr. Moore in a Brooklyn courthouse, laughing with other lawyers about Mr. Ferguson's case. Mr. Moore tried to tell him that it was untrue, that he had not been discussing that case, but he said he realized then that his client had a serious problem.</p>
        <p>While the police investigation produced no substantial new insights about Mr. Ferguson's motives today, the shooting ignited contentious exchanges among elected officials, civil rights leaders, and railway workers and management.</p>
        <p>Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato this morning issued a statement calling it a "damn shame that New York State does not have the death penalty because that is the only fitting punishment for this cold-blooded killer." In turn, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo said, "The death penalty has nothing to do with madness," and countered that the only solution is "to get rid of the guns."  Jackson Plans Visit</p>
        <p>Later in the day, several prominent black leaders, including the Rev. Al Sharpton and the Rev. Herbert W. Daughtry, held a news conference on the steps of City Hall, urging that blacks in general not be blamed for the crime. "We want to make it unequivocally clear that there is no one, particularly in any movement where I've been involved, with any way to justify or uphold what happened on the Long Island Rail Road," Mr. Sharpton said. "The people in the media who attempted to demonize black and Hispanic dissatisfaction by saying this man was inspired or condoned by us when he did a very sick and perverted act is unfair."</p>
        <p>Also, the Episcopal Diocese of Long Island announced today that the Rev. Jesse Jackson will preach at the cathedral in Garden City on Sunday in response to the shootings.</p>
        <p>At another news conference, Stuart Sanveriro, president of the Long Island Rail Road Police Benevolent Association, called the trains "unsafe" and said the railroad needed to triple the size of its 216-person police force. Railroad officials responded that the rate of crime against passengers had dropped over the last few years.</p>
        <p>DEATH ON THE L.I.R.R.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
