<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater; A Surprising Third Act in an Actress's Career</title>
    <meta content="30MARK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1172358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Blair</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dead, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D8173CF933A05752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater; A Surprising Third Act in an Actress's Career</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blair Brown discusses her long run as Broadway actress in many productions; interview; photos; her latest role is in The Dead (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BROADWAY actress.'' Sounds almost quaint, doesn't it? A career better suited to another era, a job like ''footman'' or ''linotypist,'' that once held a secure position in the working world and now seems a rather dubious path to gainful employment. With the slow decline of the Broadway play, and the dearth of musical roles for women over 50, a middle-aged actress expecting to find steady, varying work on Broadway might be a candidate for some sort of professional intervention.</p>
        <p>So what is to be made of the unconventional trajectory of Blair Brown, the erstwhile star of television sitcoms (''The Days and Nights of Molly Dodd'') and of movies (''Altered States'') who has reinvented herself as, gulp, a Broadway actress?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BROADWAY actress.'' Sounds almost quaint, doesn't it? A career better suited to another era, a job like ''footman'' or ''linotypist,'' that once held a secure position in the working world and now seems a rather dubious path to gainful employment. With the slow decline of the Broadway play, and the dearth of musical roles for women over 50, a middle-aged actress expecting to find steady, varying work on Broadway might be a candidate for some sort of professional intervention.</p>
        <p>So what is to be made of the unconventional trajectory of Blair Brown, the erstwhile star of television sitcoms (''The Days and Nights of Molly Dodd'') and of movies (''Altered States'') who has reinvented herself as, gulp, a Broadway actress?</p>
        <p>Last year, she scored a critical triumph in ''Cabaret,'' replacing Mary Louise Wilson as the dowdy landlady, Fraulein Schneider, and surprising audiences with the suppleness of her voice. This month, she moved back to Broadway in another singing role as Gretta Conroy, the nostalgic wife in Richard Nelson and Shaun Davey's musical adaptation of ''The Dead,'' the story by James Joyce.</p>
        <p>And nearly as quickly as you can say ''Equity contract,'' she is heading into rehearsals for ''Copenhagen,'' Michael Frayn's cerebral London play about German and Danish nuclear physicists that opens on Broadway on April 11.</p>
        <p>So rare is Ms. Brown's theatrical long run that it is difficult to recall the last time a major American actress hopped from a lead role in a new musical to a new play in a single Broadway season. And that she has accomplished it in such dramatic hard times makes it all the more unlikely.</p>
        <p>No one is more aware of this than the classically trained Ms. Brown, who has appeared on the stage from time to time in notable productions, like the Public Theater's ''Threepenny Opera'' with Raul Julia in 1976 and David Hare's controversially short-lived ''Secret Rapture'' on Broadway in 1989. ''I feel like I'm hitting my stride,'' she said with a laugh the other day in her Chelsea apartment. ''You start to feel richer and richer, and you know you have more and more to give.''</p>
        <p>It wasn't until her role in Tom Stoppard's ''Arcadia'' at Lincoln Center Theater in 1995 that she settled into a serious stage career, a return that has earned her increasingly admiring notices. Of her work in ''Cabaret,'' Vincent Canby wrote in The New York Times that, in her ''beautifully simple, direct and rich performance'' she discovered ''shades of feeling that are entirely new to this production.''</p>
        <p>In addition to her work on Broadway, Ms. Brown has been taking some theatrical risks farther afield, playing, for example, Marguerite Gautier last summer in a highly praised revival of Tennessee Williams's ''Camino Real'' at the Williamstown Theater Festival.</p>
        <p>''For me, the last year and a half has seen doors flying open,'' said Ms. Brown, who is forthright in a playful sort of way when supplying her age -- ''the same as the president's'' (he is 53). ''It's a time in your life when you figure you're about to be tossed, when you think, God, I feel doors closing just when I feel as if I'm coming into my prime.''</p>
        <p>Doors seem to have swung wildly in the career of Ms. Brown, who remains best known for the four years she spent in the late 1980's and early 90's playing lovable, procastinating Molly on the NBC series that became a cult hit when it shifted to Lifetime on cable. Before that, though, came an active movie career, and the prospect of a level of stardom that she never quite achieved. ''I was right after Blythe,'' as in Danner, is how Ms. Brown describes herself on the producers' flow chart of actresses who went through marquee moments in Hollywood before Hollywood moved on to the next young actress.</p>
        <p>But as Ms. Brown acknowledges, she may not have been sufficiently hungry, or perhaps not enough of a specific type, to sustain a top-tier movie presence in the 1980's. ''You're sort of on every list, which means you're sort of on no list,'' she said, sipping English tea in the living room of the brownstone apartment that she shares with her son, Robert, 17. The actress, who never married, had Robert with the actor Richard Jordan, who died of a brain tumor a few years ago. It was partly because of her desire to bring up her son in New York City that the focus of her career shifted.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot more to her life than show business,'' said Gregory Mosher, the former artistic director of Lincoln Center Theater and one of the producers of ''The Dead.'' Mr. Mosher, who has known Ms. Brown for 20 years, said politics has always been a passion they shared: he remembered bumping into her in New Hampshire in 1992, when on the spur of the moment she had bundled up Robert and gone to campaign for Bill Clinton in the Democratic primary. ''She took responsibility for her life and her career,'' Mr. Mosher added. ''And I have never heard her say a mean thing about anyone, well, maybe not never, but she's always funny when she does it.''</p>
        <p>Now that she is being cast regularly, she views the theater as her natural domain. ''I do think there are different kinds of actors,'' she said. ''Jennifer Jason Leigh'' -- with whom she appeared in ''Cabaret'' -- ''loved doing a play, but she adores doing movies, she lives and breathes them.'' Ms. Brown, on the other hand, said she never felt that burning need.</p>
        <p>Her initial goal was the stage. She attended the National Theater School of Canada after graduating from the Madeira School in the Washington suburbs where she grew up, and spent several years appearing in classical theater in Canada, including, at the age of 21, a Shakespeare Festival season in Stratford, Ontario, where she played bit parts in ''The School for Scandal'' and ''The Merchant of Venice.''</p>
        <p>''I learned a lot, but I was a terrible ingenue,'' Ms. Brown said. ''It was really torture, a really unhappy company. And it didn't matter how bad they were, but they always hired directors with English accents.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown does not go in much for deep analysis of her acting ability. That is partly because she is highly self-critical. In fact, she had such difficulty seeing herself on the screen that she could not face watching the daily rushes on a movie set. ''I see someone else,'' she said. ''I see me in an idealized form that isn't there.''</p>
        <p>Theater, of course, offers other worries, but even when she was busiest with film work, she would think of returning to the stage. She was asked, for example, to try out to replace Bernadette Peters in the Pulitzer Prize-winning Broadway production of ''Sunday in the Park With George.'' But, she said, ''I didn't have the nerve to audition for it.''</p>
        <p>What she has discovered in more recent years is a new fearlessness when it comes to singing for a job, as well as an appreciation for what happens to a dramatic performance in a long stage run: ''You're like a Clydesdale by the end -- stronger and stronger.''</p>
        <p>As an actress, Ms. Brown has often impressed smart people in the theater, most famously the British playwright David Hare, with whom she was romantically involved for several years. In a 1989 television interview recently broadcast again in Britain, Mr. Hare declared, ''The only actress I've written for is Blair Brown.'' (Years later, he would write ''Amy's View'' for Judi Dench.)</p>
        <p>''With Blair,'' he added, ''for whom I wrote 'The Secret Rapture' and for whom I wrote 'Strapless,' I have responded to something in her which is a sense of practical, everyday goodness in her performances.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brown speaks a bit wistfully of Mr. Hare, with whom, she said, she is no longer in contact: ''I miss his friendship,'' she said, and with that, made it clear that she would say no more on the subject. But if Mr. Hare sensed something dependably generous in her earlier work, then that attribute has been transformed into something deeper now, an evolution that can be detected in the progressively more complex stage performances she has been providing.</p>
        <p>''Arcadia'' was clearly just a re-entry point; her turn as Hannah Jarvis, a landscape historian, was a bit stiff and did not seem an ideal fit. By ''Cabaret,'' though, last spring, she seemed more comfortable. She brought a tragic element to Fraulein Schneider, a lonely German woman who ultimately rejects a Jewish suitor out of a kind of cowardice: Fraulein Schneider cannot face the brutal consequences of marrying a Jew in Nazi Germany. There was, all over Ms. Brown's portrayal, an aura of  mournful foreknowledge.</p>
        <p>Although she has never minded reading for a part in a play, a musical audition was always more intimidating. ''It seemed so tough and cutthroat,'' she said. When, however, her agent was asked a year and a half ago, ''Does Blair sing?'' and then called her and asked, ''Do you sing?'' Ms. Brown got up the nerve to go for it. ''I got the music,'' she said, about John Kander and Fred Ebb's ''Cabaret,''  ''and I went and sat in my car and learned the songs from the CD.''</p>
        <p>It was, in fact, a bit of a shock to see the woman who played perky Molly Dodd wearing a mask of fear and longing onstage. And now again, in ''The Dead,'' she is at the emotional core of a large ensemble piece, playing a wife in late-1890's Ireland whose memory of an innocent love from long ago exposes a tender element of misunderstanding in her marriage to Gabriel Conroy, portrayed by Christopher Walken. The memory is jogged at a Dublin Christmas party when she takes notice of a young man in a series of glances that are misinterpreted by her husband.</p>
        <p>''I think she's tapped into the sensuality,'' said the playwright, Mr. Nelson, who took over the direction during rehearsals before the opening in the fall at Playwrights Horizons. ''It's about someone who is middle-aged who taps into a youthful sexual passion. She has to be sexy, which she can do.''</p>
        <p>MS. BROWN, who talks easily on a range of subjects, from the filmic style of Ken Russell (who directed her in ''Altered States'') to the political prospects of Hillary Clinton, says that a life in the theater gives her room for a life outside the theater. ''I like living in my own house,'' she said. ''When you are in a movie, it's you and the movie.'' But she's also under no illusion that her streak couldn't come to a halt after ''Copenhagen.''</p>
        <p>''I think it's good timing,'' she said. ''I could have come in two years later, and none of these things would have happened. In this business, you're always waiting for the ax to fall.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
