<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Courthouse Death: One Family's Tragedy -- A special report.; When Passion Explodes Into a Deadly Rage</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="609883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOMESTIC VIOLENCE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">OLMSTEAD, LARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALMONOR, DANIELLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALMONOR, MAX P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DD1530F93BA25756C0A965958260" item-length="3076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Courthouse Death: One Family's Tragedy -- A special report.; When Passion Explodes Into a Deadly Rage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY OLMSTEAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OLMSTEAD, LARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was dramatic -- a woman killed by her estranged husband in Brooklyn Family Court, a bullet fired into the back of her head as she sat on a bench waiting for their case to be called.</p>
        <p>To legal and social-services professionals who knew her, the death of Danielle Almonor two months ago carried a sobering message that made the loss all the more painful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was dramatic -- a woman killed by her estranged husband in Brooklyn Family Court, a bullet fired into the back of her head as she sat on a bench waiting for their case to be called.</p>
        <p>To legal and social-services professionals who knew her, the death of Danielle Almonor two months ago carried a sobering message that made the loss all the more painful.</p>
        <p>Their dispute was not a secret one, played out behind closed doors. Instead, it was a struggle marked by months of harassment that drew wide attention. Even her superiors got involved, trying to get her husband's superiors to intercede.</p>
        <p>But nothing helped. The slaying took place in the building where such conflicts are settled -- a graphic reminder that sometimes neither institutions nor caring individuals are able to prevent personal passion from exploding into an act of violence. Part of the System</p>
        <p>The Almonors -- Danielle, 38, a Federal probation officer, and Max, 52, a state parole officer -- were part of the system.</p>
        <p>Schooled in the dynamics of domestic disputes, they had access to supportive co-workers, therapists, counseling and court programs. Their bosses knew of their problems, yet a week before Mrs. Almonor's death, the State Parole Division handed Mr. Almonor the gun he would use to kill her. Mrs. Almonor sought the protection of Family Court, and ended up being gunned down inside of it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor is awaiting trial on murder charges. Through his attorney, he maintained that the shooting was justified and that his wife or others were armed and possibly intended to shoot him.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the legal outcome, Mrs. Almonor has joined the 2,000 to 4,000 women who are killed each year by their present or former male partners. At least another two million are seriously beaten.</p>
        <p>Most experts agree that no system can stop all acts of violence by people determined to hurt others. But this case begged the question: If the system couldn't help the Almonors, whom could it help?</p>
        <p>Such concerns seemed remote for the couple when they met in the mid-1970's at the University of Bordeaux, in France, where both obtained journalism degrees.</p>
        <p>Danielle Port, chubby and insecure as a child in the small town of Perigueux, delighted in the attentions of Mr. Almonor, a well-spoken man 14 years her senior.</p>
        <p>Born in Haiti, he immigrated to the United States in the mid-1960's and became a citizen. He had worked as a counselor, as a teacher. He had been married before and had three sons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor and Miss Port married Nov. 2, 1979, in New York, and their daughter, Melissa, was born the next year. The wedding accomplished something important to the new Mrs. Almonor -- it allowed her to stay in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor pursued a bachelor's degree at John Jay College of Criminal Justice and in 1984 started working as a state parole officer. His wife, who at first spoke little English, raised their daughter and began a slow but determined assimilation into American culture.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Mrs. Almonor also began studying at John Jay. In 1986, she obtained United States citizenship; the following year, she graduated from college with honors.</p>
        <p>By 1989, Mrs. Almonor was studying social work at Hunter College; she would get her master's in 1992.</p>
        <p>She took a job at the Children's Aid Society and in June 1991, was hired by the United States Probation Department for the Eastern District of New York, on Clinton Street in downtown Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Her colleagues there were impressed by her intelligence and compassion, her desire to help others. And they were intrigued by her personality, blunt and direct. Some found it charming, others brusque.</p>
        <p>Probation Officer Joan Collins said Mrs. Almonor was the kind of person who, at a meal, might say, "Give me your bread," and reach across, take it off your plate and eat it. Mrs. Almonor expected those she knew to treat her the same way.</p>
        <p>She struck up close friendships with a few colleagues. Soon, she was telling them of problems in her marriage. The Problems  Behind Facade, Troubled Lives</p>
        <p>The Almonors lived in a second-floor apartment in a seven-story, red-brick building on Beverly Road, a block off busy Flatbush Avenue in Brooklyn. Mr. Almonor and the building's superintendent, Jeremiah Johnson, liked to play dominoes, or have a beer, or just hang out and talk with friends.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor was the kind of person who minded his business, Mr. Johnson said. "But he has a short temper," he added. "If you say something he doesn't like, he will jump up and get in your face."</p>
        <p>At one point, the Johnsons and the Almonors organized a neighborhood watch to keep drug dealers away from their building. Many neighbors saw the Almonors as a team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson knew better. "She looked happy, but she was never happy," he said.</p>
        <p>One reason was Mr. Almonor's gambling. Mr. Almonor liked poker, Mr. Johnson said, and frequently would travel to Atlantic City to play, sometimes twice in the same day. Mounting Gambling Debts</p>
        <p>His losses mounted. The couple had hoped to buy a house, but could not. Mrs. Almonor told her friends that she finally had to separate her finances from his.</p>
        <p>When she got her job at the Probation Department, the marriage really started deteriorating, friends of both agreed. Although her salary of around $32,000 was well below the $44,000 he earned as a parole officer, some in the law-enforcement field saw the Federal system as carrying more prestige. That bothered Mr. Almonor.</p>
        <p>"He didn't want her to go up in life," Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>After she got her job, people who knew Mrs. Almonor noticed her gaining new friends, new confidence. She seemed to be growing, but her marriage was not.</p>
        <p>Late in 1991, Mrs. Almonor moved out, taking Melissa with her and renting an apartment nearby.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor worked to convince her to return. Arthur Lewis, Mr. Almonor's attorney, said the husband became involved with a gambling support group and the couple attended a counseling session early in 1992. Mr. Almonor emerged encouraged. She had indicated, he thought, that they could try to work things out, that she was coming back. A Plot to Discredit</p>
        <p>But she did not. In February 1992, Mr. Almonor phoned her boss, Stephen J. Rackmill, chief Federal probation officer for New York's eastern district, and asked him to help persuade Mrs. Almonor to reconcile. Mr. Rackmill said he replied that it would be inappropriate for him to intervene.</p>
        <p>A month later, copies of an anonymous letter were sent to a Federal judge, the Department of Immigration, the State Department, the F.B.I., the C.I.A. It said Mrs. Almonor had a shady background in France that called into question her fitness to serve as a probation officer. And it accused her of being hired as the result of a sexual relationship with Mr. Rackmill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rackmill, who had just assumed his role as chief probation officer, had not even hired Mrs. Almonor. Nevertheless, an investigator in the Federal courts' administrative office was dispatched from Washington.</p>
        <p>The investigation concluded that Mr. Almonor was the likely author of the letter, and found nothing improper about the way Mrs. Almonor was hired. But it did turn up that Mrs. Almonor had failed to disclose that she had been seeing a psychotherapist.</p>
        <p>Like all new employees, Mrs. Almonor was on probation her first year. The decision was made to extend her probation a year, through June 1993. Confrontation  Sense of Pain, Sense of Betrayal</p>
        <p>More letters were sent, and Mrs. Almonor reported receiving threats from her husband. The distractions were causing her to fall behind in her work. Her supervisors decided to confront Mr. Almonor.</p>
        <p>On April 14, Jim Fox, deputy chief probation officer, went to the parole division's office on Fulton Street, along with Steve Brighton, a supervising officer who also was a classmate of Mrs. Almonor's at Hunter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor listened politely, even as Mr. Brighton said forcefully: "Max, you just need to let Danielle go. You need to back off and let her go."</p>
        <p>Mr. Brighton recalled that Mr. Almonor "was very controlled," but "underlying, there was a sense of hurt."</p>
        <p>Later that afternoon, Mr. Fox and Mr. Brighton met with one of Mr. Almonor's supervisors to advise him of the letters.</p>
        <p>Despite the meetings, the letters continued. Now they claimed that Mrs. Almonor was having an affair with Mr. Brighton, which he denied. Before it was over, a steady stream of correspondence would be sent to a number of agencies, charging that the United States Probation Department was involved in a racist conspiracy to take Mrs. Almonor from her husband. Much of it now was signed by Mr. Almonor, who is black. His wife was white.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brighton felt a growing uneasiness over the situation, and it was not just over being thrust into the firing line.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Mrs. Almonor worked in an overwhelmingly white environment, Mr. Brighton realized. And he could understand why Mr. Almonor might feel a sense of betrayal. "She got her citizenship through him," he said. "She gets her degree, joins the feds and that's it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Brighton was also concerned about Mrs. Almonor's response to the conflict. He wondered if she thought fully enough about how Mr. Almonor would react if she left the marriage. He told her: "There's a price." The Mediators  Concern Rises As Agencies Feud</p>
        <p>As concern mounted, Miss Collins, the probation officer, agreed to hide Mrs. Almonor and Melissa in her apartment.</p>
        <p>About 11:30 A.M. on Easter Sunday, the phone rang. The caller hung up immediately. Then there were obscene calls. Altogether, there were nine harassing calls that day.</p>
        <p>The next day, Miss Collins recalled, Mrs. Almonor met with her husband to resolve a bill. He told her he had been to her apartment on Argyle Road and taken her clothing.</p>
        <p>Alarmed, Mrs. Almonor, Miss Collins and Mr. Fox went to the apartment. Indeed, all her clothes were gone.</p>
        <p>Back in the office Wednesday, April 22, Mr. Fox called Mr. Almonor, who agreed to return the goods if someone could come by his place and pick them up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox headed to Mr. Almonor's apartment, accompanied by Elaine Terenzi, a fellow supervisor. They carried a temporary order of protection Mrs. Almonor had obtained against her husband that day from Brooklyn Family Court.</p>
        <p>When they arrived at Beverly Road, they encountered a visibly distraught Mr. Almonor, who said he had contemplated suicide. "I sat in my car for about five minutes with a gun in my mouth," he told them.</p>
        <p>Maybe now was not a good time to serve the order of protection, thought Mr. Fox and Ms. Terenzi. Instead, they talked with him for more than two hours, about counseling, about threats. They asked him to give them his gun; he declined. They talked about Melissa.</p>
        <p>"Do you love your daughter?" Ms. Terenzi asked. "Then you can't kill Danielle or yourself."</p>
        <p>They got the clothes back and left, feeling that one or both Almonors would end up dead if someone did not do something soon.</p>
        <p>The next day, Ms. Terenzi contacted the office of the Brooklyn bureau chief for the State Parole Division, who dispatched a subordinate to meet with her. Ms. Terenzi's message: "He's one of yours. Take care of him. I'm not saying fire the guy, but get him help."</p>
        <p>She handed him a copy of her notes of the encounter at the apartment. Noting that Mr. Almonor's job required him to carry a weapon, she added: "This guy is dangerous, and the gun has got to go." Protection Order Extended</p>
        <p>Concerns quickly developed over how the state would deal with the matter. Mr. Rackmill said he received a call from a parole administrator who asked, "Who the hell are you guys to come into our office, telling us how to discipline our own people?"</p>
        <p>"You have an employee that's out of control," Mr. Rackmill responded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rackmill had Mr. Fox prepare a detailed chronology of the events, covered it with a cordial letter, and on April 29 shipped it to Rick Levy, regional director of the State Division of Parole.</p>
        <p>That was the last correspondence between the two agencies. In July, a Brooklyn Family Court judge granted Mrs. Almonor a "permanent" order of protection from her husband, good for a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor and his bosses agreed that some time off might be beneficial. Mr. Almonor was on leave May 7 through June 22, then began a six-month absence Aug. 17. He handed in his badge and .38-caliber service revolver.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor spent much of his leave on extended trips to France. His absence was a relief to his wife. She put in extra hours to catch up with her work. Mr. Rackmill and senior staff decided to expand her duties to include field work. She began training to qualify for a firearm.</p>
        <p>Two days before New Year's Day 1993, Mrs. Almonor went to Supreme Court in Brooklyn and filed for divorce. The Slaying  Divorce Request And a Court Date</p>
        <p>Around mid-February, a memo was posted near the receptionists' desk at the Probation Department. It was from Mrs. Almonor, asking that all her calls be screened except those from her daughter.</p>
        <p>Max was back.</p>
        <p>He called the office frequently. He was seen around the building.</p>
        <p>In one sense, Mrs. Almonor and her attorney, Estelle Masielo, were relieved that Mr. Almonor had turned up. The divorce papers needed to be served in person.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Almonor was upbeat. He told neighbors he was confident his wife would return to him. He also talked with Terry Rodie, district manager for Community Board 14, to which he had been appointed in April 1992. With all his personal problems, he had contributed little. He told Ms. Rodie he had been ill and that he was looking forward to putting some energy into the board.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, March 4, Mr. Almonor returned to work. The next day, he got his gun back.</p>
        <p>One day later, Saturday, a process server found Mr. Almonor at his apartment and handed him the divorce complaint. As the server left, Mr. Almonor looked out the window. He thought he spotted some of his wife's co-workers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Masielo talked with her client. Mr. Almonor had asked for an appearance in Family Court that Friday, March 12, to request a revision in custody and child support arrangements. With the divorce papers filed, Mrs. Almonor needed only to ask the judge to transfer the custody issues to Supreme Court, so the case could be consolidated. It was an appearance that could be handled without an attorney present.</p>
        <p>Still, it would be the first time Mrs. Almonor would see her husband in months. Should Ms. Masielo accompany her client? Finally, the lawyer said the decision was Mrs. Almonor's. Mrs. Almonor said she could handle it by herself.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Mrs. Almonor arrived at Family Court around 9:30 A.M. She took the only seat left in the fifth-floor waiting area and opened a suspense novel, "The Pelican Brief," by John Grisham.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor showed up and approached his wife several times. At one point he handed her a white envelope, containing a note.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor demanded that she read the material; Mrs. Almonor sharply told him to leave her alone.</p>
        <p>Eventually, 11 o'clock approached. Mr. Almonor was back, and handed his wife an envelope. This time, she ripped it to pieces.</p>
        <p>"You wait here," Mr. Almonor said, according to the woman sitting next to Mrs. Almonor, Maryjane Winn. "I'll be back in a minute."</p>
        <p>Through his attorney, Mr. Almonor said he felt in danger as he approached a short time later. He thought Mrs. Almonor had a gun, and that he saw someone with a gun in the row behind her. Mark Hale, an assistant district attorney, said neither was the case.</p>
        <p>In any event, there was a loud pop -- it sounded like a firecracker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almonor had fired his service revolver three times. One shot entered through the base of his wife's head, traveled through the back of her head at an angle and lodged in her brain. Another shattered bone in Ms. Winn's right shoulder, broke a rib and lodged in the center of her chest, near her heart. The third missed everyone.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Almonor lay on the floor, blood pouring from the back of her head, as people trampled one another in an attempt to flee. Someone broke a leg; another suffered a bad cut on the scalp.</p>
        <p>There were no court security officers in the waiting area when the shooting occurred, but several approached quickly when they heard the commotion. The suspect placed his service revolver on a chair, surrendering, and Officer Thomas Mannhaupt grabbed it.  The Aftermath  Shattered Lives, Preventive Steps</p>
        <p>Max Almonor was ordered held without bond, charged with second-degree murder, assault and reckless endangerment. His trial date is Sept. 7.</p>
        <p>Melissa Almonor is being cared for by one of Mr. Almonor's sons, Merault. Maryjane Winn is in physical therapy at St. Vincent's Hospital and is seeing a psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>At Family Court -- where security measures were harshly criticized after the shooting -- an airport-style X-ray machine has been added, and officials have asked for more court officers. Law-enforcement officers say they are being questioned more closely about their reasons for being in the building; if they are there on personal business, they must give up their weapons.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, as they identified her body, located relatives in France and helped arrange her funeral, Mrs. Almonor's colleagues in the Probation Department wrestled with grief and anger.</p>
        <p>Many felt that, given the order of protection against Mr. Almonor and a documented history of troubled behavior, the State Parole Division's decision to return his gun was risky and premature.</p>
        <p>David Ernst, spokesman for the parole division, said officials reacted "in what we believed was an appropriate and prompt and prudent manner, given the information available at the time."</p>
        <p>Estelle Masielo sat at work the following week virtually immobilized, crying much of the time. She asked repeatedly: What if I had been there? Maybe I could have intercepted the letters. Maybe I could have calmed him down, defused the situation.</p>
        <p>Maybe you'd be dead, said her law partner, Gail Rich. Ms. Masielo finally accepted, more or less, that she could not have prevented the slaying.</p>
        <p>Others worked through the same issues. "What could I have done?" asked Rick Gray, a probation officer and friend who had eaten breakfast that morning with Mrs. Almonor. "I've turned this over and looked at this from a lot of angles. And the objective answer is: Nothing."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Gray and the others, that answer provided, at best, only an uneasy peace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
