<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ITT Seeking More Bidding, With Board As Auctioneer</title>
    <meta content="Y07HOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="971162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Itt Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hilton Hotels Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Starwood Lodging Trust</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DD1739F934A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ITT Seeking More Bidding, With Board As Auctioneer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ITT Corp directors say they want bidding between Hilton Hotels Corp and Starwood Lodging Trust to continue, and that they are best qualified to handle auction process; this draws angry response from Hilton, which ends talks with ITT, claiming it is not receiving same access to informationas its rival, Starwood Lodging; ITT shareholders will be asked to vote for one of two competing slates of directors on Nov 12; Hilton is expected to continue its bid even if its slate loses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Continuing a multibillion-dollar chess match, the directors of the ITT Corporation said yesterday that they wanted the bidding between the Hilton Hotels Corporation and the Starwood Lodging Trust for control of the company to continue, and that they were best qualified to handle the auction process.</p>
        <p>The recommendation -- which drew an angry response from Hilton -- came as lobbying by the two sides intensified ahead of Wednesday's annual shareholder meeting. At that meeting, shareholders will be asked to vote for one of two competing slates of directors. While Hilton has vowed to pull its bid if it loses the vote, some analysts say that Hilton is in the fight for the long pull and that a loss next week would only be a temporary setback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Continuing a multibillion-dollar chess match, the directors of the ITT Corporation said yesterday that they wanted the bidding between the Hilton Hotels Corporation and the Starwood Lodging Trust for control of the company to continue, and that they were best qualified to handle the auction process.</p>
        <p>The recommendation -- which drew an angry response from Hilton -- came as lobbying by the two sides intensified ahead of Wednesday's annual shareholder meeting. At that meeting, shareholders will be asked to vote for one of two competing slates of directors. While Hilton has vowed to pull its bid if it loses the vote, some analysts say that Hilton is in the fight for the long pull and that a loss next week would only be a temporary setback.</p>
        <p>After raising its bid on Monday to $80 a share in cash and stock from $70, Hilton, the hotel and gaming company, had held two days of talks with ITT, once a conglomerate but now a hotel and gaming company. But yesterday Hilton ended those discussions, saying it was not receiving the same access to information that its rival, Starwood, had been afforded. Hilton said it would continue its proxy fight, but threatened to pull its offer off the table if its slate is not elected at next week's meeting.</p>
        <p>Last month, ITT accepted an offer of $82 a share in cash and stock from Starwood. ITT said yesterday that it was still legally bound by its merger agreement with Starwood, but that under that agreement it could hold discussions with both parties about bids.</p>
        <p>''I think we were being used,'' Stephen F. Bollenbach, Hilton's president and chief executive, said in a telephone interview. ''We were not getting anything of value, and we were reading they were swell guys now because they were working with us. They weren't.''</p>
        <p>''We have zero interest in an auction that is run by ITT board members, assuming they even do it,'' Mr. Bollenbach said. ''It is my opinion that it is the sole objective of the board and senior management to maintain their jobs.''</p>
        <p>The charges prompted a fierce verbal exchange between ITT and Hilton that lasted most of the day.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Bernard Nussbaum, a lawyer at Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz and Hilton's outside counsel, Philip A. Gelston, a lawyer at Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore who works for ITT, called Mr. Bollenbach's charge baseless, and said in closing that ''false public statements could impact a proxy contest.''</p>
        <p>Wall Street, which has seen the two sides sling mud at each other for more than 10 months now, reacted to the latest salvos with aplomb. On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, ITT shares fell 62.5 cents, to $79.625. Hilton's stock price rose by 56.25 cents, to $31.625. And Starwood, which is widely expected to raise its bid before next week's meeting, saw its share price decline by $1.4375, to $58.8125.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Litt, an analyst who covers real estate investment trusts for Paine Webber, said Mr. Bollenbach ''wants to discredit the ITT board members and get his slate elected on Wednesday.''</p>
        <p>''ITT is saying, 'We are conducting a competitive auction,' which is what they have to do,'' he added.</p>
        <p>But other analysts said shareholders had reason to be cautious.</p>
        <p>''These are actions that fall on deaf ears,'' said Bruce Turner, an analyst at Salomon Brothers. ''I think shareholders remain very skeptical that they are going to be good guys now, despite their rhetoric.''</p>
        <p>To underscore its intent to conduct an auction if it is re-elected, ITT's board said yesterday that it had voted to hold the company's 1998 annual meeting ''if needed,'' by March, and to allow an election contest to be held at that meeting.</p>
        <p>In addition, the board said it would call a special shareholders meeting if requested by 10 percent or more of ITT's shareholders between Dec. 15 and the March annual meeting.</p>
        <p>''We expect the 1998 annual meeting will never occur because the sale of ITT will have closed,'' Paul Kirk, an independent ITT director since 1989, said in the statement. ''But we want our stockholders to know they will have an early opportunity to vote again if necessary.''</p>
        <p>One development that could sway the attitudes of shareholders could come today. Institutional Shareholder Services, a group that issues advice on proxy fights to about 400 big institutions, is expected to issue a recommendation on which slate to vote for at Wednesday's meeting. Such a recommendation could sway about 25 million shares, or about 20 percent of ITT's shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>The recommendation could also force Barry S. Sternlicht, Starwood's chairman, to raise his bid, as analysts expect.</p>
        <p>Since the current offers are so close, and ITT's board wants both parties to go higher, the ISS recommendation is likely to be based on factors other than price.</p>
        <p>In the end, the offer with the biggest cash component is likely to win out. An ISS recommendation in favor of Hilton could force Mr. Sternlicht to push his bid higher, perhaps as late as Monday, analysts said.</p>
        <p>But because the ITT board said it did not believe that either Starwood or Hilton had come up with its best -- and last -- bids, the auction could run well past the meeting next week.</p>
        <p>That is not likely to happen if Hilton's slate of directors is approved. But ITT's board urged shareholders yesterday to avoid looking at the coming meeting as a referendum on the two current offers.</p>
        <p>''This meeting is simply a mechanism for ITT stockholders to decide which board they want to continue to conduct the auction,'' Rand V. Araskog, ITT's chairman and chief executive, said in the statement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
