<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Notebook; Press Gets the Scoop on the Next TV Season</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="461080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HOLLYWOOD (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDB153EF93BA25754C0A967958260" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Notebook; Press Gets the Scoop on the Next TV Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARTER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a semi-annual ritual, the press that covers the television industry heads to Hollywood for a three-week dose of details about the coming season. This summer's event is being held in the Universal City Hotel, on a hill that overlooks a stage on the Universal Studio lot where tourists flock to watch the "Miami Vice" shootout attraction.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the event is to give reporters and critics a chance to ask television executives, producers and stars about budgets, programming philosophies and how it feels to work with the famous Mr. or Ms. So-and-So. Parties are given, photos are staged, stars are paraded, all with the idea that reporters will go home dazzled and give the new season's offerings a helpful plug.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a semi-annual ritual, the press that covers the television industry heads to Hollywood for a three-week dose of details about the coming season. This summer's event is being held in the Universal City Hotel, on a hill that overlooks a stage on the Universal Studio lot where tourists flock to watch the "Miami Vice" shootout attraction.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the event is to give reporters and critics a chance to ask television executives, producers and stars about budgets, programming philosophies and how it feels to work with the famous Mr. or Ms. So-and-So. Parties are given, photos are staged, stars are paraded, all with the idea that reporters will go home dazzled and give the new season's offerings a helpful plug.</p>
        <p>The press tour began more than two decades ago as a promotional effort on the part of the broadcast networks, but it has grown into something larger, encompassing cable and even public television. The event has no name, but after years of participation by the press, who formed their own group called the Television Critics Association to help plan the event, it has now adopted T.C.A. as its quasi-official designation.</p>
        <p>The entire cable industry was allotted only three days, in which the channels squeezed in more than 20 interview sessions. About 120 reporters turned out for the cable portion of the event; the number is expected to grow to about 150 by the time the network portion begins on Saturday. The publications represented range widely in size, from such major ones as TV Guide, Variety, The Philadelphia Inquirer, the Chicago Tribune and USA Today, to Teen magazine and such smaller newspapers as The Virginian-Pilot, of Norfolk, and the Sonoma (Calif.) Index-Tribune.</p>
        <p>For the cable industry, access to this much press in one place has been regarded as especially vital. Even though many of the channels get less than an hour to run though what they are planning for the next six months, they usually offer up a star ( American Movie Classics had Dorothy Lamour, the Family Channel had Glenn Ford, Nickelodeon had Dick Van Dyke) for a soupcon of Q. and A.</p>
        <p>Indeed, new cable channels angle to be included, but as Carol Vernon, a spokeswoman for the National Cable Television Association put it, "No new network can get in easily anymore."</p>
        <p>Thus, on Tuesday afternoon, as the T.C.A. was getting off the ground, the new cable television channel Comedy Central (one part Ha!, one part the Comedy Channel, both now defunct) had exactly 30 minutes to try to make an impression on about 60 reporters.</p>
        <p>Tony Fox, the director of public relations for the channel, began with an almost frantic plea for the milling crowd to take their seats. Bob Kreek, the president of the channel, described the current status of the channel through a soft din of chatter. The clock was ticking.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Fox, the presentation was all but crucial: it was, he knew, a rare opportunity to alert the press to a channel most of them barely knew existed.</p>
        <p>Until about halfway through the presentation Mr. Fox feared things were going badly. Then a program made up of clips from public-access cable channels kicked in. Among the moments that got the biggest laughs: a group energetically playing musical selections on pizza boxes and a woman using her cat as a set of bagpipes.</p>
        <p>Later Mr. Fox said: "I think it went very well. But next time we've got to get at least 45 minutes."</p>
        <p>The major players -- HBO , MTV , Turner , Showtime -- have more time and bigger stars. There is even, occasionally, a running theme.</p>
        <p>Jack Lemmon, discussing a new HBO comedy movie he has made, decribed how the theatrical movie business can no longer do "well-written little stories" because they might make only $5 million or $10 million and that might cause the studio head to be fired. He said: "The whole business has gone right over a precipice and down. You're going to have to blow up heads and bodies." Special Effects Galore</p>
        <p>Later that day, the producer Gale Anne Hurd, who has blown up numerous heads and bodies in such feature films as "Aliens," "The Abyss" and the current "Terminator 2," described how she had successfully made "Cast a Deadly Spell," a special-effects-laden picture for HBO, for $6.2 million after it was turned down by a studio that thought its prospective $25 million budget would blow up into $40 million.</p>
        <p>She called the smaller budgets of movies made for television "quite refreshing" and "very needed in this industry."</p>
        <p>Richard Dreyfuss, who is starring in an HBO film about the Alfred Dreyfus scandal in France, discoursed passionately on how he had had a lifelong fascination with the subject because he once believed he was related to the French Army officer accused of treason, imprisoned and later exonerated.</p>
        <p>The comedian Billy Crystal held a press conference about "Sessions," a new HBO show about a man and his therapist that he has written but in which he does not appear. He sprinkled the group interview with jokes, but when a reporter asked if the series wasn't a "depressing" topic Mr. Crystal bristled, calling the question "unfair" and defining the show as not about a man's problems but about his life. He also said it was "very funny," not depressing.</p>
        <p>Afterward, he said he was stunned by the "moronic" questions.</p>
        <p>In a later press conference a reporter asked HBO's new boxing commentator, George Foreman, what was the biggest meal he ever ate. (For the record: two dozen eggs, a pound of bacon and about a half a loaf of bread.)</p>
        <p>But neither Mr. Crystal's nor Mr. Foreman's question would be in the running in a contest for most memorable question asked at one of these events. One year Billy Packer, CBS's commentator for its coverage of college basketball's Final Four tournament, was asked: "If it's a championship, why do they stop with four teams?"</p>
        <p>HBO, which has established a reputation for finding inventive ways to call attention to its upcoming projects -- usually by throwing atmospheric dinner parties -- on Tuesday night rented a huge unused mansion in Pasadena called the Wayne Manor because it was used as Batman's residence in the old ABC Television series.</p>
        <p>Amid ersatz gargoyles and neon candlelight, the press mingled with HBO executives and stars. Ms. Hurd, five months pregnant and wearing a magenta dress and a Terminator-sized engagement ring, outshone the neon. She arrived with her husband-to-be, the director Brian De Palma.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foreman, HBO's new boxing commentator, came in and posed affably with a gargoyle.</p>
        <p>Robert Duvall, the star of a coming HBO mini-series based on the life of Stalin, sat at a table and spoke for hours on his intense research on the Russian dictator. "I know I look more like Lenin," he said. Later the raw realities of television budgets were taken up once again. The producer Mark Carliner broke the news that Mr. Duvall's choice of director on the film might not be acceptable because of the film's byzantine financial backing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duvall said it was time to take the matter up with his agent, and he left.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
