<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oiler Passing Game Overwhelms Chiefs</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="409214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSTON OILERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">KANSAS CITY CHIEFS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Kansas City Chiefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7113FF934A25751C1A966958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oiler Passing Game Overwhelms Chiefs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Dec. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kansas City Chiefs prepared all week for Houston's run-and-shoot offense, confident that their big-play defense could again slow Warren Moon and his receivers. But the Chiefs were also hoping for rain, sleet or snow. The more wicked the weather, the Chiefs believed, the more unlikely that the Oilers would be able to execute.</p>
        <p>Well, a steady drizzle fell for most of the second half here this afternoon, but that and the Chiefs' defense weren't nearly enough to dampen Moon's pinpoint passing and his receivers' array of acrobatic catches. Moon threw for 527 yards -- the second highest passing-yardage total in National Football League history -- and for touchdown passes of 24, 87 and 2 yards as Houston toppled the Chiefs, 27-10.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kansas City Chiefs prepared all week for Houston's run-and-shoot offense, confident that their big-play defense could again slow Warren Moon and his receivers. But the Chiefs were also hoping for rain, sleet or snow. The more wicked the weather, the Chiefs believed, the more unlikely that the Oilers would be able to execute.</p>
        <p>Well, a steady drizzle fell for most of the second half here this afternoon, but that and the Chiefs' defense weren't nearly enough to dampen Moon's pinpoint passing and his receivers' array of acrobatic catches. Moon threw for 527 yards -- the second highest passing-yardage total in National Football League history -- and for touchdown passes of 24, 87 and 2 yards as Houston toppled the Chiefs, 27-10.</p>
        <p>he loss spoiled the Chiefs' chance to clinch at least a wild-card playoff berth in a game played before 61,756 fans at Arrowhead Stadium. Kansas City slipped to 9-5; Houston improved to 8-6.</p>
        <p>Moon, who completed 27 of 45 passes, fell only 27 yards short of the N.F.L. record for passing yardage, set 39 years ago by Norm Van Brocklin of the Los Angeles Rams. With approximately three minutes left today, the Oilers had the football but kept it on the ground and ran out the clock to end the game.</p>
        <p>"Records are nice, but they are not that important to me," said Moon. He threw for more than 300 yards in a game for the ninth time this season, tying Dan Marino's record set in 1984. This season, Moon has thrown for 4,001 yards and 32 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>"I'm not going to throw just to set a record," he said. "We had the game. We just wanted to win and get out of here. Today, we were challenged and we were ready for that challenge. This is a good feeling because this is one of the best defenses in the game and they have the best cornerback combination in the game. Sure, a little of it was revenge, but a lot of this today was to quiet the doubters still out there about this team."</p>
        <p>A year ago, Kansas City dominated the Oilers here, winning by 34-0 and limiting Moon to 8-of-20 passing for only 99 yards. The quarterback had one pass intercepted, was sacked four times and threw for a long gain of 26 yards. Big Game for Jeffires</p>
        <p>Today, Haywood Jeffires was his favorite target. Jeffires caught 9 passes for 245 yards and made the 87-yard score.</p>
        <p>"Warren was hot and God was with me today," Jeffires said of his career-best effort. "This was special."</p>
        <p>The Oilers entered this game salivating at the Chiefs' penchant for playing single coverage in the secondary. The Chiefs' starting cornerbacks -- Albert Lewis and Kevin Ross -- are superior single-coverage cornerbacks. Stan Petry and Jayice Pearson, however, are not. Petry and Pearson were inserted in place of two Chiefs linebackers to handle the Oiler formations, which always include at least four wide receivers.</p>
        <p>Moon said later that he was not picking on the Chiefs' additions, but it was obvious early on that Petry and Pearson were primary targets.</p>
        <p>Houston led at halftime by 10-7. Moon sparkled in the second half and Houston's defense was smothering, knocking Steve DeBerg, the Kansas City quarterback, out of the game in the second half with a broken little finger on his left hand. DeBerg re-entered with a splint on his hand, but he was virtually ineffective. Late in the game, he had his first intercepted pass in his last 233 passes.</p>
        <p>Lloyd Burris, a Chief safety, said the secondary mixed zone coverage with single-man coverage, but Moon, who was sacked four times, always seemed to have an answer.</p>
        <p>"We had no doubt we could cover their receivers man to man, but Warren was on the money and his receivers really went after the ball," Burris said.</p>
        <p>Ernest Givins, the Oilers' leading receiver, who watched starring efforts by Jeffires and Tony Jones, who had four catches for 61 yards and two touchdowns, said: "That's a heck of a team that would challenge us and play that much single coverage. They've got guts. We've been praying for a team to try that against us and we finally got that today. Warren Moon gets better as the years go on.  He has all of the tools, but don't forget, he has many tools around him."</p>
        <p>Marty Schottehmeimer, the Chiefs' head coach, wasn't about to forget that point.</p>
        <p>"My experience against Warren has been to put pressure on him," he said, "but we got a guy who was sizzling and he has some guys around him who are excellent players."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
