<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federated Is Said to Be In Tax Case</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERATED STORES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE (IRS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CAMPEAU CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARMASH, ISADORE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED91330F93AA15755C0A966958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federated Is Said to Be In Tax Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISADORE BARMASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARMASH, ISADORE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Internal Revenue Service is said to be considering a tax claim of more than $1 billion against Federated Stores Inc. The basis for the claim is said to be that the Campeau Corporation misallocated the ''good will'' of Federated when it acquired the retail chain in 1988.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Internal Revenue Service is said to be considering a tax claim of more than $1 billion against Federated Stores Inc. The basis for the claim is said to be that the Campeau Corporation misallocated the ''good will'' of Federated when it acquired the retail chain in 1988.</p>
        <p>The Internal Revenue Service is said to be considering a tax claim of more than $1 billion against Federated Stores Inc. The basis for the claim is said to be that the Campeau Corporation misallocated the ''good will'' of Federated when it acquired the retail chain in 1988.</p>
        <p>Campeau, a mall developer based in Toronto, paid more than $7 billion for Federated in 1988, $3 billion more than the company's book value. But soft retail sales caused the highly leveraged deal to falter when Campeau could not meet its debt payments, and Federated filed for protection from its creditors under Chapter 11 of the Federal Bankruptcy Code last January.</p>
        <p>Financial people and representatives of creditors involved in the bankruptcy said yesterday that the I.R.S. might seek to regain as much as 40 percent of the $3 billion allocated by Campeau to good will in its merger with Federated.</p>
        <p>'No Action' Yet</p>
        <p>In Cincinnati, a Federated spokeswoman, Carol Sanger, said: ''There have been no specific discussions with the I.R.S. This is all based on market rumor.''</p>
        <p>An I.R.S. spokesman in Washington said that he could not comment on the agency's plans.</p>
        <p>Federated Stores is the American arm of Campeau, which operates both Federated Department Stores and Allied Stores Inc. Among its stores are Bloomingdale's, Abraham &amp; Straus and Stern's in the New York area; Burdine's, Maas Brothers and Jordan Marsh in Florida; Rich's in Atlanta; Jordan Marsh in Boston; Bon Marche in Seattle, and Lazarus in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The term good will is often used in mergers in which the purchase price substantially exceeds a company's book value. If the target company has a book value of, say, $500 million on its balance sheet and a purchaser pays $750 million, the extra $250 million is considered the good will a company has accumulated among its suppliers and customers. This good will is sometimes carried on the books of companies as an asset.</p>
        <p>No Deduction Allowed</p>
        <p>But under I.R.S. provisions, a tax deduction may not be taken for good will, so companies tend to allocate the good will to assets that are deductible, like leases or a customer list. In recent cases, the I.R.S. has raised questions about the value of some assets to which good will has been assigned and has sometimes opposed the way in which such assets were depreciated.</p>
        <p>''There is frequently tension between the I.R.S. and a business taxpayer over the applicability of good will on a depreciable asset,'' said Richard Cohen, senior partner at Winthrop, Stimson, Putnam, Roberts, a New York law firm. ''This has resulted in a good bit of litigation over the allocation of good will to such assets as customer lists, leaseholds or business relationships.''</p>
        <p>For the most part, other lawyers said yesterday, taxpayers have prevailed in such cases; in some, the tax resulting in a successful I.R.S. claim was much lower than what the agency originally sought.</p>
        <p>In addition to retail companies, the issue has been raised in mergers involving media companies and banks.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
