<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wide-Open Field For French Open</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, ROBIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FRENCH OPEN (TENNIS)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61531F934A15756C0A966958260" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wide-Open Field For French Open</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINN, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Last year the French Open lurched to an improbable conclusion when two 17-year-old dark-horse contestants made history by stubbornly outlasting their elders on the red clay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Last year the French Open lurched to an improbable conclusion when two 17-year-old dark-horse contestants made history by stubbornly outlasting their elders on the red clay.</p>
        <p>Last year the French Open lurched to an improbable conclusion when two 17-year-old dark-horse contestants made history by stubbornly outlasting their elders on the red clay.</p>
        <p>This year the Open is fraught with conjecture before it has begun because everyone still in the running -the list of dropouts verges on the legendary - looks more like a dark horse than a sure thing.</p>
        <p>Not even the teen-aged co-champions from 1989, presumably a year older and wilier, think it especially realistic that they can retain their only Grand Slam titles.</p>
        <p>The preparation of Michael Chang, the defending men's champion, is in a shambles because of his failure to survive opening matches at three consecutive Euopean clay-court events.</p>
        <p>Hoping to mesmerize himself into the proper frame of mind for the rigors in store at Roland Garros, the 18-year-old Chang has been studying a videotape of his 1989 campaign.</p>
        <p>Hasn't Won on Clay</p>
        <p>Chang, whose 1990 record is a dismal 2-5 after a difficult, and perhaps premature comeback from a hip fracture, is the only player among the seeded men not to have won a match on clay this year.</p>
        <p>''I'm not where I want to be, but to just win one match would turn things around and relieve some of the pressure,'' said Chang from Marseilles, where he intended to use an exhibition event as a final tuneup.</p>
        <p>Chang's first opponent in Paris is Cassio Motta of Brazil, a veteran who hasn't ventured past the third round in 11 previous appearances. If Chang gets past a potential meeting with Emilio Sanchez of Spain in the round of 16, his prospective quarterfinal opponent is third-seeded Andre Agassi, the only top-seeded player with a relatively clear path through the early rounds.</p>
        <p>Arantxa Sanchez Vicario of Spain, the defending women's champion whose dogged performance in last year's final spoiled Steffi Graf's quest for a repeated sweep of a quartet of Grand Slam events, has not beaten Graf since then.</p>
        <p>''I know Steffi will want revenge at the French,'' said Sanchez Vicario. ''My mind is thinking I can do it again, but if I don't it's no small thing that I won last year's trophy. Not many players can say they've ever won a Grand Slam.''</p>
        <p>Fortitude to Unfold</p>
        <p>Sanchez Vicario could play last year's French Open junior champion, Jennifer Capriati, in the round of 16.</p>
        <p>The fitness and fortitude of Graf, winner of seven of the last eight Grand Slams, as usual will determine the direction in which the women's draw unfolds.</p>
        <p>Graf was not happy with herself after erratic shotmaking cost her a 66-match unbeaten streak and the German Open final a week ago. She will be able to rely on vengeance as a significant contributor to her motivation this time around: she wants to regain her title from Sanchez Vicario and curtail the 25-match winning streak of Monica Seles, the 16-year-old who so soundly defeated her in West Berlin.</p>
        <p>''It's only natural,'' said Graf, ''for me to want to win the French Open, and of course to beat Sanchez Vicario.''</p>
        <p>If Gabriela Sabatini is in form on clay, Graf's first stern test could come in the semifinals; from there, a clash with Seles in the finals appears inevitable.</p>
        <p>The hottest players on the circuit, Thomas Muster of Austria, whose 26-4 record on clay in 1990 is unequaled among the men, and Seles, of Yugoslavia, who has beaten Graf and Martina Navratilova while amassing five straight tournament victories, have both spoken of springtime burnout.</p>
        <p>But there is little chance that they won't rejuvenate themselves in time to make their presence felt here.</p>
        <p>None of the favorites on the men's side, not even top-seeded Stefan Edberg and second-seeded Boris Becker, are targeted for easy early rounds.</p>
        <p>Edberg may have to fend off the 1983 French Open champion, Yannick Noah, to get to a quarterfinal meeting with Andrei Chesnokov of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>A Major Rebound</p>
        <p>Becker has never won a clay title and has four accomplished opponents ahead of him en route to a quarterfinal battle with Muster, the player who has rebounded with a vengeance from the knee surgery he required after being struck by a drunken driver on the eve of his match against Ivan Lendl at the Lipton finals a year ago.</p>
        <p>''There is no favorite for the French,'' said Muster after subduing Chesnokov in the final of the Italian Open. ''There are many good clay-court players who can win. It will be a very open tournament this year.''</p>
        <p>Plenty of the French Open's openness can be traced to the good clay-court players who won't be here.</p>
        <p>The three-time champions Lendl and Mats Wilander, and the two-time champion Navratilova, have chosen to forgo this year's rendition. Wilander's game has been beset by distractions, the most daunting of them the serious illness of his father.</p>
        <p>Lendl and Navratilova ascribe their decision to skip the French to its proximity to Wimbledon, the third leg of the Grand Slam and the event by which both are transfixed. Playing on Cobblestones?  Lendl, seeking a storybook completeness in his career, is still chasing his first Wimbledon title. Navratilova is determined to capture a record ninth Wimbledon before she will consider easing herself away from the daily competitive grind.</p>
        <p>Navratilova thinks the two weeks between the slams is inadequate for making the stylistic transition from clay to grass.</p>
        <p>''You may as well try to play golf on cobblestones,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Another missing protagonist is John McEnroe, who cited the usual aches and pains in withdrawing from his sixth consecutive event.</p>
        <p>McEnroe has never won the French, and the slow red clay has long been a source of frustration that he can ill afford this year when just an additional $1,000 in fines would force his disqualification from Wimbledon.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
