<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Night Bloomers and Venus Flytraps</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="613384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD113BF935A35755C0A965958260" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Night Bloomers and Venus Flytraps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL the garden books I am reading this year are colored by Sara Stein's "Noah's Garden: Restoring the Ecology of Our Own Back Yards," which tells the story of how one gardener began to realize that her neat and tidy lawn, her perennial beds full of exotic shrubs and flowers had left no place for wildlife. "Noah's Garden" has affected the way I read other books and also the way I look at plants. Now, when I am enraptured by a viburnum or a butterfly bush at the local nursery, I ask, is this one the birds and butterflies could use?</p>
        <p>Anyone prone to falling asleep in botany class might enjoy NATURAL AFFAIRS: A Botanist Looks at the Attachments Between Plants and People (225 pp., Villard, $25), by Peter Bernhardt, whose first book was the whimsical "Wily Violets and Underground Orchids." Many botanists are adventurers (after all, they get paid to tramp through savannas and jungles) but few have the storyteller's ability to take the rest of us, for example, on a journey into the sexual parts of a flower -- to find the threads of a saffron crocus (Crocus sativus, if you care), uh, fascinating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL the garden books I am reading this year are colored by Sara Stein's "Noah's Garden: Restoring the Ecology of Our Own Back Yards," which tells the story of how one gardener began to realize that her neat and tidy lawn, her perennial beds full of exotic shrubs and flowers had left no place for wildlife. "Noah's Garden" has affected the way I read other books and also the way I look at plants. Now, when I am enraptured by a viburnum or a butterfly bush at the local nursery, I ask, is this one the birds and butterflies could use?</p>
        <p>Anyone prone to falling asleep in botany class might enjoy NATURAL AFFAIRS: A Botanist Looks at the Attachments Between Plants and People (225 pp., Villard, $25), by Peter Bernhardt, whose first book was the whimsical "Wily Violets and Underground Orchids." Many botanists are adventurers (after all, they get paid to tramp through savannas and jungles) but few have the storyteller's ability to take the rest of us, for example, on a journey into the sexual parts of a flower -- to find the threads of a saffron crocus (Crocus sativus, if you care), uh, fascinating.</p>
        <p>But they are -- when you follow Mr. Bernhardt from the moment he gets cheated in a grocery store in Sydney, Australia (he buys some fake saffron for the "unbelievably low price of 50 cents"), to his painless explanation of where saffron comes from (three gangly stigma stalks, or threads, that hang like "untied shoelaces" from the flower's pistil, or female organ), and why the real McCoy is virtually worth its weight in gold (the flowers are gathered in the fields of Spain and Portugal by pickers on their hands and knees; the threads are then pinched off, one by one).</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernhardt analyzed the material, found it to contain nothing but dyed cut-up flower parts, sans golden threads, and reported it to the health department. The distributor was fined $1,000 for using artificial dyes, which was getting off easy, writes the botanist: "In 1444, Jobst Findeker was burned alive with his sacks of adulterated saffron helping to fuel his fire" in medieval Germany. "A dozen years later two men and a woman were buried alive for the same offense."</p>
        <p>The practical gardener may want to add THE AMERICAN MIXED BORDER: Gardens for All Seasons (240 pp., Macmillan, $35), by Ann Lovejoy, to the one shelf of true-grit books. Ms. Lovejoy, who gardens on Bainbridge Island, Washington, writes with the easy authority of a dirt gardener with a deep knowledge of plants and enough years of seeing great gardens and knowing great gardeners (like the British designer Penelope Hobhouse and Marco Polo Stufano, the director of horticulture at Wave Hill in the Bronx) to have absorbed the constantly shifting elements that make up that amorphous slippery thing: good design. Just go look, she counsels. If you look enough, what you see will seep into your unconscious, then you can do the rest.</p>
        <p>A mixed border, in case you're wondering, leaps free of the formal perennial bed and mixes woody plants, deciduous trees, evergreens and shrubs with bulbs and perennials, annuals and vines. With examples from her own island garden in the Pacific Northwest, as well as others in both the United States and Britain, Ms. Lovejoy examines everything from hedges to that mighty annual, the castor bean.</p>
        <p>She writes with a forthright energy that turns away from Mother England's gardening edicts as easily as it embraces them -- depending on what's needed. Formal hedges, she points out, do not fit in the American garden unless you have an estate and the requisite estate gardener to keep it trimmed. But what about an informal hedge of mountain laurel and rhododendrons, she suggests, or a mixed one of evergreen viburnums, rhododendrons and holly with spring-blooming shrubs like Chinese lilac, spireas and deutzia? She writes of the importance of knowing and accepting the site and conditions of your land, and of the needs of children and animals. If a plant founders, she says, don't drench it in pesticides; kick it out.</p>
        <p>My only complaint about her book is that a number of alluring photographs are left unidentified. A wine-colored barberry in Helen Dillon's garden in Dublin, for instance, looks terrific next to some bright red flower that looks like a rose on a strawberry vine, but we don't know what it is.</p>
        <p>I'm a pushover for night-bloomers, but THE EVENING GARDEN (256 pp., Macmillan, $25), written and illustrated by Peter Loewer, would be a treat for anyone starting a garden that comes into its own when the sun goes down. Mr. Loewer, who gardens in Asheville, N.C., also did the more than 100 line drawings that enhance the honest romance, as well as the botany, of this book. I have long been meaning to plant some evening primroses, but Mr. Loewer's description of the hawk moth stretching its long tongue down the flower tubes to drain them of every last drop of nectar decided me once and for all. Not to mention other details about the primrose: that American Indians used a root tea of Oenothera biennis to treat obesity; that oil from primrose seed is used to treat premenstrual syndrome and arthritis. There are hundreds of plants listed here, including 124 species of evening primroses.</p>
        <p>A small but precious book is LANDSCAPE PLANTS FOR THE TWENTY-FIRST CENTURY (72 pp., Friends of the National Arboretum, paper, $7.50), by Erik A. Neumann. If you love crab apples but want a disease-resistant variety, or if you fell in love with one of the "Girl" magnolias this spring (I fell for Susan, a red-purple one), this no-nonsense guide clearly describes each tree's habits, its flowering and fruiting patterns and cultivation needs.</p>
        <p>An important book for bulb gardeners is THE GARDENER'S GUIDE TO PLANT CONSERVATION (187 pp., World Wildlife Fund, paper, $12.95), by Nina T. Marshall. It points out that plants like trillium, which takes seven years to grow from seed to flowering size, and the giant snowdrop (Galanthus elwesii), which is difficult to propagate because of the extreme climatic conditions in the mountains of its native Turkey, are still being collected in the wild and sold commercially. The handbook sums up the international laws governing endangered wild plants, counsels how to avoid buying them, then devotes most of its pages to a clear listing of threatened or endangered wildflowers and whether they can be propagated or grown from seed. It also lists important sources of information, like the Center for Plant Conservation in St. Louis and the Eastern Native Plant Alliance in McLean, Va.</p>
        <p>When I feel depressed about the ravaging of Venus flytraps by collectors in North and South Carolina, I dip into HEDGEMAIDS AND FAIRY CANDLES: The Lives and Lore of North American Wildflowers (232 pp., Ragged Mountain Press/McGraw-Hill, $21.95), by Jack Sanders, illustrated by Dawn Peterson. Here you will find that Pliny advised the use of catnip for scorpion bites and that the Delaware Indians used it in a tea to calm squalling babies; that chickweed is good to leave in the lawn, because birds love it, and so might you, if you stopped dousing your lawn with pesticides. Chickweed tastes like spinach (I know, I've eaten it) and is high in vitamin C and phosphorus.</p>
        <p>On the subject of lawns, REDESIGNING THE AMERICAN LAWN: A Search for Environmental Harmony (166 pp., Yale University, $19.95), by F. Herbert Bormann, Diana Balmori and Gordon T. Geballe, is an extremely readable summation of the origins of the addiction to lawns, and of the environmental reasons why Americans should kick the habit. (The National Academy of Science, for instance, has found that homeowners use up to 10 times more chemical pesticides an acre than farmers do.) The book explores ways to replace the mowed monoculture -- with ground covers, grasses and wildflowers, trees and shrubs that will provide cover and food for wildlife. And lawn junkies take note: there are plenty of low-maintenance, disease-resistant grasses now on the market.</p>
        <p>Anne Raver writes about gardening for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anne Raver writes about gardening for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
