<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel Is Seeking to Ease Law On Divorce in Rabbis' Courts</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="613352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIVORCE, SEPARATIONS AND ANNULMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NAHADAR, MIRI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE1238F935A35755C0A965958260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel Is Seeking to Ease Law On Divorce in Rabbis' Courts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The details get obscure, but to cut through the thicket:</p>
        <p>Miri Nahadar entered marriage in Iran when she was only 15, and had two children, who are now 22 and 17. She emigrated to Israel with other Iranian Jews after the ayatollahs took power in 1979, found her husband unwilling to hang around for more than 5 minutes at a time and finally decided, 10 years ago, that she wanted nothing more from life than a divorce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The details get obscure, but to cut through the thicket:</p>
        <p>Miri Nahadar entered marriage in Iran when she was only 15, and had two children, who are now 22 and 17. She emigrated to Israel with other Iranian Jews after the ayatollahs took power in 1979, found her husband unwilling to hang around for more than 5 minutes at a time and finally decided, 10 years ago, that she wanted nothing more from life than a divorce.</p>
        <p>She might as well have asked for the moon.</p>
        <p>Her husband said no. Because Israel has no civil marriage or divorce, the dispute went as required to the rabbinical courts, whose judges concluded that while he was an unworthy man who should give her what she asked for, they had no power to compel him.</p>
        <p>Desperate, Mrs. Nahadar agreed a few years ago to her husband's demand for a $12,000 payment for his signature on a bill of divorce. In no time, he raised the price to $25,000. Then he made it $60,000, and she realized there would be no limit to what she regarded as plain extortion. Now, at 39, a bank teller in Jerusalem, she feels hopelessly trapped and, above all, angry at the rabbis.</p>
        <p>"They should force him to give me a divorce," she said. "He didn't buy me. I'm talking about my life." Thousands Affected</p>
        <p>In a country where social issues become intertwined with religious imperatives, thousands of people, most of them women, are similarly unable to extricate themselves from unwanted marriages as the result of economic and theological realities. Their plight is serious enough to have caught the attention of the Government, which seeks to provide relief through a new law proposed to Parliament.</p>
        <p>Under Jewish custom, a man mired in such circumstances may go off and live with another woman and, as long as she is unmarried, they may also have children, who would not be considered illegitimate. No such luck for wives in these situations, who are often afraid even to be seen with other men as long as they are technically married and who know that children born of those relationships would carry the stigma of illegitimacy for generations.</p>
        <p>"I'm alone every night, every Sabbath, every holiday," says a 25-year-old woman who has been trying for three years to persuade her husband to accept the rabbinical court's admonition to divorce her. "Sometimes he says he loves me. Sometimes he says he wants money. Sometimes he says he is doing this only to get revenge."</p>
        <p>The Orthodox rabbis who control the rabbinical courts sympathize, but insist that their hands are tied under Jewish law except in extraordinary cases. According to the law, it is the man who gives the bill of divorce. In addition, both spouses must agree. While that requirement was introduced centuries ago as a protection for women, to keep them from being summarily tossed aside by their husbands, it has boomeranged in situations like Mrs. Nahadar's. 'That Is a Bad Case'</p>
        <p>"I agree that is a bad case," said Rabbi Eliyahu Ben-Dahan, general director of the Rabbinical Courts. "But we can only suggest that he give her a divorce. We cannot force him."</p>
        <p>The Government bill before Parliament, generally welcomed by rabbis, would impose civil penalties on spouses who fail to abide by rabbinical divorce decrees within 30 days. They could lose their passports, driver's licenses, credit cards and checking accounts -- the idea being to disrupt normal life so much that they quickly get the point.</p>
        <p>Women's groups applaud the proposal, but some say it lets the rabbinical courts off the hook. In their view, the problem is not tradition but Orthodox rabbis, who, they say, ignore possible solutions that fall outside the most narrow interpretation of the law.</p>
        <p>Among the persuasive weapons at the rabbis' disposal are imprisonment and heavy fines for recalcitrant spouses. Maimonides, the great 12th-century rabbi and scholar, said that even flogging was acceptable, although Israeli law forbids it.</p>
        <p>"It would be a terrific solution," said Sharon Shenhav, legal adviser to Naamat, a women's group. "Actually, there's a well-organized system of this in ultra-Orthodox communities. They have hit squads. They even carry beepers to let each other know when the husband leaves his house. They make him an offer he can't refuse."</p>
        <p>If beatings are outlawed, Mrs. Shenhav argues, rabbis should at least send these husbands to jail. "I assure you that on the way to prison, most of them will give a divorce," she said. Uncomfortable With Force</p>
        <p>But judges acknowledge that they are uncomfortable with that tactic. Rabbi Shilo Raphael, chief rabbinical judge in Jerusalem, says he has ordered jailings only 10 times in 14 years on the court, each one a case in which the husband went well beyond reason. "If you can fight with a rifle, why use a cannon?" he said.</p>
        <p>Besides, jail does not always work.  Rejecting all offers of immediate freedom and rabbinical blessings, Yihya Avraham has preferred to stay behind bars for the last 30 years rather than divorce his wife, Ora, who left him four decades ago. He is now 80; she is 64.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Uri Regev, a Reform rabbi who heads the Israel Religious Action Center in Jerusalem, says one solution would be to permit civil divorces here, or at least to end the Orthodox monopoly. That is not likely to happen soon, though, certainly not in time for Mrs. Nahadar, who feels her biological clock ticking relentlessly away.</p>
        <p>"This can drag on another 10 years," she said. "I won't need a divorce when I'm 50."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
