<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Penobscot Bay</title>
    <meta content="WDMAIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/04/travel/WDMAINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1413157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maine</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Penobscot Bay (Me)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curtis, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine/Penobscot Bay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Maine</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDF1038F937A3575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Penobscot Bay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Penobscot Bay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE CURTIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curtis, Wayne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing On column describes upcoming events, sightseeing, lodging and restaurants along Maine's Penobscot Bay; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A safe conversation starter along the western shore of Penobscot Bay in Maine these days is to ask, ''Can you believe what's happened to . . .'' and then insert the name of Belfast or Rockland or any other town in the area.</p>
        <p>The region's transformation in the past decade has been remarkable. As long-entrenched industries have faded, the arts have blossomed. Perhaps nowhere is this more evident than in Rockland, until recently noted for its malodorous fish-processing plant. Residents once joked that it was Camden-by-the-Sea and Rockland-by-the-Smell. No more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along the western shore of Penobscot Bay, long-entrenched industries have faded while the arts have blossomed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A safe conversation starter along the western shore of Penobscot Bay in Maine these days is to ask, ''Can you believe what's happened to . . .'' and then insert the name of Belfast or Rockland or any other town in the area.</p>
        <p>The region's transformation in the past decade has been remarkable. As long-entrenched industries have faded, the arts have blossomed. Perhaps nowhere is this more evident than in Rockland, until recently noted for its malodorous fish-processing plant. Residents once joked that it was Camden-by-the-Sea and Rockland-by-the-Smell. No more.</p>
        <p>The harbor has been cleaned up, and MBNA, a major credit card company, now occupies a tidy corporate campus on a landscaped bluff overlooking lobster boats and schooners. And the city has emerged as a mini-mecca for the arts, with an outstanding art museum serving as a hub, and galleries, boutiques and restaurants dotting the attractive brick downtown.</p>
        <p>Route 1 between Rockland and Bucksport stitches together a wide assortment of cities, towns and villages ideal for lazy exploration. There are quiet islands, an impressive fleet of sailing ships for day sails or overnights, old-fashioned lobster pounds, and even a miniature mountain range great for hikes. In short, visitors will find all of summer here.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>On Aug. 10 the Kelmscott Rare Breeds Foundation, a farm on Route 52 in Lincolnville, (207) 763-4088, online at www.kelmscott.org, is host to Rare Breeds Day, with demonstrations and displays highlighting its mission of preserving rare and endangered livestock, including the Gloucestershire Old Spots pig, Kerry cattle and Cotswold sheep. General admission, $5. The farm is open daily except Monday.</p>
        <p>In Bangor, about 20 miles upriver from the mouth of the Penobscot River, the 64th National Folk Festival, (207) 947-5205, www.national folkfestival.com, kicks off at 6 p.m. Aug. 23 and runs through Aug. 25, with outdoor performances at a downtown riverside park. This is the first of three years that Maine will be host to the festival, which is sponsored in part by the National Endowment for the Arts. Acts range from polka to zydeco, hula to hip-hop, and performers from BeauSoleil (Cajun) and the Holmes Brothers (blues and gospel) to Brian Marshall and His Tex-Slavic Playboys (polka). Free.</p>
        <p>Through Aug. 30, Bay Chamber Concerts, (207) 236-2823, www.bay chamberconcerts.org, presents performances every Thursday and Friday at 8 p.m. at the historic Rockport Opera House, a white clapboard affair dating back to 1891 and seating 400 in modern padded seats. On Aug. 22 and 23, the First Chair All Star concert features principal musicians from major orchestras playing the music of Franz Schubert. The season finale stars the jazz violinist Regina Carter. Tickets are $26.</p>
        <p>The New England Auction of Antique, Classic and Special Interest Vehicles takes place Aug. 24 at the Owls Head Transportation Museum, (207) 594-4418, www.ohtm.org. With some 200 vehicles up for sale (from a 1915 Ahrens-Fox pumper truck to a 1933 Rolls-Royce town car), it's entertaining even if you're not in the market. General admission, $8. Auction preview Friday Aug. 23 from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. and from 7 a.m. on the day of the auction.</p>
        <p>More than a dozen windjammers make their summer home in Maine, and the largest gathering of the fleet occurs in Camden Harbor on Windjammer Weekend, (207) 236-4404, www.windjammerweekend.com, Aug. 30 to Sept. 1. Concerts, fireworks, boat tours and a showing of the 1937 movie ''Captains Courageous'' at the Bayview Street Cinema, just off the harbor, are part of the festivities. All events are free.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>The Farnsworth Art Museum and Wyeth Center, 16 Museum Street, Rockland, (207) 596-6457, online at www.farnsworthmuseum.org, is a compound of eclectic buildings in downtown Rockland. The Wyeth Center -- which the museum opened in 1998 in a converted white clapboard church -- is the repository for the Maine-related work of the Wyeth family. The magical paintings of N. C. Wyeth are featured on the first floor, and on the second floor (through Jan. 5) is ''Capturing Nureyev: James Wyeth Paints the Dancer,'' a traveling exhibition of paintings and drawings by his grandson. ''Themes and Variations,'' a retrospective of the Color Field pioneer Kenneth Noland, is up till Oct. 13.</p>
        <p>The best cruise bargain in Maine is the round-trip ferry between Rockland and Vinalhaven Island, (207) 596-2202. The 15-mile crossing takes 75 minutes each way, passes scenic Owls Head Light, and winds through a cluster of spruce-covered islands before arriving at Carver's Harbor. Six departures daily; the round-trip fare is $10.50, $4.50 ages 5 to 11.</p>
        <p>In Camden, a number of excellent walking trails wind through the knobby mountains of Camden Hills State Park, Route 1, (207) 941-4014, where hikers are rewarded with expansive views of the bay and its islands. Back at sea level, several outfitters lead kayaking tours, including two-hour Camden harbor tours by Maine Sport Outfitters, (800) 722-0826, www.mainesport .com, $45 adult, $35 ages 10 to 15. The tour includes a lesson in the basics, and is suitable for those who've never been in a kayak.</p>
        <p>The Lazy Jack, Camden Public Landing, (207) 230-0602, a fishing schooner built in 1947, now carries up to 13 passengers on two-hour excursions from the Camden waterfront. Before scudding out into the open bay, passengers on the wooden deck get a close look at the 1896 Curtis Island lighthouse, which sits with improbable picturesqueness atop rocky bluffs. Children must be 10 or older; the fare is $25 a person.</p>
        <p>Putting the region into its historic context -- as fabled home of sea captains and shipbuilders -- is the Penobscot Marine Museum, Route 1, Searsport, (207) 548-2529, www .penobscotmarinemuseum.org. The museum, near the head of the bay, has intriguing artifacts and maritime art spread among eight buildings in a villagelike setting, ranging from a Victorian farmhouse and barn to a brick storefront and the former town hall. Admission $8.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The Captain Lindsey House Inn, 5 Lindsey Street, Rockland, (800) 523-2145, fax (207) 596-2758, www.lindseyhouse.com, is a stout, three-story brick structure dating back to 1832 in the heart of Rockland. The nine guest rooms are decorated with bold colors and both contemporary furnishings and antiques. The first floor features a library, a guest office, a patio and a nook where a Continental breakfast, included in the rate, is served. Doubles begin at $120 between June 1 and Oct. 15, $65 off season.</p>
        <p>A short drive south of Rockland, the East Wind Inn, Tenants Harbor, (207) 372-6366, fax (207) 372-6320, www.eastwindinn.com, is a quiet waterside retreat. The 25 rooms are decorated in an unaffected grandmother's-summer-house style, with busy wallpaper and eclectic furniture. All rooms have views of the water; six share a bathroom. Doubles with private bath $159 to $299 until Sept. 9, from $139 afterward; with shared bath, $129 in summer, $109 in September.</p>
        <p>Budget: On the island of Vinalhaven is the Tidewater Motel, Carver's Harbor, (207) 863-4618, fax (207) 863-4917, www.tidewatermotel.com, built on an old granite bridge that spans the waterway between harbor and estuary. The best of the dozen rooms have balconies right over the water, from which one can closely monitor the goings-on in the harbor. Doubles $105 to $150 (from $85 after Labor Day).</p>
        <p>The Towne Motel, 68 Elm Street, Camden, (800) 656-4999, fax (207) 236-0075 and at www.midcoast.com/townemotel, offers 18 clean, basic, affordable rooms in downtown Camden within easy walking distance of the harbor and restaurants. The upstairs rooms are slightly larger and less dated; two inn-style rooms are above the office. Doubles are $90 to $115 through October, from $59 to $75 late fall through spring.</p>
        <p>Luxury: Four miles north of Camden, the Cedarholm Garden Bay, Route 1, Lincolnville, (207) 236-3886, www.cedarholm.com, consists of six shingled cottages, four of which are newly constructed and at the end of a quiet gravel road in the woods near the ocean's edge. The cottages are private, and feature hardwood floors and cathedral ceilings; two have cobblestone fireplaces, sleeping lofts and spacious kitchenettes. Oceanside doubles $259 to $295 till late October, then $175 to $225.</p>
        <p>The modern, full-service Samoset Resort, 220 Warrenton Street, Rockport, (800) 341-1650, fax (207) 594-0048, www.samoset.com, is known for its oceanside golf coursewith sweeping panoramas of the bay. The 178 large, modern rooms all have balconies or terraces, and guests at the 230-acre resort have a choice of four restaurants, indoor and outdoor pools, and numerous activities. Doubles in August, $269 to $325, from $189 in September.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Since opening two years ago, Primo, 2 South Main Street, (Route 73), Rockland, (207) 596-0770, has regularly received accolades in the national culinary news media. Melissa Kelly's sophisticated but unintimidating menu features plenty of local products, and meals are prepared more with an eye to please than to impress. If you're not in the mood for skate with green apples or beef tenderloin with mushroom and potato hash, there's simple but perfect wood-fired pizza. Primo is a few minutes' drive south of Rockland; reservations are essential during the peak summer season, although the bar can seat a few last-minute customers. Open nightly for dinner until September, then closed Tuesday. Dinner for two with wine, about $120.</p>
        <p>Marquis Restaurant, 297 Commercial Street (Route 1), Rockport, (207) 230-1226, has been a local secret for years, housed in an unassuming Camden inn. This past June, the chefs and owners, Scott Marquis and Rebecca Brown, moved to an 1872 homestead on Route 1 near the Camden-Rockport line. The appealing menu features creative offerings like lobster and mussels served with a ginger-soy butter sauce, and veal chop with a chanterelle demi-glace. Dinner for two with wine: about $100.</p>
        <p>At last count the menu at Cafe Miranda, 15 Oak Street, Rockland, (207) 594-2034, featured 38 entrees, representing a sort of potpourri of global cuisines (homemade kielbasa with local kraut, Viet-style pork-and-shrimp cakes, macaroni and cheese made with ''massive cheeses, not Kraft''). The restaurant is compact, with a friendly and informal feel. Open Tuesday through Saturday for dinner. About $70 for two, with wine.</p>
        <p>A spectacular view sometimes means so-so food, but not at Atlantica, 1 Bayview Landing, Camden, (888) 507-8514. This airy bistro offers dining indoors and out, and looks out directly on Camden's picturesque harbor. Entrees include ginger-and-brown-sugar crusted scallops with noodles, and haddock with a tropical fruit salsa. Dinner for two, with wine, about $100. Open Tuesday to Sunday for lunch and dinner.</p>
        <p>Lobster Pound Restaurant, Route 1, Lincolnville Beach, (207) 789-5550, serves hearty, basic fare overlooking a beach and ferry slip in a wonderfully austere dining room of highly varnished floors and tables. There's fresh lobster, of course, but also prime rib and roast turkey and, for dessert, Indian pudding and strawberry pie. Open daily for lunch and dinner. Lunch for two, about $30; dinner with wine, $60.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN WAYNE CURTIS, a freelance writer, lives in Maine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">WAYNE CURTIS, a freelance writer, lives in Maine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
