<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To the Point</title>
    <meta content="04FASHIOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/04/magazine/04STYLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1413365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montauk (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sischy, Ingrid</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DA143BF937A3575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To the Point</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To the Point</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ingrid Sischy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sischy, Ingrid</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ingrid Sischy article on the appeal of Montalk, LI, for fishermen, surfers, artists, writers and regular people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Montauk Point!'' Walt Whitman exclaimed in an 1861 article in The Brooklyn Standard. ''How few Americans there are who have not heard of thee -- although there are equally few who have seen thee with their bodily eyes.'' Stuck on Main Street in August in a traffic jam, witnessing crowds of people spilling out of Mr. John's Pancake House, anyone can see that things have changed a lot in the 141 years since Whitman wrote his love letter to the place, but other things, like the topography, have not. ''To a mineralogist,'' Whitman wrote, ''I fancy Montauk Point must be a perpetual feast . . . earths of all colors, and stones of every conceivable shape, hue, and destiny.'' It is these rocks and reefs that have helped make Montauk such a mecca for surfers on the East Coast.</p>
        <p>Recently, Montauk even made a fan out of Herbie Fletcher, who is West Coast surfing royalty if anyone is. Not knowing much about the sport's finer points, I asked Fletcher what it is that makes Montauk work for so many surfers. His reply: ''It's like an oldtime Waikiki, you know, where there's big boards and small waves and beautiful weather.'' Fletcher also brought up something that almost everyone who loves the place says: that it feels timeless and that even though it is so American, parts of it could also be in Africa, Greece, Ireland or Cuba. Fishermen and surfers aren't the only ones who go for Montauk in a big way. Its sense of openness, evocativeness and romance has been a magnet for a heterogenous group of locals from Ralph Lauren to Edward Albee. Artists have been drawn here for decades. This is where Mick Jagger and Keith Richards wrote ''Memory Motel,'' where Thomas Moran painted the sea and the light in the late 19th century, where Childe Hassam memorialized the lighthouse around 1920, where Andy Warhol escaped when he'd had his fill of fabulousness, where Julian Schnabel has built a painting studio that looks like a cross between a lodge in Africa and a frontier outpost in the Wild West.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Whitman to Weber, the surf's still up in Montauk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Montauk Point!'' Walt Whitman exclaimed in an 1861 article in The Brooklyn Standard. ''How few Americans there are who have not heard of thee -- although there are equally few who have seen thee with their bodily eyes.'' Stuck on Main Street in August in a traffic jam, witnessing crowds of people spilling out of Mr. John's Pancake House, anyone can see that things have changed a lot in the 141 years since Whitman wrote his love letter to the place, but other things, like the topography, have not. ''To a mineralogist,'' Whitman wrote, ''I fancy Montauk Point must be a perpetual feast . . . earths of all colors, and stones of every conceivable shape, hue, and destiny.'' It is these rocks and reefs that have helped make Montauk such a mecca for surfers on the East Coast.</p>
        <p>Recently, Montauk even made a fan out of Herbie Fletcher, who is West Coast surfing royalty if anyone is. Not knowing much about the sport's finer points, I asked Fletcher what it is that makes Montauk work for so many surfers. His reply: ''It's like an oldtime Waikiki, you know, where there's big boards and small waves and beautiful weather.'' Fletcher also brought up something that almost everyone who loves the place says: that it feels timeless and that even though it is so American, parts of it could also be in Africa, Greece, Ireland or Cuba. Fishermen and surfers aren't the only ones who go for Montauk in a big way. Its sense of openness, evocativeness and romance has been a magnet for a heterogenous group of locals from Ralph Lauren to Edward Albee. Artists have been drawn here for decades. This is where Mick Jagger and Keith Richards wrote ''Memory Motel,'' where Thomas Moran painted the sea and the light in the late 19th century, where Childe Hassam memorialized the lighthouse around 1920, where Andy Warhol escaped when he'd had his fill of fabulousness, where Julian Schnabel has built a painting studio that looks like a cross between a lodge in Africa and a frontier outpost in the Wild West.</p>
        <p>As we might expect, the locals take great pride in the fact that Montauk is so ''un-Hampton-like,'' so ''unfashiony.'' Still, something about its soul and spirit showed up on the runways of Paris this summer when Helmut Lang presented his hit men's wear collection for next spring. The time Lang had spent moseying around Montauk, poking his head in and out of surf shops, was partly what led to a line of clothes that was full of surprises and packed with a sense of style and newness but still remained tailored. As usual, Lang took that which inspired him and twisted it into a whole different ballgame. When I was talking to him about the punk surf style in his ''Next Wave'' collection, he said, ''Surfing has existed for a long time, of course, but it is even sharper and stronger and more graphic now.''</p>
        <p>The locals might be surprised by that. By now they're probably inured to the beach boys and girls in their midst. One thing is for sure -- Montauk is its own universe. As Dick Cavett, who for decades has spent long stretches of time here, wryly put it to me, ''In Montauk, you so rarely get caught in a stalled subway train.'' His equally witty wife, the actress Carrie Nye, elaborated further, using her famous Southern drawl: ''There's a sense when you do get to Montauk that you've gone somewhere. There is that huge sigh that you are away. When you come back to town, you have forgotten how to use money. You have forgotten how to wear shoes. You have forgotten how to look over your shoulder.'' Cavett and Nye, like everyone else I talked to about Montauk who spends much time there, asked me to be careful about how nice I make it sound. They want to keep it from being ''Hamptonized.'' As a recent Montaukite, I can't say I blame them. So I compromised. I promised I would write, ''Too bad it's sooooo far from New York.''</p>
        <p>Montauk Memory  ''The first time I came here was about 30 years ago, and that's when I met Peter Beard, who had just finished touring with the Stones. He was with Lee Radziwill and Bea Feitler. I felt like an appropriate thing to wear to Montauk was an old Triumph motorcycle T-shirt that said 'The Hot One.' And Truman Capote came up to me and said, 'Are you the hot one?' and I said, 'No, but I wish I was.'''</p>
        <p>Bruce Weber</p>
        <p>STYLE Ingrid Sischy is the editor of Interview magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ingrid Sischy is the editor of Interview magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
