<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turks May Face Long Road to the European Union</title>
    <meta content="04ISTA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/04/international/europe/04ISTA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1413489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7D9123BF937A3575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turks May Face Long Road to the European Union</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Turks May Face Long Road to the European Union</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL SIMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simpson, Daniel</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union's commitment to Turkey remains in doubt, even if Turkey abolishes death penalty and expands civil rights of Kurds; beneath veneer of Turkish democracy lies society where generals, who have seized power three times, still hold sway; freedom of expression is restricted to muzzle Kurdish separatists; torture remains accepted weapon of securityforces in certain circumstances (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even if Turkey truly resolves two deeply controversial issues  abolishing the death penalty and expanding the civil rights of a restive Kurdish population -- it may be misleading to think that membership in the European Union is just around the corner.</p>
        <p>The government remains divided, though polls show that two-thirds of Turks support membership, primarily in the hope of a much needed economic lift. But, as one Western diplomat put it, ''there are few signs that Turkey has the collective will to adopt the common practices of the European Union.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even if Turkey abolishes the death penalty and expands civil rights to its Kurdish population, membership in the European Union is not around the corner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even if Turkey truly resolves two deeply controversial issues  abolishing the death penalty and expanding the civil rights of a restive Kurdish population -- it may be misleading to think that membership in the European Union is just around the corner.</p>
        <p>The government remains divided, though polls show that two-thirds of Turks support membership, primarily in the hope of a much needed economic lift. But, as one Western diplomat put it, ''there are few signs that Turkey has the collective will to adopt the common practices of the European Union.''</p>
        <p>The European Union is in the midst of an expansion into the former Communist countries of Eastern Europe, but its commitment to Turkey remains in doubt. ''It's not just a problem of Turkey's seriousness about reform; the E.U. is not all that serious either,'' said another diplomat from the European Union. ''There's a lot of doubt among member states about whether Turkey really belongs in the club.''</p>
        <p>Turkey has advanced markedly, both economically and politically, since the military dictatorship of the early 1980's, leaving many Turks with little patience for lectures from Brussels bureaucrats, whom they often accuse of failing to understand them.</p>
        <p>But beneath the veneer of Turkish democracy lies a society where the generals, who have seized power three times, still hold sway.</p>
        <p>Freedom of expression is restricted to muzzle Kurdish separatists and anyone who tries to mix religion with politics, while torture remains an accepted weapon of the security forces in certain circumstances.</p>
        <p>Many Turks are frustrated with their leaders, whose feuding, cronyism and over-borrowing are blamed for plunging the economy into a downturn that led Turkey to seek a $16 billion International Monetary Fund bailout last year.</p>
        <p>Runaway inflation and the austerity demanded by the fund have cut real wages and increased unemployment. People are now pinning their hopes on the European Union, Turkey's main trading partner, hoping for a quick fix.</p>
        <p>''Joining the E.U. has become a national obsession, which everyone seems to believe will solve all of Turkey's problems at a stroke,'' said Umit Ozdag of the Center for Eurasian Strategic Studies in Ankara.</p>
        <p>Early elections are scheduled for November, with the new Parliament determining who will be prime minister.</p>
        <p>Ismail Cem, the Europhile foreign minister who resigned after nationalists blocked reforms, has formed a new party, called New Turkey. It is dedicated to integration with the European Union and is likely to attract urban voters, particularly businesspeople.</p>
        <p>A rival party, the Justice and Development Party, features figures from two parties that previously were outlawed for their Islamist overtones. It is very popular but has far fewer Western friends than Mr. Cem. The Justice Party has also rattled both secularists and generals in Turkey.</p>
        <p>The party's leader, Recep Tayyip Erdogan, was jailed as a religious fundamentalist in the 1990's after publicly reciting a poem that was deemed seditious. He was mayor of Istanbul at the time and could be banned from holding office again.</p>
        <p>Abdullah Gul, who would stand to succeed him, is campaigning on an anticorruption platform and supports European Union membership, partly because it would guarantee religious freedom. ''I don't want to establish religious rule,'' he said. ''Turkey is getting more and more open. We can't turn things back.''</p>
        <p>The treatment of Turkey's Kurds, whose guerrilla movement ended a 15-year rebellion in the southeast in 1999 after 30,000 deaths, is another hindrance to European Union membership. Not long ago, a minibus driver was convicted of supporting terrorists after an army sergeant objected to Kurdish music being played to his passengers.</p>
        <p>Turks are not convinced that the European Union would accept a Muslim country as one of its biggest members.</p>
        <p>''Most people in the E.U. are not prepared to stomach the idea of having borders with Iraq, Iran and Syria,'' said Hasan Unal, an international relations expert at Bilkent University. ''Even if they do let Turkey join, it will not be for another 20 years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
