<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nancy Sarf, Adam Feinstein</title>
    <meta content="03sarf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/03/fashion/weddings/03sarf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarf, Nancy Botta (Nancy Botta Feinstein)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feinstein, Adam Todd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D91E3EF930A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nancy Sarf, Adam Feinstein</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nancy Sarf, Adam Feinstein</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nancy Botta Sarf and Adam Todd Feinstein are to be married by Rabbi Marcia Rappaport this morning at the apartment of friends, Larry and Michele Marsh, in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, is a consultant who reviews financial reports for accuracy at F &amp; D Reports Information Clearing House in Great Neck, N.Y., which provides financial and credit consulting advice to manufacturers; she was until three years ago the vice president for operations at the firm. She graduated from Adelphi. She is a daughter of Mary Botta and Alfred R. Botta of Mineola, N.Y. Her father retired as a deputy director for administration in Manhattan with the Office of Mental Retardation and Development Disabilities of New York State. Her mother is the senior coordinator of student advisement at Adelphi's School of Education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nancy Botta Sarf and Adam Todd Feinstein are to be married by Rabbi Marcia Rappaport this morning at the apartment of friends, Larry and Michele Marsh, in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nancy Botta Sarf and Adam Todd Feinstein are to be married by Rabbi Marcia Rappaport this morning at the apartment of friends, Larry and Michele Marsh, in New York.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, is a consultant who reviews financial reports for accuracy at F &amp; D Reports Information Clearing House in Great Neck, N.Y., which provides financial and credit consulting advice to manufacturers; she was until three years ago the vice president for operations at the firm. She graduated from Adelphi. She is a daughter of Mary Botta and Alfred R. Botta of Mineola, N.Y. Her father retired as a deputy director for administration in Manhattan with the Office of Mental Retardation and Development Disabilities of New York State. Her mother is the senior coordinator of student advisement at Adelphi's School of Education.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 34, is a managing director for research at Lehman Brothers in Manhattan, where he specializes in analyzing health care stocks. He is also a chartered financial analyst. He graduated from the University of Maryland. He is a son of Donna Feinstein and Lawrence N. Feinstein of Delray Beach, Fla. His mother is a teacher's aide who works with autistic students at the Heritage Elementary School in Lake Worth, Fla. His father is the general manager of Rooms to Go in Jensen Beach, Fla., a furniture store that is part of a chain.</p>
        <p>The couple's story is a tale of love lost and found. They began dating in 1991 when Ms. Sarf, like Mr. Feinstein, was a student at the University of Maryland. They were seriously involved for two years, but then she returned to New York, while he stayed in Maryland to finish his studies. After they had gone their separate ways, she met another man, whom she married in 1994. She had three children before divorcing in 2003.</p>
        <p>''Then one day a friend of mine, Karen Inglima, asked if there were anyone from the past that I thought of, and I told her I loved Adam,'' Ms. Sarf recalled. So Ms. Inglima plugged his name into a Google search and found that his phone number at Lehman Brothers was listed. She called and left a message saying that Ms. Sarf wanted to speak with him.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Feinstein, who knew she had married and had assumed that his opportunity to be with Ms. Sarf had evaporated, heard that message, he said, ''The feeling of great happiness was surreal, but I also had a lot of anxiety not knowing the purpose of the call.''</p>
        <p>His doubts were immediately dissipated. ''It didn't feel like someone I hadn't seen in years,'' he said. ''We had such a great connection.'' And when he saw her walk into the restaurant where they met a week later, ''the world just stopped,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Even the fact that she had three children did not dissuade him. ''Being a bachelor in New York, I hadn't thought about children,'' he said, ''but it was never a concern. They just seemed like a natural extension of Nancy.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
