<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way the Beatles Remember It</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="810091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BEATLES, THE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRISON, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCARTNEY, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARR, RINGO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LENNON, JOHN (1940-80)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOZINN, ALLAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BEATLES ANTHOLOGY, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EED71239F93AA25752C1A963958260" item-length="1322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way the Beatles Remember It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOZINN, ALLAN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Beatles learned early that the quickest way to get the world's attention  was to go on television. In 1963, they had a string of No. 1 records and had been playing nonstop tours of small British theaters for years, but it wasn't until they appeared on a popular variety show, "Val Parnell's Sunday Night at the London Palladium," that October that the national press began to write about Beatlemania. When they visited the United States for the first time, four months later, they skipped the theater circuit and went directly onto "The Ed Sullivan  Show," beaming their well-tested charm directly to some 73 million viewers.</p>
        <p>Now, a quarter-century after their breakup and 15 years after John Lennon was murdered, the Beatles are returning to television. In "The Beatles Anthology," a six-hour documentary on ABC Sunday, Wednesday and Thanksgiving Day at 9 P.M., Paul McCartney, George Harrison and Ringo Starr offer what they consider the definitive telling of the Beatles' story, with ample commentary from Lennon, who covered the subject thoroughly in radio and television interviews during his lifetime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Beatles learned early that the quickest way to get the world's attention  was to go on television. In 1963, they had a string of No. 1 records and had been playing nonstop tours of small British theaters for years, but it wasn't until they appeared on a popular variety show, "Val Parnell's Sunday Night at the London Palladium," that October that the national press began to write about Beatlemania. When they visited the United States for the first time, four months later, they skipped the theater circuit and went directly onto "The Ed Sullivan  Show," beaming their well-tested charm directly to some 73 million viewers.</p>
        <p>Now, a quarter-century after their breakup and 15 years after John Lennon was murdered, the Beatles are returning to television. In "The Beatles Anthology," a six-hour documentary on ABC Sunday, Wednesday and Thanksgiving Day at 9 P.M., Paul McCartney, George Harrison and Ringo Starr offer what they consider the definitive telling of the Beatles' story, with ample commentary from Lennon, who covered the subject thoroughly in radio and television interviews during his lifetime.</p>
        <p>Included, too, are dozens of performance clips, most of them not broadcast in 30 years or more, and quite a few never shown in the United States. But undoubtedly among the show's biggest lures are the broadcast premieres of "Free  as a Bird" and "Real Love," two unfinished Lennon recordings to which the surviving Beatles have added their voices and instruments to create what they apparently feel entirely comfortable describing as new Beatles tracks. The rights to the first broadcasts of these recordings pushed the cost of the show for ABC up to a reported $20 million.</p>
        <p>The "Anthology" has actually been in the works since late 1969, just before the Beatles split up, making it probably the most slowly gestating production in television history. Originally called "The Long and Winding Road" (the name was  changed when Mr. Harrison objected that the title was too closely associated with a McCartney song), it was the brainchild of Neil Aspinall, the head of the  Beatles' own company, Apple.</p>
        <p>"I compiled as much footage as I could, from sources all over the world," said Mr. Aspinall, who joined the group's entourage as road manager in 1961. "I  edited what I had to about an hour and forty-five minutes, put the closing credits from 'Magical Mystery Tour' at the end so that people would know it was  over and sent it around to everybody to see what they thought. Then it sat on the shelf for 20 years."</p>
        <p>By "everybody" Mr. Aspinall meant the Beatles, who all approved the project but had no intention of cooperating on it or on anything else. Between 1970 and  1989, lawsuits against one another and against their record label, EMI, kept them at odds. But now and then the project did come off the shelf. In the mid-1980's, Mr. Aspinall wrote to a handful of directors and proposed that they  finish the project. Steven Spielberg, Martin Scorsese and Ridley Scott were among them. Only Mr. Spielberg responded, but he said he was too busy making "E. T."</p>
        <p>When the lawsuits were settled, the nature of the project changed. With 20 years' distance between them and Beatlemania, the surviving Beatles agreed it was time to talk about it.</p>
        <p>"We had started to regroup and get friendly again," Mr. McCartney said, "and  we thought, maybe we should do this definitive story of the Beatles. We could answer some questions that people feel have been unanswered. Lots of people have been writing books, and we figured maybe we could give our own point of view."</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspinall assembled a production team that included Chipps Chipperfield, who had been director of programming at EMI's video arm, Picture Music International, and had produced several documentaries about Mr. McCartney; Geoff Wonfor, best known for directing "The Tube," a popular British music television  series and Bob Smeaton, who signed on as writer and series director, having worked on several classical and pop-music shows.</p>
        <p>The team, which started work in 1992, has actually produced several versions  of the "Anthology." After its film incarnation, the "Anthology" was reconfigured as a video series. The first cut was a leisurely 10 hours, as the eventual home video release (due next spring) will be. But when the series was being auctioned to television companies, Mr. Aspinall found that the bidders preferred a more compact edition. So the team cut its original production in half.  A few  weeks ago, they were still tinkering, adding here and trimming there.</p>
        <p>"Certain things have been really surprising," Mr. Smeaton said. "I think most of us think of 'Sgt. Pepper' as the greatest album they made. So when we did the programs, we put together a big section on 'Sgt. Pepper.' And when the guys looked at it, they all said the same thing, without knowing what each other said, and that was, 'Why did you spend 15 minutes on "Sgt. Pepper" and only five minutes on "Rubber Soul"?' We said, 'Because it's "Sgt. Pepper." ' And they said, 'No, but to us it was just another album; we didn't think it was any better than "Rubber Soul" or "Revolver." ' So for once, you're hearing it from their side, what they really thought."</p>
        <p>There is also, of course, the music, much of which is heard uncut and uninterrupted.</p>
        <p>"When you give partial performances of songs," Mr. Smeaton said, "people feel cheated. People should be able to watch this as an event, and know that when they get to 'Strawberry Fields,' they're going to hear all of it. When they get to 'Revolution,' they're going to hear all of it. With 'Hey Jude,' it may not be all seven minutes, but it will be five and a half."</p>
        <p>Mr. Smeaton is aware that although very little Beatles video has been released officially, collectors have been trading in bootleg copies of television and concert films for years. So he has taken the trouble to become familiar with what's out there so that the programs would hold surprises even for viewers with substantial archives. Common trading items, like the 1965 Shea  Stadium concert and 1964 performances in Melbourne, Australia, and in Washington, have been restored to pristine condition.</p>
        <p>Certain familiar promotional clips, like those made for "Paperback Writer," "Strawberry Fields Forever" and "A Day in the Life" have been re-edited, incorporating unused film from the original sessions. Some of this film, Mr. Smeaton said, had never even been processed. That was also the case with some of the Beatles' own home movies, which they supplied for the show.</p>
        <p>"For me, the early television footage has been the most interesting," Mr. Chipperfield said. "There's a segment from 'Blackpool Night Out,' in 1965, and because it's a television show, the sound and the recording quality are very good, and the audience isn't very noisy. And I think when people see this, they'll realize how good they were as a live band."</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Harrison, who has typically been reluctant to discuss his Beatle past, was apparently won over by some of the film.</p>
        <p>"When we started the project," Mr. Smeaton said, "I don't think George was that into it. And when he came in to look at what we'd done, the first time, I think he came in expecting not to like it, or that it would be a painful process for him. But when he looked at it, he said, in so many words, it wasn't such a bad time after all."</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
