<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Armory for All?</title>
    <meta content="21armo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/21/arts/design/21armo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060124T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1733541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seventh Regiment Armory (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Antiques Show</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seventh Regiment Armory Conservancy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seventh Regiment Armory (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seventh Regiment Armory (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Robertson, Rebecca</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D7123FF932A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Armory for All?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Armory for All?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Announcement by Seventh Regiment Armory Conservancy that space will be transformed into institution for visual and performing arts as part of ambitious redevelopment plan creates concern among antique dealers and show organizers that they may lose crucial venue for selling their wares; conservancy officials say that only third of its programming would be devoted to such fairs in future, but major venues like currently running Winter Antiques Show would survive; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For antiques collectors roaming from booth to booth yesterday at the Seventh Regiment Armory, things seemed much the same as in previous years. Collectors cast a critical eye on silver teapots and Aubusson carpets; connoisseurs lingered in the lavish period rooms.</p>
        <p>But for dozens of dealers and show organizers across the country and abroad, the cavernous Park Avenue space was the focus of growing anxiety. An announcement on Tuesday that the armory will be transformed into an institution for the visual and performing arts raises the prospect that many entrepreneurs will lose a crucial sales point for their wares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An announcement on Tuesday that the Seventh Regiment Armory will be transformed into an institution for the visual and performing arts raises the prospect that many entrepreneurs will lose a crucial sales point for their wares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For antiques collectors roaming from booth to booth yesterday at the Seventh Regiment Armory, things seemed much the same as in previous years. Collectors cast a critical eye on silver teapots and Aubusson carpets; connoisseurs lingered in the lavish period rooms.</p>
        <p>But for dozens of dealers and show organizers across the country and abroad, the cavernous Park Avenue space was the focus of growing anxiety. An announcement on Tuesday that the armory will be transformed into an institution for the visual and performing arts raises the prospect that many entrepreneurs will lose a crucial sales point for their wares.</p>
        <p>''It's something I definitely count on,'' said Valerie Carberry, who owns a gallery in Chicago and exhibits at two armory art fairs a year. ''If I can't return to New York as an exhibitor, it would have a significant impact on my business.''</p>
        <p>The Seventh Regiment Armory Conservancy, which runs the building, said that only a third of its programming would be devoted to arts, antiques and craft fairs in the future. But it said the major ones would survive -- like the current fair, the Winter Antiques Show, running through Jan. 29, and the Modernism show, held each November.</p>
        <p>''This will continue to be the world center for art and antique shows,'' said Wade F. B. Thompson, a co-chairman of the conservancy.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Robertson, who will become chief executive of the future arts institution in March, said its mission had still to be determined. The goal is ''getting the right mix that supports our programming vision,'' she said in a telephone interview from Lincoln Center, where she is the outgoing executive director of the center's ambitious redevelopment project.</p>
        <p>Sanford Smith, who produces several art shows at the armory -- including Modernism, Works on Paper, the Antiquarian Book Fair and Art 20 -- said that forfeiting the space to a resident arts institution would hurt city revenues, not to mention his own. ''It's a major economic engine in New York City,'' he said. ''There are no alternatives in the city if the armory shuts out these shows.''</p>
        <p>Existing alternatives include the Manhattan piers and the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center. But exhibitors say these places are no match for the armory, which takes up a full square block between 66th and 67th Streets and between Park and Lexington Avenues. Its Drill Hall, site of the art fairs, measures 55,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>''The armory is fantastic,'' said Barry Friedman, a gallery owner. ''It's the nicest venue New York has for antique fairs or art fairs.'' He said the Javits Center was unattractive to many dealers and collectors, in part because of its location on the far West Side.</p>
        <p>''It's the kiss of death all the way out there,'' he said. ''It's great for refrigerators or cars, but not for art.''</p>
        <p>The armory's location in the heart of the Upper East Side, home to the old and new rich, is a real advantage, dealers say. ''Within a 10-block radius of that building, there is probably more money than anywhere else,'' Mr. Smith said. ''Because of the location, people come back a second or third time, and that's when they do their buying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said the six shows that he helped to organize included more than 600 exhibitors from around the world, many of whom could earn 30 to 40 percent of their annual income from just one armory event.</p>
        <p>Then there are the workers who pull the shows together and the ancillary businesses that benefit, like caterers and florists, he said. ''Carpenters, electricians, exposition workers and Teamsters all earn a living'' from armory shows, Mr. Smith said. ''It would eliminate a couple thousand jobs.''</p>
        <p>Charles A. Gargano, chairman of the Empire State Development Corporation, the building's landlord, said that the new and old art functions were not mutually exclusive and that exhibitors should fight to keep their slots. ''I would recommend they negotiate with the conservancy and try to make a deal,'' he said. ''All we're trying to do is to help this building survive and be renovated. It's highly underused.''</p>
        <p>The development corporation acts on behalf of the state, which owns the armory and recently negotiated a 99-year lease with the conservancy.</p>
        <p>Tom Congalton, an antiquarian bookseller in New Jersey who exhibits at the armory's New York Book Fair, said: ''My reaction is dismay. Do we need another cultural institution when there are so few venues for exhibitions of this sort?''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Robertson said there was ''no flexible open floor space'' for the visual and performing arts in the city. ''That's what we're going to offer that's different from everywhere else,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Cristyne L. Nicholas, the president of NYC &amp; Company, the city's tourism bureau, said that she knew of no economic analysis of what the armory generates in terms of tourism or tax revenue, but that a reduced roster of shows need not have an adverse impact.</p>
        <p>''I'm always concerned when there is the potential of losing exhibit space in New York City because it's so valuable,'' she said. ''But if it can be a cultural institution that can operate year round and draw visitors and residents to the armory and at the same time showcase art shows, it is a win-win.''</p>
        <p>The armory has long been talked about as a potential visual or performing arts site. The New York Philharmonic considered it as a summer home and, more recently, as a place to temporarily relocate during the planned renovation of Avery Fisher Hall. As long ago as 2000, Ms. Robertson -- a member of the conservancy board -- discussed creating a large performance space in the round for dance and theater.</p>
        <p>That year, Harvey Lichtenstein, chairman of the BAM Local Development Corporation, which is creating a cultural district centered around the Brooklyn Academy of Music in Fort Greene, wrote in support of the idea in a letter to the conservancy. ''At a time when artists are searching for unconventional spaces and initiating large-scale mixed media projects,'' he said, ''the armory would fill a huge void in the city.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Robertson said at the time that the Whitney Museum of American Art would also play a role in the restored armory. Jan Rothschild, a spokeswoman for the Whitney, said this week, ''We've been talking with them.''</p>
        <p>A renovation of the 1879 armory is expected to start in the spring of 2009 and be completed by the fall of 2010, Ms. Robertson said, at an estimated cost of $100 million to $200 million.</p>
        <p>In the short term, Ms. Robertson said, the conservancy would do some basic refurbishing, like cleaning the building and landscaping, as the search for an architect to reconceptualize Drill Hall begins. The building -- 180,000 square feet over all -- is a designated landmark, featuring 16 reception rooms by architects including Louis Comfort Tiffany and Stanford White.</p>
        <p>But the building has fallen into disrepair. Mr. Congalton said some of his buyers ''leave in disgust because they don't like the bathrooms.''</p>
        <p>And when meetings take place in the Tiffany Room, he added, people try to keep them brief so they can leave ''before the ceiling falls in.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 24, 2006, Tuesday  A credit in The Arts on Saturday with a picture of the Seventh Regiment Armory in Manhattan misspelled the photographer's given name. She is Marilynn K. Yee, not Marilyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 24, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A credit in The Arts on Saturday with a picture of the Seventh Regiment Armory in Manhattan misspelled the photographer's given name. She is Marilynn K. Yee, not Marilyn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
