<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Crowd and Conductor, a Return to the Familiar</title>
    <meta content="21phil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/21/arts/music/21phil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1733544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichler, Jeremy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masur, Kurt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Masur, Kurt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3D7123FF932A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Crowd and Conductor, a Return to the Familiar</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Crowd and Conductor, a Return to the Familiar</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY EICHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eichler, Jeremy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeremy Eichler reviews performance by New York Philharmonic conducted by Kurt Masur at Avery Fisher Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looking healthy, trim and a bit wistful, Kurt Masur returned to his old podium last night to conduct the New York Philharmonic in the first of three performances in Avery Fisher Hall. Before a single note was played, he received a familiar warm welcome from the crowd.</p>
        <p>Mr. Masur served as the orchestra's music director from 1991 to 2002. It was a lengthy tenure by Philharmonic standards, and his achievements were significant. Most fundamentally, he restored orchestral discipline and lifted performance standards to an admirably high level. He also brought to his post some deeply held convictions about music as a vehicle for social transformation, an idealism he had honed during his 26 years as a conductor and civic leader in East Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kurt Masur's conducting seemed as focused and grounded as ever on Thursday night at Avery Fisher Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looking healthy, trim and a bit wistful, Kurt Masur returned to his old podium last night to conduct the New York Philharmonic in the first of three performances in Avery Fisher Hall. Before a single note was played, he received a familiar warm welcome from the crowd.</p>
        <p>Mr. Masur served as the orchestra's music director from 1991 to 2002. It was a lengthy tenure by Philharmonic standards, and his achievements were significant. Most fundamentally, he restored orchestral discipline and lifted performance standards to an admirably high level. He also brought to his post some deeply held convictions about music as a vehicle for social transformation, an idealism he had honed during his 26 years as a conductor and civic leader in East Germany.</p>
        <p>But the Masur years at the Philharmonic were not all harmonious. To achieve his vision, Mr. Masur was reputedly tough and confrontational with the musicians, some of whom spoke out against him after he stepped down. He also clashed at times with the orchestra's executive leadership and its board. In certain quarters, his departure in 2002 was not quite a tearful goodbye.</p>
        <p>Since stepping down, Mr. Masur, 78, has hardly been lounging by the swimming pool. He now leads the London Philharmonic and the Orchestre National de France. Onstage last night, his conducting seemed as focused and grounded as ever.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, the program began and ended with core Masurian repertory. Beethoven's ''Pastoral'' Symphony came first, with Mr. Masur gently bidding the music forward in spacious, measured strides. He seemed to bear no grand interpretive agenda but was content to let the Wordsworthian scenes of rustic life roll leisurely by as if recollected in due tranquillity. The strings had a warm and smooth sheen, and the woodwinds found a fitting sweetness of tone.</p>
        <p>After intermission, the Canadian pianist Louis Lortie offered two works by Liszt: the seldom-heard ''Fantasy on Motifs from Beethoven's 'Ruins of Athens' '' and the more familiar ''Totentanz.'' A nimble and imaginative soloist, Mr. Lortie tossed off both works with a satisfying combination of thunder and insouciance.</p>
        <p>Any lingering memories of Beethoven's pastoral vistas were quickly dispersed by the evening's close, thanks to Prokofiev's ''Scythian Suite.'' Assembled in 1915 from a discarded ballet score, the work is a famously brash souvenir from the composer's early days as a would-be enfant terrible. Scored for an enormous orchestra, it quakes with heavy-hitting ostinatos and ghostly clouds of dissonance. Mr. Masur's reading possessed the wisdom of moderation, doing justice to the music's sardonic swagger without forgetting the composer's inner classicist, which was, after all, waiting just around the corner in his First Symphony.</p>
        <p>The program is repeated tonight at 8 in Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center; (212) 875-5030.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
