<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thomas Cole, Early American Pessimist</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="694307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="ART VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART (WASHINGTON)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIMMELMAN, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLE, THOMAS (1801-48)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DB1F3AF93AA25755C0A962958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thomas Cole, Early American Pessimist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Kimmelman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIMMELMAN, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"THOMAS COLE: LANDSCAPE Into History" is the latest effort by the National Museum of American Art, under its director, Elizabeth Broun, to examine art in the context of social and political history. The museum's preachifying "West as America" exhibition of 1991 argued that the grandiose landscapes of later 19th-century artists like Thomas Moran and Albert Bierstadt celebrated the westward expansion of the United States. This time the results are much better.</p>
        <p>Cole was the right man at the right time. The founding father of the Hudson River School of American landscapists, he started out in the wrong place. He was born in Lancashire, England, in 1801, the son of an industrious but hapless small-time woolens manufacturer who moved his family to the United States in 1818 looking for better luck. He didn't find it, but his son did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"THOMAS COLE: LANDSCAPE Into History" is the latest effort by the National Museum of American Art, under its director, Elizabeth Broun, to examine art in the context of social and political history. The museum's preachifying "West as America" exhibition of 1991 argued that the grandiose landscapes of later 19th-century artists like Thomas Moran and Albert Bierstadt celebrated the westward expansion of the United States. This time the results are much better.</p>
        <p>Cole was the right man at the right time. The founding father of the Hudson River School of American landscapists, he started out in the wrong place. He was born in Lancashire, England, in 1801, the son of an industrious but hapless small-time woolens manufacturer who moved his family to the United States in 1818 looking for better luck. He didn't find it, but his son did.</p>
        <p>Teaching himself to paint, learning the rudiments of landscape from a book, no less, Cole made a sketching trip up the Hudson in 1825 and out of it produced a group of works that won him immediate recognition. New York was a small city then, but even so, Cole's brief career in it (he died in 1848) was remarkable for its rapid success.</p>
        <p>He painted the Catskills and the White Mountains and scenes as far north as Mount Desert Island, Maine, when taste was growing for views of these subjects as they began to give way to encroaching development and the steam engine. His dramatic vistas of unspoiled wilderness and newly settled territories, and of picturesque tourist spots like Kaaterskill Falls minus the tourists, were paeans to an Arcadian image of America, potent visions of the young country that were already nostalgic and mythopoeic.</p>
        <p>Cole also painted historical landscapes, as he called his expressly moralizing biblical, literary and allegorical scenes. He was a deeply religious man, steeped in the works of the Romantic poets. The history paintings were inspired by those two facts and also by a couple of extended trips he took to Europe, where he painted Florence, Rome and the Roman campagna, and immersed himself in Claude, Poussin, Turner and Salvator Rosa. His crowning achievement was the five-part "Course of Empire," a series about the rise and fall of civilization worthy of Cecil B. DeMille in its refulgent spectacle.</p>
        <p>Art historians and collectors have tended to prize Cole's scenes of America for their supposed candor and as progenitors of what followed in American landscape painting but to dismiss the history paintings as cornball pretension. They can be cornball, to be sure, but lovably so. It didn't help him that he never learned how to draw a figure ("Prometheus Bound" resembles a lumpy sunbather on holiday in the Alps checking his tan). Still, there's something endearing, even moving, about Cole's earnestness.</p>
        <p>The thesis of the exhibition's organizers, William Truettner, a curator at the National Museum of American Art (he also did "The West as America"), and Alan Wallach, a professor at the College of William and Mary, is that the history paintings and the American landscapes should not be regarded as separate activities but as two sides of the same ideological coin. Both were grounded in a skepticism toward the changes brought about by Andrew Jackson's Presidency, changes based on utilitarianism and democratic principles that Cole and his rich patrons equated with mob rule. Cole's American landscapes, the curators argue, were constructed visions of a purified and already disappearing America, while paintings like "The Course of Empire" warned about the fate of a materialistic society that has lost its moral and religious bearings. The two strands of Cole's art intertwined.</p>
        <p>Mr. Truettner and Mr. Wallach make their case prudently. They have brought together 70 paintings, including both "The Course of Empire" and Cole's other major allegorical series, "The Voyage of Life." (The show remains on view here through Aug. 7, then goes to the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford; a stop at the New-York Historical Society in Manhattan has been canceled.) In the catalogue, they include an essay by Christine Stansell and Sean Wilentz, Princeton professors, that sets the historical stage for Cole's art. Mr. Truettner reviews past writings on Cole, and Mr. Wallach talks about him in relation to his patrons.</p>
        <p>Their approach is not as altogether new as they imply; the catalogue for the "American Paradise" show at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1987 covered some of the same ground, for example. And occasionally they stretch for a point that might be argued the other way round, as when Mr. Wallach sees "underlying conflict" based on fears about Jacksonianism in Cole's famous panorama "The Oxbow." To his credit, Mr. Wallach acknowledges the possibility of alternative views. His and Mr. Truettner's argument isn't at all like "The West as America" in its tone, and generally it makes sense.</p>
        <p>Certainly Cole's art is pervaded by a Romantic melancholia and reflectiveness that may well have been affected, as they suggest, by his pessimism about America's direction. There are a number of pictures about the penalties of hubris and excess: "Expulsion From the Garden of Eden," for one, a composition he shamelessly cribbed from an English contemporary, John Martin.</p>
        <p>HE BELONGED, IN THE END, TO an evangelical tradition that is as distinctly American as his scenes of the Catskills. He extolled hard work and hardship as the price of salvation and regarded unspoiled nature as "a fitting place to speak to God" (his words). At the same time, he saw everything in terms of cycles. Civilizations rise and decay, people age and die, but God, in the form of Nature, endures. One of his most accomplished paintings is "Desolation," the last installment in "The Course of Empire," a Claudian pastoral of ancient ruins that makes just this point: Nature reclaims the site where the overreaching empire flourished.</p>
        <p>Countless American landscapists built on Cole's achievement, repeating and reinterpreting the schemata he invented. Moran and Bierstadt were among them. The question this show leaves unanswered is how Cole's visions of an endangered paradise could be so easily turned into their triumphant celebrations of Manifest Destiny.  ART VIEW  Correction:  June 19, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on page 32 of the Arts and Leisure section today about an exhibition of paintings by Thomas Cole at the National Museum of American Art in Washington includes an outdated reference to the show's travel schedule. After the section went to press, the museum an nounced that the exhibition would open at the Brooklyn Museum on Jan.  13, 1995. It will also be on view, as scheduled, at the Wadsworth Athene um in Hartford beginning Sept. 11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on page 32 of the Arts and Leisure section today about an exhibition of paintings by Thomas Cole at the National Museum of American Art in Washington includes an outdated reference to the show's travel schedule. After the section went to press, the museum an nounced that the exhibition would open at the Brooklyn Museum on Jan.  13, 1995. It will also be on view, as scheduled, at the Wadsworth Athene um in Hartford beginning Sept. 11.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
