<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whose Burden In the Mideast?</title>
    <meta content="l23mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1792004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krulwich, Bruce Dov</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Awad, Mahmoud M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freedman, Shalom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riley, Esther</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC1E31F930A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whose Burden In the Mideast?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four letters comment on Sept 18 editorial suggesting that Pres Bush should try to broker peace between Israel and Palestinians; Bruce Dov Krulwich says Hamas must renounce terror and show commitment to peaceful coexistence before negotiations can be successful; Mahmoud M Awad holds that Palestinians are not problem; Shalom Freedman says Hamas has one basic item on its agenda, destruction of Israel; Esther Riley says US must lean on Israel as much as it does on Palestinians if progress is to be made</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Real Test for the Palestinians'' (editorial, Sept. 18):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Real Test for the Palestinians'' (editorial, Sept. 18):</p>
        <p>The Israeli-Palestinian peace talks in 2000, operating under the assumption that Israel will concede one-sidedly and unendingly under the threat of terror, resulted not in peace but in an intifada.</p>
        <p>President Bush has been clear that he supports peace talks, but only when terror is off the table and all are operating in the true search for peaceful coexistence.</p>
        <p>Hamas's refusal to renounce terror is consistent with its taking control of Gaza a year ago and using it only as a launching pad for missiles.</p>
        <p>It must renounce terror and show commitment to peaceful coexistence before negotiations can hope to be successful.</p>
        <p>Bruce Dov Krulwich  Beit Shemesh, Israel, Sept. 18, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a Palestinian-American, I agree that the Bush administration should not squander any opportunity to work for peace between the Palestinians and Israel. But your editorial portrays the Palestinians as the problem.</p>
        <p>You claim that all Israel has to do is ''turn over tax revenues and stop expanding settlements.'' Yet Israel is the occupier of the Palestinian people.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians have no rights or freedom. They have no control over their destiny. To top it off, they are humiliated and harassed daily.</p>
        <p>It is these conditions that breed extremism. There are numerous United Nations resolutions calling upon Israel to end its occupation, but no one enforces them.</p>
        <p>It is time for Israel to recognize the rights of the Palestinians to live in peace and security. So the real test is on Israel. We must speak out against the horrors being visited upon the Palestinian people.</p>
        <p>Mahmoud M. Awad  Riverview, Mich., Sept. 19, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Hamas has one basic item on its agenda, the destruction of Israel. It cannot distance itself from that goal even in lip service without calling into question its very reason for being.</p>
        <p>Therefore, urging the Bush administration to broker between Hamas and Israel is urging a complete absurdity.</p>
        <p>Shalom Freedman  Jerusalem, Sept. 18, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You write, ''If progress is to be made, Israel will need to turn over tax revenues and stop expanding settlements.''</p>
        <p>How right you are! The fact that Israel has gotten by with these acts can be attributed to our government's failure to insist that Israel live up to its treaties and abide by international law.</p>
        <p>The United States must lean on Israel every bit as much as it does on the Palestinians if progress is to be made.</p>
        <p>Esther Riley  Fairfax, Calif., Sept. 18, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
