<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Money Pursuing Big Prey in Europe</title>
    <meta content="21private" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/21/business/21private.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1711183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFD6123FF932A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Money Pursuing Big Prey in Europe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big Money Pursuing Big Prey in Europe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being thwarted in several big deals, some private equity firms are considering a new tack in Europe: try even bigger deals.</p>
        <p>Private equity has set its sights on some behemoths, including Centrica, the British natural gas supplier, and the French construction materials company Compagnie de Saint-Gobain, according to several executives involved in the discussions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being thwarted in several big deals, some private equity firms are considering a new tack in Europe: try even bigger deals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After being thwarted in several big deals, some private equity firms are considering a new tack in Europe: try even bigger deals.</p>
        <p>Private equity has set its sights on some behemoths, including Centrica, the British natural gas supplier, and the French construction materials company Compagnie de Saint-Gobain, according to several executives involved in the discussions.</p>
        <p>Any negotiations are at a very early stage, and private equity groups have not yet formed teams to try to take on these giants.</p>
        <p>But the sheer size of what they are considering -- Centrica has an £8.5 billion ($15 billion) market capitalization and Saint-Gobain's is 16.1 billion euros ($19.3 billion) -- is a telling indicator of the cash-abundant state of the private equity industry now.</p>
        <p>Many private equity shops have done record fund-raising this year. Buyout funds have raised $149 billion through mid-October, already besting the record of $98 billion in 2000, according to Private Equity Intelligence, a research firm. Fourteen giant funds alone raised $66 billion among them.</p>
        <p>The hard part may be spending all that money.</p>
        <p>Strategic buyers -- companies seeking to buy rivals or to enter a new market or business -- have returned to the market in force. They can often afford to offer more for a target company than a private equity investor because they can ultimately obtain savings from reducing costs, by cutting overlapping jobs or units.</p>
        <p>In May, Naguib Sawiris, the Egyptian telecommunications magnate, knocked out an alliance led by the Blackstone Group, an investment and advisory firm, to take control of the Italian mobile phone company Wind. In July, France Télécom swooped in and bought up the Spanish mobile company Amena at the last minute, knocking out two groups of private equity buyers who had put in months of work on the deal.</p>
        <p>And competition is fierce among the private equity shops themselves, driving up prices for assets to the point where some funds drop out of the bidding because they do not think they can get a decent return for their investment. At the same time, many of the small to midsize companies that would be likely targets in Europe, those with market capitalizations of less than $10 billion, have already been gobbled up.</p>
        <p>That leaves private equity shops looking for even bigger prey. Two alliances of private equity shops have been vying this fall for TDC, formerly Tele Danmark, Denmark's largest telecommunications company, which has a 66 billion kroner ($10.6 billion) market capitalization. But there is no guarantee either offer will go through, telecommunications bankers say, and there is still a threat that another telecom company may come in and win the deal.</p>
        <p>Some experts say there is no reason private equity shops cannot pursue $20 billion deals, or even larger ones. The model of a big buyout is still the $25 billion deal that Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company made for RJR Nabisco in 1989.</p>
        <p>''The ideal businesses are cash-generative businesses,'' Mark O'Hare, the managing director of Private Equity Intelligence, said. ''If it works at $1 billion, it will work at $20 billion, and there's nothing to stop that.''</p>
        <p>Both Centrica and Saint-Gobain fit that criterion.</p>
        <p>Centrica, which owns British Gas, the telecom business Onetel and the locksmith and plumbing business Dyno, had £878 million in cash flow through the first six months of 2005, up from £742 million a year earlier. The company's stock closed on Thursday at 232 pence, close to where it was a year ago. Spinning off one of the company's disparate businesses could be a good way for private equity players to try to generate quick returns, bankers say.</p>
        <p>Any attempt to buy Saint-Gobain is predicated on the French company's failing in its attempt to take over BPB, a British building materials company. BPB has repeatedly rebuffed Saint-Gobain's efforts, but may still capitulate. Saint-Gobain generated 2.6 billion euros in cash in 2004, up 5.7 percent from a year ago. The company's stock is up 5.5 percent during the year.</p>
        <p>A $20 billion deal has both advantages and risks for a private equity investor.</p>
        <p>Private equity firms generally put up a small percentage of their capital for a buyout, and finance the rest with debt. They are reluctant to allocate a substantial portion of any fund to one company.</p>
        <p>If they aimed for a takeover of $20 billion or more, any alliance would have to include so many private equity players that there might be too few left out to form a rival bid, keeping competition down.</p>
        <p>Even though money is plentiful, there are still some natural limits to what private equity buyers can purchase, because of the complications from involving the number of firms necessary to put together a big deal.</p>
        <p>''You can get into tricky territory much above $20 billion,'' William Maltby, European head of financial sponsors at Deutsche Bank, said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
