<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="21bizdigest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1711214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DF133FF932A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ford Plans Plant Closings in Restructuring After Reporting a Quarterly Loss of $284 Million  The Ford Motor Company will announce a restructuring of its American operations in January that will include plant closings and job cuts, the company's chief executive, William Clay Ford Jr., said. His statement came as his company reported a $284 million loss in the third quarter, its first quarterly loss since the final three months of 2003. The company said it lost $1.49 billion, before taxes, in its North American automotive operations. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>The United Auto Workers announced the details of its tentative agreement with General Motors and said that for the first time, G.M.'s union retirees will have to pay deductibles, monthly premiums and co-payments. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Google Tops Expectations with Third-Quarter Profit  Finding more ways to make money from its spot as the world's most popular Internet search engine, Google topped Wall Street expectations and its own forecast and posted sharply higher profit in the third quarter. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Congress Passes Lawsuit Shield Law for Gun Industry  Congress delivered a long-sought victory to the gun industry when the House voted to shield firearms manufacturers and dealers from liability lawsuits. The bill now goes to President Bush, who has promised to sign it. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Medical Publication Questions a Diabetes Drug  An article in the Journal of the American Medical Association said the proposed diabetes pill Pargluva seems to significantly increase risks of heart attacks and strokes, and an accompanying editorial said the drug's sponsors, Bristol-Myers Squibb and Merck, had submitted misleading data to the Food and Drug Administration that ''may have fostered an illusion of safety.'' [C7.]</p>
        <p>Roche has agreed to meet with four generic drug companies to discuss allowing them to manufacture the anti-influenza drug Tamiflu, which is in short supply as countries stockpile it to prepare for a possible flu pandemic. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Facing increasing generic competition and concerns about the heart risks of Celebrex, its once-popular painkiller, Pfizer said its third-quarter profit fell 50 percent, to $1.6 billion, and its sales fell 5 percent from the year earlier period. Profit for the current quarter will fall far short of analysts' forecasts, the company said and its shares fell 8 percent. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Advertising Executive Resigns Over Remarks  Neil French, a well-known advertising executive and worldwide creative consultant at WPP Group, the world's second-largest agency holding company, resigned his position amid an uproar over remarks he made at an industry event about female creative executives. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SBC's Profit Falls on Costs of Hurricane and a Merger  SBC Communications said its profit slipped 41 percent in the third quarter partly because its wireless unit, Cingular, had higher costs related to hurricanes and its merger with AT&amp;T Wireless. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Senate Panel Approves Digital Television Measure  A Senate panel approved legislation to complete the slow migration from analog to digital television by 2009, a transition of enormous importance to the television, cable and wireless telephone industries. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Nigeria Reaches Deal to Pay Debts at a Discount  Nigeria reached an agreement with the Paris Club of creditors to pay off $30 billion of debt for $12 billion, a significant breakthrough for a nation long deemed too wealthy with oil money and too corrupt to be granted relief from debt accumulated over years of misrule. [A14.]</p>
        <p>Chinese Economy Grew 9.4 Percent in Third Quarter  China's roaring economy grew 9.4 percent in the third quarter of this year, fueled by surging exports, strong investments in infrastructure and solid retail sales, according to a government report. [C4.]</p>
        <p>China's rapid economic growth has fostered a tourist boom among the mainland Chinese, with Southeast Asia the favorite destination, at least for now. And, like travelers for centuries before them, they are developing a reputation, which some say is loud and obnoxious. [C1.]</p>
        <p>After a quarter-century of growth powered largely by exports, China is showing signs of opening a new chapter of strong growth, this time propelled by domestic spending. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Europe Fails Again to Reach Deal for Lower Farm Tariffs  The European Union failed again to deliver new cuts in its farm tariffs and subsidies, held back by France's refusal to allow deeper reductions, while other trading nations laid pressure on Europe to act. Brazil's foreign minister, Celso Amorim, left, who has become a spokesman for developing nations in these talks, urged Europe to break the logjam. [C13.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Fall Sharply on Report of High Inflation  Stocks sold off sharply, pushing the three major gauges down more than 1 percent, after a major inflation gauge hit a 25-year high and stirred fears of higher interest rates, while Pfizer posted disappointing quarterly results. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 133.03 points, to 10,281.10. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index sank 17.96 points, to 1,177.80. The Nasdaq composite index dropped 23.13 points, to 2,068.11. [C7.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ford Plans Plant Closings in Restructuring After Reporting a Quarterly Loss of $284 Million  The Ford Motor Company will announce a restructuring of its American operations in January that will include plant closings and job cuts, the company's chief executive, William Clay Ford Jr., said. His statement came as his company reported a $284 million loss in the third quarter, its first quarterly loss since the final three months of 2003. The company said it lost $1.49 billion, before taxes, in its North American automotive operations. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>The United Auto Workers announced the details of its tentative agreement with General Motors and said that for the first time, G.M.'s union retirees will have to pay deductibles, monthly premiums and co-payments. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Google Tops Expectations with Third-Quarter Profit  Finding more ways to make money from its spot as the world's most popular Internet search engine, Google topped Wall Street expectations and its own forecast and posted sharply higher profit in the third quarter. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Congress Passes Lawsuit Shield Law for Gun Industry  Congress delivered a long-sought victory to the gun industry when the House voted to shield firearms manufacturers and dealers from liability lawsuits. The bill now goes to President Bush, who has promised to sign it. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Medical Publication Questions a Diabetes Drug  An article in the Journal of the American Medical Association said the proposed diabetes pill Pargluva seems to significantly increase risks of heart attacks and strokes, and an accompanying editorial said the drug's sponsors, Bristol-Myers Squibb and Merck, had submitted misleading data to the Food and Drug Administration that ''may have fostered an illusion of safety.'' [C7.]</p>
        <p>Roche has agreed to meet with four generic drug companies to discuss allowing them to manufacture the anti-influenza drug Tamiflu, which is in short supply as countries stockpile it to prepare for a possible flu pandemic. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Facing increasing generic competition and concerns about the heart risks of Celebrex, its once-popular painkiller, Pfizer said its third-quarter profit fell 50 percent, to $1.6 billion, and its sales fell 5 percent from the year earlier period. Profit for the current quarter will fall far short of analysts' forecasts, the company said and its shares fell 8 percent. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Advertising Executive Resigns Over Remarks  Neil French, a well-known advertising executive and worldwide creative consultant at WPP Group, the world's second-largest agency holding company, resigned his position amid an uproar over remarks he made at an industry event about female creative executives. [C1.]</p>
        <p>SBC's Profit Falls on Costs of Hurricane and a Merger  SBC Communications said its profit slipped 41 percent in the third quarter partly because its wireless unit, Cingular, had higher costs related to hurricanes and its merger with AT&amp;T Wireless. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Senate Panel Approves Digital Television Measure  A Senate panel approved legislation to complete the slow migration from analog to digital television by 2009, a transition of enormous importance to the television, cable and wireless telephone industries. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Nigeria Reaches Deal to Pay Debts at a Discount  Nigeria reached an agreement with the Paris Club of creditors to pay off $30 billion of debt for $12 billion, a significant breakthrough for a nation long deemed too wealthy with oil money and too corrupt to be granted relief from debt accumulated over years of misrule. [A14.]</p>
        <p>Chinese Economy Grew 9.4 Percent in Third Quarter  China's roaring economy grew 9.4 percent in the third quarter of this year, fueled by surging exports, strong investments in infrastructure and solid retail sales, according to a government report. [C4.]</p>
        <p>China's rapid economic growth has fostered a tourist boom among the mainland Chinese, with Southeast Asia the favorite destination, at least for now. And, like travelers for centuries before them, they are developing a reputation, which some say is loud and obnoxious. [C1.]</p>
        <p>After a quarter-century of growth powered largely by exports, China is showing signs of opening a new chapter of strong growth, this time propelled by domestic spending. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Europe Fails Again to Reach Deal for Lower Farm Tariffs  The European Union failed again to deliver new cuts in its farm tariffs and subsidies, held back by France's refusal to allow deeper reductions, while other trading nations laid pressure on Europe to act. Brazil's foreign minister, Celso Amorim, left, who has become a spokesman for developing nations in these talks, urged Europe to break the logjam. [C13.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Fall Sharply on Report of High Inflation  Stocks sold off sharply, pushing the three major gauges down more than 1 percent, after a major inflation gauge hit a 25-year high and stirred fears of higher interest rates, while Pfizer posted disappointing quarterly results. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 133.03 points, to 10,281.10. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index sank 17.96 points, to 1,177.80. The Nasdaq composite index dropped 23.13 points, to 2,068.11. [C7.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
