<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arafat Tells Clinton Israel's 10% Pullback Offer Is Short</title>
    <meta content="Y23MID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6D7173BF930A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1241" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arafat Tells Clinton Israel's 10% Pullback Offer Is Short</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat, in talks with Pres Clinton at White House, rejects Israel's offer to withdraw from less than 10 percent of West Bank in three phases over several months; moves toward meeting Israeli demands on revision of Palestinian charter and further security cooperation; Israel wants to carry out only one withdrawal from West Bank before final settlement is reached, while Arafat is insisting that there be three, as Israel agreed to in earlier accords; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In talks here this week with President Clinton, Israel offered a withdrawal from less than 10 percent of the West Bank, in three phases over several months, officials on all sides said today. But the Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat told Mr. Clinton in his own talks today that the offer was insufficient, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, in a series of talks today and tonight, moved some way toward meeting Israeli demands on the revision of the Palestinian charter and further security cooperation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In talks here this week with President Clinton, Israel offered a withdrawal from less than 10 percent of the West Bank, in three phases over several months, officials on all sides said today. But the Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat told Mr. Clinton in his own talks today that the offer was insufficient, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, in a series of talks today and tonight, moved some way toward meeting Israeli demands on the revision of the Palestinian charter and further security cooperation.</p>
        <p>But a significant gap remains, in that Israel wants to carry out only one withdrawal from the West Bank before a final settlement is reached, while Mr. Arafat is insisting that there be three, as Israel agreed to in earlier accords, and that each one be ''credible.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Arafat met with Mr. Clinton, Vice President Al Gore, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright and the Director of Central Intelligence, George J. Tenet, details of Israeli and Palestinian positions became more clear, as did some American ideas to bridge the slowly narrowing gaps between them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat agreed with an American proposal that the two other withdrawals agreed to in the 1993 and 1995 Oslo accords take place after  talks on a final settlement begin, the officials said. More important than the exact size of the first redeployment, Mr. Arafat told Mr. Clinton, is the principle that the Israelis talk to the Palestinians about it, and not just decide on it on their own.</p>
        <p>In talks with Mr. Clinton earlier this week, Prime Minister Benjamin  Netanyahu of Israel said he would agree to only one withdrawal, matched by reciprocal Palestinian actions against terrorism, before final-status negotiations on a permanent settlement are held. Those talks will determine the final borders to which Israel will withdraw. Israel also argued that the Oslo accords allow the Israelis alone to decide the size of interim redeployments, with no need to negotiate them with the Palestinians or the Americans.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging that the Israeli interpretation is legally correct, American officials responded  that the ''spirit'' of the accords, which embody mutual recognition between the Israelis and the Palestinians, means that Palestinian concerns and sensitivities should also be taken into account.</p>
        <p>The Americans would also like the initial, phased Israeli withdrawal to take place over several weeks, not  several months, the officials say, and to contain two phases. They also said  Mr. Netanyahu is seeking too much specific reciprocity.</p>
        <p>Since both sides are trying to set out their best possible positions before entering final-status talks, American officials say compromises on key issues are possible.</p>
        <p>They are urging Israeli and Palestinian leaders to think through their responses to the American proposals  and to come up with new ideas for a meeting of Mr. Netanyahu, Mr. Arafat and Ms. Albright in about two weeks. The Israelis asked that the meeting take place in the Middle East, while the Americans prefer Europe, the officials say.</p>
        <p>Ms. Albright has said she will return to the Middle East only when there is an accomplishment in the long-stalled peace effort. But even if the meeting produces a joint communique of essential agreement, officials said it would probably be followed by a second meeting, after Mr. Netanyahu reports to his Government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu, for example, is insisting that the Palestinians alter their charter in a formal way, with a new vote by the Palestine National Council, the Palestinian legislature, to excise clauses calling for the destruction of Israel.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Arafat brought Mr. Clinton a detailed letter listing the clauses that have been excised, said the State Department spokesman, James P. Rubin.</p>
        <p>Yossi Beilin, an Israeli Labor Party politician who took a key role in negotiating the accords in which Mr. Arafat promised to alter the charter, saw the letter a few days ago and said it fully meets Mr. Arafat's obligations, Israeli officials say. But Mr. Netanyahu's Likud Government is likely to reject the letter as insufficient, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials say they need produce a new charter only when they gain a state of their own, which can serve as its constitution. To insist on a new formal charter before then is unreasonable, they say, because Mr. Arafat has already met his commitment to rescind the offending clauses in the accords he signed in 1993 and 1995.</p>
        <p>The final-status talks should also be accompanied, the Americans and the Palestinians say, by a ''time out'' from any Israeli construction of new settlements on the West Bank and from other actions perceived as provocative that prejudge the final-status negotiations. Israeli officials say they do not have any desire to derail  the talks once they begin.</p>
        <p>The heart of the problem, said  James J. Zogby, president of the American Arab Institute, one of the most prominent spokesmen for Arab Americans, is that the Palestinians and the Israelis assumed at Oslo that after a third withdrawal, Israel would retain some parts of the West Bank for security purposes, but that most of it would become a Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu's Government, however, has indicated that it intends to keep a large part of the West Bank in any final settlement, Mr. Zogby said. That is unacceptable to  Mr. Arafat, who wants to get as much land under his control as he can before final negotiations.</p>
        <p>Saeb Erekat, Mr. Arafat's lead negotiator, said Mr. Clinton told Mr. Arafat today, ''I don't accept what Netanyahu is offering but I can't accept what you are demanding.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat has been reported to be asking for an initial withdrawal from 30 percent of the West Bank; some American officials think 15 percent could work as a compromise if it delivers the final-status talks that Mr. Netanyahu insists on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zogby said he was pleased that for the first time today Mr. Clinton spoke of a settlement where ''the Palestinians can realize their aspirations to live as a free people,'' while ''the Israelis can live in security, recognized by all their neighbors.''</p>
        <p>That expression is close to calling for Palestinian statehood, he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Albright, at a brief news conference, said that both leaders were working hard on hard problems, and that Mr. Clinton was playing an unusually active role in pushing them toward compromise.</p>
        <p>''I do expect at some stage I will try to get a trilateral meeting,'' she said. ''But we need some results soon. We can't go on with endless meetings.''</p>
        <p>With his meetings lasting into the night, there was no indication whether Mr. Arafat would take up an invitation to visit the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, officials said.</p>
        <p>The museum spokeswoman, Mary Morrison, said she did not rule out a visit on Friday, but Palestinian officials said Mr. Arafat was being told by some of his advisers that a visit now, after the controversy over his invitation, might make him look weak in the eyes of some Arab leaders. American officials said a visit might not take place this week at all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
