<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Festivals Or Short Runs</title>
    <meta content="23VIDA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HOME VIDEO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D8163BF930A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Festivals Or Short Runs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Home Video column on upcoming release of several little films from promising young directors and independent distributors; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week the independently produced movie is enjoying its annual due at the Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah. By this time next week, though, home video will have an unusually active independent scene of its own.</p>
        <p>Dealers would prefer it differently, of course. A big new studio movie or two each week stokes activity around the new-releases section, but with the exception of ''The Game,'' a middling thriller with Michael Douglas, video hasn't had a big new movie all month. In fact, on Tuesday (the day most videos are released) perhaps the best-known addition will be Jacques Demy's 34-year-old ''Umbrellas of Cherbourg,'' available in a new edition from Fox Lorber.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This week the independently produced movie is enjoying its annual due at the Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah. By this time next week, though, home video will have an unusually active independent scene of its own.</p>
        <p>Dealers would prefer it differently, of course. A big new studio movie or two each week stokes activity around the new-releases section, but with the exception of ''The Game,'' a middling thriller with Michael Douglas, video hasn't had a big new movie all month. In fact, on Tuesday (the day most videos are released) perhaps the best-known addition will be Jacques Demy's 34-year-old ''Umbrellas of Cherbourg,'' available in a new edition from Fox Lorber.</p>
        <p>Otherwise next week's roster is filled with an unusual profusion of little movies from promising new directors and independent distributors, all of which drew attention at festivals or received good reviews during theater runs that were too brief to earn them much awareness with potential audiences.</p>
        <p>None of the films will get a Schwarzenegger welcome in stores,  but video is often handed much worse than ''Gravesend,'' for example, a gritty story of the Brooklyn streets made by Salvatore Stabile, a 22-year-old with chutzpah and talent who received $60,000 to finish a movie he originally shot for $5,000. The film, about a bunch of bumbling low-lifes who rove the streets filling up a car trunk with bodies, is ''presented'' by Oliver Stone and earned Mr. Stabile an invitation from Steven Spielberg's Dreamworks Studios to make two more movies under more monied circumstances.</p>
        <p>Another of next week's touted coming attractions is ''Star Maps,'' a film by Miguel Arteta about an 18-year-old Mexican boy (Douglas Spain) who aspires to be an actor but is recruited by his father to be a male prostitute on the streets of Los Angeles. The film, his first feature, was bought by Fox Seachlight last year at Sundance and earned strongly favorable critical notice before disappearing in a flash from theaters.</p>
        <p>Also available next Tuesday will be Angela Pope's ''Hollow Reed,'' a small British film about child abuse, homophobia and a horrendous family break-up, and John Irvin's nicely malevolent film noir ''City of Industry,'' with Harvey Keitel and Stephen Dorff as jewel thieves in an artfully run-down Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>This Tuesday there was ''Cafe Society,'' Raymond De Felitta's evocatively atmospheric little film based on the infamous Mickey Jelke-Patricia Ward prostitution case of 1952. ''The rare 50's piece that gets it right,'' Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Now one can only hope that video stores follow suit and direct viewers to these films and others like them.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a nominal theater release or appeared on television.</p>
        <p>THE DEANNA DURBIN COLLECTION. At MGM in the 1930's she lost out to Judy Garland, but Ms. Durbin went on to Universal and made several notable musical comedies. In ''Something in the Wind" (1947, 89 minutes), with Donald O'Connor, she is kidnapped by a fellow who thinks she's the former mistress of his late uncle. In ''Up in Central Park'' (1948, 88 minutes), a crooked politician (Vincent Price) tries to use her for his own gain. And in ''For the Love of Mary'' (1948, 91 minutes), a White House switchboard operator (Ms. Durbin) juggles three suitors (after which the actress retired from the screen and moved to France). Universal. $19.98. each.  EXPRESSO BONGO and BEAT GIRL. The first of two films set in the London rock world of the late 1950's and early 60's, ''Expresso Bongo'' (1959, 111 minutes) stars Laurence Harvey as a sleazy talent agent who comes up with a hot bongo player (Cliff Richard) but loses him to a pushy American (Yolande Donlan). In ''Beat Girl'' (1960, 85 minutes), a pouty teen-age Bardot type (Gillian Hills) prowls the city's clubs and basement dives, resentful of her father's French girlfriend and ripe for exploiting by a ruthless strip-joint operator (Christopher Lee). Kino. $24.95 each. Release date: Tuesday. Information: (800) 562-3330.  LAVERNE AND SHIRLEY: THE COLLECTOR'S EDITION. Four episodes in the lives of those bottle-cappers at the Shotz Brewery, brash Laverne (Penny Marshall) and prim Shirley (Cindy Williams). The cassette includes ''The Society Party,'' the premiere episode of the 70's sitcom, and informative liner notes. Columbia House. $19.95. Information: (800) 638-2922.</p>
        <p>HOME VIDEO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
