<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="17PUBL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poison Ivy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">l'Association des Maitres Cuisiniers de France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menes, Yves</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gin Lane (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DB133DF934A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Alex Kuczynski and Phoebe Hoban</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column notes that author James Brady attended party celebrating publication of his novel Gin Lane even though he is suffering from poison ivy; also notes that Metropolitan Club executive chef Yves Menes was named chef of year by l'Association des Maitres Cuisiniers de France at ceremony in Essex, Vt; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No Writer's Block, But Writer's Itch</p>
        <p>JAMES BRADY, a columnist for Advertising Age and Parade magazines, was not being a schmoozy and glad-handing author at the party celebrating the publication of his new novel, ''Gin Lane'' (St. Martin's Press).</p>
        <p>Schmoozy he was. But with absolutely no glad-handing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No Writer's Block, But Writer's Itch</p>
        <p>JAMES BRADY, a columnist for Advertising Age and Parade magazines, was not being a schmoozy and glad-handing author at the party celebrating the publication of his new novel, ''Gin Lane'' (St. Martin's Press).</p>
        <p>Schmoozy he was. But with absolutely no glad-handing.</p>
        <p>Poison ivy, you know.</p>
        <p>''I was out pulling weeds in the garden,'' Mr. Brady explained, his skin a pastiche of pinks and reds. ''I don't know anything about botany. I could be pulling up champion roses or rare botanicals, so when I pulled up the poison ivy, I guess it just didn't register.''</p>
        <p>Though he was not gripping and grinning at the book party, he did manage some physical contact. ''I can still slink my arm around a woman's shoulders and pull her close to me,'' he said. Assuming, of course, that she is wearing long sleeves.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brady's previous page-turner, ''Further Lane'' (St. Martin's, 1997), looked at the celebrity-driven whirl of East Hampton, N.Y., where the poison-ivy garden is. ''Further Lane'' drew attention because it dropped the names of real people. Mr. Brady said that MARTHA STEWART, who was mentioned, still refuses to discuss it with him. (Well, what do you expect when you kill off a lifestyle-guru character who obviously resembles her with a privet-hedge stake to the heart?)q</p>
        <p>''Gin Lane'' is set in nearby Southampton and revolves around an early-morning radio personality a lot like DON IMUS.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brady's formula of naming novels for well-manicured streets in the Hamptons seems to be working: he said that he would call the next one Lily Pond Lane, a thoroughfare one block from the beach in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>''It was either that or Nathan Lane,'' he groaned as he set down his drink, grimaced and scratched his neck.</p>
        <p>Food Notes</p>
        <p>YVES MENES, the executive chef at the Metropolitan Club, was named chef of the year by l'Association des Maitres Cuisiniers de France at a ceremony in Essex, Vt. ''Who would have thought they would come all the way from France and beyond to beautiful Vermont,'' said Mr. Menes, whose flight was delayed at takeoff because of engine trouble and arrived 90 minutes late. That was not his only airplane problem: the silver trophy he won was too big to take with him as carry-on luggage on his flight home to Manhattan. Solution: he entrusted it to JEAN-YVES PIQUET, the executive chef at the University Club, who was driving to New York. . . . PAUL NEWMAN, whose Newman's Own brand has raised more than $90 million for charity, told PATRICIA POE of The Free Press in Rockland, Me., that he was ''thinking of coming out with an ice cream called 'Soft Porn.' '' Mr. Newman, who was in Maine shooting the LUKE MANDOKI film ''Message in a Bottle,'' added, ''I would love to get public reaction.'' Ms. Poe wrote that as ''kind of an afterthought,'' Mr. Newman said, ''People take themselves so seriously -- it just drives me nuts.'' In New York, where people take things (but never themselves) seriously, a spokeswoman for Newman's Own said, ''There's nothing to it on our end.''</p>
        <p>Out and About</p>
        <p>The only thing missing as MILTON BERLE, 89, celebrated his Methuselah-like career was a rim shot. ''We were sitting on the couch one night,'' he told the crowd at the Fifth Avenue apartment of the songwriter DENISE RICH, ''and she asked if we could go upstairs and make love. I said, 'Honey, you can only do one or the other.' '' . . . ''I love it,'' the Internet gossip MATT DRUDGE said of the media magazine Brill's Content. Mr. Drudge, who wore a Walter Winchell-style hat to a party celebrating the first issue, added, ''I'll be covering it aggressively -- coverage of the coverage of the coverage.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Alex Kuczynski and Phoebe Hoban</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
