<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Air France Backs Stock Swap in a Union With KLM</title>
    <meta content="Y30AIR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/30/business/worldbusiness/30AIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1523556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Klm Royal Dutch Airlines Nv</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Air France</org>
        <org class="online_producer">British Airways Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Airlines</org>
        <org class="online_producer">SkyTeam</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7D7113DF933A0575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Air France Backs Stock Swap in a Union With KLM</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Air France and KLM to Merge and Create 3rd-Largest Airline</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Air France's board approves proposed stock swap with KLM shareholders; no deal has been reached; labor union representatives on Air France's board oppose proposal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sweeping combination of Air France and KLM moved closer tonight when Air France's board approved a proposed stock swap with KLM shareholders, a member of the board said. If the deal wins the approval of KLM, the big Dutch airline; of the French and Dutch governments; and of regulators on both sides of the Atlantic, the combination would surpass British Airways to become Europe's largest airline company.</p>
        <p>A KLM spokesman in the Netherlands said earlier today that while the airlines had been in continuous discussions, no deal had been reached. But KLM's board was meeting tonight to formulate a response to the Air France proposal, a Dutch radio broadcast said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The boards of Air France and KLM have agreed to a sweeping combination of two of Europes largest airlines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sweeping combination of Air France and KLM moved closer tonight when Air France's board approved a proposed stock swap with KLM shareholders, a member of the board said. If the deal wins the approval of KLM, the big Dutch airline; of the French and Dutch governments; and of regulators on both sides of the Atlantic, the combination would surpass British Airways to become Europe's largest airline company.</p>
        <p>A KLM spokesman in the Netherlands said earlier today that while the airlines had been in continuous discussions, no deal had been reached. But KLM's board was meeting tonight to formulate a response to the Air France proposal, a Dutch radio broadcast said.</p>
        <p>Labor union representatives on Air France's board had opposed the proposal. One, Yvon Touil of the leftist General Confederation of Labor, told reporters about some details of the plan at the conclusion of the board meeting.</p>
        <p>The proposal would make each airline a wholly owned subsidiary of a new holding company based in Paris, he said; Air France shareholders would get about 85 percent of the new company's equity and KLM shareholders the rest. The deal would take the legal form of a capital increase by Air France.</p>
        <p>The board meeting adjourned without issuing a statement. Air France's chairman, Jean-Cyril Spinetta, is expected on Tuesday to announce the board's decision to approve a letter of intent for the deal. The French government has made clear it would support the proposal.</p>
        <p>In the 12 months ended March 31, Air France and KLM together had 19.7 billion euros ($22.6 billion) in revenue; by comparison, American Airlines' revenue in the period was $17.3 billion.</p>
        <p>Investors bid up Air France shares 1.3 percent today, to 13.69 euros, in anticipation of a deal; KLM rose just under 1 percent, to 11.96 euros.</p>
        <p>The proposal would finesse two problems facing cross-border airline mergers. One is the Dutch government's unwillingness to allow a foreign country to have majority control of a Dutch airline; the proposed merger would dilute the French government's current 54 percent stake in Air France to about 45 percent of the new holding company.</p>
        <p>The other problem is the potential loss of KLM's landing rights outside the European Union under aviation treaties that depend on the nation of ownership of each airline. The proposal would keep KLM technically Dutch by creating a special Dutch nonprofit foundation that would hold 51 percent of its voting rights, though none of its equity.</p>
        <p>Referring to the proclamation of an intended marriage, François Cabrera, a representative at Air France of another labor union, said, ''The wedding banns have been published.'' He spoke after union leaders had been briefed by Mr. Spinetta but before the board voted on the proposal.</p>
        <p>The union leaders said they were told that Air France hoped a merger would lead to savings of 400 million euros ($458 million) over five years, which some analysts called modest.</p>
        <p>The combination would bring KLM into the SkyTeam alliance set up in June 2000, led by Air France and Delta; it includes Aeroméxico, Alitalia, CSA Czech Airlines and Korean Air. Adding KLM would make SkyTeam the largest such grouping, surpassing the Star Alliance led by Lufthansa and United. Mr. Touil said a committee of four executives each from KLM and Air France would examine the carriers' fleets, networks and alliances.</p>
        <p>The possibility of a merger has provoked strong feelings in the Netherlands, a small country with little need for domestic flights. KLM is the oldest international airline in the world and a source of national pride that some Dutch people fear would be swallowed up in a merger. The government of Prime Minister Jan Peter Balkenende has expressed concern about jobs at Schiphol Airport, KLM's hub.</p>
        <p>In France, a deal would allow the government to meet a goal of reducing its stake in Air France despite soft stock markets.</p>
        <p>Emmanuel Jahan, another Air France union leader, told reporters that the board of the new holding company would consist of 16 directors -- 11 French, 4 Dutch and one representing Alitalia, which owns 2 percent of Air France stock. Alitalia has applied political pressure in recent weeks not to be excluded from any Air France deal with KLM.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
