<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accounts Chock-Full, Or a Plan Half Empty?</title>
    <meta content="Y01IMP$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/01/business/01IMPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1D81438F932A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accounts Chock-Full, Or a Plan Half Empty?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Accounts Chock-Full, or a Plan Half Empty?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House proposal to simplify and expand tax-preferred savings accounts may not increase savings, according to economists, who say that its main impact may be to tilt tax system away from its current bias in favor of immediate consumption; at same time if it becomes law, it is expected to shift some tax revenue from distant future to present; table gives overview of Bush administration's proposed sweeping overhaul of savings and retirement accounts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House's proposal to simplify and expand tax-preferred savings accounts has just one problem: it may not increase saving.</p>
        <p>Instead, economists say, its main impact may be to tilt the tax system away from its current bias in favor of immediate consumption. At the same time, if it becomes law, it is expected to shift some tax revenue from the distant future to the present.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NewsAnalysis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House's proposal to simplify and expand tax-preferred savings accounts has just one problem: it may not increase saving.</p>
        <p>Instead, economists say, its main impact may be to tilt the tax system away from its current bias in favor of immediate consumption. At the same time, if it becomes law, it is expected to shift some tax revenue from the distant future to the present.</p>
        <p>Since Congress approved the first I.R.A.'s in 1974, economists have tried to measure whether people use such programs to save more or just transfer money from existing saving accounts that lack a tax advantage. The evidence has been mixed. Yet skepticism over the administration's latest proposal was widespread, even uniting academics who have long disagreed about the effects of tax-preferred plans on household saving.</p>
        <p>''When one thinks, 'Are we going to get a lot more saving out of this?' I just don't know,'' said David A. Wise, a professor at Harvard whose research indicates that I.R.A.'s and 401(k)s promote extra saving.</p>
        <p>His sometime rival, John Karl Scholz, a professor of economics at the University of Wisconsin at Madison, was even more dismissive. ''My best guess is that this would reduce private saving in aggregate,'' Professor Scholz said, ''rather than increase private saving.''</p>
        <p>Despite their differences, both economists agree that few people are constrained by current limits on contributions to I.R.A.'s and 401(k) plans. So the higher limits in the administration's proposal might not have much effect on saving.</p>
        <p>The new program would allow individuals to put away up to $15,000 of their after-tax income each year into two separate accounts, with no taxes on any earnings from their saving. Each year, the maximum contribution would rise with inflation. All the money in the new accounts, known as Lifetime Savings Accounts, could be taken out at any time tax free, while the money set aside in the expanded Retirement Savings Accounts would remain saved until age 58, except in cases of death or disability.</p>
        <p>''That's going to take care of almost everybody's saving,'' said Gary V. Engelhardt, an associate professor of economics at Syracuse University. Except for the wealthiest families, the $30,000 that a married couple could put aside every year would be more than enough to cover what they can afford to save. ''Effectively all your saving is going to be sheltered,'' Professor Engelhardt said.</p>
        <p>Even with higher limits on tax-preferred saving, the government might have a hard time encouraging more people to begin putting money aside. ''You're not going to get the participation rates you do in employer-based plans,'' said William G. Gale, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, a liberal policy group.</p>
        <p>Professor Wise agreed. For most people, he said, ''this is small potatoes relative to 401(k) plans.'' Replacing saving plans aimed at medical care and higher education with one lifetime account, Mr. Engelhardt warned, could also curb savers' enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Gale noted, economists have little data to use in forecasting the behavior of high-income people, who are currently barred from contributing to Roth I.R.A.'s, which work in the same way as the new accounts.</p>
        <p>Contributions to traditional I.R.A.'s, which offer an upfront tax deduction in exchange for being taxed at ordinary income rates when money is withdrawn, would stop under the White House's plan. Their replacement could even lead to lower saving rates, Professor Wise said.</p>
        <p>''The upfront deduction is the thing that gets people's attention,'' he argued. ''I would question whether you might not have a decline in contributions.''</p>
        <p>He predicted that some middle-income people who contribute to traditional I.R.A.'s would not switch to the new accounts, because they would no longer receive the immediate tax break.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that it is going to be skewed toward upper-income individuals,'' Mr. Engelhardt said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, that is almost unavoidable. Most proposals to increase saving inherently favor the well-to-do because they are the only ones who can afford to set aside income beyond their immediate needs. ''They do proportionally more saving than lower-income individuals,'' Mr. Engelhardt said. Moreover, the wealthy have a greater incentive to avoid taxation. ''They face higher marginal tax rates,'' he said, ''and have bigger tax benefits from these types of vehicles.''</p>
        <p>Combined with President Bush's plan to protect dividend income from personal taxes, this latest proposal also moves toward a goal long favored by a number of economists, including R. Glenn Hubbard, the chairman of the president's Council of Economic Advisers: the transformation of the income tax into a tax on consumption.</p>
        <p>With a pure consumption tax, there is no disadvantage to spending money in the future instead of the present; the tax -- effectively paid at the time of a purchase -- is always the same. In a sense, eliminating taxes on saving achieves the same goal, even with an income tax in place. That transformation would be on the horizon if the new saving rules became law. ''I can't imagine that there's ever going to be a taxable dividend or capital gain or anything else if we do this and the president's other proposal,'' Mr. Gale said.</p>
        <p>Aside from its effects on the character of the tax system and income inequality, making the entire savings of almost all Americans eligible for a tax shelter could also put a dent in the government's annual revenue.</p>
        <p>''Clearly the government's going to forgo a lot of tax revenue,'' Professor Scholz said. ''Households with two incomes -- like me and my lawyer wife -- we'll be real capable of taking full advantage of these things.''</p>
        <p>After 20 years, an individual who saved at the program's maximum levels could have $300,000 in principal yielding tax-free income. But while the government would be giving up a big revenue stream in the future, the new accounts are likely to generate extra taxes in the near term to the extent people with traditional I.R.A.'s take up the Treasury's offer to convert them.</p>
        <p>''If they get people to convert existing funds, and pay a tax on the conversion, they'll show a big gain in revenue in the short term, and a big loss in the long term,'' Mr. Gale said. ''It's a gimmick, in that it's shifting revenue from the future to now.''</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
