<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY NEWS: Encountering The Digital Age -- An occasional look at computers in everday life.; The Keyboard Becomes a Hangout For a Computer-Savvy Generation</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEENAGERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHOENIX (ARIZ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNET</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKOFF, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOUCETTE, DANIELLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKIBBEN, JULIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEGER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Phoenix</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DA1138F932A0575BC0A965958260" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY NEWS: Encountering The Digital Age -- An occasional look at computers in everday life.; The Keyboard Becomes a Hangout For a Computer-Savvy Generation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKOFF, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sixteen-year-old Jon Leger, a high school student in Port Arthur, Tex., does not consider himself a computer whiz. In fact he doesn't see himself as particularly special in any way.</p>
        <p>"People at school treat me like I'm nothing," he said. But on the Internet, the network of networks, accessible to anyone with a personal computer modem, he has found his place in a world that extends far beyond his home city in southeast Texas. "On the net," he said, "people are willing to talk to me. It's a huge self-esteem booster."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sixteen-year-old Jon Leger, a high school student in Port Arthur, Tex., does not consider himself a computer whiz. In fact he doesn't see himself as particularly special in any way.</p>
        <p>"People at school treat me like I'm nothing," he said. But on the Internet, the network of networks, accessible to anyone with a personal computer modem, he has found his place in a world that extends far beyond his home city in southeast Texas. "On the net," he said, "people are willing to talk to me. It's a huge self-esteem booster."</p>
        <p>The Internet, once exclusively the domain of scientists and academics, is becoming a much more diverse community. No one knows how many of its 15 million users are children and teen-agers, but network researchers estimate their ranks to be in the tens or even hundreds of thousands and certain to grow as computers and software continue to plunge in price and as commercial and informal networks connected to the Internet continue to proliferate. Not All Nerdy Loners</p>
        <p>These young people are not necessarily nerdy loners, and they are definitely not all male. A network user is as likely to encounter Julie McKibben, a fifth grader in Phoenix, or Danielle Doucette, a high school student who numbers cheerleaders and athletes among her friends in Waldwick, N.J., as to find Ben Kotcher, a 16-year-old computer expert in Reading, Ohio.</p>
        <p>Nor are these all children of affluence. Granted, it is probably more likely for a child to become a networker if Mom or Dad uses a home PC to do the taxes or if the hottest new Apple Macintosh Quadra happens to be in the den. But many children are introduced to network computing through school or special programs, like the summer camp at Phoenix College that brought Julie McKibben on-line.</p>
        <p>The simple fact is anyone today who is under age 18 has never known a world without personal computers.  And the technology is unfolding in ways more meaningful, and much less passive, than the televised global village that was held out as the information-age ideal to an earlier generation.</p>
        <p>Thanks to interactive computer networks offering games, bulletin boards and chat groups, a virtual neighborhood is taking shape.</p>
        <p>"These children are pioneering the creation of a new kind of public space that you and I don't understand yet," said Zane Vella, a New York computer researcher who is developing a computer outpost called Cityspace where children can visit on Internet.</p>
        <p>Call it the Digital Hangout.</p>
        <p>Danielle Doucette, the New Jersey high school student, has found the computer networks a perfect way to extend her social world. Each evening she spends about an hour on a commercial network called the Imagination Network, "chatting" via her keyboard with teen-agers all over the country. For $12.95 a month, she gets 30 hours of evening and weekend use on the Imagination Network, which is operated by Sierra On-Line Inc. of Oakhurst, Calif.</p>
        <p>"I've met a lot of my friends this way," she said. "It's different from real life because you're not inhibited; people can say whatever they like. You can be more open and less shy." On-Line Flirtations</p>
        <p>Danielle said she had an on-line boyfriend in California for several months, but she ended the electronic flirtation when he announced that he wanted to come east for a visit. "That would have been just too hard," she said.</p>
        <p>Many computer experts, and young networkers, too, say the networks have made computing a more social experience, helping end the stereotype of the pimple-faced boy who forsakes people and sunshine to sit alone before the cold glow of a video monitor.</p>
        <p>"Computer networks offer a powerful tool for cutting across gender lines and making computers attractive to girls in ways that weren't possible before," said Mitchel Resnick, a professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology's Media Laboratory.</p>
        <p>And, because most of the systems are text-only, there is an emphasis on the written word that would gladden any English teacher's heart. From Port Arthur, Jon Leger's network travels led him to a community college president in Silicon Valley who corrects his on-line grammar.  Using Network at Camp</p>
        <p>Jon spent many days this summer helping elementary schoolchildren like the fifth grader Julie McKibben at the summer camp in Phoenix create word-only computer games, after he electronically stumbled upon the youngsters while wandering the network. (To keep a promise, he stayed up until 4 A.M. one night finishing the design for a keyboard volleyball game for his young, unseen friends. "Spike!" a player must type, to send a screamer over the net; "dig!" the opponent must respond, if he or she has any hope of saving the point.)</p>
        <p>The Phoenix summer camp was run for a group of 27 elementary students with learning difficulties from low-income families. Each day, Julie and the others spent as much as three hours on-line, typing instructions and reading from computer screens, whether corresponding with electronic pen pals like Jon Leger, or using word descriptions to create elaborate fantasy worlds on a type of network known as a Muse, for multi-user simulation environments.</p>
        <p>"It was real fun," Julie recalled in a telephone interview. "I made a stable with 32 stalls and a bale of hay in each stall. I made a horse named Claudia that was white with a mane as black as midnight." She said she and her classmates had also worked with other children on the network to create a textual description of Europe that they could then "tour."  Bridging Technology Gap</p>
        <p>The summer project exceeded the teachers' hopes. "It was a miracle," said Billie Hughes, an education professor at Phoenix College. "These kids sat down and read and wrote for three hours, and they didn't want to go away. They were hooked."</p>
        <p>Teachers, computer experts and sociologists view the emergence of computer networks not only as a way to motivate underachievers but also as a lifeline that can bridge the technology gap between rich and poor children.</p>
        <p>"This is a refuge for the kids because their family life in the world outside is extremely violent in all senses," said Ann Jocknick, director of Computers and You, a computer education center for children in the Tenderloin district, a low-income, high-crime section of San Francisco. "This is a safe space to come in and explore and take risks, and a lot of children really blossom here."</p>
        <p>The international links that computer networks create offer a particularly compelling avenue for broadening students. One of the first was created in 1990 by Odd de Presno, a Norwegian computer journalist, who set up a nonprofit organization called Kidlink. In its three years, Kidlink has connected more than 10,000 children in more than 50 countries. Link to Cape Canaveral</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, for example, Jamie Wilkerson, a fifth-grade teacher at Rosewood School in Rock Hill, S.C., used Kidlink to lead a computer discussion of a planned space shuttle launching. From a computer keyboard at Cape Canaveral, she narrated the event, including the dramatic shutdown of the engines just seconds before launching. Sending questions and receiving answers were her students in Rock Hill, as well as several dozen children from six other countries.</p>
        <p>It was hardly the first time Mrs. Wilkerson's students had logged on with her. "We have accessed more information in one year through the network, than I could ever get my children to see in a library or in textbooks," she said.</p>
        <p>But understand, despite such lofty uses of computer networking, the youth of America are still, well, the youth of America.</p>
        <p>Ben Kotcher, a high school junior in the Cincinnati suburb of Reading, Ohio, thanks the network for expanding his social circle. "I have close friends in Massachusetts who I know as well as my friends here in Cincinnati," he said. "The hardest thing is that I can flirt with girls, but I can't go out with them. I guess networks aren't a replacement for the real world."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
