<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indoors And Out, A Big Show</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930908T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CBS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LETTERMAN, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, BILL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LATE SHOW WITH DAVID LETTERMAN (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF143FF932A0575BC0A965958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indoors And Out, A Big Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARTER, BILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Letterman finally opened on Broadway last night, bringing much of his old NBC show with him to his new address: CBS and the Ed Sullivan Theater.</p>
        <p>The opening was accompanied by almost as much media excitement as the first time Elvis showed up next to Ed. Much of that excitement spilled out into the streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Letterman finally opened on Broadway last night, bringing much of his old NBC show with him to his new address: CBS and the Ed Sullivan Theater.</p>
        <p>The opening was accompanied by almost as much media excitement as the first time Elvis showed up next to Ed. Much of that excitement spilled out into the streets.</p>
        <p>In fact, with the taping of the show restricted to ticket-holders and Mr. Letterman steering clear of last-minute interviews, the main excitement for the crush of reporters who converged on the scene for most of the day was out on the street.</p>
        <p>The line of satellite dishes across Broadway from the theater was exceeded only by the line of grinning ticket-holders that stretched along 53d Street toward the stage entrance.</p>
        <p>Reporters from more than 30 television stations, from as far away as Phoenix, Houston and Minneapolis, and magazine shows like "Entertainment Tonight" and "Inside Edition" milled around, all but bumping into one another as they interviewed anyone who seemed relevant, from the waiting fans of Mr. Letterman, to the CBS pages assigned to steer the crowd inside for the first edition of "Late Show With David Letterman," which was taped at 5:30 yesterday afternoon, to the many CBS executives who turned up for a screening party.</p>
        <p>The CBS chairman, Laurence A. Tisch, stopped outside to express his pleasure at having broken out his bankroll to sign on Mr. Letterman. "He is a very big star," Mr. Tisch said. "He's worth every penny. We're delighted to have him, and we're delighted he's doing his show in New York."</p>
        <p>On the West Coast, Mr. Leno, host of the main competition, the "Tonight" show on NBC, took note of Mr. Letterman's debut in several jokes. In his monologue, he talked about the Clinton Administration's problems in persuading the networks to carry his speech on health care because of all the competition: "Hey, pal, join the club," Mr. Leno said.</p>
        <p>Later he asked: "How come you never hear about the game show wars? You never see Pat Sajak and Alex Trebek fighting it out."</p>
        <p>During the day, the television reporters, assigned to send back reports for their stations' local newscasts at noon and 5 and 6 P.M., walked through their reports as if each moment was of some urgency.</p>
        <p>The Hello Deli on 53d Street did a brisk lunchtime business under a banner that said, "Welcome Mr. Letterman; #1 Late Show Legend." The Luminaries Gather</p>
        <p>The event, which took on the atmosphere of a rock concert mixed with a street fair, was the culmination of more than a year of intense coverage of Mr. Letterman's transfer from 12:35 A.M. on NBC to 11:35 P.M. on CBS. It included such exciting moments as the arrival of Calvert DeForest, who used to play Larry (Bud) Melman before NBC laid claim to his character, in a black stretch limo with a crew from "Inside Edition" in tow, and an elegantly rendered butter bust of Mr. Letterman's head, which one fan from Minneapolis proudly displayed under the "Late Show" marquee, complete with slices of bread for dipping.</p>
        <p>CBS's party was held inside McGee's Pub, a neighborhood drinking establishment that operates from a storefront in the same building as the theater. CBS paid $4 million for the theater, more than that to renovate it and as a side benefit became the landlord of McGee's. The network spruced the place up for the event, adding six television monitors for the evening.</p>
        <p>Mr. Letterman praised the renovation during the show and used a special music video to celebrate the contribution of the construction workers who finished the job, begun in February, just days before he went back on the air.</p>
        <p>Howard Stringer, the president of the CBS Broadcast Group and the man most responsible for the successful courting of Mr. Letterman, was the host. Guests included Jeff Sagansky and Peter Tortorici, CBS's two highest-ranking program executives, who flew in from Los Angeles for the premiere; Edward Grebow, the CBS executive credited with masterminding the renovation of the Sullivan theater, and Lee Gabler, who heads the television division at the Creative Artists Agency, Mr. Letterman's agents. The agency negotiated the deal that is to pay Mr. Letterman about $14 million a year for the next three years.</p>
        <p>The head of Creative Artists, Michael Ovitz, who is Mr. Letterman's agent, also flew in from Los Angeles to attend the taping of the first "Late Show." He sat inside the show's brand-new control room with Peter Lassally, one of Mr. Letterman's two executive producers. Just Another Day? Hardly</p>
        <p>"It's not just another opening to another show," Mr. Stringer said. "With all these expectations, if the show winds up with like a 2 rating, I may walk out into the Hudson until my hat floats."</p>
        <p>Most of the CBS executives expected Mr. Letterman to score a 10 or 12 rating, something approaching the 11.8 that Mr. Leno received on his first night as host of the "Tonight" show, the job Mr. Letterman wanted. (Each rating point represents 942,000 homes.)</p>
        <p>After the show, the CBS executives were even more confident. Mr. Stringer said Mr. Letterman had exceeded his expectations. "Huge laughs," he said. He said that CBS didn't even mind that Mr. Letterman spent much of his first show tweaking his former bosses at NBC. Far from being cowed by NBC's threats to sue him if he used material similar to his old show, Mr. Letterman seemed to revel in it. "You have to expect Dave to be Dave," Mr. Stringer said.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Mr. Leno said he spent the day as he would any other Monday, though perhaps with a little bit more interest in what was going on in New York.</p>
        <p>"David's been doing this for 11 years," Mr. Leno said. "He knows what he's doing."</p>
        <p>Then he added: "I'm just hoping Hurricane Emily hits the East Coast in time. And why couldn't 'Nightline' have saved its Michael Jackson story for tonight? No, I'm sure Dave will do a great show."</p>
        <p>As for his own position, Mr. Leno, noting that he had gone through the dismissal of his executive producer and long-time manager, Helen Kucknick, as well as an extremely close call over losing his "Tonight" show job to Mr. Letterman, all in his first year on the show, said, "After all I've been through, Dave's show is the least of my worries."</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 8, 1993, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 31 about a sculpture of David Letterman outside the Ed Sullivan Theater in Manhattan misstated the work's origin in some copies. It came from the Minnesota State Fair in Falcon Heights, not from Minneapolis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 8, 1993, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 31 about a sculpture of David Letterman outside the Ed Sullivan Theater in Manhattan misstated the work's origin in some copies. It came from the Minnesota State Fair in Falcon Heights, not from Minneapolis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
