<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haiti's Premier Is Installed, but in Washington and Amid Heat</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALVAL, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BINDER, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF143AF932A0575BC0A965958260" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haiti's Premier Is Installed, but in Washington and Amid Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BINDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BINDER, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a peculiar setting for a ceremony marking the installation of a new head of government: an embassy in a foreign capital. But given the turbulent politics of Haiti, it was hardly surprising for Prime Minister Robert Malval.</p>
        <p>Rather, the occasion today at the Haitian Embassy here marked a reconciliation of bitterly divided political, military and business leaders that is intended to end violence and restore democracy to Haiti.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a peculiar setting for a ceremony marking the installation of a new head of government: an embassy in a foreign capital. But given the turbulent politics of Haiti, it was hardly surprising for Prime Minister Robert Malval.</p>
        <p>Rather, the occasion today at the Haitian Embassy here marked a reconciliation of bitterly divided political, military and business leaders that is intended to end violence and restore democracy to Haiti.</p>
        <p>The Inter-American Human Rights Commission says about 1,500 Haitians have been killed and 300,000 driven into hiding in the nearly two years of rule by a military junta since 1991.</p>
        <p>Mr. Malval, a 50-year-old businessman who was virtually unknown a month ago in Haitian political circles, became Prime Minister on Thursday after a vote by the lower house of deputies approving his Cabinet and Government program. The upper house gave its approval the day before.</p>
        <p>"There was no swearing-in," Lawrence E. Pezzullo, a special United States envoy for international negotiations on Haiti, said of today's event, "just a laying on of hands."</p>
        <p>But symbolism was heavy at the ceremony, which took place on a sweltering day reminiscent of the climate of the Caribbean, in a room made more stifling by a failure of air conditioning. Witnesses included the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, the ousted President of Haiti, who has spent most of the last 23 months here in exile after being overthrown in a violent coup, and Rene Preval, another exile who was then Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>Speeches were made in Creole, French and English. Mr. Malval, educated at the University of Miami and in Paris, said he wanted to "restore democracy to Haiti as of today." To those who would resist change, he declared, "You can kill us, but you will never kill the dream of the people of Haiti." Aristide to Return on Oct. 30</p>
        <p>Under an elaborate deal brokered last month by the United Nations with the help of the Clinton Administration, Father Aristide is to return to office in Port-au-Prince on Oct. 30.</p>
        <p>Mr. Malval was selected by Father Aristide and also gets along with Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras, who led the coup and who has agreed to retire from the scene in Port-au-Prince.</p>
        <p>Father Aristide, 40, was a Roman Catholic priest with pronounced leftist views, which made him anathema to most of Haiti's business sector. But in July, Mr. Malval arranged a meeting between Father Aristide and 200 Haitian businessmen in Miami that was called a success by all participants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Malval, the scion of an old Haitian family who became a prosperous publisher, has vowed to quit as Prime Minister in mid-December to pave the way for new elections.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
