<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton's Pick As Top Doctor Seeks Support In the Senate</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="743722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGEON GENERAL (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, HENRY W (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (SPEAKER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DB1031F935A25751C0A963958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton's Pick As Top Doctor Seeks Support In the Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a majority of the Senate still undecided on the fate of his nomination to be Surgeon General, Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. went to Capitol Hill today to begin lobbying for support.</p>
        <p>As the White House pursued a cautious strategy that it hoped would build up political support for Dr. Foster's confirmation in the next few weeks, the opposition's plans were also taking shape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a majority of the Senate still undecided on the fate of his nomination to be Surgeon General, Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. went to Capitol Hill today to begin lobbying for support.</p>
        <p>As the White House pursued a cautious strategy that it hoped would build up political support for Dr. Foster's confirmation in the next few weeks, the opposition's plans were also taking shape.</p>
        <p>Addressing a point that many Republican leaders have fretted over, Speaker Newt Gingrich said today that opponents of the nomination should avoid the divisive issue of abortion. "I would focus on the incompetence of the White House and the potential dishonesty," Mr. Gingrich told reporters, "and I would never touch the abortion issue."</p>
        <p>To win confirmation, Dr. Foster must first gain the backing of the Senate Labor and Human Resources Committee after its hearing on the appointment. If the nomination survives that process, Dr. Foster would need a majority vote in the full Senate, where Republicans hold 53 seats to the Democrats' 47.</p>
        <p>An aide to Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority whip, said today that Mr. Lott had not yet conducted a head count of Republicans, nor did he expect one soon.</p>
        <p>Telephone calls today to the offices of the 9 Republicans and 7 Democrats on on the Labor and Human Resources Committee indicated that 14 of them had not decided how to vote on the nomination.</p>
        <p>All of the Democrats on the committee have said Dr. Foster's abortion record should not be used to deny him the job of Surgeon General.</p>
        <p>Two of the committee's Republican members -- Senators Nancy Landon Kassebaum of Kansas, who heads the committee, and James M. Jeffords of Vermont -- support abortion rights. A third Republican committee member, Senator Bill Frist of Tennessee, who is a doctor and a longtime friend of the nominee, said he is leaning toward supporting the nomination but first wants Dr. Foster to clear up the confusion over his abortion record.</p>
        <p>"Frankly, I don't think many members have had more than a superficial look at his record," said Mike Horak, a spokesman for Senator Kassebaum. "If we don't have a hearing for another month, a lot of things could change both ways."</p>
        <p>President Clinton nominated Dr. Foster two weeks ago as Surgeon General, and the 61-year-old obstetrician-gynecologist from Tennessee was immediately thrust into the center of a political firestorm when it was disclosed that he had performed abortions. More trouble developed after Dr. Foster offered at least three accounts of the number of abortions he had performed.</p>
        <p>The White House made sure today that Dr. Foster's first meetings with members of the Senate were friendly ones. His only visits were with two Democratic supporters -- the Senate minority leader, Tom Dashcle of South Dakota, and Patty Murray of Washington.</p>
        <p>"There are a lot of lies out there, but I'm going to have my day," Dr. Foster told Senator Dashcle. "That's what the hearings are for. I want people to see my entire record, my whole life's work, to see me in total."</p>
        <p>On Thursday he is scheduled to meet with Senator Kassebaum and Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts, the ranking Democrat on the committee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
