<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Body of Boy Found in Bin Inside Home</title>
    <meta content="06NEWA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/06/nyregion/06NEWA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1454430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Faheem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Raheem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Tyrone</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Sherry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFDC143EF935A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Body of Boy Found in Bin Inside Home</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Body of Boy Found in Bin Inside Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN and THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J; Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Body of 7-year-old Faheem Williams is found lifeless in storage bin in basement of Newark home, where brothers Raheem and Tyrone Williams had been found earlier, neglected and brought to hospital for starvation and treatment for dehydration; authorities are searching for Sherry Murphy, who was allegedly caring for children while mother reportedly recovered from car accident in New York City hospital; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The body of a 7-year-old boy who had apparently been dead for weeks was discovered yesterday in a storage bin in a house in Newark where his two emaciated young brothers had been found in a locked basement on Saturday, law enforcement officials in New Jersey said last night.</p>
        <p>Edward Gordon, director of homicide investigations for the Essex County prosecutor's office, identified the dead child as Faheem Williams, and said his twin brother, Raheem, and a 4-year-old sibling, Tyrone, were being treated at University Hospital in Newark for starvation and dehydration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The body of a boy who had apparently been dead for weeks was discovered in a storage bin in a Newark house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The body of a 7-year-old boy who had apparently been dead for weeks was discovered yesterday in a storage bin in a house in Newark where his two emaciated young brothers had been found in a locked basement on Saturday, law enforcement officials in New Jersey said last night.</p>
        <p>Edward Gordon, director of homicide investigations for the Essex County prosecutor's office, identified the dead child as Faheem Williams, and said his twin brother, Raheem, and a 4-year-old sibling, Tyrone, were being treated at University Hospital in Newark for starvation and dehydration.</p>
        <p>While much about the case was unclear last night, Mr. Gordon said the authorities were searching for the children's mother in New York City, where she was believed to have been hit by a car and hospitalized several months ago. Her identity was not disclosed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordon said the authorities were also searching for Sherry Murphy. The children had been left in her care by the mother, according to the prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Pending a news conference today, Detective Todd McClendon, a spokesman for the Newark police, would say only that no one had been arrested and that a number of people were being questioned and sought for information about the weekend discoveries at 188 Parker Street in Branch Brook Park, a working-class neighborhood in north Newark.</p>
        <p>As the police cordoned off the area around the two-story, three-family house, neighborhood residents and acquaintances of the children expressed suspicions of a horrendous case of abuse.</p>
        <p>One acquaintance said the surviving children were extremely malnourished and appeared to have burn marks on their bodies. But investigators made no accusations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordon, providing some details in a telephone interview last night, said that Ms. Murphy's boyfriend, Shawn Slappy, 31, acknowledged that he had been living in her apartment at the house for about two weeks, but quoted him as saying he knew nothing about the children.</p>
        <p>Dawn Davis, who identified herself as Mr. Slappy's sister, said that he was a security guard at East Orange General Hospital and that he had met Ms. Murphy last fall. She described Ms. Murphy as a topless dancer.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Mr. Slappy told the authorities, Ms. Murphy was not around and he decided to go to the basement to look for a pair of work boots that he suspected Ms. Murphy had hidden from him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Slappy said he had found the basement door locked and had used a screwdriver to pry it open, Ms. Davis said. As the door swung open, Ms. Davis said, Mr. Slappy was stunned to see two small faces approaching him in the dim light. ''The only thing you could see was their heads coming toward him,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Frightened at the sight, he shut the door, ran upstairs and called the police, Ms. Davis said. She said the brothers had what looked like burn marks all over them and appeared to be starving. ''You could count every bone on their bodies,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The police took Raheem and Tyrone to the hospital, where they were listed in fair condition, but they did not find Faheem until yesterday. Mr. Gordon said Raheem had told investigators at the hospital that his twin brother had been missing for weeks.</p>
        <p>That apparently prompted the police to return to Parker Street, where they found Faheem's body in a plastic bin in another basement room. Ms. Davis said she understood the body had been hidden in a sleeping bag. The cause of death was unclear last night, pending an autopsy.</p>
        <p>The case stunned the neighborhood. ''I was shocked,'' said Miguel Hernandez, 17, who has lived on the block for three years. ''It's crazy.''</p>
        <p>He said he had seen the Williams children playing outside, but not recently.</p>
        <p>''They seemed happy,'' he said. ''Nothing really strange about them.'' But they seemed thin, he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
