<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Montoya's Victory Comes as a Relief</title>
    <meta content="02PRIX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/02/sports/othersports/02prix.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1493834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monaco Grand Prix</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spurgeon, Brad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montoya, Juan Pablo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Monaco</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Formula One</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DA1230F931A35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Montoya's Victory Comes as a Relief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Montoya's Victory in Monaco Is a Relief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRAD SPURGEON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spurgeon, Brad</byline>
      <dateline>MONACO, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Juan Pablo Montoya wins Monaco Grand Prix auto race (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On his wind-down lap through the luxurious neighborhoods of this principality today, Juan Pablo Montoya joined the thousands of spectators in clapping.</p>
        <p>And with good reason. Montoya had just won the Monaco Grand Prix, one of the two most prestigious events in open-wheel motor racing, and he also ended a lengthy period of frustration, for him and for his BMW-Williams team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juan Pablo Montoya won the Monaco Grand Prix, one of the two most prestigious events in open-wheel motor racing. It was his first win since September 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On his wind-down lap through the luxurious neighborhoods of this principality today, Juan Pablo Montoya joined the thousands of spectators in clapping.</p>
        <p>And with good reason. Montoya had just won the Monaco Grand Prix, one of the two most prestigious events in open-wheel motor racing, and he also ended a lengthy period of frustration, for him and for his BMW-Williams team.</p>
        <p>''Winning Monaco is very special; it is a bit like winning the Indy 500 in the U.S.A.,'' said Montoya, a 27-year-old Colombian who won the Indianapolis 500 in 2000.</p>
        <p>The finish today was one of the closest at Monaco since 1992, when Ayrton Senna, driving a McLaren, won by 0.215 of a second over Nigel Mansell, in a Williams. Montoya finished 0.602 of a second ahead of Finland's Kimi Raikkonen, who was driving a McLaren-Mercedes.</p>
        <p>Michael Schumacher of Germany, in a Ferrari, finished 1.1 seconds behind Raikkonen, allowing Raikkonen to increase his lead over Schumacher in the drivers' standing to 4 points, 48-44. Montoya moved to fifth from seventh in the series, with 25 points. Montoya, considered one of the most promising drivers when he started in Formula One in 2001, had not won a race since his first victory, at the Italian Grand Prix in September 2001.</p>
        <p>''I had quite a few races where I had a chance to win and then threw it away,'' he said. ''So there was a bit of pressure not to make any mistakes. It was definitely worth waiting for.''</p>
        <p>The wait for another victory at Monaco was even longer for the Williams team, which had not won here since 1983, with Keke Rosberg driving. Although Williams is third in Formula One victories with 109, it has won only three times at Monaco since the team was founded in 1977.</p>
        <p>''We are relieved that the 20 long years since we last won in Monaco is now firmly behind us,'' said Frank Williams, the team's owner.</p>
        <p>Montoya started the race from the pole last year but lost out to David Coulthard on the first corner, setting up Coulthard's victory.</p>
        <p>''Last year I had seven poles and none of them converted into wins,'' Montoya said. ''The key today was the start.''</p>
        <p>Montoya started third today. His teammate, Ralf Schumacher, started from the pole and Raikkonen started second.</p>
        <p>Schumacher led off the start, while Montoya leapt alongside Raikkonen. While Jarno Trulli of Italy, in a Renault, attacked Raikkonen from behind, Montoya came out ahead of Raikkonen.</p>
        <p>The course, which runs through narrow, winding and bumpy city streets, is one of the hardest on which to pass. So despite moving into second, once the race went beyond the first corner, Montoya had little chance to pass Ralf Schumacher, who built a 2.2-second lead after the first of 78 laps.</p>
        <p>On Lap 21, with Montoya less than half a second behind him, Ralf Schumacher made his first pit stop and handed the lead to Montoya.</p>
        <p>After making a pit stop on Lap 23, Montoya returned to the race just ahead of Ralf Schumacher, but in seventh position. Raikkonen had taken the lead, but he and all the other drivers ahead of Montoya still had to make pit stops.</p>
        <p>Michael Schumacher, who was trying to equal Senna's record of six victories at Monaco, had qualified fifth. But it was expected that his Ferrari team would have a surprise race strategy, and this seemed to be the case when a series of fast laps and a good pit stop on Lap 31 lifted Michael Schumacher to third, behind Montoya and Raikkonen, after the first round of pit stops.</p>
        <p>If he performed as well through the next stint, Michael Schumacher would win the race. In the end, Ferrari was outperformed.</p>
        <p>''I might have been able to finish higher if I had not been stuck behind Trulli in the early stages,'' Schumacher said. ''But our strategy was to go for a long first stint and that meant having more fuel, which is why I was behind him.''</p>
        <p>Michael Schumacher made his second stop on Lap 59 and Montoya took the lead again, with Raikkonen trailing him by 1.1 seconds. Schumacher rejoined the race more than 10 seconds behind them.</p>
        <p>The last 18 laps provided the most suspense. Montoya and Raikkonen stayed within a second of each other, while Michael Schumacher closed in.</p>
        <p>''It was really just a matter of putting as much pressure as possible on him to try and force him into making a mistake,'' Raikkonen said of his battle with Montoya. ''But unfortunately, he didn't.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
