<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="623588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIGEST (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DA113CF937A15754C0A965958260" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>Europe's monetary system withstood another battering from speculators, as France and Germany intervened to prop up the franc. The system appeared headed for a showdown next week at an important Bundesbank meeting.  [ Page 35. ]</p>
        <p>Speculation that Volkswagen's board would meet was denied after the company's chairman met with the Premier of Lower Saxony state, VW's largest shareholder, to discuss the dispute over Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua and G.M.  [ 35. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>Europe's monetary system withstood another battering from speculators, as France and Germany intervened to prop up the franc. The system appeared headed for a showdown next week at an important Bundesbank meeting.  [ Page 35. ]</p>
        <p>Speculation that Volkswagen's board would meet was denied after the company's chairman met with the Premier of Lower Saxony state, VW's largest shareholder, to discuss the dispute over Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua and G.M.  [ 35. ]</p>
        <p>The European unity treaty moved closer to ratification in Britain after Prime Minister Major won a vote of confidence.  [ 1. ]</p>
        <p>Ferruzzi's former head was found dead in an apparent suicide. He had come under scrutiny in Italy's corruption scandal.  [ 1. ]</p>
        <p>A $2.5 billion aid package for Russia involving wider corporate participation was sent to the Senate by the Administration.  [ 4. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>Reinstatement of Puerto Rico's $2.6 billion in tax breaks for big American companies doing business there was agreed upon by Congressional budget negotiators.  [ 26. ]</p>
        <p>A budget that can pass the Senate will be impossible without more White House compromises, Senator Moynihan said.  [ 26. ]</p>
        <p>Car and light-truck sales rose 17 percent in mid-July from the period last year, the nation's auto makers said.  [ 44. ]  Companies</p>
        <p>Bally Manufacturing has been so successful in cutting costs that it now has the money to drive deeper into the fitness business, its biggest money maker, and into gambling.  [ 35. ]</p>
        <p>Subaru is withdrawing its advertising from Wieden &amp; Kennedy after this year. The move was a surprise for the agency.  [ 35. ]</p>
        <p>Marriott shareholders overwhelmingly approved its proposal to split the company, and the company said it had settled with a majority of its preferred shareholders, who had sued.  [ 37. ]</p>
        <p>Exxon reported a 33 percent gain in second-quarter profits attributable to cost-cutting and higher demand in Europe.  [ 37. ]</p>
        <p>Chiron and Berlex said regulators had approved Betaseron, a drug for the treatment of multiple sclerosis.  [ 37. ]</p>
        <p>The $160 million being paid to Paul B. Kazarian by Sunbeam-Oster won't be lying around for long.  [ 37. ]</p>
        <p>First Interstate Bank was ordered to pay more than $13.9 million to credit card customers for overcharging fees.  [ 34. ]</p>
        <p>Two unions at American Airlines rebuffed suggestions that they negotiate an equity stake in the carrier.  [ 44. ]  Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks bounced higher in active trading. The Dow gained 21.52 points, to 3,546.74. It gained 18.45 for the week.  [ 36. ]</p>
        <p>Mexico's stock market posted its best gain of the year, lifted by a better-than-expected performance by Telefonos de Mexico.  [ 36. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury bond prices fell for the fourth straight session as the yield on the 30-year bond soared to its highest level in a month.  [ 44. ]</p>
        <p>Lumber futures prices leaped on signs that the construction industry had worked through a big supply inventory.  [ 46. ]  Your Money</p>
        <p>Business is brisk on the futures market because of the Midwest floods. But investing in futures is not for the faint of heart.  [ 33. ]</p>
        <p>Selling stocks on Monday may not be a good idea. Studies show prices tend to fall at the start of the week.  [ 33. ]</p>
        <p>Competition between Schwab and Fidelity in mutual funds is likely to lower the cost of buying and selling.  [ 33. ]</p>
        <p>Brokerage firms are working to accommodate clients with special needs, like people with hearing impairments.  [ 34. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
