<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are There Any More Like Him Down on the Farm?</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="623653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA ANGELS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUTTON, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61030F937A15754C0A965958260" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are There Any More Like Him Down on the Farm?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Welcome to the Yankee future. If you are ready for fastballs that zoom past hitters at 95 miles an hour, nasty sliders that confound and confuse and a mound presence that speaks of intensity and guile and not rookie nerves, you are ready to watch Mark Hutton pitch in a pennant race.</p>
        <p>Overcoming a first-inning run by the Angels and an unearned run in the sixth that snapped a 1-1 tie, Hutton pitched wondrously in his debut to power the Yankees to a 5-2 victory at Yankee Stadium. General Manager Gene Michael said Hutton was ready for the majors a month ago, and he looked it last night by halting the Angels on three hits and one earned run in eight innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Welcome to the Yankee future. If you are ready for fastballs that zoom past hitters at 95 miles an hour, nasty sliders that confound and confuse and a mound presence that speaks of intensity and guile and not rookie nerves, you are ready to watch Mark Hutton pitch in a pennant race.</p>
        <p>Overcoming a first-inning run by the Angels and an unearned run in the sixth that snapped a 1-1 tie, Hutton pitched wondrously in his debut to power the Yankees to a 5-2 victory at Yankee Stadium. General Manager Gene Michael said Hutton was ready for the majors a month ago, and he looked it last night by halting the Angels on three hits and one earned run in eight innings.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is premature to predict that Hutton will even last the rest of the season. But the Yankees were thrilled with his first outing and desperately hope the 6-foot-6-inch right-hander will help provide the boost their staff needs to shake free from the crowd of teams atop the American League East. Does Hutton think he will be a fixture in the rotation?</p>
        <p>"I damn well hope so," said Hutton, his Australian accent dripping with confidence. His next scheduled start is Wednesday at Detroit. An Australian Star</p>
        <p>With two Australian television stations recording Hutton's historic night and one even planning to televise the news nationally, the 23-year-old did not disappoint. The fifth Australian to ever play in the majors, and the first to ever start as a pitcher, Hutton dominated the Angels.</p>
        <p>He caused Manager Buck Rodgers to lament that his Angels club was "making stars" out of unknown pitchers, and he paced the Yankees to their 20th victory in their last 25 home games. The triumph moved the Yankees into a virtual tie for first place with the Toronto Blue Jays and Boston Red Sox.</p>
        <p>Signed for $15,000 as an 18-year-old free agent in 1988, Hutton decided to play baseball instead of Australian rules football, and it has proved to be a shrewd move. Still throwing 94 miles an hour in the eighth inning and relying on fastballs and sliders, Hutton made his second visit to the Stadium a success by outdueling the A.L. starter in the All-Star Game, Mark Langston. His other trip came eight years ago on a family vacation when he purchased a Yankee T-shirt, or a "top," as he called it.</p>
        <p>"The whole night was overwhelming," said Hutton, referring to the present. "It was pretty amazing." A Pitcher With Presence</p>
        <p>Presence. The word is constantly used by teammates and coaches when Hutton is the topic. They vowed that Hutton would not scare. He would not be afraid to attack hitters. They were right last night.</p>
        <p>Hutton was tested early. After he walked the leadoff batter, Luis Polonia, on five pitches, Polonia immediately stole second and third base to put the rookie in a hole and highlight his slow delivery. But after Damion Easley's sacrifice fly scored Polonia to make it 1-0, Hutton exhibited toughness by retiring 11 of the next 13. Polonia had not unnerved him, and Mike Stanley helped Hutton coast easier by clobbering his 16th homer in the second off Langston to tie the score. It was Stanley's fourth homer in his last six games.</p>
        <p>"Nothing seemed to bother him," marveled Stanley.</p>
        <p>Then came the sixth -- one more test for Hutton. A walk, a bunt and Polonia's single put runners on first and third with one out. After a visit from Manager Buck Showalter, Hutton tried to pick off Polonia, and his good throw nicked off Don Mattingly's glove for the first baseman's third error of the season, allowing Gary DiSarcina to score the go-ahead run.</p>
        <p>Not to worry. Hutton struck out Chad Curtis and Easley to end the inning and waited for the Yankee bats to awaken against Langston. They did with three runs and four hits in the bottom of the sixth, including Bernie Williams's pivotal two-out single that put the Yankees ahead to stay at 3-2. Hutton did not rattle on his memorable night.</p>
        <p>"That's just the way I am," Hutton said. "I don't let too many things bother me." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Even though he conferred with the Chicago Cubs' assistant general manager, SYD THRIFT, at Friday night's game, Yankee General Manager GENE MICHAEL denied a trade rumor that had the Yankees sending right-handed reliever JOHN HABYAN to the Cubs for left-handed reliever PAUL ASSENMACHER.  "We're not doing that," Michael said. "It's way out of control. All we did is talk to them." Habyan said he had been told that the Cubs wanted him and promising rookie reliever BOBBY MUNOZ for Assenmacher so the Yankees scrapped the potential deal. "It was a lie and it just snowballed," Habyan said. The rumor was so rampant that Habyan received a call from his mother in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., asking whether he was a Cub. . . . STEVE FARR pitched a hitless ninth for his 19th save.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
