<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beliefs</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="623592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDWESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GALLUP POLL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, BARRY L (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PLANTINGA, ALVIN (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB1F3CF937A15754C0A965958260" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beliefs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Steinfels</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Midwest the floods may be cresting, but the agony of loss has only begun. Among the millions stripped of homes, possessions, crops, farm land and futures, there are doubtless many who will sit, like Job, amid the ruins of their lives and ask why God has turned against them.</p>
        <p>Some Americans have already come up with answers. In St. Louis, people on radio call-in programs are proclaiming that the floods are God's punishment for the legalization of river boat gambling in the region. And nearly one of five Americans agreed with the statement in a Gallup Poll that the "floods are God's judgment on the people of the United States for their sinful ways."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Midwest the floods may be cresting, but the agony of loss has only begun. Among the millions stripped of homes, possessions, crops, farm land and futures, there are doubtless many who will sit, like Job, amid the ruins of their lives and ask why God has turned against them.</p>
        <p>Some Americans have already come up with answers. In St. Louis, people on radio call-in programs are proclaiming that the floods are God's punishment for the legalization of river boat gambling in the region. And nearly one of five Americans agreed with the statement in a Gallup Poll that the "floods are God's judgment on the people of the United States for their sinful ways."</p>
        <p>Believers may well object to that kind of certainty about God's designs. But that does not mean they have better answers of their own.</p>
        <p>Particularly since the Holocaust, the shadow of moral evil rather than natural disasters has haunted Western culture's reflections about the existence of a good and loving God. But it was not always so.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 1, 1755, when an earthquake killed thousands of people in Lisbon, the news crystallized Voltaire's longstanding suspicion of the benevolent view of nature and nature's God found in the writings of Alexander Pope and the German philosopher Leibniz as well as in conventional religion.</p>
        <p>In his "Essay on Man," Pope wrote that nature's apparently meaningless destructiveness was really "harmony not understood" and all specific evil really "universal good."</p>
        <p>Despite appearances, Pope concluded, "Whatever is, is right" -- a phrase that Voltaire used as a sardonic epigraph for his poem contrasting the horrors of the crushed lives in Lisbon with the complacency of philosophical explanations. Voltaire's protest stirred a debate across Europe.</p>
        <p>Evil with a human face, whether ethnic cleansings or random shootings of schoolchildren, may seem more malign than the impersonal violence of earthquakes, floods or tidal waves. But in some ways the depredations of nature are a greater challenge to belief that the universe is in the hands of a loving God.</p>
        <p>Believers can plausibly understand the possibility of human wrongdoing as the price that must be paid for God's creating humankind free. But what is responsible for hurricanes, floods and all the other scourges that are called "acts of God"?</p>
        <p>"Natural evil has always been the tough one," said Barry L. Whitney, a professor of religious studies at the University of Windsor, Ontario, who has just published a kind of monument to the human drive to probe the puzzle of evil and, in Milton's phrase, "justify the ways of God to men."</p>
        <p>Professor Whitney has constructed an annotated bibliography of more than 4,200 philosophical and theological writings on the problem of evil published from 1960 to 1990 -- nearly one publication every two and a half days, and that is only in English.</p>
        <p>His book is titled "Theodicy" (Garland Publishing), from the term that Leibniz coined from the Greek words for "God" and "justice" for efforts to reconcile the goodness of God and the existence of suffering.</p>
        <p>Calamities like the Midwest floods are, of course, only large-scale versions of the physical ills that assail people daily. An earthquake is a heart attack writ large; a drought does to a region what cancer or Alzheimer's disease does to a spouse.</p>
        <p>In the Bible, physical evil is sometimes the work of sinful humans, but it is also sometimes a divine chastisement, a test of faithfulness or a warning. Christians have seen not only moral evil but also the discord and harshness of nature entering a harmonious cosmos with the rebellious acts of Satan and Adam and Eve.</p>
        <p>It has been left to post-biblical thinkers to strive to order these stories and symbols into some theoretical framework. Although popular preachers may still see the hand of God working directly in calamities large and small, theologians and philosophers have grown wary of such confident connections and the vindictive, unfeeling deity they suggest.</p>
        <p>To see God directly inflicting evils for some specific divine purpose, Professor Whitney said, "is the biggest mistake we ever made in theology."</p>
        <p>Alvin Plantinga, a philosopher whose writings have been central in recent discussions of the problem of evil, has tried to meet a more modest goal. Rather than attempting a full-scale explanation of evil, he has tried to show that evil is not logically incompatible with God's existence.</p>
        <p>"The believer knows that the Lord can create a better world by permitting suffering than by not permitting it," he said, but the process is often mysterious, despite occasions "when even the sufferer can see the spiritual benefits outweighing the suffering."</p>
        <p>"If God proposes to give people freedom and make them morally responsible, He -- and we -- must be prepared for the fact that they may do evil," Professor Plantinga continued, sketching the barest outline of a "free-will defense" that he has developed with great subtlety.</p>
        <p>But to deal with natural rather than moral evil, Professor Plantinga, a Protestant who teaches at the University of Notre Dame, raises the idea that it could be attributed to other free-acting creatures. "Satan and his cohorts, for example," he said. "I know it's not a popular solution, but it is possible."</p>
        <p>Other philosophers have argued more directly that natural evils are an unavoidable condition for the existence of human freedom and moral responsibility. Without them, humans would not have the knowledge of good or bad consequences, or even the regularity of natural laws needed to conduct morally good or bad courses of action.</p>
        <p>In one way or another, many contemporary religious thinkers believe that evil implies a willing withdrawal by God to let not only humans but also all natural processes be themselves.</p>
        <p>For some thinkers, including Rabbi Harold Kushner in the best-selling "When Bad Things Happen to Good People" (Avon), this approach has also meant questioning the traditional concept of God as all-powerful.</p>
        <p>Professor Whitney put it this way: "It is a matter of seriously redefining what we mean by God. You can have a God that really loves, that persuades, that lures human beings, rather than coerces them on the model of an ancient monarch. Of course, the danger is that if we tinker with the traditional understanding of God, we may lose it entirely."</p>
        <p>And in another departure from at least some traditions, religious thinkers increasingly stress the idea of a God who suffers along with humanity.</p>
        <p>To be sure, all of this is far from the rising rivers of the Midwest or the Indian monsoon rains that have killed hundreds of people. Puzzling about evil may be an unavoidable response for serious believers, but it cannot substitute for practical action.</p>
        <p>"Philosophy does not help the person trying to save his family and home," warned David Birnbaum, the author of "God and Evil, a Jewish Perspective" (Ktav). "The appropriate response is compassion and an outstretched hand."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
