<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Williams Is Relaxed With Son In Town</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, BERNIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, BERNIE JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6DF1339F93AA15755C0A960958260" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Williams Is Relaxed With Son In Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernie Williams did not consider last night's game with the Orioles just another evening at Yankee Stadium, and it had nothing to do with the opposition. Williams was excited and he was relaxed because Bernie Jr., his 5-year-old son who had serious surgery earlier this month, watched his father play center field for the first time since his emergency operation.</p>
        <p>Both father and son are doing fine now, three weeks after a nervous Williams  bolted from Detroit to rush home to Bayamon, P.R., because Bernie Jr. was having surgery to remove a portion of the mastoid bone on the left side of his skull to drain fluids and relieve pressure. Yankee General Manager Bob Watson called it "life-saving" surgery, and Williams was so distraught after receiving the call on June 8 that he could not even discuss it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bernie Williams did not consider last night's game with the Orioles just another evening at Yankee Stadium, and it had nothing to do with the opposition. Williams was excited and he was relaxed because Bernie Jr., his 5-year-old son who had serious surgery earlier this month, watched his father play center field for the first time since his emergency operation.</p>
        <p>Both father and son are doing fine now, three weeks after a nervous Williams  bolted from Detroit to rush home to Bayamon, P.R., because Bernie Jr. was having surgery to remove a portion of the mastoid bone on the left side of his skull to drain fluids and relieve pressure. Yankee General Manager Bob Watson called it "life-saving" surgery, and Williams was so distraught after receiving the call on June 8 that he could not even discuss it.</p>
        <p>But last night, a healthy Bernie Jr. begged his father to allow him to come  to the Stadium early and behaved like any other energetic boy. The stitches have been removed from behind his left ear and Bernie Jr. has been left with a tiny scar and a lot of catching up to do with his relieved father.</p>
        <p>"The fact that he's here and my family is here means everything," Williams said. "It takes a lot of weight off my mind knowing he's feeling fine."</p>
        <p>Armed with a video game and in constant search of ice cream, Bernie sat with  his mother, Waleska, his grandparents, and his sisters, 2-year-old Beatrice and  9-month-old Bianca, behind the plate. This family snapshot did not include Bernie Sr., but it was an extremely happy picture because it occurred less than  a month after Bernie Jr.'s medical problems.</p>
        <p>"It doesn't make any sense for me to work so hard in baseball if I don't have my family there to share in my successes and failures," Bernie Sr. said.</p>
        <p>Williams described his look-alike namesake as a shy, smart boy, who is affectionate once he knows someone. Gerald Williams, who is Bernie's best friend, is also close with Bernie Jr. -- except when the topic is video games. Bernie Sr. described their typical dialogue.</p>
        <p>"Gerald, do you want to play my video game?" Bernie Jr. often asks.</p>
        <p>"I don't know how to, so I'd rather not," Gerald responds.</p>
        <p>"But I'll teach you," Bernie Jr. persists.</p>
        <p>"That'll take too long," Gerald counters.</p>
        <p>On and on they spar, with Bernie Jr. usually giving up because his potential  victim is too stubborn.</p>
        <p>"Gerald gives him a hard time because he knows that if he played him, he'd have to get beaten badly a few times before he even had a chance to win," Williams said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
