<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times;Wallace Is No Coleman</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKOW, IRA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLEMAN, DERRICK</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1D61239F93AA15755C0A960958260" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times;Wallace Is No Coleman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKOW, IRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE night five years ago, John Wallace, then a high school senior, happened to be walking down Marshall Street in Syracuse with a friend who was a freshman  on the Syracuse University basketball team. Wallace, a highly regarded player from Rochester, was on a recruiting trip to the school and taking in the sights. At that moment, there occurred a sight he'd never forget.</p>
        <p>Marshall Street is just off the main campus and, lined with bars and fast-food restaurants, is a popular place for students. Suddenly, he saw two young men come spilling out of a bar and fighting on the street. One of those in the brawl was Derrick Coleman, who was then the senior Syracuse star whom Wallace had admired as a basketball player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE night five years ago, John Wallace, then a high school senior, happened to be walking down Marshall Street in Syracuse with a friend who was a freshman  on the Syracuse University basketball team. Wallace, a highly regarded player from Rochester, was on a recruiting trip to the school and taking in the sights. At that moment, there occurred a sight he'd never forget.</p>
        <p>Marshall Street is just off the main campus and, lined with bars and fast-food restaurants, is a popular place for students. Suddenly, he saw two young men come spilling out of a bar and fighting on the street. One of those in the brawl was Derrick Coleman, who was then the senior Syracuse star whom Wallace had admired as a basketball player.</p>
        <p>Coleman's shirt was off. Another Syracuse player was holding Coleman's "gold," or necklace and rings, while he was flailing. Wallace looked on in amazement.</p>
        <p>Not long ago Wallace recalled this incident to Mike Waters, who covers Syracuse basketball for The Syracuse Post-Standard. "I don't know what Derrick's thinking about sometimes," Wallace said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more than anything else, this defines the difference between Wallace  and Coleman, though in some ways the stench of Derrick Coleman might have unfortunately seeped onto Wallace's reputation. A lot of people wonder how it is that the player who led his team to the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament final in April, and who was expected to be in the top 10 in the National Basketball Association draft, slipped all the way to 18th -- the first  pick of the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Besides Wallace, a lot of people wonder what Coleman is thinking about sometimes. In college, Coleman was arrested by the campus police and charged with breaking and entering into another student's apartment. He was involved in  several brawls. And he caused problems on the basketball team.</p>
        <p>And while Coleman, a 6-foot-10-inch power forward, possessed enormous talent  -- he was drafted No. 1 by the Nets (the first pick over all in 1990), was the N.B.A. rookie of the year and was a member of the All-Star team -- he remained a sour grape, eventually being traded to Philadelphia, where he has continued to make others ulcerous.</p>
        <p>Wallace, a 6-8 small forward, never had any noteworthy problems at Syracuse.</p>
        <p>Once, Coleman didn't show up for a Friday practice and told no one. He went home to Detroit. Coach Jim Boeheim didn't start him in the nationally televised  game against Providence on that Sunday. Wallace once missed a team flight to a game. He said the electricity in his apartment building went off, and thus the alarm clock didn't work. It checked out. Boeheim started him in the game.</p>
        <p>In Coleman's last game for Syracuse, in the N.C.A.A. round of 16, he was assessed a technical foul for throwing the ball at an opponent in a 1-point game in the fourth quarter against Minnesota, and he didn't score in the last eight minutes. Syracuse went on to be upset in that game.</p>
        <p>Wallace, in the N.C.A.A. tournament games of his senior year, was sensational. He made clutch plays and points to help Syracuse advance, and he scored 29 points and took down 10 rebounds in the loss to Kentucky in the championship game. Wallace had also made himself a better player, working on his outside shot during the previous summer. He went from a poor 3-point shooter to  a 42 percent 3-point shooter. He is also just six credits short of a degree in sociology, having taken a three-credit course this summer.</p>
        <p>There were rumors that Wallace was arrogant, or late for appointments with teams that were considering taking him higher in the draft, or that he was out of shape during evaluation workouts. (His supporters say he is shy, and there were legitimate mix-ups.) Whatever, his record in college and high school is solid.</p>
        <p>"Wallace is a fine player, who can do a multitude of things," said Isiah Thomas, vice president of the Toronto Raptors. "Some teams may have drafted for  need with centers and guards. But I think Wallace may be a godsend for the Knicks, who need a small forward who can shoot from outside. Some teams may one day regret not picking him earlier."</p>
        <p>Wallace has tried to distance himself from the Coleman influence and from comparisons. If this is taken to heart, and if an aspect of intelligence truly is learning from other people's mistakes, then John Wallace may indeed have a luminous future with the Knickerbockers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
