<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARTS BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="16ARTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1504815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philosophy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Segundo, Compay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marcuse, Herbert (1898-1979)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gogol, Nikolai (1809-52)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Billy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DB143CF935A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARTS BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Van Gelder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts Briefing column: Funeral service is held in Havana for famed Cuban singer and guitarist Compay Segundo, who has died at age 95; remains of German philosopher Herbert Marcuse, who died and was cremated in 1979, will be buried in cemetery in Berlin on anniversary of his birth there in 1898; three-foot, 200-pound marble nose, sculptured to commemorate Nikolai Gogol story, is recovered by police nearly year after it vanished from facade of building in St Petersburg, Russia; US poet laureate Billy Collins is among nominees for Britain's $16,000 Forward Prize for best poetry collection; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>HAVANA: FAREWELL TO COMPAY -- His coffin draped with a Cuban flag and topped by his customary white hat as admirers from across the country filed past, the Cuban singer and guitarist Compay Segundo was paid final respects yesterday in Havana. Segundo, who came to fame in his 90's among the elder musician statesmen in the album and film ''Buena Vista Social Club,'' died on Sunday at 95. Cuban television showed his popular videos, the BBC reported, and the press gave him credit for reviving the African-influenced style known as son. ''His death creates an unfillable void,'' Prensa Latina, the country's official news agency, said. Segundo is to be buried in Santiago de Cuba, in the eastern end of the island.</p>
        <p>BERLIN: HERBERT MARCUSE'S HOMECOMING -- Twenty-four years after his death, the philosopher Herbert Marcuse is to be buried in a cemetery in Berlin on Friday, the anniversary of his birth there in 1898. Marcuse, who argued that revolution against the repression of modern society is a precursor to utopian society, was a powerful influence on the student movements of the 1960's. Tomorrow the radical Angela Davis is to be among the speakers at a symposium in Marcuse's honor at the Free University in Berlin, Agence France-Presse reported. Marcuse was a United States citizen when he died in 1979 during a visit to what was then West Berlin. His wife, Ricky, had him cremated in Austria and sent his ashes to the United States because she ''felt that enough Jews had been reduced to ashes in Germany,'' his grandson Harold Marcuse explained on Marcuse's Web site, www.marcuse.org. The urn spent the intervening years in New Haven. After Harold Marcuse decided to return Herbert's remains to his birthplace, the city government agreed to provide an honorary grave site next to the great German philosopher Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel. ''Why give the Nazis the satisfaction of having purged the country even of the remains of some of its finest intellectuals?'' Harold Marcuse asked. ''Hasn't Germany finished its 40 years in the desert?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>HAVANA: FAREWELL TO COMPAY -- His coffin draped with a Cuban flag and topped by his customary white hat as admirers from across the country filed past, the Cuban singer and guitarist Compay Segundo was paid final respects yesterday in Havana. Segundo, who came to fame in his 90's among the elder musician statesmen in the album and film ''Buena Vista Social Club,'' died on Sunday at 95. Cuban television showed his popular videos, the BBC reported, and the press gave him credit for reviving the African-influenced style known as son. ''His death creates an unfillable void,'' Prensa Latina, the country's official news agency, said. Segundo is to be buried in Santiago de Cuba, in the eastern end of the island.</p>
        <p>BERLIN: HERBERT MARCUSE'S HOMECOMING -- Twenty-four years after his death, the philosopher Herbert Marcuse is to be buried in a cemetery in Berlin on Friday, the anniversary of his birth there in 1898. Marcuse, who argued that revolution against the repression of modern society is a precursor to utopian society, was a powerful influence on the student movements of the 1960's. Tomorrow the radical Angela Davis is to be among the speakers at a symposium in Marcuse's honor at the Free University in Berlin, Agence France-Presse reported. Marcuse was a United States citizen when he died in 1979 during a visit to what was then West Berlin. His wife, Ricky, had him cremated in Austria and sent his ashes to the United States because she ''felt that enough Jews had been reduced to ashes in Germany,'' his grandson Harold Marcuse explained on Marcuse's Web site, www.marcuse.org. The urn spent the intervening years in New Haven. After Harold Marcuse decided to return Herbert's remains to his birthplace, the city government agreed to provide an honorary grave site next to the great German philosopher Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel. ''Why give the Nazis the satisfaction of having purged the country even of the remains of some of its finest intellectuals?'' Harold Marcuse asked. ''Hasn't Germany finished its 40 years in the desert?''</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK: TWO TENORS -- They've sung on the stage of the Metropolitan Opera House. They've sung at the Colosseum in Rome, and on Saturday at 8 p.m., the young tenors Marcelo Álvarez, far left, and Salvatore Licitra will give a free performance on the Great Lawn of Central Park. Under the auspices of the New York City Department of Parks and Recreation and the Central Park Conservancy, the concert, part of a day of events celebrating the park's 150th anniversary, will include arias from ''La Bohème,'' ''Turandot,'' ''Rigoletto'' and ''Tosca,'' among other works.</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: RETURN OF GOGOL'S NOSE -- A three-foot, 200-pound marble nose, sculptured to commemorate a Nikolai Gogol (1809-1852) story, has been recovered by the police nearly a year after it vanished from the facade of a building in the middle of St. Petersburg, Russia. The police said it was found in another building, news agencies reported. ''The Nose'' (1835) by Gogol told of a military officer whose nose takes on a life of its own and roams the old imperial capital, getting into trouble and planning to move to Latvia before the major catches up with it. The stone nose had been attached to the building where the fictional officer supposedly lived.</p>
        <p>BOSTON: CENTENNIAL SUMMER -- The Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in Boston may be celebrating its centennial this year, but its ripe age doesn't mean that it's set in its ways. Beginning this week the museum, with a collection of great art spanning 30 centuries, is extending its hours and ushering in a festival of 20 new evening programs featuring concerts and films. The three-week, nine-performance Concerts Under the Canopy series on Friday and Saturday nights at 8 and Sunday afternoons at 3 offers jazz and Brazilian music under the stars and classical concerts in the afternoons in a specially designed tent in the museum's exterior gardens, a space previously inaccessible to visitors. Cinema Centennial: Movies and Music at 8:30 p.m. from July 22 through 24 and July 29 through 31 in the garden tent draws upon the Harvard Film Archive to trace the history of film with an emphasis on music, innovation and urban environment. The series, including some films presented with a live piano accompaniment, begins with selections from around 1903, when the museum was established.</p>
        <p>FOOTNOTES</p>
        <p>The United States poet laureate, Billy Collins, is on the shortlist of nominees for the $16,000 Forward Prize for the best poetry collection, billed as Britain's richest annual poetry award. The other contenders are Ciaran Carson, Ian Duhig, Lavinia Greenlaw and Paul Muldoon, the BBC reported yesterday. The winner is to be announced on Oct. 8, the eve of Britain's National Poetry Day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
