<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prize Improves This Year's Model</title>
    <meta content="16BERKOW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/16/sports/baseball/16berkow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1504950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DA153CF935A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prize Improves This Year's Model</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Game's New Rules Bring Some Passion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column contends that relating outcome of All-Star Game to home-field advantage for World Series made game more interesting; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE hype for baseball's All-Star Game last night was such that one might have expected the mother of all baseball games.</p>
        <p>Mother it wasn't. But it was a lot better than second cousin. It was adroitly played, with a number of starters sticking around for a good part of the game, something that hasn't happened in recent years, given the managers' notion to insert as many players into the game as possible. Which made winning secondary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Major League Baseball, this year's All-Star Game was an adroitly played contest that had to be considered a boffo success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE hype for baseball's All-Star Game last night was such that one might have expected the mother of all baseball games.</p>
        <p>Mother it wasn't. But it was a lot better than second cousin. It was adroitly played, with a number of starters sticking around for a good part of the game, something that hasn't happened in recent years, given the managers' notion to insert as many players into the game as possible. Which made winning secondary.</p>
        <p>There were home runs last night at U.S. Cellular Field. There were strikeouts. There were superb fielding plays. But tension there wasn't. An abundance of thrills there wasn't. Until the bottom of the eighth.</p>
        <p>Up to then, the sellout crowd of 47,609 seemed as excited by the smoking fly-over of Navy airplanes at the conclusion of the national anthem as anything that would transpire in the game. The American League took a 1-0 lead in the third, then the National League took charge with five runs in the fifth. Jason Giambi's homer in the seventh brought the American League a little closer, to 6-4. In the eighth, Vernon Wells's run-scoring double made it 6-5, and Hank Blalock, the Rangers' third baseman, followed with two-run homer to put the American League on top, 7-6, the final score.</p>
        <p>This was the first time in history that a big-league All-Star Game counted for something beyond bragging rights for one league over the other or for pride in the performance of an individual player. This was going to have an impact on the World Series, of all things. If some of the games in recent history had resembled nothing more passionate than an old-timers' game, nothing more exciting than a softball game at a family picnic, this game had cachet. The league that won the game would give its World Series representative the home-field advantage.</p>
        <p>This was the fallout from last season's All-Star Game fiasco. That game ended in a tie after 11 innings when neither manager had any pitchers left to complete the contest.</p>
        <p>In the American League dugout before the game, Alex Rodriguez, the Rangers' expensive shortstop, addressed the new wrinkle by Major League Baseball for the World Series. He said that from a personal standpoint it had no effect, ''because I always go all out.''</p>
        <p>But the impact on the postseason is significant.</p>
        <p>''It puts a huge responsibility on the guys playing in the All-Star Game for the guys who will be playing in the World Series,'' he said. ''It has huge ramifications in late October. We owe it to our peers to try as hard as we can to win.''</p>
        <p>Eric Gagne, the Dodgers' closer, said that any time he had gone on the field, ''from Little League to the majors,'' he always went out to win.</p>
        <p>''No matter what the game was,'' he said. ''I'm certain the other players feel the same way. No one wants to embarrass himself. And you always play hard. I mean, it's instinct with us. You don't think about not diving for a ball if that's how you always play. If you think about not risking injury, then you start doing things you don't do on an everyday basis. And that's when you can get hurt.''</p>
        <p>Gagne mentioned that most striking of hardnosed All-Star Game plays, when Pete Rose in 1970 barreled into catcher Ray Fosse and knocked the ball loose, scoring the run that won the game for the National League in the 12th inning. Fosse had had dinner with Rose the night before the game. Years later, Fosse acknowledged that the injury incurred in that collision cut his career short.</p>
        <p>The two managers of last night's game had spoken about what strategies they might employ. One significant point was that some players on the rosters would not get into the game.</p>
        <p>Mike Scioscia, the Anaheim and American League manager, said he apologized to some guys in advance, telling them ''there's a probability you won't play.''</p>
        <p>Dusty Baker, manager of the Cubs and the National League, said, ''I don't like guys traveling thousands of miles and not getting the opportunity of playing in front of family and friends.''</p>
        <p>But so it would have to be, especially with a close game. Six National Leaguers and six American Leaguers did not see action.</p>
        <p>In major league baseball, the All-Star Game is an exhibition. And too often the players have given the impression that that was how they treated it. When Barry Bonds picked up Torii Hunter between innings as they crossed paths after Hunter made an outstanding catch on a drive of his at last year's game, it set a discordant tone. He would never have done that in a game that had significance in the standings or in the postseason.</p>
        <p>Most fans want to see guys playing as seriously as they do in the regular or postseason. Bonds's gesture was a prime example of, as E.B. White said in another context, someone who was full of fun, but he wasn't funny.</p>
        <p>For Major League Baseball, though, anything short of last year's debacle, which this game hardly was, had to be considered a boffo success. In fact, given the come-from-behind triumph of the American League, the game was boffo, period.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
