<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Rostenkowski's Plea Deal</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="842691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSTENKOWSKI, DAN (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7DB1039F933A25757C0A960958260" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Rostenkowski's Plea Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is always a measure of sadness in seeing a skillful legislator brought  down, even if by his own corruption. But the plea bargain formally agreed to yesterday by former Representative Dan Rostenkowski, the longtime chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, brings to a satisfactory conclusion an important case involving the abuse of public trust by a powerful official.</p>
        <p>In 1994 the Chicago Democrat was indicted on 17 felony counts centered on misuse of his office. They included charges that he hired no-show employees, received kickbacks from workers, embezzled money from the House Post Office and used government money for personal and family expenses. In all, he was accused of embezzling more than $500,000 from public funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is always a measure of sadness in seeing a skillful legislator brought  down, even if by his own corruption. But the plea bargain formally agreed to yesterday by former Representative Dan Rostenkowski, the longtime chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, brings to a satisfactory conclusion an important case involving the abuse of public trust by a powerful official.</p>
        <p>In 1994 the Chicago Democrat was indicted on 17 felony counts centered on misuse of his office. They included charges that he hired no-show employees, received kickbacks from workers, embezzled money from the House Post Office and used government money for personal and family expenses. In all, he was accused of embezzling more than $500,000 from public funds.</p>
        <p>Under the plea arrangement, less generous than one he brassily rejected two  years ago, Mr. Rostenkowski pleaded guilty to two mail fraud charges involving converting House funds for personal use. The judge said his actual corruption was far greater, an assessment Mr. Rostenkowski rejected outside the courtroom.  Mr. Rostenkowski will serve 17 months in prison and pay a $100,000 fine -- an appropriately stern punishment that carries a loud warning against official corruption.</p>
        <p>This resolution also contains vindication for House Republicans like Speaker  Newt Gingrich. While still in the House minority, they refused to allow a cover-up of the House Post Office scandal, which triggered the Rostenkowski investigation. They seized the issue as a telling example of shoddy management of the House to benefit Democratic insiders, and to support their claim that the Democrats had ruled the House for too long.</p>
        <p>House Democrats remained in deep denial about Mr. Rostenkowski long after there was good reason to question his ethics. Even after he refused to testify to a grand jury looking into possible corruption in the House, his Democratic colleagues chose to ignore that evasion of his public responsibility by unanimously re-electing him as Ways and Means chairman. As the Justice Department was nearing a decision as to whether to seek an indictment against Mr. Rostenkowski, President Clinton traveled to Chicago to lavish praise on his  legislative leadership and to offer support for what turned out to be a losing re-election bid.</p>
        <p>Eric Holder, the tough-minded U.S. Attorney who vigorously pursued the Rostenkowski case, deserves special praise. He never lost sight of what he described at the time of the indictment as "the corrosive effect" of Mr. Rostenkowski's misconduct "on our democratic system of government and on the trust our citizens have in their elected officials."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
