<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business and Health; The Squeeze On Drugstores</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG STORES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUGS (PHARMACEUTICALS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAIL ORDER COMPANIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERMARKETS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">K MART CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WAL-MART STORES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREUDENHEIM, MILT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS AND HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugstores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA143DF937A35751C1A966958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business and Health; The Squeeze On Drugstores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Milt Freudenheim</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREUDENHEIM, MILT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH few doctors make house calls, many drugstores still deliver prescriptions to the homes of elderly customers. Scrambling to retain customer loyalty in the highly competitive retail pharmacy business, many drugstores specialize in advice and services. Eighty-five percent have also purchased computer systems that cost $10,000 and up, and some even have satellite links to keep supplies and insurers' payments flowing.</p>
        <p>The McKesson Corporation's PCS pharmacy card unit, for example, operates a national electronic claims-processing network. An identification card with a magnetic stripe is passed like a credit card through a $200 device, which quickly tells the druggist what the customer's health plan pays for. The bill goes electronically to a data processing center in Scottsdale, Ariz., which pays the pharmacies every two weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH few doctors make house calls, many drugstores still deliver prescriptions to the homes of elderly customers. Scrambling to retain customer loyalty in the highly competitive retail pharmacy business, many drugstores specialize in advice and services. Eighty-five percent have also purchased computer systems that cost $10,000 and up, and some even have satellite links to keep supplies and insurers' payments flowing.</p>
        <p>The McKesson Corporation's PCS pharmacy card unit, for example, operates a national electronic claims-processing network. An identification card with a magnetic stripe is passed like a credit card through a $200 device, which quickly tells the druggist what the customer's health plan pays for. The bill goes electronically to a data processing center in Scottsdale, Ariz., which pays the pharmacies every two weeks.</p>
        <p>Prompt payment is vital to the nation's 55,000 pharmacies, for their pretax profit margins have fallen to 3 percent from 5.5 percent in the 1960's. Pharmacists are being squeezed by insurers, which increasingly insist on price discounts. Insurer guidelines on prescribing drugs are followed by about 22 percent of all office-based doctors, and the number is growing, said John Schaetzl, vice president of Scott-Levin Associates, a consulting firm in Newtown, Pa., that surveys physicians.</p>
        <p>As retailing categories overlap and blur, retail druggists have had to compete with big discount chains like K Mart and Wal-Mart Stores, each with 1,000 or more pharmacies; mail-order pharmacy services, and supermarket chains, which are accustomed to even lower profit margins, based onmoving products off the shelf faster than drugstores do. And in the front of their stores, the druggists compete with the health and beauty aids sections of groceries, convenience stores, variety stores and specialty discount stores.</p>
        <p>But the pharmacy business can also be difficult for such competitors. Joseph Thomas 3d, an economist at Purdue University, said the expenses in operating a pharmacy "are very different from operating a grocery." He added, "You need pharmacists, people with knowledge and time, willing to answer questions about over-the-counter products." A sign in the West Main Pharmacy, an independent store in Penns Grove, N.J., says, "Please ask our pharmacists questions before you purchase over-the-counter drugs."</p>
        <p>"We foresee gross margins in the pharmacy business continuing to drop," said David D. Bernauer, vice president and treasurer of the Walgreen Company, which is based in Deerfield, Ill. "The bottom line to the whole thing is: Who can most efficiently distribute that prescription to the customer?" Walgreen stores, which deal with 800 insurance plans, are linked by satellite to a computer center in Mount Prospect, Ill. "In five seconds, we check the patient's eligibility and other parameters like which drugs are covered, the number of days' supply, whether generics are mandatory," he said. "The system greatly reduces the percentage of rejects and dishonored claims and the cost of shipping paperwork." Sales at Walgreen's 1,575 stores are growing by 20 percent annually, reflecting rising drug prices and the addition of 110 stores this year, Mr. Bernauer said.</p>
        <p>To compete with the chains, independents like the West Main Pharmacy work on customer service. "We can't always match the dollar figure," said Louis A. Mitchell, the owner, who is in the store daily from 9 A.M. to 9 P.M. "My main concern is that the patient has to be satisfied that what they are doing is based on good sound advice."</p>
        <p>Don Moore, an independent pharmacist who is president of the Moore Drugstore in Kokomo, Ind., maintains a staff nurse for consultations.</p>
        <p>"All retail drugstores, whether they are independent or chains, are being squeezed much more today," said David Malmberg, vice president for strategic planning with McKesson's wholesale unit, the nation's largest drug wholesaler.</p>
        <p>Insurers that pay most of the cost of drugs directly to the store may account for 75 percent of the prescription business by the end of the decade, said Robert J. Mandelbaum, a pharmacist who is a vice president of the 1,136-store Revco chain, based in Twinsburg, Ohio. Revco is adding patient counseling areas to its stores.</p>
        <p>Some druggists are developing niche markets like joint ventures with hospitals to supply equipment for home health care. And Fay's, based in Liverpool, N.Y., which has 185 drugstores, is opening free-standing operations just to supply nursing homes. "They are a large growth end of our prescription business," said Henry A. Panasci, Fay's chairman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
