<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aide Defends Cranston but Talks of 'Link' to Gifts From Keating</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONGRESSIONAL INVESTIGATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LINCOLN SAVINGS &amp; LOAN ASSN (IRVINE, CALIF)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRANSTON, ALAN (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCAIN, JOHN S (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLENN, JOHN (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">INOUYE, DANIEL (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIEGLE, DONALD W JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DECONCINI, DENNIS (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEATING, CHARLES H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACOBSON, JOY N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings and Loan Associations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD91030F937A35751C1A966958260" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aide Defends Cranston but Talks of 'Link' to Gifts From Keating</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Alan Cranston's chief fund-raiser acknowledged today that her boss's intervention on behalf of Charles H. Keating Jr. might have prompted campaign contributions to the Senator and his political organizations.</p>
        <p>"In retrospect, I think that there was a link there," the fund-raiser, Joy N. Jacobson, said in a deposition whose transcript was released today by the Senate Ethics Committee. But in further testimony today, she said any link was in Mr. Keating's mind and insisted that there were no improprieties. And she vehemently denied that there was any pact between Mr. Keating and Mr. Cranston to trade favors for political contributions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Alan Cranston's chief fund-raiser acknowledged today that her boss's intervention on behalf of Charles H. Keating Jr. might have prompted campaign contributions to the Senator and his political organizations.</p>
        <p>"In retrospect, I think that there was a link there," the fund-raiser, Joy N. Jacobson, said in a deposition whose transcript was released today by the Senate Ethics Committee. But in further testimony today, she said any link was in Mr. Keating's mind and insisted that there were no improprieties. And she vehemently denied that there was any pact between Mr. Keating and Mr. Cranston to trade favors for political contributions.</p>
        <p>Testifying in the fourth week of hearings on allegations that Mr. Cranston and four other Senators breached rules by pressuring Federal regulators to help Mr. Keating's Lincoln Savings and Loan Association, Ms. Jacobson said, "There are a lot of people who are not subtle about what it is they want, and there was no reason to have to deal with those people." Tears From DeConcini</p>
        <p>In earlier testimony that evoked tears from Senator Dennis DeConcini, Senator Daniel K. Inouye told the committee that his family and aides had implored him not to speak to defend the five Senators, but that he felt he had to.</p>
        <p>"I believe what is on trial here are not the five colleagues of mine, but the United States Senate -- and for that matter, the Congress of the United States," said Mr. Inouye, a Hawaii Democrat who has been in the Senate since 1963 and who served on the panels investigating the Watergate and the Iran-contra affairs.</p>
        <p>The panel's special counsel, Robert S. Bennett, said Ms. Jacobson's acknowledgment of a link was central in establishing a connection between donations to Mr. Cranston and favors for Mr. Keating.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobson's deposition came in July. In the course of it, Mr. Bennett told her that there was "a repeated pattern here of action being taken on behalf of Mr. Keating right before or right after you and the Senator are asking for large sums of money to be donated."</p>
        <p>Mr. Cranston's campaigns and political groups collected close to $1 million from Mr. Keating, his family or employees -- far more than any of the other Senators in the Ethics Committee's inquiry. They are Mr. DeConcini and John McCain of Arizona, Donald W. Riegle Jr. of Michigan and John Glenn of Ohio. All but Mr. McCain are Democrats.  Breaking a Senate Rule</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Jacobson was not on Mr. Cranston's Senate staff when she raised money for him, she described to the committee today how she played an integral role in his office. She would sometimes sit at a round table in the majority whip's office in the Capitol, she said, where she would phone donors and make appointments, with Mr. Cranston, the Senate's second-ranking Democrat, at times sitting nearby.</p>
        <p>The testimony prompted Senator Trent Lott, a Mississippi Republican who sits on the ethics panel, to remind Ms. Jacobson that a Senate rule prohibits fund-raising on Senate premises. She said she had never heard of the rule.</p>
        <p>In portraying Ms. Jacobson as a crucial link between Mr. Cranston and Mr. Keating, Mr. Bennett quoted from several memorandums she wrote to the Senator, explicitly suggesting actions he should take on behalf of Lincoln.</p>
        <p>She described how she would sit in on meetings with Mr. Cranston and Mr. Keating and his associates, even though she knew nothing about banking issues. While Mr. Cranston had testified that the meetings helped Ms. Jacobson with her fund-raising, she said that was not the case. Big Sums Were Asked</p>
        <p>"Obviously, that's Senator Cranston's assumption of why I was there," Ms. Jacobson said. "I did not have to be in a meeting like that to know what was of concern to contributors. I didn't think it was a terribly effective use of my time."</p>
        <p>Mr. Keating, whose savings and loan ultimately collapsed, is under indictment on criminal fraud charges in California.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobson said she and Mr. Cranston sometimes differed on how aggressively they should solicit contributions. In one case, she suggested that he ask Mr. Keating for $250,000 for a voter registration group he supported, but Mr. Cranston wanted to double the request.</p>
        <p>"I just thought that was too big a jump," Ms. Jacobson said in the deposition. "He said, 'I think he'll do a half million dollars.' " Eventually Mr. Cranston asked for $250,000 and received it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inouye was called essentially as a character witness by Mr. DeConcini, who was the focus of negative attention last week when two witnesses depicted him as being deeply involved with Mr. Keating. While Mr. Inouye conceded under questioning that he had not read all the evidence, he said he had watched much of the proceedings on television and believed that the five Senators did nothing out of the ordinary on behalf of Mr. Keating. He sounded bewildered that his colleagues were even under investigation.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Chairman," he told Howell Heflin, the Alabama Democrat who is head of the committee, "the generations may have passed me by. But up until recently, it was considered a virtue or quality of a Senator or any legislator to be a fighter."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
