<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holy Whistling Helium! Another Quantum Trick</title>
    <meta content="08HELI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/08/science/08heli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1648229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Helium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California (Berkeley)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Packard, Richard E (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoskinson, Emile</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D81E3BF93BA35751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holy Whistling Helium! Another Quantum Trick</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Holy Whistling Helium! Another Quantum Trick</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Richard E Packard, University of California, Berkeley, physics professor, and graduate student Emile Hoskinson conduct study on properties and behavior of cooled helium 4, which has two protons and two neutrons in its nucleus; study, which is published in journal Nature, involved pushing superfluid helium through holes to manipulate its energy flow; process causes helium to make whistling sound; drawing (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the world of quantum physics, particles leap through impenetrable barriers or exist in two places at once, secret codes can't be broken, electrical currents pass through wires without resistance. Here's another quantum trick: liquid helium that whistles.</p>
        <p>Writing last month in the journal Nature, Dr. Richard E. Packard, a professor of physics at University of California, Berkeley, and Emile Hoskinson, a graduate student, described the feat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have discovered a feat of quantum physics that involves mini-tornadoes and superfluids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the world of quantum physics, particles leap through impenetrable barriers or exist in two places at once, secret codes can't be broken, electrical currents pass through wires without resistance. Here's another quantum trick: liquid helium that whistles.</p>
        <p>Writing last month in the journal Nature, Dr. Richard E. Packard, a professor of physics at University of California, Berkeley, and Emile Hoskinson, a graduate student, described the feat.</p>
        <p>They cooled helium -- specifically helium 4, which has two protons and two neutrons in its nucleus -- to minus 456 degrees Fahrenheit, a few degrees above absolute zero. At ultracold temperatures, helium 4 condenses into a type of liquid known as a superfluid, able to flow utterly without friction.</p>
        <p>They then pushed the helium through tiny holes about a thousandth the width of a human hair -- and that is when the whistling started.</p>
        <p>The reason is that a frictionless liquid does not behave as one might expect. One might expect that pushing a frictionless liquid would accelerate it to ever-increasing speeds -- but it doesn't. The speed tops out at a few miles per hour.</p>
        <p>What physicists have found instead is that vortexes -- mini-tornadoes -- spontaneously arise in the superfluid, and as the mini-tornadoes grow longer and longer, they crash into one another and into the sides of the container, and energy is lost.</p>
        <p>Pushing helium 4 through a tiny hole sped up the flow, creating a vortex. ''It will eventually crash into the walls,'' Dr. Packard said. ''Then the energy gets turned into just heat.'' Dissipating the energy dropped the speed of the superfluid flow. The cycle repeated. ''It's accelerating, then dropping,'' Dr. Packard said, ''accelerating, then dropping.''</p>
        <p>That produces pressure waves that can be picked up by a sensitive microphone and turned into sound.</p>
        <p>But with a single hole, the mini-tornadoes form and crash at random intervals, and the noise would sound like noise. In the Berkeley experiment, the helium was pushed through a grid containing 4,225 holes. The expectation was that 4,225 random noises would mostly cancel out one another.</p>
        <p>Instead, when Mr. Hoskinson donned headphones and listened to the helium, he heard a pure, clear tone, like a pennywhistle (online at nytimes.com/science), with the pitch changing with the pressure applied to the superfluid.</p>
        <p>Dr. Packard said the vortexes at the different holes appeared to interact with one another, causing them to form and crash all at the same pace. ''Maybe it's like crickets synchronizing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The phenomenon is not just a silly quantum trick; it could be used for gyroscopes to measure wobbles in Earth's spin or by submarines for better navigation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
