<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Converted Schoolhouses: Keeping a Little Local History Alive</title>
    <meta content="03LIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/03/realestate/03LIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1608626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS: LIVING HERE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Swede Township (ND)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Cole Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EEDF1431F930A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Converted Schoolhouses: Keeping a Little Local History Alive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Converted Schoolhouses: Keeping a Little Local History Alive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Seth Kugel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Cole Morris Jr on living in converted schoolhouse in Swede Township, ND; photos and brief descriptions of similar properties for sale around country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Cole Morris Jr., 66, retired teacher and real estate developer  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  WHERE -- Swede Township, N.D.</p>
        <p>My house was built as a school in 1918, and it was called Swede Township School No. 1. When they closed it in 1959, the school had 13 students. The students consolidated and went into the Kulm school district. It's still Swede Township. Everything around me is almost all German, but in my particular township are mostly Swedes. Practically all my neighbors are the very same neighbors whose families homesteaded the land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A resident of Swede Township, N.D., lives in an old converted schoolhouse, cooking in a kitchen that used to be the school's hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Cole Morris Jr., 66, retired teacher and real estate developer  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  WHERE -- Swede Township, N.D.</p>
        <p>My house was built as a school in 1918, and it was called Swede Township School No. 1. When they closed it in 1959, the school had 13 students. The students consolidated and went into the Kulm school district. It's still Swede Township. Everything around me is almost all German, but in my particular township are mostly Swedes. Practically all my neighbors are the very same neighbors whose families homesteaded the land.</p>
        <p>It's got a steeple on it and the original bell tower, it's a typical, very typical, North Dakota country school. When it was built it cost $1,920, for the material and everything. They put a little addition on it in 1927 and that cost $725. A lot of the kids rode their horses to school, so there was a little barn in the back where they could keep their horses during the day.</p>
        <p>Right after it closed it became the township meeting hall. Then a lady who went to school there as a child bought it and used it as a summer home for a few years, and then my brother-in-law and I bought it in 1982. It was never really empty.</p>
        <p>We split it up so on the inside we have two bedrooms, we have a major living room, and then what used to be the hall we made a kitchen. It's just a real cozy hunting lodge. During the summer, I get out there every two weeks. It's about 130 miles from my regular home, in Wahpeton.</p>
        <p>I know all the neighbors. What happens to so many of these rural schools is they just become destroyed. They're abandoned, and then it doesn't take long before raccoons and things get in. The people like the idea that their school is intact, and it's a little part of history out there.</p>
        <p>As told to Seth Kugel</p>
        <p>ON THE MARKET  Information was provided by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Gualala, Calif.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $950,000  The one-room 1920's Fish Rock Schoolhouse was converted into a small two-bedroom house with one bathroom in the 1970's. There is also a small one-bedroom schoolteacher's cottage; it can be used as a rental or as a guesthouse. The buildings are on one of two adjacent two-acre cliffside lots that are being offered as a package. The other lot is empty. They are on the ocean in Mendocino County near the private Sea Ranch community. Agent: Debbie Rosson, Coldwell Banker Pacific Real Estate, (800) 660-3591, www.cbpac.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Florence, Colo.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $700,000  This 9,000-square-foot house was built as the Emerson School in 1895 in this small town on the Arkansas River in the Rocky Mountains, less than an hour south of Colorado Springs. Each of the bedrooms is 25 by 30 feet and has a walk-in closet. There are a large exercise room, two bathrooms and 13-foot ceilings. Agent: Brandon Angel, Keller Williams Realty, (719) 240-6471; www.florenceschoolhouse.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Beulah, Mich.  WHAT -- One-room house  HOW MUCH -- $99,000  The floor plan of this 1920's one-room schoolhouse has been little changed. The house is 1,000 square feet and has been used for the last 40 years as a summer home. The belfry is intact, and the bell still works. An attic room is above a detached two-car garage. The property is 2.4 acres and in Benzie County, a recreational area 12 miles from Lake Michigan. Nearby are Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore and golf and skiing at Crystal Mountain resort. Agent: Judy Stovak, International Realty Plus, (231) 882-4347; www.judystovak.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Wilmot, N.H.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $195,000  Built in 1880 as the Dodge Schoolhouse, this house is on nearly two acres, including land on both sides of the road, about halfway between Concord and Hanover and near Interstate 89. The house is 950 square feet and has one bathroom, a den, a wood-burning stove, a three-season screen porch and a detached two-car garage. A brook runs through the property, which is a 90-minute drive northwest of Boston. Agents: Karen Baker and Stefan Timbrell, Country Houses Real Estate, (603) 526-4020; www.countryhousesre.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Mosquero, N.M.  WHAT -- 2,000 acres with schoolhouse ruins  HOW MUCH -- $351,000  This stone shell of a 1936 schoolhouse is about 40 by 60 feet. A roof, a floor and other work could turn it into a vacation house or a hunting lodge. The ranch is 30 miles off a paved road and comprises four unfenced, noncontiguous pieces of land, with access rights, within another larger ranch. Mosquero is 150 miles east of Sante Fe. Game in the area include mule deer, Barbary sheep, quail, dove and turkey. Broker: Sam Morrow, United Country Mesa Realty, (505) 487-2910; www.logan-nm-realestate.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Dorset, Vt.  WHAT -- 7-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $2.7 million  The schoolhouse, which serves as a one-bedroom guesthouse on this 169-acre estate, was built in 1776 in Enfield, Mass., and moved before the town was submerged during the filling of the Quabbin Reservoir from 1939 to 1946. It has a vaulted ceiling, pine paneling, a kitchenette, a fireplace, a sleeping loft and two bathrooms. The main house is 5,000 square feet, was built in 1775 and has four bathrooms. There is a three-car detached garage. Broker: Deke August, Dorset Village Properties, (802) 867-5300; www.dorsetrealestate.com.</p>
        <p>HAVENS: LIVING HERE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
