<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The AT&amp;T Chief's Report Card</title>
    <meta content="22MIKE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/22/business/media/22MIKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Comcast Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, C Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Comcast Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Armstrong, C Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DA1F3EF931A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="2142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The AT&amp;T Chief's Report Card</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The AT&amp;T Chief's Report Card</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>C Michael Armstrong's performance as AT&amp;T chairman assessed in light of his plan to sell company's cable television business to Comcast and join what will be renamed AT&amp;T Comcast as chairman; he has failed to realize original plan of creating vast network that could deliver any communications service to anyone, anywere; has been more victim of outside forces than of bad strategy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1998, just two days after AT&amp;T announced its great leap into the cable television business, C. Michael Armstrong, the chairman, was already exasperated.</p>
        <p>''The disinformation, it's incredible,'' he said in an interview barely 48 hours after the company had announced a $31.8 billion deal to acquire Tele-Communications Inc. ''I've never seen anything like it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although C. Michael Armstrong failed to realize his original plan for AT&amp;T, in many ways, he was more a victim of outside forces than of a bad strategy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1998, just two days after AT&amp;T announced its great leap into the cable television business, C. Michael Armstrong, the chairman, was already exasperated.</p>
        <p>''The disinformation, it's incredible,'' he said in an interview barely 48 hours after the company had announced a $31.8 billion deal to acquire Tele-Communications Inc. ''I've never seen anything like it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong, a former top executive at Hughes and I.B.M., had moved into the corner office at AT&amp;T's Basking Ridge, N.J., headquarters eight months earlier with a mandate to reshape the company. With his bid to acquire TCI, then the No. 2 cable provider, AT&amp;T took a bold step to regain what it had lost under government pressure in 1984: direct lines into millions of homes. But Wall Street, confused by the deal's audacity and concerned that it would weaken AT&amp;T's earnings, sent the company's shares plummeting.</p>
        <p>It was the first time that Mr. Armstrong, a proud, barrel-chested man looking to cap four decades in business by reinvigorating one of the world's most august corporations, found himself on one page and AT&amp;T investors on another.</p>
        <p>But it would not be the last. By the time AT&amp;T's leap into cable essentially ended last week, when Mr. Armstrong agreed to sell the company's cable assets to Comcast for $47 billion in stock plus $20 billion in debt, the disconnect had almost become a theme of Mr. Armstrong's tenure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong failed to realize his original plan for AT&amp;T, which was to create a vast network that could deliver any communications service to anyone, anywhere. But in many ways, he was more a victim of outside forces than of a bad strategy.</p>
        <p>The stock market and the industry's technology assumptions have changed dramatically since Mr. Armstrong came to AT&amp;T four years ago. And even if the cable systems end up carrying nothing more than TV shows and Internet traffic -- rather than all-in-one communications that also replace the telephone -- Mr. Armstrong will be able to persuasively argue that he performed perhaps as well as anyone could have for AT&amp;T and its shareholders, under the circumstances that were thrust upon him.</p>
        <p>''I think he did the best he could with the cards he was dealt,'' Amos Hostetter Jr., the former chairman of MediaOne and an AT&amp;T board member, said in an interview Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong had an acute, ambitious vision of where AT&amp;T needed to go, of how it needed to re-establish direct links with customers, lest it wither amid the flourishing Bell local phone carriers. Given time, it might have worked.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Armstrong struggled to persuade investors, especially after the collapse of the dot-com and telecommunications stock bubble. In the end, when Mr. Armstrong, striding toward his vision, realized that he was losing his flock, he returned to the Wall Street fold with a vision that was far less ambitious.</p>
        <p>With the cable deal, Mr. Armstrong, 63, has essentially defined his career's end. If the acquisition is completed in about a year, as is expected, Mr. Armstrong will leave AT&amp;T and join what will be renamed AT&amp;T Comcast as chairman.</p>
        <p>By then, AT&amp;T will probably have issued a new stock to track its consumer operations, and the remaining AT&amp;T will focus on providing voice and data communications services to business customers. (AT&amp;T spun off its wireless operation as an independent company last summer.) The remaining AT&amp;T, offering communications services for business and homes, will probably be run by David W. Dorman, now AT&amp;T's president.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T Comcast will be under the wing of the Roberts family that controls Comcast. Brian Roberts, 42, will be AT&amp;T Comcast's chief executive. Mr. Armstrong has a deal to serve as AT&amp;T Comcast's chairman until 2005.</p>
        <p>Were it enough that Mr. Armstrong rescued AT&amp;T from looming oblivion, he might be remembered as one of the greatest executives of his generation. When things were bleak, he kept his company and its shareholders in the great game of communications and media with a run-scoring double. But he missed the home run that he had defined so ambitiously.</p>
        <p>''Armstrong gets an A for a bold great plan,'' said Howard Anderson, founder of the Yankee Group, a research firm, and a communications expert who has followed AT&amp;T for three decades. ''He gets a C for implementation and gross miscalculation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong admits to mistakes.</p>
        <p>''I did not see the dot-com, telecom implosion,'' he said. ''That basically took the values out of what the market had been giving us for the investments we had been making.''</p>
        <p>''It was a fast shift,'' he added, ''and it surprised all of us.''</p>
        <p>If AT&amp;T had kept going the way it was going when Mr. Armstrong arrived in 1997, there might not even be much of an AT&amp;T at all by now.</p>
        <p>The sequence of events at AT&amp;T between 1996 and 1997 bordered on the farcical. In October 1996, the company hired a printing company executive, John R. Walter, as president and heir-apparent to Robert E. Allen, then the chief executive and chairman. Nine months later, the board essentially fired Mr. Walter; one of AT&amp;T's directors, Walter Y. Elisha, said that Mr. Walter lacked the ''intellectual leadership to lead AT&amp;T.''</p>
        <p>Seemingly spent by his astute spinoff of AT&amp;T's equipment business as Lucent Technologies, Mr. Allen appeared to withdraw into a shell. Yet even then it was clear that AT&amp;T needed a new vision to overcome the harsh fact that its long-distance telephone business could no longer sustain the company's future. The Telecommunications Act of 1996 had created a path for the Bell local phone companies to get into long distance. The door was also opened for AT&amp;T to return to the local market, but there was no sign the company was prepared to push through it.</p>
        <p>Fed up with Mr. Allen, the board finally hired Mr. Armstrong as chairman and chief executive in the fall of 1997. He had been a leading candidate for the job a year earlier but Mr. Allen had demanded that his successor serve an apprenticeship as AT&amp;T's president before ascending to the top job. Mr. Armstrong had refused. Now he had it -- on his terms -- but the chalice had been poisoned.</p>
        <p>''If he had been brought in when they should have brought him in, he would have been the crowning hero,'' Mr. Anderson of the Yankee Group said. ''But by waiting 18 months, the plan collapsed.''</p>
        <p>That plan was to rejuvenate AT&amp;T by investing in three growth businesses that would allow the company to maintain and build on its customer relationships. The first was advanced digital wireless services. The second was data and Internet services for business customers, an opportunity that AT&amp;T had largely ceded to WorldCom and Sprint. The third, and the most important, was to assemble a cable infrastructure that would allow AT&amp;T to bypass the Bell companies and establish direct links to homes so it could deliver telephone, television and high-speed data services.</p>
        <p>In the plan's execution, Mr. Armstrong made significant miscalculations, analysts say. At least as important, however, AT&amp;T's long-distance business, which generated much of its cash, eroded far faster than anyone expected. And investors lost patience long before the plan could deliver its payoff.</p>
        <p>While the wireless and data communications components of Mr. Armstrong's plan were relevant, they paled in importance beside the cable strategy. AT&amp;T's bedrock was its consumer long-distance business and it was clear that if AT&amp;T did not connect to those consumers in a new, more direct way, then those customers would eventually be gobbled up by the Bell companies.</p>
        <p>And so, in 1998 AT&amp;T made the deal to acquire TCI and the next year, MediaOne Group, another big cable operator. It was in the structure of these deals that Mr. Armstrong now appears to have made his first significant miscalculation. Not only were those deals expensive, but they also added immensely -- MediaOne in particular -- to AT&amp;T's ballooning debt load.</p>
        <p>At the end of 1997, AT&amp;T's total debt stood at about $17 billion. By the end of last year, that figure was about $65 billion (though much of that debt has been paid off).</p>
        <p>''I think we paid full prices,'' for the cable systems, Sanford I. Weill, chairman of Citigroup and an AT&amp;T director, said in an interview. ''In retrospect we would have been better off, obviously, doing those deals for more stock rather than cash.''</p>
        <p>In addition, most analysts were skeptical that AT&amp;T could meet its own schedule and price outline for deploying the full panoply of services that Mr. Armstrong envisioned.</p>
        <p>Some of these issues could have been ameliorated had Mr. Armstrong installed a stable, well-respected management team for the company's cable operation. But he was not able to retain or attract a cable industry veteran to work under him, so Mr. Armstrong turned instead to Daniel E. Somers, AT&amp;T's chief financial officer. Mr. Somers had run a Canadian cable company for two years, but he was never perceived on Wall Street as the sort of first-rate cable operator required to pull off Mr. Armstrong's ambitious agenda.</p>
        <p>By the middle of last year, the storm clouds had gathered over Basking Ridge. AT&amp;T's core consumer long-distance business, which was being counted on to stay afloat while the company furiously built its future, was being swamped.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the collapse of the dot-com stock bubble caused many investors who had come to applaud AT&amp;T's plan for the future to begin to worry more about its ability to deliver earnings growth in the present. The credit rating agencies came calling, too, concerned about AT&amp;T's swelling debt load.</p>
        <p>By the fall of 2000, time had run out. The directors decided to cut bait, split the company into its component parts and hope that shareholders would get more from multiple entities than they would from one. If there would be no AT&amp;T empire, then at least there might be a collection of city states to make up for it.</p>
        <p>''I think Mike was a brilliant strategist and I think he still is,'' Mr. Weill said. ''It was hindered by the fact that it cost us a lot of money, which made us take on a lot of debt.''</p>
        <p>In October 2000, the company announced that it would ''restructure'' itself into three independent companies with four separate stocks. The wireless and cable units would be spun off, while the remaining telecommunications company would issue a new stock to track its flagging consumer operations. That announcement opened the way for the months of negotiations that led to last week's deal with Comcast.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Armstrong arrived at AT&amp;T, the company had a market value of about $75 billion. Now, AT&amp;T plus the portion of the independent AT&amp;T Wireless that was given to AT&amp;T's shareholders is roughly worth a combined $95 billion. Over the same period the combined value of WorldCom and MCI, which WorldCom acquired, has declined from about $59 billion to about $45 billion.</p>
        <p>The rough financial calculations suggest that the cable strategy was a wash or a modest loser for the company's shareholders, who are nonetheless better off than those of AT&amp;T's rivals, Sprint and WorldCom. Last week, AT&amp;T said that the Comcast deal valued AT&amp;T's cable subscribers at $4,500 each. AT&amp;T said it paid $4,100 for each of those customers, but the company no doubt spent at least a few hundred dollars per subscriber when it upgraded its cable systems to deliver more advanced services.</p>
        <p>By early 2003, the investors who held one AT&amp;T stock when Mr. Armstrong arrived will own four: shares in AT&amp;T Wireless, shares in AT&amp;T Comcast (if the deal is approved), a core AT&amp;T stock for a company focused on business-services, and a dividend-paying tracking stock for the consumer businesses. Mr. Armstrong's hope is that the combined value of those four equities will be higher than one AT&amp;T stock would have had on its own.</p>
        <p>And it could have been worse, far worse.</p>
        <p>''AT&amp;T, this icon, would have disappeared if we remained just what we were,'' Mr. Armstrong said in a reflective interview Thursday. ''To now know that AT&amp;T will still be around for the next century and to be able to complete that with satisfaction and value is something I'm proud of. I hope it will be judged fairly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
