<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Weekend; The Historic Challenge to Segregation</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POITIER, SIDNEY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SEPARATE BUT EQUAL (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DC1738F936A35757C0A967958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Weekend; The Historic Challenge to Segregation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tracing events that led to the United States Supreme Court's school-desegregation decision in 1954, "Separate but Equal" is the kind of film that today is likely to be done only for television. The heart of the story is about fundamental national issues that have to be placed in historical, legal and moral contexts. Crucial information must be digested. No action-adventure pyrotechnics here. These are serious matters and, quite admirably, "Separate but Equal" keeps them that way in its deliberately slow, almost stately fashion. The four-hour movie, a "G.M. Mark of Excellence" presentation, will be broadast in two segments, Sunday and Monday, on ABC at 9 o'clock.</p>
        <p>Of course, the writer and director George Stevens Jr. knows quite well that an audience has to be wooed and won. Network television is not interested in purely altruistic projects, no matter how worthy. So Mr. Stevens had the good sense to persuade Sidney Poitier to return to television after 35 years and portray Thurgood Marshall, who was chief counsel to the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, which brought the school segregation challenge to the Supreme Court in the case known as "Brown v. Board of Education."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tracing events that led to the United States Supreme Court's school-desegregation decision in 1954, "Separate but Equal" is the kind of film that today is likely to be done only for television. The heart of the story is about fundamental national issues that have to be placed in historical, legal and moral contexts. Crucial information must be digested. No action-adventure pyrotechnics here. These are serious matters and, quite admirably, "Separate but Equal" keeps them that way in its deliberately slow, almost stately fashion. The four-hour movie, a "G.M. Mark of Excellence" presentation, will be broadast in two segments, Sunday and Monday, on ABC at 9 o'clock.</p>
        <p>Of course, the writer and director George Stevens Jr. knows quite well that an audience has to be wooed and won. Network television is not interested in purely altruistic projects, no matter how worthy. So Mr. Stevens had the good sense to persuade Sidney Poitier to return to television after 35 years and portray Thurgood Marshall, who was chief counsel to the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund, which brought the school segregation challenge to the Supreme Court in the case known as "Brown v. Board of Education."</p>
        <p>Mr. Poitier's performance is the film's linchpin. The actor bears no physical resemblance whatsoever to Mr. Marshall, but he powerfully captures the quiet passion of a determined advocate. His Marshall moves cautiously but relentlessly. He is suffused with compassion, whether it be for his colleagues and clients or for his devoted wife (Gloria Foster) who is struggling with cancer. This is an old-fashioned movie portrait of a hero, reminiscent of the days when Paul Muni would make Emile Zola larger than life. Mr. Poitier is simply splendid.</p>
        <p>But it's hardly a one-man show. The support is remarkable across the board. Burt Lancaster is the soul of courtly but tough dignity as John W. Davis, the lawyer for the other side, himself once a candidate for the Presidency. And Richard Kiley is truly superb as Earl Warren, the new Chief Justice, who, being a politician and not a jurist, is expected by many to be little more than the colorless manager of a team of all stars. But it is Warren who, after concluding that the case is a moral issue, sets out to make the court's decision for desegregation unanimous.</p>
        <p>"Separate but Equal" is a story that could only have come out of the United States. It begins in a rural South Carolina school with black children reciting the Pledge of Allegiance. Tired of seeing his students having to walk five or six miles to school while busloads of white children speed past them, the preacher who also serves as schoolteacher (Ed Hall) asks the local superintendant for a single bus and is told it would be too costly. The preacher decides to draw up a petition, and that attracts the attention of a lawyer in New York named Marshall. What will turn out to be a historic event begins in deceptively modest circumstances.</p>
        <p>There are setbacks, and there are legitimate differences of opinion. Some black leaders strenuously oppose the N.A.A.C.P.'s efforts, arguing that a Supreme Court defeat would set back the black cause for perhaps decades. But in the end, the law of the land recognized what a South Carolina judge had said earlier in a dissenting opinion: "Segregation can never produce equality. It is an evil that must be eradicated."</p>
        <p>"Separate but Equal" intelligently and movingly captures a turning point in the nation's history.  Also of Interest</p>
        <p>"The Sunset Gang" (Channel 13, tonight at 9). The first episode of this "American Playhouse" trilogy -- adapted by Ronald Ribman from stories by Warren Adler -- takes a fierce swipe at the concept of marital loyalty. The scene is the Florida retirement community of Sunset Village. Velvil (Harold Gould) and Genendel (Tresa Hughes) meet at the local Yiddish club and fall in love. The problem is they both have living spouses, remnants of more than 45 years of marriage. And what will the children say? No matter. The elderly lovers decide to, as they used to say in the 60's, do their own thing. Here is still further evidence that the times they really are a-changin'. Separate but Equal Written and directed by George Stevens Jr.; director of photography, Nic Knowland; costumes by Francine Jamison-Tanchuck; music by Carl Davis; production designer, Veronica Hadfield; a New Liberty Production in association with Republic Pictures Television; George Stevens Jr. and Stan Margulies, co-executive producers. Sunday and Monday at 9 P.M. on ABC. Thurgood Marshall . . . Sidney Poitier John W. Davis . . . Burt Lancaster Earl Warren . . . Richard Kiley Robert Carter . . . Cleavon Little Buster Marshall . . . Gloria Foster Gov. James F. Byrnes . . . John McMartin Josiah B. Tulley . . . Graham Beckel The Rev. J. A. DeLaine . . . Ed Hall Alice Stovall . . . Lynne Thigpen W. B. Springer . . . Macon McCalman</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
