<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Golden Days Of Lunch Boxes and Pez</title>
    <meta content="TRDZ0701" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barker Character, Comic and Cartoon Museum (Cheshire, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barker, Gloria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barker, Herb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED8143DF934A35751C1A961958260" item-length="311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Golden Days Of Lunch Boxes and Pez</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barker Character, Comic and Cartoon Museum in Cheshire, Conn, displays 20,000 items of character memorabilia from collection of Herb and Gloria Barker, who have been gathering merchandise based on characters from comic strips, cartoons, radio, television and advertising for 18 years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Little Orphan Annie decoder badge, Mickey Mouse toothpaste and a Lone Ranger ring are among the 20,000 novelties on display at the Barker Character, Comic and Cartoon Museum in Cheshire, Conn.</p>
        <p>Lunch boxes and mugs hang from the rafters; display cases are crammed with toys, games, dolls, books and other character memorabilia. The collection belongs to Herb and Gloria Barker, who have been gathering merchandise based on characters from comic strips, cartoons, radio, television and advertising for about 18 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Little Orphan Annie decoder badge, Mickey Mouse toothpaste and a Lone Ranger ring are among the 20,000 novelties on display at the Barker Character, Comic and Cartoon Museum in Cheshire, Conn.</p>
        <p>Lunch boxes and mugs hang from the rafters; display cases are crammed with toys, games, dolls, books and other character memorabilia. The collection belongs to Herb and Gloria Barker, who have been gathering merchandise based on characters from comic strips, cartoons, radio, television and advertising for about 18 years.</p>
        <p>The Barkers' eclectic collection went on display in September. Each item is labeled with its present market value, but nothing is for sale. Audio tapes offer history lessons about the development of cartoons, for example, or the popularity of Pez dispensers. While offering memories for adults who might see toys they owned as children, the museum is a source of information about popular culture over the past century.</p>
        <p>A renovated farmhouse on several landscaped acres houses the museum. The former stable, now a theater, offers cartoons from the 30's on a big screen throughout the day, and the chicken coop serves as a children's playhouse. Also on the grounds is the Barker Animation Art Gallery, open Monday to Saturday, where original animation art cels, drawings and prints are sold.</p>
        <p>The museum, at 1188 Highland Avenue (Route 10) in Cheshire, Conn., is open Tuesday to Saturday 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission is free. Guided tours start every half hour on Saturday, along with children's programs, which may include a trivia contest or a scavenger hunt, art lessons or singing with costumed characters. Information: (800) 995-2357 or (203) 272-2357.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
