<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Offers an Explanation of His Comment About Kerry</title>
    <meta content="11CHEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/11/politics/campaign/11cheney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1610468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Des Moines (Iowa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDD1230F932A2575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Offers an Explanation of His Comment About Kerry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cheney Offers Explanation of Comment About Kerry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, Sept. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Dick Cheney offers explanation of his Des Moines campaign forum statement suggesting that United States could 'get hit again' if voters elect Sen John Kerry; says next president must anticipate more attacks; asserts that Pres Bush will pursue more effective policy than Kerry; says Kerry's voting record does not reveal strategies needed to win war on terror; Kerry campaign is not satisfied with explanation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an interview published Friday, Vice President Dick Cheney said he wanted to ''clean up'' the impression he left at a campaign forum on Tuesday when he said that the United States could ''get hit again'' if voters made the wrong choice in November.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with The Cincinnati Enquirer on Thursday, an account of which the paper published on Friday, the vice president said, ''I did not say, If Kerry is elected, we will be hit by a terrorist attack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Dick Cheney said he wanted to "clean up" the impression he left when he said that the country could "get hit again" if voters made the wrong choice in the fall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an interview published Friday, Vice President Dick Cheney said he wanted to ''clean up'' the impression he left at a campaign forum on Tuesday when he said that the United States could ''get hit again'' if voters made the wrong choice in November.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with The Cincinnati Enquirer on Thursday, an account of which the paper published on Friday, the vice president said, ''I did not say, If Kerry is elected, we will be hit by a terrorist attack.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Whoever is elected president has to anticipate more attacks. My point was the question before us is: Will we have the most effective policy in place to deal with that threat? George Bush will pursue a more effective policy than John Kerry.''</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Cheney's first public explanation since he told an audience of about 350 people in Des Moines, ''It's absolutely essential that eight weeks from today, on Nov. 2, we make the right choice, because if we make the wrong choice, then the danger is that we'll get hit again and we'll be hit in a way that will be devastating from the point of view of the United States, and that we'll fall back into the pre-9/11 mindset, if you will, that in fact these terrorist attacks are just criminal acts, and that we're not really at war.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney has been focusing this week on forums, gatherings of a few hundred hand-picked supporters in swing states, partly because his aides believe the intimate setting helps soften the vice president.</p>
        <p>At a gathering on Friday outside Sheboygan, Wis., on the lawn of the Johnsonville sausage factory, Mr. Cheney denied, in response to a question, that the United States had gone to war in Iraq out of a desire to take control of that country's oil reserves.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to stay a day longer than necessary,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''If we were interested in oil, for instance, we'd have stayed in Saudi Arabia. We've pulled most of our forces out there.''</p>
        <p>The war on terror began in Afghanistan, he said, a poor country without oil reserves.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who'd suggest we'd be there for the oil, I think, doesn't understand the basic, fundamental decision the president had to make,'' the vice president said. That decision, he said, was to go on the offense both against terrorists and the countries that harbor and help him.</p>
        <p>And at a forum in Milwaukee on Friday afternoon, Mr. Cheney again compared the national security credentials of President Bush and Senator Kerry, though he stopped well short of declaring Mr. Kerry a threat to public safety.</p>
        <p>''We honor John Kerry for his military service,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''We are not in the business of challenging his patriotism. I do challenge his judgment.''</p>
        <p>He said that a close look at the senator's votes on national security issues over the years showed that he did not ''reflect the views and philosophies of the kind of man who would follow the kind of strategies we would need to win the war on terror.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney also reminded the audience about the terrorist attacks in Madrid, shortly before Spain's national elections and said, ''That is something we have to be concerned about as well here.''</p>
        <p>The Kerry campaign, which has sharply condemned Mr. Cheney's remarks in Des Moines, said it was not satisfied with his explanation.</p>
        <p>''We all saw Dick Cheney's remark,'' said Phil Singer, a campaign spokesman, ''and we all understood the disgraceful and dishonorable implications. Instead of more spin, it might be nice to actually get the truth from Dick Cheney or even an apology.''</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
