<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preserving the Past and Speeding Traffic West of Washington</title>
    <meta content="28FERR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Whites Ferry Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Whites Ferry Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Whites Ferry (Maryland)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Potomac River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Loudoun County (Va)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fairfax County (Va)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montgomery County (Md)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD9153AF93BA15750C0A961958260" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preserving the Past and Speeding Traffic West of Washington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WHITES FERRY, Md., March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White's Ferry, last on Potomac River, has carried travelers between Maryland and Virginia shores since 1826, and is used today by many commuters who are happy to avoid Beltway around Washington's crowded suburbs; photo; map; ferry's future is imperiled by Virginia's plan for new connecting road to spur even more development in Fairfax and Loudoun Counties; Maryland has taken opposite approach, protecting thousands of acres of farmland in Montgomery County (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wayne Greathouse came east from West Union, W. Va., eight years ago looking for work, and got no farther than the Jubal A. Early ferry here on the Potomac River, connecting this town of seven people on the Maryland side with the outskirts of Leesburg, Va., on the other.</p>
        <p>He hired on as a captain and has been at it ever since. ''A very boring job,'' Mr. Greathouse said today, closing the gates behind a half-dozen cars for the 5-minute, 1,000-yard ride.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wayne Greathouse came east from West Union, W. Va., eight years ago looking for work, and got no farther than the Jubal A. Early ferry here on the Potomac River, connecting this town of seven people on the Maryland side with the outskirts of Leesburg, Va., on the other.</p>
        <p>He hired on as a captain and has been at it ever since. ''A very boring job,'' Mr. Greathouse said today, closing the gates behind a half-dozen cars for the 5-minute, 1,000-yard ride.</p>
        <p>Boring it may be for Mr. Great house and the two other captains of the last Potomac ferry, which operates 18 hours a day, every day, except in floods, continuing a service that began in 1826.</p>
        <p>But as the regions around the terminal points continue to gain population, the ferry is playing an increasingly large role in the lives of people commuting between Montgomery County, the most populous in Maryland, and the high-tech corridors around Dulles Airport in the Virginia counties of Fairfax and Loudoun.</p>
        <p>Estimates released last week by the United States Census Bureau show that while the population of Montgomery County increased by 7.9 percent, to 816,999, from April 1990 to July 1996, Loudoun County's population jumped 43.2 percent, to 123,333, making it the fastest-growing county in the United States outside the Deep South and the West.</p>
        <p>With increasing frequency, motorists are paying the $5 ferry fee to slice as much as 30 minutes off a drive that would otherwise include the next nearest Potomac crossings, bridges 25 miles to the southeast on the Washington Beltway or about 23 miles to the northwest at Point of Rocks, Md., and Taylorstown, Va.</p>
        <p>Malcolm Brown, whose family has owned the ferry since just after World War II, said the craft that operated through 1988 could accommodate only 8 cars. The ferry now in use can carry 24. ''We're up to several hundred cars crossing twice a day during rush hours,'' Mr. Brown said, sitting in his cluttered office here, a room above his market, which sells food, beer, bait and tackle.</p>
        <p>With traffic especially thick throughout Northern Virginia, the Jubal A. Early is a hit with motorists. ''If I had my choice, I'd much rather use the ferry,'' said Steven Futrowsky, a fraud investigator for a bank in Gaithersburg, Md., who was on his way to Leesburg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Futrowsky said he used the ferry several times a year, and not just to save time.</p>
        <p>''It's much more pleasant than roads where you have bumper-to-bumper traffic,'' he said. ''It's also like stepping back in time, rather than being in the rat race.''</p>
        <p>Julio Pereira, a Montgomery County cab driver returning from Leesburg, said he was a first-time customer and loved the experience.  ''This is beautiful,'' Mr. Pereira said, waving his arms toward the Potomac. ''It reminds me of my country, Paraguay. We have many ferries there, but they are much bigger.''</p>
        <p>The Jubal A. Early was named for a Confederate general who crossed the Potomac just downstream from here on his way to a raid in the Washington area in 1864. In some ways, the scenery at both landings seems hardly changed from then, when the ferry was used primarily to move produce wagons, cattle and soldiers.</p>
        <p>Nor does much of the immediate area on the Maryland side appear so different. With Maryland tightly controlling business and residential development, Montgomery County leads the United States among all counties in the number of acres preserved for farmland, 46,813.</p>
        <p>The Virginia side reflects a different strategy. Growth of all kinds -- commercial, retail and residential -- is everywhere. Although the narrow road leading from the ferry landing meanders through rustic settings for a mile or two, just beyond is enormous development, fueled by a steady exodus of people from Washington and its close-in suburbs.</p>
        <p>Linda Beecher of Leesburg, who was taking the ferry to a doctor's appointment in Rockville, Md., said she and her husband moved to Loudoun County four years ago to escape the growing sprawl of neighboring Fairfax County. Now, they are contemplating moving farther west.</p>
        <p>''We moved out to Leesburg because Fairfax was so over-developed,'' Mrs. Beecher said, ''and you used to see bumper stickers that said, 'Don't Fairfax Loudoun.' But they have Fairfaxed Loudoun, and we're looking to move again.''</p>
        <p>To ease traffic in Northern Virginia, state transportation officials have proposed building a western spur off Interstate 95 south of Washington near Quantico that would run through Loudoun, cross the Potomac over a bridge that would be constructed several miles from Whites Ferry and continue on through Montgomery County to Interstate 270.</p>
        <p>The chief benefit for Virginia would be creating easy access for Maryland residents to major areas of shopping and jobs in Northern Virginia. But Maryland officials, fiercely intent on protecting the Montgomery County farmlands, oppose such a highway.</p>
        <p>So does Mr. Brown, whose ferry might easily be put out of business by a closer bridge.</p>
        <p>''Maryland has spent 30 years setting up the most advanced program in the country to protect farmland,'' Mr. Brown said. ''If we got that highway in here, all this open space I grew up with would be gone overnight. I would be more concerned about that than my ferry closing.''</p>
        <p>Whites Ferry Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
