<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Biggest Hospital Operator Attracts Federal Inquiries</title>
    <meta content="28CARE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HEALTH CARE'S GIANT: Powerhouse Under Scrutiny -- A special report." name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH CARE'S GIANT: Powerhouse Under Scrutiny -- A special report."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia/hca Healthcare Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia Spring View Medical Center (Kentucky)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cedars Medical Center (Miami, Fla)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health Care Financing Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vladeck, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottlieb, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichenwald, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbanel, Josh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6D9133AF93BA15750C0A961958260" item-length="3665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Biggest Hospital Operator Attracts Federal Inquiries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Gottlieb, Kurt Eichenwald and Josh Barbanel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbanel, Josh; Eichenwald, Kurt; Gottlieb, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, Health Care's Giant, on Government investigations of business practices at nation's largest health care company, Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation, which runs about 350 hospitals and treats 125,000 people a day; Federal agents have raided hospitals and doctors' offices in El Paso, carting off truckloads of billing records; Health Care Financing Administration chief Bruce Vladeck reports review of 'upcoding,' in which hospitals inflate seriousness of illnesses to get higher Medicare payments; civil and criminal investigators also probe referrals by Columbia doctors to medical services in which they have interests; yearlong investigation by The New York Times finds Columbia hospitals submit more and higher bills than comparable institutions, with extra Medicare payments of nearly $50 million in Texas alone in 1995; company, less than ten years old, controls seven percent of nation's hospitals, mostly in Sunbelt; Columbia is Medicare's single largest biller, and Medicare money makes up 36 percent of company revenue; analyses of high billings by Columbia Spring View Medical Center in Kentucky and Cedars Medical Center in Miami detailed; graph; practice of encouraging doctors to invest in hospitals where they practice also probed (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Law enforcement officials and several Government agencies are investigating an array of business practices at the nation's largest health care company, the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation, which runs about 350 hospitals and treats 125,000 people a day.</p>
        <p>The Government's scrutiny of Columbia came to light last week in a Federal criminal investigation of Columbia operations in El Paso. In a raid of Columbia hospitals and doctors' offices, agents with search warrants carted off truckloads of billing and medical records. The inquiry appears, at least in part, to involve the company's dealings with Medicare, the Federal health insurance program for the elderly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Law enforcement officials and several Government agencies are investigating an array of business practices at the nation's largest health care company, the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation, which runs about 350 hospitals and treats 125,000 people a day.</p>
        <p>The Government's scrutiny of Columbia came to light last week in a Federal criminal investigation of Columbia operations in El Paso. In a raid of Columbia hospitals and doctors' offices, agents with search warrants carted off truckloads of billing and medical records. The inquiry appears, at least in part, to involve the company's dealings with Medicare, the Federal health insurance program for the elderly.</p>
        <p>But a yearlong examination of Columbia by The New York Times has found that the company faces problems on several fronts. The Federal agency that runs Medicare is trying to determine if certain Columbia hospitals engaged in a practice known as upcoding, in which hospitals receive larger payments from Medicare by inflating the seriousness of illnesses they treat.</p>
        <p>''A specific review is going on of upcoding at Columbia hospitals,'' said Bruce Vladeck, the head of the agency, the Health Care Financing Administration.</p>
        <p>In addition, Federal civil and criminal investigators are examining whether it is illegal for Columbia doctors with a financial interest in outside medical services associated with the company's hospitals -- like home care and rehabilitation -- to send patients to them.</p>
        <p>The Times's examination of Columbia, including a computer analysis of more than 30 million billing records, casts some light on the Government's concerns. Among the findings were these:</p>
        <p>*Many Columbia hospitals bill Medicare for high-paying respiratory treatments far more often than do competing hospitals serving similar populations. Federal authorities called such findings an indication of possible overbilling of the program.</p>
        <p>*In Texas, where Columbia has its greatest number of hospitals, Medicare paid unusually high amounts for Columbia patients who received costly services like home care. Mainly because of Columbia's use of these services, Medicare pays nearly 10 percent more for treatment that begins at a Columbia hospital than at other Texas hospitals. That meant extra Federal payouts of nearly $50 million in 1995, the last year for which data are available, the analysis shows.</p>
        <p>*In a Federal-state investigation last year in Florida, law-enforcement agents interviewed four hospital officials who said they or their colleagues had been offered enticements or approached about jobs while Columbia was trying to buy their institutions. The inquiry was closed without prosecution, but a memo summarizing the inquiry has been referred for review to a dozen other law enforcement agencies.</p>
        <p>Columbia executives said that the company's policies and practices adhered to the law, and that its use of medical services outside the hospital were in the best medical interests of its patients.</p>
        <p>As for billing practices, the executives attributed any disparities between the company and its competitors to Columbia's more efficient operation. Rather than billing too much, the executives said, its competitors are billing too little.</p>
        <p>''We believe that Columbia is more efficient in accurately billing the Medicare program than are our competitors,'' said David Manning, a Columbia vice president. He said that the company maintained an internal compliance program that was charged with making sure Medicare was billed appropriately.</p>
        <p>In response to the Federal-state inquiry in Florida, a company spokeswoman, Lindy B. Richardson, said Columbia could not comment completely because it had not seen the summary memorandum, which describes the testimony obtained by the Government. But she added that based on The Times's description the testimony appeared to be uncorroborated by documents, ''thus undermining the credibility of the allegations.''</p>
        <p>The investigations of Columbia's Medicare billing practices come as the Clinton Administration has introduced legislative proposals to crack down on fraud and abuse in the program, which many in Washington fear could go broke in less than five years.</p>
        <p>Columbia, which is based in Nashville, has been a leader in the impressive revival of the nation's for-profit hospital business. Not yet 10 years old, Columbia controls about 7 percent of the nation's hospitals -- as well as hundreds of related medical operations -- in 38 states, mostly in the Sun Belt. With 285,000 employees, it is the nation's ninth-largest employer, bigger than General Electric, bigger than McDonald's.</p>
        <p>Because of its size, Columbia is Medicare's single largest biller. Reimbursements from the program make up 36 percent of the company's revenue, by far its largest source.</p>
        <p>As Columbia has tried to acquire hospitals across the country, it has often found itself at loggerheads with some state regulators, not-for-profit hospitals and community groups. At the same time, though, it has helped bring a bottom-line sense of efficiency to the hospital industry. Columbia, which has $20 billion in annual revenue, has also become a top-performing health care stock.</p>
        <p>But since the El Paso raid last week, Columbia's stock price has suffered, falling almost 7 percent in the first two days after the investigation was disclosed. Yesterday, the shares closed at $37.50, down 12.5 cents, in trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>A Federal law enforcement official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said that investigations of Columbia were going on in cities besides El Paso. From Florida to Texas to Illinois to Nevada, agents with the Federal Bureau of Investigation have been interviewing witnesses about the company's practices. Peter Young, a consultant in Florida who has advised a number of Columbia's not-for-profit competitors, said that Federal agents had gotten in touch with him several times about Columbia's dealings with Medicare and other Federal programs.</p>
        <p>The Billing  A Propensity For Higher Fees</p>
        <p>The Federal review of Columbia's billing practices began at a small Kentucky hospital, Columbia Spring View Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Responding to queries from The Times about the hospital last year, the Medicare agency reviewed Spring View's records. The agency's review, which focused on billings for four related respiratory illnesses, found that the hospital charged Medicare for the most expensive one far more often than did nearby competitors. And it charged for the least expensive ones far less often.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said the results raised concerns that Spring View might be inflating its Medicare payments through upcoding.</p>
        <p>Medicare pays a fixed rate for treatment of each of roughly 470 coded illnesses. Rates vary sharply -- the more severe the illness, the more Medicare pays. In upcoding, a hospital bills for a more severe illness than the one treated -- and is thus paid more.</p>
        <p>At Spring View, the review found its bills were ''skewed'' toward the highest-paying cases, Mr. Vladeck said: ''The a priori numbers are definitely a source of concern.''</p>
        <p>In 1995, Spring View billed for treating 191 cases of complex respiratory infection and only 10 cases of the lower-paying pneumonia with complications. By contrast, four nearby hospitals billed more than twice as many cases of pneumonia with complications as of the complex infection -- 263 to 117. At Spring View, Medicare pays roughly $5,700 for treatment of a complex respiratory infection, or about $1,700 more than a case of pneumonia with complications.</p>
        <p>In the wake of those findings, Mr. Vladeck said, the agency opened its wider examination of Columbia hospitals. Mr. Vladeck made his comments over several months, as The Times's investigation evolved.</p>
        <p>To examine Columbia's billing on a larger scale, The Times analyzed records from Florida and Texas -- where Columbia's hospitals are most concentrated -- and found the same pattern as at Spring View.</p>
        <p>The Times's analysis found that in Texas in 1995, the latest year for which data are available, five Columbia general-care hospitals ranked tops for the proportion of cases billed at the highest-paying of the four respiratory codes. In Florida, the top 6 billers, and 7 of the top 10, were Columbia hospitals.</p>
        <p>At Columbia's Cedars Medical Center in Miami, 93 percent of the respiratory cases in the four codes were in the highest-paying category, ranking it fourth in the state. Across the street at the county hospital, Jackson Memorial, only 28 percent of the billings were for that code.</p>
        <p>Cedars billed for 355 cases of complex respiratory infection -- the best-paying diagnosis -- and only 28 cases of the three lower-paying diagnoses. Among the cases studied, it did not bill a single case of the lowest-paying illness, simple pneumonia. At Cedars, Medicare pays roughly $6,800 for a case of complex respiratory infection, and only $3,150 for simple pneumonia.</p>
        <p>Particularly striking was how the billing at Cedars changed after Columbia took over. In 1992, when it last operated independently, 31 percent of the respiratory cases were billed at the highest rate. A year later, 76 percent were, and in 1995, 9 of 10 cases came under the top category.</p>
        <p>When The Times examined more than 100 pairs of Medicare codes that define an illness as simple or complex, it found that, in an aggregate 9 cases out of 10, Columbia hospitals in Florida were more likely than others to choose the more complex -- and more highly paid -- code. The magnitude of the differences varied but over all were found to be statistically significant.</p>
        <p>At Columbia, employees responsible for billing Medicare recalled being presented with lists of ''focus codes'' on which Columbia wanted them to concentrate, each with alternatives that were far more remunerative. In particular, they mentioned several codes later examined by The Times.</p>
        <p>Hospitals across the country try to code as aggressively as possible, to receive the highest reimbursement a patient's symptoms will allow. Before Columbia even came into existence, hospitals were being caught going beyond simply aggressive billing. A series of Federal studies on upcoding, some of which focused on the respiratory codes, concluded that upcoding had cost Medicare hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>If upcoding is found, the agency seeks restitution. If a pattern of upcoding is found, the case can be referred for possible prosecution for fraud. Few cases have been prosecuted but Medicare overbilling related to upcoding and other activities has been identified at numerous hospitals and among large numbers of doctors.</p>
        <p>Mark Krushat, who participated in those studies for the Inspector General office that monitors Medicare, called the findings by The Times an initial indicator of a potential problem. But he said that only an analysis of patient charts could confirm violations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning of Columbia said that the company's billing is ''in complete adherence to all applicable Federal laws.''</p>
        <p>The Investing  Physicians Have Stake In Costly Services</p>
        <p>Since its start, Columbia has invited doctors to invest in the hospitals where they practice. At the same time, it built highly profitable networks of medical services affiliated with the hospitals, offering home care, rehabilitation and the like.</p>
        <p>Now, Government investigators are examining whether those two initiatives might, in combination, violate a law prohibiting doctors from referring patients to facilities in which they invest.</p>
        <p>The 1992 law, written by Representative Pete Stark, Democrat of California, was intended to curb doctors who might tailor treatments to their personal investments, rather than patient need. Physicians were barred from referring patients to medical businesses like home care agencies if they owned a stake in them.</p>
        <p>But Congress allowed hospital investments, in part because doctors were often the only ones willing to open rural hospitals.</p>
        <p>Columbia relied on the exemption to sell hundreds of doctors stakes in health networks anchored by its hospitals. But those networks also own such services as home care agencies and skilled nursing facilities built around the hospitals.</p>
        <p>Should those services really be considered part of the hospital exemption? Medicare is examining whether Columbia's doctor investors may be violating the law by indirectly profiting from referrals to businesses they cannot otherwise own.</p>
        <p>''To the extent that their physicians have ownership relationships with any of these long-term-care services, I think that raises real legal questions about whether that's allowable behavior under the law,'' Mr. Vladeck said. ''If we have physicians who are referring patients to home-care agencies or skilled nursing facilities in which they have an ownership, that may very well be against the law.''</p>
        <p>The agency is analyzing whether to issue rules specifically barring physician-investors from referring patients to any outpatient service facilities included in their investment, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>Compounding Medicare's concern is the runaway cost of the services, the fastest-growing piece of the program's budget.</p>
        <p>Last year, a Congressional advisory panel noted that such services consumed almost a quarter of all Medicare payments in 1995, compared with just 9 percent in 1990.</p>
        <p>While it pays a pre-set amount for hospital care no matter how much that treatment actually costs, Medicare uses a far more lucrative method to pay for treatment outside the hospital: it pays an amount based on what the provider says its costs were.</p>
        <p>The Government hoped that payment structure would limit expensive hospitalization. And hospitalization rates have dropped.</p>
        <p>But the structure also led to huge, unanticipated expenses, particularly for services provided after hospitalization. The advisory panel, the Prospective Payment Assessment Commission, concluded that the system ''encourages the development of new facilities and rewards those that have high cost.''</p>
        <p>An analysis by The Times of Columbia's business in Texas shows that care provided after hospitalization cost Medicare far more than such services provided by rivals. That was mainly because Columbia patients use the services more often, and at higher cost.</p>
        <p>For example, Medicare's cost from the time of hospitalization until 30 days after the patient was discharged averaged $9,011 at non-Columbia hospitals in Texas. But at Columbia hospitals, that same course of care cost on average 9.5 percent more, or a difference of $855. Alone, the treatment after hospitalization cost Medicare on average nearly 23 percent more, or $667, at Columbia. All figures were adjusted for differences in severity and conditions of illnesses.</p>
        <p>As a result, the course of care for patients treated at Columbia hospitals in 1995 cost Medicare at least $48 million more than if the care had been billed at the state average.</p>
        <p>Columbia patients were sent to skilled-nursing units 27 percent more often than other patients with similar illnesses, the analysis found, and they cost Medicare 44 percent more for such care, or an extra $306 each. Similar outcomes were found for rehabilitation. Columbia used home care at the same rate as its rivals, but home care at Columbia cost more.</p>
        <p>In El Paso, as in other Texas cities, scores of doctors are investors in Columbia medical networks. In that city, the average cost in 1995 for the course of care -- $11,072 -- exceeds the average for the city's non-Columbia hospitals by more than 11 percent. The cost for treatment outside the hospital was 23 percent higher.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning, the Columbia vice president, said that the company's development of these services demonstrated its commitment to providing a quality continuum of care. One factor in their costs to Medicare, he said, was the program's policy of paying start-up costs for these units in the first few years of their operation.</p>
        <p>''It is not in any patient's interest to be served in an acute-care setting when less-intensive care is more appropriate,'' he said, adding that Medicare encouraged ''hospitals and physicians to deliver care in the most appropriate setting.''</p>
        <p>A Columbia consultant also noted that large Columbia hospitals with teaching programs -- a modest part of the company's Texas presence -- were somewhat less expensive than other similar hospitals.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Vladeck questioned the value of much of the care provided by these ancillary services throughout the industry.</p>
        <p>''I don't have confidence that the dollars we are spending are buying increased benefits for beneficiaries,'' he said. ''They're buying services, but the extent people are benefiting is really questionable.''</p>
        <p>The Acquiring  Accusations of Offers Made to Executives</p>
        <p>Investigators from some agencies now examining Columbia practices in El Paso and elsewhere earlier spent more than a year delving into another key piece of Columbia's business: How it acquires hospitals.</p>
        <p>Agents from the F.B.I., the Internal Revenue Service and the State of Florida worked with Federal prosecutors examining Columbia's acquisition efforts there.</p>
        <p>They found executives who said that as they talked with the company about the sale of hospitals they managed Columbia offered them perquisites and promises of jobs. The agents concluded that such offers might have violated laws against bribes to officials of institutions receiving Federal money.</p>
        <p>''All of these inducements were made by, or on behalf of, Columbia to persons in position of responsibility at hospitals which received millions of dollars in Federal funds and were arguably made for the purpose of affecting the decisions of those persons,'' the agents wrote in a Feb. 26, 1996, memorandum summarizing the inquiry.</p>
        <p>The agents recommended against prosecution, in part because of the small value of the perks offered and also because of concerns about the quality of evidence, which involved conversations difficult to corroborate. But they recommended referring the evidence to 12 state and Federal law enforcement and regulatory agencies.</p>
        <p>The memo summarizing that evidence was distributed to those agencies late last year. A copy was obtained by The Times.</p>
        <p>In it, the agents describe the story of John Geanes, the administrator of South Miami Hospital in Miami. Columbia was one of the hospital's several suitors, and Mr. Geanes played an important role in negotiations.</p>
        <p>The memo says that Mr. Geanes reported that he was first approached by a consultant to South Miami who told him ''that large sums of money were available to people who delivered a hospital to Columbia.''</p>
        <p>Soon, Dan Moen, president of Columbia's Florida division, approached Mr. Geanes. According to the memorandum, Mr. Moen ''offered to 'protect' Geanes by creating a position for him at Columbia and offered him investment opportunities with Columbia which would make him 'wealthy.' ''</p>
        <p>Shortly after, Mr. Geanes told investigators, he ran into Richard L. Scott, Columbia's chief executive, in a restaurant parking lot. In that encounter, the memo says, Mr. Scott ''inquired of Geanes regarding Geanes' desire to work in North Carolina.''</p>
        <p>Within days, Mr. Geanes received a call from another Columbia executive offering him a job in that state, the memo says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Geanes immediately informed hospital lawyers of each approach. South Miami was sold to another hospital. Once the hospital ''decided not to sell out to Columbia, the offers to Geanes ceased,'' the memo says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Geanes, who is no longer with the hospital, said he had made his statements under subpoena before a grand jury and refused to comment further.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moen did not return phone calls. Ms. Richardson, the Columbia spokeswoman, declined to comment fully until she researched the events, but she said ''the integrity of this company is impeccable.''</p>
        <p>Three other hospital officials told law enforcement agents that they or their colleagues had been offered personal benefits or approached about jobs as the company was negotiating to buy their hospitals.</p>
        <p>For example, Joe Kiefer, the chief executive of a hospital in Tarpon Springs, Fla., told investigators that, while negotiating a sale to Columbia, the company offered him a trip to the Super Bowl -- including tickets, travel and hotel accommodations. Mr. Kiefer declined; the negotiations were unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>During the investigation, the agents made oral and written requests for interviews with senior Columbia executives, including Mr. Scott and Mr. Moen. The case was closed months later, the memo says, without any response from the executives.</p>
        <p>How the Analysis of Medicare Costs Was Done</p>
        <p>The study of Medicare costs is based on an analysis of more than 30 million records of Medicare patients who were admitted to hospitals in Texas and Florida in 1995. The New York Times matched records of these patients with bills for hospital readmissions, admissions to rehabilitation and skilled nursing units, outpatient services and doctor bills within 30 days of discharge.</p>
        <p>To account for differences among patients, hospital stays were grouped into 1,500 categories that took into account the type and severity of patient conditions. Costs figures and referral rates were then calculated and adjusted to account for differences in conditions.</p>
        <p>The possibility that differences found in costs or referral rates between Columbia/ HCA hospitals and the typical Texas hospital were due to chance alone is less than 1 in 10,000. Differences remained after taking into account statewide variations in hospital size and wage rates.</p>
        <p>The study included only patients in conventional Medicare programs for the elderly who were admitted to an acute care hospital. It excluded patients admitted for drug or psychiatric treatment, patients transferred to hospitals from nursing homes and other institutions, patients living out of state and patients discharged in the last 30 days of 1995.</p>
        <p>The study did not calculate precisely how much of the post-hospital care was paid to a Columbia/HCA affiliate across Texas. But it examined such payments for referrals to rehabilitation units in two metropolitan areas, Corpus Christi and El Paso, and found that a large proportion went to Columbia facilities.</p>
        <p>To examine differences in medical coding practices for simple and complex respiratory infection and pneumonia, The Times compared groups of related Medicare payment codes using 1995 Medicare records for Florida and Texas.</p>
        <p>JOSH BARBANEL</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE'S GIANT: Powerhouse Under Scrutiny -- A special report.  This article was written and reported by Martin Gottlieb and Kurt Eichenwald. The computer analysis was by Josh Barbanel, who also contributed additional reporting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This article was written and reported by Martin Gottlieb and Kurt Eichenwald. The computer analysis was by Josh Barbanel, who also contributed additional reporting.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
