<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gifts to Modern, For All to Share</title>
    <meta content="12INSI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitney Museum of American Art</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Walters Art Gallery (Baltimore, Md)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehrenkranz, Joel S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Warhol, Andy (1928?-87)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maurer, Gilbert C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Kooning, Willem (1904-97)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johns, Jasper</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenquist, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guston, Philip (1913-80)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6D9113AF931A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gifts to Modern, For All to Share</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; architect Philip Johnson, who has long been a donor of art works to Museum of Modern Art, gives museum nine more paintings: two by Willem de Kooning, two by Jasper Johns, two by Andy Warhol, two by James Rosenquist and one by Philip Guston; photo; Joel S Ehrenkranz is named president of Whitney Museum of American Art, replacing Gilbert C Maurer; on June 15 second and fourth floors of 1974 building that is part of Walters Art Gallery in Baltimore will be closed for renovations; by Aug 15, entire building will be shut for three-year $18.5 million renovation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of his 91 years, Philip Johnson has been an important figure at the Museum of Modern Art. He has been a member of its curatorial staff, the institution's official architect, and a trustee since 1957. He has also been a consistently generous donor, giving the museum seminal paintings, drawings and sculpture by modern masters like Andy Warhol, Jasper Johns, Franz Kline and Mark Rothko. Mr. Johnson has also contributed mightily to the Modern's design collection, adding furniture and objects by architects like Ludwig Mies van der Rohe and Marcel Breuer.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Johnson gave the museum nine paintings: two by Willem de Kooning, two by Jasper Johns, two by Warhol, two by James Rosenquist and one by Philip Guston. All may be familiar to those who have visited Mr. Johnson's compound in New Caanan, Conn. Some have also been loaned to major shows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most of his 91 years, Philip Johnson has been an important figure at the Museum of Modern Art. He has been a member of its curatorial staff, the institution's official architect, and a trustee since 1957. He has also been a consistently generous donor, giving the museum seminal paintings, drawings and sculpture by modern masters like Andy Warhol, Jasper Johns, Franz Kline and Mark Rothko. Mr. Johnson has also contributed mightily to the Modern's design collection, adding furniture and objects by architects like Ludwig Mies van der Rohe and Marcel Breuer.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Johnson gave the museum nine paintings: two by Willem de Kooning, two by Jasper Johns, two by Warhol, two by James Rosenquist and one by Philip Guston. All may be familiar to those who have visited Mr. Johnson's compound in New Caanan, Conn. Some have also been loaned to major shows.</p>
        <p>''I decided it's not fair to the artists to have their work stuck in the country when they could be in a museum for everyone to see,'' Mr. Johnson said in a telephone interview this week. ''I wanted to give things that fitted the Modern's collection best.''</p>
        <p>Glenn D. Lowry, the museum's director, said the gift raised the Modern's collection of contemporary art five notches, in part because such works rarely come on the market, and when they do, they're too expensive for any museum to buy.</p>
        <p>''These are works nobody else could get,'' Mr. Lowry said.</p>
        <p>One of the de Koonings, which are both untitled, is from 1982. The other, from 1977, is the first of his works from the 70's to enter the Modern's permanent collection. De Koonings from that decade are considered among the most desirable to own. The painting, an abstract seascape with heavily impastoed surfaces, was included in his retrospective at the National Gallery of Art in Washington and the Metropolitan Museum of Art four years ago.</p>
        <p>One of the Johns works in the gift is ''Summer'' (1985), the first of the artist's ''Four Seasons'' paintings to enter the Modern's collection. It was seen in the Modern's Johns retrospective in 1996.</p>
        <p>''Summer'' is a complex work, with the outline of a man (the artist's own figure) standing against a stone wall on the left and many of Mr. Johns' signature images on the right. Hanging from a ladder beneath a field of stars are quotations from his work: the cross-hatching, the double flag and the outstretched arm within a half-circle. A sea horse represents St. Martin, where the artist has a studio.</p>
        <p>One Warhol is a self-portrait painted in 1966, the other his iconic ''S &amp; H Green Stamps,'' a 1962 silk-screen of row after row of the stamps. It is a great complement to his ''Campbell's Soup Cans.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's gifts, which go up today on the the walls of the museum's third-floor galleries of contemporary painting and sculpture, will be on view for about six weeks.</p>
        <p>Whitney Excitement</p>
        <p>There's been a changing of the guard at the Whitney Museum of American Art.</p>
        <p>At the museum's board meeting last week, Joel S. Ehrenkranz was named the Whitney's president, replacing Gilbert C. Maurer, who is stepping down after four years. Mr. Ehrenkranz, a lawyer who has been on the board since 1975, has been its treasurer for the last five years, and before that was its vice president.</p>
        <p>He recently assumed another critical role at the museum. He is chairman of a search committee looking for a director to replace David A. Ross, who has become director of the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. Willard Holmes is the Whitney's acting director.</p>
        <p>Extending the museum's educational activities is high on his agenda, Mr. Ehrenkranz said, adding that he hoped to show more of the permanent collection now that fifth-floor permanent galleries have opened.</p>
        <p>''But more than anything, I want to encourage scholarship,'' he said. ''It would give us all great pride if we could be a high-quality scholarly institution.''</p>
        <p>Baltimore Renovation</p>
        <p>On Monday, the second and fourth floors of the 1974 building that is part of the Walters Art Gallery in Baltimore will be closed for renovations. By Aug. 15, the entire building will be shut for a three-year $18.5 million renovation.</p>
        <p>The face lift, by Kallmann McKinnell &amp; Wood Architects, of Boston, will feature a glass atrium rising four stories, with a spiral staircase suspended in mid-air.</p>
        <p>''The initial reason for the renovation is to upgrade the climate-control system, which is grossly outdated,'' said Gary Vikan, director of the Walters. ''It will also drastically transform the visual cacophony of this neo-brutalist building.''</p>
        <p>He added that the museum had been raising money for both the renovation and a larger endowment.</p>
        <p>After the renovation, the 1974 building will still hold the gallery's Egyptian, Greek and Roman, Medieval and Islamic art, as well as its 19th-century collections, its manuscript and rare book departments and temporary exhibition galleries. But each of these will be reinstalled and enlarged.</p>
        <p>The Walters's 1904 building, next to the newer one, will remain open during the renovation, as will its Hackerman House Museum of Asian Art. Highlights from the permanent collection will be shown in the 1904 building, along with special shows, beginning with ''The Invisible Made Visible: Angels from the Vatican,'' set to open on Nov. 8.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vikan said the museum would soon begin originating more of its own exhibitions.</p>
        <p>''We want to be more in the public eye,'' he said. ''We have not reached our potential.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
