<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Stage and Off</title>
    <meta content="12BROA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival '98</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puppets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Theater (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Livent Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfe, George C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Idle, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seuss (Dr) (Theodor Seuss Geisel)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcburney, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krieger, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vitucci, Susan J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On the Town (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seussical (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Street of Crocodiles (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Love's Fowl (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Festivals/Lincoln Center Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Festivals/Next Wave Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/George C Wolfe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5D9113AF931A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Stage and Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rick Lyman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; Public Theater's revival of On the Town, which was performed in Delacorte Theater in Central Park last summer but had difficulties transferring to Broadway when two choreographers left show, is now set to begin previews on Oct 16 at Gershwin Theater; George C Wolfe will direct; Eric Idle, formerly of Monte Python, will write book for new musical, Seussical, being put together by Livent, based on works of Dr Seuss; Simon McBurney, whose Theatre de Complicite brought its critically praised production of Ionesco's The Chairs to Broadway, is coming back to New York next month for Lincoln Center Festival '98; will reprise Street of Crocodiles, one of troupe's most highly praised productions; photo; Henry Krieger, composer of such big Broadway shows as Dreamgirls and Side Show, has written music for Love's Fowl, performance piece with puppets by Susan J Vitucci, being presented at New York Theater Workshop in East Village (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Final Curtains, New Beginnings</p>
        <p>The circle of life: Struggling shows drop away (''Honour,'' ''The Diary of Anne Frank,'' ''1776,'' ''The Life,'' ''The Sunshine Boys,'' ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo'') as new ones rise to take their place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Final Curtains, New Beginnings</p>
        <p>The circle of life: Struggling shows drop away (''Honour,'' ''The Diary of Anne Frank,'' ''1776,'' ''The Life,'' ''The Sunshine Boys,'' ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo'') as new ones rise to take their place.</p>
        <p>The Public Theater's revival of ''On the Town,'' which was performed in the Delacorte Theater in Central Park last summer but had difficulties transferring to Broadway when two choreographers left the show, is now set to begin previews on Oct. 16 at the Gershwin Theater.</p>
        <p>George C. Wolfe will direct the revival, as he did in the park, and his new choreographer will be Keith Young, a former principal dancer for Twyla Tharp who will make his Broadway choreography debut.</p>
        <p>Only one bit of casting has been confirmed: Lea DeLaria will return as the wisecracking taxi driver.</p>
        <p>After the Broadway success of John Leguizamo's one-man ''Freak,'' Sandra Bernhard has decided to bring her one-woman show, ''I'm Still Here . . . Damn It!,'' to the Booth Theater in mid-October.</p>
        <p>''I thought we might as well take it to the next level,'' Ms. Bernhard said, adding that the show would be similar to the one she performed earlier this year at the Westbeth Theater.</p>
        <p>''After taking the summer off and having a baby, I imagine there will be some new material,'' she said. ''The show evolves.''</p>
        <p>Gregory Mosher, one of the producers of Mr. Leguizamo's show, said extensive polling of the audience members at ''Freak'' showed that 93 percent were under 50 and 75 percent under 35.</p>
        <p>This convinced him that, with the right marketing and the right show, younger people could be drawn into a Broadway theater.</p>
        <p>''They're there,'' Mr. Mosher said. ''That audience is really there.''</p>
        <p>The Hit in the Brit?</p>
        <p>Eric Idle, formerly of Monty Python, will write the book for a new musical being put together by Livent based on the works of Dr. Seuss.</p>
        <p>''Seussical,'' which will also reunite the ''Ragtime'' team of the lyricist Lynn Ahrens, the composer Stephen Flaherty and the director Frank Galati, is to have its first reading in August 1999 at Livent's Summer Festival of New Works in Toronto and a full production sometime in 2000.</p>
        <p>''The hardest part was resolving the book writer, to find an exciting comedic element but somebody who had great humanity and understands the Seussian world,'' said Garth Drabinsky, Livent's creative director. ''Eric has great affinity for these books and for the storytelling.''</p>
        <p>Livent has also firmed up plans for ''Fosse: A Celebration in Song and Dance,'' a collaboration among Richard Maltby, as director; Ann Rein king, as co-director and co-choreographer, and Chet Walker, as co-choreographer. The show is based on Bob Fosse's original choreography, and Gwen Verdon, who had been Fosse's wife and longtime leading lady, will be an artistic adviser.</p>
        <p>The show is set to have its premiere on July 16 at the Ford Center for the Performing Arts in Toronto, with plans to move to the Colonial Theater in Boston in September and the Ahmanson Theater in Los Angeles in December before opening on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Up From 'The Chairs'</p>
        <p>Simon McBurney, whose Theatre de Complicite brought its critically praised production of Ionesco's comedy ''The Chairs'' to Broadway for a limited run that ends tomorrow, is coming back to New York next month for the Lincoln Center Festival '98.</p>
        <p>Mr. McBurney will reprise ''Street of Crocodiles,'' one of the troupe's most highly praised productions, based on short stories by Bruno Schulz, a Polish Holocaust victim who was once forced by the Gestapo to sort books for burning.</p>
        <p>''We had said that if we ever revived it, it would be in New York,'' Mr. McBurney said. ''The stories themselves have no hint of the pleasure of conventional narrative. Our production is not a play, as we understand a play. And I would not call it drama, as we understand drama. But it is definitely theater.''</p>
        <p>The director said his Broadway experience with ''The Chairs'' was, all in all, a good one.</p>
        <p>''Here there is an immense appreciation of the skill of the actor and a real delight in the craft,'' he said. ''And there is a very definite desire for a good time here in New York.''</p>
        <p>Chicken as Songbird</p>
        <p>If you're wondering where to find Henry Krieger, composer of such big Broadway shows as ''Dreamgirls'' and ''Side Show,'' he's down in the East Village playing piano for a bunch of puppets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krieger first saw Susan J. Vitucci performing ''Love's Fowl'' two years ago. A performance piece with puppets, it involves the discovery of the secret diaries of La Pulcina Piccola, also known as Chicken Little, and her romantic adventures after the sky-is-falling incident.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krieger volunteered to write music for the show. and it grew into a kind of mock opera, sung in Italian with English supertitles. He plays the male parts, and Ms. Vitucci the female parts. The show is in previews for a Wednesday opening at the New York Theater Workshop.</p>
        <p>''We are very serious about everything having to do with this particular chicken,'' Mr. Krieger said. ''We feel it's kind of our special lot in life to portray her life in all its passion.''</p>
        <p>Along the Way</p>
        <p>Two Off Broadway shows strongly identified with their lead performers are going to try replacing them. Hal Linden will take over for Eli Wallach in ''Visiting Mr. Green'' at the Union Square Theater beginning on July 7. And for four weeks, starting on July 7, Michael Cerveris will take over ''Hedwig and the Angry Inch'' from the show's vacationing star and author, John Cameron Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Roger Rees and Dana Ivey will open the season for Playwrights Horizons in September in a new comedy by Evan Smith, ''The Uneasy Chair.''</p>
        <p>''When I Was a Girl I Used to Sing and Shout,'' which won Sharman Macdonald The Evening Standard's Most Promising Playwright Award in 1984, will finally get its New York premiere, beginning on Aug. 5 at the John Mongtgomery Theater.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
