<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="12PUBL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Yorker (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hearst, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tarantino, Quentin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED81E3AF931A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Kit R. Roane, Glenn Collins, and David Firestone</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column notes that Patricia Hearst is subject of New Yorker magazine article that says she has been object of Federal drug investigation; also notes that director Quentin Tarantino was arrested on assault charges stemming from fight in East Village restaurant in May; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Hearst Unveils</p>
        <p>This sounds like a headline her grandfather would have printed: PATRICIA HEARST bares all, or almost all. But Ms. Hearst's striptease was not for a newspaper story; it was for the JOHN WATERS film ''Pecker,'' which is scheduled to be released in the fall. She plays an art collector. ''The day that Patricia Hearst arrived in Baltimore to start work on this movie,'' said JEREMY WALKER, a spokesman for Mr. Waters, ''she went to his house. She undid the dress that she brought. It dropped to the floor and she was wearing the slip that she's wearing in the movie, and she said, 'How's this?' John said, 'It's perfect.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hearst, who was kidnapped in 1974 and convicted of robbing a bank with her captors, has been in the headlines this week because a New Yorker magazine article said she had been the object of a Federal drug investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Hearst Unveils</p>
        <p>This sounds like a headline her grandfather would have printed: PATRICIA HEARST bares all, or almost all. But Ms. Hearst's striptease was not for a newspaper story; it was for the JOHN WATERS film ''Pecker,'' which is scheduled to be released in the fall. She plays an art collector. ''The day that Patricia Hearst arrived in Baltimore to start work on this movie,'' said JEREMY WALKER, a spokesman for Mr. Waters, ''she went to his house. She undid the dress that she brought. It dropped to the floor and she was wearing the slip that she's wearing in the movie, and she said, 'How's this?' John said, 'It's perfect.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hearst, who was kidnapped in 1974 and convicted of robbing a bank with her captors, has been in the headlines this week because a New Yorker magazine article said she had been the object of a Federal drug investigation.</p>
        <p>The inquiry began when a suspicious package was delivered to her Connecticut home several months ago. Ms. Hearst called the local police, but Federal agents arrived; later they said they had been tipped off that the package held narcotics. The New Yorker said Ms. Hearst thought someone was trying to hurt her chances for a Presidential pardon.</p>
        <p>Lack of Chivalry</p>
        <p>QUENTIN TARANTINO, who parlayed his interest in crime novels into such films as ''Pulp Fiction,'' was arrested yesterday on assault charges. The charges stem from a fracas last month at a restaurant in the East Village.</p>
        <p>The police said that Mr. Tarantino argued with LEILA MWANGI, who witnesses said was complaining about the way black people were portrayed in his highly stylized films. Apparently Mr. Tarantino did not take her criticisms well and struck her with his fist, said DETECTIVE JOSEPH PENTANGELO, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>A Family Uncorks</p>
        <p>There was a bit of a mystery at a dinner at La Caravelle restaurant in Manhattan last night celebrating the 300th anniversary of Krug Clos du Mesnil Champagne: How could there be a tricentennial if the Krug family did not begin producing wine until 1843?</p>
        <p>''The vineyard itself was indeed established in 1698,'' said CAROLINE KRUG, 32, the company's heiress-apparent.</p>
        <p>Ah, oui. ''Our catalogue states this chronology clearly,'' said MICHAEL BROADBENT, chairman of the international wine department at Christie's, the Manhattan auction house, which is scheduled to auction 27 lots of Clos du Mesnil today for up to $600 a magnum.</p>
        <p>Music Notes</p>
        <p>It sounded like Christmas in June at the annual dinner of the Songwriters' Hall of Fame on Wednesday: FREDDY COLE, the younger brother of Nat King Cole, performed ''The Christmas Song'' in honor of MEL TORME, who wrote it. . . . They screamed and squealed the way they did in the old days. But the 200 Menudo groupies who greeted the Latin teen-age sensations at La Guardia Airport yesterday are grownups now. The quintet was arriving for the Puerto Rican Day parade on Sunday. ''I guess they've grown up a little bit,'' said one fan, GAIL COLON, who admitted to having done some growing up herself. ''But they're still my age.''</p>
        <p>Celebrity Spotting</p>
        <p>BEN CRENSHAW, the two-time Masters champion, was seen at the East Hampton Point restaurant in East Hampton, N.Y., with BONNIE BISTRIAN and her husband, BEN KRUPINSKI, the contractor to the stars who labored on Martha Stewart's 24-room house and is also an owner of East Hampton Point. Were they planning a golf date? Ms. Bistrian and her brother, Barry, want to build a golf course, but environmentalists have raised objections.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Kit R. Roane, Glenn Collins, and David Firestone</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
