<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Proposes Paying Towns To Take Waste</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="416035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOW-LEVEL RADIOACTIVE WASTE SITING COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB103BF93BA25752C0A967958260" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Proposes Paying Towns To Take Waste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acknowledging that New York State probably could not force a community to accept a low-level nuclear waste dump against its will, the state commission charged with finding a dump today proposed a different approach: offering money.</p>
        <p>The Low-Level Radioactive Waste Siting Commission, whose members have been run off of research sites and burned in effigy in the upstate counties where they have identified potential dumps, called on Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the Legislature to adopt a "benefits package" of road construction funds and other local assistance for any community that decides to take the waste site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acknowledging that New York State probably could not force a community to accept a low-level nuclear waste dump against its will, the state commission charged with finding a dump today proposed a different approach: offering money.</p>
        <p>The Low-Level Radioactive Waste Siting Commission, whose members have been run off of research sites and burned in effigy in the upstate counties where they have identified potential dumps, called on Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the Legislature to adopt a "benefits package" of road construction funds and other local assistance for any community that decides to take the waste site.</p>
        <p>While other states have adopted variations of a benefit package to soften resistance to similar waste sites, the resolution here appears to represent a clear shift in New York's approach to the problem. It was also blunt acknowledgment that incentives were needed to get such sites built, even though state officials insist they will be safe.</p>
        <p>Previously, the state had said that it would conduct its search on purely scientific grounds, and would choose the best site from a technical standpoint, even if the surrounding communities were hostile. But the commission, in a one-page resolution released here, said it had concluded that "imposing such a site on an unwilling community has little or no possiblility of success."</p>
        <p>All the states are acting under Federal mandate to find a home by 1993 for the low-level waste they generate, which is now shipped to storage sites in South Carolina, Nevada and Washington State.  'A Horrible Idea'</p>
        <p>The commission's proposal produced no immediate takers today, and residents in some of the communities in Allegany and Cortland Counties that made the oriinal list of finalists reacted bitterly.</p>
        <p>"No way," said John L. Smith, a member of the town board in Taylor, a Cortland County community near three of the potential waste sites. "It could be a million dollars and we'd say no. What's a million dollars worth compared to your health?" He said he and other town residents feared the dump would leak, despite state assurances that it would not.</p>
        <p>Sally Campbell, a member of the Allegany County Non-violent Action Group, who was arrested last year while trying to block commission members taking geologic samples from a proposed site, described the commission proposal as "a horrible idea." The commission, she added, was "trying to take advantage of the economic problems that a lot of rural governments are facing. They're trying to find a sucker."</p>
        <p>Still, with the size of the proposed benefits package still undetermined, it remains unclear whether some community in the state might ultimately find it large enough to consider accepting the dump.  No Specifics</p>
        <p>The commission did not outline specifics for the package, saying that should be worked out by state agencies, the Legislature and the Governor, who are already grappling with falling revenues and large budget gaps.</p>
        <p>Anne W. Crowley, Governor Cuomo's spokeswoman, said that Mr. Cuomo had always been "supportive" of providing assistance to any community that might suffer adverse financial consequences -- for example, declining home values -- if it accepted the dump. But she said Mr. Cuomo had not seen today's resolution and could not comment on it.</p>
        <p>Maurice D. Hinchey, the Ulster County Democrat who is chairman of the State Assembly's Environmental Conservation Committee, said he would look on a benefits package not so much as an inducement to a community, but as a recognition that "there has to be some element of fairness for whoever takes it."</p>
        <p>Any adoption of a benefits package would not change existing laws establishing technological criteria for the site, such as the type of rock composition or permeability of the soil, said Barbara S. Congemi, a spokeswoman for the siting commission.</p>
        <p>But, she said, if a community that could meet such criteria now came forward and volunteered to take the dump, "we would seriously want to take a look at that."</p>
        <p>Low-level waste, some of which is considered a serious threat to public health if not safely stored, is generated in nuclear plants and in many industrial and medical procedures. It includes contaminated clothes, tools, machine parts and resins. New York produces 80,000 cubic feet of waste a year, enough to fill an Olympic-sized swimming pool.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
