<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crawford's Injury Puts a Strain on Two Knicks</title>
    <meta content="08knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/08/sports/basketball/08knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Crawford, Jamal</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DF1231F93BA35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crawford's Injury Puts a Strain on Two Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crawford Injury Puts Strain on 2 Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., March 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question was only halfway out when Eddy Curry started to chuckle. His expression gave away the answer before he said a word. Yes -- absolutely, unequivocally yes -- Curry misses his friend Jamal Crawford.</p>
        <p>''Definitely,'' Curry said with a resigned smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks’ 2-2 record since Jamal Crawford’s injury fails to reflect how much the Knicks miss him  in particular, how much Eddy Curry and Stephon Marbury miss him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question was only halfway out when Eddy Curry started to chuckle. His expression gave away the answer before he said a word. Yes -- absolutely, unequivocally yes -- Curry misses his friend Jamal Crawford.</p>
        <p>''Definitely,'' Curry said with a resigned smile.</p>
        <p>It has been a week since Crawford was lost to a season-ending stress fracture in his right ankle. The Knicks have gone 2-2. But the record fails to reflect how much the Knicks miss him -- in particular, how much Curry and Stephon Marbury miss him.</p>
        <p>Without Crawford's playmaking and shot making, Marbury is carrying an unusually heavy load, in both scoring and playing time. Without Crawford's clever passes and lobs, Curry has had to work twice as hard to score.</p>
        <p>Curry had averaged 20 points a game over the last three months, but is averaging 15.5 in Crawford's absence. Curry converted 63 percent of his field goals in January and February, but has made 20 of 45 (.444) over the last four games.</p>
        <p>''You miss those lob passes and those just easy passes, easy buckets, they kind of get you in the flow of the game,'' Curry said of Crawford.</p>
        <p>Curry and Crawford's chemistry, and close friendship, began early in their careers, as teammates with the Chicago Bulls. None of the Knicks' guards are as persistent at feeding the ball inside as Crawford. And no one else has the knack for zipping well-timed lobs for Curry to slam home.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks also miss the mere threat of Crawford -- their best clutch-time shooter -- on the court. Curry is again being bottled up by aggressive double teams. And Marbury, who had refashioned himself as a second or third option, has out of necessity become the Knicks' leading scorer.</p>
        <p>Marbury was averaging 14.5 points and 11.5 field-goal attempts a game before Crawford was injured. In the last four games, Marbury has averaged 33.8 points and 20 field-goal attempts. Marbury has scored at least 30 points in three straight games.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to do what I've got to do to try to help the team win,'' Marbury said. ''That's it.''</p>
        <p>The scoring role comes naturally to Marbury, a former All-Star who once dominated his position. But Marbury is 30 with a chronically sore knee and a sore big toe. He is in his 11th season. It is questionable whether Marbury -- who has averaged 46 minutes over the last four games -- can sustain this pace over the final 20 games. But he may have to if the Knicks (28-34) are going to stay in the playoff hunt.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to sit here and say that I'm not feeling it,'' Marbury said of the increased workload, ''but due to the injuries that have occurred, it's been a little bit more of a strain. But conditioning-wise, I'm fine.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks lost Tuesday night to Seattle when Marbury missed a 3-pointer in the final minute and a free throw with nine-tenths of a second left. But the Knicks probably would have been routed if not for Marbury's performance to that point. He scored 40 points and hit eight 3-pointers, tying his career high. He scored 17 points in the final 6 minutes 49 seconds. It was among his most impressive performances of the season.</p>
        <p>This was not the game plan Coach Isiah Thomas envisioned, but it may be the formula that carries the Knicks through March and April. The burden on Marbury will be eased only if Curry can find his way through the double teams, or if Quentin Richardson and Steve Francis can consistently make shots.</p>
        <p>After Tuesday's loss, Thomas resisted the notion that the Knicks were leaning too much on Marbury. Instead, he pointed to the Knicks' 14 missed free throws.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've become overreliant,'' he said. ''We did a good enough job to win the basketball game. If we make free throws, this is a 10-point game and we're not having this conversation.''</p>
        <p>As might be expected, Wednesday's practice was devoted in part to free-throw shooting and to teaching Curry how to handle the defensive attention. Curry has been dealing with double teams for most of the last two months, but now the second defender is often a big man, instead of a guard.</p>
        <p>David Lee's absence for the last six games has also hurt Curry. Although Lee is not a shooter, he commands attention because of his offensive rebounding. Jared Jeffries, one of the Knicks' worst shooters, is now playing extensively, and teams have no fear of leaving him open.</p>
        <p>Curry admitted the last two games have been particularly tough.</p>
        <p>''It was the first time that I really felt like I was hurting the team,'' he said of Tuesday's loss. But Curry, who said he had tired legs Saturday in Atlanta, said fatigue would not be a factor in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>''It's March, and I've got a realistic chance of making the playoffs,'' he said. ''So this is the time when I'm really trying to turn it on. I'm really putting a lot of pressure on myself. I need to just relax out there.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Nate Robinson returned to practice after a weeklong bout with a stomach virus that left him physically depleted. Robinson, who needed intravenous fluids when the virus first struck him eight days ago, said he had lost 10 pounds. ''Everybody called me 'the Ghost' when I came back,'' he said. ... David Lee's recovery from a sprained right ankle and muscle strain in his right leg continues to drag. Lee pulled himself out of practice, and his status for Saturday's game against Washington is unclear. Lee had predicted he would be back for Tuesday's game.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
