<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPUS PLAYBOOK</title>
    <meta content="30florida" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DC1730F933A0575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPUS PLAYBOOK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY (NYT)</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaky Footing</p>
        <p>If Alabama cannot straighten out its kicking game, the Crimson Tide may have a long afternoon in Gainesville today against No. 5 Florida (4-0). Alabama lost in double overtime to Arkansas last week, 24-23, when the freshman Leigh Tiffin missed three field-goal attempts and an extra point.</p>
        <p>Alabama (3-1) will also be challenged by the Gators' offense, which is averaging 289.8 yards passing and 175.8 rushing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shaky Footing</p>
        <p>If Alabama cannot straighten out its kicking game, the Crimson Tide may have a long afternoon in Gainesville today against No. 5 Florida (4-0). Alabama lost in double overtime to Arkansas last week, 24-23, when the freshman Leigh Tiffin missed three field-goal attempts and an extra point.</p>
        <p>Alabama (3-1) will also be challenged by the Gators' offense, which is averaging 289.8 yards passing and 175.8 rushing.</p>
        <p>Joe Kines, Alabama's defensive coordinator, was quoted on the team's Web site talking about Florida's offense:</p>
        <p>''I have never seen a system that has all the parts of football: the power, the zone, the option, play action, the empty, five wideouts, short yardage, two tight ends. I don't think there is a part of football they don't cover.''</p>
        <p>Other major games today:</p>
        <p>No. 1 Ohio State at No. 13 Iowa</p>
        <p>No. 3 U.S.C. at Washington State</p>
        <p>No. 24 Georgia Tech at No. 11 Virginia Tech</p>
        <p>Purdue at No. 12 Notre Dame</p>
        <p>In Division III, Trinity's 31-game winning streak will be on the line against its New England Small College Athletic Conference rival Williams at Weston Field in Williamstown, Mass.</p>
        <p>Rolling Right Along</p>
        <p>Texas Christian lost to Brigham Young on Thursday night, ending what was the longest active winning streak in N.C.A.A. Division I (13 games). The nation's longest active winning streaks.</p>
        <p>A Modest TV Premiere</p>
        <p>On Sept. 30, 1939 -- 67 years ago today -- a college football game was televised for the first time.</p>
        <p>Fordham, then a national power, played Waynesburg (Pa.) at Randalls Island Stadium. Fordham won, 34-7. The game was shown on W2XBS, an experimental station that became WNBC-TV.</p>
        <p>According to estimates at the time, there were perhaps 200 sets in the metropolitan New York area, and the game attracted 500 viewers.</p>
        <p>The play-by-play announcer was Bill Stern, a leading sportscaster of that era, and the pregame interviews were handled by a 26-year-old Mel Allen.</p>
        <p>Fifty years after the game, Dom Principe, a star fullback for Fordham, told the sports historian Stanley Grosshandler, ''The fact that the game was televised was of no significance to us.''</p>
        <p>Jack McPhee, the referee in the game, said: ''When I returned to my home in Youngstown, Ohio, I told my wife about it. She was all excited, asking me what television was and how did it work. Of course, I did not know.''</p>
        <p>FRANK LITSKY (NYT)</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
