<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Firebrand Ortega On the Comeback Trail</title>
    <meta content="30nicaragua" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/30/world/americas/30nicaragua.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nicaragua</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ortega, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montealegre, Eduardo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Nicaragua</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Venezuela</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Sandinista National Liberation Front</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Organization of American States</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ortega, Daniel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chavez, Hugo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Burton, Dan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DC1730F933A0575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Firebrand Ortega On the Comeback Trail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Firebrand Ortega on the Comeback Trail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>MANAGUA, Nicaragua, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Ortega, former leftist president of Nicaragua, stands his best chance to return to power after three failed attempts in last 15 years; Ortega is front-runner in race splintered among five candidates; opinion polls give him about 30 percent support; Bush administration is supporting former Foreign Min Eduardo Montealegre in Nov 5 election; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Washington's old cold war nemesis, Daniel Ortega, is as divisive a figure as he ever was as a 30-something revolutionary who took on Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>After three failed attempts to return to power in the last 15 years, El Comandante, as Mr. Ortega is widely known, is once again smiling down from campaign billboards across Nicaragua. Now 60 and balding with a slight paunch, he stands his best chance yet of returning to power in elections on Nov. 5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Washington’s old cold war nemesis, Daniel Ortega of Nicaragua, has his best chance yet of returning to power in elections on Nov. 5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Washington's old cold war nemesis, Daniel Ortega, is as divisive a figure as he ever was as a 30-something revolutionary who took on Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>After three failed attempts to return to power in the last 15 years, El Comandante, as Mr. Ortega is widely known, is once again smiling down from campaign billboards across Nicaragua. Now 60 and balding with a slight paunch, he stands his best chance yet of returning to power in elections on Nov. 5.</p>
        <p>Though opinion polls give Mr. Ortega about 30 percent support, he is the front-runner in a race splintered among five candidates. Yet the sentiment against him is broad and the scrambling to head off an Ortega victory is intense, and not just in Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>The prospect has stirred deep anxiety in the Bush administration, which envisions him as a new ally for President Hugo Chávez of Venezuela in challenging United States policy. Mr. Chávez has lent his support to Mr. Ortega, while Washington has sent word in no uncertain terms that aid will be re-evaluated if Mr. Ortega is elected.</p>
        <p>The latest in a string of visitors to Managua was Representative Dan Burton of Indiana, chairman of the House subcommittee on Western Hemisphere affairs. While insisting that he was not telling Nicaraguans how to vote, he made it clear to local reporters that he opposed Mr. Ortega and that relations between Nicaragua and the United States would suffer should he win.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ortega's fiercest opposition is homegrown. He is not just a candidate. He is the main issue in the race.</p>
        <p>Nicaraguan politics continue to revolve around the mustachioed former Marxist, who led the country after the leftist Sandinista National Liberation Front overthrew the Somoza family's four-decade military dictatorship. Continuing domestic divisions during his administration, including a rightist insurgency backed by the United States, left the lush countryside bathed in blood.</p>
        <p>''This decision that the voters are going to take on Nov. 5 is a question of national survival,'' Eduardo Montealegre, the candidate of the Nicaraguan Liberal Alliance, said in an interview. ''With Ortega we're not going to survive.'' Mr. Montealegre, who served as foreign minister and finance minister in conservative administrations, has the blessing of Washington.</p>
        <p>Another candidate, Edmundo Jarquín, an economist and former Sandinista diplomat, criticized Mr. Ortega for being ''all about conflict,'' intent on riling the United States at every opportunity.</p>
        <p>Still another, José Rizo, a former vice president from the pro-business Constitutionalist Liberal Party, said Mr. Ortega's first stint as president, in the 1980's, was marked by human rights abuses and a failed economy -- compounded, of course, by a trade embargo imposed by President Reagan.</p>
        <p>A fifth candidate, Edén Pastora, a former Sandinista leader once known as Commander Zero, trails well behind the others.</p>
        <p>The plethora of challengers has boosted Mr. Ortega's chances, especially since his party orchestrated a rules change several years ago allowing a presidential candidate to win with as little as 35 percent of the vote and a five-point lead over the nearest rival.</p>
        <p>That electoral math may allow Mr. Ortega to squeak out a victory in the first round of balloting. Should he fail to do so, his chances are considered slim in a runoff, in which the anti-Ortega vote would be likely to dominate, said Alejandro Serrano Caldera, a political analyst.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Ortega regards himself as so much of a target that he avoided a televised debate earlier this month in which the four other candidates participated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ortega wears heavy boots and a white collarless shirt on the campaign trail. He shakes every hand he can but strides quickly past reporters seeking to question him. His stump speeches are vintage Ortega -- passionate appeals to the poor in this country, one of the most down and out in the Western Hemisphere. But he says his Marxist days are a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>After toppling Anastasio Somoza in 1979 and seizing power, the Sandinistas confiscated private property and formed alliances with Cuba and the Soviet Union. The United States responded by backing insurgents, known as the contras, intent on topping Mr. Ortega.</p>
        <p>In 1990, after a long and destructive war, a peace agreement led to new elections, which Mr. Ortega lost to a coalition of opposition parties led by Violeta Barrios de Chamorro.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ortega tries to soothe some audiences by insisting that his presidency would be different this time around. He speaks of his desire to tame ''savage capitalism'' by, for instance, renegotiating the trade agreement that Nicaragua and other countries in Central America have signed with the United States.</p>
        <p>Still, he raised alarms recently when he criticized the election observers sent by the Organization of American States. The presence of many of his loyalists on the national electoral commission prompted fears of vote rigging.</p>
        <p>And when he gets out into the countryside, Mr. Ortega still insinuates heavily that the landless ought to get plots of their own.</p>
        <p>This somewhat ambiguous approach has won over some new converts, even as Mr. Ortega has fallen out with some longtime loyalists who consider him a sellout to the revolution.</p>
        <p>The years have indeed shown Mr. Ortega to be far less of an ideologue than he used to be when he railed against the West. A shrewd political operator by any measure, he has tried to widen his base by embracing old rivals, including some in the Constitutionalist Liberal Party of Arnoldo Alemán, a conservative former president.</p>
        <p>''Ortega is like a pendulum who moves from one side to the other and is more pragmatic than ideological,'' said Carlos Chamorro, a political analyst and son of Violeta Chamorro.</p>
        <p>Aiding Mr. Ortega's campaign more than anything is the suffering that many Nicaraguans endure. Despite some gains -- a big drop in the national debt and steady economic growth -- many feel left out of the country's recovery and are willing to give Mr. Ortega's populism another try.</p>
        <p>''He'll be better this time,'' said Margarita de Jesús Calero, 58, a grandmother from Managua who stood in the sun the other day for a glimpse of her candidate. ''He has more experience. He knows where he wants to go now.''</p>
        <p>But the memories of the war years are too strong for others to forget, despite Mr. Ortega's talk of debt forgiveness and other subsidies for the poor.</p>
        <p>''When he was president before, we didn't have food and our children were off fighting,'' said María del Carmen Cerda, 52, whose family is divided into pro- and anti-Sandinista factions. ''The only thing he gave us was sorrow.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ortega's most prominent convert is Jaime Morales, a former member of the contra guerrillas. Mr. Morales has joined Mr. Ortega's campaign as the vice presidential candidate and sees a change in Mr. Ortega for the better.</p>
        <p>He said he received compensation from Mr. Ortega several years ago for his house, which the Sandinistas seized in the 1980's and in which Mr. Ortega still lives. The compensation was part of Mr. Ortega's effort to heal old wounds, Mr. Morales said.</p>
        <p>''The Daniel Ortega of today is not the Daniel Ortega of years ago,'' he said. ''I can understand all the anxiety, but we have to stop living in the past.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
