<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Quality TV, Mad Scientist Returns</title>
    <meta content="30beak" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/30/arts/television/30beak.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zaloom, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDD1730F933A0575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Quality TV, Mad Scientist Returns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Quality TV, Mad Scientist Returns</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Elizabeth</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sixteen years ago Congress adopted the Children's Television Act to increase the amount of educational and informational programming for youth on broadcast stations, leading to the creation of the award-winning mad-scientist series ''Beakman's World.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday the Federal Communications Commission updated the rules to increase the amount of educational and informational children's programming that stations need to show as they move into the digital era and split their signal into many different program streams. And once again, it's ''Beakman's World'' to the rescue, but this time in reruns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Television stations’ demand for so-called educational and informational programming is growing, but executives say the supply isn’t, so it’s “Beakman’s World” to the rescue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sixteen years ago Congress adopted the Children's Television Act to increase the amount of educational and informational programming for youth on broadcast stations, leading to the creation of the award-winning mad-scientist series ''Beakman's World.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday the Federal Communications Commission updated the rules to increase the amount of educational and informational children's programming that stations need to show as they move into the digital era and split their signal into many different program streams. And once again, it's ''Beakman's World'' to the rescue, but this time in reruns.</p>
        <p>Stations' demand for so-called E/I, or educational and informational, programming is growing, but programming executives say the supply isn't, as producers find it more lucrative to make new shows tied to merchandise. While the Federal Communications Commission hopes that the new rules will increase quality programs for children, Sony Pictures Television decided there was also a market for old episodes of ''Beakman's World,'' a show that first appeared in syndication in 1992.</p>
        <p>It later moved to CBS, which canceled it in 1998; it has occasionally surfaced on cable and local stations since then. The series returned last week -- not updated -- on more than 200 stations reaching 97 percent of American television homes.</p>
        <p>The live-action show, a spinoff of the Universal Press Syndicate comic strip ''You Can With Beakman and Jax,'' features the wacky, spike-haired scientist, his loud female assistant and a man wearing a rat suit. They enact messy, try-at-home experiments of the pop-bottle-rocket variety and explain complex principles like the theory of relativity (in six minutes).</p>
        <p>''We tried to break down that fear factor'' about science, said Paul Zaloom, the actor who played Beakman.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five stations across the country owned by the Fox Television Stations group bought the rights to the reruns; they include WNYW (Channel 5) in New York City, which is carrying two episodes back to back on Saturdays at noon. On their first return outing last week, the audience in New York was twice what it was a year ago in the time period.</p>
        <p>''Our E/I core programming is extremely important to us,'' said Frank Cicha, senior vice president of programming for the Fox stations. But, he added, ''when you look around the business, there is not a myriad of choices as far as F.C.C. kids programming is concerned.''</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. already requires stations to show three hours of such programming each week, labeled E/I, or risk losing their licenses. New digital technology allows stations to split their television signals into six additional channels, which will now be required to carry as many as three hours of educational programming each week, in proportion to the amount of other programming they show.</p>
        <p>KOIN-TV, the CBS affiliate in Portland, Ore., plans to run ''Beakman's World'' on a digital multicast channel. Marty Ostrow, the station's president and general manager, said that while CBS supplies KOIN with the three hours of weekly educational programming it needs, ''you can never be too safe.''</p>
        <p>''We tend to try to overcompensate,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sony executives said they heard the same from other stations. ''We saw the need for E/I programming both from a regulatory standpoint'' and from one of station demand, said John Weiser, president of distribution for Sony Pictures Television.</p>
        <p>While some programs that use the educational label are little more than a compilation of, say, animal clips, Mr. Weiser noted that ''Beakman's World'' was ''really teaching kids about science.''</p>
        <p>''This is a real value proposition,'' he said. ''Kids can walk away and be smarter from watching it.''</p>
        <p>There were 91 ''Beakman's World'' episodes made; while never a top ratings-grabber, the series won numerous honors and was shown worldwide.</p>
        <p>''The way the television business works today, no one could afford to make a show like this anymore,'' said Mr. Zaloom, now 54, noting that the program, shot on a soundstage, cost $250,000 a half-hour episode.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the stuff is merchandise-driven now,'' he added in an interview, or, in what he referred to as ''a weasel-thon,'' stations simply relabel existing shows as educational.</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. lets stations monitor whether they are in compliance, which children's advocates have complained allows some stations to skirt the requirements.</p>
        <p>''If you start watching what is labeled E/I, very little is 'Beakman's World,' '' said Gloria Tristani, a former F.C.C. commissioner who is now president of the Benton Foundation, which works on public interest issues as they relate to communications. ''I would pose that maybe half of it wouldn't pass the test, if anyone were monitoring it,'' she said, adding that there had been no recent studies.</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. first tried to update its children's television obligations for broadcasters in 2004, prompting opposing lawsuits from the television industry, which thought the new rules were too strict, and children's advocates, who found them lax. Ms. Tristani was part of a committee with representatives from both sides that reached a compromise adopted unanimously by the F.C.C. on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In addition to requiring educational programming on multicast stations, the new rules put limits on how Web site addresses can be used in conjunction with both broadcast and cable programming, to protect children from overly commercial online material.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicha of Fox said he liked ''Beakman's World'' because it did not talk down to children, and he does not worry it will be dated, noting, ''Stuff like this is ageless.''</p>
        <p>''Persistence of vision is still about persistence of vision,'' said Mr. Zaloom, referring to a science principle explored on the show. ''Not much has changed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
