<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answering The Mail</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA163BF932A35757C0A966958260" item-length="303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answering The Mail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD GLADSTONE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Q. Our teak furniture has an oiled finish that has become quite dark over the years. When new, the furniture was rubbed with linseed oil several times, and I have since been told that was a mistake, that I should have used mineral oil. I think the furniture needs to be cleaned, but am not sure how to do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Q. Our teak furniture has an oiled finish that has become quite dark over the years. When new, the furniture was rubbed with linseed oil several times, and I have since been told that was a mistake, that I should have used mineral oil. I think the furniture needs to be cleaned, but am not sure how to do so.</p>
        <p>Q. Our teak furniture has an oiled finish that has become quite dark over the years. When new, the furniture was rubbed with linseed oil several times, and I have since been told that was a mistake, that I should have used mineral oil. I think the furniture needs to be cleaned, but am not sure how to do so. Would soap and water hurt?</p>
        <p>A. Cleaning wood furniture with soap and water is never a good idea if it can be avoided, and in your case I do not think it would do the job. Linseed oil was a mistake, since that darkens as it oxidizes, but mineral oil also would be a mistake because it never dries and attracts dirt. I suggest cleaning the finish by rubbing with fine steel wool dipped into mineral spirits or a similar paint thinner (it is best to work outside, if you can). As you scrub each section, wipe immediately with a dry cloth and change cloths often, as they get dirty. When dry, rub with fine sandpaper (No. 220), then apply one of the penetrating teak sealers sold in most paint stores.</p>
        <p>Q. Our concrete basement floor has been painted many times, and the layers of paint are now cracking, blistering, peeling and powdering. In addition, the walls, which are cement block, have been whitewashed many times and are also peeling. What is the best way to clean up and repaint this mess?</p>
        <p>A. On the walls, use a wire brush and scraper to remove as much of the old paint as possible; it would be best if you could get all of it off. Then apply a coat of a masonry bonding sealer and finish with one or two coats of a latex masonry paint. The only sure cure for removing all the old paint off the floors is by using a heavy-bodied chemical paint remover (sold in all paint and hardware stores). When down to the raw concrete, scrub with detergent, then paint with two coats of latex deck paint.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
