<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lisztian Treasure Comes Into Its Own</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="HOME ENTERTAINMENT: SOUNDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRUTCHFIELD, WILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD113BF932A35757C0A966958260" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lisztian Treasure Comes Into Its Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Will Crutchfield</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRUTCHFIELD, WILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The great composers of Italy honored their poetical classics - Dante, Ariosto, Petrarch, Tasso - but tended not to set their words to music. They must all have known Petrarch's sonnets to Laura from childhood, but it was Franz Liszt who made three of them into magnificent songs. He set them in 1839, shortly before making some tours with the tenor Giovanni</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The great composers of Italy honored their poetical classics - Dante, Ariosto, Petrarch, Tasso - but tended not to set their words to music. They must all have known Petrarch's sonnets to Laura from childhood, but it was Franz Liszt who made three of them into magnificent songs. He set them in 1839, shortly before making some tours with the tenor Giovanni</p>
        <p>The great composers of Italy honored their poetical classics - Dante, Ariosto, Petrarch, Tasso - but tended not to set their words to music. They must all have known Petrarch's sonnets to Laura from childhood, but it was Franz Liszt who made three of them into magnificent songs. He set them in 1839, shortly before making some tours with the tenor Giovanni Rubini.</p>
        <p>Petrarch was a good inspiration for Liszt. The two were a lot alike, not least in the ambiguity of their characters, pulled between spiritual aspiration and a keen hunger for worldly honors. The sonnets are among Liszt's most satisfactory compositions. They are impassioned and richly melodious; their various sections hang together, as isn't always the case in Liszt; the piano and vocal writing, both rewarding, are in balance; there is responsiveness to the finer shades of the poetry, and the feeling for Italianate tenorial lyricism is superb (even if Liszt's accentuation of the language requires some correction).</p>
        <p>Since the centennial of Liszt's death in 1986, this once-neglected treasure has been recorded on CD by at least six tenors, most recently Alfredo Kraus (Capriccio 10 272, a mixed song recital accompanied by Edelmiro Arnaltes) and Nicolai Gedda (Bluebell ABCD 021, the first in a two-disk set of Liszt songs with Lars Roos). These are joined by a live concert version from the baritone Renato Bruson (Capriccio 10 295, with Marcus Creed at the piano).</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Kraus and Mr. Gedda are over 60, and it is very impressive to hear how many feats of vocalism they still command, but at a certain point one begins to feel that the focus is more on the hurdles to be cleared than on the expressive content. Mr. Gedda is sensitive enough to include messa di voce and pianissimo (up to high D flat) among the feats, and while grateful for that, I would rather he had kept up the more basic accomplishment of flowing, free-sounding tone. Mr. Kraus is better in that respect, but in the best parts of Mr. Bruson's recording (transposed down, of course) one finds a mellow, reposeful tone and a dignity of poetic sentiment that are missing in the others. This performance, though, is undermined by really funereal tempos and a dragging, labored accompaniment.</p>
        <p>The best version is still Luciano Pavarotti's with John Wustman (London 421 526-2), despite some musical carelessness and some frayed vocal edges. The celebrated tenor can take a line of declamation and run with it, and he has the basic vocal wherewithal to make sense of the writing. These are generous, passionate performances, and the singer's long experience with the songs tells positively.</p>
        <p>HOME ENTERTAINMENT: SOUNDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
