<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New &amp; Noteworthy</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="501687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPERBACK BOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK TRADE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D71F31F93AA25752C0A964958260" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New &amp; Noteworthy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TRAIL OF HEART'S BLOOD WHEREVER WE GO, by Robert Olmstead. (Avon, $11.) A Vietnam veteran who has become the undertaker in a small New England town learns some surprising lessons about the way people die. The result is "a kind of prose 'Spoon River Anthology' " notable for "the intelligence and humaneness of the voice, the grace and clarity of the prose," Michael Malone said here in 1990.</p>
        <p>BAGHDAD WITHOUT A MAP: And Other Misadventures in Arabia, by Tony Horwitz. (Plume, $10.) Tony Horwitz knew he was adrift in an unfathomable land when, at Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's funeral, a man who had been chanting "Death to America" confessed that his dream had always been to visit Disneyland and take his children on the teacup ride. From his "wacky, often hair-raising, experiences,  [ the author ]  has fashioned 'Baghdad Without a Map,' a very funny and frequently insightful look at the world's most combustible region," Barry Gewen said here last year. "Fearlessness is a valuable quality in a travel writer, and Mr. Horwitz, who is now a reporter for The Wall Street Journal, seems as intrepid as they come."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TRAIL OF HEART'S BLOOD WHEREVER WE GO, by Robert Olmstead. (Avon, $11.) A Vietnam veteran who has become the undertaker in a small New England town learns some surprising lessons about the way people die. The result is "a kind of prose 'Spoon River Anthology' " notable for "the intelligence and humaneness of the voice, the grace and clarity of the prose," Michael Malone said here in 1990.</p>
        <p>BAGHDAD WITHOUT A MAP: And Other Misadventures in Arabia, by Tony Horwitz. (Plume, $10.) Tony Horwitz knew he was adrift in an unfathomable land when, at Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's funeral, a man who had been chanting "Death to America" confessed that his dream had always been to visit Disneyland and take his children on the teacup ride. From his "wacky, often hair-raising, experiences,  [ the author ]  has fashioned 'Baghdad Without a Map,' a very funny and frequently insightful look at the world's most combustible region," Barry Gewen said here last year. "Fearlessness is a valuable quality in a travel writer, and Mr. Horwitz, who is now a reporter for The Wall Street Journal, seems as intrepid as they come."</p>
        <p>A GRAVEYARD FOR LUNATICS: Another Tale of Two Cities, by Ray Bradbury. (Bantam, $10.) Two childhood friends, a pulp science fiction writer (much like the young Mr. Bradbury) and a special effects wizard, are hired by a big Hollywood studio to make a horror movie. " 'A Graveyard for Lunatics' combines elements of the detective story, the Hollywood novel and the monster fable in a manner that is intermittently effective, nearly unique and frequently charming," Tom Nolan said here in 1990. Bantam has also republished Mr. Bradbury's DEATH IS A LONELY BUSINESS ($10), in which the same young writer investigates murders at a decaying amusement park on the old Venice Beach pier. In 1985 our reviewer, Geoffrey O'Brien, said, "Ray Bradbury's most devoted readers, who are many, will enjoy this close-up of his mind."</p>
        <p>MARS BECKONS: The Mysteries, the Challenges, the Expectations of Our Next Great Adventure in Space, by John Noble Wilford. (Vintage, $12.) It was disappointing to learn on the first Mariner voyage that there were no canals on Mars, but later visits showed a volcano twice as high as Everest and a canyon stretching the width of the United States. "Mr. Wilford provides a highly readable summary that also captures the manned-mission-to-Mars debate," Marcia Bartusiak said here in 1990.</p>
        <p>STONE HEART, by Luanne Rice. (Ivy, $5.99.) Returning home to Connecticut to start her life anew, an archeologist named Maria Dark is disturbed by hints that her younger sister is trapped in a pathological marriage. This novel is "a remarkably understated account of domestic violence," Alice McDermott said here in 1990.</p>
        <p>THE GOOD RAIN: Across Time and Terrain in the Pacific Northwest, by Timothy Egan. (Vintage, $10.) A correspondent for The New York Times in Seattle describes the magic that makes this corner of the United States one of the most beautiful places on earth -- and one of the most threatened. In 1990 our reviewer, Sarah Boxer, said the book "is not only furious but quite lovely."</p>
        <p>ICY CLUTCHES, by Aaron Elkins. (Mysterious Press/ Warner, $4.99.) On a trip to Alaska a forensic anthropologist investigates a 30-year-old murder involving members of a scientific team buried in an avalanche. "Aaron Elkins's new mystery sparkles aplenty with those eye-catching scenic descriptions he does so well," Marilyn Stasio said here in 1990.</p>
        <p>BENJAMIN O. DAVIS JR., AMERICAN: An Autobiography. (Plume, $13.) After becoming the first black to graduate from West Point in the 20th century, the author found that his struggles against institutionalized racism had only begun. Last year The Times's Herbert Mitgang called this book "an important addition to the shelf of civil rights and military literature."</p>
        <p>MURDER AT THE NATIONAL CATHEDRAL, by Margaret Truman. (Fawcett Crest, $5.99.) A playboy priest is found dead in Washington's landmark Episcopal church. "Miss Truman may be a stodgy writer, but she has always been a stickler for authenticity," Marilyn Stasio said in The Book Review in 1990. "Accordingly, she does well here with her close descriptions of her imposing setting and with the details of the religious business conducted there."</p>
        <p>A PARROT WITHOUT A NAME: The Search for the Last Unknown Birds on Earth, by Don Stap. (University of Texas, $14.95.) After accompanying two ornithologists on expeditions in the Peruvian jungle, the author shows that there is nothing especially sedate about bird watching. In 1990 The Times's Gerald Gold said, "The book, though packed with intellectual and emotional joy and high jinks and humor, engenders a feeling of sadness that the earth will not remain filled forever with such endless mysterious frontiers; that our great-grandchildren and beyond will not know the wonder of the unknown."</p>
        <p>THE SKEPTIC DISPOSITION: Deconstruction, Ideology and Other Matters, by Eugene Goodheart. (Princeton University, $12.95.) In 1985 our reviewer, Morris Dickstein, said this book about contemporary literary criticism is "a fair-minded, generous critique of the deconstructionist theories of Jacques Derrida, Paul de Man and their followers."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
