<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All-Stars Shoot, Score and Shoot More</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="501633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALL STAR GAMES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1331F93AA25752C0A964958260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All-Stars Shoot, Score and Shoot More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Hockey League All-Star Game is the one hockey game of the year after which the losing players don't grouse and mutter and answer questions, heads down, with one or two words and cliches. And this afternoon, it didn't matter that the Campbell Conference had defeated the Wales Conference here at the Spectrum by 10-6: Bryan Trottier was happy to have been a part of it and to have scored a goal.</p>
        <p>"I played my first All-Star Game here in Philadelphia," said Trottier, a former Islander and current Pittsburgh Penguin who played in his first All-Star Game in 1976 and was added to this season's game under the senior category established last season. "I played my 1,000th game here, too, and the fans gave me a standing ovation. I have a few special memories here."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Hockey League All-Star Game is the one hockey game of the year after which the losing players don't grouse and mutter and answer questions, heads down, with one or two words and cliches. And this afternoon, it didn't matter that the Campbell Conference had defeated the Wales Conference here at the Spectrum by 10-6: Bryan Trottier was happy to have been a part of it and to have scored a goal.</p>
        <p>"I played my first All-Star Game here in Philadelphia," said Trottier, a former Islander and current Pittsburgh Penguin who played in his first All-Star Game in 1976 and was added to this season's game under the senior category established last season. "I played my 1,000th game here, too, and the fans gave me a standing ovation. I have a few special memories here."</p>
        <p>The best memories of this All-Star Game, the league's 43d, will go to Brett Hull of the St. Louis Blues, who scored two goals and assisted on another and won a motor vehicle as the player of the game. He was right wing on a line with Los Angeles center Wayne Gretzky, who had a goal and two assists. The combination of hockey's best sniper and hockey's best setup artist was something special to see.</p>
        <p>"I had the feeling I was going to get a couple of chances today," said Hull, the league's leading goal scorer, who missed last year's All-Star Game because of a foot injury. "Gretzky is extremely easy to play with."</p>
        <p>Theoren Fleury of Calgary also scored twice for the Campbells, as did Brian Bellows of Minnesota. It was the first All-Star Game ever with no penalties. The Campbells had 42 shots on goal and the Wales had 41. The Campbells led by 2-1 after one period, then took command with six goals in the second off goalie Don Beaupre of the Washington Capitals.</p>
        <p>It also was the first game ever to include two players from the former Soviet Union. They were Buffalo's Aleksandr Mogilny and Detroit's Sergei Fedorov. Mogilny scored a goal for the Wales and Fedorov had two assists for the Campbells. In the skills competition the night before, Fedorov won the speed-skating event and Mogilny finished second. After the game today, they posed together for pictures on the ice. Wide-Open Game</p>
        <p>"I was a little nervous," Fedorov said. "I am so excited and very happy for me and for my friend, Alex Mogilny. To be an All-Star is a very big surprise for me. I am so happy to play on the same team as Wayne Gretzky."</p>
        <p>Also scoring for the winners were Trevor Linden, Jeremy Roenick, and Gary Roberts. Also scoring for the losers were Kevin Stevens, Scott Stevens, Owen Nolan and Randy Burridge.</p>
        <p>As is usually the case with these games, the players joked about the lack of checking and rough play and about the wide-open style that favors goal-scorers.</p>
        <p>"Larry Robinson gave me the best advice," said Mark Tinordi of the Campbells. "He said, 'When Mario Lemieux comes on the ice, get off.' "</p>
        <p>Lemieux didn't have a point today.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>In the not-too-distant future, the regular-season and playoff games may be somewhat more like All-Star Games than they are now. Although there is no movement to ban body checking or to increase scoring, the league's general managers are seriously considering a stricter prohibition against fistfighting. Such a change, if it comes about, would be revolutionary for the league. "It has never been discussed from the point of view of league philosophy as much as it is now," said GERRY MEEHAN, general manager of the Buffalo Sabres, who was the chairman of a committee that debated the issue last week. The conversation was serious and lively, although Meehan declined to divulge details. "Let's just say there are people at both extremes and there are moderates," he said. The general managers can't pass legislation, but their recommendations are usually taken seriously by the Board of Governors, made up of team owners and their representatives, who take the formal vote.</p>
        <p>Today's All-Star Game was held at the home rink of the Philadelphia Flyers, who won the Stanley Cup in 1974 and 1975 with a style that employed fistfighting as a regular tactic. Since then and because of that, the league has toughened regulations against fighting, eliminating most of the bench-clearing brawls and multiplayer tiffs. But serious fights still occur, as they did earlier this week, and sometimes get major exposure on the newscasts in the United States, which doesn't carry N.H.L. games on an over-the-air network.</p>
        <p>WAYNE GRETZKY and MARIO LEMIEUX, two of hockey's top stars, have urged a ban on fighting in recent years. Gretzky in particular has said that highlights of fights on local newscasts give a distorted, negative image and hurt the marketing of the sport. Asked this weekend if he expects the league to ban fighting, Gretzky replied: "I'll be gone before it is accomplished." Gretzky will celebrate his 31st birthday on Jan. 26; he has been in the league since 1979.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
