<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Minibus From Loneliness</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="501185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK TIMES NEEDIEST CASES FUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D61539F93AA25752C0A964958260" item-length="396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Minibus From Loneliness</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"What would I do in Florida?" The answer Julia has in mind is plain: nothing. Since her parents emigrated from Poland in 1910, she has lived in Brooklyn. It is where she went to school, got her first job sewing ($3 a week), where she married, raised a family and bought her daughter a home. Julia, 90 years old and widowed, is mentally sharp and too vigorous to sit home all day, but she can no longer go out walking in the winter or at night. Julia hates to ask her grandchildren on Long Island for favors, and her daughter is now 70 and blind.</p>
        <p>So every weekday, a minibus operated by the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged provides her with round-trip transportation to the Williamsburg Senior Center, where she enjoys a hot lunch, planned activities and the company of friends. The minibus, which serves senior citizens of all races and creeds, is just one of many programs for the elderly supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"What would I do in Florida?" The answer Julia has in mind is plain: nothing. Since her parents emigrated from Poland in 1910, she has lived in Brooklyn. It is where she went to school, got her first job sewing ($3 a week), where she married, raised a family and bought her daughter a home. Julia, 90 years old and widowed, is mentally sharp and too vigorous to sit home all day, but she can no longer go out walking in the winter or at night. Julia hates to ask her grandchildren on Long Island for favors, and her daughter is now 70 and blind.</p>
        <p>So every weekday, a minibus operated by the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged provides her with round-trip transportation to the Williamsburg Senior Center, where she enjoys a hot lunch, planned activities and the company of friends. The minibus, which serves senior citizens of all races and creeds, is just one of many programs for the elderly supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Eighty-year-old Minnie knows how easily isolation can overtake those growing old. The onset of arthritis and a heart condition forced Minnie to become homebound, sadly alone with her memories. Now, with access to the minibus, an Irving Berlin song or a life story is readily shared with peers. "We tell each other what's on our hearts," Minnie explains. "Our children moved away. Both parents work today, so they have no time for us. They have a better life," Minnie adds, her voice brimming with pride. "We paved the way for them. But now we're very, very lonesome people."</p>
        <p>For retirees who years ago decided to remain in the city, and who now have outlived spouses and friends, living alone in decayed neighborhoods has brought unanticipated sorrows and fears. The recession squeezes New York's oldest residents particularly hard, as purchasing power shrinks on fixed incomes and the interest on life savings declines.</p>
        <p>Throughout this year, The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund will rescue tens of thousands of the city's elderly from hunger and loneliness. Even a small donation can provide a wealth of comfort and care for the isolated and infirm. The holiday season is past but the 80th appeal continues. All who can are asked to help.</p>
        <p>Tax-deductible contributions should be sent to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund, Post Office Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
