<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Like Ike: Recalling a Human Leader</title>
    <meta content="30TVCOVER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1585396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selleck, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisenhower, Dwight David (1890-1969)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ike: Countdown to D-Day (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D8163EF933A05756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Like Ike: Recalling a Human Leader</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of television program Ike: Countdown to D-Day, to be broadcast on Memorial Day, on A&amp;E; Tom Selleck plays Dwight D Eisenhower; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE run-up to the invasion of Normandy plays out in a miasma of rain, fog and cigarette smoke in ''Ike: Countdown to D-Day,'' which will be telecast tomorrow, Memorial Day, at 8 p.m. in anticipation of the 60th anniversary of the invasions on June 6.</p>
        <p>Starring Tom Selleck as Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower, the two-hour A&amp;E movie begins in December 1943, as Eisenhower persuades Prime Minister Winston Churchill to make him supreme commander of the Allied Expeditionary Force preparing to invade Europe, and ends with Eisenhower receiving the first reports on the invasion. It is a war movie with no war. It is, instead, a study in leadership, decision making and moral clarity -- how one man had to cut through the fog and smoke and mist to decide whether, when and where to put tens of thousands of lives at risk in what would become the decisive battle of World War II and a metaphor for virtuous sacrifice in a noble cause.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE run-up to the invasion of Normandy plays out in a miasma of rain, fog and cigarette smoke in ''Ike: Countdown to D-Day,'' which will be telecast tomorrow, Memorial Day, at 8 p.m. in anticipation of the 60th anniversary of the invasions on June 6.</p>
        <p>Starring Tom Selleck as Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower, the two-hour A&amp;E movie begins in December 1943, as Eisenhower persuades Prime Minister Winston Churchill to make him supreme commander of the Allied Expeditionary Force preparing to invade Europe, and ends with Eisenhower receiving the first reports on the invasion. It is a war movie with no war. It is, instead, a study in leadership, decision making and moral clarity -- how one man had to cut through the fog and smoke and mist to decide whether, when and where to put tens of thousands of lives at risk in what would become the decisive battle of World War II and a metaphor for virtuous sacrifice in a noble cause.</p>
        <p>The creation of the film dates back to the mid-1990's, when Stephanie Germain went to Lionel Chetwynd with the idea of doing something on Eisenhower. Mr. Chetwynd, who is credited as screenwriter and one of three executive producers of the film (Ms. Germain and Delia Fine are the others), said he was interested in a discrete slice of Eisenhower's life rather than a standard biography.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to find one small aperture, which stands for the whole beast,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He found it in the preparations for D-Day, particularly the 72 hours leading up to the invasion. The script was kicked around until, with the 60th anniversary looming, Mr. Selleck was recruited to play Ike and the project began to come together. It was filmed in New Zealand in February and early March in four weeks.</p>
        <p>Known best for his role as a private detective in the television series ''Magnum, P.I.,'' Mr. Selleck is hardly a dead ringer for the bald, avuncular Eisenhower. Even he was a bit puzzled when asked if he was interested in doing the movie. ''My agent called and said it was going to be offered, and my first reaction was: 'You're kidding me. I'll read it, but what are they thinking?'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chetwynd, a longtime friend of Mr. Selleck, said he was less interested in physical similarities and more concerned with capturing Eisenhower's character. ''First, I wanted an actor with extraordinary range, not just a guy with a bald head,'' he said. ''Second, I wanted someone who could convey what Eisenhower brought to the table, both his confidence and his self-doubt. Tom's the kind of guy you can play poker with over the phone. He's an honest, decent guy who understands the reasons why you would want to make this film.''</p>
        <p>Selleck went on to dye his hair gray and shave the top, making him a credible physical Ike. To prepare for the role, he read books like Stephen Ambrose's ''Supreme Commander: The War Years of General Dwight D. Eisenhower'' and Eisenhower's own ''At Ease: Stories I Tell to Friends.''</p>
        <p>He also read the memoir by Eisenhower's son John and spent an hour listening to him talk about his father. ''He really loved his dad, and one thing that he said, and he meant it as praise, was that it must be really hard for an actor to undertake someone so ordinary,'' said Mr. Selleck. ''And that was a big key for me. Because Ike was an Iowa farm boy, son of a pacifist, pretty much, and -- I don't want to make it a cliché -- an ordinary man put in an extraordinary situation.''</p>
        <p>So his Ike is a figure of great natural charm and tact, able to play off the substantial egos of the other generals. He's tough when he has to be and, above all, human. Mr. Selleck said he looked for private moments when Eisenhower revealed what was churning inside him in a way that he could not in public. But one of the film's emotional high points is a group scene in which Ike goes out to banter with a company of paratroopers after making the excruciating decision to deploy them as close as possible to the German lines, where the risk is greatest.</p>
        <p>The film has the appeal of both history and American myth. Ike does the right thing, he does it in the right way, and even his decision about the paratroopers works out well.</p>
        <p>Make no mistake. This is a movie about the events of 60 years ago, featuring legendary generals and historical figures like Omar Bradley (James Remar), Walter Bedell Smith (Timothy Bottoms), George S. Patton (Gerald McRaney), Winston Churchill (Ian Mune), Charles de Gaulle (George Shevtsov) and Bernard Law Montgomery (Bruce Phillips). Still, with a more contemporary invasion hanging in the balance, with its own momentous decisions and decision makers, it's hard to view the film without being reminded of its modern-day parallels. Precisely what it says about them is something that even the people who made the film don't quite agree on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chetwynd is one of Hollywood's most prominent conservatives; his credits include ''D.C. 9/11: Times of Crisis,'' a glowing docudrama about President Bush's response to the Sept. 11 attacks. And it's difficult not to read the movie, at least in part, in the context of the current day -- from the portrayal of Charles de Gaulle as an arrogant fop to Eisenhower's speeches about God, sacrifice and liberation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chetwynd says he does not want to politicize the film, but ''if you're satisfied with the political predicate laid down for the war in Iraq, then, yeah, you have a lot to learn from this film.'' If you're not satisfied with the argument, he added, the film is still ''damn good entertainment.''</p>
        <p>The director, Robert Harmon, said that he and Mr. Chetwynd disagreed about the war in Iraq and that he would be upset if anyone saw this film as any kind of parable about the current war. The most striking difference between then and now, he said, is that World War II was fought with a vivid sense of national unity and moral clarity that has not characterized the wars since. ''If anything, you view it with almost a wistful look back on the relative simplicity of the issues,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Selleck said there was no political agenda behind the film. ''My guess is if people see anything analogous in our present situation,'' he said, ''it will just validate the preconceived beliefs they had in the first place.''</p>
        <p>In the end, he said, this is a movie about Eisenhower, his time and the decisions he made that changed history.</p>
        <p>''I came away with a renewed appreciation of the burden of leadership,'' he said. ''And Eisenhower may very well have been the perfect person at the right time.''</p>
        <p>IKE: Countdown To D-Day  Monday at 8 p.m. on A&amp;E</p>
        <p>On the cover: Tom Selleck as Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower.</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
