<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Black Mountain Magic</title>
    <meta content="t--t--p128--133--asheville--" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Travel Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="128" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/19/travel/tmagazine/19ts-asheville.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1747750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Carolina</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0DD1231F93AA25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Black Mountain Magic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Arts and Crafts in the Blue Ridge Mountains</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wells Tower</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before spring has fully broken, and the streets of Asheville, N.C., are not yet thronged with visitors, the town radiates a comfortable desolation. Even the surrounding Blue Ridge Mountains look neglected and dozy, like a mussed lavender coverlet on an unmade bed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once a destination for consumptives and the avant-garde, Asheville, N.C. is now a stop on the art circuit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before spring has fully broken, and the streets of Asheville, N.C., are not yet thronged with visitors, the town radiates a comfortable desolation. Even the surrounding Blue Ridge Mountains look neglected and dozy, like a mussed lavender coverlet on an unmade bed.</p>
        <p>When I pulled into town one weekend evening, the streets were empty, and I found the front desk at the Best Western hotel abandoned. After a full 10 minutes, the clerk materialized, looking as if I had stirred her from a nap. When I got into my room, at last, I was greeted by a proud and handsome hair curling from the bathroom sink. It was placed there deliberately, I supposed, by a housekeeper in a spell of winter doldrums, and I was grateful for its affirming message: ''I am still here.''</p>
        <p>I don't live very far from Asheville, and I have always enjoyed the place. Asheville appeals to well-heeled vacationers with an appetite for boutiques and clean air, and also to nouveau bohemians lured by its long-standing renown as an upland hearth for beatnikry. The trouble is that in the clement seasons, it's hard to negotiate Asheville's streets without fighting your way through crowds of people in either jester hats or monogrammed cuff links. So I decided to stop by well ahead of the season, when the town wasn't busy with the work of endearing itself to visiting wallets.</p>
        <p>Asheville has been attracting travelers in quantity for well over a century. Most of its early tourists were sufferers from consumption, gout or rheumatism seeking relief in the clean, highland ether and nearby hot springs, whose curative effects local entrepreneurs touted profitably. In 1935, respiratory troubles brought F. Scott Fitzgerald there for an extended stay, though according to local reports, he mostly devoted himself to getting drunk. His wife, Zelda, was a familiar guest at an Asheville mental hospital, where she famously burned to death when it caught fire in 1948. The novelist Thomas Wolfe grew up here, unhappily, in his mother's boarding house on Spruce Street. Consumptives were unwelcome in Mrs. Wolfe's rooms.</p>
        <p>As the tuberculosis age subsided, connoisseurs of rural Americana descended on Asheville in search of mountain crafts -- quilts, woodwork, earthenware -- that the region brimmed with because the inhabitants were so impoverished that they had to make by hand what they could not buy. In the 1930's, with the founding of Black Mountain College, a short distance up the road, the local artscape grew more glamorous and fraught. The school was an experiment in progressive education, and it attracted among its faculty forward-thinking luminaries like John Cage, Josef Albers, Willem de Kooning, Merce Cunningham, Buckminster Fuller and Robert Motherwell. Albert Einstein, Walter Gropius and John Dewey sat on the college's advisory board.</p>
        <p>In 1956, after 23 years in operation, the college shut its doors. Walking the streets of Asheville today, one sees little afterglow of the aesthetic firestorm of the Black Mountain days. On Broadway Street, opposite the Namaste Yoga and Healing Center, is the Black Mountain College Museum and Arts Center, a storefront exhibition space dedicated chiefly to wistful celebrations of former students and faculty members. Other than that, it seems as if the creative impulse has softened over the years, and instead of storming the confines of convention, it drifts in gentler directions, toward beeswax candles and tender-hued watercolors of sun-dappled lanes.</p>
        <p>A two-hour walking survey of downtown galleries turned up an inconceivable number of paintings of trees, rendered in assorted intensities of autumn splendor; sculptures of trout, bear, a bloodthirsty-looking possum and a hippopotamus wearing a halo; bright and frangible arrays of glass craft; and enough clay artifacts -- both traditional and neopsychedelic -- to supply a small nation with hand-turned crockery.</p>
        <p>Street for street, it would be difficult to find a rural urb more amply stocked with local-scale charisma than Asheville.2 You find none of the vacant storefronts of cracked plate glass that in recent decades have become a defining architectural motif of many small Southern towns. There are at least two good bookstores and dozens of restaurants, many of them excellent, where during the tourist industry's season of repose you can promptly find a seat. (Go to Table, on College Street. If the duck and white bean soup is on the menu, have two bowls of it at least.)</p>
        <p>Vitality returned to Asheville only recently. Following the Great Depression, the downtown succumbed to an enduring blight, and much of its collection of Art Deco and Romanesque-style buildings lay vacant and shuttered until the late 1970's, when a population of artists and craftspeople moved in, seeking cheap lofts. But in the face of an increasingly pressurized real estate market, Asheville's most concentrated colony of artists can be found near the banks of the French Broad River, which slides greenly through the west side of town.</p>
        <p>To reach the River District, as the area is known, you take Clingman Avenue out of downtown, down a steepish grade superintended by viny kudzu ghosts. At the bottom of the hill, you turn left onto Roberts Street at a gray-painted brick building, where a gilt-lettered sign reads: ''Mr Gray says Mind your bourgeois table manner but do not forget your proletarian bite.'' The district is an assemblage of attractively distressed, previously forsaken structures from Asheville's bygone industrial age: a cotton mill, a tannery, a gas plant, a brewery, produce storage sheds, a concrete block plant, an ice factory, etc.; now they are mostly lofts and studios in various states of rehabilitation. One hundred or so local artists work and, in some cases, live there; many of them do not mind if you stop in for a visit.</p>
        <p>One afternoon I visited Lisa Shenouda, a 28-year-old photographer and video artist who works in a cozy, warrenlike studio in the upstairs of a former candle factory, within earshot of a kennel of yowling dogs. Shenouda, whose parents are Egyptian, moved to Asheville four years ago after graduating from Cornell University and not entirely getting by in Brooklyn. ''I thought I was going to go back to New York after a couple of years, but I realized I'd have to give up space and time,'' she said, metaphysically. ''So I stayed.''</p>
        <p>The photographs that Shenouda showed me were mostly of kewpie dolls in whimsical tableaus: kewpie dolls lazing in a field of marshmallows and hoary Sno Ball treats; kewpie dolls marauding through a thicket of grass; kewpie dolls staring blankly from the shade of cocktail umbrellas. She also screened two brief videos from her series titled ''Suburban Nightmares.'' The first showed a woman in a hysterical confrontation with her Tupperware collection. In the second, another unhappy woman attempted to bake a cake but accidentally baked a baby instead.</p>
        <p>Some of the River District's contemporary artists harbor open resentment for work that they feel rests complacently on the craftsy laurels that have defined the Asheville art scene for the last hundred years or so, but they coexist peacefully with the craftspeople there.3 The neighborhood is home to woodworking, textile and ceramics shops, and also a new, improbable addition to the home-wrought goods community: Blue Ridge Biofuels, an outfit selling hand-produced diesel fuel, made of reprocessed vegetable oil salvaged from the deep-fat fryers of local restaurants.</p>
        <p>Between Roberts Street and a set of railroad tracks is the Wedge Building, a renovated produce warehouse, where two dozen or so artists currently toil. The Wedge's owner is John Payne, a gaunt man of 56 with a tidy white goatee and hair the color of old piano keys. ''I make marionettes,'' he told me one afternoon. Given the scale of Payne's puppets, that would be like Robert Smithson, the creator of ''Spiral Jetty,'' saying, ''I fool around with dirt.'' Payne led me down to the far end of his studio, where a steel crow the size of a Piper Cub was balanced on a perch made of flagpole-gauge brass tubing. It had a head like a sharpened watermelon, eyes of a cold, hostile cast and a 16-foot wingspan feathered with black steel mesh.</p>
        <p>Payne stepped behind me and grabbed a pair of handles, fitted to cables that were in turn attached to several joints on the crow's anatomy. The huge wings unfurled, raising a screeching, clanking ruckus that was fearsome to the ears. The bird swung violently on its perch, eyes aswivel. With its beak gnashing an uncomfortable distance from my nose, I felt a sudden sympathy for those saltwater minnows you see swimming vulnerably in shoreline pools.4</p>
        <p>The next morning, I visited with Lauren Gibbes and Jason Weatherspoon, who live and work several doors down from Payne. Gibbes is a fine-boned woman of 26 with long brown hair and large dark eyes. The space she shares with Weatherspoon is a large brick warehouselike enclosure with concrete floors, a sleeping loft and a wood stove behind a wall of bare two-by-fours.</p>
        <p>The paintings that Gibbes had on display were deft, faintly arch references to the color-saturated, low-glamour world of 1970's television. They were mostly diptychs and triptychs, salvaged from screen shots of retro game shows and photographs that she had come across online: a teenage cheerleader reclining in the summer grass, her eyes obscured by a glittering bar of diamond dust; a woman in a straining bodice, gazing with dark amour at the adjacent panel, which showed a walnut-colored thoroughbred, glistening as if it had been dipped in baby oil; a contestant on ''The Match Game'' caught in a slack-jawed reverie under the studio lights, emanating a grim, jaundiced radiance.</p>
        <p>Then Weatherspoon, who is a co-owner of the biodiesel facility, walked in, and we had a look at his sculptures, of which there were a few dozen, crowding a concrete slab on one end of the room. Weatherspoon, 30, wore his hair pulled back in a ponytail, and had a goatee twisted into a clutch of little stubs. He sculptures ceramic figures, beautifully wrought but far darker than what tends to sell in downtown galleries. We looked at his sculpture of a squalling, grotesquely obese baby with its face sinking into its torso flab. ''It's my new American cherub,'' he said. He showed me a near-life-size couple in cross-legged copulation, each participant bald and painted in a lustrous coat of candy-apple-red auto paint, the man holding out a beseeching palm and grimacing, despite the circumstances, with deep displeasure. He also showed me his reimagining of the Buddha, recast as a thunderously fertile, ecstatic woman with a gigantic bosom spilling out of her arms, and a second bosom on top of her head, but instead of nipples, each cranio-breast was punctuated by a set of male sexual anatomy.</p>
        <p>When we'd finished the tour, Weatherspoon bent down to pet a piebald Chihuahua that was scratching at his pant leg. He and Gibbes laughed and stared at the floor and talked about how, while contemporary art was beginning to find its place in Asheville, it was still rough going for people making art that wouldn't necessarily brighten someone's living room. Weatherspoon sighed. ''It's tough being a contemporary artist in the South,'' he said. ''We had a bunch of tourists in here the other day. They looked around and looked around, and after a while they said, 'Don't y'all do any pictures of trees?'''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
