<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWN WITH: William Kennedy; Albany as It Is, as It Wa And as It Is Being Imagined</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, WILLIAM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">VERY OLD BONES (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA103DF934A15756C0A964958260" item-length="1368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWN WITH: William Kennedy; Albany as It Is, as It Wa And as It Is Being Imagined</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH KOLBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is after midnight, and William Kennedy and some of his old pals have just closed the Boulevard, a dim, cavernous saloon sandwiched between the tire outlet stores on Central Avenue. His pals drift off, pleading fatigue; Mr. Kennedy still has a few hours to go.</p>
        <p>All evening he has been reminiscing about his favorite topic, old Albany, home to the crooks, bums and scoundrels -- real and fictional -- who populate his novels. Among the most colorful is Jack (Legs) Diamond, and in spite of -- or perhaps because of -- the late hour, he decides to take his vistor to see where Albany's most notorious bootlegger was murdered. He can point to the exact spot where Legs' luck ran out: a second-floor bedroom in a yellow-brick row house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is after midnight, and William Kennedy and some of his old pals have just closed the Boulevard, a dim, cavernous saloon sandwiched between the tire outlet stores on Central Avenue. His pals drift off, pleading fatigue; Mr. Kennedy still has a few hours to go.</p>
        <p>All evening he has been reminiscing about his favorite topic, old Albany, home to the crooks, bums and scoundrels -- real and fictional -- who populate his novels. Among the most colorful is Jack (Legs) Diamond, and in spite of -- or perhaps because of -- the late hour, he decides to take his vistor to see where Albany's most notorious bootlegger was murdered. He can point to the exact spot where Legs' luck ran out: a second-floor bedroom in a yellow-brick row house.</p>
        <p>The room is directly above Mr. Kennedy's office. He bought the old house several years ago in a gesture that is almost too obvious a metaphor for his relationship with this city's seedy past. Mounting the stairs, he explains how Legs was sleeping when three shots to his head permamently interrupted his dreams. Mr. Kennedy opens the closet to point out a patch of the original wallpaper -- brown with pink primroses -- that has been preserved in Legs' memory.</p>
        <p>Back downstairs, sitting with a glass of Irish whiskey and a sheaf of Legs Diamond clippings, he said: "This may seem like an obsession, but it is not. This is the residue of an obsession."</p>
        <p>Albany has been William Kennedy's home for most of his 64 years; still, wherever he goes he finds the city fascinating. In a desolate spot under a highway overpass he recognizes the heart of the city's old red-light district, the Gut, where mobsters went for a good time. Where a stretch of office buildings now stands he spies the gaudy nightclubs where showgirls and their dates hung out. His own chosen haunts -- restaurants and bars where he is on a first-name basis with the waiters -- are places whose metamorphoses he recounts with the enthusiasm of an archeologist let loose on the Acropolis.</p>
        <p>Cafe Capriccio, an intimate restaurant tucked away in a nondescript section of downtown Albany, counts Mr. Kennedy as a regular, and it is there that many of his evenings, including this one, begin. "This was LoPresti's grocery," he said, heading into the restaurant for dinner. "To our right, that was the old Italian neighborhood.</p>
        <p>"There were two theaters right here," he continued, gesturing toward a stretch of parking lot. "And one saloon after another, with shows and vaudeville acts and dancing. I remember when this was a wide-open city, an all-night city."</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Kennedy is out of town a lot, traveling on behalf of his new book, "Very Old Bones" (Viking). So when he showed up at Capriccio's, there was more commotion than usual. A trio of waiters rushed over to greet "Billy." They hovered over his table, a corner booth, just as their predecessors in an earlier, more flamboyant Albany might have hovered over a big-spending hood.</p>
        <p>Except for Gov. Mario M. Cuomo -- a friend of his -- Mr. Kennedy is probably the city's only celebrity, but unlike Governor Cuomo, he is not a particularly imposing presence. He is of average height and average build, and he speaks like a man who would really prefer to be listening. All the attention seemed vaguely embarrassing to him.</p>
        <p>"Very Old Bones," Mr. Kennedy's sixth novel, is a further exploration of the Phelan clan that drank its way through "Ironweed" and "Billy Phelan's Greatest Game." The book has received glowing reviews, and the author could be forgiven for reclining on his laurels for a few months. But he is already ruminating out loud on his next project, a novel about Albany's infamous Democratic machine.</p>
        <p>Despite its dim reputation, Mr. Kennedy talks about the machine in tones edging toward admiration. "Rockefeller tried to destroy it," he said over a bottle of red wine and a plate of ravioli. "Dewey tried to destroy it. Nobody could ever destroy it. I know that the political life of the machine has got 50,000 stories, and I'm going to tell a couple of them."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy grimaces at the word "autobiography." His novels are not about his family, he insists; rather they are about "people who have traits similar to all the people I've ever known." Still, his impression of the machine comes from intimate blood relations.</p>
        <p>"My whole family was part of it," he said. "My granduncle worked for the city in various ways. My father ended up as a deputy sheriff. My mother's first cousin drove the Black Maria, the van they hauled prisoners in. Later, when he got too fat, they made him a guard. Everybody kicked in. It was very well regulated."</p>
        <p>As he warms to his topic he speaks with the loose syntax of his characters: "I love that whole era. I suppose it was political evil; they stole elections. But the people got jobs and work -- they didn't make much money, but they had jobs. I remember one guy inherited a lot of money, but he drank himself out of it and wound up cutting grass behind the school in North Albany. It wasn't quite the dole; it was a job. Two-hundred and thirty-five janitors in the Albany County Courthouse -- that was the kind of thing they were capable of."</p>
        <p>In the opening to "O, Albany!" his only nonfiction work about the city, Mr. Kennedy says he is writing "not as a booster of Albany, which I am, nor as an apologist for the city, which I sometimes am, but rather as a person whose imagination has become fused with a single place." It is a tribute to Mr. Kennedy's imagination that it has come, in small ways at least, to reshape the city itself.</p>
        <p>The Boulevard, for example, where he stopped for a drink after dinner, exists because of his novel "Ironweed." When the movie version was being filmed, producers transformed an empty building into a Depression-era bar for the scene where Meryl Streep, playing Helen Archer, makes her singing appearance. This faux bar was then turned into a real bar, with the dusky light and dim murals of the movie version left intact. On the walls there are photographs of Mr. Kennedy, who played a patron in the movie's bar scene.</p>
        <p>"They kept giving us this fake beer to drink," he said, recalling his days as an extra. "It was terrible."</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Kennedy likes to describe Albany as "a state of mind," he began his career as a novelist escaping rather than pursuing the city. After growing up here and graduating from Siena College here and then doing a four-year stint as a reporter with The Albany Times-Union, he was tired of the place -- "I didn't think there were any girls in town," he said -- and went looking for adventure in Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>There he worked at The Puerto Rico World Journal and The San Juan Star, married his wife, Dana Sosa, and wrote short stories about the island and its inhabitants. "I didn't think about Albany," he said. "I was trying to write from some abstract place, some exotic place, Cuban revolutionaries, Puerto Rican transients, Puerto Rican artists. Those were O.K. stories, but the grounding of the stories I wrote afterward was so much more susbtantial."</p>
        <p>Finally, he started work on a novel set in Albany, "The Angels and the Sparrows." The book never found a publisher. But it introduced the author to the Phelans and it showed him who his fictional friends were.</p>
        <p>In 1963, his father got sick and Mr. Kennedy returned to Albany. He went back to The Times-Union for several years, then got a teaching job at the State University at Albany, all the while writing stories. His big break came in 1983 with the publication of "Ironweed." The book won the Pulitzer Prize; the author received a MacArthur "genius" award.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Kennedy has come a long way in his last three decades in Albany, he has not moved much at all. He still lives in a rambling farmhouse outside the city that he and his wife bought on their return from Puerto Rico. He still goes to bars with the same friends, though many of the old bars are gone. And he still writes about the same endearing inebriates.</p>
        <p>"Albany is my town because I know it," he said "That's what's important. It's where I come from. If I came from somewhere else I might be the Minneapolis writer or the Buffalo writer. I think of it as a gift."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
