<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Freshman's Star Power</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="821582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDSCLAW, CHAMIQUE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLES, CHARLIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D81339F93AA35752C0A960958260" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Freshman's Star Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLES, CHARLIE</byline>
      <dateline>KNOXVILLE, Tenn., Jan. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the age of 11, Chamique Holdsclaw was thrown to the lions, competing on the playgrounds of New York against boys who were often older than she was. By the time she was a teen-ager, she was turning heads with her play at Christ the  King High School in Queens and stirring curiosity about how long it would take for her to make an impact on the college level.</p>
        <p>Not long at all, it turns out. Less than halfway through her freshman season  at the University of Tennessee -- the most storied women's basketball program in the country -- the 6-foot-2-inch Holdsclaw is the team's leading scorer. If anything, she is almost too good for a freshman, for she now has to balance the  ability that makes her the team's go-to person with a modesty that still has her looking to older teammates to take charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the age of 11, Chamique Holdsclaw was thrown to the lions, competing on the playgrounds of New York against boys who were often older than she was. By the time she was a teen-ager, she was turning heads with her play at Christ the  King High School in Queens and stirring curiosity about how long it would take for her to make an impact on the college level.</p>
        <p>Not long at all, it turns out. Less than halfway through her freshman season  at the University of Tennessee -- the most storied women's basketball program in the country -- the 6-foot-2-inch Holdsclaw is the team's leading scorer. If anything, she is almost too good for a freshman, for she now has to balance the  ability that makes her the team's go-to person with a modesty that still has her looking to older teammates to take charge.</p>
        <p>It's an awkward conflict and it came into view last Saturday, when the national champion Connecticut Huskies defeated the Lady Vols on their home court, 59-53, partly because Tennessee made only one field goal in the game's last 6 minutes 40 seconds. For Tennessee, which dropped to 11-2, it was the first loss at home in four years.</p>
        <p>"I made kind of a freshman mistake," Holdsclaw, a forward, said. "My nature is not to be a pushy person. And I kind of just watched there when we fell behind, thinking the upperclassmen would help us come back, instead of getting in there myself. I was like a spectator when I should have been doing all I could, too."</p>
        <p>Someone who noticed was Connecticut Coach Geno Auriemma.</p>
        <p>"For the most ballyhooed freshman in the country, she seems to be doing a great job of blending in," he said afterward. "But you see, blending in and taking charge are two things that don't mix. She probably felt like taking charge, but in a program like Tennessee's she was probably thinking some upperclassman would do it."</p>
        <p>Still, Auriemma has no doubt that Holdsclaw is destined for collegiate greatness.</p>
        <p>"She has everything to be great," he said. "And she hasn't scratched the surface on what she's capable of doing. Her shooting is good and it's going to get better. She rebounds well now, and I only see it getting better. And she has tremendous savvy for a freshman."</p>
        <p>The savvy, in part, comes from those years in the playground, where Holdsclaw took every contest against those older boys to heart.</p>
        <p>"That made me tougher, because the boys play a more physical game," she said. "When I first got out there, I was actually horrible. Nobody wanted to pick me. As I got better, everybody started wanting me."</p>
        <p>It was on the playground, Holdsclaw said, that she developed a knack of tipping in offensive rebounds, rather than trying to bring the ball down and then go back up only to have the shot stuffed.</p>
        <p>"After you get a lot of shots blocked, you realize you have to get the ball back up there quicker," she said.</p>
        <p>And it was in the playground that she worked hard on her dribbling and outside shooting because she didn't want to be labeled as simply someone who had to play close to the basket. "I wanted to bring some versatility to my game," she said.</p>
        <p>Which she undoubtedly has. At Tennessee, which has won three national titles  and is hungry for a fourth, Holdsclaw leads the team in scoring (15.2 average) and rebounds (9.3), and is drawing comparisons to Bridgette Gordon, who set the  school career scoring record from 1985-88.</p>
        <p>"Chamique Holdsclaw is a special talent and a special individual," said Tennessee Coach Pat Summitt, in her 22d season. "I've not had a freshman come in and have the numbers across the board that Chamique has."</p>
        <p>Michelle Marciniak, the Tennessee senior point guard, said the most difficult thing for any player to master under Summitt is her defensive system.</p>
        <p>"It takes a year to learn and a year to practice," Marciniak said. "By the third year, you're ready to execute it. Coach is only rarely satisfied. But I've told Chamique several times that we're all proud of the way she's come in here and handled the role she's been put in.</p>
        <p>"Besides her talent -- and she can flat out score -- I see something special  in Chamique in how badly she wants to learn."</p>
        <p>Still, beyond everything else, there is that pressure to take charge. "The coaches tend to get on me," Holdsclaw said. "They've said to me, 'You don't have freshman skills and you don't have a freshman body, so we're not going to treat  you like a freshman.'</p>
        <p>"Sometimes I think, 'Oh my, I've got three more years to have to deal with this.' But I realize it's helping me to get better. I'm real happy with my decision. I like to meet people, and I've met people from all over."</p>
        <p>Some of them she meets right on the court. Connecticut's Nykesha Sales, assigned to guard Holdsclaw during much of Saturday's game, took particular notice of Holdsclaw's ability to rebound and drive to the basket.</p>
        <p>"It's kind of scary to think how good she can be," Sales said. "She's playing well now, and just imagine when she gets really comfortable out there."</p>
        <p>Imagine, indeed. Holdsclaw was recruited by Connecticut, among other schools, and right now she could be teaming up with Jennifer Rizzotti on the court. Who wouldn't want to contemplate that combination?</p>
        <p>But it won't happen. Holdsclaw is in Tennessee, happy with her choice. She is wearing No. 23, in recognition of both Michael Jordan and the 23d Psalm, which starts, "The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want."</p>
        <p>"When I was in the eighth grade, my grandmother told me how important that verse can be in your life," Holdsclaw said. "I always remembered that."</p>
        <p>It came in handy as the college recruiters came knocking on the door. It comes in handy now, in this season of quick transition.</p>
        <p>"After everything I've been through in my life," she said, "I feel I can handle about anything."</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
