<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="821357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA1339F93AA35752C0A960958260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavy Snowfall Buries More Retailer Hopes The blizzard slammed retailers in the Northeast, after they were already reeling from a grim Christmas season. Department stores, shopping malls, specialty shops and local merchants pulled down the gates and went home, some as early as Sunday afternoon, as blustery winds swept shoppers and millions of their dollars from the troubled industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heavy Snowfall Buries More Retailer Hopes The blizzard slammed retailers in the Northeast, after they were already reeling from a grim Christmas season. Department stores, shopping malls, specialty shops and local merchants pulled down the gates and went home, some as early as Sunday afternoon, as blustery winds swept shoppers and millions of their dollars from the troubled industry.</p>
        <p>But insurance claims for things like roof damage, frozen pipes and damaged cars also are imminent. The 20-state storm of March 1993, the fifth-most-costly  catastrophe, resulted in $1.75 billion of claims. [Page 1.]</p>
        <p>Huge Chip Growth in '95</p>
        <p>The semiconductor market grew by a remarkable 40 percent in 1995, to $154.7 billion in revenue, according to a report by Dataquest, a market research firm.  The industry benefited from the enormous applications in all types of electronics, not just personal computers. Another good year is predicted. Intel  continued to lead the industry; its revenue totaled $13.8 billion in 1995. [46.]</p>
        <p>Globalstar Shines</p>
        <p>Lockheed Martin could not agree on a price for Loral's 31 percent interest in Globalstar, which plans to provide telephone service by bouncing signals off 48  low-orbiting satellites. But stock market investors seized on the company's new  prominence, driving its share price up sharply. [50.]</p>
        <p>During the final stages of the negotiations with Loral, it appears that some options traders got word of what was going on. Floyd Norris: Market Place. [52.]</p>
        <p>Trump Makes Headway</p>
        <p>In a sign that his financial recovery is gathering speed, Donald J. Trump moved  to fold his Taj Mahal Casino Resort in Atlantic City into his publicly traded casino company. That company, Trump Hotels, plans to attract new investors. [50.]</p>
        <p>Flat Panel Maker Is Sold  Matsushita agreed to acquire an American pioneer in the effort to develop flat panel display screens. The American company, Plasmaco, apparently needed money to its work on notebook computer screens and wall-hanging televisions. [59.]</p>
        <p>Small Movement on Budget  Republican leaders edged much closer to President Clinton's spending proposals for Medicare and Medicaid, raising faint hope of a budget deal. But leaders on both sides suggested that they have more or less reached the limits of their ability to compromise. And it is not at all clear that the remaining differences in these programs, or on issues ranging from tax cuts to welfare spending, are close to resolution. [8.] The idea of discarding the elaborate Federal tax system in favor of a simple flat tax is about to become a full-fledged issue in the Presidential campaign. [7.]</p>
        <p>Alcoa Shares Drop  Alcoa shares fell when the company reported strong earnings that were nonetheless below Wall Street expectations. [62.]</p>
        <p>Investment in Mexican Hotels  Morgan Stanley and the Mexican hotel operator Grupo Posadas announced plans to invest roughly $200 million over the next 18 months to buy a number of Mexican hotels. The money represents the first major influx of capital into the Mexican  tourism industry since the peso was devalued in 1994. [59.]</p>
        <p>Heyward Promoted at CBS  CBS named Andrew Heyward, a longtime producer of news programs, to head CBS News, which has languished. [51.]</p>
        <p>A New Logo In South Africa  The national airline of South Africa is forming an unusual partnership to develop a revamped look for everything from the logos on the tails of the planes to the color scheme of the ticket folders. Many of the changes are felt to be necessary because of associations of its previous designs to the apartheid system. The partners tackling that challenging task are Diefenbach Elkins, an American corporate identity consulting company, and a South African advertising  agency. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [51.]</p>
        <p>Bond Yields Steady  Bond prices showed little change as the storm kept many traders from getting to  work. [62.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
