<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 14 Bronx Workers, a Small, Small Token</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTIN, DOUGLAS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT NEW YORK (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D71638F932A25757C0A964958260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 14 Bronx Workers, a Small, Small Token</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Douglas Martin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTIN, DOUGLAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Great Moments Room in Yankee Stadium is adorned with pictures of heroes -- Ruth, Gehrig, DiMaggio, Joe Louis. On Tuesday morning, they will be joined by even bigger heroes, most of whom would otherwise have been unsung.</p>
        <p>For the 16th straight year, New York City employees who work in the Bronx and who demonstrated valor will receive gold-plated medals. They are based on a medal of valor designed for the Police Department by Tiffany's in 1877. The stylish "NY" on that medal later became the symbol of the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Great Moments Room in Yankee Stadium is adorned with pictures of heroes -- Ruth, Gehrig, DiMaggio, Joe Louis. On Tuesday morning, they will be joined by even bigger heroes, most of whom would otherwise have been unsung.</p>
        <p>For the 16th straight year, New York City employees who work in the Bronx and who demonstrated valor will receive gold-plated medals. They are based on a medal of valor designed for the Police Department by Tiffany's in 1877. The stylish "NY" on that medal later became the symbol of the Yankees.</p>
        <p>If past years are indicative, crowds of uniformed police officers, firefighters and sanitation workers, among others, will form a raucous standing-room-only crowd as they applaud 14 colleagues. Beaming wives and crying babies will be in ample supply.</p>
        <p>The awards were started by New York Telephone, which unsuccesfully tried to expand them to other boroughs and then abandoned them altogether several years ago. Other Bronx businesses took up the slack. It seemed a shame to abandon one of the few expressions of public gratitude to those who risk so much.</p>
        <p>"At least it's something," declared Edward F. Arrigoni, chairman of New York Bus Service, one sponsor.</p>
        <p>The honorees are nominated by their own agencies for heroism, either on or off duty. They emblematize a commitment to public service many people think has vanished altogether. It hasn't.</p>
        <p>Michael Finer wears his maternal grandfather's platinum ring, signifying completion of his grandfather's 20th year in the Fire Department. Mr. Finer himself became a fireman 14 years ago after six years in the Police Department. It wasn't holding the head of another policeman in his lap as blood poured from the shotgun holes in his neck that moved him to seek other work. The erratic hours were straining his marriage.</p>
        <p>Whether his idea of a change was to begin rushing into fires for a living is at least problematical. He is being honored for pulling another firefighter to safety seconds before a tenement exploded.</p>
        <p>He didn't sleep for a while after that, the same thing that happens when a colleague dies. Why does he keep on keeping on?</p>
        <p>"I still ideally believe I can help," he answered. "Don't ask me why sometimes."</p>
        <p>Sam Gibbs was working the night shift as a sanitation worker when he and his partner, Mickey May, saw a burning building. While Mr. May called for help, Mr. Gibbs caught a woman who had leapt from a second-story landing, then raced inside to rescue her child.</p>
        <p>"I just did what I thought was right," Mr. Gibbs said.</p>
        <p>The worst part for this affable man, who coaches youths in basketball and the martial arts, was looking at the terribly damaged eyes of the burned child. He doesn't think of himself as a hero.</p>
        <p>"I don't know how I did it," he said. "I just did it because I like kids. I like life, period."</p>
        <p>Rafael Giordani is a transit policeman who saw three people going through a subway exit gate without paying their fares. He and his partner, Grace Zwisdak, started to issue a summons.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, one of the men pressed a pistol to Officer Giordani's head and there was a shootout. Officer Giordani shot and killed one of the group, all of whom were armed. The other two were later arrested.</p>
        <p>Was all this worth the $1.15 a token then cost? "Whether it's $1.15 or $50,000, if it's a police action, it's worth it," he said. "The monetary amount has nothing to do with it."</p>
        <p>A most certitudinous man. "I've always believed in certain values," he continued. "Without those values, you're really nothing."</p>
        <p>Charles Compton is the third generation of court officers in his family. Each day, it is his job to bring order to the Criminal Division of the Bronx Supreme Court, not the world's most tranquil setting.</p>
        <p>His agency honored him for using his gun while off duty on City Island to bluff and subdue a crazed man with a shotgun. The man was menacing a group of people whom he seemed to know. No shots were fired and no one was injured.</p>
        <p>How important is this honor? "It's a big thing for me, because I recently lost my Pop, and he served 40 years in the court system," Mr. Compton said.</p>
        <p>Heroes, yes. But hardly ones with illusions about this ragged metropolis. Officer Giordani, for instance, is angered that the man who held a gun to his head was sentenced to just 2 3/4 years. And Mr. Gibbs has this to say about the state of the Bronx he cleans daily: "The city is sad. Nothing surprises me."</p>
        <p>All the more reason to end this column with the only two words that do these heroes justice:</p>
        <p>Thank you.  ABOUT NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
