<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Wall St. Said To Gain Most In Policy Shift</title>
    <meta content="Y20PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/20/business/20PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4DB1039F933A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Wall St. Said To Gain Most In Policy Shift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission study concludes brokerage firms have pocketed millions of dollars from new competitive arrangement in trading of stock options, while passing on almost none of money to customers; study was ordered after introduction of competition in options market led to proliferation of payments for order flow, in which specialists at exchanges paid money to brokerage firms in exchange for directing orders to those exchanges; commission finds that from November 1999 through September 2000 options specialists paid $33 million to retail brokerage firms for directing their orders (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brokerage firms have pocketed millions of dollars from the new competitive arrangement in the trading of stock options, while passing on almost none of the money to customers, the Securities and Exchange Commission concluded in a study released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The study was ordered after the introduction of competition in the options markets -- where options on any given stock historically traded on only one exchange -- led to a proliferation of payments for order flow, in which specialists at exchanges paid money to brokerage firms in exchange for directing orders to those exchanges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brokerage firms have pocketed millions of dollars from the new competitive arrangement in the trading of stock options, while passing on almost none of the money to customers, the Securities and Exchange Commission concluded in a study released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The study was ordered after the introduction of competition in the options markets -- where options on any given stock historically traded on only one exchange -- led to a proliferation of payments for order flow, in which specialists at exchanges paid money to brokerage firms in exchange for directing orders to those exchanges.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. surveyed 24 brokerage firms, which it said accounted for nearly all options trades by individual investors. Of those, it found that 19 had begun taking payments for order flow, and had directed orders to specialists that were paying for it. One other firm had established reciprocal relationships that amounted to the same thing, while four firms have so far refused to accept the payments.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. study did not identify the firms that were refusing to accept the payments. But it noted that while virtually all the brokerage firms said they tried to send orders to the best markets, the firms that took payments tended to choose markets that were different from the ones that did not have an economic stake in where the order was sent.</p>
        <p>An executive of one options exchange, speaking on the condition he not be identified, said the four not taking payments for order flow were Merrill Lynch, Salomon Smith Barney, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter and PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>The commission found that from November 1999 through September 2000 the options specialists paid $33 million to retail brokerage firms for directing their orders, with one brokerage firm collecting $6 million and six others getting more than $2 million each. None of the large recipients passed those payments on to customers, either through reduced commissions or rebates.</p>
        <p>''In fact,'' the report said, ''only one firm has significantly reduced retail commissions for executing listed options orders, and another maintains a policy to rebate payments received for order flow to customers.''</p>
        <p>But while the payment for order flow has clearly made money for brokerage firms, it is not clear if it has cost customers money. Those costs would show up in the spreads -- the difference between what a customer would have to pay for an option and what he could get by selling it at the same time.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. measured such spreads three ways. By the first measure, the quoted spread, it appears that spreads fell when competition began, but have since risen back to the previous levels. The same picture emerges if one looks at another measure, which the S.E.C. called the realized spread, which compares the price a customer gets with the price at a later point in time, and thus takes into effect the informational value of a customers' trade.</p>
        <p>But by the third measure, the effective spread, which simply measures the difference between prices of actual customer buys and sells, the spread fell after competition came in and has remained around the lower level ever since. By that measure, which may be the best one, it appears that the costs of payments to brokers are being borne by the specialists, not passed on to customers in higher trading costs. Some at the commission say they believe that situation will not endure, and that realized spreads will widen as well.</p>
        <p>''The ultimate effect on investors remains to be seen,'' said Arthur Levitt, the S.E.C. chairman, in an interview yesterday. ''The case for continued vigilance is clear.''</p>
        <p>Until August 1999, the options exchanges had generally observed a nonaggression policy, in which the exchanges did not try to trade options that historically had been traded at another exchange. But then, with a new options exchange on the horizon and the threat of antitrust action, they began to list one another's options, often relying on specialist firms that dominated the trading to bring in customer orders.</p>
        <p>But regulators did not make sure that the competition would arrive in a way that necessarily benefited customers. There was no electronic link between exchanges to allow an order to be sent to a market offering a better price, and there were no rules governing where orders were sent.</p>
        <p>In October 1999, Susquehanna, a large specialist operating in different options on various exchanges, began paying for order flow. Others soon followed, and business began moving toward those specialists.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board Options Exchange, long the dominant exchange, found itself losing business and feared that its specialists, many of whom were not national firms, would be unable to compete effectively to purchase order flow. So it instituted a policy of imposing what amounted to a tax of 40 cents a contract on each trade, with that money paid by the specialist or floor trader that made the trade and being available to be paid for order flow. Other exchanges soon followed with similar plans, although nearly all of them decried the practice.</p>
        <p>Another way that competition could have gone would have been a strict time-price priority, in which the exchange that first posted a price would get the first order at that price. But the S.E.C. did not require that, and without electronic links it would have been difficult to enforce.</p>
        <p>In the current system ''specialists on the competing options exchanges typically will promise to match the displayed prices of other exchanges,'' the S.E.C. report said. ''These passive 'price matching' practices may weaken the incentive to display competitive quotes, because displaying a superior quote does not necessarily ensure attracting additional order flow. Over time, therefore, the quotes being matched may become wider, increasing execution costs to investors.''</p>
        <p>Reaction from the options exchanges was muted. ''I'm happy the S.E.C. is going to continue to look at it, especially in the area of best execution,'' said Peter Quick, the president of the American Stock Exchange. Similarly, Meyer S. Frucher, the chairman of the Philadelphia Stock Exchange, said ''payment for order flow is an abomination if it does not come with absolute best-execution requirements.'' They referred to the obligation of a broker to get the best price for a customer.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, as the report noted, it is not easy to determine how good execution is. All the exchanges, and some of the specialists, are putting out information to show they provide quality executions, but the report noted that the reports are not comparable and that only the American Stock Exchange has been willing to provide information needed by an independent firm hired by some institutional investors to try to compile statistics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
