<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y20BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/20/world/20BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DE1039F933A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compile by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: JEHOVAH'S WITNESS VICTORY  Jehovah's Witnesses chalked up a victory in their legal battle to be granted official status. The constitutional court, Germany's highest, overturned a 1997 ruling that the 200,000 Witnessees should be refused recognition as belonging to a public body, saying the church's application should be reassessed. If a church is declared a public body, it can levy taxes on its members and is itself exempt from most forms of taxation.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: JEHOVAH'S WITNESS VICTORY  Jehovah's Witnesses chalked up a victory in their legal battle to be granted official status. The constitutional court, Germany's highest, overturned a 1997 ruling that the 200,000 Witnessees should be refused recognition as belonging to a public body, saying the church's application should be reassessed. If a church is declared a public body, it can levy taxes on its members and is itself exempt from most forms of taxation.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: 17 DIE IN PRISON ASSAULT  Soldiers stormed 20 prisons to force an end to a mass hunger strike, setting off clashes that killed 2 soldiers. At least 15 inmates died, most of them leftist prisoners who set themselves on fire, officials said. Some 200 prisoners went on a hunger strike to protest plans to transfer them to smaller cells from large domitories, which the government says are used by prisoners as indoctrination centers.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: MAD COW REQUEST  Austria asked the European Union for permission to ban all imports of German beef and cattle after Germany said there could be more cases of mad cow disease in its livestock. Austria, one of the few European countries that have had no reported cases of the disease, plans to put the the nationwide ban into effect tomorrow.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: BLOOD DONATION CURBS  Authorities said they would no longer accept blood donated by people who lived in Britain for over a year between 1980 and 1996, in an effort to lessen the risk of spreading the human form of mad cow disease. The measure, which is already in effect in the United States, Canada, Germany, Austria, Italy and Australia, affects only about seven-tenths of 1 percent of potential blood donors.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: SIGNING ON  Yugoslavia became the 120th country to sign on to the International Criminal Court, the first permanent tribunal created to try war criminals. The Yugoslav foreign minister, Goran Svilanovic, signed on a visit to New York to speak in a Security Council debate on Kosovo. Yugoslavia is still considering what to do with a separate Balkan tribunal indictment of the former president, Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: FORGIVING DEBT  Canada moved to make good on a promise to help the world's poorest countries, declaring a debt repayment moratorium on $451 million owed by 11 poverty-stricken nations. The 11 nations are Benin, Bolivia, Cameroon, Ethiopia, Ghana, Guyana, Honduras, Madagascar, Senegal, Tanzania and Zambia. Finance Minister Paul Martin said the countries had ''demonstrated, first, commitment to reform, and second, a respect for basic human rights.''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>BAHRAIN: RESTORING PARLIAMENT  Bahrain announced plans to restore an elected Parliament, which was dissolved in 1975, and set up a constitutional monarchy. A new national charter will be presented to the emir, Sheik Hamad bin Issa al-Khalifa, on Saturday and submitted to a referendum. The mainly Shiite Muslim opposition has campaigned for Parliament to be restored, setting off unrest that cost at least 38 lives between 1994 and 1999. The unrest eased after Sheik Hamad took over last year after the death of his father.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ALGERIA: REBELS' TOLL CLIMBS  Rebels killed 22 villagers in the latest attack on civilians in the Muslim holy month of Ramadan, residents said. The raid followed a machine-gun attack on a bus on Sunday in which 19 people died. The village slayings brought to about 70 the number of people killed in three days and to more than 200 in Ramadan, seen by guerrillas fighting for a fundamentalist Islamist state as the optimum period for publicizing their struggle.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>CONGO: FLEEING TO ZAMBIA  Large numbers of soldiers and civilians from Congo fled to Zambia as a rebel offensive intensified on the border, witnesses and Zambian intelligence officials said. The new influx adds to 3,400 Congolese government troops, 300 Zimbabwean soldiers and up to 60,000 civilians who have fled to Zambia in the last two weeks from a Rwandan-backed Congolese rebel offensive on government supply lines in an attempt to take control of the frontier.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: TESTIFYING AGAINST ESTRADA  The main witness in President Joseph Estrada's impeachment trial testified that he diverted about $2.6 million in state funds to Mr. Estrada and his family. Luis Singson, left, a provincial governor, said he and a presidential aide took the money to the president's residence after Mr. Estrada won the 1998 election. He said Mr. Estrada told him he needed the money to recover election expenses. Mr. Estrada is on trial before the Senate impeachment court on corruption and bribery charges.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: READY FOR TALKS  In a step toward peace talks, President Chandrika Kumaratunga said in a speech in Paris that the government is ready to wind down the war and negotiate with Tamil rebels who have been fighting for a separate homeland since 1983. A rebel leader, Velupillai Prabhakaran, had proposed the talks, but demanded a respite from the fighting.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: PRESIDENT'S ADMISSION  President Abdurrahman Wahid conceded on a brief visit to the separatist region of Aceh what many human rights groups have long said: that the government had mishandled the conflict, which has taken thousands of lives since the rebellion began in 1976. Mr. Wahid called on the military to end its attacks on civilians and invited the rebels to return to the bargaining table.</p>
        <p>Calvin Sims (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
