<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop and Jazz Guide</title>
    <meta content="31POP.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971107T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="969215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED71131F932A05753C1A961958260" item-length="4544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop and Jazz Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in New York City this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>''ALL JOBIM,'' Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Antonio Carlos Jobim, the inventor and master of bossa nova, wrote indelibly seductive songs that are equally prized by pop singers and jazz musicians. Those paying tribute include Sting, Al Jarreau, the Brazilian songwriter Ivan Lins, the tenor saxophonist Joe Lovano, the classical guitarist Sharon Isbin and other Brazilian and American musicians in well-planned combinations. Tonight at 8; tickets are $30 to $57 (Jon Pareles).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in New York City this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>''ALL JOBIM,'' Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Antonio Carlos Jobim, the inventor and master of bossa nova, wrote indelibly seductive songs that are equally prized by pop singers and jazz musicians. Those paying tribute include Sting, Al Jarreau, the Brazilian songwriter Ivan Lins, the tenor saxophonist Joe Lovano, the classical guitarist Sharon Isbin and other Brazilian and American musicians in well-planned combinations. Tonight at 8; tickets are $30 to $57 (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>D GENERATION, Coney Island High, 15 St. Marks Place, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 674-7959. Glam rock, that pungent brew of high fashion, low morals  and gender-bending outrageousness, has always found its earthiest practitioners on the streets of New York. This East Village-based band of veteran club punks carries the torch once held by the New York Dolls and points it toward the millennium. On this, the biggest dress-up day of the year, the band shares the bill with some local hard-core favorites, Murphy's Law, Electric Frankenstein and Backseat Driver. Cash prizes will be awarded for the best costumes. The show begins tonight at 7:30; tickets are $15 in advance, $20 on the day of the show, and all ages may attend (Ann Powers).  * DON CABALLERO, Coney Island High, 15 St. Marks Place, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 674-7959. The musicianly spirit of progressive rock -- all those odd time signatures, angular melodies, arbitrary stops and starts and flurries of technical display -- survives in Don Caballero, an instrumental band from Pittsburgh. The guitars line up one dissonant, asymmetrical, aggressive riff after another, or dissolve into planned noise, while the drums subdivide the time, clatter and splash. Tomorrow night at 10:30.  Admission is $8 (Pareles).  JACK DeJOHNETTE, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-3080. The drummer's new album and band, both called ''Oneness,'' deal with open spaces and rhythm; the tunes mercurially open up or tighten, and drums and rhythmic patterns are often the focus, inspiring the rest of the group to react intuitively. The band includes the pianist Michael Cain, the percussionist Don Alias and the bassist Jerome Harris, and it will play at 9 and 11 tonight through Sunday. Cover charge is $25 tonight and tomorrow and $20 on Sunday, with a $10 minimum all nights (Ben Ratliff).  CESARIA EVORA, Town Hall, 123 West 43d Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824. The morna songs of the Cape Verde Islands, off the coast of Senegal, capture longing and memories and determination in melodies that rise and then waft to earth; they have the world-weary grace of bossa novas, tangos and the best cabaret songs. Cesaria Evora has brought morna to Europe and the United States, and her liquid-amber voice, filled with melancholy wisdom, makes the songs indelible. Sharing the bill is Sally Nyolo, a singer from Cameroon who used to be in Zap Mama. Tomorrow at 8 P.M.; tickets are $35 (Pareles).  JOHN FAHEY AND JOHN HAMMOND, Tramps, 51 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 544-1666. Two individualists meet for a special night of solo guitar music. Mr. Hammond has battled accusations of racial mimicry during his long career as a bluesman, but his impassioned singing and fretwork prove his authenticity. The real treat on this bill, however, is the chance to see the reclusive Mr. Fahey -- a master of the acoustic guitar who is now playing electric, continuing the relentless quest for innovation that has made him a hero to players ranging from folk purists to post-rock experimenters. Fahey opens the show Sunday at 8 P.M.; tickets are $10 (Powers).  VICENTE FERNANDEZ, at Radio City Music Hall, 1260 Avenue of the Americas, at 50th Street (212) 247-4777. In Mexico, Vicente Fernandez is a household name, a television star who owes his fame to songs about loving, crying and suffering. With his dramatic tenor voice and his wall-shaking vibrato, Mr. Fernandez brings out all the melodrama of Mexican ranchera songs that bounce and laugh as they detail vast heartaches. Sunday at 8 P.M.; tickets are $37 to $62 (Pareles).  RACHELLE FERRELL, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592. Rachelle Ferrell is one of those singers who is almost impossible to believe. She's almost stupifyingly virtuosic, and she uses her virtuosity in the old-fashioned way: she's there to make an audience go home exhausted, thinking that they'll never forget the show they have just heard. She sings a mixture of rhythm-and-blues that's not particularly popular critically. The people in the trenches who buy tickets love her. Shows tonight through Sunday night are at 9 and 11:30; the cover is $35 with a $5 minimum (Peter Watrous).  * GOLDIE, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, Manhattan, (212) 777-6817. The disk jockey and producer Goldie was one of the first nonanonymous stars to emerge from England's jungle clubs. His 1995 album, ''Timeless'' (FFRR/ Polygram), mixed jungle's dub-reggae bass lines and sudden bursts of chattering double time under floating keyboard chords and, sometimes, full-fledged songs. He is now performing with live musicians and has probably come up with some new surprises. Tomorrow night at 12:30 A.M.; tickets are $16.50 in advance and $20 if bought tomorrow (Pareles).  * ANTONIO HART QUARTET, Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, West Village, 1-888-794-6499. Antonio Hart, an alto-saxophonist, has his ambitions all over the place, from hard-driving jazz with a very up-to-date sensibility, to gospel, to salsa. Good thing he has some of the best new players to go the distance with him, including the pianist James Hurt and the drummer Nasheet Waits. The band has progressively cohered for a few years; you will hear a solo or two that will lay you flat. Tomorrow at 11 P.M. and 12:30 A.M.,  tickets $5 to $20 (Ratliff).  RUSSELL MALONE, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, between 11th Street and Waverly Place, West Village, (212) 255-4037. He's the most imaginative young guitarist working in mainstream jazz, a musician who apparently knows the history of the guitar. He's just as likely to play some Django Reinhardt lines as he is to laughingly leave a tune's harmony in rubble. He's best known as a member of Diana Krall's group; in his own context he can be thrilling, a wild improviser with a streak of blues. Sets tonight through Sunday are at 9:30, 11:30 and 1; there is no third set Sunday night. The cover is $15 and there is a $10 drink minimum (Watrous).  MYRA MELFORD, Roulette, 228 West Broadway, at White Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-8242.  She has no accompanists, but this isn't quite the same as when a good jazz pianist plays a snoozy solo set in a small club. In the 80's, before forming her jazz trio, Ms. Melford thrived in the medium of the solo piano performance, exposing her equal affinity for strict, nearly ragtime rhythms and unmetered passion; she played a lot of prepared piano too. In this concert she'll perform pieces written by herself, Dave Douglas, Henry Threadgill, Butch Morris and others. Tomorrow at 9 P.M.; admission is $8 (Ratliff).  MOUSE ON MARS, Other Music, 15 East Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 477-8150. Mouse on Mars plays electronics-driven lounge music with a Jetsons ambiance; it will be opening for its kindred spirits Stereolab on Monday and Tuesday at Irving Plaza but is also playing a free show at this store on Sunday at 7 P.M. (Pareles).  THE NEED, at Dumba Gardens tonight, 57 Jay Street between Front and Water Street, Dumbo, Brooklyn, voice mail (212) 726-2686; and tomorrow, at the Cooler, 416 West 14th Street, West Village, (212) 229-0785. The experimental-college town of Olympia, Wash., came to prominence in the early 1990's as a seedbed for political punk rock, much of it made by young women eager to reinject some radical fuel into cultural feminism. The spirit these bands displayed was awesome, but their musicianship stayed at the bare minimum. Olympia's second wave is picking up where their older sisters left off. The Need -- former Kicking Giant member Rachel and her partner, Radio -- specializes in surreal tales of sex, violence and body modification set against harsh science-rock made on home-modified instruments. It is rising to the top of the underground with some of the weirdest and most fearless rock Olympia has produced. Tonight, at Dumba Gardens, the show begins at 9, with Dos Mujeres en Camino and the Patsy sharing the bill; tickets are $5 and all ages may attend. Tomorrow at the Cooler, the show begins at 11 P.M. with Flux Information Science and B. J. Snowden opening; admission is $8 (Powers).  BETH ORTON, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-1224. She looks like she walked out of a Clairol Herbal Essence commercial from the mid-1970's, and her musings lean toward the dreamily metaphysical. But this Northern English songstress steeps a voice like afternoon sunlight in the whirl of London's techno scene to come up with a brand of folk that's distinctly modern. Come early to hear the pistachio-flavored psychedelic pop of Granddaddy. The show begins tomorrow at 8 P.M.; tickets are $12.50 in advance and $14 the day of the show (Powers).  LEE (SCRATCH) PERRY WITH MAD PROFESSOR AND THE ROBOTIKS BAND; SPRING HEEL JACK, Wetlands, 161 Hudson Street, TriBeCa, (212) 966-4225. Two generations of tricksters play their cosmic pranks in New York this  weekend. Perry, the revered eccentric largely responsible for the trippy dub style of reggae regularly pilfered by today's electronica artists, teams up with his old crew in what will undoubtedly be a nonlinear performance. Spring Heel Jack, an English duo at the top of the aforementioned electronica wave, expand upon their own experiments in mind-altering sound. The two bands share the stage tonight; doors open at 9, and tickets are $25 (Powers).  TITO ROJAS, Latin Quarter, 2551 Broadway at 96th Street, Manhattan, (212) 864-7600. He's one of the best living Puerto Rican singers, an improviser who performs with his own orchestra. He has been lucky; he still has hits. When he sings, he drives the rhythmic point home with a big, bellowing voice. When he sings Arsenio Rodriguez's songs, it's an experience, and to give some sense of his stature, he's the man who often closes the big salsa extravaganzas at Madison Square Garden. The show, tomorrow night, starts at 11; there's a $20 cover for women, $25 for men (Watrous).  SON SEALS, Chicago Blues, 73 Eighth Avenue, below 14th Street, West Village, (212) 924-9755. Son Seals is the quintessential Chicago bluesman, roaring and growling his pain while his guitar wails and jabs. Tonight and tomorrow, with sets at 9:30 and 11 P.M. and 12:30 A.M. Admission is $20 (Pareles).  * JACKY TERRASSON TRIO, Iridium, 48 West 63d Street, Manhattan, (212) 582-2121. The last time this trio came through town, they made a stir. Mr. Terrasson, after a few years separation from the drummer Leon Parker, has recently gotten back to playing with him, and the reunited trio shows the degree to which both young players have grown. With Ugonna Ukegwo on bass, the group is probably as free as jazz can get without abandoning patterns; it's incredibly rhythmic and thoughtful; it's graceful and intuitive and textural. And where an hour of the band could once be too much rum and Coke, now they tend to settle into ideas; the dazzle meter isn't always in the red. Sets are at 8:30, 10:30 and 12 A.M. tonight through Sunday; there is no late show on Sunday; the cover is $20, with a $10 food or drink minimum (Ratliff).  * MIKE WATT, Tramps, 51 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 544-1666. Going against the practical odds -- his groggy baritone has minimal range, and he swallows his lyrics -- Mr. Watt, once the bassist of the Minutemen, has coughed up a concept album, ''Contemplating the Engine Room'' (Sony), that is by turns silly, grave and touching. Mr. Watt's father was an engine-room hand in the Navy out of San Pedro, Calif., and using a woolly language of homemade slang he has fused fragments of his father's biography with the story of his relationship with D. Boon, the Minutemen's guitarist and singer, who died in 1990. It's a big and messy poetic conceit (one recurring theme is rhythm section as engine room), but Mr. Watt, alongside the excellent guitarist Nels Cline and the drummer Stephen Hodges, pulls it off. Opening: Bardo Pond's slow but stubbornly convincing trance-rock and Railroad Jerk's quick but unconvincing soul-rock.  Tonight at 9; tickets are $12 (Ratliff).  * YO LA TENGO, at Westbeth Theater Center, 151 Bank Street, between West and Washington Streets, West Village, (212) 741-0391. Yo La Tengo's songwriters, the husband-and-wife team of Ira Kaplan on guitar and Georgia Hubley on drums, prize succinct, tuneful songs about the modest pains and pleasures of daily life and love. From those songs, however, a welter of fuzz-tone and feedback can erupt at any time, like a psychedelic disruption of the ordinary. After 12 years of recording, Yo La Tengo is only getting better. Tonight and tomorrow at 7 P.M.; an all-ages concert will be held on Sunday at 2 P.M. where no alcohol will be served; various opening acts; tickets are $12 (Pareles).  ZIN, S.O.B.s, 204 Varick Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. A hot little Haitian band, Zin knows its way around the groove that gets a dance party going. Like most working Haitian bands, it is relaxed yet completely taut, and there aren't any mistakes on the bandstand. The musicians are there to turn out the crowd; they've done it before, and they like to play. The show tonight starts at 11; the cover is $17 (Watrous).</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 7, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>An entry in the Pop and Jazz Guide of Weekend last Friday about the singer Mike Watt, once the bassist with the Minutemen, misstated the year that D. Boon, the Minutemen's guitarist and singer, died. It was 1985, not 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 7, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>An entry in the Pop and Jazz Guide of Weekend last Friday about the singer Mike Watt, once the bassist with the Minutemen, misstated the year that D. Boon, the Minutemen's guitarist and singer, died. It was 1985, not 1990.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
