<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>H.C.A. Management Makes A Buyout Offer of $4 Billion</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="187846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOSPITAL CORP OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWAN, ALISON LEIGH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D6123DF937A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>H.C.A. Management Makes A Buyout Offer of $4 Billion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWAN, ALISON LEIGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The management of the Hospital Corporation of America yesterday made a formal offer of $51 a share, or roughly $4 billion, for the Nashville-based hospital chain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The management of the Hospital Corporation of America yesterday made a formal offer of $51 a share, or roughly $4 billion, for the Nashville-based hospital chain.</p>
        <p>The management of the Hospital Corporation of America yesterday made a formal offer of $51 a share, or roughly $4 billion, for the Nashville-based hospital chain.</p>
        <p>The offer, consisting of $43 in cash and $8 in unspecified securities, is 8.5 percent higher than a $47-a-share package that the management said on Sept. 15 that it might offer. But on Oct. 6 the company's directors, on the advice of their financial advisers at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company, rejected that tentative price as inadequate.</p>
        <p>While no rival group has made a public counteroffer, Humana Inc., of Louisville, Ky., has reportedly hired Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc. to advise it on a possible merger. Combined, the two companies would be the nation's largest hospital chain by far, with more than $9 billion in annual revenue and about 170 hospitals.</p>
        <p>An investment banker familiar with Hospital Corporation said Morgan Stanley had told members of management how much they would have to sweeten their bid for it to recommend the offer to shareholders as a fair deal.</p>
        <p>The management group, led by Thomas F. Frist Jr., the company's chairman and chief executive, has not disclosed the identity of the third parties working with it on the buyout offer. But the Morgan Guaranty Trust Company is understood to be arranging a bridge loan of more than $500 million for a buyout.</p>
        <p>Hospital Corporation has about 72 million shares outstanding, and the management group would need well over $4 billion in financing to buy all the equity, including options and other convertible equity, and to cover expenses. Any buyer would also have to assume $2.1 billion in existing debt on the company's books.</p>
        <p>The announcement of the management offer was made late yesterday afternoon, after the company's stock had closed unchanged at $44.50 a share on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Reached at his home last night, Irving S. Shapiro, head of Hospital Corporation's independent directors, would not say whether the latest package would be accepted.</p>
        <p>''I can't discuss that,'' he said. ''It's a matter for the committee to consider.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro said the special committee that he heads would consider the latest bid before its expiration date next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>An arbitrager who has been following Hospital Corporation said the relatively quick expiration of the offer meant that management ''was really putting the board's feet to the fire.''</p>
        <p>A company spokesman, Victor L. Campbell, acknowledged that the offer's duration was unusually brief. ''It's quick, but this has been under discussion between the management and the board for almost a month,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Charles A. Leeds Jr., director of risk arbitrage at Balis, Zorn, Gerard, valued the offer at the bottom of the range of credible offers, between $51 and $57 a share.</p>
        <p>''My guess is the board of directors has pretty much decided to sell the company if they get a sufficient bid,'' he said. Because the latest bid is at the bottom of the range, Mr. Leeds said, the company's independent directors might do something similar to what the GAF Corporation's directors did when they were faced with a less-than-ideal management proposal to buy the company.</p>
        <p>''The board will probably accept the bid contingent on the management leaving the bidding open for a higher bidder,'' he said. In other words, it will let shareholders decide. ''Then, the key question is whether Humana or anyone else will top the bid.''</p>
        <p>Humana may be waiting for Hospital Corporation's board to approve an offer by management. Then it would presumably be difficult for the board to argue that a higher counteroffer would be unfair to shareholders.</p>
        <p>''Humana has held back, and assuming the special committee blesses this offer, then indeed the company is in play,'' said John F. Hindelong, an analyst at Smith Barney, Harris Upham &amp; Company. Nonetheless, he thinks the odds are ''less than 50-50'' that Humana will make an unsolicited $4 billion-plus acquisition in light of troubles it is facing in its insurance subsidiary. A better idea, he said, is for Hospital Corporation to sell Humana some hospitals that fit into the Humana system, satisfying Humana and paying down its own acquisition debt all the sooner.</p>
        <p>The $51-a-share offer for Hospital Corporation is well above its recent stock price. The company's shares were languishing as low as $30 in August before management announced it was exploring a buyout. In 1983 the shares traded as high as $56 a share, and they have since seesawed between $28 in 1985 and the low $50's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
