<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Quayle Questions</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTS AND PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUAYLE, DAN (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE133CF93BA35756C0A967958260" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Quayle Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days before President Bush's coronary episode, Vice President Quayle was asked on CNN whether he was troubled that only 19 percent of people polled said they would vote for him for President. Well, Mr. Quayle replied cheerfully, when "you think of my 19 percent and the President's 81 percent, we've got it all."</p>
        <p>Dan Quayle is a sunny and unvengeful man. According to former Senate colleagues, he is also weightier than given credit for, and might prove a surprisingly serviceable successor to Mr. Bush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days before President Bush's coronary episode, Vice President Quayle was asked on CNN whether he was troubled that only 19 percent of people polled said they would vote for him for President. Well, Mr. Quayle replied cheerfully, when "you think of my 19 percent and the President's 81 percent, we've got it all."</p>
        <p>Dan Quayle is a sunny and unvengeful man. According to former Senate colleagues, he is also weightier than given credit for, and might prove a surprisingly serviceable successor to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Yet depending on which polls you read, a distinct minority of Americans share that belief. They find him barely plausible as Vice President and supremely implausible as President. It is a judgment that Mr. Bush needs to weigh carefully as he contemplates the 1992 campaign. Why not the best? Or at least, why not better?</p>
        <p>The Quayle Question is actually three. Can Mr. Bush find someone else? Will he find someone else? Should he find someone else?</p>
        <p>The answer to the first question is surely yes. Anyone who watched Lyndon Johnson waltz Arthur Goldberg to the United Nations from a seat of lifetime honor on the Supreme Court can never underestimate a President's capacity to make artful switches.</p>
        <p>The answer to the second question is no, at least at the moment. His aides insist that Mr. Quayle will be on the ticket in 1992. Further, Mr. Bush is a stubborn man, and even if he feels he made a mistake he is unlikely to concede it unless it is clear next year that Mr. Quayle will constitute an overwhelming liability. Mr. Bush also knows that it would be unfair to draw any strong conclusions from Mr. Quayle's record as Vice President, an office that tends to diminish rather than enhance its occupants. Indeed, Mr. Quayle has received polite applause for stretching the job's limits by serving as head of the National Space Council and pushing American business interests abroad.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Quayle's overall record in public life is extraordinarily thin. His Senate career produced little of consequence. He lacks international scope and throughout his career has professed and represented a dismayingly narrow slice of the political spectrum. Even now he surrounds himself with cold war conservatives.</p>
        <p>The main worry, however, is not about what Mr. Quayle thinks but about his judgment, depth and seriousness of purpose -- expressed by the Latin word gravitas. Try as he might, Mr. Quayle still cannot shake his image as an amiable lightweight who, when he bounced up to meet George Bush after his surprise selection in New Orleans, reminded one observer of "the second or third lead in a spring break movie."</p>
        <p>Nor, come to think of it, has he really tried all that hard to shake that image. His foreign trips include as much sports as diplomacy, and during the furor over John Sununu's free use of government transportation for private purposes, Mr. Quayle hopped a military jet to play golf in Georgia. Not for nothing has the Secret Service given him the code name "Scorecard."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush now seems to be recovering rapidly, to the relief of all Americans. But even as they wish him well, their Quayle questions endure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
