<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commerce Follows Artists Into the SoHo of Shanghai</title>
    <meta content="06ARTS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/06/arts/design/06ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1398180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanghai (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Esaki-Smith, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED61E3AF935A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commerce Follows Artists Into the SoHo of Shanghai</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Commerce Follows Artists Into the SoHo of Shanghai</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anna Esaki-Smith</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Esaki-Smith, Anna</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Esaki-Smith Arts Abroad column on artists' colony that is taking shape in once abandoned waterfront warehouses in Shanghai, China; artists fear warehouses, sold to developers, will be razed for commercial development and park; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An artists' community is growing here along the meandering Suzhou Creek, which empties into the Huangpu River at the northern tip of this city's riverside esplanade. Abandoned waterfront warehouses, hulking memorials to the manufacturing days of Shanghai, provide artists with huge work spaces.</p>
        <p>Last year newspapers heralded the return of fish to the creek, suggesting that an ambitious billion-dollar city cleanup had improved upon a past when raw sewage and chemicals were routinely dumped into its waters. More recently, vast apartment complexes have sprung up in a place where residents used to keep their windows shut year-round because of the stench.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As was the case with its namesake in Manhattan, the tug of commercial possibilities may uproot a growing artists' community in an area often called Shanghai's SoHo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An artists' community is growing here along the meandering Suzhou Creek, which empties into the Huangpu River at the northern tip of this city's riverside esplanade. Abandoned waterfront warehouses, hulking memorials to the manufacturing days of Shanghai, provide artists with huge work spaces.</p>
        <p>Last year newspapers heralded the return of fish to the creek, suggesting that an ambitious billion-dollar city cleanup had improved upon a past when raw sewage and chemicals were routinely dumped into its waters. More recently, vast apartment complexes have sprung up in a place where residents used to keep their windows shut year-round because of the stench.</p>
        <p>This creekside area that has been revitalized is often called Shanghai's SoHo. But as was the case with its namesake in Manhattan, the tug of commercial possibilities may uproot the growing artists' community. The land beneath the warehouses containing studios and galleries has recently been sold to developers, artists say, and the warehouses could be razed for commercial development and a park.</p>
        <p>''We live in a commerce-driven society,'' said Li Liang, the owner of Eastlink Gallery, which covers 6,500 square feet on the second floor of a former grain warehouse along Suzhou Creek. ''You try to do new things, influence society, but in the end you pretty much know what the results will be.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago the Shanghai Biennial, a government-sponsored art show designed to put the city on the cultural connoisseurs' map, took place at two sites in town, but a band of intrepid artists with no official ties put on a series of their own shows, including one at Eastlink.</p>
        <p>Their exhibitions included a video of three artists walking around town as their blood dripped into tubes from catheters in their arms, and a live performance of a diaper-clad artist floating down the Huangpu in a plastic bubble. Some of the shows were shut down by city authorities, which frayed the relationship between the local government and rebel artists.</p>
        <p>The art at Eastlink is not the sort favored by the nouveau riche of China. Some of it is installation art, like a pyramid of layered blue-green glass shown at an exhibition earlier this year, paired with a television screen enclosed in a wooden box. Mr. Li said he focused more on exposing people to forms of modern art than on actually selling it. Officials at the Shanghai Cultural Bureau would not comment on development plans for the Suzhou Creek area.</p>
        <p>Teng Kun-yen, 52, a Taiwanese architect, also has a vision about how to marry art with commerce as he works in a former rice warehouse thought to have once belonged to a local gangster. He has given city officials his proposal to transform 30 waterfront warehouses into eight cultural centers focusing on music, fashion, architecture and other arts. Although he doesn't know the status of his proposal, he said he felt that some officials might be leaning in his direction. He said his hopes were buoyed by the suspension of plans to build a garbage-disposal plant next to his studio, where three old buildings were demolished.</p>
        <p>He admitted, however, that conflict seemed to reign. City and district authorities are unclear about how to develop the Suzhou Creek area, Mr. Teng said, and are ''entangled in disputes.''</p>
        <p>The warehouse containing Mr. Teng's studio was built in 1933 and has an Art Deco facade, massive wooden beams and high ceilings. Mr. Teng spent around $100,000 renovating the roughly 25,000-square-foot space, and the yearly rent is just over $40,000. The infrastructure was so solid that little basic reconstruction was needed.</p>
        <p>The appeal of the warehouses is not just their large size and affordability, but their embodiment of Shanghai's history as a bustling international trading port. Mr. Teng said he believed that his building was designed by Americans.</p>
        <p>In the early 1990's many old factories along the creek closed or their operations moved to rural areas as the state-run economy of China began to implode and Shanghai started to reinvent itself as a financial center.</p>
        <p>During the subsequent development boom here, blocks of historic buildings were razed to make room for modern offices. Many people fear that the same fate awaits the warehouses.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Teng said he saw a promising precedent in the preservation of the hall where the Communist Party was born and of nearby buildings in central Shanghai, which now house upscale restaurants and cafes. If the government wants to go ahead with a preservation project, ''the speed of doing things is unimaginable,'' Mr. Teng said, adding, ''Democratic countries can't do that.''</p>
        <p>In a last-ditch effort to save the historic warehouse area, preservationists are mounting a letter-writing campaign to this city's mayor. Even if construction of modern buildings gains momentum, there is optimism that some buildings will be preserved. Most artists realize, however, that the lure of commerce over culture may be too mighty for city authorities to resist.</p>
        <p>A woman who works at a gallery in the Suzhou Creek district said, ''Only a sliver of hope remains.''</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
