<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haskins Sees Own Image On the Court</title>
    <meta content="30RHOD$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="919390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Minnesota</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haskins, Clem</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD6103AF933A05750C0A961958260" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haskins Sees Own Image On the Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden's Sports of The Times column on University of Minnesota's basketball coach Clem Haskins, who has taken team to its first Big Ten title since 1982 and to its first NCAA Final Four berth; Haskins comments on his team's success (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLEM HASKINS reminds me of my high school principal. In the middle of the day, when we changed classes and our voices became too loud, Mr. Miller's voice would cut through the din with a simple, chilling pronouncement: ''This is still Harlan High.'' Then the roundup would begin. We were a public school, but Mr. Miller had his own dress code: no sweatshirts, no blue jeans, no miniskirts, no dark glasses. He was strict. And respected.</p>
        <p>Thirty years later, the authority of his voice still resonates. Thirty years from now, Haskins's Minnesota players will reflect on their coach's hard-hearted rules and smile: no earrings, no tattoos, no hats worn backward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLEM HASKINS reminds me of my high school principal. In the middle of the day, when we changed classes and our voices became too loud, Mr. Miller's voice would cut through the din with a simple, chilling pronouncement: ''This is still Harlan High.'' Then the roundup would begin. We were a public school, but Mr. Miller had his own dress code: no sweatshirts, no blue jeans, no miniskirts, no dark glasses. He was strict. And respected.</p>
        <p>Thirty years later, the authority of his voice still resonates. Thirty years from now, Haskins's Minnesota players will reflect on their coach's hard-hearted rules and smile: no earrings, no tattoos, no hats worn backward.</p>
        <p>For the last two weeks, the nation has been exposed to Haskins's view of the world: compassion, hard-edged authenticity, no-nonsense. In his own way, Haskins insists he will not be overwhelmed by contemporary culture.</p>
        <p>''I think earrings were made for ladies to wear, and that's the way I look at it,'' he said. ''I have some players who wear tattoos, I have some kids who wear earrings, but they wear them in their private surroundings. They know there's a time and place for everything.''</p>
        <p>Ideals weren't enough to defeat Kentucky yesterday, but in a business in which adults tell recruits what they want to hear, Haskins is refreshing. He speaks of what he knows. He will stop a shooting drill and gather the team around to make a point: ''I could score 50 when I had to. They couldn't check me.''</p>
        <p>If someone challenges, Haskins can go to the record books and show it is true. He was an all-America guard his senior year at Western Kentucky; they called him Clem the Gem.</p>
        <p>In 1967, Haskins was the third pick in the National Basketball Association draft and played nine seasons in the league.</p>
        <p>Haskins was raised in Campbellsville, Ky., and was a star in high school, but he was not recruited by the University of Kentucky, whose head coach, the legendary Adolph Rupp, was one of the last to integrate his basketball program. The snub wounded Haskins but gave him valuable perspective.</p>
        <p>That alone isn't enough to break a press, or win a national championship. But it may be enough to help his players win the national championship of life. Haskins, as much as any coach -- and more than most -- understands what it takes to survive and prosper.</p>
        <p>During the tournament he has derided coaches, high school and college, for failing to meet the challenge of leading youth. ''I think the trend in America is kind of sick because we don't have strong enough people to stand up for what's right and what's wrong,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After his pro career, Haskins came back and coached at Western Kentucky for six seasons, then moved to Minnesota. In his first two seasons at Minnesota, the Gophers struggled through a 21-game Big Ten losing streak. Now, he has taken Minnesota to its first Big Ten title since 1982 and to its first Final Four berth.</p>
        <p>Largely because of Haskins, Courtney James, a key player who was in and out of trouble off the court in high school in Indianapolis, was able to return home in triumph.</p>
        <p>At a time when sports driven by American talent and marketing have had a profound impact on global culture, Haskins has embraced the long-forgotten notion that athletes can be a positive force for leadership.</p>
        <p>''Athletes are high-profile individuals,'' he said. ''And when they're at school with caps on backward, with tattoos on, with earrings, the student body will copy that style.''</p>
        <p>For Haskins, success is not about national championships. Success in life is about turning the corner. Moving on.</p>
        <p>When a reporter asked whether he still harbored bad feelings toward Kentucky for the school's slight so many years ago, Haskins said he once might have approached the Kentucky game with extra zeal.</p>
        <p>''But I've matured a lot over the years,'' he said. ''The things that happened back in those days don't mean anything. That was 30 years ago. This is a different time zone. I probably had some hatred in my heart, but that is not there anymore. It's another ball game.''</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
