<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Nation's Growing Role as Staging Ground for Islamic Extremists</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="SPECTER OF TERROR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SUDAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BASHIR, OMAR (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TURABI, HASSAN AL- (SHEIK)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC1E3AF935A15755C0A965958260" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Nation's Growing Role as Staging Ground for Islamic Extremists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sudanese passports held by eight Muslim fundamentalists charged with planning terrorist acts in New York cast a spotlight on the growing role of the African country as a staging ground for radical Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>Since coming to power in a 1989 coup, the military government of General Omar al-Bashir and its partner in government, the Islamic National Front led by Sheik Hassan al-Turabi, have instituted one of the strictest Muslim fundamentalist social orders in the world. Exporting Revolution</p>
        <p>Two years ago Sudan struck a strategic alliance with Iran. Western and Egyptian security experts say Iran supplies the Sudan with free oil, sells some arms and trains Sudanese and Arab fundamentalists to form vanguard Muslim militias.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sudanese passports held by eight Muslim fundamentalists charged with planning terrorist acts in New York cast a spotlight on the growing role of the African country as a staging ground for radical Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>Since coming to power in a 1989 coup, the military government of General Omar al-Bashir and its partner in government, the Islamic National Front led by Sheik Hassan al-Turabi, have instituted one of the strictest Muslim fundamentalist social orders in the world. Exporting Revolution</p>
        <p>Two years ago Sudan struck a strategic alliance with Iran. Western and Egyptian security experts say Iran supplies the Sudan with free oil, sells some arms and trains Sudanese and Arab fundamentalists to form vanguard Muslim militias.</p>
        <p>The security experts say several hundred Iranian Revolutionary Guards have located themselves in a score of training camps throughout the Sudan, using that country as a bridge in an effort to export Islamic revolution to countries of the Middle East, particularly those ruled by secular, pro-Western governments like that of Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak.</p>
        <p>In Washington, a State Department spokesman said today that the United States was "very disturbed" by the close links between Sudan and Iran but had no evidence that Sudan had been conducting or sponsoring terrorist acts.</p>
        <p>The State Department spokesman, Mike McCurry, added that a number of fundamentalist groups considered to be terrorists -- including the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, the Palestinian Hamas and Islamic Jihad -- have offices in Khartoum, the Sudanese capital. He added that there were reports that Iranian Revolutionary Guards were training Sudanese Islamic militiamen.</p>
        <p>The United States has orchestrated an unofficial embargo of the Sudan and has spoken of instituting "safe havens" there for the non-Muslim segment of the Sudanese nation in the south. The non-Muslims in the South reject Islamic rule in the North.</p>
        <p>Egyptian, Tunisian and Algerian officials have repeatedly asserted that hundreds of fundamentalist arrested for terrorists acts in those countries have confessed to having received military training, money and travel documents from the Sudan before infiltrating back to their home countries. Power Behind Sudan Regime</p>
        <p>Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, the Egyptian cleric whose followers were implicated in both the World Trade Center bombing and the recent bomb plot, received his entry visa to the United States in Sudan, where he had been a frequent visitor to confer with Mr. Turabi over plans to overthrow the Egyptian Government.</p>
        <p>There is little doubt that the real power behind the Sudanese regime is Mr. Turabi, a longtime member of the Muslim Brotherhood political group founded in Egypt in 1928. The brotherhood has established movements in virtually every Arab country.</p>
        <p>A well-educated fundamentalist who has wide influence over many Arab fundamentalist groups, Mr. Turabi has instituted a reign of terror in the Sudan. The sheik also heads what is known as the Popular Arab Islamic Conference, dedicated to spreading a fundamentalist Islam through North Africa and the Middle East.</p>
        <p>"Islam is the only force that remains in that part of the world," Mr.  Turabi said in an interview. "There is nothing else left to inspire the young, to mobilize them, to give them vision, a sense of allegiance."  SPECTER OF TERROR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
