<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regulators Will Decide Fate of Bid For Mandalay</title>
    <meta content="15CASI$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/15/business/15casino.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1589616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mgm Mirage Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mandalay Resort Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerkorian, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MGM Mirage Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bellagio</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Mgm Grand</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB1130F936A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regulators Will Decide Fate of Bid For Mandalay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Regulators Will Decide Fate of Bid for Mandalay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MGM Mirage's $4.8 billion acquisition of Mandalay Resort Group is expected to face much scrutiny from Federal Trade Commission and State of Nevada; proposed combination would create gambling giant that would reshape control of Las Vegas Strip and give combined company vast influence over everything from hotel rates to airline fares to how high-rollers are rewarded; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Kirk Kerkorian appears to have won over the Mandalay Resort Group in a $4.8 billion merger with his MGM Mirage hotel and casino empire, there is one player left to beat: regulators.</p>
        <p>The proposed combination of MGM Mirage and Mandalay, which the companies revived over the weekend and are expected to approve today, would create a gambling giant that would reshape control of the Las Vegas Strip and give the combined company vast influence over everything from hotel rates to airline fares to how high-rollers are rewarded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Kirk Kerkorian appears to have won over Mandalay Bay on a merger with his MGM Mirage hotel and casino empire, there is one player left to beat: regulators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that Kirk Kerkorian appears to have won over the Mandalay Resort Group in a $4.8 billion merger with his MGM Mirage hotel and casino empire, there is one player left to beat: regulators.</p>
        <p>The proposed combination of MGM Mirage and Mandalay, which the companies revived over the weekend and are expected to approve today, would create a gambling giant that would reshape control of the Las Vegas Strip and give the combined company vast influence over everything from hotel rates to airline fares to how high-rollers are rewarded.</p>
        <p>How much influence is too much? If regulators answer that question by requiring the combined company to sell any of its prized properties to receive approval, a frenzied bidding war will most likely erupt among rivals, turning the Strip into a real-life Monopoly game.</p>
        <p>The property list of the companies is striking: it includes Las Vegas's most celebrated hotels and casinos like the Bellagio, MGM Grand, Mirage, Mandalay Bay, Luxor, Excalibur, New York-New York and Treasure Island. The company would control more than half the 72,000 hotel rooms and game tables along the brightly lighted boulevard that snakes through the city.</p>
        <p>The central question facing the Federal Trade Commission and the State of Nevada is how to define the market for MGM Mirage and Mandalay. Is it simply Las Vegas or does it include casinos and riverboats across the country? Or is the market even broader, including all vacation spots and cities with convention centers?</p>
        <p>If previous rulings by regulators on similar issues are any indication, the deal is likely to face much scrutiny.</p>
        <p>''I think it's more likely than not that the F.T.C. will find there is a narrow market,'' said Mike Cowie, a former senior litigation counsel and assistant director at the F.T.C. responsible for leading the Merger Litigation Task Force, who is now a partner at the law firm of Howrey Simon Arnold &amp; White in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Las Vegas is a brand,'' he said. ''It is going to be difficult to argue that Atlantic City is a direct substitute.''</p>
        <p>That, however, is exactly how MGM and Mandalay are planning to argue that the market should be defined. They contend that they compete for business and leisure dollars with hotels and cities across the country and even around the world.</p>
        <p>They are also expected to argue that they are under increasing competition and pressure from casinos on Indian reservations nationwide, especially those in Southern California, which they say are stealing many of their customers who used to fly out for the weekend.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the merger argue that the deal will lead to less competition among the hotels on the Strip and, therefore, higher prices for rooms as well as possibly even air fares, which are often part of package deals. The transaction could also effect the largest and wealthiest gamblers, known in the business as whales -- typically provided free or ''comped'' travel and accommodations and often other services.</p>
        <p>But two previous cases may be instructive on defining the market. In 1997, the Justice Department sued to block a deal between Vail Resorts and Ralston Resorts, which was aimed at merging some of Colorado's most-prized ski resorts, including Vail, Beaver Creek, Keystone and Breckenridge.</p>
        <p>Despite vigorous arguments from Vail and Ralston that they competed with ski resorts and other vacation spots across the country, the Justice Department determined that their market was quite narrow, defining Colorado's upscale ski resorts as a distinct and unique market.</p>
        <p>The F.T.C. took a similar view of the market for cruise vacations when Royal Caribbean Cruises and the Carnival Corporation fought to acquire P&amp;O Princess Cruises, arguing that the market was not all vacation spots as the companies argued but limited solely to cruise lines.</p>
        <p>Both of those transactions were ultimately approved with some concessions, but they do provide an important framework that could form the basis of the F.T.C.'s decision-making process as it investigates the MGM Mirage-Mandalay deal.</p>
        <p>The possibility of a blocked deal or forced concessions, or at least a prolonged investigation, has been one of the biggest sticking points during the negotiations between MGM Mirage and Mandalay. Indeed, Mandalay had all but abandoned the deal last Friday night because MGM had refused to agree to divest itself of any properties on the Strip if regulators made such a demand.</p>
        <p>Friday night, Mandalay's president and chief financial officer, Glenn W. Schaeffer, derided MGM's bid, saying, ''MGM was simply unwilling to accept the risk that regulators would require any divestitures or other regulatory fixes.''</p>
        <p>By Sunday, however, MGM returned with a new offer that included a guarantee to make such concessions and a slightly raised bid of $71 a share, up from the $69 that had been offered on Friday. Shares of MGM rose 60 cents yesterday, to $48.20, while those of Mandalay slid 82 cents, to $67.60.</p>
        <p>What those concessions might be is an important question. Analysts said the combined company would probably consider shedding either Circus Circus, its oldest hotel, or Treasure Island, both of which appeal to lower-end consumers compared with the likes of the Bellagio. But both of those hotels are near the site where Steven Wynn is building an upscale hotel, giving them an opportunity to participate in a potential revival of that end of the Strip.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
