<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Backpack: An Inalienable Right?;Student and Her School Tangle Over Civil Liberties</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BACKPACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BERNARDS TOWNSHIP (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEREDITH, ELYSE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D71639F930A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Backpack: An Inalienable Right?;Student and Her School Tangle Over Civil Liberties</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>HAMILTON TOWNSHIP, N.J., March 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On one side of the courtroom was a willfully defiant 14-year-old honor student, well versed in the civil disobedience of Thoreau and the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and eager to start carrying her maroon backpack to classes again.</p>
        <p>On the other was the principal and some teachers from William Annin Middle School in Bernards Township, N.J., and the district superintendent, all eager to persuade Judge Solomon A. Metzger of the Office of Administrative Law that bulging backpacks were threats to the health and safety of students and teachers and deserved to be outlawed from classrooms, halls and the cafeteria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On one side of the courtroom was a willfully defiant 14-year-old honor student, well versed in the civil disobedience of Thoreau and the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and eager to start carrying her maroon backpack to classes again.</p>
        <p>On the other was the principal and some teachers from William Annin Middle School in Bernards Township, N.J., and the district superintendent, all eager to persuade Judge Solomon A. Metzger of the Office of Administrative Law that bulging backpacks were threats to the health and safety of students and teachers and deserved to be outlawed from classrooms, halls and the cafeteria.</p>
        <p>So began a civil-liberties-versus-school-authority clash today between the eighth grader, Elyse Meredith, and the educational hierarchy of a well-heeled suburb hoping for Judge Metzger's blessing that its ban on backpacks is reasonable and its enforcement powers have not been exceeded.</p>
        <p>During their testimony today, Annin's staff members depicted a backpack craze turned dangerous in a school of 500 students. Teachers talked of monster and mega backpacks overflowing with cans of hair spray and stuffed animals in the halls of Annin; of tripping over straps poking into aisles from beneath desks; of getting whacked in the face by careless students turning abruptly, and of the backpack machismo of eighth-grade boys intimidating sixth graders.</p>
        <p>"You have three or four boys coming down a hallway," said a guidance counselor, James Buist. "It creates a bit of a flow problem,"</p>
        <p>Sandra Hyde, a math teacher, testified about being struck twice in the face by the backpacks of students who turned unwittingly into her path. No permanent  injuries, she told Judge Metzger, just "startling blows."</p>
        <p>"I need to now be defensive as I walk through the hallways," Ms. Hyde said, "because I never know."</p>
        <p>Miss Meredith said she did not consider backpacks as safety threats, and rejected the argument about the unwary tripping over straps protruding into aisles. "I feel they're almost like an extension cord on the floor," she said during a court recess.</p>
        <p>When the school imposed the ban on Jan. 2, Miss Meredith ostensibly began her disobedient behavior by refusing to stash her backpack in her locker, as the school rule required. She has complained that the three-minute break between classes is not enough time to go back and forth from her locker, and each class  requires a separate three-ring binder. The books are heavy.</p>
        <p>But she also views her struggle more philosophically. She has read Thoreau's  essay "Civil Disobedience."</p>
        <p>"I admire him and Martin Luther King, too," she said outside court. "I feel this is all a question of liberties. I feel it's important to stand up for liberties you have, to keep them. I feel it's taking away students' rights to property."</p>
        <p>Her defiance of Annin School's backpack ban has cost her 10 days in suspensions from classes. She served that time in a room in the school, doing homework under the watch of a teacher. A ruling last month forced her to abandon her maroon backpack, a moderate-sized one like those lugged around by millions of college and high school students. She now carries her books and other belongings to class in a black attache case that her father, Charles Meredith, gave her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meredith seems to delight in his daughter's fight, although he regrets that she has received her first B-plus at Annin after a string of A's. He is a burly former football coach and history teacher at Rutherford High School in Bergen County who now works as a salesman. For now, he is serving as his daughter's lawyer, albeit one a bit unpolished procedurally. Several times today, Judge Metzger admonished him gently to ask direct questions and refrain from offering opinions.</p>
        <p>"We've always taught her that the first element of intelligence is questioning," Mr. Meredith said of his daughter outside of court. "The purpose of this country is to think critically. That's the purpose of education, theoretically."</p>
        <p>Miss Meredith's challenge might extend beyond Annin School. If the backpack ban is upheld, other school districts in New Jersey might be encouraged to enact similar prohibitions. Only a few have them now in middle schools, including Bridgewater, Raritan, and Flemington. Bernards Township's school board has already spent $10,000 fighting this battle, and the Superintendent, Dalen Showalter, said the district would appeal if it loses this round of the fight.</p>
        <p>This is the second time that Judge Metzger, an administrative law judge, has  heard the case this year. Initially, the board came before him on an emergency basis and asked him to order Miss Meredith to obey. He refused, calling the ban  a "minor school rule," and said he was not convinced that Miss Meredith had to submit to authority.</p>
        <p>"If other parents and children do not understand, then it is the kind of learning opportunity that civics teachers pray for," Judge Metzger wrote in early February. The school board appealed to the State Education Commissioner, Leo F. Klagholz, and he overruled Judge Metzger, deciding that Miss Meredith's disobedience was akin to anarchy.</p>
        <p>But her classmates today seemed unwilling to join Miss Meredith in a mass protest. Some seemed already weary of the two-month-old dispute.  "She's never going to win," said John Cooney, a fellow eighth grader.  "The backpacks are a fire hazard. The judge should decide that if the principal makes a decision, the kids should follow it."</p>
        <p>To a few parents, the issue is also economic. Mary Besbris, whose son Jeremy  is an eighth grader there, suggested that the district has its priorities confused. "We can't even get the supplies we need, and now we're paying lawyers' fees," Mrs. Besbris said. "Let the kid go."</p>
        <p>To the school board, however, the broader issue is whether the rule is reasonable and within the board's rule-making authority, an important point for  school boards statewide.</p>
        <p>The school board's lawyer, Les Aron, sought to justify the rule today on grounds that the backpacks pose a safety risk. A substitute teacher at Annin, Dorthy Norris, told of tripping over a backpack and falling. Her ankle hurt for six or seven weeks, she said. Elaine Lent, who teaches fine arts and industrial technology, said she tripped twice over backpacks, hurting a thigh the first time and an arm the second.</p>
        <p>Of her second fall, she said: "It just knocked the wind out of me, it really  did. I would not consider it a major injury, but it was nasty."</p>
        <p>The hearing will continue on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
