<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Diet Wheel Again Spins To Protein</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIET AND NUTRITION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMLIN, SUZANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dieting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dieting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6D81639F930A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Diet Wheel Again Spins To Protein</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE HAMLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMLIN, SUZANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FRAN McCULLOUGH, a book editor in Manhattan who has lost 60 pounds in the last year, is relishing the response of people who haven't seen her for a while  ("Is that really you, Fran?"). Friends of Janet Pope, a decorative artist in Baltimore, shake their heads in awe at her weight loss -- 56 pounds in 13 months -- accomplished, like Ms. McCullough's, by cutting down on carbohydrates and concentrating on protein.</p>
        <p>Buoyed by these testimonials from carbohydrate dropouts, driven by curiosity  and burdened with 14 surplus pounds, I joined the protein packers for five weeks. It was in direct opposition to my normal, deeply committed, plant-based complex-carbohydrate life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FRAN McCULLOUGH, a book editor in Manhattan who has lost 60 pounds in the last year, is relishing the response of people who haven't seen her for a while  ("Is that really you, Fran?"). Friends of Janet Pope, a decorative artist in Baltimore, shake their heads in awe at her weight loss -- 56 pounds in 13 months -- accomplished, like Ms. McCullough's, by cutting down on carbohydrates and concentrating on protein.</p>
        <p>Buoyed by these testimonials from carbohydrate dropouts, driven by curiosity  and burdened with 14 surplus pounds, I joined the protein packers for five weeks. It was in direct opposition to my normal, deeply committed, plant-based complex-carbohydrate life.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, I lost weight, gained new admiration for protein, kept my respect for complex carbohydrates and began to question some of the very tenets  of dietary dogma. Like many others, I found myself falling into the whirlpool of increasingly contradictory information supplied by a number of reputable scientists.</p>
        <p>As a child of the 60's, I was more than familiar with high-protein diets popularized in that era by three diet doctors: Irwin Stillman, Robert Atkins and the late Herman Tarnower.</p>
        <p>And here the diets were back again, in slightly altered form. Dr. Atkins has  resurfaced with "Dr. Atkins' New Diet Revolution" (M. Evans &amp; Company, 1992, $19.95). Rachel F. and Richard F. Heller, both professors at Mount Sinai School  of Medicine in Manhattan, have followed their best-selling "Carbohydrate Addict's Diet" with a more-structured high-protein plan, "Healthy for Life" (Dutton, 1995, $24.95). The newest entry, and the one I relied on, is "Protein Power" (Bantam, $21.95), by Dr. Michael R. Eades and Dr. Mary Dan Eades. Published in January, there are now 40,000 copies in print.</p>
        <p>Appearing on the best-seller list this month for the first time was "The Zone" (Regan Books, 1994, $22), by Barry Sears with Bill Lawren, dealing with a  protein-specific diet originally developed for high-performance athletes. In May, "The 5 Day Miracle Diet" is scheduled to be published by Ballantine Books.  Written by Adele Puhn, a nutritionist on Long Island with a celebrity clientele, the book stresses protein and downplays carbohydrates.</p>
        <p>Was there, perhaps, more to dieting than grains, greens and beans?</p>
        <p>Marion Nestle, a nutritionist, was not sympathetic to my planned short-term defection from the complex-carbo camp. "Not the protein diet again," she sighed  when I related my regime. As the chairwoman of the department of nutrition and food studies at New York University and a member of the committee that establishes dietary guidelines for the Agriculture Department, Dr. Nestle stands firmly with the low-fat greens and grains group.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Adam Drenowski, the director of the Human Nutrition Program at the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan, was somewhat bemused. He observed that diet trends -- particularly high complex carbohydrate versus high protein -- swing back and forth like a pendulum. "Given the historical cycle of dieting, it is probably inevitable that the protein diet is with us again," he said.</p>
        <p>He speculated that the return to protein might be an almost-unconscious backlash to what he calls "the Dean Ornish school of dieting," a reference to a  diet high in plant-based complex carbohydrates, in which only 10 percent or less of a day's calories are from fat.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ornish, the author of "Eat More, Weigh Less" (HarperCollins, 1993), adamantly defends his severely structured lifetime eating plan, which was originally designed for recovering coronary patients.</p>
        <p>"The protein people are spreading misinformation and half-truths," he said. "This is a serious setback to real scientific research."</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, I began to reacquaint myself with meat, poultry, fish, tofu, eggs, cheese, bacon, pork rinds and other animal products, mostly because of the success stories emanating from Bantam, the publisher of "Protein Power." Over the last year, Irwyn Applebaum, its president, has lost 36 pounds ("I started when I read the manuscript," he said) by cutting out most carbohydrates; Nita Taublib, the vice president, has lost 80 pounds, and Ms. McCullough, the editor  of the book, and her husband, David, and daughter, Kate, 22, have lost a total of 110 pounds.</p>
        <p>Like them, I immediately banished polenta, risotto, pasta, pizza, exotic grains, potatoes, beans, legumes, bagels, rice cakes and other daily pleasures.  I don't often crave sweets or cereals, so it was not a big problem to rule them  out.</p>
        <p>But red meat? Standing in front of the refrigerated carcasses, I identified with the sacrificial victims. After years of avoidance, I could not continue to  eat red meats or bring myself to eat the animal fats (butter and cream, for example) allowed on the diet. I continued to use olive oil.</p>
        <p>I still ate salads and vegetables (except for high-carbohydrate corn and carrots). I drank a glass or two of wine daily (the authors of "Protein Power" are oenophiles) and the requisite 8 to 10 glasses of water.</p>
        <p>But I had to severely limit almost all fruit. The Eades view all carbohydrates -- complex carbohydrates like pasta and grains as well as simple carbohydrates like table sugar -- as dietary villains. And many fruits are carbohydrate mine fields.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, the Eades have worked with 4,000 patients at their Arkansas Center for Health and Weight Control in Little Rock. They are believers in the insulin-resistant school of dieting, a concept shared, to one degree or another, by all high-protein-diet advocates.</p>
        <p>Insulin resistance is the inability of the body to process carbohydrates properly, turning the sugars into fat and sending out an insistent demand for more carbohydrates. Scientists generally agree that 20 to 25 percent of the population is insulin-resistant.</p>
        <p>But how about the rest of us? Healthy people with no history of serious obesity, who just need to lose a slothful 10 to 20 pounds? And how healthy is a  steady diet of protein?</p>
        <p>The Eades have worked out a formula for dieters based on optimum lean body mass. In my case, the daily allowance was 60 grams of protein and 30 grams of carbohydrate, the reverse of my norm.</p>
        <p>Initially, I felt unpleasantly full most of the time and out of sorts. I missed crunching on rice cakes, although an adequate substitute was deep-fried pork rinds (they have no carbohydrates, and an unlimited amount is allowed on the Eades plan), which taste like salty, lightweight Styrofoam.</p>
        <p>By Day 3, I felt quite ill -- dizzy, and with a pounding heart. I called Dr.  Michael Eades in Little Rock, and he said that I was experiencing severe potassium loss due to losing so much water so fast. (As his book advises, I was  taking a comprehensive vitamin supplement but had failed to take the recommended potassium supplement.) After lots of beef broth and potassium pills, I was back  on track in two days.</p>
        <p>I was beginning to suspect that I was not meant for a high-protein diet, that I had what the Eades call "an evolved system," a body that had adjusted well to  utilizing whole-food carbohydrates even though, they contend, humans were originally designed only to process protein.</p>
        <p>"If it's not broke, don't fix it," said Dr. Mary Dan Eades, who does not advocate a protein diet for everyone.</p>
        <p>But I persisted in moderation: I ate small amounts of poultry and fish and, every day, had hard-boiled eggs, cottage cheese or soy protein. I avoided most carbohydrates and continued to eat many salads and vegetables. I avoided fruit altogether, afraid that if I ate the small amount allowed I would lose myself to mango madness.</p>
        <p>Out of lust, however, came loss: the 14 pounds drifted away, my muscle tone improved and I felt newly energized. I now have new respect for protein. But I felt sadness, too, at such shameless disloyalty to my complex-carbohydrate credo.</p>
        <p>"People lose weight or maintain it because they eat less and move more, it's  that simple," said Dr. Nestle, as she listened to the sagas of those who have flouted conventional wisdom with the protein diet.</p>
        <p>"The most important thing you can do for your health is to lose weight, if that's a problem," she said. "And if the protein diet works for you, that's fine, as long as it's not for longer than six weeks. It's too hard on your kidneys to process a lot of protein for longer than that."</p>
        <p>Much protein also has the disadvantage of being coupled with a lot of fat. The Eades, however, think that it is carbohydrates, not fats, that are elevating cholesterol and triglycerides, a possible new marker for potential heart disease.</p>
        <p>Elevated triglycerides were what drove Dr. Michael Jaffe, an orthopedic surgeon in Dayton, Ohio, to the Eades diet. Last year, at 57, Dr. Jaffe, who exercised regularly and ate a low-fat diet, had a severe heart attack. He went on the lower-fat Ornish plan, which he continued for three months, until he found that his triglycerides, which had previously been normal, had risen. For the last three weeks, he has been on the high-protein program on the chance the  Eades may be right, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jaffe says he believes the final truth is in laboratory work. "How can a  diet be bad for you if your lab work is normal?" he asked, adding that a five-year controlled study, sponsored by the Government, should be done comparing both diets.</p>
        <p>Dr. Louis J. Aronne, the director of the Comprehensive Weight Control Center  at New York Hospital and author of "Weigh Less, Live Longer" (John Wiley &amp; Sons, $22.95), said that sometimes he will switch patients to a low-fat, high-protein diet if they do not lose weight on a low-fat, high-carbohydrate program, which he thinks is ultimately healthier.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Eades, however, he is adamant that fat remain low in a high-protein diet.</p>
        <p>"We simply don't know all the answers yet," Dr. Arrone said.  "What we have learned through these past decades of trying to find a way to lose weight and -- the key factor -- keep it off, is that there is no one diet that works for everyone."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
