<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Istanbul Inaugurates A New Portal to the Porte</title>
    <meta content="30REP.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1195803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ataturk International Airport (Istanbul)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinzer, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Istanbul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DB1530F933A05757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Istanbul Inaugurates A New Portal to the Porte</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinzer, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corresponedent's Report on modern new international terminal at Turkey's Ataturk International Airport (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A GLITTERING new international terminal has opened at Ataturk International Airport, finally giving visitors a modern gateway to this many-splendored city.</p>
        <p>Istanbul's old international terminal was intimate, and those who used it regularly appreciated the speed with which they could sometimes negotiate their way past the various control points. For most passengers, however, it was a highly unsuitable point of entry to Turkey. It was dark, crowded and often plagued by long lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A GLITTERING new international terminal has opened at Ataturk International Airport, finally giving visitors a modern gateway to this many-splendored city.</p>
        <p>Istanbul's old international terminal was intimate, and those who used it regularly appreciated the speed with which they could sometimes negotiate their way past the various control points. For most passengers, however, it was a highly unsuitable point of entry to Turkey. It was dark, crowded and often plagued by long lines.</p>
        <p>The new terminal, built in 22 months at a cost of $306 million, could not be more different. It is four times the size of the old one, bright and airy with tall ceilings and broad corridors.</p>
        <p>Instead of a few cramped booths selling duty-free items, there are dozens of shops, ranging from a toy store to a gallery that specializes in reproductions of old maps and prints. Among the many places to eat is one with stir-fried Chinese dishes to order.</p>
        <p>Passengers used to have to take a shuttle bus between the terminal and the parking area, but no longer. A covered garage adjoining the terminal has space for more than 7,000 cars. The garage is said to be the biggest of its kind in Europe, and the terminal is the third biggest building in Turkey.</p>
        <p>Although President Suleyman Demirel officially opened the terminal in January, it is not complete. Workers are still drilling and patching in several places.</p>
        <p>With an annual capacity of 14 million passengers, the terminal is to be expanded to 20 million within a few years. It has been built with modern techniques designed to make it resistant to earthquakes.</p>
        <p>Of the 160 check-in desks, 64 belong to Turkish Airlines, which has become a comfortable and generally efficient carrier, especially on international routes. Baggage conveyers can handle 10,000 pieces of luggage an hour.</p>
        <p>Until the new terminal opened, most arriving planes were forced to park on the tarmac, and passengers were bused to passport control or transit lounges. Now fewer people are experiencing that inconvenience.</p>
        <p>With 64 passport control booths and 34  X-ray machines, the terminal should be able to offer no-wait service to most passengers. But these posts are sometimes unmanned, so lines persist.</p>
        <p>There are other quirks, some of which may be resolved as administrators recognize them. Signs in the main concourse are inadequate, and some check-in counters are difficult to find. At the information desk, multilingual receptionists are cheerful and eager to help, but even they do not yet know where to direct some passengers.</p>
        <p>The main departure concourse is more than half a mile long and is served by a single moving sidewalk. Since the sidewalk moves in only one direction, passengers who want to go the ''wrong'' way must walk.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the airport managers declined to answer questions about this apparent design flaw. It may be difficult to correct, but other start-up problems should be easier to resolve. Shops in the departure area offer a rich selection of modern and historic postcards, for example, but there is no place to buy stamps. Public telephones along the departure concourse accept only prepaid cards, but no cards are for sale.</p>
        <p>Several passengers have also complained about surly treatment from security agents who run the X-ray machines, which can put an unpleasant end to a vacation.</p>
        <p>By any standard, however, Istanbul has taken a giant step toward accommodating international air passengers. The old terminal was something of an embarrassment, certainly inadequate to serve as the main  gateway to a country that is now among the world's top 20 tourist destinations. The new one is an apt symbol of Turkey's campaign to reach European levels of efficiency.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
