<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Issue of Family Values, Clinton Unveils an Agenda of His Own</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="778646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FAMILIES AND FAMILY LIFE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DA1E3EF93AA15754C0A963958260" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Issue of Family Values, Clinton Unveils an Agenda of His Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, ALISON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Synthesizing many of his recent positions into a platform to compete with the reigning conservative manifestos, President Clinton today outlined a 14-point "American Family Values Agenda" ranging from a higher minimum wage to a national crusade against teen-age pregnancy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made clear that he would not let the Republicans alone define family values. He outlined measures that he said would help families grapple with the economic and social problems they face, proposals for the preservation and expansion of gun-control laws, for instance, and for moderate increases in health insurance coverage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Synthesizing many of his recent positions into a platform to compete with the reigning conservative manifestos, President Clinton today outlined a 14-point "American Family Values Agenda" ranging from a higher minimum wage to a national crusade against teen-age pregnancy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made clear that he would not let the Republicans alone define family values. He outlined measures that he said would help families grapple with the economic and social problems they face, proposals for the preservation and expansion of gun-control laws, for instance, and for moderate increases in health insurance coverage.</p>
        <p>"Families do not eat and breathe and sleep political slogans," Mr. Clinton said in an address to a conference of the American Federation of Teachers, the nation's second-largest teachers union.</p>
        <p>In the first direct indication that he plans a campaign against tobacco use by young people, Mr. Clinton included a battle against teen-age smoking in his list. "If you want to cut health care costs and increase life expectancy, do something to stop all these kids who are beginning to smoke at early ages," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was greeted with a standing ovation by the several thousand convention delegates gathered at a Washington hotel who clapped and chanted, "Four more years."</p>
        <p>"I must say I enjoyed the class being a little rowdy this afternoon," Mr. Clinton joked.</p>
        <p>The President did not make any direct comparison of his own agenda for family values with the House Republicans' Contract With America or the Christian Coalition's 10-point plan called the "Contract With American Families."</p>
        <p>But since last November's Republican sweep of Congress, Mr. Clinton has been searching for some formulation of his own to pose against the Contract With America's 10 planks and the emphasis placed on cultural issues by the Republican Presidential contenders.</p>
        <p>While agreeing with Republicans that Americans have to take more responsibility for themselves, he said that many of their problems stemmed from economic woes that government should help address.</p>
        <p>"We don't have to have a partisan, divisive fight about family values," Mr. Clinton said. "And we don't have to argue whether we need improvements in personal conduct or political policies and economic policies. The truth is, we need a whole bunch of both."</p>
        <p>Borrowing the language of the right though not its policy prescriptions, he said, "What we really need is an American family values agenda." He then rattled off 14 points, many of which were calls for protection of existing Government programs and Administration initiatives against cuts by the Republican Congress. He called for an end to cuts in environmental programs, supported public broadcasting and called for the preservation of a law that gives employees the right to family medical leaves from work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
