<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rembert Reaches the Jets After an Indirect Route</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="351759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARVIN, AL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1538F93AA35756C0A966958260" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rembert Reaches the Jets After an Indirect Route</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL HARVIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARVIN, AL</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I., May 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: There was nobody at La Guardia Airport to pick up Reggie Rembert and bring him to the Jets' minicamp on Monday, so he took a taxi and wound up becoming a part of the kind of broken pattern he almost never ran as a wide receiver at West Virginia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: There was nobody at La Guardia Airport to pick up Reggie Rembert and bring him to the Jets' minicamp on Monday, so he took a taxi and wound up becoming a part of the kind of broken pattern he almost never ran as a wide receiver at West Virginia.</p>
        <p>There was nobody at La Guardia Airport to pick up Reggie Rembert and bring him to the Jets' minicamp on Monday, so he took a taxi and wound up becoming a part of the kind of broken pattern he almost never ran as a wide receiver at West Virginia.</p>
        <p>''This guy in a plain car said he was a taxicab driver and said, 'Give me $79 and I'll take you there,' '' said Rembert, who had permission to report late because he was still taking exams at West Virginia.</p>
        <p>''He drove around for a couple of hours, stopped about four or five times to ask directions,'' the player explained. ''Everybody told him to go this way and then go that way and then we got stuck in traffic for a while. The plane landed at 3:35 and I didn't get here until after 6.''</p>
        <p>Though the ride took more than twice as long as it should have, Rembert, who has been timed in 4.45 seconds for the 40-yard dash, remains the fastest receiver in camp. He had a reputation as a game-breaker at West Virginia, where he was a two-year starter catching the often improvisational passes of the quarterback, Major Harris. In Fact, a First-Rounder? The 6-foot-4-inch, 200-pound Rembert was picked by the Jets on the second round of the college draft last month. ''I watched the first round on television and after nobody picked me, I went out and started washing my car,'' Rembert said. ''Then my girlfriend came out and told me that the Jets had called. I was glad that no other wide receivers had been picked on the first round.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Rembert could be considered a first-round pick with an asterisk. He was the second receiver chosen over all, behind Alex Wright of Auburn, the Dallas Cowboys' second-round selection. Both were among the first 28 players taken (26th and 28th, respectively) because three teams forfeited first-round picks for taking players in the supplemental draft last summer.</p>
        <p>Nervous Hands</p>
        <p>Rembert was a little nervous in the workout this morning, dropping a couple of passes, and he seemed to have some trouble in the afternoon lining up and running patterns because the system at West Virginia was just to get open and let Harris find you. Neither Rembert nor Coach Bruce Coslet of the Jets was upset, though.</p>
        <p>''The same thing happened when I first came to West Virginia,'' said Rembert, a junior college all-American at Independence Community College in Kansas before transferring. ''I was so anxious to make the team and to do well that I was nervous.''</p>
        <p>When asked about Rembert, Coslet, a former tight end and offensive coordinator with the Cincinnati Bengals, said: ''He's still thinking and not running. We'll play a little street football here. We'll just be a little more controlled with it. I used to run down and scrape the guy covering me off the fire hydrant. I tell the guys to just try to get free, but we do it in certain parameters.''</p>
        <p>Injury for Zawatson</p>
        <p>The Jets got a bit of a bad break in their efforts to shore up their sagging offensive line when Dave Zawatson, a 6-5, 275-pound guard-tackle from California acquired from the Chicago Bears in the Plan B draft, fell and broke two bones in his left hand.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
