<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wrongly Jailed, 2 Clear Last Hurdle Before Freedom</title>
    <meta content="15FREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/15/nyregion/15FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">False Arrests, Convictions and Imprisonments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faison, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shepherd, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ulysses, Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheston, Arlet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Van Buren</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DC143AF936A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wrongly Jailed, 2 Clear Last Hurdle Before Freedom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLE M. CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christian, Nichole M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Faison and Charles Shepherd, wrongly jailed in murder of livery cab driver Jean Ulysses in Brooklyn 14 years ago, are released after police arrest Arlet Cheston, who has confessed to crime; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day when freedom was supposed to belong to Anthony Faison and Charles Shepherd, when they were supposed to walk quickly out of a Brooklyn courtroom and return to their lives after 14 years in prison, the men found themselves sitting before a judge for nearly an hour before being released. For them, it was justice's final delay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Faison, 35, and Mr. Shepherd, 38, were convicted in 1987 in the murder of Jean Ulysses, a Haitian livery driver in Brooklyn. Their conviction hinged on the testimony of a witness who later admitted she had lied to collect a $1,000 reward. On Friday, the police arrested the man they now say was responsible for the killing, Arlet Cheston. Mr. Cheston has confessed to the crime, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day when freedom was supposed to belong to Anthony Faison and Charles Shepherd, when they were supposed to walk quickly out of a Brooklyn courtroom and return to their lives after 14 years in prison, the men found themselves sitting before a judge for nearly an hour before being released. For them, it was justice's final delay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Faison, 35, and Mr. Shepherd, 38, were convicted in 1987 in the murder of Jean Ulysses, a Haitian livery driver in Brooklyn. Their conviction hinged on the testimony of a witness who later admitted she had lied to collect a $1,000 reward. On Friday, the police arrested the man they now say was responsible for the killing, Arlet Cheston. Mr. Cheston has confessed to the crime, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>So yesterday, the families of Mr. Faison and Mr. Shepherd gathered in the courtroom for a hearing that they were told would be just a formality. They wept and shouted ''It's about time'' as the men were led into the courtroom.</p>
        <p>And then they gasped, as the freedom that had seemed so near appeared in jeopardy. Justice Robert S. Kreindler of State Supreme Court, the same judge who presided over the men's trial, began to question prosecutors over and over again as to whether they were certain Mr. Faison and Mr. Shepherd should be exonerated.</p>
        <p>''I presided at the trial back in '87 and, very frankly, after hearing the testimony I was pretty well convinced both defendants were guilty,'' Justice Kreindler said.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors from the Brooklyn district attorney's office spent nearly an hour assuring the judge by recounting new evidence provided by the police, as well as from Ronald L. Kuby, the lawyer for the men, and Michael S. Race, a private investigator. Mr. Race had spent years investigating the case at the request of Mr. Faison.</p>
        <p>The new evidence included an affidavit from a woman who said she had received a letter from an ex-boyfriend bragging about there being two men behind bars for a crime he had committed. The letter writer was Mr. Cheston, lawyers said.</p>
        <p>Justice Kreindler did not appear convinced. He asked a barrage of questions, sending some family members storming from the courtroom.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to believe that a person for a rather small reward would name two innocent people as murderers,'' the judge said.</p>
        <p>Family members said they were outraged.</p>
        <p>''If he had taken that much time 14 years ago to check the evidence, we wouldn't be here,'' said Mr. Shepherd's younger brother, Richard, who left the courtroom in disgust. ''They shouldn't have to go through this today.''</p>
        <p>Mitch Benson, an assistant district attorney, tried to bring the hearing to an end by explaining how Mr. Cheston's fingerprints had been found in the car where Mr. Ulysses was shot in the head. The witness who initially identified Mr. Faison and Mr. Shepherd as the robbers, Carolyn Van Buren, had testified that she saw them standing outside the cab, with Mr. Faison firing the fatal shot.</p>
        <p>''No fingerprints connected Mr. Faison and Mr. Shepherd to the case,'' Mr. Benson told the judge. ''But when we specifically compared Arlet Cheston's fingerprints to this case, two of fingerprints from his left hand matched the glass partition inside the cab.''</p>
        <p>Justice Kreindler eventually ended his inquiry and offered an apology. ''There wasn't anything we could do that would change anything,'' he said. ''I firmly believed Carolyn Van Buren when she testified at the trial. How do you know when someone is lying? It was just the two of you that knew you were innocent. We did what we believed was right.''</p>
        <p>When the judge gave the order to release Mr. Faison and Mr. Shepherd, the two men bowed their heads in disbelief. And again their families shouted. Eventually, the men made their way out of the courtroom and into a sea of hugs, high-fives and television lights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Faison, still dressed in prison togs with his identification number stitched on them, tried his best to handle the emotional reunion and the swarm of reporters.</p>
        <p>''I'm very grateful,'' he said as officers hurried him onto an elevator past reporters and much of his family, including his 14-year-old son. ''I have no reason to be bitter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shepherd seemed equally dazed by the attention.</p>
        <p>''I prayed about this day, but seeing how the judge was acting, it was hard to take,'' he said. ''He had the evidence right there and he still treated us like we were guilty. I'm just happy to be free.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
