<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journal; Blowing In the Wind</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DD1E31F933A15752C1A962958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journal; Blowing In the Wind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICH, FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of all the comebacks of Election '94, surely the strangest is the counterculture. Declared dead in the 1970's and finally laid to permanent rest at Woodstock II last summer, the counterculture was long ago annexed by a corporate culture that employs the Beatles' "Revolution" to hawk Nikes.</p>
        <p>But now Newt Gingrich, echoing other Republican moralists like William Bennett and Dan Quayle, has brought the counterculture back -- not for a reunion concert, alas, but as a scapegoat with flowers in its hair. Not only is the counterculture being held responsible for the excesses of Bill Clinton -- a non-inhaling Fleetwood Mac fan, of all unlikely hippies -- but for everything immoral, violent and sexually explicit in American culture today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of all the comebacks of Election '94, surely the strangest is the counterculture. Declared dead in the 1970's and finally laid to permanent rest at Woodstock II last summer, the counterculture was long ago annexed by a corporate culture that employs the Beatles' "Revolution" to hawk Nikes.</p>
        <p>But now Newt Gingrich, echoing other Republican moralists like William Bennett and Dan Quayle, has brought the counterculture back -- not for a reunion concert, alas, but as a scapegoat with flowers in its hair. Not only is the counterculture being held responsible for the excesses of Bill Clinton -- a non-inhaling Fleetwood Mac fan, of all unlikely hippies -- but for everything immoral, violent and sexually explicit in American culture today.</p>
        <p>The prospect of turning back the cultural clock is scaring some in the arts and show business, who do not relish the prospect of a Perry Como "Duets" album and smell a whiff of McCarthyism in any cultural blame game. The Los Angeles Times wonders if a new G.O.P. era of movie censorship is at hand. The Washington Post reports that the networks, already terrified by a V-chip that might regulate violence in TV sets, now anticipate an S-chip regulating sex. And every liberal watchdog worries about the future of the National Endowment for the Arts and PBS, long branded by the Gingrich gang as countercultural perversion incarnate.</p>
        <p>Having run against "Murphy Brown" and Robert Mapplethorpe and lost in '92, the emboldened Republicans of '94 now apparently feel they can run against the Stones -- Rolling, Oliver, Sharon, whatever -- with impunity in '96. Democrats can only hope they try. Republicans who rail against the counterculture at this late date are far more out of touch with the public than they think, Sonny Bono's efforts to bring them up to speed notwithstanding. If a party championing smaller government now uses a big-government stick to beat up on culture, counter- or otherwise, it may end up maiming its own partisans.</p>
        <p>Culture -- high and low, good and bad, moral and sleazy -- does not divide along party lines. Few would doubt that TV shows like "Melrose Place" and "Studs" epitomize what Mr. Gingrich vilifies in our culture, but who is responsible for them? Not the counterculture, but Fox, the network owned by Rupert Murdoch, publisher of The New York Post, one of the most conservative papers in the United States.</p>
        <p>Who is the most successful purveyor of violent entertainment on the big screen? Arnold Schwarzenegger, another Republican. Who is the most vocal fan of Mick Jagger and Bruce Springsteen to emerge from the elections? George Pataki. By contrast, it was Janet Reno who tried to jawbone Hollywood to reduce film violence and Tipper Gore who led a battle against dirty rock lyrics.</p>
        <p>The audience that consumes culture, whether at chamber-music concerts or multiplexes, also defies political stereotyping. Trying to illustrate the gulf between the Gingrich-Republican culture and the Democratic counterculture, a conservative Wall Street Journal editorialist last week seized upon the opposite poles of John Wayne movies and "Doonesbury." But instead of waiting for Wayne movies to resurface on cable or biding time with "The Book of Virtues," much of that conservative crowd is joining its liberal neighbors in watching "Roseanne," "Interview With the Vampire" and other hit entertainments that parade single moms, homosexuals, mindless violence and other scourges of the Gingrich world view.</p>
        <p>What politicians don't know about culture of all sorts could fill a "Ring" cycle. In the smartest book written from the inside about the American conservative movement, "Dead Right," David Frum recalls Ronald Reagan's affection for such kitsch as Remington bronzes and Jack Kemp's for "The Wizard of Oz" when he writes that "few intellectual movements have ever displayed so much philistinism so proudly." Is Bill Clinton, devotee of Kenny G, any better?</p>
        <p>Instead of initiating a new round of culture wars, Republicans and Democrats alike might benefit by actually stopping to wade into the culture of 1994 and listen to what it is saying. A few hours spent contemplating the intensely moral American outlaws of "Pulp Fiction" might even help them understand why 63 percent of the country rejected both parties by electing not to vote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
