<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Public Housing, on the Air</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EAST RIVER HOUSES (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HARLEM (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAIBORNE, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DA1031F933A15752C1A962958260" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Public Housing, on the Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER KINGSON BLOOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Verleen Brown had her own radio show, she would discuss hairstyles.</p>
        <p>"I could talk about different ways of braiding, teach people to braid," said Miss Brown, 17, who is coiffed in beads and cornrows. "It could be good." If he controlled the airwaves, Rafael Santiago, 19, would be a DJ, playing rap artists like Dr. Dre and Ice Cube. "I think I would like that," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Verleen Brown had her own radio show, she would discuss hairstyles.</p>
        <p>"I could talk about different ways of braiding, teach people to braid," said Miss Brown, 17, who is coiffed in beads and cornrows. "It could be good." If he controlled the airwaves, Rafael Santiago, 19, would be a DJ, playing rap artists like Dr. Dre and Ice Cube. "I think I would like that," he said.</p>
        <p>The teen-agers, residents of the East River Houses, on First Avenue from 102d to 105th Streets, may be able to test their skills as early as next month. Pending routine approval of an applicationfiled last week, the public housing development will soon be the first in the city to have its own radio station, housing officials say. Allan Monczyk, a housing spokesman, said he knew of no other housing project with a station.</p>
        <p>But don't expect to hear the voices of these East Harlem residents around the city. With less than one-tenth of a watt of power, the East River Community Radio Station will only reach AM listeners within two or three blocks. The power level of the station will be so low that it will not need a Federal Communications Commission license, said Richard Engelman, chief of the F.C.C.'s technical standards branch.</p>
        <p>Organizers of the station -- which is still without call letters -- say the size of the audience matters less than the number of residents who can be trained for jobs in radio.</p>
        <p>"These children who are standing here on the corners, we really need to bring their thinking back," said Barbara Claiborne, the president of the tenants' association at the East River Houses. "We don't have jobs to give them, but we can give them some training. Can you hear them going around saying, 'Hey listen -- my little brother's on the radio!' "</p>
        <p>Mrs. Claiborne, 51, has lived at East River Houses for 30 years and has headed the tenants' association since 1986. She is also a night engineer at WWRL (1600-AM), where she has a gospel-music show from 2:30 to 5 A.M. Two months ago, she and other tenants were trying to figure out what to do with a $10,000 grant from the Housing Authority's Drug Elimination Program that was allocated four years ago but never used.</p>
        <p>"I said, 'Listen, let's go for a miniature radio station," Mrs. Claiborne recalled. "They said, 'That's a good idea.' "</p>
        <p>A former student at the Queen Broadcasting Center in Manhattan, she asked her teachers and their friends to help. Three agreed to serve as engineers, setting up equipment and supervising operations. The engineers will plan to offer classes for teen-agers and young adults.</p>
        <p>"We will come in and show them all aspects of production,from station operation management, news gathering and production to how to be an on-air personality," said Bill Holden, 40, who teaches at the Queen Broadcasting Center and works as assistant program director at WOSX, an FM station in Westchester. Mr. Holden said he would compile a list of local commercial stations with internship programs, with hopes that the most highly motivated students will eventually qualify.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Claiborne has picked out an unused basement room to use as a studio for the station, which she hopes will eventually broadcast 24 hours a day. "We're just all really into it," she said. J.K.B.  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: HARLEM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
