<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Families of Chechnya's Disappeared Seek Answers</title>
    <meta content="10CHEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/10/world/10CHEC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1292097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dachny (Chechnya)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chechnya</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7D6123BF933A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Families of Chechnya's Disappeared Seek Answers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>GROZNY, Russia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of relatives in Chechnya wait in vain for those who have vanished since Russia launched its second war against rebels who want independence for Chechnya; families of those who disappeared keep vigil outside Russia's military prisons and police stations; they take risks in mine fields where corpses are thought to be hidden; they canvass offices of aid workers or anyone else who keeps lists; some Chechen families pay money in shadowy network that trades on rumors and sells information on where bodies might be found; that is how one of largest human dumping grounds of war was discovered in Feb, next to Russia's main military base in Chechnya; dozens of bodies bearing gunshot and knife wounds, their hands and feet bound, have been dug up near base in Dachny; Russian officials say they will conduct investigation to determine how they got there, although civilian prosecutors charged with finding facts have no authority to force testimony from Russian military officers and soldiers who may have witnessed killings; 51 bodies dumped in Dachny illustrate concern and frustration expressed by Chechens, human rights organizations, and even many Russians, that evidence of killings of civilians is being buried in Chechnya; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The families  of those who have disappeared  and are disappearing -- in Chechnya can be seen keeping vigil outside Russia's military prisons and police stations, showing photos to those who enter.</p>
        <p>They can be seen navigating the topography of destruction, taking risks in mine fields where corpses are thought to be hidden, and they canvass the offices of aid workers or anyone else who keeps lists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The families  of those who have disappeared  and are disappearing -- in Chechnya can be seen keeping vigil outside Russia's military prisons and police stations, showing photos to those who enter.</p>
        <p>They can be seen navigating the topography of destruction, taking risks in mine fields where corpses are thought to be hidden, and they canvass the offices of aid workers or anyone else who keeps lists.</p>
        <p>Sometimes Chechen families pay money in the shadowy network that trades on rumors and sells information on where bodies might be found.</p>
        <p>That is how one of the largest human dumping grounds of the war was discovered in February next to Russia's main military base in Chechnya. Dozens of bodies bearing gunshot and knife wounds, their hands or feet bound, were dug up between the weeds and summer cottages of Dachny, an abandoned settlement a few hundred yards from the Khankala base.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said they would conduct a thorough investigation to determine how they got there. Meanwhile, thousands of relatives wait in vain for those who have vanished since Russia launched its second war against the rebels who want independence for Chechnya.</p>
        <p>''I have a feeling he is alive,'' said Taisa Imakayeva, who cooks at a four-table cafe converted from a truck trailer that sits in the shade of poplar trees. During the bombing of the village of Duba Yurt on March 6, 2000, her brother, Balaudin Imakayev, was taken away by the Russian military. He was 42.</p>
        <p>''We were 25 people leaving the village on foot after it was bombed,'' she said. ''The women and children were separated and loaded onto an army truck to take them to the checkpoint. Then it went back to pick up the men. We haven't seen them since.''</p>
        <p>She has been to several prisons and camps where Chechen men are being held, and several hospitals, too.</p>
        <p>''He has epilepsy and a poor heart and has been an invalid,'' she said, adding, ''Another invalid with a paralyzed leg was with him.''</p>
        <p>She has visited all of the aid agency offices that keep lists, and she followed a reporter out of the cafe, smoothed her green scarf and black dress and pressed the vital details of her brother's disappearance. ''I know there is probably nothing you can do, but I just feel better telling someone about him,'' she said. ''He shouldn't leave life this way.''</p>
        <p>To find the body and commit it to the earth is everything in this tradition-bound land, where an eye for an eye and blood for blood still hold. And though many families persist in their search for fathers, brothers and sons, many are also beginning to understand that some of their mysteries will never be solved.</p>
        <p>The 51 bodies dumped in Dachny illustrate the concern and frustration expressed by Chechens, human rights organizations -- and many Russians -- that evidence of the killing of civilians is being buried in Chechnya. Civilian prosecutors charged with finding the facts have no authority to force testimony from Russian military officers and soldiers who may have witnessed the killings.</p>
        <p>The father and brother of Adam Chimayev, 38, had been looking for him since his disappearance on a highway south of Grozny last December.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chimayev was no ordinary civilian.</p>
        <p>He was a former rebel leader and deputy minister of state security in Chechnya, but he had received amnesty, family members said, and he carried a certificate from Russia's Federal Security Service to prove it, said Ramzan Eltuyev, the missing man's uncle. ''He could pass through all the checkpoints.''</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Chimayev disappeared, the uncle continued, ''Someone came to them and gave them a map.'' The family paid several thousand dollars for the drawing, which told them that the body was in the second or third cottage in Dachny.</p>
        <p>''We went there on our own, but found booby traps,'' Mr. Eltuyev said. When the family returned with Russian military officials and experts to clear mines, ''In the first house they found three fresh corpses, and in the second house they found our brother,'' he said. ''He had three pistol shots in the heart. We buried him the next day.''</p>
        <p>The only forensic specialists to have examined all of the bodies found at Dachny said in an interview that they were so ill-equipped to conduct professional examinations that in all but one case they could not state a clear cause of death, and that their examinations would never stand up in court if the killers were ever brought to justice. Fewer than half of the bodies were identified.</p>
        <p>''We did not even have a scalpel,'' said Maskhud Chumakov, a Chechen pathologist who works with a colleague, Vakha Akhmadov, in two grimy offices ventilated by several artillery strikes during the war. They were assigned to the team of prosecutors that investigated the dumping ground.</p>
        <p>No autopsies were performed, no tissue samples taken.</p>
        <p>''We only had rubber gloves,'' said Mr. Chumakov, ''and when we dictated our findings to the investigators, instead of saying death was caused by such and such, we said the death 'may have been caused' '' by gunshot or knife wounds.</p>
        <p>''I have been a forensic expert for 17 years,'' Mr. Chumakov said, ''and I know these examinations could easily be rejected by any court.''</p>
        <p>Russian officials asserted that most of the corpses at Dachny were those of Chechen rebels, but as families came to identify bodies, it turned out that more than a dozen were civilians who had disappeared in the last year.</p>
        <p>At least four were women, including the wife of a former federal judge and two of her cousins seized by masked men in military fatigues at a Grozny market last June.</p>
        <p>Vladimir Kalamanov, who is President Vladimir V. Putin's special representative for human rights in Chechnya, asserted in a news conference recently that of the 462 missing person reports he had compiled, 46 had been resolved.</p>
        <p>But no tally of the missing will be possible until the conflict here ends and the Chechens who have fled the region, joined rebel formations in the mountains or lie buried or otherwise hidden can be accounted for.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the disappearances continue. In April four Chechen herders from the village of Alleroi -- a father, his 15-year-old son and two nephews, ages 12 and 14 -- took a herd of 250 to pasture lands little more than a mile from the village. The next day, a neighbor spotted the herd heading home unattended.</p>
        <p>''I went there on my motorcycle,'' said a close relative. ''It was raining hard and we were yelling for them. I even climbed an oil derrick to look for them.''</p>
        <p>The next day, dozens of villagers went to the pasture by bus and formed a human chain. When they entered a nearby forest, a man cried out in anguish that he had found them. They lay face down, each shot in the back of the head.</p>
        <p>''For what have you been murdered?'' a brother called out in the forest as the search ended.</p>
        <p>Russian officials here and in Moscow blamed Chechen rebels for the killings, a response that has become almost reflexive in the propaganda contest between Moscow and the Chechen rebel command.</p>
        <p>The herders' relative who ventured out of Alleroi to meet a reporter said there was no evidence of who had killed them, though family members suspected Russian Army troops encamped in the area.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
