<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="575626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D6173EF933A25751C1A964958260" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>N.H.L  Leafs' Power Display on Power Play</p>
        <p>Toronto's power play was more efficient than Detroit's penalty killing and the result was a 5-3 victory by the Maple Leafs over the Red Wings last night in Toronto. The Maple Leafs scored a season-high five power-play goals. Mike Foligno, with a pair of goals, John Cullen, Dmitri Mironov and Doug Gilmour connected to help Toronto to its first victory in five games. Mironov also had three assists and Gilmour two. Steve Yzerman had a power-play goal for the Red Wings, who now have one victory in seven games. Jimmy Carson and Gerrard Gallant were the only skaters to score with both teams at even strength. Toronto wound up 5 for 9 with a man advantage and the Leafs killed off five of six minors they took. The game also marked the return of Detroit's Bob Probert to an ice surface on Canadian soil in almost four years. Until last Friday, when he received permission from United States immigration authorities to re-enter the United States, he'd been unable to cross the border since a March 1989 arrest on drug-possession charges. (AP) Sabres 5, Bruins 2: Aleksandr Mogilny scored three goals as Buffalo snapped a four-game streak without a victory by beating Boston. The victory by the Sabres, whose only two victories in their last 13 games had come against the expansion Ottawa Senators, stopped the Bruins' winning streak at four games. Mogilny's fourth career hat trick gave him 20 goals for the season. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>N.H.L  Leafs' Power Display on Power Play</p>
        <p>Toronto's power play was more efficient than Detroit's penalty killing and the result was a 5-3 victory by the Maple Leafs over the Red Wings last night in Toronto. The Maple Leafs scored a season-high five power-play goals. Mike Foligno, with a pair of goals, John Cullen, Dmitri Mironov and Doug Gilmour connected to help Toronto to its first victory in five games. Mironov also had three assists and Gilmour two. Steve Yzerman had a power-play goal for the Red Wings, who now have one victory in seven games. Jimmy Carson and Gerrard Gallant were the only skaters to score with both teams at even strength. Toronto wound up 5 for 9 with a man advantage and the Leafs killed off five of six minors they took. The game also marked the return of Detroit's Bob Probert to an ice surface on Canadian soil in almost four years. Until last Friday, when he received permission from United States immigration authorities to re-enter the United States, he'd been unable to cross the border since a March 1989 arrest on drug-possession charges. (AP) Sabres 5, Bruins 2: Aleksandr Mogilny scored three goals as Buffalo snapped a four-game streak without a victory by beating Boston. The victory by the Sabres, whose only two victories in their last 13 games had come against the expansion Ottawa Senators, stopped the Bruins' winning streak at four games. Mogilny's fourth career hat trick gave him 20 goals for the season. (AP)</p>
        <p>Whalers 6, Senators 2: After losing their playoff safety net this season, Hartford is finding a cushion in Ottawa. Mark Janssens and Jamie Leach scored in the second period as the Whalers took control en route to their victory at home. Half of the Whalers' eight victories and two of their four home victories have been against Ottawa, which is 0-14-0 on the road. Nick Kypreos, Zarley Zalapski, Patrick Poulin and Terry Yake added third-period scores for Hartford. (AP) TENNIS  McEnroe Triumphs; Chang Upsets Agassi</p>
        <p>Displaying frequent touches of brilliance, John McEnroe, a former No. 1 player, began what could be his last big tournament by trouncing Nicklas Kulti of Sweden, 6-1, 6-4, at the Grand Slam Cup yesterday in Munich, Germany. After his victory, McEnroe, stayed to watch Michael Chang stun second-seeded Andre Agassi, 6-4, 6-2. Michael Stich, the local favorite, produced another upset by eliminating top-seeded Stefan Edberg, 7-6, 6-7, 8-6. Stich broke Edberg for a 7-6 lead in the final set, and converted his first match point when the Swede sent a forehand long. Third-seeded Pete Sampras, winner of the first Grand Slam Cup in 1990, became the third American to reach the quarterfinals by beating Aleksandr Volkov of Russia, 6-3, 6-4. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
