<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Refugee Kurds Occupy Tent City After Guerrillas Lift Barricades</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="AFTER THE WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KURDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ZAKHO (IRAQ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUDETIC, CHUCK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC123BF933A05757C0A967958260" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Refugee Kurds Occupy Tent City After Guerrillas Lift Barricades</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SUDETIC,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SUDETIC, CHUCK</byline>
      <dateline>ZAKHO, Iraq, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Allied officers ordered Kurdish guerrilla leaders today to let Kurdish refugees through rebel checkpoints and into a safe-haven zone in northern Iraq. A Kurdish commander complied, and the first refugee families arrived tonight at the tent city near this occupied town.</p>
        <p>Until today, the guerrillas had barred many refugees from trekking down the mountain roads from their muddy camps along the Turkish-Iraqi border, insisting that the zone set up by the United States, Britain, France and the Netherlands was not secure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Allied officers ordered Kurdish guerrilla leaders today to let Kurdish refugees through rebel checkpoints and into a safe-haven zone in northern Iraq. A Kurdish commander complied, and the first refugee families arrived tonight at the tent city near this occupied town.</p>
        <p>Until today, the guerrillas had barred many refugees from trekking down the mountain roads from their muddy camps along the Turkish-Iraqi border, insisting that the zone set up by the United States, Britain, France and the Netherlands was not secure.</p>
        <p>But after a 40-minute meeting with allied commanders and a tour of the safe-haven area, the senior Kurdish commander, General Ali, was airlifted to several Kurdish rebel checkpoints, where he ordered his men to lower the barricades that they had been using to delay the refugees' return.</p>
        <p>By evening, wheezing buses and dusty British military trucks carried the first 20 or so exhausted but smiling Kurdish families to the American-built tent city a mile from here. Dozens of other refugees drifted into Zakho, moving back to homes abandoned a month ago when the Kurdish uprising was crushed by President Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>In the last few days, several hundred Kurdish voluteers, mostly men, had been airlifted in to help set up the safe zone. The flow of refugees is expected to increase significantly in the next few days. About 500,000 Kurds, Assyrian Christians and members of other ethnic and religious groups remain in the mountain encampments.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether all guerrilla checkpoints will be open. "The Pesh Merga are not a unified organization," said a United States officer who asked not to be identified. He referred to the rebels by their name in Kurdish, which means "those who face death."</p>
        <p>The allies were also angered by reports that guerrillas at some checkpoints were exacting tribute from refugees for safe passage. The rebels were accused of discriminating against Christians and allowing their friends to pass while holding others back, said Col. James Jones, commander of the 24th Marine Expeditionary Unit in Zakho.</p>
        <p>Colonel Jones said the allied officers told the rebels "to knock that stuff off."</p>
        <p>"It's immoral and it's got to stop," Colonel Jones said. "They're straight-out bandits."</p>
        <p>General Ali told his men to lift their barriers after a 40-minute meeting with Maj. Gen. Jay M. Garner of the Army, commander of the allied operation in Iraq, and other allied military leaders this afternoon at the United States command center in Zakho.</p>
        <p>"We asked them to come in to discuss the return of their people," General Garner said at a news conference after the meeting. "The Pesh Merga checkpoint has been refusing to let people return, so we asked General Ali to resolve that for us. He did."</p>
        <p>General Garner accompanied General Ali on a tour of Zakho after the meeting to show him the allied security presence. An American military helicopter later flew General Ali to a guerrilla checkpoint above Zakho, where he ordered his followers to let the waiting refugees pass.  'The Way Is Open. Go.'</p>
        <p>"The Pesh Merga said to go," said 36-year-old Anwar Khalil Sidiq, who arrived with his wife and five children at the tent city tonight. "They said: 'The way is open. Go.' "</p>
        <p>"They never said this before," he said. "We are happy to be here, but we are extremely upset. My brother's child died in the mountains."</p>
        <p>At his outpost beside the rubble of the former mountain village of Kani Masi this evening, General Ali refused to comment on today's events, saying he had a toothache.</p>
        <p>American and British Marine officers met with General Ali on Sunday at Kani Masi to try to persuade him to let the refugees pass the guerrilla checkpoint. After the meeting the rebel general said that no order to allow the refugees to pass could be given without the approval of Massoud Barzani, who leads one of the main Kurdish rebel groups.  British Transport Refugees</p>
        <p>"I know he was going to go up to see Barzani and they were going to talk about it," said Lieut. Col. John Hogan of the Marines, who was at Sunday's meeting. "It appeared that their information was somewhat faulted, that their impression was that the Iraqi presence was much stronger in Zakho than it actually is."</p>
        <p>British Royal Marines transported about 70 refugees, along with a goat and two sheep, from the checkpoint after the guerrilla barriers came down. "One bloke asked if he could bring his dog," said Sgt. Robbie Robinson of the Royal Marines. "We said, 'Yeah, bring what you like.' "</p>
        <p>"We just drove and started picking people up when we saw them," he said. "We've started the ball rolling."</p>
        <p>With the refugee logjam apparently broken at the Pesh Merga checkpoints, the questions now focus on how many of the refugees are willing to walk back over the mountains to Iraq, and whether the allied relief operation in Iraq is ready to receive them.</p>
        <p>Aid officials are uncertain about how many refugees will seek shelter at the sole American-built tent city and how many will move directly back into their homes. Colonel Hogan said planners believed that only a fraction of the refugees would choose the tent city.  Tents for 6,000 People</p>
        <p>The 1,180 tents now in the refugee camp near Zakho can hold about 6,000 people, said Lieut. Col. Mike Hess of the 353d Civil Affairs Command of the Army, based in the Bronx. He added that the camp would eventually have room for about 20,000 people.</p>
        <p>The United States plans to build several tent cities east of Zakho to absorb returning refugees, and military units began work several days ago to expand the safe-haven zone, arranging for the Iraqi armed forces and security troops to move from the area. "We are just kicking the can down the road a little every day," General Garner said.</p>
        <p>Deep in the mountains about 70 miles east of Zakho, American and British Marines today reconnoitered roads that will be used to transport supplies to the planned tent cities.</p>
        <p>"Right now we're taking a look at the route," said Capt. Keil Gentry of the Marines at an Iraqi Army checkpoint. "It's very sensitive. We are not out here to start a war; we're out here to peacefully move the Iraqis out and protect the Kurds."</p>
        <p>A member of an Iraqi tank crew at the checkpoint said his men were awaiting orders to pull back to the town of Dohuk, but it is uncertain whether the Iraqi troops have received withdrawal orders.</p>
        <p>AFTER THE WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
