<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amazon Advocate's Unsettling Vision</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUTZENBERGER, JOSE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE173DF933A05757C0A967958260" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amazon Advocate's Unsettling Vision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>BRASILIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALONE in a cottage, deep in a forest here, lives a man with unruly white hair and an unsettling vision of the world.</p>
        <p>"Modern industrial society is a fanatic religion," Jose Antonio Lutzenberger said recently, his hands and hair flying. "We are demolishing, poisoning, destroying all life systems on the planet."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALONE in a cottage, deep in a forest here, lives a man with unruly white hair and an unsettling vision of the world.</p>
        <p>"Modern industrial society is a fanatic religion," Jose Antonio Lutzenberger said recently, his hands and hair flying. "We are demolishing, poisoning, destroying all life systems on the planet."</p>
        <p>Unlike traditional prophets, this 64-year-old visionary has a fax machine and a Government title: Special Secretary for the Environment. No hermit, this agronomist has become the most traveled member of the year-old Government of President Fernando Collor de Mello.</p>
        <p>Drawing on his fluent English and German, Mr. Lutzenberger has taken part in environmental meetings from London to Nairobi, from New York to Geneva. Today he is credited with having single-handedly reversed an international perception that the Brazilian Government is indifferent to the fate of the Amazon rain forests.</p>
        <p>Dressed in blue jeans and a safari shirt, Mr. Lutzenberger elaborated recently here over lunch on his environmental vision.</p>
        <p>"Destroying the Amazon is like auctioning the 'Mona Lisa' to a room full of shoeshine boys," he said. "The valuable work of art might be sold for a few dollars. Very important bidders are absent. Future generations are absent." Prospect of a Dead Planet</p>
        <p>He said modern industrial society was driving human beings to exhaust the earth's atmosphere and resources.</p>
        <p>"We are signing I.O.U.'s that our children cannot pay," warned Mr. Lutzenberger, the son of German immigrants to southern Brazil."We are acting as if we were the last generation on the planet." Without a radical change in course, he said, the earth will end up "like Venus -- a dead planet."</p>
        <p>While many environmentalists advocate recycling as a means of reducing the consumption of limited resources, Mr. Lutzenberger dismisses such proposals as "technical fixes."</p>
        <p>"We can't extend the model of Germany and the United States to the rest of the world," he said. "A world with three billion or more private cars is unthinkable. So is a world with thousands of big chemical complexes and thousands of nuclear or coal-fired stations. So we must think of something else."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutzenberger's voice seems destined to win a wider audience in coming months. Rio de Janeiro is to act as host next year to the United Nations' Second World Conference on Environment and Development. Before that meeting, the Brazilian environmentalist may have to address increasing criticism at home that his only achievement so far has been cosmetic: improving Brazil's image overseas.  Accused of Wasting Time</p>
        <p>His critics say Mr. Lutzenberger often wastes time and energy on minutiae, berating gardeners at the environmental institute over the use of pesticides or feuding with a passenger who had insisted on smoking on the Rio-Brasilia air shuttle.</p>
        <p>Last May, Mr. Lutzenberger criticized Brazil's environmental agency for having twice as many employees in Brasilia and Rio de Janeiro as in Brazil's nine Amazonian states. Almost a year later, he has done little to decentralize the agency.</p>
        <p>Reflecting his aversion to dealing with administrative details, he moved last year to the National Park of Brasilia, where he now conducts most business from his residence, the former park director's cottage.</p>
        <p>In the capital, critics assert that the Collor Government is more interested in image than substance. They say the federal Government paid $440,000 last year to film a three-hour television special on the Amazon for world distribution, while the environmental agency spent only $1 million fighting fires in the Amazon.  Winning Grants and Loans</p>
        <p>As environmental ambassador, Mr. Lutzenberger has helped win a significant amount of money for Brazilian environmental projects, notably $150 million in grants from Germany and $117 million in low-interest loans from the World Bank. But Government budget officials refuse to release the money that would be the Brazilian counterpart for the World Bank loan, which means that the country has been paying interest on the loan without receiving any disbursements.</p>
        <p>Asked about these and other problems, Mr. Lutzenberger said with an irritated wave of the hand: "I have to work with insensitive bureaucrats and tunnel-vision technocrats. I'm interested in philosophy. These technical details do not interest me."</p>
        <p>In a rare interview last year with Brazilian journalists, Mr. Lutzenberger told reporters from O Globo, a Rio de Janiero newspaper, "It's not with plans and projects that things are resolved, but with a new philosophy."</p>
        <p>Among sympathizers for his philosophy, opinions are divided.</p>
        <p>"With Lutzenberger, Brazil has reaped spectacular benefits in terms of international public image," said Stephan Schwartzman, a senior scientist for the Environmental Defense Fund in Washington. "But all the Brazilian environmentalists say there has been little real change."</p>
        <p>Taking a different tack, Thomas J. Lovejoy, assistant secretary for external affairs at the Smithsonian Instititution, said, "Nobody looked to Moses for management skills."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
