<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="16SPAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/16/arts/16SPAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1551049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEED91130F935A25752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="5801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 36-01 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. One of the largest collections of moving-image artifacts. Through Feb. 8, the Fifth New York Film Critics Circle Series, with screenings introduced by various film critics. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''To Die For'' (1995), by Gus Van Sant, starring Nicole Kidman and introduced by Megan Lehmann; at 4:15 p.m., ''Privilege'' (1967), by Peter Watkins, introduced by Armond White. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Miami Blues'' (1990), by George Armitage, introduced by Mike D'Angelo; at 4 p.m. ''Dead Ringers'' (1988), by David Cronenberg, introduced by Nathan Lee. Other screenings this weekend: tonight at 7:30 p.m., and tomorrow and Sunday at 6:30 p.m., ''Nights of Cabiria'' (1957), by Federico Fellini. On view through November, ''Tim Burton Drawings,'' an exhibition of more than 24 drawings, watercolors and sketches related to his films. Museum hours: Wednesdays through Thursdays, noon to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; and by appointment. Film and video showings are free with admission unless otherwise noted. Museum admission: $10; 65+ and students, $7.50; ages 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger and for everyone, Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m.; Friday evenings screenings are extra. Information: (718) 784-0077 or www.movingimage.us.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing of events, fairs and festivals in the New York region this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 36-01 35th Avenue, at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. One of the largest collections of moving-image artifacts. Through Feb. 8, the Fifth New York Film Critics Circle Series, with screenings introduced by various film critics. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''To Die For'' (1995), by Gus Van Sant, starring Nicole Kidman and introduced by Megan Lehmann; at 4:15 p.m., ''Privilege'' (1967), by Peter Watkins, introduced by Armond White. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Miami Blues'' (1990), by George Armitage, introduced by Mike D'Angelo; at 4 p.m. ''Dead Ringers'' (1988), by David Cronenberg, introduced by Nathan Lee. Other screenings this weekend: tonight at 7:30 p.m., and tomorrow and Sunday at 6:30 p.m., ''Nights of Cabiria'' (1957), by Federico Fellini. On view through November, ''Tim Burton Drawings,'' an exhibition of more than 24 drawings, watercolors and sketches related to his films. Museum hours: Wednesdays through Thursdays, noon to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; and by appointment. Film and video showings are free with admission unless otherwise noted. Museum admission: $10; 65+ and students, $7.50; ages 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger and for everyone, Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m.; Friday evenings screenings are extra. Information: (718) 784-0077 or www.movingimage.us.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. The recently reopened Arthur Ross Hall of Meteorites, with the 34-ton Ahnighito meteorite, the world's largest, on display. ''Petra: Lost City of Stone,'' with objects from the ancient Jordanian city, as well as 19th-century drawings and prints; through July 6; timed tickets to the exhibition are $19; students and 60+, $16.50; children under 12, $13. ''Vietnam: Journeys of Body, Mind and Spirit,'' an exhibition on Vietnamese life with photography, sculpture, clothing and other items; through March 7. ''Seasons of Life and Land: Arctic National Wildlife Refuge,'' a display of more than 40 large-format photographs by Subhankar Banerjee; through March 7. ''Living in America: The Haitian Experience,'' a celebration of Haitian culture continues. Tomorrow at 1:30 and 4 p.m., a musical performance by La Troupe Makandal; at 3 p.m., a panel discussion about voodoo as a source of inspiration in the Linder Theater. Sunday at noon and 2 p.m., voodoo drumming and dance; at 1 p.m., a lecture about Vodou Ritual Dances; at 4 p.m., a musical performance by La Troupe Makandal. In the Imax Theater, ''Volcanoes of the Deep Sea,'' documenting expeditions to the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, and ''India: Kingdom of the Tiger,'' a docudrama about a hunting expedition by Jim Corbett, an early-20th-century writer and conservationist. Tickets to one Imax feature, including museum admission, are $19; students and 60+, $12.50; children under 12, $10. General museum suggested admission: $12; students and 60+, $9; 12 and younger, $7; under 2, free. Combination ticket, including museum and Rose Center admission and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $22; students and 60+, $16.50; 12 and younger, $13; under 2, free. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m., except the first Friday of most months, when the Rose Center is open until 8:45 for ''Starry Nights''; tonight the Winard Harper Sextet is featured. Information: amnh.org, (212) 769-5100 or (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY'S ROSE CENTER FOR EARTH AND SPACE, Central Park West at 81st Street. Hours: daily, 10 a.m to 5:45 p.m. The Rose Center is open on Friday nights until 8:45. Space shows run every half-hour all day. Suggested admission to the museum, which includes the Rose Center: $12; students and 60+, $9; 2 to 12, $7; under 2, free. Combined admission to the museum, the Rose Center and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $21; students and 60+, $15.50; 2 to 12, $12.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100. Reservations: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>FRAUNCES TAVERN MUSEUM, 54 Pearl Street, second floor, Lower Manhattan. The museum, in a former tavern, is dedicated to the study and interpretation of early American history and culture. One of the period-room displays is the Long Room, the site of George Washington's farewell address. ''Colonists, Revolutionaries, Builders: Freemasons in America,'' with material relating to Washington, Paul Revere, Benjamin Franklin and Lafayette; ''Washington at War,'' with a look at his battle experiences; and ''The Societies of the Sons of the Revolution,'' devoted to the patriotic deeds of the 28 state societies. Other permanent exhibitions are the Clinton Room, named for George Clinton, the first American-born governor of New York, and a re-creation of an early-19th-century private dining room. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; closed Sundays and Mondays. Admission: $3; $2 for those under 18 and 65+; free for children under 6. Information: (212) 425-1778.</p>
        <p>HISPANIC SOCIETY OF AMERICA, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Washington Heights. Dedicated to Hispanic culture, with fine and decorative arts of the Iberian Peninsula from prehistory to the present. ''Convergence and Diversity: Art of the Hispanic World,'' a mini-exhibition highlighting treasures from the collection, including recent acquisitions not yet exhibited; several Roman pieces from the era of the Spanish-born Emperors Trajan and Hadrian will be on view through Aug. 10. Gallery talk tomorrow at noon by Dr. Marcus B. Burke, curator of paintings. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 926-2234.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. Tomorrow night at 7:30 and 9, performance by Risky Business, a bluegrass group. Part of the weekend Tavern Concert Series. Admission, $12; $10 for members ($1 off for participants taking part in the ''Cool New York'' series. More than 25 buildings from the late 17th to the 19th century, restored and furnished, now decorated for the holidays, with demonstrations of holiday activities. Museum admission: $5; 62+, $4; students and children 5 to 17, $3; free for children under 5 and members of the Staten Island Historical Society. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. This preserved late-Federal brick house with a Greek Revival interior, once owned by Seabury Tredwell, a wealthy hardware dealer, was built in 1832. The house holds the original furniture, clothing and personal articles of the Tredwells, who lived there for nearly 100 years. Self-guided tours are available on weekdays; guided tours on Saturdays and Sundays. Current exhibitions: ''The Tredwells: A Family Tree in Pictures,'' through Jan. 30; ''The Changing Silhouette of Fashion: Six Decades of Tredwell Costumes,'' through Feb. 16. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $3; members and children under 12, free. Reservations and information: (212) 777-1089.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. The museum collects, preserves and presents material related to the city's history. ''Glass and Glamour: Steuben's Modern Moment, 1930-1960'' captures a pivotal moment in 20th-century design when Steuben Glass embraced the vocabulary of modernism and linked its image to the glamour of New York City; through April 25. ''Big and Green: Toward Sustainable Architecture in the 21st Century'' explores large-scale development that is simultaneously energy-efficient, healthful for its inhabitants and economically viable; through Monday. Hours: Tuesdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. for registered groups only; Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $7; 62+, students and children, $4; families, $12. Information: (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. A collection of taped radio and television broadcasts and exhibitions in other media, including drawings, posters and photographs. Tomorrow through Feb. 22, marathon screenings of HBO's ''Sex in the City.'' Season One, episodes 1 to 6, tomorrow from 1 to 4 p.m. Season One, episodes 7 to 12, Sunday, 1 to 4 p.m. ''A Celebration of George Balanchine: Selected Television Work,'' through March 7. ''Hello, I'm Johnny Cash,'' a screening series covering the country singer's career, in four parts; through Jan. 25, Part Four: ''The Man In Black (1970-present).'' Presented with a companion radio listening series, ''The Man in Black: Johnny Cash on Radio,'' through Feb. 1. Screenings Tuesdays through Sundays at 2 p.m., and Thursdays at 6 p.m. Also on display, ''Backstage at CBS-TV's Chronoscope: A Portrait of the Post-World War II Era,'' an exhibition of photographs from 1951-1955, through January. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $10; $8 for students and 62+; $5 for children 12 and younger. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 2 West 77th Street, Manhattan. ''Picturing Need: Poverty and Its Relief in New York, 1736-2002,'' an exhibition of paintings, prints, drawings, documents and photographs demonstrating the various efforts over time at improving the lives of the needy in New York City; through January. ''Recovery: The World Trade Center Recovery Operation at Fresh Kills,'' an exhibition of more than 50 photographs; through March 21. ''The Birds of Central Park: Audubon's Watercolors,'' 431 original watercolors created by John James Audubon (1785-1851) for ''The Birds of America'' (1827-38); through Feb. 15.''Children at Risk: Protecting New York City's Youths 1653-2003,'' paintings, prints, maps and documents from the society's collection as well as those from the Children's Aid Society and the New York City Municipal Archives; through April 4. ''Ann Zane Shanks: Behind the Lens,'' photography exhibition; through Feb. 29. ''Home Sewn: Three Centuries of Stitching History,'' through April 18. The Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture is a permanent gallery on the fourth floor. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; children and 62+, $5. Information: (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY, Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street. ''Depression-Era Prints and Photographs From the W.P.A. and F.S.A.,'' an exhibition of more than 70 works by Dorothea Lange, Arthur Rothstein, John Collier and others, on view through tomorrow. ''Russia Engages the World, 1453-1825,'' an exhibition of books, manuscripts and other works on paper, on display through January. Free. Hours: Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 11 a.m. to 7:30 p.m.; Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; closed Sundays, Mondays and holidays. Free guided tours are available daily at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. Exhibition information: (212) 869-8089; www.nyl.org.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM AND MARKETPLACE, South and Fulton Streets, Lower Manhattan. In this 19th-century port district with restaurants, shops and bars, the museum has galleries, a maritime crafts center and a fleet of historic vessels. Two new exhibitions on view through April. ''Captive Passage: The Transatlantic Slave Trade,'' a display of African art and artifacts, and ''By the Gladness of the River: Creativity at the Seaport, 1950 to the Present,'' photographs of artists, writers, composers and others who have lived or worked in the area. Hours: daily 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission, $8, $6 for students and 65+; $4 for children 5 to 12; free for members and children under 5. Information: (212) 748-8600. Information: (212) 748-8600; the marketplace, (212) 732-7678.</p>
        <p>Garden</p>
        <p>QUEENS BOTANICAL GARDEN, 43-50 Main Street, Flushing. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''Healing With Food, Part II,'' a workshop that focuses on Eastern healing traditions and modern nutrition. Second in a series devoted to food, herbs and health; fee: $10; $5 for members. In bloom: Christmas roses. Garden Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Free. Information: (718) 886-3800.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>LUNAR NEW YEAR CELEBRATION, Mott and Canal Streets, Chinatown. Events celebrating the Year of the Monkey begin tomorrow at 2 p.m. with music and dancing. On Sunday at 2 p.m., there will be acrobatic and martial arts displays. Sponsored by the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association. Information: (212) 764-6331.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES. Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Monk Mania at the Cloisters,'' a scavenger hunt for adults inside the Inwood branch of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Fee: $30, includes museum admission. Meeting place and other information: (212) 726-1529.</p>
        <p>SCHUBERT'S ''WINTER,'' CUNY Graduate Center, 365 Fifth Avenue at 34th Street, Manhattan. A staged performance of Schubert's song cycle. Featuring Lynn Redgrave, narrator; Terry Cook, bass-baritone; Caroline Stoessinger, pianist. Sunday at 4 p.m. Donation: $10. Information: (212) 817-8215.</p>
        <p>MARTIN LUTHER KING JR. CELEBRATION CONCERT, nave, Riverside Church, 490 Riverside Drive, at 120th Street, Morningside Heights. With readings and inspirational music, featuring church choirs and musical groups, Ebony Ecumenical Ensemble and Coro Cantico Nuevo. Sunday at 4 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 870-6722.</p>
        <p>''MYTHS AND LEGENDS OF THE GREEK PEOPLE,'' Bohemian Hall, 29-19 24th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. An event with storytelling, poetry, theater, music and dance. Sunday at 2:15 p.m. In Greek and English. Sponsored by Cypreco of America (Cypriot Immigrants Cultural Organization of America). Donations accepted. Information: (718) 626-7896.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN PUBLIC LIBRARY, Grand Army Plaza, at Prospect Park. Readings by authors featuring Colin Channer tomorrow at 2 p.m. (part of the Caribbean Author Series); and Junot Díaz, Rhina P. Espaillat and César Sánchez Beras, Sunday at 2 p.m. (part of the Dominican Author Series). Information: (718) 230-2100.</p>
        <p>GRAND CENTRAL HOLIDAY TRAIN SHOW, New York Transit Museum Gallery Annex at Grand Central Terminal. Includes a model of the terminal. Free. Hours: today and Monday, 8 a.m. to 8 p.m.; tomorrow and Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Through Monday. Information: (212) 878-0106.</p>
        <p>''NEW YEAR'S SAMURAI SPECTACLE,'' Sol Goldman 14th Street Y.M.-Y.W.H.A., 344 East 14th Street, East Village. A celebration of the Japanese New Year featuring samurai sword performances, rice pounding, music and dance. Sunday, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $7; children 3 and up, $5. Sponsored by the Japanese Parenting and Family Center at the Y. Information: (212) 780-0800, Extension 224.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS. Today at 1 p.m., ''Greenwich Village'' covers the neighborhood with a special emphasis on its history and architecture, meeting at the Washington Arch. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''The 'Official' Gangs of New York Tour,'' led in conjunction with Miramax Films, exploring the history, people, legends and lore of Five Points, meeting on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street. Tomorrow at 2 p.m. ''Immigrant Labor, Immigrant Triumph,'' covering the history of the garment industry in New York, meeting at the Washington Arch. Sunday at 1 p.m., ''The Multi-Ethnic Eating Tour'' exploring the cuisine of the Jewish East Side, Chinatown and Little Italy, meeting at Essex and Delancey Streets. Fee for each tour, $12; students and 63+, $10; $16 for eating tour; $14 for students and 63+. Information: (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING. Four tours tomorrow: at 10 a.m., ''Thought for Food'' visits the Upper West Side, meeting on the northwest corner of 79th Street and Broadway; at noon, ''Haunted Midtown Area,'' with stops at several haunted homes and buildings, meeting on the northwest corner of 57th Street and Seventh Avenue; at 1:45 p.m., ''Fine Flatiron District,'' including a stop at the birthplace of Theodore Roosevelt and the former sites of the Lord &amp; Taylor and Arnold Constable department stores, meeting on the northwest corner of 23rd Street and Fifth Avenue; at 4 p.m., ''Cosmopolitan Yorkville,'' including stops at Gracie Mansion, the Henderson Place Historic District and the former site of the Ruppert Brewery, meeting on the southwest corner of 86th Street and Lexington Avenue. Fee for each, $5. Information: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY. Today at 11 a.m., ''Downtown: Inside and Out,'' a walk from Bowling Green to Wall Street with stops at various historical landmarks, meeting at the National Museum of the American Indian at 1 Bowling Green. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''The Park in Winter'' explores the structures and sculptures of Central Park, meeting at the General Sherman Monument, Fifth Avenue at 59th Street. Sunday at noon ''Manhattanville: Hidden in Plain Sight,'' a tour of the West Harlem neighborhood, the focus of new development plans, meeting at the southwest corner of 125th Street and Broadway. Monday at 11 a.m., ''Touring Martin Luther King Jr. Boulevard (125th Street), from Lenox Avenue to the Hudson River, meeting at the Lenox Lounge, southeast corner of Lenox Avenue and 125th Street. Fee for weekday tours, $12, $10 for members; weekends, $15 and $12. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS, N.Y. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Crimes of Old New York,'' a historical walking tour of crimes in New York City, meeting at the Museum of the American Indian, 1 Bowling Green. Tomorrow at 6 p.m., ''Joe Sent Me: A Historic Speak-Easy Tour'' passes three former speak-easies in SoHo and Greenwich Village and many historic cast-iron buildings, meeting at Dean &amp; DeLuca, southeast corner of Broadway and Prince Street, SoHo; refreshments not included. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Dandies, Dudes and Shady Ladies'' explores the low-life haunts of Soho and the Bowery, meeting at the subway kiosk at Astor Place; not recommended for children. Fee for each: $10. Information: (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>ALL POINTS TOURS. Tomorrow and Sunday at at 1 p.m., ''World Trade Center Site: Ground Zero,'' with stops at the Winter Garden, St. Paul's Chapel and buildings under construction, meeting in front of the Stage Door Deli, northeast corner of Church and Vesey Streets, Lower Manhattan. Fee: $12; for 60+, $10. Information: (718) 273-1813.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK GALLERY TOURS. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Art Gallery Walking Tour in Chelsea'' visits 10 modern art galleries with exhibitions of painting, sculpture, electronic media and photography, meeting at the lobby of 526 West 26th Street. Fee: $15. Information: (212) 946-1548.</p>
        <p>DR. PHIL: NEW YORK TALKS AND WALKS. Tomorrow through Monday at 1:30 p.m., ''Welcome to the Neighborhood: Bill Clinton's Harlem,'' meeting in front of the former president's Harlem office, 55 West 125th Street. Sunday at 10:30 a.m., ''When Harlem was Yiddish,'' passing religious sites as well as homes and shops, meeting in front of Mr. Clinton's office. Fee for each, $15. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE. Today through Sunday at 2 p.m., a tour of historic sites, landmarks and ethnic groups in Brooklyn in the Fort Greene, Clinton Hill and Brooklyn Heights neighborhoods. Sunday at 10 a.m., a tour of downtown Brooklyn with a stop for gospel music. Both meet in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, Downtown Brooklyn. Fee for each, $25. Information: (718) 789-0430.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
