<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nokia Warns Of Slowdown In the Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y24NOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/business/worldbusiness/24NOKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1459157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nokia Oy Ab</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapner, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ollila, Jorma</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nokia Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D91F30F937A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nokia Warns Of Slowdown In the Quarter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nokia Warns of Slowdown in the Quarter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE KAPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kapner, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Jan. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nokia warns that sales and earnings growth will slow early this year, even as it reports fourth-quarter profit that slightly exceeds expectations; says fourth-quarter sales grew 1 percent, to 8.84 billion euros ($9.5 billion), from 8.78 billion euros year earlier; net income grew 8 percent, to 1.25 billion euros compared with 1.15 billion euros year ago; chief executive Jorma Ollila comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nokia, the world's largest manufacturer of mobile phones, warned today that sales and earnings growth would slow early this year, even as it reported a fourth-quarter profit that slightly exceeded expectations.</p>
        <p>The mobile phone industry has been squeezed between consumers, who have been slow to buy new phones with updated features like color screens and cameras, and operators, who have delayed building new infrastructure to conserve cash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nokia, the world's largest manufacturer of mobile phones, warned on Thursday that sales and earnings growth would slow early this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nokia, the world's largest manufacturer of mobile phones, warned today that sales and earnings growth would slow early this year, even as it reported a fourth-quarter profit that slightly exceeded expectations.</p>
        <p>The mobile phone industry has been squeezed between consumers, who have been slow to buy new phones with updated features like color screens and cameras, and operators, who have delayed building new infrastructure to conserve cash.</p>
        <p>As a result, the financial performance of even the industry leaders like Nokia, which makes two of every five handsets sold, has tended to seesaw.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of mixed information coming out of these companies,'' James Heal of Commerzbank Securities said. ''The industry is in a sort of no man's land.''</p>
        <p>Jorma Ollila, Nokia's chairman and chief executive, acknowledged the difficulty of making accurate financial predictions in the current environment. ''We are living in a particularly uncertain world,'' Mr. Ollila told analysts today on a conference call. ''We're cautious, yes, but also realistic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ollila said that Nokia expected market conditions to remain challenging, and his cautiousness was evident in the financial targets Nokia provided for the first quarter, which were lower than some analysts had anticipated.</p>
        <p>At worst, Nokia, based in Espoo, Finland, said first-quarter revenue in its handset division, the company's largest, might not show any growth in the period or, at best, might grow as much as 9 percent. Nokia said revenue for the entire company, which also includes a division that makes network equipment, was likely to grow at an even slower pace than the range forecast for the handset unit.</p>
        <p>Nokia said it expected to report first-quarter earnings of 15 cents to 19 cents a share, compared with 19 cents a share in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Shares of Nokia closed down nearly 5 percent, to 13.59 euros, in trading in Helsinki. In New York, its American depository receipts -- each representing one share of the company -- fell 64 cents, or 4.3 percent, to $14.30.</p>
        <p>Even though Nokia's sales in the fourth quarter grew an anemic 1 percent, to 8.84 billion euros ($9.5 billion), from 8.78 billion euros a year earlier, the company managed to increase earnings by cutting costs, increasing its market share and using its buying power to negotiate the best terms with suppliers, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Nokia said it increased its market share for handsets in the fourth quarter to 39 percent, more than double that of its nearest rival, Motorola of the United States.</p>
        <p>Net income, excluding good will, amortization and nonrecurring items, grew 8 percent in the fourth quarter, to 1.25 billion euros, or 26 cents a share, compared with 1.15 billion euros, or 24 cents a share, a year earlier. A consensus of analysts polled by Reuters expected the company to earn 24 cents a share in the recent period.</p>
        <p>''There's something for the bears and something for the bulls,'' said Richard Wiseman of Insight Investment Management. ''Most of the numbers are within the consensus range, but the earnings guidance for the first quarter was disappointing.''</p>
        <p>With some rivals low on cash, Nokia is in the enviable position of having more than $9 billion on hand. The company said today that it would begin using that money to buy back its own stock, beginning in March, once its annual shareholders meeting has been held.</p>
        <p>After declining slightly last year, the number of handsets sold worldwide grew this year by 5 percent, to 405 million, according to Nokia's estimates.</p>
        <p>Nokia has introduced new models like phones with cameras, color screens and the ability to download video clips from the Internet. But so far consumers have tended to shun the more expensive models in favor of more basic phones that sell for less.</p>
        <p>Lauri Kivinen, a Nokia spokesman, said the average sales price for handsets probably hit bottom in the fourth quarter and was likely to rise later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
