<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hitler's Secretary Looks Back in Sorrow</title>
    <meta content="24BLIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/movies/24BLIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1459109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World War II</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hitler, Adolf</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DF1F30F937A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hitler's Secretary Looks Back in Sorrow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hitler's Secretary Looks Back in Sorrow</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary'' was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Elvis Mitchell's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 10; the full text is online at nytimes.com/movies. The subtitled German-language documentary opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>It probably makes sense for filmmakers not to prod an 81-year-old woman too hard, and the gentleness extended to the subject of ''Blind Spot'' seems to grow out of such courtesy. That 81-year-old woman, though, is Traudl Junge, and the full title of the documentary is ''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary.'' She was secretary to Hitler from 1942 through the end of the war. The access the filmmakers gained to Junge is remarkable, and it compensates for a lack of cinematic flair; it's concrete, cold and hard, with Junge speaking about being a few feet away from arguably the worst tyrant of the 20th century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A riveting examination of how a young girl with no plan for her life found herself in the bunker with Hitler at the end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary'' was shown as part of last year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Elvis Mitchell's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 10; the full text is online at nytimes.com/movies. The subtitled German-language documentary opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>It probably makes sense for filmmakers not to prod an 81-year-old woman too hard, and the gentleness extended to the subject of ''Blind Spot'' seems to grow out of such courtesy. That 81-year-old woman, though, is Traudl Junge, and the full title of the documentary is ''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary.'' She was secretary to Hitler from 1942 through the end of the war. The access the filmmakers gained to Junge is remarkable, and it compensates for a lack of cinematic flair; it's concrete, cold and hard, with Junge speaking about being a few feet away from arguably the worst tyrant of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>This is by no means a great film. The plain-wrap sameness of the camerawork would be unforgivable if not for the woman who can't quite look into the lens, even now; the unshakable shame coming from this woman accounts for a great deal. The Third Reich was such a part of her life that she ended up marrying Hitler's manservant.</p>
        <p>The film says she never spoke about her time with Hitler until she agreed to be interviewed for ''Blind Spot.'' (She died in February after a long bout with cancer and just hours after the film's premiere in Berlin.)</p>
        <p>The wave of regrets and rationalizations she spins is an incredible thing to witness. Perhaps it's fortunate that the filmmakers don't exercise a great deal of technique: the entirety of ''Blind Spot'' is Junge speaking right into the camera, with blackouts between the various confessions to break them up. It's possible, too, that the documentary's Austrian filmmakers, André Heller and Othmar Schmiderer, don't have much technique to exercise, but it would be a waste to empty into this project anyway. The understanding -- and it's the right one -- is that their subject is plenty; there's no point in flashing things up.</p>
        <p>As she speaks in an even tone, what she provides is a view of office life, blaming herself for being a part of it. She reveals that she could have refused the job. ''But I didn't do that because I was simply too curious,'' she allows. And it's the minutiae she offers -- a kind of crime-scene analysis, an accretion of small details like Hitler's affection for his dog and the minor interaction he had with Eva Braun -- that are fascinating.</p>
        <p>It's tough to go into a film with such a provocative title without having expectations raised through the roof. But ''Blind Spot'' doesn't supply a huge amount of new information. Its strength is from the pieces of information Junge offers about herself; her plain-spoken quality about being so close to ultimate evil and how much of it she managed to shield herself from tells us a great deal about ourselves.</p>
        <p>It's reminiscent of an old routine of Richard Pryor's in which he talked about the fronting bluster that tough brothers said they would show versus the reality of how quickly they buckle under. The old saw carries a great deal of pain; clichés are so overused because they're true. Junge talks about how easily Germans went along with the plan, offering a stereotypical observation that falling into place behind Hitler fit into the national personality: ''The Germans are very good at organizing.''</p>
        <p>''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary'' won't change anyone's mind about the horrors of the Third Reich because what you get from it is a riveting examination of how a young girl with no plan for her life and a bullying father found herself in the bunker with Hitler at the end.</p>
        <p>''Blind Spot: Hitler's Secretary'' is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It has descriptions of violence.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
