<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Rise on Job Data And Iraqi Troop Buildup</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DE113DF93BA35753C1A962958260" item-length="518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Rise on Job Data And Iraqi Troop Buildup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks rallied yesterday after a three-session slide, bolstered first by the September jobs report and then by news of an Iraqi buildup of troops near the Kuwaiti border.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department reported yesterday that nonfarm employment rose by 239,000 jobs, below widespread expectations on Wall Street of an increase of over 250,000.  In addition, the unemployment rate dropped to a four-year low of 5.9 percent, from 6.1 percent in August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks rallied yesterday after a three-session slide, bolstered first by the September jobs report and then by news of an Iraqi buildup of troops near the Kuwaiti border.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department reported yesterday that nonfarm employment rose by 239,000 jobs, below widespread expectations on Wall Street of an increase of over 250,000.  In addition, the unemployment rate dropped to a four-year low of 5.9 percent, from 6.1 percent in August.</p>
        <p>This lessened the likelihood of an immediate increase in interest rates by the Federal Reserve to contain inflation and brought relief to the stock market. Bonds also benefited, and the yield on the bellwether 30-year Treasury bond declined to 7.90 percent, from 7.95 percent on Thursday.</p>
        <p>"Everybody was waiting for the employment numbers and they were weaker than expected," said Robert Freedman, president of John Hancock Mutual Funds. "That took some of the uncertainty out of the market and we had a pretty broad rally."</p>
        <p>The gains in secondary issues were significantly greater than in blue chips. The Nasdaq composite index rose 5.77 points, to 749.96, while the Dow Jones industrial average advanced 21.87 points, to 3,797.43.  The Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks increased 2.74 points, to 455.10.</p>
        <p>"The growth areas of the stock market are starting to look interesting," Mr. Freedman said. "If the economy slows down to an increase of 3 or 3.5 percent in the gross domestic product, growth stocks may be more attractive than cyclical stocks."</p>
        <p>Advances on the New York Stock Exchange topped declines, 1,245 to 946. Volume rose to 285.6 million shares from Wednesday's level of 271.4 million shares.</p>
        <p>Oil issues surged after reports of troop movements in Iraq and an increase in crude oil prices. Crude oil for November delivery surged as much as 45 cents before closing at $18.26, up 1 cent, on the New York Mercantile Exchange. Exxon was up 1 1/2, to 58 5/8; Texaco rose 1 1/8, to 61 1/8, and Chevron climbed 1, to 42 1/4.</p>
        <p>Stocks of arms makers also gained, not only on the news from Iraq but also on reports that President Clinton had sent an aircraft carrier to the Persian Gulf. United Technologies advanced 1/2, to 62 1/8; Northrop Grumman rose 5/8, to 46 1/8, and Raytheon increased 3/8, to 63 3/4.</p>
        <p>Some retailers that had announced increases in same-store sales on Thursday also performed well yesterday. Nordstrom closed at 44, up 2 7/8, and Ann Taylor gained 1/4, to 39 1/4.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. reached a two-year high, climbing 2 3/8, to 71 1/8. The company is expected to have a profit in the third quarter, compared with a loss a year earlier, which some analysts see as a sign that overall corporate earnings for the quarter will be strong.</p>
        <p>Motorola, which had been weak in recent days, rose 1 5/8, to 50 3/4. And United Healthcare, a health maintenance organization with steady margins and expectations of good third-quarter results, advanced 1 3/4, to 53 1/4.</p>
        <p>In Tokyo, stocks ended higher. The Nikkei index of 225 issues closed up 89.52 points, or a half of 1 percent, at 19,744.75. On Thursday, the Nikkei fell 96.32 points.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
