<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sheffield and Giambi Linked to Balco in Book</title>
    <meta content="23book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/23/sports/baseball/23book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1748919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giambi, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheffield, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fainaru-Wada, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lance</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Game of Shadows (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sheffield, Gary</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giambi, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDA1630F930A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sheffield and Giambi Linked to Balco in Book</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Yankees Linked to Balco in Book About Bonds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR; Tyler Kepner contributed reporting from Tampa, Fla., for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees players Jason Giambi and Gary Sheffield are named as steroid users in book Game of Shadows: Barry Bonds, BALCO, and the Steroids Scandal that Rocked Professional Sports, by Mark Fainaru-Wada and Lance Williams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new book that details Barry Bonds's use of performance-enhancing drugs reports that Gary Sheffield allegedly received testosterone and human growth hormone from Greg Anderson, Bonds's trainer.</p>
        <p>The book's authors had reported in The San Francisco Chronicle that Sheffield, the Yankees' right fielder, told a federal grand jury that he unknowingly used designer steroids sold to him by Anderson. Yesterday, Sheffield denied using human growth hormone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are allegations of performance-enhancing drug use by Gary Sheffield and Jason Giambi in a new book about Barry Bonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new book that details Barry Bonds's use of performance-enhancing drugs reports that Gary Sheffield allegedly received testosterone and human growth hormone from Greg Anderson, Bonds's trainer.</p>
        <p>The book's authors had reported in The San Francisco Chronicle that Sheffield, the Yankees' right fielder, told a federal grand jury that he unknowingly used designer steroids sold to him by Anderson. Yesterday, Sheffield denied using human growth hormone.</p>
        <p>''Anything else I'm linked to?'' he said in Tampa, Fla. Told it was testosterone, he said, ''Great.'' He added, ''It really doesn't matter to me.''</p>
        <p>Sheffield avoided punishment by Major League Baseball, which did not test for steroids until 2003, two years after he first trained with Bonds, and does not test for human growth hormone.</p>
        <p>The book, ''Game of Shadows: Barry Bonds, BALCO, and the Steroids Scandal that Rocked Professional Sports'' (Gotham), expands upon the award-winning reporting by Mark Fainaru-Wada and Lance Williams of The Chronicle, and is to be released today.</p>
        <p>They largely follow the parallel stories of Bonds and Victor Conte Jr., the founder of the Bay Area Laboratory Co-Operative in Burlingame, Calif. Balco specialized in performance-enhancing cocktails for athletes. Conte is serving four months in prison for steroid distribution and money laundering.</p>
        <p>Many of the allegations in the book, which are supported by grand jury transcripts, documents and interviews, have been reported in The Chronicle. Sports Illustrated also ran an extensive excerpt about Bonds earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Another Yankee, Jason Giambi, who admitted to steroid use in his grand jury testimony, according to Fainaru-Wada and Williams, is implicated in the book and shares the cover photograph with Bonds. In the book, the authors write that during a trip by major league All-Stars to Japan after the 2002 season, Bonds told Giambi that his performance-enhancing drugs were better than Giambi's.</p>
        <p>After the trip, the book reports, Giambi flew to the Bay Area, where Anderson took him to a hospital for blood and urine testing, which showed the steroid Deca Durabolin in his system.</p>
        <p>With steroid testing looming in the major leagues, the book says that Anderson advised Giambi to stop using Deca Durabolin and sold him injectable testosterone as well as Balco's the clear, which contained the steroid THG, and a testosterone-based balm dubbed the cream.</p>
        <p>Bonds, in his grand jury testimony reported in The Chronicle, testified that he thought the Balco products were flaxseed oil and an arthritis salve.</p>
        <p>The book's central subject is Bonds. The authors write of his jealousy of Mark McGwire's 70 home runs in 1998; his zealous embraceof illicit, performance-enhancing drugs; his affair with Kimberly Bell, to whom he gave $80,000 in cash from memorabilia sales and autograph sessions to help her buy a house; and his grand jury testimony, in which he reportedly denied using steroids.</p>
        <p>According to the book, he testified that he placed a couple of drops of the clear under his tongue. ''And I was like, to me, it didn't even work.'' He said that all he wanted, at age 39, was pain relief and to recover to play a day game after a night game.</p>
        <p>''I never asked Greg,'' he said, referring to Anderson. ''When he said it was flaxseed oil, I said, 'Whatever.' ''</p>
        <p>The book examines Bonds's drug-use regimen in 2002: during a three-week cycle, the authors claim, he received human growth hormone injections every other day. In between, he used the clear and the cream. At the end of the cycle, Bonds took Clomid, a fertility drug, to help him recover his natural ability to produce testosterone, which is undermined by steroid use.</p>
        <p>The book says that Anderson would go to Bonds's house to inject human growth hormone or administer the clear.</p>
        <p>The authors quote a ''source familiar with Bonds'' who described concerns expressed by Bonds's father, Bobby, the former major leaguer, about his son's steroid use. The book says that the elder Bonds, who was dying of cancer, is said to have told his son that he had his big contract and the single-season home run record. ''He should think about his life,'' the senior Bonds said, according to the authors.</p>
        <p>The book also reports that:</p>
        <p>Bonds left threatening phone calls on Bell's answering machine and, in 2003, told her she had to ''disappear,'' apparently because of the financial problems posed by funnelling cash to her that was not reported to the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>A Balco defense lawyer, Troy Ellerman, believed Bonds was lying when he said that he never knowingly took steroids. And he said that Bonds's lawyer, Michael Rains, ''made it very clear to us that he wanted us to do everything we could to make sure Barry's name was protected. There wasn't any payment involved, there weren't an threats, there wasn't any quid pro quo, but he made it very clear that Barry would appreciate it if we kept him out of it.''</p>
        <p>The sprinter Chryste Gaines, who preceded Marion Jones as a client of Balco's, gave permission to Conte to work with Jones as long as Gaines got a cut of what Jones paid. Conte eventually paid Gaines $7,350. Gaines is serving a two-year suspension by the Court of Arbitration for Sport for taking THG.</p>
        <p>Jones, who won three gold medals at the 2000 Summer Olympics, was on an aggressive, Conte-designed drug regimen -- human growth hormone, insulin, the clear, steroids and erythropoietin, or EPO -- but could be careless. In May 2001, she left a drug injector in her hotel room with what she allegedly said was a ''thousand dollars' worth of growth hormone in it.'' Jones has repeatedly denied using steroids or any other drugs.</p>
        <p>Balco's testing found that the sprinter Tim Montgomery, who would become romantically involved with Jones, was an ''out-of-control juicer.''</p>
        <p>Conte is quoted as saying, ''You're oversaturated with performance-enhancing drugs,'' and is said to have put Montgomery on a cycle of the clear and human growth hormone.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
