<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup Chief Will Add Chairman's Title, Ending Weill Era</title>
    <meta content="22citi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/22/business/22citi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1748702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prince, Charles O III</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weill, Sanford I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Citigroup Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prince, Charles O III</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Weill, Sanford I</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDE1630F931A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup Chief Will Add Chairman's Title, Ending Weill Era</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Citigroup Chief Will Add Chairman's Title, Ending Weill Era</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citigroup's board announces that chief executive Charles O Prince III will soon also hold chairman's title, which has long belonged to Sanford I Weill; election is sign of Citigroup board's confidence in Prince, even though company's financial results during his tenure have so far been mixed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of Citigroup announced yesterday that the chief executive, Charles O. Prince III, would soon also hold the chairman's title, which has long belonged to Sanford I. Weill.</p>
        <p>The decision, though not unexpected, is largely symbolic for a man who had been Mr. Weill's handpicked successor and chief executive for the last three years. But on Wall Street, where business cards and corner office nameplates are scrutinized for significance, it is the latest example of Mr. Prince putting his own stamp on the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of Citigroup announced yesterday that the chief executive, Charles O. Prince III, would soon also hold the chairman's title, which has long belonged to Sanford I. Weill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The board of Citigroup announced yesterday that the chief executive, Charles O. Prince III, would soon also hold the chairman's title, which has long belonged to Sanford I. Weill.</p>
        <p>The decision, though not unexpected, is largely symbolic for a man who had been Mr. Weill's handpicked successor and chief executive for the last three years. But on Wall Street, where business cards and corner office nameplates are scrutinized for significance, it is the latest example of Mr. Prince putting his own stamp on the company.</p>
        <p>The election is also a sign of the Citigroup board's confidence in Mr. Prince, even though the company's financial results during his tenure have so far been mixed.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Citigroup shares slipped 18 cents, to $47.22. The shares have remained virtually flat since Mr. Prince took over as chief executive in 2003.</p>
        <p>At the close of Citigroup's shareholder meeting on April 18, Mr. Prince will take on the role of chairman held by Mr. Weill, as he retires from the company.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the board gave Mr. Weill, 73, the honorary title of chairman emeritus, but he will receive no additional compensation nor participate in its meetings. He has a consulting contract with Citigroup.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Alain J. P. Belda, Citigroup's lead director and the head of Alcoa, said that the elevation of Mr. Prince recognized his ''superior leadership'' as chief executive. ''We believe he will be a strong and effective chairman,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While some investors and analysts have questioned whether Mr. Prince was up to the challenge of running a global bank, he has been on a mission to prove them wrong.</p>
        <p>Since taking the helm, Mr. Prince has begun mapping out a course to overhaul the company. With the Federal Reserve barring Citigroup from large mergers, Mr. Prince went on a campaign last year to improve the company's controls and restore its tarnished reputation. Now, he is shifting the focus toward operations overseas. And unlike Mr. Weill, a master in deal making, Mr. Prince is preaching the gospel of internal sales and profit growth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prince, 56, is also shaking up Citigroup's senior executive ranks, replacing Mr. Weill's team with his own group of younger managers.</p>
        <p>Robert B. Willumstad, Citigroup's former chief operating officer, left last summer and is now a director at American International Group, after months of speculation surrounding his next move. Marjorie Magner, who ran Citigroup's global consumer division, quit last fall to pursue other work outside of banking. Last week, Michael A. Carpenter, the head of Citigroup's alternative investments division who was close to Mr. Weill, said he planned to leave soon.</p>
        <p>While many corporate governance advocates have called for the separation of the chairman and chief executive jobs and Citigroup faces a shareholder proposal on the matter again this year, the appointment of Mr. Prince suggests the company's policy will not change.</p>
        <p>In its proxy statement, Citigroup maintained that the roles of its independent and lead directors provided adequate checks and balances.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
