<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miniatures and Hefty Dressers: Open Season on Antiques</title>
    <meta content="21VOGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1170157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDE123DF932A15752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miniatures and Hefty Dressers: Open Season on Antiques</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Previews of miniatures and other art objects at upcoming winter antiques sales in New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ads for this year's Winter Antiques Show say it is ''still setting the standard after 46 years.'' But nowhere do the ads explain what that standard is.</p>
        <p>When the show began it was the only event of its kind in New York. London had Grosvenor House and Paris had the Biennale des Antiquaires. During its early years there was always a crush of collectors elbowing their way to be the first through the heavy carved doors of the Seventh Regiment Armory to beat the competition. Now the atmosphere is more relaxed: dozens of antiques shows pack the calendar of the cavernous armory each season, and many more have opened throughout the shopping capitals of the world. With age, each develops its own standard, spirit and direction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ads for this year's Winter Antiques Show say it is ''still setting the standard after 46 years.'' But nowhere do the ads explain what that standard is.</p>
        <p>When the show began it was the only event of its kind in New York. London had Grosvenor House and Paris had the Biennale des Antiquaires. During its early years there was always a crush of collectors elbowing their way to be the first through the heavy carved doors of the Seventh Regiment Armory to beat the competition. Now the atmosphere is more relaxed: dozens of antiques shows pack the calendar of the cavernous armory each season, and many more have opened throughout the shopping capitals of the world. With age, each develops its own standard, spirit and direction.</p>
        <p>In the worldwide spectrum of antiques shows, the winter event in New York falls somewhere between the super-charged European Fine Art Fair in Maastricht in the Netherlands, where museum curators go hoping to discover something they must add to their permanent collections, and a collectibles fair like the various Wendy's Shows held several times a year.</p>
        <p>Since its inception, the Winter Antiques Show has explored all facets of American antiques and American taste, offering everything from folk art and formal American and English furniture to decorative objects like porcelains, miniatures and silver. This year is no exception. But as is true at each fair, there are a few new twists.</p>
        <p>''We've tried to broaden the show,'' said Catherine E. Sweeney, the show's director. ''Some of the new dealers are tops in their field, yet this is the first time they have ever done a show.''</p>
        <p>Seasoned visitors will notice the absence of a few prominent dealers, whose reasons for missing the show vary. Among them are Frank and Barbara Pollack, specialists in primitive paintings and painted furniture; Marguerite Riordan, whose booth always featured top-quality American paintings, needlework and furniture; America Hurrah, experts in rare quilts; and Acanthus, a Manhattan-based antiquities dealer. In their place are six dealers with specialties ranging from antique clocks and miniatures to antiquities and Continental furniture.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to persuade new dealers to exhibit. Those who participate in several shows a year moan about the dearth of good material on the market, which may explain why prices at the show are consistently high. Among the most expensive works this year is an $8 million painting by the American Impressionist Frank Weston Benson. There are also considerably cheaper finds like an $850 pair of tiny 18th-century creamware dishes or a late 19th-century Nantucket lightship basket for $1,000. And there is a lot in between, most of it catering to Wall Street moguls itching to spend their year-end bonuses, or decorators in search of just the right piece of furniture for a client, or new homeowners searching for all the trappings that make a house a home. Buyer, beware: it's quite possible to go to the show looking for something practical like a dining room table but to leave  with something whimsical like an 18th-century miniature. Dealers say they are playing to shoppers who want only the unusual.</p>
        <p>''There's a tremendous demand for the best,'' said Robert Israel, an  owner of Kentshire Galleries in Manhattan. ''The middle market has disappeared. People these days want what's truly rare.'' As an example, Mr. Israel points to a pair of shadowboxes crafted from tiny seashells, circa 1750.</p>
        <p>Sumpter Priddy III, a new dealer from Alexandria, Va., who specializes in Southern decorative and fine arts, decided to do the show because ''it exposes me to a different crowd.'' Along a center wall of his booth is a red mahogany desk and bookcase made in Richmond, Va., by a Philadelphia-trained cabinetmaker named Henry Ingle, who had done work for Thomas Jefferson and gone to Richmond to work on the state Capitol. The carving on the piece, Mr. Priddy said, was done in 1790 by William Hodgson, a British-trained carver who also worked on the state Capitol. The price is $285,000. Nearby hangs a piece of Boston-school needlework by Lydia Doggett, a girl who was growing up in the 1780's, depicting Adam and Eve with a serpent lurking in an apple tree. It costs $58,000.</p>
        <p>Another new exhibitor worth a look is the Safani Gallery, a Manhattan dealer specializing in ancient art. Among the star works in its booth is a 39-inch-tall Roman marble torso copied from a Greek statue, which Alan Safani bought from an American collector. It costs $750,000. ''I've been trying to get into this show for years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then there is Elle Shushan's Augustus Decorative Arts of Manhattan, whose tiny booth is painted light green and packed with more than 100 portrait miniatures hanging from floor to ceiling on back ribbons. One of the best is a portrait of Jasper Cropsey, a merchant captain in New York and an ancestor of the Hudson River School painter by the same name. Painted around 1780-95, it conceals a locket of the captain's hair at the back of the frame. (Miniatures carry big prices: this one costs $12,500.) Another portrait, of Frederick, Prince of Wales, son of George II, is the only known version except for two in the collection of Queen Elizabeth. Its price is $8,500.</p>
        <p>Also expensive are the antique timepieces at the booth of Jonathan Snellenburg, another Manhattan  dealer and newcomer to the show. His booth features an important French neo-Classical ormolu clock shaped like an urn, signed by the painter Denis Leve and dated 1768. The urn is adorned with a climbing serpent and Sevres porcelain panels.</p>
        <p>The show also features some 20th-century furniture and objects. Geoffrey Diner, a Washington dealer, has a Greene &amp; Greene front-porch lantern of patinated copper and iridescent glass from the Arts and Crafts-style Robert R. Blacker House in Pasadena, Calif. Priced at $115,000, it hangs near a pair of chairs by the British architect C. F. A. Voysey.</p>
        <p>One booth is trying to plug into the Internet age. Florian Papp, the Madison Avenue dealer in English furniture, has hung a flat-screen computer monitor that will flash the dealer's inventory continuously on a wall surrounded by three Northern European chairs with delicate curved arms. ''We're trying to make people look at furniture as sculpture,'' said Mindy Papp, president of Florian Papp. ''We don't think computers are going to take over the world, but they can complement what we do.''</p>
        <p>Florian Papp has specialized in furniture for three generations. Other dealers with an interest in furniture include Guy Bush, a Washington dealer who runs G. K. S. Bush. He said he had been keeping a block-and-shell bureau dating from around 1770 ''under wraps'' just to exhibit at the show. He believes it was made by Benjamin Burnham, a well-known cabinetmaker from Colchester, Conn. Mr. Bush said a mate to the bureau belongs to the Winterthur Museum in Delaware, which may explain why the price is $900,000.</p>
        <p>One of the show's old-timers is Thomas Devenish, a Madison Avenue dealer with one of the best eyes in the business. An exquisite red-lacquer bookcase with elaborate chinoiserie is one of his star pieces this year. Made in England around 1708, it is priced at $1.25 million.</p>
        <p>What distinguishes this show from the rest are the small, quirky objects that seem to lurk around every corner. Where else would you find a rare bronze figure of a European made in China in the mid-18th-century, for $28,000? ''My booth is entirely devoted to the colonial trade,'' said Marc J. Matz, a dealer from Cambridge, Mass., who is selling the figure. ''It's an expanding market. A lot of pieces were reinterpretations from colonial designers made with exotic timbers.''</p>
        <p>The market for Shaker works has also expanded. Suzanne Courcier and Robert W. Wilkins, dealers from Austerlitz, N.Y., have an extremely rare sample stone cut by Henry Clay Blinn, a Shaker in Canterbury, N.H., in 1848, when he was 23. It was made in preparation for the stone set up at a sacred outdoor site in Canterbury. The stone was first sold in 1968 in Concord, N.H., in the first important auction of Shaker furniture and objects. The dealers today are asking $35,000. Thirty-two years ago it fetched $110.</p>
        <p>Treasure Map</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of antiques shows in Manhattan this weekend.</p>
        <p>WINTER ANTIQUES SHOW, Seventh Regiment Armory, Park Avenue and 67th Street. Today through Jan. 30. Daily, noon to 8:30 p.m., except Sundays and on Thursday when it runs until 6 p.m. Admission: $16 a day. Information: (212) 472-0590.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES AT THE OTHER ARMORY, 69th Street Regiment Armory, 68 Lexington Avenue, between 25th and 26th Streets. Today and tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $10; free for children under 16. Information: (212) 255-0020.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CERAMICS FAIR, National Academy of Design, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street. Today, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m.; tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $15 (includes entry on more than one day); free transportation (by limousine) between the Ceramics Fair, the Winter Antiques Show, Sotheby's and Christie's is available for those with  tickets to the shows. Information: (212) 289-0496.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
