<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Basel</title>
    <meta content="WDBASE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/05/travel/WDBASEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1389515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Basel (Switzerland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pfanner, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Basel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Switzerland</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EED71F3EF936A35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Basel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Basel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PFANNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pfanner, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column on events, sightseeing, hotels and restaurants in Basel, Switzerland; photos; maps; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bern may be the capital, Zurich the largest city and Geneva the most international, but Basel can make a fair claim to being the bourgeois-bohemian heart of a new Switzerland that has streamlined its fashion sense and its diet, while loosening up on marijuana and neutrality.</p>
        <p>With more than 30 museums and dozens of art galleries in a city of only 200,000 people, it is perhaps no surprise that the chic Italian- and French-influenced restaurants that are springing up around Basel seem to be filled with black-clad curators. (The diners may actually work for Novartis or Roche, the giant pharmaceutical companies based in Basel, but the city has a long tradition of mixing business with art patronage.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Basel is the bourgeois-bohemian heart of a new Switzerland that has streamlined its fashion sense and its diet, while loosening up on marijuana and neutrality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bern may be the capital, Zurich the largest city and Geneva the most international, but Basel can make a fair claim to being the bourgeois-bohemian heart of a new Switzerland that has streamlined its fashion sense and its diet, while loosening up on marijuana and neutrality.</p>
        <p>With more than 30 museums and dozens of art galleries in a city of only 200,000 people, it is perhaps no surprise that the chic Italian- and French-influenced restaurants that are springing up around Basel seem to be filled with black-clad curators. (The diners may actually work for Novartis or Roche, the giant pharmaceutical companies based in Basel, but the city has a long tradition of mixing business with art patronage.)</p>
        <p>Outside, in the cobblestone squares, skateboarders openly puff on joints, something they have been able to do undisturbed since last year, when the authorities began easing rules on marijuana use.</p>
        <p>To be sure, this Basel coexists with a less worldly version; step away from the Rhine, which runs through the middle of town, and you may encounter boisterous soccer fans munching on sausages and gulping down beer. There you are also more likely to hear criticism of Switzerland's recent vote in favor of joining the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Near the linguistic border with Switzerland's French speakers -- and so close to France and Germany that it shares an airport with Mulhouse, France, and Freiburg, Germany -- Basel has always been a European crossroads.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>One of the city's most prominent international gatherings is its 20th- and 21st-century art fair, Art Basel, which draws top dealers from all over the world to Basel's convention center, at the Messeplatz on the right bank of the Rhine, (41) 58-200-2020, fax (41) 58-206-2686, www.artbasel .com. This year's edition runs from June 12 through 17. More than 1,000 artists, more than 260 galleries and at least 20 countries are expected to participate. Admission is $18.</p>
        <p>From June 11 to 16, Liste 02, the Young Art Fair, an alternative to Art Basel, features displays from 46 galleries from 15 countries, in a brewery that has been converted to loft spaces for exhibitions and new media at Burgweg 15; (41) 61-692-2021; www.liste.ch. Open 1 to 9 p.m.; $8.50.</p>
        <p>''Claude Monet . . . Up to Digital Impressionism,'' through Aug. 4 at Fondation Beyeler, Baselstrasse 101 in the suburb of Riehen, a 30-minute tram ride from the center, (41) 61-645-9700, www.beyeler.com, focuses on Monet's late works and examines his influence on later artists, including video artists. Open daily. Admission is $10, $12.50 on weekends.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of 20th-century art, ''Painting on the Move,'' takes up residence at three museums from May 26 to Sept. 8. (A $12.50 ticket admits you to all three; all are closed on Mondays.) For the overview, visit the Kunstmuseum, St. Alban-Graben 16, (41) 61-206-6262, www.kunst  museumbasel.ch, a muscular 1930's interpretation of a Venetian palazzo. The permanent collection features the Renaissance artist Hans Holbein, whom Basel considers a native son, but is also strong in 20th-century art. The Museum für Gegenwartskunst (Contemporary Art), St. Alban-Rheinweg 60, (41) 61-272-8183, is focusing on post-1968 themes. And the Kunsthalle, Steinenberg 7, (41) 61-206-9900, will look at new ways of dealing with reality in painting.</p>
        <p>Theater Basel is will perform Mozart's ''Magic Flute'' June 15, at 7:30 p.m., Theaterstrasse 7, (41) 61-295-1133; theater-basel.ch; $30 to $56.</p>
        <p>Musical Theater Basel, at the convention center, actentertainment.ch, will present ''Evita,'' May 28 to June 9; Tickets $36 to $74; www.ticket corner.ch at (41) 848-800-800; www .messe.ch/musical.asp#top.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>A good place to begin a visit is the Münster, or cathedral, whose red sandstone spires and colorful roof dominate the city's modest skyline from a peaceful square high on the left bank of the Rhine. The cathedral was rebuilt in the Gothic style after an earthquake destroyed most of the original Romanesque structure in 1356. The interior is rather plain.</p>
        <p>In the nearby Theaterplatz, a Rube Goldberg-like mobile sculpture by Jean Tinguely, with incongruously shaped limbs spinning around and squirting water, serves as a magnet for tourists and skateboarders.</p>
        <p>A short walk away is the Barfüsserplatz, surrounded by galleries, shopping streets, restaurants and nightclubs, the bustling social center of the left bank, also known as Grossbasel (Greater Basel), which is on the Swiss and French side of the Rhine. Looking the other way from the Münster, you can gaze out over Kleinbasel (Small Basel), an enclave surrounded by Germany. Most of the major sights are on the left bank, but the convention center, a few hotels and the Fondation Beyeler, perhaps Basel's most celebrated museum, are on the other side.</p>
        <p>One of the most enjoyable things to do in Basel is to stroll along the medieval, cobblestoned streets on the left bank, whether following the signposted routes suggested by the tourist office (Schifflände 5; 41-61-268-6868) or simply wandering aimlessly, stumbling on highlights like the gaudily decorated 16th-century city hall on the Marktplatz smack in the center.</p>
        <p>You can cross the river by tram or on foot using six bridges, but a more atmospheric way to cross is by ferry. These wooden boats, powered only by the current but kept from floating away downstream by overhead cables, cross the river at four places; the most convenient is just downhill from the Münster (75 cents).</p>
        <p>On the right bank, in the suburb of Riehen, is the Fondation Beyeler, Baselstrasse 101 in Riehen; (41) 61-645-9700. This collection of works ranging from post-Impressionists to Mark Rothko, assembled by Hildy and Ernst Beyeler, opened in 1997. The understated design by Renzo Piano -- the most prominent feature is a flat, translucent roof -- makes great use of natural light; Alberto Giacometti's spiny figures seem poised to spring onto the surrounding hillsides. Open daily from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. (Wednesdays until 8); $7.50.</p>
        <p>The Fondation Beyeler is one of many striking examples of modern architecture that dot Basel outside the old city center. Another intriguing building, which opened in 2000, is perched in the railyard behind the main train station. There, Herzog &amp; de Meuron, the hip Swiss firm that oversaw the transformation of a London power station into Tate Modern, has designed what must be the world's most elegant track-switching and traffic control center, a sleek, copper-sheathed slab that demonstrates the continued vitality of Swiss design (if also the considerable budget of the country's rail  system).</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The most interesting hotel in Basel, if not the most luxurious, is the Teufelhof, Leonhardsgraben 47-49, (41) 61-261-1010, fax (41) 61-261-1004, www.teufelhof.com, part of a cultural, dining and lodging complex that also includes a theater and art displays, as well as a shop selling wines and other products for gourmands. Actually there are two hotels here, the Kunsthotel and the Galeriehotel. The eight quirky but comfortable rooms in the Kunsthotel are decorated as installations by various artists. The current theme is time. In one room, newspapers hang from the ceiling; a new issue of the German weekly Die Zeit is added every week. The Galeriehotel's 25 rooms are simpler, but artists' works, available for sale, are hung on the walls. Double rooms range from $160 to $280.</p>
        <p>Hotel Krafft, Rheingasse 12, (41) 61-690-9130, fax (41) 61-690-9131, www.krafftamrhein.ch, on the Kleinbasel riverbank, has less imaginative rooms -- there is a slightly worn, 1970's feel to the furnishings, and not all of the 52 rooms have private baths -- but it is convenient to the convention center, and the views over the old city on the opposite side of the river are impressive. Doubles with bath, $130 to $165.</p>
        <p>Budget: There are few true bargains to be had in Basel, which caters to business travelers, though many hotels offer weekend discounts. One good choice is Hotel Rochat, Petersgraben 23, (41) 61-261-8140, fax (41) 61-261-6492, www.hotelrochat.ch, in an attractive Victorian building centrally situated in Grossbasel. The 50 rooms have modern, if slightly institutional, furnishings. Alcohol is not available in minibars or at the restaurant. (The hotel is owned by the Blue Cross, a Swiss organization that works against alcohol abuse.) Doubles, $119.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The most expensive 88 rooms in Basel are in the Hotel Drei Könige am Rhein, Blumenrain 8, (41) 61-260-5050, fax (41) 61-260-5060, www.drei-koenige-basel.ch, known in French as the Hôtel des Trois Rois au Rhin. The three kings referred to are not the biblical wise men but three rulers who met in 1026 in an inn that stood on the site. Its elegantly appointed suites seem designed for similar summit meetings. Double rooms, some with river views and marble baths, are $345 to $430.</p>
        <p>Hotel Euler, Centralbahnplatz 14, (41) 61-275-8000, fax (41) 61-275-8050, www.hoteleuler.ch, has 64 elegant, if slightly dated, rooms, and there is a Belle Époque feel to its piano bar and restaurant, though the location near the train station is perhaps less central and less attractive than some of the alternatives. Doubles, $280 to $365.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Despite the fact that Basel lies in German-speaking Switzerland, the culinary influence of the nearby French speakers is evident in the city's newer, more fashionable restaurants; traditional places tend  to serve stick-to-your-ribs German fare. In the former category is Bel Étage, Leonhardsgraben 49, (41) 61-261-1010, fax (41) 61-261-1004, part of the Teufelhof complex, where tables are widely spaced on an inlaid parquet floor. Appetizers include a delicious foie-gras-and-duck sausage; entrees are a mix of French, German and Italian flavors, including filet of St. Pierre in mustard sauce with lentils and leeks. Dinner for two with wine is about $220. Lunch Tuesday to Friday, dinner Tuesday to Saturday.</p>
        <p>Another popular spot for Basel's chic set is the Restaurant Kunsthalle, Steinenberg 7, (41) 61-272-4233, fax (41) 61-272-4255, in the Kunsthalle, the art gallery near the Barfüsserplatz. There is a fine restaurant, and the brasserie, a stylish update on the Parisian variety, with dark wood paneling and frescoed ceilings, has a similar menu at more modest prices. Among the choices are excellent steaks and paper-thin paillard de veau. Dinner for two with wine is about $125 in the restaurant, about half that in the brasserie. Lunch and dinner daily.</p>
        <p>More traditionally Germanic fare, and gemütlichkeit, can be found at Gifthüttli, Schneidergasse 11, (41) 61-261-1656, fax (41) 61-261-1456, with a menu in German as well as in Swiss dialect. There are 13 kinds of cordon bleu (6 with veal, 7 with pork). Dinner for two with wine, $80. Lunch and dinner Monday through Saturday.</p>
        <p>A good budget choice for lunch is the Café Restaurant Papiermühle, St. Alban-Tal 35, (41) 61-272-4848, fax (41) 61-273-9248, just outside the center in the picturesque St. Alban quarter. The restaurant is spare and unpretentious, and views out the window to an old mill add charm. The limited but often-changing menu features vegetarian and pasta-based dishes. Lunch for two (the restaurant is closed in the evening except Friday) is about $50, including a simple wine. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN ERIC PFANNER is the London correspondent for The International Herald Tribune.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ERIC PFANNER is the London correspondent for The International Herald Tribune.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
