<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Expansion Leads to Inner Space</title>
    <meta content="05COV.$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/05/realestate/05COV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1389646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Public Library</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Packer Collegiate Institute (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carnegie Hall (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Library</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DE1331F936A35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Expansion Leads to Inner Space</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Expansion Leads to Inner Space</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some of New York City's famous institutions that need space are expanding within and below their buildings; such is path being taken by South Court building of New York Public Library, which fills southern courtyard at Fifth Avenue and 40th Street, middle school of Packer Collegiate Institute, entirely new structure that will rise within nave of Victorian Gothic church in Brookly Heights, and Judy and Arthur Zankel Hall, carved from bedrock under main auditorium of Carnegie Hall; projects detailed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LET science hunt for tiny particles and distant stars. In New York, the quest is for something more elusive: room.</p>
        <p>Imagine a 40,000-square-foot office and educational center, a three-story school or a 650-seat theater. Now, imagine squeezing any one of them into a landmark without altering the exterior. There is no going up or out. The only way is in or down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cultural institutions in New York with no room to expand go the extra mile and build underground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LET science hunt for tiny particles and distant stars. In New York, the quest is for something more elusive: room.</p>
        <p>Imagine a 40,000-square-foot office and educational center, a three-story school or a 650-seat theater. Now, imagine squeezing any one of them into a landmark without altering the exterior. There is no going up or out. The only way is in or down.</p>
        <p>And that is the path taken at the South Court building of the New York Public Library, which fills the southern courtyard at Fifth Avenue and 40th Street; the middle school of Packer Collegiate Institute, an entirely new structure that will rise within the nave of a Victorian Gothic church in Brooklyn Heights; and Judy and Arthur Zankel Hall, carved from bedrock under the main auditorium of Carnegie Hall -- an operation that John L. Tishman, chairman of the Tishman Construction Corporation, the construction managers, likened more to mining than building.</p>
        <p>''We very much admire the leadership of the institutions in going the extra mile,'' said Sherida E. Paulsen, chairwoman of the Landmarks Preservation Commission.</p>
        <p>Very often, the extra mile is subterranean. More than 60 percent of expansion designed for the Pierpont Morgan Library by the Renzo Piano Building Workshop and Beyer Blinder Belle will be underground. The Spence School is digging a gymnasium under the former Billy Rose house at 56 East 93rd Street, in an expansion designed by Buttrick White &amp; Burtis.</p>
        <p>''Space in the ground is becoming more and more valuable,'' said Frank J. Sciame Jr., chief executive of F. J. Sciame Construction, the construction managers of the South Court and Spence projects.</p>
        <p>Even the library dug deeper than it planned when it first announced the South Court project in 1998. The extra space gained by excavation permitted the addition of a 178-seat auditorium under the 40th Street truck loading dock, which was always part of the courtyard and has been integrated into the new structure.</p>
        <p>Above the auditorium and loading dock are four new floors. The first, level with the library's main entrance hall, is the Celeste Bartos Education Center, a 24-seat visitors' orientation theater and two classrooms with a total of 30 computer stations. Offices are on the second, third and fourth floors. Also on the fourth floor are a staff lounge and ''quiet room'' where employees can escape the noise of the library.</p>
        <p>The $29 million project is to open next month. The 80-by-80-foot courtyard was identified as a potential expansion area long before Paul LeClerc assumed the presidency in 1993. ''I joked, 'Show me the Bernini plans,' '' he recalled, referring to Gian Lorenzo Bernini's unrealized 17th-century design for the Louvre.</p>
        <p>The white Danby marble walls of the courtyard are fully detailed with pediments and arches, quoins and brackets, keystones and balusters, wreaths and scrolls, designed 91 years ago by Carrère &amp; Hastings. ''The whole key was to make the new space comfortable within the existing walls,'' said Lewis Davis of Davis Brody Bond, architects of the addition.</p>
        <p>To preserve the integrity of the courtyard walls, the floors of the inserted structure stop four feet short, permitting the original details to be seen. The space between the old and new buildings is enclosed under a skylight. The cantilevered floors are edged with lighting coves lined in aluminum leaf, designed by Fisher Marantz Stone. The structural engineers are Weidlinger Associates and the mechanical and electrical engineers are Atkinson Koven Feinberg.</p>
        <p>The new structure is frankly modern. No attempt was made at incorporating any complementary Beaux-Arts flourishes, apart from the use of Danby marble. ''To have built faux Carrère &amp; Hastings in 2002 would have been not only inauthentic but anachronistic,'' Dr. LeClerc said.</p>
        <p>However, the past is acknowledged in the atrium staircase that leads down to the auditorium, which will take visitors past the bottom of the dressed marble facade and through the exposed rubble-stone foundations under the library itself, cut away in a kind of archaeological layering.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to show what this building really is,'' said Nathan C. Hoyt of Davis Brody Bond. ''Here is a piece that most people would never get to see.''</p>
        <p>There are still some sheer walls of Manhattan schist visible under the main auditorium of Carnegie Hall -- gray, glinting, grainy and forbidding -- peppered with one-inch holes testifying to the drilling, blasting, picking, cracking and hammering that began in 1999 and ended last month. All told, some 6,300 cubic yards of bedrock were removed from the hall; that is enough to fill about 1,550 Ford Expeditions to the brim.</p>
        <p>But there is still a lot left. For instance, a rock outcropping about 15 feet high defines the southeast edge of the storage area in which movable seats for the parterre level of the auditorium will be stored. ''The excavation was the single most expensive element in the project,'' said Richard M. Malenka, director of administration at Carnegie Hall. ''We did not take out one cubic inch more than we had to take out.''</p>
        <p>Zankel Hall is to open in September 2003. The construction costs account for about 72 percent of a $100 million campaign that includes educational programs and an endowment. Robert Harth, the executive and artistic director, said the campaign is about 98 percent of the way toward its goal.</p>
        <p>Polshek Partnership Architects are the designers. Robert Silman Associates are the structural engineers, as they are on the Morgan Library and Packer Collegiate Institute project. Flack &amp; Kurtz are the mechanical and electrical engineers.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the library, which was essentially built in open air, Carnegie Hall created a new building under -- and therefore necessarily supporting -- the historic Isaac Stern Auditorium. Steel shoring columns were erected under the auditorium. The original cast-iron columns were removed and the weight of the auditorium was transferred temporarily to the steel. That allowed the bedrock to be excavated by means ranging from pickax to explosives. ''In the end, the rock got so hard that we blasted,'' said Mr. Silman. ''In a way, it's much kinder than a hoe ram. A millisecond and then it's over.''</p>
        <p>To support the Stern Auditorium permanently, a canted, elliptical one-foot-thick concrete wall was built that also serves as an egglike shell around Zankel Hall. The egg shape is visible from surrounding lobbies and walkways. The weight of the Stern Auditorium was transferred from the shoring columns to the ellipse, which is 114 feet at its longest and 76 feet at its widest.</p>
        <p>Although the bedrock is to be walled over, a small portion may be exposed to give visitors an idea of the unforgiving environment from which the hall was hewn.</p>
        <p>A sense of historic layering is part of the plan by the Packer Collegiate Institute to erect an entirely independent three-story structure within the shell of the 133-year-old former St. Ann's Episcopal Church, at Clinton and Livingston Streets, which the school has owned for 33 years. It was designed by James Renwick Jr., the architect of St. Patrick's Cathedral and Grace Church.</p>
        <p>Though the undercroft was long ago fitted up for the lower school, the main sanctuary has been little used since 1987, when it was deemed unsafe for large assemblies. It is an astonishing space, rising 87 feet to the peak of the ceiling, a gingerbread forest of intricate wood trusses, some inscribed with hexagrams that look like Stars of David. Along the nave are some of the first cast-iron columns used for a house of worship in America, topped by capitals that are bouquets of dahlias, daisies, roses and ivy.</p>
        <p>A new three-story steel and glass structure, 40 feet wide and 31 feet high, will be constructed within the nave, rising from entirely independent foundations. It will contain 18 classrooms. The balconies will be removed from the side aisles, leaving them open. The ''roof'' of the new structure will also yield usable classroom space.</p>
        <p>Hardy Holzman Pfeiffer Associates designed the structure as part of a master plan, to be completed for the 2003-4 school year, that includes a new glass-enclosed link among the Packer buildings at the crook of the L-shaped campus and a dining hall and commons in the old parish house. The overall project will cost $23 million, said Barbara Smith Delmhorst, director of development. Packer plans to raise $10 million and borrow the rest through tax-exempt bonds. The mechanical and electrical engineers are Cosentini Associates. The construction manager is the Lehr Construction Company, working with HRH Construction.</p>
        <p>Because the new middle school structure will not abut any exterior walls, one of the critical questions was how to get daylight to the classrooms, said Pamela J. Loeffelman, a principal at Hardy Holzman Pfeiffer.</p>
        <p>That led to the decision to replace most stained-glass windows with clear glass. The rose window showing the ascension of Jesus is destined, with several others, for St. Joseph's University in Philadelphia, where Carmen R. Croce, the curator of the university collections, is assembling stained glass as the basis of a future gallery. Other windows will go to the Corning Museum of Glass in Corning, N.Y., the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Brooklyn Museum of Art, said Sandra L. Polsak of Levien &amp; Company, Packer's project representative. The remaining windows will be restored by the Clerkin Higgins studio in Brooklyn. Architectural elements not reused by Packer will be salvaged by Olde Good Things.</p>
        <p>Some Christian elements are still visible, like stenciled monograms of ''IHS,'' the first three letters of Jesus in Greek, and an alpha and omega, symbolizing God. It seems to be up for discussion whether these will be painted over. ''We wanted to replace the most potent religious iconography,'' said Susan Restler, chairwoman of the board, ''but not go to the extreme of saying there couldn't be any.''</p>
        <p>Rather than referring to the new middle school as St. Ann's, Packer students have been heard to call it Hogwarts, Ms. Loeffelman said, after Harry Potter's fantastic alma mater, the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry. Naturally, she takes this as a compliment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
