<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Misspent Youth? Tell That to My Victims</title>
    <meta content="30RITU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/30/travel/30RITU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1492801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="RITUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gustines, George Gene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD81F31F933A05756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Misspent Youth? Tell That to My Victims</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Misspent Youth? Tell That to My Victims</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE GENE GUSTINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gustines, George Gene</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Gene Gustines Rituals column on fun of playing card game spades, which he dates back to his sophomore year at Brooklyn Technical High School; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY obsession with spades began in 1986 during my sophomore year at Brooklyn Technical High School. Unlike the smaller, nerdier, comic-collecting clique that counted me as a member, playing spades at Tech made me part of a large community -- every third student seemed to carry a deck. We played before class, at lunch and (if we could get away with it) whenever we had a substitute teacher.</p>
        <p>Part of the appeal of the four-player game is the team play. Each person bets on how many ''books'' or ''tricks'' -- a round of four cards -- he will take for his team. The more face cards and spades you have, the better. At school, we were cocky betters, so combined bids of 14 books (only 13 are possible) were frequent, making one team's downfall inevitable and, for the victors, delicious. When playing with less brash adults, however, those kinds of bids are rare. The fun is in the game's psychology -- learning each player's tics and reading body language for subtle giveaways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>My obsession with spades began in 1986 during my sophomore year at Brooklyn Technical High School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY obsession with spades began in 1986 during my sophomore year at Brooklyn Technical High School. Unlike the smaller, nerdier, comic-collecting clique that counted me as a member, playing spades at Tech made me part of a large community -- every third student seemed to carry a deck. We played before class, at lunch and (if we could get away with it) whenever we had a substitute teacher.</p>
        <p>Part of the appeal of the four-player game is the team play. Each person bets on how many ''books'' or ''tricks'' -- a round of four cards -- he will take for his team. The more face cards and spades you have, the better. At school, we were cocky betters, so combined bids of 14 books (only 13 are possible) were frequent, making one team's downfall inevitable and, for the victors, delicious. When playing with less brash adults, however, those kinds of bids are rare. The fun is in the game's psychology -- learning each player's tics and reading body language for subtle giveaways.</p>
        <p>My playing opportunities dried up after graduation. At college, a hectic schedule and being able to leave for lunch did not encourage much spades-bonding. Though I did get in a couple of games with a few former Tech students, it wasn't until 1995, when my niece followed in my footsteps at Tech, that I had a chance to reconnect with the game. I told her about my favorite teachers, the fastest subway routes and the joys of spades. I also taught her how to cut class, but that's another story.</p>
        <p>About two years later, my partner, Steve, and I stumbled onto a regular spades game with Wallace, a colleague, and his friend Bob. We had originally come together to play hearts, but while gossiping, snacking and drinking, we realized that we all liked spades. I do not recall a ''Eureka!'' moment. It was more a gradual shared awareness that hearts, while mindlessly satisfying on the computer, was not so thrilling for four adults. So we switched and, lo, our one-Saturday-a-month game was born.</p>
        <p>As a rule, Steve and I never play on the same team. Victories would be great, but what would defeats do to our home life? We don't need that kind of domestic strife. Having us on different sides also allowed us to break up the possible threat of a Wallace-and-Bob team. They have a history of playing bridge, so we wanted to deny them the advantage of subtle or possibly subconscious signals.</p>
        <p>Each side, I think, is evenly matched. Wallace and I are the risk-averse players on our teams; if either of us bids zero (in which one player bets on his ability to take no books at all), we won't be easy to sabotage. Steve and Bob are the daredevils. They have caused both delight and stress for their teammates. Bob and Wallace are good at counting cards. While the results of the last round can be a surprise for Steve and me, Bob and Wallace often know which team will come out on top.</p>
        <p>Our monthly games have regulations regarding location (we rotate among our three homes, with an occasional road trip) and food (we prefer that the host whip up something at home). We can usually look forward to homemade bread at Bob's and Tex-Mex at Wallace's. Steve's culinary repertory consists of turkey meatloaf, vegetable lasagna and his recently introduced beef empanadas. I cannot prepare a bowl of cereal without risking a three-alarm fire. On the rare occasions I feel guilty about my gastronomical ineptitude, I request takeout from my favorite Upper West Side restaurant -- my mother's kitchen.</p>
        <p>Many of our friends do not understand the appeal of our monthly game. They picture us as silver-haired and delicate, sipping tea and eating cucumber sandwiches. Somehow, a smoky, burly poker game -- whether dollars or cents are at stake -- does not have this image problem. At our spades game, only bragging rights are up for grabs and they have been a huge factor in keeping our card game going.</p>
        <p>We became creative and recently held a special edition of our game. We recruited four more players and held a potluck, seven-cycle, round-robin tournament. The wine flowed freely, the macaroni was cheesy and the skill levels were varied. It was a head-spinning night -- and not just because I opted for vodka.</p>
        <p>With different team combinations in each round, I found myself playing with Steve or Wallace and against Bob at various times of the night. All the old alliances and strategies went out the window. All these new players to assess! Just when you could begin to gauge their strengths and weaknesses, it would be time to rotate.</p>
        <p>The competition was as exhilarating as it was discombobulating.</p>
        <p>But I won.</p>
        <p>RITUALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
