<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Vineyard Reawakens to a Sound of Hammers</title>
    <meta content="30VINE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/30/realestate/luxury/30VINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1492802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memorial Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Martha's Vineyard (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Martha's Vineyard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Repairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorial Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Martha's Vineyard (Mass)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EED81F31F933A05756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Vineyard Reawakens to a Sound of Hammers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Vineyard Reawakens to a Sound of Hammers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on activities of contractors, gardeners, painters, window cleaners and others who spruce up houses and gardens for summer visitors on weekend before Memorial Day; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL over Martha's Vineyard, shadbushes were blooming, peepers were peeping, the goldfinches had yellowed up nicely, and year-round humans who care for the nests of their migratory cousins were in a state of near frenzy. Spring came late this year; it snowed in April, and ferry traffic was off by nearly 7 percent through the first week of May. But suddenly, Memorial Day was only a week away, and the Vineyard was scrambling to get that relaxed island aesthetic up and running for another summer.</p>
        <p>'' 'They're coming, they're coming,' everybody is telling themselves, 'they're coming,' '' said Lila DiBiaso in a brief moment of inactivity in front of the drink cooler at Alley's General Store in the heart of West Tisbury. Ms. DiBiaso's company, Botanica, cares for 19 gardens around the island. The ''they'' in question are the nearly seven seasonal visitors for every one year-rounder who, by the height of summer, swell the island population from 15,000 to something over 105,000. It is a ratio that seems to hold true for businesses open, houses occupied, cars backed up at Five Corners, fund-raisers held, or ibuprofens ingested.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the weeks before Memorial Day, Martha's Vineyard hustles to get that relaxed island aesthetic up and running for another summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL over Martha's Vineyard, shadbushes were blooming, peepers were peeping, the goldfinches had yellowed up nicely, and year-round humans who care for the nests of their migratory cousins were in a state of near frenzy. Spring came late this year; it snowed in April, and ferry traffic was off by nearly 7 percent through the first week of May. But suddenly, Memorial Day was only a week away, and the Vineyard was scrambling to get that relaxed island aesthetic up and running for another summer.</p>
        <p>'' 'They're coming, they're coming,' everybody is telling themselves, 'they're coming,' '' said Lila DiBiaso in a brief moment of inactivity in front of the drink cooler at Alley's General Store in the heart of West Tisbury. Ms. DiBiaso's company, Botanica, cares for 19 gardens around the island. The ''they'' in question are the nearly seven seasonal visitors for every one year-rounder who, by the height of summer, swell the island population from 15,000 to something over 105,000. It is a ratio that seems to hold true for businesses open, houses occupied, cars backed up at Five Corners, fund-raisers held, or ibuprofens ingested.</p>
        <p>At summer paradises up and down the Northeast coast, the weeks before Memorial Day bring a host of rituals that are as ingrained as marching in parades, or tossing lilac boughs into the outgoing tide. On Nantucket, Block Island and the little isles of Penobscot Bay, caretakers are making ready. At Watch Hill and on the North Fork, plumbers turn on the water. Even in Bucks County and the Catskills, contractors speed from one job to the next; a few shingles here, a dangling outdoor screen there.</p>
        <p>''It's crazy, really,'' Ms. DiBiaso continued. ''We were working down in West Chop this morning, and we were surrounded by all these big empty houses, and we're all planting and cultivating and thinking, 'They're coming, they're coming, they're coming.' ''</p>
        <p>In Edgartown, which is the most carefully painted, if monochromatic, town on the island, it seemed as if ladders were up on nearly every other house on North Water Street. The old white was being sanded and scraped, the new white was being applied. The same was true for the famous gingerbreads of Oak Bluffs; only there the ladders were shorter and the colors were, well, colors. A new coat of ''serenity yellow'' for the Cottage Museum, ''mission rose'' for the Oak Bluffs Inn.</p>
        <p>The contractors, gardeners, painters, window cleaners and others are on the front line, to be sure. But the specter of bike-racked S.U.V.'s in the near distance had woken up almost every corner of the 108-square-mile island. The Steamship Authority was already up to its full summer weekend schedule of 25 car ferries, up from a dozen on a midwinter weekday. Daily flights to the Vineyard from various mainland airports on Cape Air, meanwhile, will be tripled to nearly 45 by mid-June.</p>
        <p>At the Menemsha Store, boxes were piled high in the aisles, and Kevin Oliver, the owner, had enlisted his father to help stock the newly expanded grocery shelves. ''Customers have been asking for more and fancier food,'' the younger Mr. Oliver said, holding up a box of Hob Nob cookies, ''so we finally listened and shrunk the souvenir section.''</p>
        <p>Around the corner Donald Poole, whose father started Poole's Fish Market a half century ago selling the day's catch door to door out of a baby carriage filled with ice, was dashing off to Boston to renew his retailer's licenses. ''You don't want to do it too soon,'' he said, ''because the minute you get the license you have to start sending in weekly reports on all the species even if you're not open yet.''</p>
        <p>Summer people want more than a roof over their heads, a fish on their grills, and a Hob Nob between meals; they want their toys in the water. At the Martha's Vineyard Shipyard in Vineyard Haven, ''Zinc Mon,'' a k a Ricky Duncan, made a last check of the propeller of Patrol, a Fortier 26, before it was lowered into the water only a handful of days before the big weekend. Patrol is the committee boat for the Edgartown Yacht Club, and people can't properly race yachts in Edgartown if Patrol is still in dry dock.</p>
        <p>''We got held up a little by the weather, but with a couple of 55-hour weeks I think we're about caught up,'' Mr. Duncan said as the next boat in line was backed down toward the harnesses of the travel lift. ''But see that little whaler over there on the beach?'' he pointed. ''That's my boat. And it's looking like it will be the last one in the water this year.''</p>
        <p>At Alley's General Store, Jack MacKay, the manager, said, ''it is mostly a matter of adding, adding, adding inventory. By the height of the season we have more than 200 vendors, and we're turning over virtually the entire stock every week. It's wild.'' Mr. MacKay has the look of a marathon runner, primed for the race but far too experienced to squander energy unnecessarily early.</p>
        <p>IT'S infectious, the spring buzz, even for the class of year-rounders who have honed their nostalgia to a sharp edge and who muse annually about spending August in Nova Scotia.</p>
        <p>For more than a few islanders, however, the arrival of summer means an involuntary migration into boxes and out of their winter homes. These are long-term residents with school-aged children, young couples with newborns, and a lot of 20- and 30-somethings who have not given up their hope of making a permanent life on the island. Ends that might meet in winter, when a small house might cost $1,000 a month, do not come close in summer when that same amount will rarely get a single room with bathroom and kitchen privileges.</p>
        <p>''For us that's the real story,'' Ms. DiBiaso said that afternoon in Alley's. ''We're working all day getting everything ready, and then at night we're all looking for housing and packing and moving. We're moving into a barn tonight, in fact.''</p>
        <p>The first English-speaking visitors to Martha's Vineyard were day-trippers who came in the summer of 1602. They were met by friendly Wampanoag Indians who gave them gifts of cooked fish and tobacco, and they went away happily promising to return. Only later did the off-islanders require the Indians to move out. Today at the top of the cliffs in Aquinnah, at the westernmost tip of the island, various Vanderhoops and other friendly Wampanoags still sell chowder and other necessities to visitors. Theirs are among the oldest tourist stops on the island.</p>
        <p>''Believe it or not Memorial Day is usually one of our biggest days of the year,'' said Brenda Hayden, the manager of the Broken Arrow snack bar. Ms. Hayden's wampum bracelets occupy almost all the space between her wrist and elbow, and she happily admits to being a rare Vineyarder who likes the sight of the pink and white tour buses rumbling up the hill.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the big weekend was windy, raw and mostly wet; nowhere more so than at the howling tip of Aquinnah. Still, on that spitting Memorial Day, people had to wait for a spot at the top of the hill by the Broken Arrow, where only a week before in bright sunshine, they could have parked wherever they wanted. ''It was big yesterday,'' said Ms. Hayden, her wampum now covered with a winter parka.</p>
        <p>It was even bigger inside the warm dining room of the Aquinnah Shop at the very top of the cliffs. There, a line of people milled around waiting for a table.</p>
        <p>''Saturday was pretty nuts,'' said Cully Vanderhoop, an owner, from back in the kitchen. His hands were in a bowl full of batter. ''We didn't get a break all day.'' Mr. Vanderhoop dropped a battered fillet into the deep fry.</p>
        <p>''But that's why we're here,'' he said over the wild applause of the hot oil.</p>
        <p>HAVENS Paul Schneider is the author of ''The Enduring Shore: A History of Cape Cod, Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket'' (Henry Holt).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Schneider is the author of ''The Enduring Shore: A History of Cape Cod, Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket'' (Henry Holt).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
