<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gossip Gets A Book Deal, But What About Sales?</title>
    <meta content="19goss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/19/books/19goss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1798141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Post</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Simon &amp; Schuster Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stern, Jared Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDD1F30F93AA25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gossip Gets A Book Deal, But What About Sales?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gossip Gets a Book Deal, but What About Sales?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE BOSMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bosman, Julie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The news that Simon &amp; Schuster has signed a book deal with Jared Paul Stern, a former New York Post gossip reporter, may have some people wondering what boldface names Mr. Stern will name in the book. But the more appropriate question might be: Why?</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern was abruptly dismissed from The Post's Page Six column last spring amid allegations that he had tried to extort $220,000 from Ronald W. Burkle, a California billionaire who was a regular target in the column. The publishing house paid a reported six figures for his book.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If recent publishing history is any guide, a book by the former Page Six reporter Jared Paul Stern will be a tough sell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The news that Simon &amp; Schuster has signed a book deal with Jared Paul Stern, a former New York Post gossip reporter, may have some people wondering what boldface names Mr. Stern will name in the book. But the more appropriate question might be: Why?</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern was abruptly dismissed from The Post's Page Six column last spring amid allegations that he had tried to extort $220,000 from Ronald W. Burkle, a California billionaire who was a regular target in the column. The publishing house paid a reported six figures for his book.</p>
        <p>But if recent publishing history is any guide, ''Stern Measures,'' as the book is tentatively titled, will be a tough sell. The book is likely to land in one of two spaces: either the story of a misbehaving journalist's fall from grace, a spot previously occupied by Jayson Blair of The New York Times and Stephen Glass of The New Republic, or a tell-all by a New York gossip reporter (Paula Froelich, Ian Spiegelman and Deborah Schoeneman). Neither category has proved particularly lucrative in book publishing recently.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair, a Times reporter who resigned after it was discovered that he had fabricated and plagiarized a number of articles, wrote a memoir, ''Burning Down My Masters' House,'' published in 2004 by the former New Millennium Press. The book sold roughly 4,000 copies, according to Nielsen BookScan. (BookScan records sales at bookstores, online retailers and some mass merchandisers, which make up roughly 70 to 80 percent of a new hardcover's sales.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Glass, then a 25-year-old reporter and editor at The New Republic, was fired from the magazine in 1998 after his editors learned that he had fabricated dozens of articles. In 2003, Mr. Glass turned his story into a novel whose protagonist, also named Stephen Glass, fabricates articles while working at a magazine called The Washington Weekly. Like Mr. Blair's, the book sold about 4,000 copies.</p>
        <p>The book fizzled with critics, too: writing in The Washington Post, Chris Lehmann called it ''not much of a novel.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern is not the first, or even the second, Page Six reporter who has turned the experience into a book. Ms. Froelich, who still works on the column, and Mr. Spiegelman, whose tenure there ended over an angry e-mail message that Mr. Spiegelman sent to the ex-boyfriend of an ex-girlfriend, both published books within the last two years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Froelich's, ''It!: 9 Secrets of the Rich and Famous That'll Take You to the Top,'' a guide to becoming famous, published by Miramax Books, did the best: it sold about 9,000 copies. Mr. Spiegelman's, a novel titled ''Welcome to Yesterday,'' the story of a gossipmonger at a New York tabloid, sold just 1,000 copies, according to BookScan.</p>
        <p>And Ms. Schoeneman, a former gossip columnist for New York magazine, didn't fare much better with her novel, ''4% Famous,'' published by Shaye Areheart Books, a division of Random House, last year. It sold 4,000 copies in hardcover.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern's publisher, Touchstone Fireside, appears to have grander visions for the book. In a news release announcing the deal yesterday, Touchstone promised that ''Stern will deliver the scoop on the glamorous heights and seamy underbelly of the gossip industry and the New York tabloid wars.''</p>
        <p>The criminal investigation focusing on Mr. Stern's actions earlier this year has not been closed, but prosecutors have not brought charges against him.</p>
        <p>Mark Gompertz, the executive vice president and publisher of Touchstone, said in an interview that he had bought the book, which has yet to be written, based on a proposal of ''a few pages.'' He said he hoped that ''Stern Measures'' would be a serious book, a sort of ''Kitchen Confidential'' of the gossip industry.</p>
        <p>''What interests me is the whole culture of celebrity, this whole gossip industry, so I thought, Who better to write a book about it?'' said Mr. Gompertz, adding that he hoped the story of Mr. Burkle would not play a large role in the book.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Stern will certainly draw from his tenure at The Post in writing the book, Mr. Gompertz said. ''He'll definitely use his experience over the last 11 years,'' he said. ''I would imagine that's what's going to be interesting.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
