<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He's Still Running Out There Somewhere</title>
    <meta content="19Fitness" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/19/fashion/19Fitness.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061109T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1798120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Karnazes, Dean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDE1F30F93AA25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He's Still Running Out There Somewhere</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He’s Still Running Out There Somewhere</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID SHEFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sheff, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the morning of Oct. 6, Dean Karnazes, 43, the world's most famous ultramarathon runner, crossed the finish line of a race through Valley of Fire State Park in Overton, Nev. He was accompanied by 35 runners who had signed up for the 20th leg of Mr. Karnazes' much-publicized Endurance 50, a stunt that has him running 50 marathons in 50 states in 50 days.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has a different reason for being here,'' said Dr. Paul Stowe, one of the racers and a physician from Las Vegas, ''I'm always interested in meeting anyone crazier than I am.'' He looked over at Mr. Karnazes, who was sitting in an oversize chest filled with ice to speed muscle recovery. ''This guy definitely qualifies.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking part in 50 marathons is met with admiration and skepticism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the morning of Oct. 6, Dean Karnazes, 43, the world's most famous ultramarathon runner, crossed the finish line of a race through Valley of Fire State Park in Overton, Nev. He was accompanied by 35 runners who had signed up for the 20th leg of Mr. Karnazes' much-publicized Endurance 50, a stunt that has him running 50 marathons in 50 states in 50 days.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has a different reason for being here,'' said Dr. Paul Stowe, one of the racers and a physician from Las Vegas, ''I'm always interested in meeting anyone crazier than I am.'' He looked over at Mr. Karnazes, who was sitting in an oversize chest filled with ice to speed muscle recovery. ''This guy definitely qualifies.''</p>
        <p>Another runner, Eric Le Clair, had driven overnight from Southern California, arriving at 2 a.m.. (He slept in his car at the side of a road.) After the race, Mr. Le Clair, 29, an assistant cross-country coach at La Salle High School in Pasadena, told Mr. Karnazes, ''You have no idea how much you have inspired me.'' His voice cracked with emotion as he presented Mr. Karnazes with what he said was one of his most prized possessions, the insignia of his division in the Army. ''He is exactly who I want to emulate,'' Mr. Le Clair said after. ''He is superman. He is the absolute best.''</p>
        <p>But not everyone agrees. ''Karnazes is a good runner, though not the greatest runner,'' said Kevin Setnes, the president of the American Ultrarunning Association. ''He's not even in the top 10 in the U.S.'' Other ultramarathoners not only belittle Mr. Karnazes' talent, but also attack him. ''Dean Karnazes is all about Dean Karnazes,'' Mark Long, a marathon runner, wrote in a posting on an ultrarunning forum, ''In my opinion, the self proclaimed Ultra Marathon Man has put a dark cloud in the ultra running community.''</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Karnazes, this relatively small group -- roughly 9,000 people compete annually in ultramarathons, races of more than 26.2 miles, compared with the more than 400,000 who run marathons -- had no superstars. Outside magazine once described the sport's ''unspoken code of modesty, humility and silent suffering,'' and so perhaps it's not surprising that some ultrarunners resent the first of them to attract widespread attention.</p>
        <p>Much of the enmity toward Mr. Karnazes is ''plain old-fashioned jealousy,'' conceded Pam Reed, 45, a champion ultramarathoner from Tucson. ''We complain about him, but would many runners change places with him in terms of sponsors and endorsement deals and magazine covers? In a heartbeat.'' Indeed, Ms. Reed has been trying. She has had been the subject of magazine articles and a ''60 Minutes'' segment, along with Mr. Karnazes, and is on a book tour for her memoir, ''The Extra Mile.''</p>
        <p>But if he's not the best ultrarunner, or even in the top 10, then why has he become the most famous one? Mr. Karnazes admits that he has been successful in part because he's a good businessman and promoter. (No doubt he's been helped by having an M.B.A., 15 years of experience as a marketer for health care and technology companies as well as experience running an organic foods company.)</p>
        <p>Others say that another factor can't be overemphasized. Pamela Streeter, a spectator at the San Francisco race, put it succinctly: ''He's a stud muffin.''</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt that his good looks and great body helped get him on magazine covers,'' Mr. Setnes said. Nor did they hurt when it came to his selection by Sports Illustrated Women as one of the world's sexiest men in sports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karnazes' most ardent fans, however, insist that it's not brawn but brain and heart that won them over. It's common to hear them say that his book, ''Ultramarathon Man: Confessions of an All-Night Runner,'' which made The New York Times's best-seller list for nonfiction in 2005, changed their lives. The book has training and dietary tips, but it is mostly an inspirational memoir. ''I read it, stopped drinking and started running,'' said Larry Friedman, 47, a San Francisco banker who now does ''short 50-mile'' races. ''I felt that his story was my story.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Karnazes' is the story of a high school track star from Southern California who gave up running to pursue, as he put it, ''surfing, windsurfing and drinking.'' In the book, he wrote, ''My energy needed an outlet, and all-night benders filled that need.''</p>
        <p>That is, until his midlife crisis reached a peak on the eve of his 30th birthday. Sick of being miserable, he impulsively donned a pair of old sneakers and began running. He left San Francisco and didn't stop until he reached the coastal town of Half Moon Bay, 7 hours and 30 miles later. ''Everything changed that night,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Karnazes has taken on increasingly difficult challenges. He has finished the Western States 100-mile Endurance Run 11 times. For eight consecutive years, he has run a 199-mile 12-person relay race from Calistoga to Santa Cruz, Calif. In half of them, he raised money for children awaiting organ transplants. The other teams have had 12 runners. Team Dean has had one. He ran his longest race to date, 350 miles, earlier this year. It took 81 hours, during which time he never slept, unless you count ''sleep running,'' which he says he has done a few times.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Karnazes, his running evolved from avocation to vocation; he quit his day job in August. He makes what he said is ''a good living'' -- he declines to say how good -- from book earnings; a low six-figure advance for a follow-up about the Endurance 50; speaking fees of up to $15,000 an appearance; and lucrative sponsorship deals. His primary sponsor is the North Face, for which he helped design an endurance running shoe. He also has a deal with Nature's Path, a health food company, although Mr. Karnazes says he eats pizza, microwave burritos, Cinnabon rolls, Slurpees and cheesecake during these long runs. ''I'm burning more than 600 calories an hour,'' he said. ''I have to replenish them or I'll pass out.''</p>
        <p>Chris Carmichael, who coached Lance Armstrong, modified Mr. Karnazes' regular diet of vegetables and wild salmon, as well as his exercise regimen, in preparation for the Endurance 50.</p>
        <p>To better help Mr. Karnazes recover between marathons, Mr. Carmichael increased the ultrarunner's intake of carbohydrates (to 65 percent of his diet from 55 percent) and fats (to 22 percent from 18 percent) and lowered his intake of protein (to 18 percent from 22 percent). He also changed his workouts. Instead of two 50-plus mile runs a week supplemented by shorter runs, Mr. Karnazes began running every day, sometimes twice a day, for two to three hours at a time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karnazes isn't the first person to come up with a 50-50-50 run. Sam Thompson, 25, an ultrarunner from Bay St. Louis, Miss., completed a similar feat this summer. (He did so without much fanfare.) And the ultrarunning association sponsors tougher runs that go from California to New York City in 64 days. The average race length is 42 miles.</p>
        <p>Being first or doing the most, Mr. Karnazes said, was never the point. ''This was a family vacation run amok, really,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''We looked at a map and realized we could time a trip with some of the county's big marathons -- Boston, New York -- and thought we would recreate our own where there weren't ones scheduled,'' Mr. Karnazes said.</p>
        <p>His motivation, he said, was to spend time with his family, see America and earn money for Karno Kids, his charity that supports the Special Olympics and Girls on the Run, an organization that teaches preteenagers to develop self-respect.</p>
        <p>His wife, Julie, took time off from her dental practice, and they took their children, Alexandria, 12, and Nicholas, 8, out of school. The children are being tutored by Mr. Karnazes' mother, a retired teacher. ''We're like any other family on vacation with 50 strangers tagging along,'' Julie Karnazes said.</p>
        <p>Some legs of the trip have required air travel -- to get, for example, from the Maui Marathon to a race the next day in Surprise, Ariz. -- but the family often travels in a decked-out RV with two TV's and a chin-up bar. They plan to continue until the 50th race: the New York City Marathon, Nov. 5.</p>
        <p>And then?</p>
        <p>Mr. Karnazes hasn't decided. Sitting awkwardly in the ice chest after the Nevada race, he hinted he might conquer new ground. ''There are the Canadian provinces to consider,'' he said. ''There is Europe.'' He shrugged. ''Running is when I am at peace. It's when I'm happiest. You see things you never otherwise would see. You feel things you never otherwise would feel.'' He looked up from the ice bath. ''Why would I stop?''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 9, 2006, Thursday  An article on Oct. 19 about the ultramarathoner Dean Karnazes misstated the dietary changes he made to help him recover between marathons. The figures should have added up to 100 percent for each diet. His old diet consisted of 57 percent carbohydrates, not 55 (he increased this to 65 percent); and 20 percent fat, not 18 percent (he increased this to 22 percent). He reduced proteins to 13 percent (not 18); in the old diet, the figure was 23 percent (not 22).</p>
        <p>The article also misstated the age of Mr. Karnazes' daughter, Alexandria. She is 11 years old, not 12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 9, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Oct. 19 about the ultramarathoner Dean Karnazes misstated the dietary changes he made to help him recover between marathons. The figures should have added up to 100 percent for each diet. His old diet consisted of 57 percent carbohydrates, not 55 (he increased this to 65 percent); and 20 percent fat, not 18 percent (he increased this to 22 percent). He reduced proteins to 13 percent (not 18); in the old diet, the figure was 23 percent (not 22).</p>
        <p>The article also misstated the age of Mr. Karnazes' daughter, Alexandria. She is 11 years old, not 12.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
