<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Across the Country, Movers, Shakers and Contenders</title>
    <meta content="28outlook" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/28/sports/ncaafootball/28outlook.final.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1697960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3D91F3EF93BA1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="2990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Across the Country, Movers, Shakers and Contenders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Across the Country, Movers, Shakers and Contenders</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIG EAST</p>
        <p>WINNER After losing Miami and Virginia Tech a year ago, the Big East lost Boston College this season but gained Louisville, Cincinnati and South Florida. Louisville, which finished 11-1 last season, immediately becomes the favorite. Quarterback Brian Brohm and running back Michael Bush are stepping in as starters, but they will benefit from four returning offensive linemen. If they can avoid injury and keep strong on defense, they ought to secure the Big East's Bowl Championship Series berth. A clash with Pittsburgh on Nov. 3 should be a game to watch.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Dave Wannstedt brings some excitement as the new coach at Pittsburgh. Quarterback Tyler Palko played great down the stretch last season and ought to be even better this year. Although Wannstedt usually favors the run, he is expected to rely on Palko and the passing game. West Virginia is always competitive, but the Mountaineers lost talented players at quarterback and wide receiver. Rutgers has experience and needs to make some noise or Coach Greg Schiano could be in trouble. Greg Robinson takes over as the coach at Syracuse, where he has his work cut out for him.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Pittsburgh receiver Greg Lee was sixth in the nation with 108.1 yards a game, but he has been hampered by a shoulder injury in preseason practice. Rutgers receiver Tres Moses was 11th in the country with 96 yards a game. South Florida running back Andre Hall was ninth in the nation with 123.4 yards a game.</p>
        <p>BIG TEN</p>
        <p>WINNER With quarterback Chad Henne, running back Michael Hart and a good group of receivers led by Steve Breaston, Michigan is the favorite to repeat as conference champion (the Wolverines shared the title last season with Iowa) and challenge for a national championship. The schedule is favorable, with home games against Notre Dame and Ohio State. A game on Oct. 22 at Iowa is a potential speed bump. The defensive secondary is a question mark, but the offense is capable of making up for it.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS An upset victory over Texas on Sept. 10 could give Ohio State the confidence it needs to make a run at the conference title. The defense is the Buckeyes' strength with A.J. Hawk leading the best group of linebackers in the country. Receiver and returner Ted Ginn Jr. merits full attention whenever he is on the field. The biggest question is at running back. Purdue's veteran defense and its favorable schedule could keep it in the race. Iowa returns quarterback Drew Tate, an all-Big Ten selection last season. Penn State has the defense, but the offense needs to improve.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Minnesota running back Laurence Maroney was fourth in the conference with 112.3 yards a game. Northwestern linebacker Tim McGarigle and end Loren Howard are among the best at their positions. Penn State receiver Derrick Williams is a newcomer with loads of talent. Iowa linebackers Chad Greenway and Abdul Hodge are a strong pair.</p>
        <p>BIG 12</p>
        <p>WINNER Conventional wisdom says this will be the year Texas beats Oklahoma for the first time since 1999, but history makes Oklahoma the favorite. Running back Adrian Peterson is a Heisman Trophy candidate, but he will be running behind a revamped offensive line, and the starting quarterback job is still being contested among Paul Thompson, Tommy Grady and Rhett Bomar. The defensive front is as strong as always, but a secondary that often got burned is a potential problem.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Texas is loaded with talent and quarterback Vince Young will lead the offense with his quick feet and improving arm. Running back Selvin Young will need to emerge to balance the offense, but he will be running behind a great line. The first-year defensive coordinator Gene Chizik comes over from Auburn and has lots of talent to work with. Defensive tackle Rodrique Wright is the best in the conference and safety Michael Huff will lead the secondary. Texas Tech, with 16 returning starters, seems ready to take the next step. The North Division is up for grabs with Iowa State, Missouri and Colorado being the favorites. Missouri quarterback Brad Smith has potential to be an exciting player if he is allowed to run. In its second season under Bill Callahan, Nebraska bears watching.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Texas Tech receiver Jarrett Hicks led the conference with 98.1 yards a game. Texas A&amp;M quarterback Reggie McNeal threw 14 touchdowns and only 4 interceptions last season. Iowa State running back Stevie Hicks could lead the Cyclones to the North Division title. Colorado's Mason Crosby is one of the top kickers in the nation.</p>
        <p>PAC-10</p>
        <p>WINNER Southern California is the prohibitive favorite in the Pac-10 with the best offense in the nation. The Heisman Trophy-winning quarterback Matt Leinart returns, as does running back Reggie Bush, who may be the most talented player in the nation. Receivers Steve Smith and Dwayne Jarrett round out the threats on offense, which will be led by the first-year coordinator Lane Kiffin, who replaces Norm Chow, who left for the N.F.L. The defense needs to replace a lot of talent and overcome some off-the-field issues. Road games against Oregon, Arizona State, Notre Dame and Cal could be troublesome and the Trojans will need some luck to repeat as national champs.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Running back Marshawn Lynch is going to be Cal's top option on offense, with Joseph Ayoob, a junior-college transfer, and Nathan Longshore competing to replace Aaron Rogers at quarterback. Arizona State will need Sam Keller to continue to emerge at quarterback, and its defense is improved. Oregon hopes to bounce back from its first losing season since 1993. Coach Tyrone Willingham takes over a Washington team whose 1-10 record last season was the worst in the university's history.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Oregon State receiver Mike Haas was third in the nation with 114.9 yards a game last season. Washington State linebacker Will Derting is one of the hardest hitters in the conference. U.C.L.A. linebacker Spencer Havner led the Pac-10 in tackles last season. Cal linebacker Desmond Bishop, a junior-college transfer, is a newcomer to watch. U.S.C. safety Darnell Bing is often overshadowed by the Trojans' talent on offense.</p>
        <p>SOUTHEASTERN</p>
        <p>WINNER With quarterback Chris Leak poised for a breakout season and the reputation of the new coach, Urban Meyer, for winning right away, Florida is the favorite. On defense, the Gators have lots of potential in the secondary, including safety Jarvis Herring. Receiver Andre Caldwell is a big-play threat on offense. There is a lot of pressure on Meyer and the Gators to succeed after three years of underachieving under Ron Zook, but they seem up to the task.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Tennessee had its share of off-the-field problems in the off-season but still have enough talent to tussle with Florida in the SEC East Division and contend for the conference title. Running back Gerald Riggs, a Heisman candidate, returns and the Volunteer defense is tough. L.S.U. will play host to Florida and Tennessee, which puts the Tigers' first-year coach, Les Miles, in position to make a quick impression. The Tigers have a great group of receivers and a strong defensive front, which should help them win the SEC West. Alabama, with the third-year coach Mike Shula, has one of the best defenses in the nation. Auburn and Georgia are potential dark horses. Steve Spurrier, the new South Carolina coach, makes the Gamecocks worth watching.  PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Tennessee tackle Jesse Mahelona and L.S.U. tackle Kyle Williams are among the best defensive linemen in the nation. Georgia tight end Leonard Pope is a valuable weapon. Auburn's Marcus McNeill is one of the top offensive linemen in the country.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC COAST</p>
        <p>WINNER Virginia Tech made a surprising run to the conference title in its first season in the conference despite not having quarterback Marcus Vick, who was suspended for all of last season because of off-the-field problems. The brother of Falcons quarterback Michael Vick, Marcus Vick is back this season, making the Hokies the favorites in the conference. Cornerback Jimmy Williams leads a defense that allowed 12.8 points a game last season, second best in the nation. If Marcus Vick can live up to his potential and avoid off-the-field problems, the Hokies will be tough to beat.</p>
        <p>The conference has been broken into two divisions, the Coastal and the Atlantic, and will feature a title game for the first time.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Miami, which will be in the Coastal Division with Virginia Tech, is breaking in a new quarterback, Kyle Wright, but Wright has enough talent around him to ease into the role. Receiver Lance Leggett and tight end Greg Olsen will be valuable targets. Return man and cornerback Devin Hester is capable of a big play every time he touches the ball, and Miami's defensive front is very good. Florida State running back Leon Washington will lead its offense, and despite a turbulent off-season at the quarterback position, the Seminoles will be contenders in the Coastal Division. N.C. State, in the Atlantic Division, had the nation's top defense last season and the Wolfpack, along with Georgia Tech, which is in the Coastal Division, are potential sleeper picks.  PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Georgia Tech receiver Calvin Johnson was second in the conference with 69.8 yards receiving a game. Ends Mario Williams (N.C. State) and Mathias Kiwanuka (Boston College) are big-play defenders. Virginia offensive tackle D'Brickashaw Ferguson is the best lineman in the conference.</p>
        <p>SMALL CONFERENCES</p>
        <p>WESTERN ATHLETIC  Southern Methodist, Tulsa, Rice and Texas-El Paso have left for Conference USA, and Idaho, New Mexico State and Utah State join the conference. Despite all that movement, little has changed in the WAC Boise State and Fresno State are still the top teams, with their game on Nov. 10 likely to decide the conference champion. Last season, Boise State won 11 games before falling to Louisville in the Liberty Bowl. This season, the Broncos open at Georgia, then go to Oregon State before playing host to Bowling Green on Sept. 21. If the Broncos can win those, they will be in the B.C.S. picture. Boise State returns quarterback Jared Zabransky, running back Lee Marks and much of their offensive line, so scoring should not be a problem. Fresno State ended its season with an overtime victory over Virginia in the MPC Computers Bowl. This year the Bulldogs have to beat Boise State for their season to be a success. That game will be followed by a trip to face U.S.C. Fresno State will run the ball with the tandem of Bryson Sumlin and Wendell Mathis, who together rushed for 25 touchdowns last season. Combine that with a passing attack led by the returning quarterback Paul Pinegar and the Bulldogs should put up some points. Louisiana Tech and Hawaii lost a lot of talent but could still contend.</p>
        <p>MOUNTAIN WEST  New Utah coach Kyle Whittingham replaces Urban Meyer and has some big shoes to fill. The Utes, winners of their last 16 games, must replace quarterback Alex Smith and try to match last season's improbable run to a Fiesta Bowl victory. Brian Johnson, who saw some action last season, will step in at quarterback and will be throwing to solid receivers. Linebacker Spencer Toone will anchor the defense, which figures to be strong. Unlike last season, there will be more competition for the Utes in the conference. Wyoming returns 19 starters from a squad that beat U.C.L.A. in the Las Vegas Bowl. Receiver Jovon Bouknight had 1,075 yards receiving last year and he returns along with quarterback Corey Bramlet, running back Ivan Harrison and much of the defense. Texas Christian, in its first season in the conference, could be ready to bounce back from last year's down season. New Mexico running back DonTrell Moore rushed for over 1,000 yards last season and is one of the premier offensive players in the conference, but he is returning from a torn A.C.L. Brigham Young has a new coach, Bronco Mendenhall, but it may be another year or two before they get things rolling again.</p>
        <p>MID-AMERICAN  The conference loses Central Florida and Marshall to Conference USA, but there is plenty of talent left. Bowling Green is an offensive powerhouse and should be the favorite. Omar Jacobs threw for 4,002 yards and 41 touchdowns (with only 4 interceptions) to lead an offense that was second in the nation in total yards with 506.3 a game and was fourth with 44 points a game. Running back P.J. Pope will give Bowling Green balance on offense. The Falcons have nonconference games against Wisconsin and Boise State and will face Miami of Ohio on the road. Miami of Ohio returns quarterback Josh Betts and much of the offensive line. The receiving corps is also strong and linebacker Terna Nande returns to anchor the defense. Toledo quarterback Bruce Gradkowski, who completed 70.2 percent of his passes and threw 27 touchdown passes last season, returns to lead a wide-open offense. The defense allowed 126 points in its first two games last season and will have to improve. Northern Illinois figures to run the ball with returning tailback Garrett Wolfe, who was fifth in the nation with an average of 150.5 yards a game last season.</p>
        <p>CONFERENCE USA  With Louisville gone to the Big East, the balance of power will shift in the conference. South Florida and Cincinnati are also gone to the Big East, but Texas El-Paso, Marshall, Tulsa, S.M.U. and Central Florida will come aboard in the new two-division conference. Army also leaves to become an independent. Coach Mike Price is in his second year at UTEP. after an 8-4 season and his team shapes up as the one to beat. Quarterback Jordan Palmer, the younger brother of the former U.S.C. quarterback Carson Palmer, and all of his favorite targets are back as the Miners hope to post back-to-back winning seasons for the first time since 1987-88. Running back Tyler Ebell, who transferred from U.C.L.A., is a player who could make a difference. Memphis running back DeAngelo Williams was third in the nation with 162.3 yards a game and he ran for 22 touchdowns. Alabama-Birmingham, 7-5 last season, is coming off its first bowl appearance and could make some noise. Southern Mississippi lost some talent on defense but ought to be a strong contender.</p>
        <p>SUN BELT  Who led the nation in rushing in 2003? North Texas' Patrick Cobbs. After he got injured last season, who led the nation in rushing? North Texas' Jamario Thomas, with an average of 180.1 yards a game. The two will team up in the backfield this season and make the Mean Green the team to beat in the Sun Belt. The only thing holding it back is a new quarterback and a revamped offensive line. Middle Tennessee is an up-and-coming program, but quarterback Clint Marks (14 interceptions) will have to improve. Middle Tennessee will play host to North Texas on Sept. 10, so it will need to prove itself early. Troy made a splash with victories over Marshall and Missouri at the start of last season but faded in the middle of the year. The Trojans travel to play North Texas on Oct. 4. Louisiana-Monroe returns 18 starters and could be a dark horse.</p>
        <p>IVY LEAGUE  It looks like Pennsylvania and Harvard, who have won the last five league titles, are at the top Last season, Harvard went 10-0 to win the league by one game over Penn, which it beat, 31-10. Harvard needs to replace quarterback Ryan Fitzpatrick, who was last year's player of the year in the league. The return of the preseason I-AA All-American running back Clifton Dawson ought to help matters, as should its stalwart defense. Penn quarterback Patt McDermott leads a group of gifted returning players and the Quakers' defense-- which ranked first in the league last year -- should be just as good. Brown is the closest competitor in the conference and gave Harvard its closest game last season, a 35-34 Brown loss. Brown running back Nick Hartigan is one of the top backs in the conference. Yale, Cornell, Princeton and Columbia will compete for the fourth spot. Dartmouth has a new coach, Buddy Teevens, who won a league title as a player in 1978 and was an assistant under Steve Spurrier at Florida.</p>
        <p>INDEPENDENTS</p>
        <p>Notre Dame  The new coach Charlie Weis is looking at a typically tough Notre Dame schedule with road games against Pittsburgh, Michigan and Purdue. The Irish also have U.S.C. and Tennessee at home as well as a matchup with Washington and their former coach Tyrone Willingham. Quarterback Brady Quinn showed improvement last season and ought to get better under Weis. Notre Dame has gone 11-13 over the last two seasons and will have to retool on defense. If the defense can improve, the Irish could be fine.</p>
        <p>Navy  As always, the Midshipmen will grind it out on the ground. Last season, Navy went 10-2 and averaged 289.5 yards rushing a game, third best in the country. Its leading rusher, Kyle Eckel, is gone and a new quarterback, Lamar Owens, will be taking the snaps, but Navy's defense is improving. The Midshipmen open the season at Maryland and an upset there would get them going in the right direction.</p>
        <p>Army  Bobby Ross brought high expectations to West Point but still finished 2-9 and ended the season with five losses. Running back Carlton Jones was a bright spot with 17 touchdowns and 1,269 yards. Expect improvement, but the Black Knights will likely struggle again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIG EAST.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BIG EAST</p>
        <p>WINNER After losing Miami and Virginia Tech a year ago, the Big East lost Boston College this season but gained Louisville, Cincinnati and South Florida. Louisville, which finished 11-1 last season, immediately becomes the favorite. Quarterback Brian Brohm and running back Michael Bush are stepping in as starters, but they will benefit from four returning offensive linemen. If they can avoid injury and keep strong on defense, they ought to secure the Big East's Bowl Championship Series berth. A clash with Pittsburgh on Nov. 3 should be a game to watch.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Dave Wannstedt brings some excitement as the new coach at Pittsburgh. Quarterback Tyler Palko played great down the stretch last season and ought to be even better this year. Although Wannstedt usually favors the run, he is expected to rely on Palko and the passing game. West Virginia is always competitive, but the Mountaineers lost talented players at quarterback and wide receiver. Rutgers has experience and needs to make some noise or Coach Greg Schiano could be in trouble. Greg Robinson takes over as the coach at Syracuse, where he has his work cut out for him.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Pittsburgh receiver Greg Lee was sixth in the nation with 108.1 yards a game, but he has been hampered by a shoulder injury in preseason practice. Rutgers receiver Tres Moses was 11th in the country with 96 yards a game. South Florida running back Andre Hall was ninth in the nation with 123.4 yards a game.</p>
        <p>BIG TEN</p>
        <p>WINNER With quarterback Chad Henne, running back Michael Hart and a good group of receivers led by Steve Breaston, Michigan is the favorite to repeat as conference champion (the Wolverines shared the title last season with Iowa) and challenge for a national championship. The schedule is favorable, with home games against Notre Dame and Ohio State. A game on Oct. 22 at Iowa is a potential speed bump. The defensive secondary is a question mark, but the offense is capable of making up for it.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS An upset victory over Texas on Sept. 10 could give Ohio State the confidence it needs to make a run at the conference title. The defense is the Buckeyes' strength with A.J. Hawk leading the best group of linebackers in the country. Receiver and returner Ted Ginn Jr. merits full attention whenever he is on the field. The biggest question is at running back. Purdue's veteran defense and its favorable schedule could keep it in the race. Iowa returns quarterback Drew Tate, an all-Big Ten selection last season. Penn State has the defense, but the offense needs to improve.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Minnesota running back Laurence Maroney was fourth in the conference with 112.3 yards a game. Northwestern linebacker Tim McGarigle and end Loren Howard are among the best at their positions. Penn State receiver Derrick Williams is a newcomer with loads of talent. Iowa linebackers Chad Greenway and Abdul Hodge are a strong pair.</p>
        <p>BIG 12</p>
        <p>WINNER Conventional wisdom says this will be the year Texas beats Oklahoma for the first time since 1999, but history makes Oklahoma the favorite. Running back Adrian Peterson is a Heisman Trophy candidate, but he will be running behind a revamped offensive line, and the starting quarterback job is still being contested among Paul Thompson, Tommy Grady and Rhett Bomar. The defensive front is as strong as always, but a secondary that often got burned is a potential problem.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Texas is loaded with talent and quarterback Vince Young will lead the offense with his quick feet and improving arm. Running back Selvin Young will need to emerge to balance the offense, but he will be running behind a great line. The first-year defensive coordinator Gene Chizik comes over from Auburn and has lots of talent to work with. Defensive tackle Rodrique Wright is the best in the conference and safety Michael Huff will lead the secondary. Texas Tech, with 16 returning starters, seems ready to take the next step. The North Division is up for grabs with Iowa State, Missouri and Colorado being the favorites. Missouri quarterback Brad Smith has potential to be an exciting player if he is allowed to run. In its second season under Bill Callahan, Nebraska bears watching.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Texas Tech receiver Jarrett Hicks led the conference with 98.1 yards a game. Texas A&amp;M quarterback Reggie McNeal threw 14 touchdowns and only 4 interceptions last season. Iowa State running back Stevie Hicks could lead the Cyclones to the North Division title. Colorado's Mason Crosby is one of the top kickers in the nation.</p>
        <p>PAC-10</p>
        <p>WINNER Southern California is the prohibitive favorite in the Pac-10 with the best offense in the nation. The Heisman Trophy-winning quarterback Matt Leinart returns, as does running back Reggie Bush, who may be the most talented player in the nation. Receivers Steve Smith and Dwayne Jarrett round out the threats on offense, which will be led by the first-year coordinator Lane Kiffin, who replaces Norm Chow, who left for the N.F.L. The defense needs to replace a lot of talent and overcome some off-the-field issues. Road games against Oregon, Arizona State, Notre Dame and Cal could be troublesome and the Trojans will need some luck to repeat as national champs.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Running back Marshawn Lynch is going to be Cal's top option on offense, with Joseph Ayoob, a junior-college transfer, and Nathan Longshore competing to replace Aaron Rogers at quarterback. Arizona State will need Sam Keller to continue to emerge at quarterback, and its defense is improved. Oregon hopes to bounce back from its first losing season since 1993. Coach Tyrone Willingham takes over a Washington team whose 1-10 record last season was the worst in the university's history.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Oregon State receiver Mike Haas was third in the nation with 114.9 yards a game last season. Washington State linebacker Will Derting is one of the hardest hitters in the conference. U.C.L.A. linebacker Spencer Havner led the Pac-10 in tackles last season. Cal linebacker Desmond Bishop, a junior-college transfer, is a newcomer to watch. U.S.C. safety Darnell Bing is often overshadowed by the Trojans' talent on offense.</p>
        <p>SOUTHEASTERN</p>
        <p>WINNER With quarterback Chris Leak poised for a breakout season and the reputation of the new coach, Urban Meyer, for winning right away, Florida is the favorite. On defense, the Gators have lots of potential in the secondary, including safety Jarvis Herring. Receiver Andre Caldwell is a big-play threat on offense. There is a lot of pressure on Meyer and the Gators to succeed after three years of underachieving under Ron Zook, but they seem up to the task.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Tennessee had its share of off-the-field problems in the off-season but still have enough talent to tussle with Florida in the SEC East Division and contend for the conference title. Running back Gerald Riggs, a Heisman candidate, returns and the Volunteer defense is tough. L.S.U. will play host to Florida and Tennessee, which puts the Tigers' first-year coach, Les Miles, in position to make a quick impression. The Tigers have a great group of receivers and a strong defensive front, which should help them win the SEC West. Alabama, with the third-year coach Mike Shula, has one of the best defenses in the nation. Auburn and Georgia are potential dark horses. Steve Spurrier, the new South Carolina coach, makes the Gamecocks worth watching.  PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Tennessee tackle Jesse Mahelona and L.S.U. tackle Kyle Williams are among the best defensive linemen in the nation. Georgia tight end Leonard Pope is a valuable weapon. Auburn's Marcus McNeill is one of the top offensive linemen in the country.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC COAST</p>
        <p>WINNER Virginia Tech made a surprising run to the conference title in its first season in the conference despite not having quarterback Marcus Vick, who was suspended for all of last season because of off-the-field problems. The brother of Falcons quarterback Michael Vick, Marcus Vick is back this season, making the Hokies the favorites in the conference. Cornerback Jimmy Williams leads a defense that allowed 12.8 points a game last season, second best in the nation. If Marcus Vick can live up to his potential and avoid off-the-field problems, the Hokies will be tough to beat.</p>
        <p>The conference has been broken into two divisions, the Coastal and the Atlantic, and will feature a title game for the first time.</p>
        <p>CHALLENGERS Miami, which will be in the Coastal Division with Virginia Tech, is breaking in a new quarterback, Kyle Wright, but Wright has enough talent around him to ease into the role. Receiver Lance Leggett and tight end Greg Olsen will be valuable targets. Return man and cornerback Devin Hester is capable of a big play every time he touches the ball, and Miami's defensive front is very good. Florida State running back Leon Washington will lead its offense, and despite a turbulent off-season at the quarterback position, the Seminoles will be contenders in the Coastal Division. N.C. State, in the Atlantic Division, had the nation's top defense last season and the Wolfpack, along with Georgia Tech, which is in the Coastal Division, are potential sleeper picks.  PLAYERS YOU MAY NOT HAVE HEARD OF Georgia Tech receiver Calvin Johnson was second in the conference with 69.8 yards receiving a game. Ends Mario Williams (N.C. State) and Mathias Kiwanuka (Boston College) are big-play defenders. Virginia offensive tackle D'Brickashaw Ferguson is the best lineman in the conference.</p>
        <p>SMALL CONFERENCES</p>
        <p>WESTERN ATHLETIC  Southern Methodist, Tulsa, Rice and Texas-El Paso have left for Conference USA, and Idaho, New Mexico State and Utah State join the conference. Despite all that movement, little has changed in the WAC Boise State and Fresno State are still the top teams, with their game on Nov. 10 likely to decide the conference champion. Last season, Boise State won 11 games before falling to Louisville in the Liberty Bowl. This season, the Broncos open at Georgia, then go to Oregon State before playing host to Bowling Green on Sept. 21. If the Broncos can win those, they will be in the B.C.S. picture. Boise State returns quarterback Jared Zabransky, running back Lee Marks and much of their offensive line, so scoring should not be a problem. Fresno State ended its season with an overtime victory over Virginia in the MPC Computers Bowl. This year the Bulldogs have to beat Boise State for their season to be a success. That game will be followed by a trip to face U.S.C. Fresno State will run the ball with the tandem of Bryson Sumlin and Wendell Mathis, who together rushed for 25 touchdowns last season. Combine that with a passing attack led by the returning quarterback Paul Pinegar and the Bulldogs should put up some points. Louisiana Tech and Hawaii lost a lot of talent but could still contend.</p>
        <p>MOUNTAIN WEST  New Utah coach Kyle Whittingham replaces Urban Meyer and has some big shoes to fill. The Utes, winners of their last 16 games, must replace quarterback Alex Smith and try to match last season's improbable run to a Fiesta Bowl victory. Brian Johnson, who saw some action last season, will step in at quarterback and will be throwing to solid receivers. Linebacker Spencer Toone will anchor the defense, which figures to be strong. Unlike last season, there will be more competition for the Utes in the conference. Wyoming returns 19 starters from a squad that beat U.C.L.A. in the Las Vegas Bowl. Receiver Jovon Bouknight had 1,075 yards receiving last year and he returns along with quarterback Corey Bramlet, running back Ivan Harrison and much of the defense. Texas Christian, in its first season in the conference, could be ready to bounce back from last year's down season. New Mexico running back DonTrell Moore rushed for over 1,000 yards last season and is one of the premier offensive players in the conference, but he is returning from a torn A.C.L. Brigham Young has a new coach, Bronco Mendenhall, but it may be another year or two before they get things rolling again.</p>
        <p>MID-AMERICAN  The conference loses Central Florida and Marshall to Conference USA, but there is plenty of talent left. Bowling Green is an offensive powerhouse and should be the favorite. Omar Jacobs threw for 4,002 yards and 41 touchdowns (with only 4 interceptions) to lead an offense that was second in the nation in total yards with 506.3 a game and was fourth with 44 points a game. Running back P.J. Pope will give Bowling Green balance on offense. The Falcons have nonconference games against Wisconsin and Boise State and will face Miami of Ohio on the road. Miami of Ohio returns quarterback Josh Betts and much of the offensive line. The receiving corps is also strong and linebacker Terna Nande returns to anchor the defense. Toledo quarterback Bruce Gradkowski, who completed 70.2 percent of his passes and threw 27 touchdown passes last season, returns to lead a wide-open offense. The defense allowed 126 points in its first two games last season and will have to improve. Northern Illinois figures to run the ball with returning tailback Garrett Wolfe, who was fifth in the nation with an average of 150.5 yards a game last season.</p>
        <p>CONFERENCE USA  With Louisville gone to the Big East, the balance of power will shift in the conference. South Florida and Cincinnati are also gone to the Big East, but Texas El-Paso, Marshall, Tulsa, S.M.U. and Central Florida will come aboard in the new two-division conference. Army also leaves to become an independent. Coach Mike Price is in his second year at UTEP. after an 8-4 season and his team shapes up as the one to beat. Quarterback Jordan Palmer, the younger brother of the former U.S.C. quarterback Carson Palmer, and all of his favorite targets are back as the Miners hope to post back-to-back winning seasons for the first time since 1987-88. Running back Tyler Ebell, who transferred from U.C.L.A., is a player who could make a difference. Memphis running back DeAngelo Williams was third in the nation with 162.3 yards a game and he ran for 22 touchdowns. Alabama-Birmingham, 7-5 last season, is coming off its first bowl appearance and could make some noise. Southern Mississippi lost some talent on defense but ought to be a strong contender.</p>
        <p>SUN BELT  Who led the nation in rushing in 2003? North Texas' Patrick Cobbs. After he got injured last season, who led the nation in rushing? North Texas' Jamario Thomas, with an average of 180.1 yards a game. The two will team up in the backfield this season and make the Mean Green the team to beat in the Sun Belt. The only thing holding it back is a new quarterback and a revamped offensive line. Middle Tennessee is an up-and-coming program, but quarterback Clint Marks (14 interceptions) will have to improve. Middle Tennessee will play host to North Texas on Sept. 10, so it will need to prove itself early. Troy made a splash with victories over Marshall and Missouri at the start of last season but faded in the middle of the year. The Trojans travel to play North Texas on Oct. 4. Louisiana-Monroe returns 18 starters and could be a dark horse.</p>
        <p>IVY LEAGUE  It looks like Pennsylvania and Harvard, who have won the last five league titles, are at the top Last season, Harvard went 10-0 to win the league by one game over Penn, which it beat, 31-10. Harvard needs to replace quarterback Ryan Fitzpatrick, who was last year's player of the year in the league. The return of the preseason I-AA All-American running back Clifton Dawson ought to help matters, as should its stalwart defense. Penn quarterback Patt McDermott leads a group of gifted returning players and the Quakers' defense-- which ranked first in the league last year -- should be just as good. Brown is the closest competitor in the conference and gave Harvard its closest game last season, a 35-34 Brown loss. Brown running back Nick Hartigan is one of the top backs in the conference. Yale, Cornell, Princeton and Columbia will compete for the fourth spot. Dartmouth has a new coach, Buddy Teevens, who won a league title as a player in 1978 and was an assistant under Steve Spurrier at Florida.</p>
        <p>INDEPENDENTS</p>
        <p>Notre Dame  The new coach Charlie Weis is looking at a typically tough Notre Dame schedule with road games against Pittsburgh, Michigan and Purdue. The Irish also have U.S.C. and Tennessee at home as well as a matchup with Washington and their former coach Tyrone Willingham. Quarterback Brady Quinn showed improvement last season and ought to get better under Weis. Notre Dame has gone 11-13 over the last two seasons and will have to retool on defense. If the defense can improve, the Irish could be fine.</p>
        <p>Navy  As always, the Midshipmen will grind it out on the ground. Last season, Navy went 10-2 and averaged 289.5 yards rushing a game, third best in the country. Its leading rusher, Kyle Eckel, is gone and a new quarterback, Lamar Owens, will be taking the snaps, but Navy's defense is improving. The Midshipmen open the season at Maryland and an upset there would get them going in the right direction.</p>
        <p>Army  Bobby Ross brought high expectations to West Point but still finished 2-9 and ended the season with five losses. Running back Carlton Jones was a bright spot with 17 touchdowns and 1,269 yards. Expect improvement, but the Black Knights will likely struggle again.  COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
