<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hamlin Treats Victory As More Than Comeback</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="618355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOPRITE LPGA CLASSIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMLIN, SHELLY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DE133CF93BA15755C0A965958260" item-length="386" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hamlin Treats Victory As More Than Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERS POINT, N.J., June 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shelley Hamlin won the second golf tournament today since she had breast-cancer surgery two years ago, but don't call her courageous or inspirational.</p>
        <p>"Determined and stubborn is a better description than courageous or anything else," the 44-year-old Hamlin said today after winning the $450,000 ShopRite L.P.G.A. Classic at the Greate Bay Resort and Country Club. "People come up to me and tell me I'm an inspiration. I'm just an ordinary person."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shelley Hamlin won the second golf tournament today since she had breast-cancer surgery two years ago, but don't call her courageous or inspirational.</p>
        <p>"Determined and stubborn is a better description than courageous or anything else," the 44-year-old Hamlin said today after winning the $450,000 ShopRite L.P.G.A. Classic at the Greate Bay Resort and Country Club. "People come up to me and tell me I'm an inspiration. I'm just an ordinary person."</p>
        <p>But an ordinary person whose life has changed drastically since she underwent a modified mastectomy 23 months ago.</p>
        <p>"These young ladies are so talented," Hamlin said about the pressure Beth Daniel, Judy Dickinson and Danielle Ammaccapane applied on her down the stretch.</p>
        <p>"But when you already have been through cancer, this isn't that tough," Hamlin said after her one-under-par 70 earned her a two-shot victory and $67,500.</p>
        <p>Hamlin kept her pursuers at bay with birdies on 15 and 17 to seal her third victory in the 22 years on the Ladies Professional Golf Association tour. Her first came in 1978 and her second 14 years later, seven months after the mastectomy in 1991.</p>
        <p>Daniel, in her best finish of the year, finished tied for second at 206 with Dickinson and Amy Benz. Daniel played the steadiest golf all week with no bogeys in the last 40 holes. She was unable to overtake Hamlin because she failed to make several short putts for birdie.</p>
        <p>"I had a lot of opportunities, but I couldn't get any putts to go into the hole," Daniel said. "But I definitely feel that my game is coming back."  Short of Hall of Fame</p>
        <p>Daniel is only three victories, including a major, short of meeting the stringent requirements for induction into the L.P.G.A. Hall of Fame, but she hasn't won since 1991.</p>
        <p>Benz started the day four shots back of Hamlin, but she came within one with three birdies in the first five holes and finished with a 68. Her second-place finish is her best in 11 years on the L.P.G.A. tour.</p>
        <p>"Shelley played tremendously well," Benz said about Hamlin, who played in the last group of the day with Benz and Daniel. "She made the shots coming down the stretch. She didn't make any mistakes."</p>
        <p>Ammaccapane shot two-under 69 for the third straight day and Martha Faulconer, who shot her second straight 68, finished three back of the leader.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
