<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Home Is Sweet, but It Wasn't His</title>
    <meta content="16LIHOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/16/nyregion/thecity/16LONG2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1642339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Hampton (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Sweet Home Museum (East Hampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Payne, John Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Hugh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mead, Julia C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Folk Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Folk Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DD1738F935A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Home Is Sweet, but It Wasn't His</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Home Is Sweet, but It Wasn't His</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA C. MEAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mead, Julia C</byline>
      <dateline>EAST HAMPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on John Howard Payne, who wrote lyrics to song Home, Sweet Home in 1822, in light of new report by Hugh King, director of Home Sweet Home Museum in East Hampton, NY; King, village's architectural historian, says Payne's connection with cottage that houses museum is tenuous at best, based on rumors and concocted stories; lyrics; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1822, John Howard Payne wrote the lyrics to one of the country's most popular and enduring songs, ''Home, Sweet Home.'' For all the accolades it received, he earned only a pittance from it and struggled with money problems much of his life. He was equally unsuccessful as a producer, actor and playwright. He wasn't inducted into the Songwriters Hall of Fame until 1970, 118 years after his death.</p>
        <p>Despite his lack of recognition, or perhaps because of it, for the last 75 years the Village of East Hampton has maintained the Home Sweet Home Museum as a monument to him and his sentimental song. It was here, the widely accepted stories went, that he was born or spent his childhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>EAST HAMPTON.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1822, John Howard Payne wrote the lyrics to one of the country's most popular and enduring songs, ''Home, Sweet Home.'' For all the accolades it received, he earned only a pittance from it and struggled with money problems much of his life. He was equally unsuccessful as a producer, actor and playwright. He wasn't inducted into the Songwriters Hall of Fame until 1970, 118 years after his death.</p>
        <p>Despite his lack of recognition, or perhaps because of it, for the last 75 years the Village of East Hampton has maintained the Home Sweet Home Museum as a monument to him and his sentimental song. It was here, the widely accepted stories went, that he was born or spent his childhood.</p>
        <p>The charming 18th-century shingled cottage that houses the museum on James Lane was said to have inspired the song. It contains the country's largest collection of Payne memorabilia, everything from a portrait of him as Hamlet to the embroidery his sister did as a girl.</p>
        <p>But Payne's bad luck endures. In a report released last month, the village's architectural historian and the museum director say Payne's connection with the cottage is tenuous at best, based on rumors and concocted stories.</p>
        <p>''It's sad,'' said Hugh King, the museum's director. ''So many times in his life, Payne was just in the wrong place at the wrong time.''</p>
        <p>For example, he said, Payne's successful run as Hamlet in Europe augured well for a triumphant debut on the American stage. But, in fact, his debut occurred at the end of the 1813 theater season, and he was forced to take his show on the road. What little notoriety he achieved has since dissolved into near obscurity.</p>
        <p>''And now the one lousy place in the world where he is still talked about is discovered to have almost no connection to him,'' Mr. King said, calling it ironic that Mr. Payne, who is remembered, if he is remembered at all, for having sentimentalized the idea of home, never actually put down roots anywhere himself.</p>
        <p>Although his father taught school across the street from the museum cottage for a time and his aunt once lived in there, John Howard Payne was probably not even born when his family moved from East Hampton to Manhattan and what is now Chinatown.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, William E. Hettrick, the director of Hofstra University's music history program, said he was familiar with ''Home, Sweet Home'' but not its lyricist. He called the song typical of the period, drawn from the Scots-Irish tradition, direct and homey in style, and expressing the yearning for an idealized notion of home that arose during a time of enormous immigration into the United States and widespread westward migration.</p>
        <p>The music for ''Home, Sweet Home'' is credited to Sir Henry Bishop, a British composer who wrote it for a romantic opera, ''Clari, the Maid of Milan.''</p>
        <p>Another reason ''Home, Sweet Home'' became popular, Dr. Hettrick said, was that it was easy to play on the piano, which became a fixture in middle-class households, and untrained voices could sing it easily.</p>
        <p>Paul Moravec, the Pulitzer Prize winner who teaches music at Adelphi University, said the timelessness of the lyrics' nostalgic longing may contribute to the song's popularity. ''Perhaps it has even attained the status of a folk song, a very rare achievement indeed for a consciously composed song,'' Mr. Moravec said.</p>
        <p>In the report, Mr. King, a expert in East Hampton lore, and Robert Hefner, the village's architectural historian, recommend that the museum's focus be shifted away from Payne and toward a trio of unknowns: Gustav and Hannah Buek, transplanted New Yorkers who owned the cottage from 1907 to 1927 and who turned it into a Payne shrine and a museum filled with Colonial artifacts, and Elisha Jones, the sea captain and merchant who, about 1750, transformed the cottage, then little more than a lean-to farmhouse, into a stylish Georgian residence.</p>
        <p>''I never told people that Payne ever lived here,'' said Mr. King, noting that legitimate historians have long doubted the connection. ''Instead, I talked to visitors about the Colonial Revival,'' a period in the late 19th and early 20th centuries marked by fervent nostalgia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buek, who made his money in publishing, spent much of it collecting Colonial furniture, pewter and porcelain, as well as much of the Payne memorabilia now on display. He and his wife opened the cottage for tours, apparently billing it as the inspiration for the still-popular song and de-emphasizing Payne's otherwise less-than-ideal life.</p>
        <p>Dogged by money troubles, Payne once landed in a debtors' prison in England. He is said to have pined for Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley, the ''Frankenstein'' author, but she had her eye on his best friend, Washington Irving. Payne never married.</p>
        <p>Although he achieved some level of respectability when he was appointed as the American consul in Tunis in 1841, his diplomatic career ended there 11 years later, when he died at age 60.</p>
        <p>In 1883, William Wilson Corcoran, a financier and fan, had his body exhumed and returned to the United States to be buried in Washington, another place Payne never lived.</p>
        <p>A gate that still stands at Union College in Schenectady, N.Y., where Payne studied, was erected in his memory, but most passers-by are unaware of its origin, Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>An enormous bust of Payne that once commanded a corner of Prospect Park in Brooklyn was unceremoniously put into storage on Randalls Island by the New York City Parks Department. Three years ago, Mr. King cut a deal with the city and rescued the bust, which now dominates the front room of the Home, Sweet Home Museum, now closed for the winter. It is scheduled to reopen May 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. King said that at best, Payne only visited the cottage when Elizabeth Isaacs Jones, Payne's aunt and Captain Jones's daughter-in-law, lived there. But even that is uncertain.</p>
        <p>Mr. King and Mr. Hefner said the well-preserved cottage, with its picket fence, climbing wisteria and ornate door knocker engraved with the title of Payne's song, was worthy of continued operation as a museum.</p>
        <p>''It is a setting for an idealized conception of what home is,'' Mr. King said. ''We may be oversentimentalizing, but I think there is room for sentiment.''</p>
        <p>Village leaders seem to agree. ''In effect, the myth of John Howard Payne has become part of the village's history and our representation of Home, Sweet Home is going to reflect that, as well as the facts as we now know them,'' said Larry Cantwell, the village administrator. He said the village trustees -- four of the five are from families whose presence in the village dates back to the horse-and-buggy days, and two go back even further, to the earliest settlers -- have no plans to remove either Payne's bust or any of the Payne memorabilia.</p>
        <p>In 1927, a group of concerned citizens bought the cottage and its contents from Mrs. Buek and insured its preservation as a museum by reselling everything to the village for $60,000, what was then a hefty price.</p>
        <p>But even before that, the cottage was a local icon, a symbol of East Hampton's history and the community's fixation on that history. It image appears on everything from postcards and tourist brochures to commemorative Wedgwood plates that now sell on eBay for upward of $65 each.</p>
        <p>The rumor that it inspired ''Home, Sweet Home'' was apparently spread by Henry Mulford, who sought to promote the cottage as a tourist destination, and by Morton Pennypacker, a local historian. By 1913, the Bueks were inviting reporters to tour the house, and the ensuing reports helped establish rumor as fact.</p>
        <p>''It was a good story and still is, but people believed it only because they wanted to,'' said Mr. Hefner, the architectural historian. His 99-page report, commissioned by the village trustees, recommends a few subtle changes to the museum: repainting the parlor's wood paneling a more traditional white and, paradoxically perhaps, rearranging the furniture to a homier configuration to better highlight museum's history as a home.</p>
        <p>''It says everything about East Hampton still being connected to New England and the 18th century and the nuclear settlement around the broad commons,'' Mr. Hefner said, adding that its Georgian features make it the village's best example of that period. ''There is no other house quite like it in the village. I think it is as legitimate as it ever was.''</p>
        <p>His report contains a 1927 quotation from Mrs. John W. Hand, a past president of the Ladies Village Improvement Society. ''It doesn't make any difference to us whether Mr. Payne lived in the house or not,'' she said. ''We know from letters he wrote that he was acquainted with East Hampton and loved it as we do. We know he was thinking of a house like this when he wrote 'Home, Sweet Home,' and anyway, it represents our ideal of home, sweet home, which is enough for us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
