<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tyco Ex-Chief Is Humbled, But Unbowed</title>
    <meta content="16KOZ$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/16/business/16koz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1642597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tyco International Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozlowski, L Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swartz, Mark H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kozlowski, L Dennis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFD91538F935A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tyco Ex-Chief Is Humbled, But Unbowed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tyco Ex-Chief Is Humbled, but Unbowed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with former Tyco International Ltd chief exec L Dennis Kozlowski on eve of his retrial with former Tyco chief financial officer Mark H Swartz on charges of looting company; Kozlowski says he is innocent and public perception of him is misguided; remains unapologetic about his conduct, though humbled by enormity of situation; points to solvency and success of Tyco; contends all bonuses he received were properly authorized by board; regrets allocating too much responsibility to others; graphs; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>L. Dennis Kozlowski wants to be clear: the $6,000 shower curtain wasn't his idea.</p>
        <p>The shower curtain, bought by his decorator on Tyco International's tab for an extravagantly furnished Manhattan apartment, became perhaps the most notable symbol of an era of corporate excess and conspicuous consumption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>L. Dennis Kozlowski declared his innocence in his first extensive interview since he was charged with stealing hundreds of millions of dollars from Tyco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>L. Dennis Kozlowski wants to be clear: the $6,000 shower curtain wasn't his idea.</p>
        <p>The shower curtain, bought by his decorator on Tyco International's tab for an extravagantly furnished Manhattan apartment, became perhaps the most notable symbol of an era of corporate excess and conspicuous consumption.</p>
        <p>''I understand why a $6,000 shower curtain seems indefensible,'' Mr. Kozlowski, Tyco's former chief executive, said on the eve of his retrial on charges of looting the company. ''But I didn't know about it. I just wasn't even aware of it. If somebody had come to me and said, 'Do you want to spend $6,000 on a shower curtain in that apartment?' I would have said, 'Absolutely not. Absolutely not.'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozlowski was sitting in a dreary conference room at his lawyers' office in Midtown Manhattan at eight in the morning recently, nursing his third cup of coffee. Dressed in a black shirt, a pair of jeans and hiking boots, he did not look much like a swashbuckling, custom-suit-wearing chief executive.</p>
        <p>He did not sound like one either. Soft-spoken and uncharacteristically reticent at times, Mr. Kozlowski, in his first extensive interview since he was charged more than two years ago with stealing hundreds of millions of dollars from Tyco, said that he was innocent and that the public perception of him was misguided.</p>
        <p>''People think that I'm a greedy guy; that I was overcompensated,'' he said, leaning forward in his chair. ''Greed, I think, is the key word. But while I did earn enormous sums of money, which for a poor kid from Newark was spectacular, I worked my butt off and it was all based on my performance in Tyco's long established pay-for-performance culture.''</p>
        <p>That image of greed, of course, stems from accusations that he not only awarded himself unauthorized bonuses, but that he had the company also pick up the costs of items like a $15,000 umbrella stand and half the cost of a multimillion-dollar birthday party for his wife on the Italian island of Sardinia, with a now notorious ice sculpture of Michelangelo's ''David'' that flowed vodka.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kozlowski, who faces a second trial on Tuesday in New York State Supreme Court in Manhattan, portrayed himself as a self-made entrepreneur who has become the victim of an overzealous prosecutor interested in sensational headlines and a board trying to protect itself from shareholder lawsuits. While clearly anxious about the retrial and humbled by the enormity of the situation, he remained unapologetic about his conduct at Tyco.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that I never did or intended to do anything wrong,'' he said. ''I never thought in my wildest imagination I or any of us did anything wrong my entire time there. I still cannot believe that they say words like larceny.''</p>
        <p>At the first trial of Mr. Kozlowski and Mark H. Swartz, Tyco's former chief financial officer, prosecutors drew a very different portrait, describing two calculating, arrogant executives who treated the company like their own personal piggy bank. ''They are here not because they blurred the line between themselves and Tyco,'' said Ann Donnelly, an assistant district attorney in her closing statement. ''They are here because they obliterated it, because they erased it.''</p>
        <p>The first trial ended last April in a mistrial after six months. During the deliberations, a juror who was prepared to acquit on all charges appeared to make an ''O.K.'' sign with her hand to defense lawyers, igniting a media firestorm that resulted in the juror's name being disclosed and led to a mistrial after the juror received a threatening letter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozlowski and Mr. Swartz face 31 criminal counts accusing them of stealing $170 million from Tyco by hiding details of their pay packages from the board and pilfering another $430 million by selling Tyco shares after artificially pumping up their price. Both men face up to 25 years in prison. Mr. Swartz's lawyer, Charles Stillman, declined to comment or to make Mr. Swartz available for an interview. If acquitted, Mr. Kozlowski, who is represented by Stephen Kaufman, still may face charges accusing him of evading more than $1 million in New York sales taxes on six paintings.</p>
        <p>Since the first trial, the possibility of plea deals for Mr. Kozlowksi and Mr. Swartz have been broached by prosecutors and the defense, but nothing came of it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozlowski, once the very model of a defiant, confident leader, said the possibility of prison and the emotional toll of another trial is overwhelming. ''It just eats at the pit of your stomach. It's all-consuming. It's the only thing on your mind. It's on your mind when you wake up in the morning. It's on your mind when you go to bed at night. And you dream about it. And you're scared. It's a frightening experience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozlowski's first steps into the limelight came after he became chief executive of Tyco, a New Hampshire-based manufacturer, in 1992. He quickly transformed Tyco, which he had originally joined in 1975, into a Bermuda-incorporated conglomerate that now owns dozens of companies making products ranging from surgical instruments to security systems under the brand ADT. Its stock price rose 15-fold from 1992 to 1999, before tumbling in 2001 after a series of strategic missteps. The stock fell further after Mr. Kozlowski was forced to resign in June 2001.</p>
        <p>But unlike Enron, WorldCom or Adelphia, which all suffered from huge accounting frauds and sought bankruptcy protection, Tyco never entered bankruptcy proceedings or even laid off employees en masse. Indeed, today, Tyco's stock price has rebounded and is even higher than when Mr. Kozlowski left the company, though it still remains lower than its peak.</p>
        <p>''The frustration I had over a long period of time of hearing Enron, WorldCom and Tyco spoken in the same breath -- well, Enron and WorldCom are toast,'' Mr. Kozlowski said. ''Did you watch U.S.C. play Oklahoma for the football championship? All throughout that game, it was mentioned at least 20 times that they're playing for the ADT trophy. That felt really good. Tyco's out there boasting what they're doing day in and day out.''</p>
        <p>That has made it even more difficult for Mr. Kozlowski to accept his current fate. His assets have been frozen, his passport confiscated, his travel limited to going between court appearances in New York and his homes in Florida and Nantucket, Mass.</p>
        <p>It is a long way down from flying on private jets and being driven everywhere by a chauffeur. ''I'm given an allowance to pay for food and, you know, basic essentials that I need,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In September, when the two hurricanes were bearing down on Florida, he had to seek permission from the court to pay to have his house shuttered. ''When you're looking for people who are running around South Florida with their trucks offering to board up houses, you know, they don't necessarily understand, 'Well, I'll have to call the court before I can handle this.'''</p>
        <p>The case against him, he argued, should have been heard in a civil court, not criminal. ''I do believe this is a civil case between Tyco and I. After 27 years, there was an unamicable breakup, a faulty divorce. And I do believe this should be ironed out in a civil manner and certainly not in a criminal manner.''</p>
        <p>He contends that all of the bonuses he received were properly authorized by the Tyco board or that the board had given him the discretion to make such payments. He argues that the board members who have testified that they did not authorize the payments are trying to pin the blame on him because they face a raft of lawsuits from Tyco shareholders.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kozlowski has any regrets, he said that it was that he delegated too much responsibility to others, like his decorator or to his accountants, and focused too much on building the business while not always paying attention to the finer details.</p>
        <p>''If I moved at a slower pace and paid more attention to the details like I did when I was coming up in the operating division of the company, I may have been better off in some ways,'' he said. Still, he insisted that he never stole money from the company nor had any criminal intent to do so.</p>
        <p>Indeed, if the first trial is any indictor, the retrial may turn on the issue of criminal intent. While some jurors said after the mistrial that they were prepared to convict on some of the most serious charges, nearly all said that they had wrestled with whether he and Mr. Swartz had the requisite criminal intent. Ruth B. Jordan, the one juror who was holding out for an acquittal on all charges, said at the time in an interview: ''Intent -- intent was the center of the whole case, at least for me. I don't think they thought they were committing a crime.''</p>
        <p>Several recent legal developments appear to be favorable to Mr. Kozlowski. In July, Mark A. Belnick, Tyco's general counsel, was acquitted of conspiring with Mr. Kozlowski and Mr. Swartz to take a $17 million bonus that prosecutors said was not approved and a $14.5 million interest-free loan that he did not disclose. Several jurors said after that trial that they did not believe directors from Tyco's board who testified that they had not approved the bonuses.</p>
        <p>And in November, the judge in Mr. Kozlowski's case, Michael J. Obus, dismissed the enterprise corruption count against him and Mr. Swartz. That is one of the most serious charges frequently used in Mafia prosecutions.</p>
        <p>There is much pressure on the Manhattan district attorney's office, which has yet to win a guilty verdict in any of the Tyco cases, while federal prosecutors have succeeded in a number of white-collar cases. The Manhattan prosecutors were criticized by all the jurors in the first case for a presentation that was seen as confused and often pandering.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Morgenthau, the Manhattan district attorney, declined to comment for this article.</p>
        <p>As much as Mr. Kozlowski wanted to argue his innocence, he also took great pains to correct what he said were misrepresentations of himself.</p>
        <p>''The general public perception of me -- a lot of its been brought on by a lot of inaccurate reporting in the media,'' he said. He recounted how a tabloid newspaper ran a front-page article ''saying I had this massive party on Nantucket when I wasn't even there. And then that just snowballed into a lot of other stories'' like a television newsmagazine program ''taking pictures of a big mansion in Boca Raton, Fla., and putting it on television.''</p>
        <p>''Well, they had the wrong house,'' he said. ''So it's just one thing after another. I had no rebuttals to this whatsoever.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
