<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRIME/MYSTERY: IN SHORT -- NONFICTION</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="563963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEWEN, BARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOMMERSBACH, JANA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TRUNK MURDERESS: WINNIE RUTH JUDD, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D61F3EF93BA25753C1A964958260" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRIME/MYSTERY: IN SHORT -- NONFICTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barry Gewen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEWEN, BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE TRUNK MURDERESS: WINNIE RUTH JUDD The Truth About an American Crime Legend Revealed at Last. By Jana Bommersbach. Simon &amp; Schuster, $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE TRUNK MURDERESS: WINNIE RUTH JUDD The Truth About an American Crime Legend Revealed at Last. By Jana Bommersbach. Simon &amp; Schuster, $20.</p>
        <p>Winnie Ruth Judd is the Lizzie Borden of Phoenix. Her case has entered the city's folklore and, as with any legend, the truth has become obscured over the years by rumors and exaggerations. This much seems clear: On Oct. 16, 1931, Ms. Judd was staying with her friends Agnes Anne LeRoi and Hedvig Samuelson. Both women were shot to death that night. Their bodies were found in Ms. Judd's luggage in Los Angeles three days later; Samuelson had been cut into four pieces. After an extensive manhunt, Ms. Judd was arrested, tried, convicted and sentenced to death. In 1933 she was declared insane and sent to a state mental institution where, except for several escapes, she remained until her release in 1971. She is now 87 years old and living in California under another name. Jana Bommersbach became interested in Winnie Ruth Judd while working as a reporter for New Times, a weekly newspaper in Phoenix, and a series she wrote for the paper has now been expanded into "The Trunk Murderess: Winnie Ruth Judd." Ms. Bommersbach has spoken to everyone she could find with any connection to the case, including the last living juror; she also spent three days interviewing Ms. Judd herself. She concludes that Ms. Judd acted in self-defense. Readers of this provocative if uneven book may not be wholly convinced. Crucial facts, like a bullet wound to LeRoi's head that does not suggest self-defense, are poorly explained. Motives of key figures are not adequately examined. And if Ms. Bommersbach is right about the amount of exculpatory evidence available during the trial, then Ms. Judd received the worst defense that big money could buy (from lawyers paid for by William Randolph Hearst). Ms. Bommersbach hints darkly at cover-ups and conspiracies, yet offers us little that is concrete. The most certain miscarriage of justice here is the penalty Ms. Judd paid: almost 39 years behind bars -- far longer, Ms. Bommersbach shows, than others in Arizona convicted of comparable crimes served. Whether Ms. Judd is guilty or innocent, there is no denying the sadness one feels reading about a wasted life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
