<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Work; Mapping Offshore Migration of Jobs</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="564042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CARIBBEAN AREA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL LABOR COMMITTEE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AGENCY FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (AID)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERNAGHAN, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLE, BARBARA PRESLEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D61F31F93BA25753C1A964958260" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Work; Mapping Offshore Migration of Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA PRESLEY NOBLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLE, BARBARA PRESLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he set out to document the emigration of employment from the heartland and shores of the United States, it never occurred to Charles Kernaghan, executive director of a union-sponsored research group, that there wasn't someone out there collecting the information he needed. Surely, he figured, there were professors or think-tank wonks who decorated their offices with push-pin maps of plant closings and tables of jobs lost.</p>
        <p>The data weren't available, Mr. Kernaghan says, at least not centrally and systematically. And what was there could not answer the fundamental question: Why do American companies go offshore? So, after spending several months doing more traditional forms of research in archives and libraries, Mr. Kernaghan and his colleagues, Barbara Briggs and Jack McKay, formed a bogus company. Posing as officers of an environmentally correct manufacturing company, they explored the shadowy networks of doing business as a foreigner in Central America and the Caribbean and made the improbable discovery that, advertently or inadvertently, Government programs run through the United States Agency for International Development may be encouraging American companies to go offshore. They estimate the cost to taxpayers at more than $800 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he set out to document the emigration of employment from the heartland and shores of the United States, it never occurred to Charles Kernaghan, executive director of a union-sponsored research group, that there wasn't someone out there collecting the information he needed. Surely, he figured, there were professors or think-tank wonks who decorated their offices with push-pin maps of plant closings and tables of jobs lost.</p>
        <p>The data weren't available, Mr. Kernaghan says, at least not centrally and systematically. And what was there could not answer the fundamental question: Why do American companies go offshore? So, after spending several months doing more traditional forms of research in archives and libraries, Mr. Kernaghan and his colleagues, Barbara Briggs and Jack McKay, formed a bogus company. Posing as officers of an environmentally correct manufacturing company, they explored the shadowy networks of doing business as a foreigner in Central America and the Caribbean and made the improbable discovery that, advertently or inadvertently, Government programs run through the United States Agency for International Development may be encouraging American companies to go offshore. They estimate the cost to taxpayers at more than $800 million.</p>
        <p>The project is in the shadows no longer. Earlier this year it piqued the interest of news show producers, and three Sundays ago, the CBS program "60 Minutes" broadcast a report of its own investigation.</p>
        <p>A few days later, ABC's "Nightline" ran its version of the story over two nights. Even the unflappable Ted Koppel was unable to modulate exchanges between Senator Al Gore and Labor Secretary Lynn Martin that made the Vice Presidential debate a week later look like a Quaker meeting.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration vehemently denies its policies encourage companies to move south, arguing that programs stimulate development and increase imports from the United States.</p>
        <p>The project began in Mr. Kernaghan's office at the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, one of the 21 unions that supports his work, in New York. For nearly a decade, Mr. Kernaghan's organization, the National Labor Committee in Support of Worker and Human Rights in Central America, had monitored political violence. As a delicate peace set in, he turned his attention to the problems of low-paid workers in the region's maquiladoras -- foreign-owned assembly plants.</p>
        <p>The researchers, none of whom have business experience, decided their "company," New Age Textiles, would make re-usable canvas bags that could replace the plastic and paper bags supermarkets use. They made up samples, confabulated a company history, established a mailing address and fax and phone lines and had business cards and stationery printed up.</p>
        <p>In December, they headed for a high-level trade conference in Miami to see if the idea would take flight. "We were nervous, to put it mildly," Mr. Kernaghan said. "Any questions could have blown us out of the water."</p>
        <p>Like many people who have a long-distance relationship with business, Mr. Kernaghan and his colleagues assumed that having no experience, no business plan and no information about markets, distribution or other esoterica might create a problem.</p>
        <p>Wrong. New Age Textile's eco-shopping bag was the hit of the conference. "It captivated them," Mr. Kernaghan said.</p>
        <p>The conference mutated quickly from a test of verity into a whirlwind of opportunities, as members of the group carommed from meeting to warehouse tour to live radio call-in show. One night they dined with the Mayor of Rotterdam, who wanted them to ship the bags to Europe through his port.</p>
        <p>The group spent much of its time visiting booths, pitching its bags to trade organizations from Jamaica, Honduras and El Salvador. At each booth, a representative touted his country's no-tax, low-wage, nonunionized environments and subsidies available for training workers and building factories.</p>
        <p>With more confidence, Mr. Kernaghan took the New Age Textiles show to another conference in April -- this time with "60 Minutes" in tow. In July, again accompanied by "60 Minutes," he went to Central America and the Caribbean, where he found evidence of Government money being used on projects that could undermine onshore industries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kernaghan has been using A.I.D.'s own documents, piles and piles of them, to verify his figures. On "Nightline," Secretary Martin acknowledged that A.I.D. may need a review. But she argued that the agency's programs will lead to regional prosperity, which will benefit the United States.</p>
        <p>Jack Sheinkman, A.C.T.W.U. president and one of Mr. Kernaghan's principal sponsors, recognizes that argument from debates on the North American Free Trade Agreement with Mexico. Since 1983, roughly when the A.I.D. programs began, he has watched the number of jobs in his industry drop 42 percent, to 1.02 million. At the same time, the wages of apparel workers in Central America has dropped to 30 cents an hour from 44 cents. The programs, he argues, are not helping anyone's standard of living and they appear to be impairing the ability of workers to organize.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kernaghan now has the beginnings of the job-loss/plant-closing data base he assumed would be easy to find. He and his colleagues have already inspired Congress to restrict A.I.D.'s activities. And, as he told an A.I.D. official who came to call last week, he has any number of ideas for new research -- research that will almost certainly make somebody at A.I.D. uncomfortable again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
