<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Ravens, Finding Offense Trumps All Else</title>
    <meta content="29RAVENS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/29/sports/football/29ravens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1698137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baltimore Ravens</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D9113CF93AA1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Ravens, Finding Offense Trumps All Else</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For the Ravens, Finding Offense Trumps All Else</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <dateline>OWINGS MILLS, Md.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a corridor leading to the cavernous field house where the Baltimore Ravens practice, the team has posted plaques commemorating the annual leaders in major statistical categories.</p>
        <p>Linebacker Ray Lewis is inscribed as the leading tackler so often on the little gold plates that his name appears to be mashed together into one big entry covering more than half a decade. But it is the offensive plaques that catch the eye for the lesson they offer in how a franchise can be haunted -- and halted -- by an inability to simply score points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the new season begins, the Baltimore Ravens are again desperate to prove they are not a cliché dressed in shoulder pads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a corridor leading to the cavernous field house where the Baltimore Ravens practice, the team has posted plaques commemorating the annual leaders in major statistical categories.</p>
        <p>Linebacker Ray Lewis is inscribed as the leading tackler so often on the little gold plates that his name appears to be mashed together into one big entry covering more than half a decade. But it is the offensive plaques that catch the eye for the lesson they offer in how a franchise can be haunted -- and halted -- by an inability to simply score points.</p>
        <p>That did not matter in the 2000 season, when the Ravens' defense was so dominant on the way to a Super Bowl championship that it rendered the offense virtually irrelevant. That defense allowed the fewest points in a 16-game season in N.F.L. history -- 165 -- a good thing because the offense had five games without a touchdown. They were the anti-Patriots, a team that proved you did not have to be balanced -- in fact, you barely had to be functional on one side of the ball -- to win a title.</p>
        <p>But the plaques bear the grim reminders of failed attempts since then to provide some ballast for that defense. There were the Elvis Grbac and Jeff Blake experiments at quarterback. In 2003, running back Jamal Lewis churned out 2,066 yards, more than 800 yards more than the rookie quarterback Kyle Boller managed to throw for. And last year, the leading receiver was Travis Taylor, with only 421 yards, underscoring just how bad a receiving corps Boller was working with after the Ravens' aborted attempt to acquire Terrell Owens.</p>
        <p>As the new season begins, the Ravens are again desperate to prove they are not a cliché dressed in shoulder pads. If they fail this time, it will not be for the lack of trying.</p>
        <p>The former Giants coach Jim Fassel, who tutored Boller last season, was installed as the offensive coordinator to shore up a unit that finished 31st in the league last season. Rick Neuheisel, the former college wunderkind who recruited Boller while at the University of Washington, is the new quarterbacks coach. Derrick Mason, a 90-plus-catch receiver with the Titans, was signed. And the Ravens used a first-round draft pick on receiver Mark Clayton, who joins former first-rounders like Boller and tight end Todd Heap.</p>
        <p>Coach Brian Billick, who got the Ravens job partly because of the powerhouse offense he helped construct in Minnesota in the late 1990's, compares his conundrum to those of Indianapolis Coach Tony Dungy and Cincinnati Coach Marvin Lewis. Those two have been branded defensive gurus, much as Billick made his name as an offensive mastermind. And as head coaches, all three have had to deal with the bewilderment and frustration that comes with watching one unit -- in these cases, not the unit they are most familiar with -- dominate the team.</p>
        <p>''God has a strange sense of humor,'' Billick said. ''Do I care how we win? No. I don't make a penny for leading the league in any offensive category. But I make a lot of money if we win games. So greed is good.''</p>
        <p>Billick was joking, but he had just come from a news conference in which he spent most of his time defending Boller, who played so poorly in a preseason game against the Eagles that he was booed by the home fans.</p>
        <p>The Ravens reject the notion that they have a limited window of opportunity to make another Super Bowl run while this defense is so dominant. They have reloaded since 2000 with first-round draft picks like safety Ed Reed and linebacker/defensive end Terrell Suggs, even as Ray Lewis speaks of being the league's most valuable player at age 30.</p>
        <p>But the analysis of this team is simplistic and inescapable: If the Ravens' offense cannot become at least respectable, the franchise will continue to waste a defense that will be remembered as one of the best ever.</p>
        <p>''We've known it would be very tough to do it the way we did it,'' Ravens General Manager Ozzie Newsome said. ''We've tried to upgrade offensively.''</p>
        <p>But this year represents the most concerted effort since 2001, when the Ravens -- mindful that a scorched-earth salary-cap purge was coming in 2002 -- thought they had a chance to repeat as champions by keeping the defense intact and bringing in Grbac to lend some firepower to the offense.</p>
        <p>That plan failed and the purge took its toll, but the Ravens made it back to the playoffs in 2003 and were expected to go back last year. Newsome said the team was bitter that it missed the playoffs last season. Now, in Boller's third year, the Ravens hope he will have his Drew Brees moment, when the concerns about his mechanics and his supporting cast will give way to his natural ability, and he will come into his own, as Brees did with the Chargers last season.</p>
        <p>As the Ravens see it, Boller must improve by just the slimmest of margins to make a difference. He completed 55 percent of his passes last season; the Ravens want it to be 60 percent, the cutoff line for good N.F.L. quarterbacks. By Billick's calculations, that means Boller would have to complete just two more passes a game over a 500-pass season. Then, the traditional Ravens philosophy will take over: Give Jamal Lewis the ball and let the defense do the rest.</p>
        <p>''When you have a defense built full of first-rounders, you're going to have an easier time,'' Suggs said. ''We have a lot of stars built in. Whenever you've got a team like this, you want to make a run for it. I think this is our best chance to win it. We got the pieces on offense, and we definitely got the pieces on defense.''</p>
        <p>But the Ravens have thought that before, and all they have had to show for it since the 2000 season are a lot of defensive players in the Pro Bowl. Even now, the Ravens cannot stay away from gilding their already golden defense. On the day they signed Mason as a free agent, they also signed cornerback Samari Rolle from the Titans.</p>
        <p>''We have a fair amount of assets on offense,'' Billick said. ''We have a chance to have that balance. But it's been a five- or six-year process getting there.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
