<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jailhouse Heroes Are Hard To Find</title>
    <meta content="29stan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/29/arts/television/29stan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1698222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Wentworth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purcell, Dominic</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Prison Break (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Fox Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EED61F3EF93AA1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jailhouse Heroes Are Hard To Find</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jailhouse Heroes Are Hard to Find</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley reviews opening episode of new television series Prison Break starring Wentworth Miller and Dominic Purcell; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fear is the flavor of the new season. Network dramas are offering sinister spies, supernatural forces and even a giant sea monster in the hopes of siphoning off some of the success of ABC's plane-wreck series ''Lost.''</p>
        <p>But the scariest perils are the ones closest to home, especially if home is a maximum security correctional facility. ''Prison Break,'' which begins on Fox tonight, is more intriguing than most of the new network series, and it certainly is one of the most original.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prison life is scary, but most of the time it is deadly boring. Luckily, Fox's new network series, "Prison Break," is not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fear is the flavor of the new season. Network dramas are offering sinister spies, supernatural forces and even a giant sea monster in the hopes of siphoning off some of the success of ABC's plane-wreck series ''Lost.''</p>
        <p>But the scariest perils are the ones closest to home, especially if home is a maximum security correctional facility. ''Prison Break,'' which begins on Fox tonight, is more intriguing than most of the new network series, and it certainly is one of the most original.</p>
        <p>Michael Scofield (Wentworth Miller) robs a bank in order to go to prison and break out again with his brother, Lincoln Burrows (Dominic Purcell), a death row inmate. Lincoln insists he was framed, and Michael is determined to help him escape and prove his innocence.</p>
        <p>Michael has meticulously planned a way out, including tattooing blueprints of the prison on his chest, only to discover too late that he badly underestimated the hurdles that lurk behind bars. Before he can start loosening the basement bolts, he has to maneuver past shivs, race riots, corrupt guards, sexual assault, mob collusion and a government conspiracy with tentacles that reach to the White House.</p>
        <p>Fox's hit series ''24'' served as a model for ''Prison Break,'' but that counter-terrorism drama has to keep ratcheting up the threat level, from a presidential assassination attempt to a nuclear attack. The dangers on ''Prison Break'' are more restricted and the countdown is less confining. (Michael has a month before his brother is scheduled to be executed, not 24 hours.) Prison offers its own special terrors: one of the first questions in the 1997 guidebook ''How to Survive Federal Prison Camp'' is ''Am I going to be raped like I've seen on TV?'' The answer is a qualified no.</p>
        <p>There are about 2.1 million people in prison today, a corrections population that is bigger than several good-size cities combined. So it is curious that despite the ever-increasing number of crimes on television, the punishment is so rarely explored. Depiction of prison life is mostly confined to the lyrics and imagery of hip-hop music videos. ''Oz,'' the HBO series that ended in 2003, was the exception -- a layered and extraordinarily brutal look deep inside the Oswald State Penitentiary.</p>
        <p>One might expect broadcast networks to try and develop their own, tamer versions, as they did with ''The Sopranos,'' and are now trying to do with ''Nip/Tuck.'' Villainous heroes are still taboo on network television in a way that sex and violence are not.</p>
        <p>Networks remain skittish about glorifying criminals too openly. ''Line of Fire,'' an ABC series about a crime boss in Richmond, Va., flopped. So did ''Skin,'' Fox's series about a Hollywood pornography king. Convicts are the most problematic characters, and not just because they make poor role models. Television dramas almost always incorporate romantic subplots, and the dating rituals of lockdown are dicey, to the say the least. Even the grittiest crime dramas include hints of glamour and it is hard to find any aspirational subtext to prison life.</p>
        <p>''Prison Break'' does not try to go as deep as ''Oz,'' and its characters are not nearly as finely drawn. Instead, the series has a found a way to tap the horrors of prison life to create a suspenseful thriller. Even the sets have an authentic look: the series was shot inside the Victorian-era Joliet Correctional Center, in Illinois, where the serial killer John Wayne Gacy was briefly held and which was closed in 2002.</p>
        <p>Michael and Lincoln have at least one ally on the outside. Lincoln's ex-girlfriend, Veronica Donovan (Robin Tunney), is a lawyer who represented Michael in his bank robbery case. She too wants to believe that Lincoln was framed, and tries to investigate his case on her own. She practices real estate law, however, and is a bit slow-witted when it comes to anticipating the risks of looking into a government conspiracy. It could be that she is just distracted by her fiancé, an investment banker pressing her to set a date for the wedding.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, who was in the movie ''The Human Stain,'' does not show a broad range of emotion, but he projects an unflappable determination that confounds his fellow prisoners and intrigues the attractive prison doctor, Sara Tancredi (Sarah Wayne Callies). But Michael has a long way to go before he can get himself to the infirmary.</p>
        <p>Henry Pope (Stacy Keach) is the warden, but Fox River State Penitentiary and its corrupt guards are really ruled by a former mob boss, John Abruzzi (Peter Stormare). Territory is balkanized. Black inmates occupy the basketball court, while whites control the bleachers -- and they are led by a pedophile serial killer who seeks to assert control over Michael, as well.</p>
        <p>Prison life is scary, but it most of the time it is deadly boring. Luckily, ''Prison Break'' is not.</p>
        <p>Prison Break  FOX, tonight at 9, Eastern and Pacific times; 8, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created and written by Paul Scheuring; pilot episide directed by Brett Ratner; Mr. Sheuring, Mr. Ratner, Mike Pavone, Matt Olmstead, Marty Adelstein and Dawn Parouse, executive producers; Michael Watkins, co-executive producer.</p>
        <p>WITH: Wentworth Miller (Michael Scofield), Dominic Purcell (Lincoln Burrows), Robin Tunney (Veronica Donovan), Amaury Nolasco (Sucre), Sarah Wayne Callies (Dr. Sara Tancredi), Peter Stormare (Abruzzi) and Stacy Keach (Warden Pope).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
