<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dispute on Pretoria's Stance on Prisoners Persists</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUTH AFRICA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICAL PRISONERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AFRICAN NATIONAL CONGRESS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WREN, CHRISTOPHER S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D61E31F930A25754C0A967958260" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dispute on Pretoria's Stance on Prisoners Persists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WREN, CHRISTOPHER S</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, July 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lifting of American trade sanctions against South Africa has failed to end an emotional argument here over whether President F. W. de Klerk has freed all political prisoners.</p>
        <p>By removing the sanctions on Wednesday, President Bush essentially accepted Pretoria's contention that all political detainees have been freed. The release of political prisoners was one of five conditions set by the United States Congress for the lifting of sanctions when it passed the Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act in 1986.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lifting of American trade sanctions against South Africa has failed to end an emotional argument here over whether President F. W. de Klerk has freed all political prisoners.</p>
        <p>By removing the sanctions on Wednesday, President Bush essentially accepted Pretoria's contention that all political detainees have been freed. The release of political prisoners was one of five conditions set by the United States Congress for the lifting of sanctions when it passed the Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act in 1986.</p>
        <p>But the African National Congress and its allies dispute that the condition has been met.</p>
        <p>The Human Rights Commission, a monitoring group sympathetic to the congress, on Thursday criticized President Bush's decision as "flawed." It said at least 800 political prisoners were still being held, including 284 who the Department of Correctional Services acknowledges had committed offenses related to security or unrest.</p>
        <p>The dispute involves two major points, the first being the definition of political prisoners. The United States says the label applies only to people persecuted for their political beliefs or unduly detained without trial -- not prisoners convicted of violent crimes, even if their motives were political.</p>
        <p>The South African Government imprisoned guerrillas for offenses like murder, arson, robbery and assault, though some have been released recently after starting hunger strikes to claim political status. The African National Congress does not deny that its jailed guerrillas committed violent acts, but says they acted under orders in the campaign against apartheid and should therefore be freed. The congress contends that those detainees were included in an agreement on political prisoners reached with the Government last August.</p>
        <p>The second point involves the legitimacy of black homelands like Bophuthatswana, which South Africa carved out and declared independent 15 years ago. The South African Government says prisoners there are held in a "neighboring state" beyond its control, although Bophuthatswana consists of half a dozen chunks of territory inside South Africa. No other country recognizes the homelands as independent.</p>
        <p>Bophuthatswana holds more than 160 prisoners who the African National Congress regards as political, including more than 140 members of a tiny defense force that was crushed by South African troops when it joined in a coup attempt in the homeland in February 1988. Bophuthatswana's prisons commissioner said on Thursday that 54 of the prisoners were on a hunger strike to force their release.</p>
        <p>"The United States does not recognize Bophuthatswana as an independent state and cannot therefore go along with State President de Klerk's claim that these prisoners, clearly political, are not the responsibility of the Government," the Human Rights Commission said.</p>
        <p>South Africa's white right wing argues that if congress African National Congress members who fought apartheid are being released, the amnesty should include white rightists jailed for defending apartheid. Most are in prison for shooting or bombing attacks against blacks. Several face extradition for an attack two years ago on a United Nations office in the Namibian town of Outjo.</p>
        <p>Robert van Tonder, leader of the white supremacist Boerestaat Party, said on Tuesday that the Government was deceiving Western governments in saying all political prisoners were freed, since "at least 15 Boer freedom fighters," among them veterans of wars in Namibia and Angola, are languishing in jail.</p>
        <p>"Is this the way in which South Africa thanks its sons for risking their lives in a long battle against Communism and terrorism?" Mr. van Tonder said.  Report of Agreement</p>
        <p>On July 1, President de Klerk reported that the Government and the congress had reached a "finality" of agreement on the question of political prisoners. A day later, the congress leader, Nelson Mandela, denied that such an agreement had been reached.</p>
        <p>The Government last week reduced the sentences of common convicts by one third. The Human Rights Commission said previous sentence reductions last December and May might have freed as many as 2,000 unidentified political prisoners but added that as many of 50,000 criminals could be back on the streets by the time the process was completed. Those released so far include two white former policemen who served a little more than three years for killing two drug dealers.</p>
        <p>Brian Currin, national director of the Lawyer for Human Rights, accused parole officials of being "obscure and dishonest" in applying President de Klerk's remission provisions to favor whites. The Citizen, a conservative daily newspaper, complained that the Government was freeing every violent criminal to satisfy the African National Congress and the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
