<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Price Gains Erode in Bond Market</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOND PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCER PRICE INDEX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAIDENBERG, H J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Producer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE173CF930A25754C0A967958260" item-length="426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Price Gains Erode in Bond Market</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By H. J. MAIDENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAIDENBERG, H J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Further evidence that the economy is still weak buoyed the prices of Treasury and other fixed-income securities yesterday, but the early gains were somewhat eroded later in the day.</p>
        <p>The debt market had expected that the Government would report basically unchanged core producer prices, excluding the volatile food and energy sectors, and it did, although the overall Producer Price Index for June dropped by three-tenths of a percent. The market also was pleasantly surprised by a drop in retail sales of two-tenths of a percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Further evidence that the economy is still weak buoyed the prices of Treasury and other fixed-income securities yesterday, but the early gains were somewhat eroded later in the day.</p>
        <p>The debt market had expected that the Government would report basically unchanged core producer prices, excluding the volatile food and energy sectors, and it did, although the overall Producer Price Index for June dropped by three-tenths of a percent. The market also was pleasantly surprised by a drop in retail sales of two-tenths of a percent.</p>
        <p>But dealers said that the bond price rises set off by the early morning reports were soon lessened by other considerations. Not only did the dollar fall sharply and thus make dollar-denominated investments less attractive, but prices of oil products and other basic commodities had a sudden and sharp rebound.</p>
        <p>Bane of Fixed-Income Market</p>
        <p>If sustained, the stronger industrial and farm commodity prices could cause a rise in inflation, the bane of the fixed-income market. Investors in fixed-income securities fear inflation and anything that could stimulate it, such as an improving economy, because this usually leads to higher interest rates on newer debt offerings, making yields and values of existing issues less attractive.</p>
        <p>Thus the drop in June retail sales confirmed fears that the May surge of eight-tenths of a percent was an aberration caused by record hot weather that greatly improved sales of all kinds of summer goods.</p>
        <p>"The bond market was so sure the core June Producer Price Index would be flat, which it was, that it ignored bad news signaled by the big drop in the latest week's initial claims for unemployment insurance reported the day before," said Steven R. Ricchiuto, chief financial economist at Barclays de Zoete Wedd Securities Inc.</p>
        <p>As for rumors that the Federal Reserve was about to ease interest rates further, Mr. Ricchiuto said they originated in the foreign exchange market and were dismissed out of hand by participants in the Treasury securities market.</p>
        <p>"But the sharp drop in the dollar's value against the mark and other key currencies was very real and it weighed on the bond market," he added. "Also causing downward pressure is the belief that the dollar will weaken further. The huge supply of new Treasury paper coming to market in the next few weeks added to the gloom."</p>
        <p>Despite the pessimism that settled over the market late in the session, the Treasury's benchmark long bonds, the 8 1/8 percent issue maturing in May 2021, held onto some early gains.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
