<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reaching for the Stars in the New Military</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY PERSONNEL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDA1238F937A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reaching for the Stars in the New Military</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 1960's, a hard-charging, freshly minted second lieutenant wanted to go to Southeast Asia to experience combat in the Vietnam War. In 1990 and 1991, commanders turned away many young officers who volunteered for action in the Persian Gulf region.</p>
        <p>For generations of American warriors, there has never been much of a question: the essence of soldiering is fighting and winning. Officers have been willing, even eager, to put themselves in harm's way, because the surest route to high rank and regard has been to lead troops into battle. But today, in the absence of old-fashioned wars with clearly defined front lines, soldiers who have toiled largely in anonymity are coming to the fore to deal with many non-traditional missions, from combatting drug dealers to pulling riot-control duty. People mastering these skills can be well on their way to the general or admiral rank once largely reserved for the battlefield veterans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 1960's, a hard-charging, freshly minted second lieutenant wanted to go to Southeast Asia to experience combat in the Vietnam War. In 1990 and 1991, commanders turned away many young officers who volunteered for action in the Persian Gulf region.</p>
        <p>For generations of American warriors, there has never been much of a question: the essence of soldiering is fighting and winning. Officers have been willing, even eager, to put themselves in harm's way, because the surest route to high rank and regard has been to lead troops into battle. But today, in the absence of old-fashioned wars with clearly defined front lines, soldiers who have toiled largely in anonymity are coming to the fore to deal with many non-traditional missions, from combatting drug dealers to pulling riot-control duty. People mastering these skills can be well on their way to the general or admiral rank once largely reserved for the battlefield veterans.</p>
        <p>The end of the cold war and a spate of peacekeeping and humanitarian missions have thrown open a new set of opportunity-filled fields in unlikely areas. The gulf war made famous an obscure Army logistician named Gus Pagonis, a major general who moved six million tons of equipment into the war zone. Logistics wizards, like those now building tent cities for Cuban boat people at Guantanamo Bay or hauling relief supplies to refugees in Rwanda, have been held in higher regard ever since.</p>
        <p>The warriors of the future will also include computer nerds and intelligence geeks guiding troops on a digitized battlefield. Even the once-dreary acquisition corps has acquired cachet as Defense Secretary William J. Perry tries to streamline how the Pentagon buys $50 billion a year in weapons and parts. Suddenly, buying blankets and combat boots is a lot sexier.  Less Room for Missteps</p>
        <p>While opening doors in some fields, the cold war's demise has meant smaller forces and fewer opportunities over all. Career paths are more competitive for young officers who need to punch the right ticket at the right time in a system that is less straightforward and far less forgiving than it was a decade ago.</p>
        <p>For instance, some young Navy and Marine Corps officers who were investigated in the Tailhook sexual-harassment scandal fell behind their peers, and even those who were cleared now face an uphill struggle. And with America's nuclear arsenal shrinking, officers who supervise missile silos under North Dakota wheat fields -- a prestige-filled mission a few years ago -- may be looking for work. "If you don't hit gates when they swing open, you may never get a chance to do it again," said one Navy commander, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. (Almost everyone interviewed insisted on anonymity to avoid violating a cardinal rule of rung-climbing: no self-aggrandizement in the press.)</p>
        <p>Fast-trackers with their sights set on the Joint Chiefs of Staff will still come from the combat arms branches: armor, infantry and artillery in the Army and Marine Corps; submarines, carrier jets and warships in the Navy, and warplanes in the Air Force.</p>
        <p>But what's hot and what's not in the military mirrors which branch of each service is on the cutting edge in war-fighting strategy. Because of the Battle of Midway in June 1942, ambitious young Navy people wanted carrier duty -- and indeed for decades carrier men rose to the top more than the brass from other naval branches. In the 1980's, American submariners who waged silent underwater duels with their Soviet counterparts rose to the top of the Navy's chain of command.</p>
        <p>Bomber pilots dominated the senior ranks of the Air Force until Vietnam, when fighter jocks shoved them aside, seizing a stranglehold they still hold.</p>
        <p>Since the Revolutionary War, the ticket to the top has been command of troops in the field. And if the officer is lucky enough for a good war to come along, all the better. "Command is still the ultimate test of an officer's abilities, and it's as important a factor as it's ever been," said Rear Adm. Patricia Tracey, the personnel director for the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
        <p>Leading troops in a popular war has always produced instant heroes. Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf was counting down his final days in the Army at the United States Central Command in Tampa, Fla., a backwater post, when Iraq invaded Kuwait in August 1990. Soldier-Statesman Is Ideal</p>
        <p>Now, for the first time since Navy gunboats plied the rivers of Vietnam, young naval officers are getting a crack at early commands, this time in small patrol boats like those now helping enforce the economic embargo against Haiti.</p>
        <p>The raft of relief and peacekeeping operations has upped the ante for soldier-statesmen. Lieut. Gen. Anthony Zinni of the Marine Corps has conducted relief missions in Russia, Iraq and Somalia and is considered such a poster boy for peacekeeping that he testified before a House committee on the Rwanda operation.</p>
        <p>In today's grudgingly politically correct military, an officer's record on opening opportunities for women also counts toward promotion. The new emphasis has opened new doors to women themselves -- ushering in female fighter pilots and warship officers. The new Chief of Naval Operations, Adm. Jeremy M. Boorda, notched his warrior stripes directing NATO operations in Bosnia.  But he also won the top Navy job because of his progressive views on opening more combat jobs for women.</p>
        <p>This attitude has yet to reach the Marine Corps and Army, where crusty generals perpetuate their self-selective club by freezing women out of the only three branches of the service that produce commandants and chiefs of staff: armor, artillery and infantry.</p>
        <p>There is no magic formula to the top, a journey that typically alternates field assignments with desk jobs and military schooling. But officers say a few tips help to navigate the shoals of promotion boards.</p>
        <p>Tip No. 1 -- Excel at the desk or in the field, but try to get field assignments as often as possible, from anti-drug operations in the Caribbean to peacekeeping duty in Macedonia, and earn command of troops early on. "With things so much more competitive now, there's no real time to grow into a new job," said Capt. Frank Dobrydney, the Navy's head of career-management policy.  "You have to hit the deck running."</p>
        <p>Tip No. 2 -- Angle for high-visibility staff jobs in major commands or at the Pentagon, where senior civilians as well as the military brass can see your work.  Build political connections, a la Brent Scowcroft and Alexander Haig. In the Army and Navy, senior generals and admirals adopt promising young officers as their "sons" and "daughters" and help manage their careers.  But avoid tying yourself too closely to one mentor.</p>
        <p>Tip No. 3 -- When the time is right, earn a graduate degree and jockey for a position at one of the military colleges, preferably the National War College in Washington. Winning a White House fellowship, as Colin L. Powell did as a young lieutenant colonel, is a career booster. A tour on the military's Joint Staff, the administrative arm of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, helps enormously.</p>
        <p>By the time an officer reaches general or admiral, politics and talent figure equally in promotions. It doesn't hurt to hitch your star to a top civilian. Adm. Paul David Miller, the commander of American forces in the Atlantic, leapfrogged over dozens of more senior admirals in the late 1980's when Navy Secretary John F. Lehman Jr. tapped him as a favorite. It pays to have a little luck.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
