<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Natural' Supermarket From Grains to Pizza</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="A LA CARTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDD1438F937A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Natural' Supermarket From Grains to Pizza</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FULL service natural-food supermarket has opened in Huntington. Straight From the Heart, at 80 East Main Street (549-3750), which bills itself as "Long Island's largest natural market," is a combination market, health store, delicatessen and restaurant. Its 7,000 square feet are crammed with everything organic, from produce to pizza, sauces, spices, grains, herbs and salads as well as hot and cold daily specials at eight tables in its tiny restaurant section.</p>
        <p>This vegeterian nirvana, which replaces an auto parts store at this site, has a climate and humidity controlled grain room that protects bulk grains from rancidity and infestation. Twenty-six organic coffees, as well as organic orzo, quinoa, granola, apple rings and dates, along with a myriad of other flours, wheats and grains can be purchased there in just the quantities home cooks need and no more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FULL service natural-food supermarket has opened in Huntington. Straight From the Heart, at 80 East Main Street (549-3750), which bills itself as "Long Island's largest natural market," is a combination market, health store, delicatessen and restaurant. Its 7,000 square feet are crammed with everything organic, from produce to pizza, sauces, spices, grains, herbs and salads as well as hot and cold daily specials at eight tables in its tiny restaurant section.</p>
        <p>This vegeterian nirvana, which replaces an auto parts store at this site, has a climate and humidity controlled grain room that protects bulk grains from rancidity and infestation. Twenty-six organic coffees, as well as organic orzo, quinoa, granola, apple rings and dates, along with a myriad of other flours, wheats and grains can be purchased there in just the quantities home cooks need and no more.</p>
        <p>Over 60 organic salads, everything from tuna to tabbouleh, are made fresh daily for take-out or eat-in.</p>
        <p>Straight From the Heart will make juice from any of its produce at a juice bar turning out orange, berry, carrot, beet, celery and cucumber concoctions, straight or blended.</p>
        <p>Pizzas, with wholewheat and brown rice crusts that sport organic sauces and spices, are the most frequently seen fare at the tables. Low-fat and soy cheeses, organic mushrooms, tofu, spinach, brocolli, bean sprouts, tomato and basil are all popular toppings.</p>
        <p>Mary and Lenny Liotta, a mother and son team from Glen Head, own Straight From the Heart. They have hired Adam Schneider, who managed the Rising Tide Health Food Store in Glen Cove and was kitchen manager at the Milleridge Inn in Jericho, as a consultant.  Last-Minute Wine Dinner</p>
        <p>The decision to have a wine-tasting meal at Panama Hattie's in Huntington Station has become a spur-of-the-moment matter. The restaurant's relatively new policy of offering a five-course tasting dinner every night, except Saturday, frees patrons from having to make plans in advance.</p>
        <p>In fact, the manager, Stacy Kaplan, says, "90 percent of the people who try the $65 dinner decide to do so after they reach the restaurant." She says, "Now there's no need to worry about having to honor a pre-paid wine dinner reservation even though the weather is terrible or someone is ill."</p>
        <p>Another distinctive aspect of Panama Hattie's wine tasting dinners is the wine itself, which is of a higher quality than that served at many similar affairs. A fragrant, intense Roussane Vieille Vignes 1991 or Old Vine's Rhone wine from Chateau de Beaucastel served recently costs around $60 a bottle.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most unusual of all is the fact that the restaurant, at 872 East Jericho Turnpike (351-1727), offers wines at the right temperature. Unlike so many Island spots, white wine is not too cold or red too warm.  Potpourri</p>
        <p>The Pine Island Grill at the Crescent, 333 Bayville Avenue, in Bayville (628-3000), has scheduled a lavish, Labor Day celebration today. It includes a reggae band on the beach, a fireworks display and a fixed price $50 dinner with seatings at 6 and 8 PM.</p>
        <p>The four-course meal includes a choice of entrees: either prime rib of beef with cornbread pudding and swiss chard, or horseradish-crusted salmon with beet, apple and watercress salad.</p>
        <p>The Raven, a 47-foot ketch that offers two-hour sails from Montauk, has teamed up with Dave's Grill on West Lake Drive, at Montauk Harbor (668-3719).</p>
        <p>Passengers who take the Raven's 3 P.M. cruise can opt for a special 5 P.M., $19.95 lobster dinner at Dave's. The dinner includes a choice of soup or salad, a one and a half pound lobster and coffee. The Raven is also offering a $5 discount off its $20 fare to passengers who purchase the dinner and cruise combination.</p>
        <p>The Country Club at Conscience Point in Southampton is featuring a Sunday night $10 country-style chicken-and-ribs barbeque meal. Wine Tasting</p>
        <p>Suzanne's Bistro at Salisbury Inn, East Meadow (794-5382), is holding an alfresco wine dinner this Saturday night in a tent at Eisenhower Park. Wines from nine areas of California will be introduced by John Sheldon, an experienced sommelier, at the $37.50 event.</p>
        <p>Due Torre, 330 Motor Parkway, Hauppaugue (435-8664), will hold a four-course, $55-wine-tasting dinner at 7 P.M. on Thursday. Palmer wines will accompany the meal, which features a rack of veal main course.  A LA CARTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
