<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE NATION: Taking Sausage; The Art of Reprocessing the Democratic Process</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DA1238F937A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE NATION: Taking Sausage; The Art of Reprocessing the Democratic Process</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALREADY, some pundits and politicians are weaving a tidy narrative around the collapse of health care reform. The Clinton Administration overreached, they say. After a long and vigorous debate about the Clinton plan, people gradually turned away from the idea of a comprehensive overhaul and Congress responded to their will. The Framers, in other words, would be pleased; the system worked.</p>
        <p>But there is another case to be made: That the system was simply overwhelmed by millions of dollars worth of lobbying, polling and advertising. That it was whipsawed by two years of strategizing and manipulation by the top consultants and theoreticians in both parties. That Americans were taken on an emotional, 18-month journey that produced not a new consensus but an exhausted paralysis -- and is likely to feed their already corrosive cynicism toward their government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALREADY, some pundits and politicians are weaving a tidy narrative around the collapse of health care reform. The Clinton Administration overreached, they say. After a long and vigorous debate about the Clinton plan, people gradually turned away from the idea of a comprehensive overhaul and Congress responded to their will. The Framers, in other words, would be pleased; the system worked.</p>
        <p>But there is another case to be made: That the system was simply overwhelmed by millions of dollars worth of lobbying, polling and advertising. That it was whipsawed by two years of strategizing and manipulation by the top consultants and theoreticians in both parties. That Americans were taken on an emotional, 18-month journey that produced not a new consensus but an exhausted paralysis -- and is likely to feed their already corrosive cynicism toward their government.</p>
        <p>In short, there is substantial evidence that the deadlock on health care is a monument not to the Framers' system, but to what we have done to it: a harrowing example of what happens when the tools, techniques and philosophy of the modern campaign are brought to bear on the policy-making process.</p>
        <p>Peter Hart, a Democratic pollster who tracked the health care issue for NBC and The Wall Street Journal, said: "The worst of the process worked. Yes, there was a dialogue, but it was so influenced and affected by the special interest groups that the public didn't get a true and honest debate. What they learned is everything they had to fear -- and very little about what they could hope for."</p>
        <p>Bob Blendon, an expert on public opinion and health at Harvard, said the public still wants to do something about the faults and failings of the health care system. They grew wary of the Clinton plan, he said, and worried that Congress was rushing to slap together a new one. "But what they say in all the polls is, 'We want an alternative plan, less threatening, less bureacuractic, but still a major plan,' " Mr. Blendon added.</p>
        <p>They might not get it. Congressional leaders say they still hope to find a modest, scaled-back alternative when they return after Labor Day. But when policy-making is played out by the rules of modern politics, as the health care struggle has been from the start, it makes compromise -- especially bipartisan compromise -- very hard to reach.</p>
        <p>This is hardly the first time that a public policy dispute spilled out of the Capitol and into the venues ordinarily used for election campaigns. The fight over Medicare in 1965, and over President Harry Truman's proposal for national health insurance in 1949, prompted a wave of leafletting and advertising. The fight over the North American Free Trade Agreement had the feel of a campaign. But campaign technique keeps developing, in a kind of arms race, and rarely has there been a more avid group of practitioners than there was in the health care struggle of 1993-94.</p>
        <p>Modern politics exalts the grass roots, so interest groups spent $50 million in advertising to cultivate "grass-roots" sentiment, much of it simply to raise fears about the risks of various plans. A study by Darrell M. West and Diane J. Heith, political scientists at Brown University, estimated that "groups opposed to the Clinton program outspent those that favored it by a 4-to-1 ratio in the advertising area." They concluded that "the one-sided nature of the ad expenditures had important consequences for the health care debate."</p>
        <p>Modern politics also reveres the lawmaker who is quiveringly sensitive to the folks back home, so the best-organized interests -- like the National Federation of Independent Business, which targeted small businesses in numerous Congressional districts -- have become as powerful as any committee chairmen searching for a compromise.</p>
        <p>Modern politics is prefaced on the idea that taxpayers are fundamentally tax-averse, so all the efforts to achieve a major expansion of coverage have been stymied by the fact that almost no one will propose a broad-based tax increase to pay for it. "Rather than educating our constituents about the tough choices, too many politicians in both parties are once again pandering to them -- promising the impossible and then feigning shock when the Congressional Budget Office inevitably weighs in with the painful truth," Representative Dan Rostenkowski wrote not long ago.</p>
        <p>"The fact is, if we want more Americans to have better insurance, we're all going to have to pay for it," the Illinois Democrat added.</p>
        <p>More than anything, modern politics never goes off campaign footing, which has proven to be particularly damaging to the prospects for health care legislation. Republicans note -- correctly -- that even before the Clinton Administration had a health care package, it had a deeply political strategy to sell the plan, and allies touting it in partisan terms.  William Kristol, a strategist for conservative Republicans, asserted in an interview: "That authorized the use of political means to oppose their campaign. And in some respects, it delegitimized them."</p>
        <p>The stakes for each party -- as a party -- became very clear very fast. Democratic strategists were telling lawmakers that a health care bill was critical to their re-election efforts; a much-circulated memo by Mr. Kristol in December warned Republicans that passage of the Clinton plan "will revive the reputation of the party that spends and regulates, the Democrats, as the generous protector of middle-class interests."</p>
        <p>The news media slipped into the campaign mode as well, said Tom Patterson, a politial scientist at Syracuse University. Much of the coverage focused on whether Mr. Clinton was winning or losing, "as opposed to the merits of health care reform," he said.</p>
        <p>The debate, by midsummer, was unrelentingly partisan, evocative of the last days of the 1988 Presidential campaign -- not fertile soil for a bipartisan deal. There are those, of course, who argue that it was a healthy debate, particularly if the alternative is the smoke-filled room. "The alternative to a political debate that engages the public is an interest group-dominated, behind-closed-doors Congressional process of making deals," Mr. Kristol said.</p>
        <p>And it can be stipulated that change of this scale is inherently hard. Joseph A. Califano Jr., who lived through the successful effort to pass Medicare in 1965, noted that Lyndon Johnson had just won re-election with 61 percent of the vote, had a 68-vote Democratic majority in the Senate, had Everett Dirksen as the Republican leader and was himself "probably the most effective legislator we've ever had." Even so, Mr. Califano said, "we had to give the doctors and hospitals what they wanted to get it passed."</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Califano said, "the climate is much more partisan today, and the lobbyists are richer and more sophisticated." He added that in 1965, "there was a great deal of confidence in the capacity of government to do something." The Atwater Doctrine</p>
        <p>Today, the public reflects a 30-year trend of lost faith in government. The consultants and the politicians -- and Mr. Patterson would add the press -- responded to that cynicism in the health care struggle and in many instances fed it, as they have in one campaign after another in recent years.  "The American poeple are cynical and turned off about all the institutions, and politics is only one of them," said Lee Atwater, the late Republican consultant, arguably the most influential of his era, in an interview in February 1990. "Bull permeates everything."</p>
        <p>Now the voters have something else to be cynical about: a two-year-long, fiercely partisan, bitterly divisive campaign that has ended -- at least so far -- in a confusing deadlock. "We had to overcome the fear of change and I think we were unable to do that," an Administration official said sadly this week. While people "intuitively know" that they are being victimized in the current system, the official said, "they're very fearful of government and very fearful of change."</p>
        <p>Of course, the problems in the health care system remain: the 39 million who are uninsured, the gaps in coverage for millions of others, the costs that consume a greater and greater share of the Federal budget and the gross domestic product. There are still legislators on Capitol Hill who remember this. In the tactical din of the modern campaign, it is easy to lose sight of the reality outside.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
