<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dallas's Loss Becomes Knicks' Huge Gain</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="752560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, CLIFTON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARPER, DEREK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DD1F3CF931A35757C0A963958260" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dallas's Loss Becomes Knicks' Huge Gain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, CLIFTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acquiring Derek Harper was one of the most important moves the Knicks have made in recent years.</p>
        <p>Just ask Dick Motta, who returned to coach the Dallas Mavericks a year too late to stop Harper from getting traded in January 1994 for Tony Campbell and a 1997 first-round pick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acquiring Derek Harper was one of the most important moves the Knicks have made in recent years.</p>
        <p>Just ask Dick Motta, who returned to coach the Dallas Mavericks a year too late to stop Harper from getting traded in January 1994 for Tony Campbell and a 1997 first-round pick.</p>
        <p>"It's no fun to watch Derek when I'm envisioning Jimmy Jackson, Harper and Jason Kidd in the same backcourt," said Motta. "You should never forget the history of trades like that."</p>
        <p>Ask Pat Riley.</p>
        <p>"I can assure you that if Dick Motta was there, it would've never happened," said Riley. "We were the beneficiaries of a team that was in major transition last year. It meant getting to the finals -- that's how I feel about it. Derek's a great competitor, a great floor leader. Every now and then, you can make some deals that are very positive. That was one of them."</p>
        <p>Ask Harper, who spent 10 1/2 seasons in Dallas before the trade.</p>
        <p>"Dick is my guy," Harper said of the man who was his coach for most of his career. "He would've made a way for me. Coach Motta is one of the guys who understands how important a veteran is to a young, rebuilding situation. He would've kept me there."</p>
        <p>Instead, Harper is New York's starting point guard and appears to have gotten a second wind late in the season. Harper played another strong game Friday night, with 17 points and 6 assists on 7-for-12 shooting, helping the Knicks gain a 101-90 victory against the Mavericks.</p>
        <p>Harper has another test facing him this afternoon, when the Knicks (46-24) and Nets (27-44) renew their rivalry at the Meadowlands in their final meeting this season. The Knicks are 3-1 this season against the struggling and banged-up Nets, who have lost three consecutive games and who may miss the playoffs for the first time in four seasons.</p>
        <p>But for Harper, playing the Nets is always a challenge. First, he will be matched against Kenny Anderson. Second, the Knicks have a knack of bringing out the best in the Nets.</p>
        <p>Harper has watched from afar as both the Nets and Anderson have struggled. Anderson was an All-Star last season, but his level of play has dropped, and for various reasons the Nets have also dropped in the standings.</p>
        <p>Harper remembers being a young point guard in Anderson's position.</p>
        <p>"I'm sure Kenny probably expected to have a great year this year, and the fact that they haven't has probably caused him to back up a little bit this year," Harper said. "But they're a very dangerous team. They match up well against us, and they play confidently against us. They're tough. People don't want to play Jersey just for the heck of it."</p>
        <p>Harper has assumed more of a leadership role both on and off the court. Riley named Harper a co-captain earlier this season, along with Patrick Ewing and Charles Oakley. And Harper has been one of the most outspoken players regarding the team's well-documented internal problems. Harper said his more active role has come naturally, due to feeling more comfortable after being in New York for more than a year.</p>
        <p>"I don't think I've been pushed into leading, but it goes with the territory," said Harper. "When you're a veteran player, you have to show some form of leadership on the basketball team. I've tried to do it. I don't think a lot of guys have felt like it has been their duty around here to do that. It's a lot easier to do it this year because guys are more comfortable with me and I'm more comfortable with them."</p>
        <p>Harper is the only Knick who has started every game, and he is second on the team in minutes played behind Ewing. But Harper has looked a half step quicker the past two weeks since Riley reinserted Greg Anthony into the rotation. There was concern that Harper, who is 33 years old, would be worn down before the playoffs. Anthony's increased playing time has given Harper a chance to rest.</p>
        <p>"It's obvious that Derek needs a good blow at times," Riley said. "He has been playing heavy minutes. I try to get him six or seven minutes a half. Greg is a player that has been here for three and a half years. We know what he can do. He has to come in and give us those minutes. It doesn't mean that sometimes I won't go with a three-guard rotation, but it depends on the situation."</p>
        <p>The Knicks enter today's game with a game-and-a-half lead over the Indiana Pacers in the race for second-best record in the league. The Nets need a victory badly, but the Knicks feel they need to win as well.</p>
        <p>"We've got 12 games left and six more at home," Riley said. "I really believe that if we lose another home game, there's a possibility that we could lose that second seed. We simply have to win the rest of our home games and do a decent job on the road to see if we can get the position that we need until the Eastern Conference finals. It's paramount that we go on the road and get whatever wins we can get." REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>JOHN STARKS has made at least one 3-point shot in each of the last 18 games. . . . HERB WILLIAMS has six blocks in his last four games.  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
