<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pageantry and Politics as Roberts Makes His Official Debut on Capitol Hill</title>
    <meta content="21CONF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/21/politics/21confirm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1688834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COURT IN TRANSITION: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, John G (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, John G Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DC153CF932A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pageantry and Politics as Roberts Makes His Official Debut on Capitol Hill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Roberts Makes His Official Debut on Capitol Hill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG; Richard W. Stevenson contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge John G Roberts spends day on Capitol Hill, meeting with senators who will vote on his nomination to Supreme Court; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Greeting official Washington on his first full day as a Supreme Court nominee, Judge John G. Roberts joined President Bush for morning coffee at the White House and later began his delicate courtship of senators at the Capitol, drawing accolades from Republicans and a polite, if cautious, welcome from Democrats.</p>
        <p>It was a day of handshakes and get-to-know-you sessions that unfolded as the first act in a highly orchestrated drama that Republicans hope will paint the nominee as an American success story with impeccable legal credentials. The judge made his debut at 7:30 a.m., looking tanned and relaxed in a charcoal gray suit as he stood by Mr. Bush in the White House Rose Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judge John G. Roberts began his delicate courtship of senators at the Capitol, drawing accolades from Republicans and a polite welcome from Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Greeting official Washington on his first full day as a Supreme Court nominee, Judge John G. Roberts joined President Bush for morning coffee at the White House and later began his delicate courtship of senators at the Capitol, drawing accolades from Republicans and a polite, if cautious, welcome from Democrats.</p>
        <p>It was a day of handshakes and get-to-know-you sessions that unfolded as the first act in a highly orchestrated drama that Republicans hope will paint the nominee as an American success story with impeccable legal credentials. The judge made his debut at 7:30 a.m., looking tanned and relaxed in a charcoal gray suit as he stood by Mr. Bush in the White House Rose Garden.</p>
        <p>''I just had a cup of coffee with the nominee and told him I thought things were off to a very good start for his nomination,'' Mr. Bush said, adding, ''I'm confident the senators will come to realize what I've come to realize: We're lucky to have a man of such wisdom and intellectual strength willing to serve our country.''</p>
        <p>But the pageantry was quickly punctuated by politics on Capitol Hill, as Republicans and Democrats sparred over how much information Judge Roberts should provide during his confirmation hearings. The White House insisted the nominee could refuse to answer questions, while Democrats pressed for access to legal memorandums Judge Roberts wrote when he worked in the solicitor general's office.</p>
        <p>''Because Judge Roberts has written relatively few opinions in his brief tenure as a judge, his views on a wide variety of vital issues are still unknown,'' said Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Outside the Capitol, conservative and liberal advocacy groups spent Wednesday mobilizing for and against the nomination. Progress for America, the group that has pledged to spend $18 million to support Mr. Bush's nominee, posted a new Web site, www.judgeroberts.com, featuring prominent Democrats hailing the judge. It quoted a lawyer for former Vice President Al Gore describing Judge Roberts as ''a brilliant lawyer'' and ''a decent man.''</p>
        <p>Women's organizations, seeking to spotlight Judge Roberts's role as the lawyer for Operation Rescue, an anti-abortion group, staged a protest. But even as dozens of women marched and chanted and waved ''Keep Abortion Legal'' placards in the sweltering heat, Kim Gandy, the president of the National Organization for Women, seemed to concede her group had an uphill fight.</p>
        <p>''Obviously we're going to be focusing on some of the swing senators,'' Ms. Gandy said when asked to explain her strategy, ''but we need to solidify our base first and make sure that the people who have historically stood up for women's rights and civil rights recognize this nominee for who he is.''</p>
        <p>One of Judge Roberts's biggest advantages is that he is a creature of Washington, well known to both Democrats and Republicans in the city. Senator John W. Warner, Republican of Virginia, for instance, once worked at Hogan &amp; Hartson, the same law firm where Judge Roberts worked before he was confirmed to the appeals court in 2003.</p>
        <p>The senator greeted the judge like an old friend on Wednesday when he spotted him in the Capitol, escorted by Senator Bill Frist of Tennessee, the majority leader.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to give a little statement, put in what I said before,'' Mr. Warner told the nominee, reminding Judge Roberts that he had introduced him during his previous confirmation hearing. Mr. Warner said that he had chatted with ''a few Hogan boys'' just that morning.</p>
        <p>Judge Roberts let out a chuckle. ''Well,'' he said, ''don't believe everything they say.''</p>
        <p>It was a rare unscripted exchange -- Mr. Warner refused to leave a corridor when Capitol Police officers tried to clear it for the judge's entry -- in a day that was carefully planned by a White House eager to introduce its nominee to the nation and the Senate on its own terms.</p>
        <p>The rollout plan, overseen by Ed Gillespie, a former chairman of the Republican National Committee, was intended to take full advantage of the power of the presidency to seize the national spotlight, beginning with Mr. Bush's televised prime-time speech from the White House on Tuesday night introducing Judge Roberts as the nation's first Supreme Court nominee in 11 years.</p>
        <p>The resulting images -- complete with the nominee's two young children playing nearby while the president spoke -- helped, in the view of administration officials, to deliver an initial impression of a modest, accomplished family man who could not be caricatured by Democrats as a fire-breathing ideologue.</p>
        <p>That choreography continued when Judge Roberts arrived at the Capitol about 1:15 p.m., surrounded by an entourage that included Fred Thompson, the former Tennessee senator who has been asked by the White House to shepherd the nominee through the Senate. Judge Roberts is expected back in the Capitol on Thursday to continue his meetings with senators.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, he met privately with the two party leaders, Mr. Frist and Senator Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, as well as with Senator Arlen Specter, the Pennsylvania Republican who is chairman of the Judiciary Committee, and Senator Patrick J. Leahy of Vermont, the committee's senior Democrat.</p>
        <p>''The United States Senate is ready to go,'' Mr. Frist declared, during a three-minute photo session that consisted mostly of benign chitchat. The pair sat side-by-side, against a backdrop of legal books and American flags, flanked by Mr. Specter and Senator Mitch McConnell of Kentucky, the Republican whip, who joked about Kentucky's basketball rivalry with Indiana, where Judge Roberts grew up.</p>
        <p>The nominee himself was mum, except for three sentences: ''I appreciate and respect the constitutional role of the Senate in the appointment process, and I'm very grateful to the senators for accommodating me and having me over here today, just after the -- the day after the announcement of the nomination. I'm very grateful for that. Thank you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid later met with Judge Roberts for about a half hour, chatting cordially about their mutual interest in Lake Tahoe as he urged him to be forthright in answering questions from the Judiciary Committee, Democratic aides said.</p>
        <p>''Welcome to the Democratic side of the United States Senate,'' Mr. Reid declared afterward with the nominee by his side and Mr. Thompson hovering in the background, adding that he was hoping for some ''lawyer-to-lawyer talk.''</p>
        <p>How serious that talk gets was a major bone of contention between Democrats and Republicans on Wednesday. The White House moved to cut off the most likely Democratic line of attack, by publicly insisting that Judge Roberts should not have to answer any questions about his views on controversial issues like abortion that are likely to come before the court.</p>
        <p>''That would be prejudging cases before they have heard them,'' said Scott McClellan, the White House spokesman. He said Mr. Bush had not asked Judge Roberts for his views on those issues.</p>
        <p>But Democrats, well aware that Judge Roberts could shift the balance of the court if he is confirmed to fill the seat of the retiring Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, pushed back.</p>
        <p>''The one thing we're quite unified about is that the nominee has to answer questions,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, ''and give us facts about not only his résumé but about his judicial philosophy and his views.''</p>
        <p>At least one powerful Republican, Mr. Specter, made it clear that he believed Judge Roberts must talk about his views on upholding legal precedent -- a line of inquiry that could lead to questions about Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court decision legalizing abortion, and cases that followed from it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter said he thought it was legitimate to ask Judge Roberts questions about his views of the reasoning in settled cases like Planned Parenthood v Casey, which upheld Roe as precedent while largely disavowing the reasoning.</p>
        <p>But as to how much of an answer should be required, the senator said: ''This is something you have to have to judge on the moment as to how it goes. You can't really tell. Also the way he handles it, how forthcoming he is, how complete he is.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Specter refused to say whether he would ultimately support the nominee -- ''I think it is important, especially for the chairman, to maintain an open mind,'' he said -- other Republicans quickly lined up behind Judge Roberts.</p>
        <p>They included Senator John McCain of Arizona and Mr. Warner, both prominent members of the so-called Gang of 14, the bipartisan group whose compromise averted a showdown over judicial nominees in May. The group of seven Democrats and seven Republicans plans to meet on Thursday morning, but, on Wednesday, Mr. McCain and Mr. Warner heaped praise on the nominee.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain said the nomination clearly did not constitute ''extraordinary circumstances'' -- the threshold the group agreed would warrant a filibuster, the parliamentary tactic Democrats had used to block some of Mr. Bush's appeals court nominees. His assessment, though, drew criticism from a leading Democrat in the group, Senator Ben Nelson of Nebraska.</p>
        <p>''Everybody ought to cool their jets on this and let the process work, not prejudge one way or another, other than to say, going in it looks good,'' Mr. Nelson said. ''I just don't know how you make up your mind before you have the entire process play out.''</p>
        <p>COURT IN TRANSITION: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
