<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Picture Changes</title>
    <meta content="NHL4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1189313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L.: LAST NIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDF173FF937A35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Picture Changes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Buffalo Sabres defeat Toronto Maple Leafs, 3-2; other NHL results noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SABRES 3, MAPLE LEAFS 2  Dominik Hasek didn't face a shot for more than 20 minutes of play, but the Buffalo goalie was anything but bored as the Sabres jumped back into the last playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Hasek wasn't tested much, but came up big when needed, as the Sabres hung on for a 3-2 victory over the visiting Toronto Maple Leafs last night. The victory, combined with Carolina's 3-2 loss at Pittsburgh, lifted Buffalo into eighth place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SABRES 3, MAPLE LEAFS 2  Dominik Hasek didn't face a shot for more than 20 minutes of play, but the Buffalo goalie was anything but bored as the Sabres jumped back into the last playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Hasek wasn't tested much, but came up big when needed, as the Sabres hung on for a 3-2 victory over the visiting Toronto Maple Leafs last night. The victory, combined with Carolina's 3-2 loss at Pittsburgh, lifted Buffalo into eighth place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>With 81 points, the Sabres are</p>
        <p>1 point ahead of the Hurricanes and 2 ahead of idle Montreal. Buffalo and Montreal have three games remaining, while Carolina will play only two more.</p>
        <p>Dixon Ward snapped a 2-2 tie with 4 minutes 43 seconds left in the first period, while Buffalo's stifling defense did the rest, limiting the Maple Leafs to eight shots over the game's final 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>The Sabres were so dominating that they held Toronto without a shot in the second period. It is the first time the Maple Leafs have had a period without a shot on goal in the 45 years the league has been keeping record of the statistic.</p>
        <p>''It was a very, very important game,'' Hasek said. ''I just tried to stay focused, and I was focused for all 60 minutes. It didn't matter if they didn't have any shots, you can't relax against a team like Toronto.''</p>
        <p>While he faced only 20 shots, Hasek made a brilliant game-saving stop, robbing Jonas Hoglund's one-timer from the slot with 6:31 left.</p>
        <p>Miroslav Satan and Michael Peca also scored for the Sabres, who have won six of seven.</p>
        <p>PENGUINS 3, HURRICANES 2</p>
        <p>Aleksei Kovalev scored twice within 33 seconds of the second period as Pittsburgh beat visiting Carolina and strengthened its hold on a playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Jaromir Jagr, who returned Saturday after missing two games with a sore back, did not score.</p>
        <p>The victory gave seventh-place Pittsburgh 84 points, 3 more than Buffalo. The Hurricanes fell to ninth place.</p>
        <p>SHARKS 1, OILERS 0</p>
        <p>Niklas Sundstrom scored a short-handed goal at 4:37 of the third period, lifting visiting San Jose to victory over Edmonton.</p>
        <p>Edmonton lost the puck in its own end and Sundstrom jammed it past Oilers goalie Tommy Salo for the Sharks' 15th short-handed goal this season, matching the Detroit Red Wings for the league's best.</p>
        <p>Steve Shields recorded his fourth shutout of the season, stopping 20 shots.</p>
        <p>San Jose, with 83 points, has a three-point lead in the Western Conference over ninth-place Vancouver for the final playoff position. Edmonton is in seventh place with 84 points.</p>
        <p>The Oilers had a chance to tie the game, with under six minutes left, when forwards Todd Marchant and Ethan Moreau broke in on a 2-on-1, but Moreau could not beat Shields up high.</p>
        <p>FLAMES 2, STARS 2</p>
        <p>Phil Housley scored the tying goal with 6:52 left as visiting Calgary rallied from a two-goal third-period deficit to tie Dallas. The point helped the 10th-place Flames in their long-shot pursuit of the eighth and final Western Conference playoff spot.</p>
        <p>N.H.L.: LAST NIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
