<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Basketball: Midwest Regional;   Hoyas Roll Past Texas Southern, 70-52</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="335347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGETOWN UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEXAS SOUTHERN UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA163AF934A25750C0A966958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Basketball: Midwest Regional;   Hoyas Roll Past Texas Southern, 70-52</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, March 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The sight of Georgetown's 7-foot-2-inch center, Dikembe Mutombo, was intimidating enough for Texas Southern today. But his 18 points, 16 rebounds and 3 blocked shots were too much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The sight of Georgetown's 7-foot-2-inch center, Dikembe Mutombo, was intimidating enough for Texas Southern today. But his 18 points, 16 rebounds and 3 blocked shots were too much.</p>
        <p>The sight of Georgetown's 7-foot-2-inch center, Dikembe Mutombo, was intimidating enough for Texas Southern today. But his 18 points, 16 rebounds and 3 blocked shots were too much.</p>
        <p>''David met Goliath, but he certainly didn't have his slingshot ready today,'' Robert Moreland, the Texas Southern coach, said after his team's 70-52 loss to the Hoyas in the first round of the Midwest Regional.</p>
        <p>The cold-shooting Tigers, unable to go inside against the taller Hoyas, hit only 27 percent against the nation's top-ranked defense. They took 33 3-point shots and made only 7.</p>
        <p>Mark Tillmon led Georgetown of the Big East Conference with 22 points as the Hoyas (24-6), seeded third in the Midwest, advanced to a second-round game at the Hoosier Dome on Sunday against Xavier.</p>
        <p>Mutombo, who is 5 inches taller than the tallest Texas Southern player, dominated the inside, along with his 6-10 teammate Alonzo Mourning, a second-team all-American, who had 12 points and 8 rebounds. The Hoyas had a 9-point lead at halftime and stretched it to as much as 18 in the second half.</p>
        <p>''We didn't defend him all day,'' Moreland said of Mutombo. ''How do you keep him from getting the ball inside when you jump as high as you can and he stretches and catches it?''</p>
        <p>Dwayne Bryant added 16 points for the Hoyas.</p>
        <p>The 14th-seeded Tigers (19-12), who are from the Southwestern Athletic Conference, were led by Fred West with 17 points.</p>
        <p>Texas Southern's Darrion Applewhite was carried from the floor on a stretcher after suffering a cut above his left eye with 2 minutes 52 seconds to go. He received five stitches, but otherwise appeared to be all right.</p>
        <p>Xavier 87, Kansas State 79</p>
        <p>Some added sleep worked wonders for the free-throw shooting of Xavier's Tyrone Hill.</p>
        <p>Hill, a 62 percent free-throw shooter for the season, scored 29 points including 17 on 17-of-18 free-throw shooting as Xavier of the Midwestern Collegiate Conference held off Kansas State of the Big Eight.</p>
        <p>''I guess it was plenty of sleep before the game,'' Hill said. ''Normally, I don't get that much sleep before a game. I got at least 10 hours.''</p>
        <p>The Musketeers (27-4) made 37 of 43 free throws to overcome a 35-point effort by Steve Henson of Kansas State (17-15).</p>
        <p>Henson, whose shooting sparked a comeback that cut a 15-point deficit to 3 in the final 12 minutes, was not satisfied with his performance. ''I scored some points but didn't get back on defense; that's my responsibility, so obviously I didn't do my job,'' Henson said.</p>
        <p>Xavier made only one field goal in the game's final seven minutes, while making 16 free throws. Kansas State trailed, 60-45, after Hill's turnaround jumper with 12:51 to play. But the lead was down to 3 when Henson made his sixth 3-pointer with 4:11 to go. Hill, who also had a game-high 14 rebounds, then made four free throws.</p>
        <p>The Musketeers missed the front end of a one-and-one opportunity twice in the final minute and were protecting an 83-79 advantage when Jamie Gladden made two free throws with 16 seconds left. Hill then secured the victory by making two free throws with seven seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>Texas 100, Georgia 88</p>
        <p>Travis Mays scored a career-high 44 points and tied N.C.A.A. tournament records by making 23 of 27 foul shots for Texas.</p>
        <p>Mays, a 6-2 guard, also became the Southwest Conference's leading career scorer. He raised his total to 2,211 points, breaking Terry Teagle's record of 2,189 at Baylor.</p>
        <p>Texas (22-8) advanced to Sunday's second round against Purdue. Georgia finished 20-9.</p>
        <p>Mays, who shot 10 for 18 from the field, made 16 consecutive free throws. The rest of the Longhorns finished a combined 3 for 18 from the foul line.</p>
        <p>Mays matched the mark of 23 free throws set by Bob Carney of Bradley in 1954 and tied the record of 27 attempts set by David Robinson of Navy against Syracuse in 1986. Mays's previous career high was 40 points against Miami last season.</p>
        <p>Purdue 75, Northeast Louisiana 63</p>
        <p>Stephen Scheffler became the N.C.A.A.'s career leader in field-goal percentage and Woody Austin made three consecutive jumpers for Purdue (22-7).</p>
        <p>Scheffler scored 23 points on 7-for-11 shooting. The 6-9 250-pound senior center went into the game with a .695 career percentage and needed to make 5 field goals to meet the N.C.A.A. standard of 400. Steve Johnson of Oregon State held the previous career mark of .678 and Scheffler ended the game at .694, having made 402 of 579 attempts.</p>
        <p>Phillip Craig led the Indians (22-8) with 17.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
