<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jones in Green: Jets Sign Top Pick For Top Dollar</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="626838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BONUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, MARVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, MARVIN (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DB1531F935A3575BC0A965958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jones in Green: Jets Sign Top Pick For Top Dollar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I., Aug. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After two weeks of frustrating negotiations, the Jets headed off a possibly longer and acrimonious stalemate with their first-round selection, linebacker Marvin Jones, by coming to terms with him today on a five-year deal worth about $6 million, including a signing bonus of about $3.5 million. Incentives could raise the value of the package to $7.5 million.</p>
        <p>Jones agreed to terms after missing 14 days of training camp and is expected to sign when he arrives at camp on Friday. He is expected to take a physical examination and travel with the Jets to their first preseason game at Pittsburgh on Saturday evening. Jones will suit up, but isn't expected to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After two weeks of frustrating negotiations, the Jets headed off a possibly longer and acrimonious stalemate with their first-round selection, linebacker Marvin Jones, by coming to terms with him today on a five-year deal worth about $6 million, including a signing bonus of about $3.5 million. Incentives could raise the value of the package to $7.5 million.</p>
        <p>Jones agreed to terms after missing 14 days of training camp and is expected to sign when he arrives at camp on Friday. He is expected to take a physical examination and travel with the Jets to their first preseason game at Pittsburgh on Saturday evening. Jones will suit up, but isn't expected to play.</p>
        <p>As of Wednesday night, Jones's agent, Drew Rosenhaus, said he and the team were far apart in negotiations. But things quickly heated up this morning when Rosenhaus spoke with the Jets' president, Steve Gutman, and General Manager Dick Steinberg.</p>
        <p>"The resolution came about because all parties recognized that all interests were best served by getting it done now," said Gutman. "It was always his intention not to have Marvin hold out and the prospect of having him not on the roster as the preseason games began was very unappetizing to him and ourselves as well."</p>
        <p>Gutman said the sides worked out a compromise. The Jets gave Jones a larger signing bonus than the team had budgeted, while Jones agreed to an additional year of service. The series of one-year contracts, averaging about $1.2 million a year, will take Jones through the free-agency period. There are incentives in the contract, which kick in after the fourth year, that could increase Jones's base salary to $2.5 million in the fifth year.</p>
        <p>To earn the incentives, Jones must play 60 percent of the defensive plays, start 70 percent of the games by the fourth year and in the fourth year he must make the Pro Bowl or be first-team defense in the American Football Conference. If he does all that, he will get a new contract in his fifth year.</p>
        <p>The five-year pact was a compromise that is based on a clause included in the contract of New England quarterback Drew Bledsoe, the No. 1 selection over all in the National Football League draft. After his fourth year, Bledsoe has the option to end his six-year contract with the Patriots.</p>
        <p>"Our major concern was to get a deal that would compensate a guy I think is a future Pro Bowler," Rosenhaus said.</p>
        <p>With Jones, the No. 4 choice over all, agreeing to terms, three of the top 10 first-round draft choices are unsigned. The highest of those is running back Garrison Hearst, who was taken with the third pick by Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Jones, speaking by telephone today from his home in Coconut Grove, Fla., said he was happy to finally have the contract done. He said he was in good condition and had spent most of his time running and lifting weights. Although he was looking forward to joining the Jets, he said, he didn't know what to expect for his first practice on Monday.</p>
        <p>"Just right now it's a mental part of the game, just trying to get back into the flow of things," he said. "I haven't had any contact for a while."</p>
        <p>On Monday, Jets Coach Bruce Coslet said that Jones might have a hard time catching up and questioned whether the linebacker would make an impact this season. Coslet didn't back off that assessment today. Extra Work Is Needed</p>
        <p>"Marvin has missed 21 practices, one scrimmage and one preseason game," Coslet said. "I know our coaches will work extra with him. Now it's up to Marvin."</p>
        <p>Jones, a 6-foot-2-inch, 240-pound consensus all-America linebacker at Florida State, was the Jets' first choice after New York flip-flopped positions with Phoenix in the draft. The Jets traded their original choice, the third one over all, for the Cardinals' top choice, No. 4 over all in the draft, and running back Johnny Johnson.</p>
        <p>The Jets like Jones because he's fast, strong and a fierce tackler. Although he has the skills to play either outside or inside linebacker.</p>
        <p>Jones was supposed to compete for the starting middle linebacker job against Kyle Clifton, a 10-year veteran and nine-year starter. But because of Jones's holdout, Clifton might have a better grip on the starting job. Clifton said he will help get Jones up to speed, even though he knows that Jones is his replacement.</p>
        <p>"That's just part of the deal," Clifton said. "That's our profession. I have no problem helping him."</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
