<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Canadians, Is U.S. Gaze Friendly?</title>
    <meta content="28CANA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="879843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canada-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Quebec Province (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5D6123CF93BA1575AC0A960958260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Canadians, Is U.S. Gaze Friendly?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Sept. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent hearing before US Congressional committee that bluntly assessed what breakup of Canada would mean for US attracted little attention in Washington, but it reverberated loudly in Toronto, leaving many Canadians either flattered by attention or resentful of outside interference; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A hearing before a United States Congressional committee this week that bluntly assessed what a breakup of Canada would mean for the United States attracted little attention in Washington. But it reverberated loudly here, leaving many Canadians either flattered by the attention or resentful of outside interference.</p>
        <p>The hearing on Wednesday before the House Subcommittee on the Western Hemisphere focused on the security and economic implications of a secession by Quebec.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A hearing before a United States Congressional committee this week that bluntly assessed what a breakup of Canada would mean for the United States attracted little attention in Washington. But it reverberated loudly here, leaving many Canadians either flattered by the attention or resentful of outside interference.</p>
        <p>The hearing on Wednesday before the House Subcommittee on the Western Hemisphere focused on the security and economic implications of a secession by Quebec.</p>
        <p>''Here it hadn't really sunk in yet that the country almost broke apart and may still do so,'' said Mel Watkins, a professor of Canadian Studies at the University of Toronto. Having the unraveling of Canada laid out in a Washington hearing room, Professor Watkins said, made Canadians pay attention in a way they never would have if the same arguments had been made in Ottawa.</p>
        <p>The hearing, broadcast in Canada and covered extensively by local newspapers, made many Canadians sqirm, especially in Quebec, as witnesses described the chaos that could follow if Quebec voted to pull out of Canada, which almost happened last October, to Washington's surprise.</p>
        <p>And some thought the United States should mind its own business. ''An exercise that is off the charts on the paranoia index,'' is how a CBC commentator described the hearing.</p>
        <p>''When big brother takes an interest, it can go both ways,'' said Alan W. Sullivan, president of the Canadian Institute of International Affairs, an independent organization in Toronto. ''The United States is such an important player in the Canadian psyche that it grates on Canadian nerves when the United States does pay attention to us, as well as when it doesn't pay attention to us.''</p>
        <p>The United States has considered Quebec a strictly domestic issue for Canada, its most important trading partner.</p>
        <p>But the Congressman who organized the hearing, Tom Campbell, a Republican from California, argued that the United States was not paying enough attention to what was going on north of the border. He said the North American Free Trade Agreement raised direct issues for the United States, like whether an independent Quebec would automatically be allowed to join Nafta.</p>
        <p>A view presented several times at the hearing was that admission for sovereign Quebec would not be automatic, and that by stating so clearly, Washington would help the people of the province understand the consequences of secession.</p>
        <p>One witness, Charles F. Doran, had already raised tempers in Canada with an article published this month in Foreign Affairs magazine speculating on the future of Canada. Mr. Doran, a Distinguished Professor of International Relations at Johns Hopkins University, argued that if Quebec seceded, Canada would unravel.</p>
        <p>The poor eastern provinces of Canada would be physically cut off from the rest of the country, he wrote, and the wealthier western provinces would have little incentive to remain in a union that subsidizes the poor provinces, or gives too much power and control to Ontario, the most populous of the 10 provinces.</p>
        <p>Professor Doran speculated that Alberta, a sparsely populated prairie province, might even try to apply for statehood with the United States. That prompted this headline in The Financial Post, a Toronto daily: ''Give us your poor, your tired, your huddled masses -- and Alberta.''</p>
        <p>Many Canadian newspapers welcomed the hearings because of the perception that Washington could analyze the Quebec issue without the histrionics it raises in Canada. But there was also some embarrassment over the airing of Canada's internal problems in Washington.</p>
        <p>Neither the United States State Department nor the Canadian Government sent any representatives to testify. In fact, no Canadians testified at all; the four witnesses were all Americans.</p>
        <p>''In a way it was a classic Canadian-American story, filled with a lot of absurdities,'' Professor Watkins said. ''There it was, a hearing about Canada, with no Canadians testifying. And though it was supposed to be for the benefit of the United States, the hearing room was filled with only Canadian journalists.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
