<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.I.G.'s Offer For Big Insurer Beats a Bid From Britain</title>
    <meta content="Y04INS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/04/business/04INSU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010405T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1283091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American International Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prudential Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Maurice R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <org class="online_producer">American International Group Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American General</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Prudential Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American companies</org>
        <org class="online_producer">aid</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Salomon Smith Barney</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Berkshire Hathaway Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DC163EF937A35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.I.G.'s Offer For Big Insurer Beats a Bid From Britain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American International Group chief executive, Maurice R Greenberg, offers $23 billion in stock for American General, one of nation's biggest life insurers, $3.5 billion less than Prudential PLC offered on March 12 but $3.3 billion more than offer is worth at end of trading day (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a bold stroke, Maurice R. Greenberg, the chief executive of the American International Group, made a competing offer yesterday for American General, one of the nation's biggest life insurers, that surpasses a bid by Prudential of Britain.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. offered $23 billion in stock for American General, $3.5 billion less than  Prudential P.L.C. had offered on March 12 but $3.3 billion more than the offer was worth at the end of trading yesterday as Prudential's shares continued to fall. The A.I.G. offer, worth about $46 a share, represents a 25 percent premium from American General's closing stock price of $36.80 yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a bold stroke, Maurice R. Greenberg, the chief executive of the American International Group, made a competing offer yesterday for American General, one of the nation's biggest life insurers, that surpasses a bid by Prudential of Britain.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. offered $23 billion in stock for American General, $3.5 billion less than  Prudential P.L.C. had offered on March 12 but $3.3 billion more than the offer was worth at the end of trading yesterday as Prudential's shares continued to fall. The A.I.G. offer, worth about $46 a share, represents a 25 percent premium from American General's closing stock price of $36.80 yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg said in an interview that he had been following the Prudential transaction closely and that as the value of the deal dropped, ''it just seemed like the right thing to put another offer on the table.''</p>
        <p>Under the A.I.G. offer, American General shareholders would receive 0.5462 to 0.6037 of an A.I.G. share as long as A.I.G.'s stock price traded within a 5 percent collar during an established period. Shares of A.I.G. closed yesterday at $80.21, down $2.74. Prudential has offered 3.66 of its shares for every American General share.</p>
        <p>On the day the Prudential deal was announced, Prudential shareholders signaled their disfavor by bidding down the company's shares 14 percent. Executives of Prudential and American General began a round of urgent meetings with important investors in the United States and Europe but could not stop the slide. Prudential's offer is now valued at $19.7 billion.</p>
        <p>A big part of the sell-off was because of concern in Britain that investors in American General would sell Prudential shares as soon as they received them because they would not want to hold foreign shares or, in the case of some pension funds, would be prohibited from doing so. So the shareholders in Europe were leaving before an avalanche of American sales. Also, many American analysts said the deal seemed to provide few benefits to Prudential beyond greater size.</p>
        <p>The negative response to Prudential's bid raised grave questions about the future success of attempts by European insurers to expand in the United States, the world's biggest market for financial services, by buying major American companies. Because of higher market values in Europe, the American companies seemed cheap by comparison. Europeans had already bought several big American insurers before Prudential made its bid for American General. But investor reaction was never so negative.</p>
        <p>Counteroffers are unusual in the staid world of insurance, and in his years of making A.I.G. one of the world's largest insurance companies, Mr. Greenberg has carefully cultivated merger partners instead of intervening in the deals of others. He said his offer was ''not hostile'' but would aid Prudential shareholders.</p>
        <p>He said he first broached the counteroffer to Robert Devlin, the chief executive of American General, in a phone call just after the close of the markets in New York yesterday. He said there had been no previous contact by him or his bankers with Mr. Devlin or his bankers on the offer.</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Devlin's reaction ''sounded very good.''</p>
        <p>''You'll have to talk with him,'' Mr. Greenberg said, ''but the body language sounded very good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Devlin did not return a phone call seeking comment last night. But Mr. Greenberg said Mr. Devlin acknowledged receiving a detailed letter on the offer and that Mr. Devlin was ''coming to see me in a day or two.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg said he had not spoken with executives of Prudential. ''I'm not going to talk to Prudential,'' he said. ''I'm talking with American General.''</p>
        <p>A Prudential spokeswoman said, ''We've seen the announcement by A.I.G., but our agreement with American General still stands.''</p>
        <p>In the next step, American General's board must vote on A.I.G.'s offer. Accepting the offer would require American General to pay Prudential a break-up fee of $600 million.</p>
        <p>''If they are offered a higher price, which they are now, they don't have any option but to accept it,'' said Colin Devine, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Devine said a counteroffer from Prudential was unlikely.</p>
        <p>A.I.G.'s offer, while less than the original value of Prudential's offer, is greater than what has been the industry's biggest deal: the $21.7 billion acquisition of General Re by Berkshire Hathaway in 1998.</p>
        <p>In 1998 American General bought Sun America, one of the biggest companies in variable annuities -- the combination of mutual funds and life insurance -- for $17.8 billion. And analysts said American General, which is also a leader in variable annuities, would dovetail nicely with Sun America. The addition of American General would also make A.I.G. a major player in life insurance.</p>
        <p>''It's a major fit,'' said Andrew Kligerman, an analyst at Bear, Stearns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg also highly values American General's consumer finance business. A.I.G. now has consumer finance operations in Asia, Latin American and Central Europe and wants to expand. ''This would give us a platform -- with people and depth -- so we can expand faster,'' Mr. Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 5, 2001, Thursday  An article in Business Day yesterday about an offer made by American International Group for the life insurer American General misstated which company bought SunAmerica, a leader in variable annuities, in 1998. It was A.I.G., not American General.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 5, 2001, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about an offer made by American International Group for the life insurer American General misstated which company bought SunAmerica, a leader in variable annuities, in 1998. It was A.I.G., not American General.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
