<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel Strikes Hard at Gaza Strip As Powell Assails Sharon Stance</title>
    <meta content="07MIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/07/international/middleeast/07MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020309T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1373818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palestinian Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip (Israel)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Powell, Colin L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D71230F934A35750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel Strikes Hard at Gaza Strip As Powell Assails Sharon Stance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Israel Strikes Hard at Gaza Strip and Shells Arafat's Compound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, March 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli forces strike hard by land, sea and air at teeming Gaza Strip, where Palestinians breach another red line when they fire rockets into Israeli town; as carnage mounts, Israeli government receives unusual rebuke from US Secretary of State Colin L Powell; he challenges Prime Min Ariel Sharon's statement that only if Israel continues to increase Palestinian losses would Palestinians sit down to talks; Bush administration has focused most of its criticism for last few months exclusively at Yasir Arafat, insisting that he could do more to curb terrorism; now Powell says both sides are pursuing policies that will only lead to greater violence; Sharon's office responds to Powell's statement by saying war was imposed on Israel by Palestinian Authority and sanctioned terrorism; Sharon says he is postponing trip to Britain and Spain next week because of escalating fray; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israeli forces struck hard today by land, sea and air at the teeming Gaza Strip, where Palestinians breached another red line on Tuesday when they fired rockets into an Israeli town. With the mounting carnage, which added 10 Palestinian and 2 Israeli dead to the toll, the government of Ariel Sharon received an unusual rebuke from Secretary of State Colin L. Powell.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell, speaking before a Congressional committee in Washington, challenged the Israeli prime minister's statement this week that only if Israel continued to increase the other side's losses would the Palestinians sit down to talks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Israeli forces struck the Gaza Strip on Wednesday, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell rebuked Israeli Prime Minister Ariel Sharon for intensifying violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israeli forces struck hard today by land, sea and air at the teeming Gaza Strip, where Palestinians breached another red line on Tuesday when they fired rockets into an Israeli town. With the mounting carnage, which added 10 Palestinian and 2 Israeli dead to the toll, the government of Ariel Sharon received an unusual rebuke from Secretary of State Colin L. Powell.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell, speaking before a Congressional committee in Washington, challenged the Israeli prime minister's statement this week that only if Israel continued to increase the other side's losses would the Palestinians sit down to talks.</p>
        <p>''Prime Minister Sharon has to take a hard look at his policies to see whether they will work,'' Secretary Powell said. ''If you declare war against the Palestinians thinking that you can solve the problem by seeing how many Palestinians can be killed, I don't know that that leads us anywhere.'' [Page A8.]</p>
        <p>For several months, the Bush administration has focused most of its criticism exclusively at Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, insisting that he could do more to curb terrorism. But after a paroxysm of killing in the last week, Secretary Powell -- who spoke by phone on Tuesday with Mr. Sharon -- said both sides were pursuing policies that would only lead to greater violence. ''It's a tragic situation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan of the United Nations also expressed his dismay today, saying that violence in the Middle East was ''completely out of hand.''</p>
        <p>In response to Secretary Powell's remarks, Mr. Sharon's office issued a statement saying that the war was imposed on Israel by the Palestinian Authority. ''Israel is only fighting back against the terrorist organization in the context of its right to self-defense,'' the statement said. ''The one who initiated this war has the power to stop it, but he continues to prefer the war of terrorism.'' Mr. Sharon also said he was postponing a  trip to Britain and Spain next week because of the escalating fray.</p>
        <p>The day's operations included another shelling of the Ramallah compound of Mr. Arafat, but this time while the Palestinian leader was meeting with the European Union envoy to the Middle East, Miguel Ángel Moratinos, and while the Israeli foreign minister, Shimon Peres, was on the telephone with Mr. Arafat. Neither Mr. Moratinos nor Mr. Arafat was injured, and there was no immediate indication whether the timing of the attack was deliberate.</p>
        <p>''It was very loud and very dangerous,'' reported Nabil Aburdeineh, an aide to Mr. Arafat who was there at the time. ''We thought it was so close that it was on the office itself. We informed Mr. Peres, and he said he would check.''</p>
        <p>The Israelis have dropped shells around Mr. Arafat's compound several times before, apparently to intimidate the Palestinian leader. Mr. Sharon has declared that he has no intention of killing him.</p>
        <p>The operation in the Gaza Strip began in the night, and the Israeli Army was reported fighting at five different areas against heavy resistance. Details were sketchy. Israel said it killed several Palestinians, arrested several others and destroyed a house in which a wanted guerrilla was hiding. Palestinians said an F-16 jet fighter fired a missile at the police headquarters in the Sheikh Radwan neighborhood in Gaza, which houses the commander of Palestinian forces in Gaza.</p>
        <p>Palestinians also reported that Israeli naval vessels approached the Gaza shore and fired missiles at the Palestinian naval police, killing four.</p>
        <p>[Early on Thursday, Israeli forces moved into the West Bank town of Tulkarm, killing one Palestinian, The Associated Press reported. In Bethlehem, the A.P. said, warplanes fired at least two missiles at the Palestinian headquarters. No casualties were reported.]</p>
        <p>The Israeli commander for Gaza, Brig. Gen. Yisrael Ziv, called the operations today successful and said they would continue.</p>
        <p>The army ordered the raids into Gaza after two crude Qassam rockets, which the Israelis say are manufactured by the militant movement Hamas, were launched into the town of Sderot on Tuesday. One struck a building and injured a child. Israel had warned that firing rockets into urban areas would have serious consequences. But with the carnage at record levels, there was little to distinguish retaliation from escalation.</p>
        <p>Most of the day's incidents were at Israeli roadblocks and checkpoints. At one roadblock near Nablus, soldiers shot two Palestinians, one fatally, and said they were carrying explosives in a bag. Near Kalkilya, another West Bank town, a man blew himself up with his own grenade after being ordered to stop.</p>
        <p>At yet another roadblock, one near Maccabim in the West Bank which had been attacked by a woman suicide bomber, soldiers opened fire on two men who began to flee after being ordered to stop. Both were wounded, and they turned out to be Israeli Arabs.</p>
        <p>With the violence, and increasing recriminations in the cabinet, the tone in the Israeli press turned distinctly angrier and more depressed.</p>
        <p>Sever Plotzer, a veteran commentator for Yediot Ahronot, spared no words: ''The house is on fire, and the government is clueless. What do you want us to do, the best of its ministers ask, shrugging their shoulders and spreading their hands in a gesture of helplessness. You bunch of impotent fools, we are tired of you. Pack your bags, gather up your papers, return the keys and leave the government.''</p>
        <p>Hemi Shalev, a respected columnist for Maariv, was less dramatic but no less direct. ''The question of questions of the national unity government was, 'what is the alternative?' But now the possibility is being raised that the right answer all this time was -- anything but this.'' Mr. Shalev expressed the hope that the firing of Qassam missiles on Sderot might finally ''awaken the Americans from their winter hibernation.''</p>
        <p>In this mood, threats by various factions to abandon the government, and force new elections, have grown, along with tensions among the ministers. The Israeli press reported that at a four-hour discussion among senior ministers on what steps to take next, Mr. Peres declared, ''Had I known that the government would find itself in this current reality in the confrontation with the Palestinians, I would not have joined Sharon's unity government.''</p>
        <p>In the current thinking, new elections would be likely to lead to Mr. Sharon's replacement by Benjamin Netanyahu, who was prime minister from 1996 to 1999. Mr. Netanyahu, also a member of the right-wing Likud, has said that if he returns to office, he would bring down the Arafat administration, wall off the Palestinians with a fence and conduct a military sweep of the Palestinian areas to clear them of weapons.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 9, 2002, Saturday  An article on Thursday about strikes by Israel against Palestinians in the Gaza Strip misspelled the surname of a commentator for the newspaper Yediot Ahronot who criticized the government for its handling of the conflict. He is Sever Plotzker, not Plotzer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 9, 2002, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about strikes by Israel against Palestinians in the Gaza Strip misspelled the surname of a commentator for the newspaper Yediot Ahronot who criticized the government for its handling of the conflict. He is Sever Plotzker, not Plotzer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
