<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home in Child Sex Abuse Case Was Deemed Safe by the City</title>
    <meta content="03ABUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Incest</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robacker, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fremgen, Theresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Curtis Elam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fremgen, Vincent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fremgen, Ezra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Incest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DC173EF930A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home in Child Sex Abuse Case Was Deemed Safe by the City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New details emerge about sex abuse case in Brooklyn; investigators say that six months before police arrested Daniel Robacker and Theresa Fremgen on charges of repeatedly raping their two daughters in filthy Brooklyn apartment, child welfare officials approved home as a safe place for the teen-age girls; even though a city caseworker was assigned to see girls twice a month, and city housekeeper was assigned to clean Bushwick apartment each weekday, neither saw signs of sexual abuse that occurred routinely; police say that all the while, Robacker, Fremgen, her ex-boyfriend and her two brothers were routinely raping and sodomizing their own children and young relatives in apartment; the five adults, many of whom are mildly mentally rtarded or illiterate, speak openly to police about rape and incest that took place; photos of suspects (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six months before the police arrested Daniel Robacker and Theresa Fremgen on charges of repeatedly raping their two daughters in a filthy Brooklyn apartment, child welfare officials approved the home as a safe place for the teen-age girls.</p>
        <p>''They are home with their parents,'' said Esther Simon, a lawyer for the Administration for Children's Services, during a court hearing in January as she recommended  that the sisters not be sent back to foster care. ''They are doing fine.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six months before the police arrested Daniel Robacker and Theresa Fremgen on charges of repeatedly raping their two daughters in a filthy Brooklyn apartment, child welfare officials approved the home as a safe place for the teen-age girls.</p>
        <p>''They are home with their parents,'' said Esther Simon, a lawyer for the Administration for Children's Services, during a court hearing in January as she recommended  that the sisters not be sent back to foster care. ''They are doing fine.''</p>
        <p>And even though a city caseworker was assigned to see the girls twice a month, and a city housekeeper was assigned to clean the Bushwick apartment each weekday, neither saw signs of the sexual abuse that occurred routinely, child welfare officials say. But all the while, the police say, Mr. Robacker, Ms. Fremgen, her ex-boyfriend and her two brothers were raping and sodomizing their own children and young relatives in apartment 2E of 232 Linden Street.</p>
        <p>The details of the abuse, which emerged yesterday as investigators released snippets of statements made by each suspect, painted a horrifying portrait of a home where two sisters were raped amid squalor and stuffed animals along with an 8-year-old boy, who was a friend of the family, while the household was under the city's watch.</p>
        <p>The five adults, many of whom are mildly mentally retarded or illiterate, spoke openly to the police about the rape and incest that took place, investigators say. And in a graphic but neatly written statement to the police, one suspect, Ezra Fremgen, described the boy as a willing accomplice, saying matter-of-factly: ''We had sex every Saturday that his father brought him by.''</p>
        <p>Child welfare officials, who are investigating the case, declined to say whether the caseworker had made all the visits required by law. And even if she had, it was unclear whether the worker would have detected signs of the sexual abuse, which is notoriously difficult to spot, especially when it is a closely guarded secret.</p>
        <p>The police said the children kept silent about the abuse for at least three years. And the girls, who were placed in foster care for three weeks last year before returning to their parents, denied ever having been sexually assaulted.</p>
        <p>But new information in the case raised disturbing questions about whether the city had adequately assessed the safety of the children. One sister, a 14-year-old, and the 8-year-old boy each had more than 18 absences from school this year, school officials said, often an indicator of trouble at home.</p>
        <p>Child welfare records indicate that Ms. Fremgen, 35, was abused or neglected when she was a teen-ager, another high-risk factor in abuse cases, city officials say. Helen Robacker, her aunt, said Ms. Fremgen was raped by a relative when she was 15.</p>
        <p>Caseworkers are required to seek out such information about the parents they monitor and to document it in the 30-day reports they file, because past abuse sometimes increases the risk of abuse to children living in the household, child welfare specialists say.</p>
        <p>But none of the psychological evaluations of Ms. Fremgen, which were conducted by the city in 1994 and by an agency contracted by the city in 1997, mention or assess the severity or impact of any abuse.</p>
        <p>Edward F. Stancik, the Special Investigator for the city schools, said that his office was poring over the children's attendance records and was working with the Brooklyn District Attorney's office.</p>
        <p>And officials at the Administration for Children's Services declined to comment about the other issues, saying they wanted to complete their inquiry first.</p>
        <p>''The matter is under investigation,'' said Leonora Wiener, a spokeswoman for the Administration for Children's Services. ''We'll have no further comment until our investigation is complete.''</p>
        <p>As the officials searched for answers to the many troubling questions, a bleak picture was developing of the suspects, whose lives were marked by poverty, mental illness and, sometimes, neglectful behavior toward children, according to court records and psychological evaluations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fremgen is mentally retarded, according to a psychological evaluation. Mr. Robacker, 40, her companion and first cousin, dropped out of school in the fourth grade. And Curtis E. James, 35, the father of the 8-year-old boy, lived on the streets and had trouble reading a newspaper, even though he completed trade school, the court records show.</p>
        <p>Homeless in 1993, Mr. James sent his son to live with Ms. Fremgen, who was his ex-girlfriend and the godmother of his son.</p>
        <p>''I've got to find a place to live,'' Mr. James told a psychologist, according to the court records.</p>
        <p>All five adults were arraigned yesterday in Brooklyn Criminal Court  on a total of 82 counts of rape, sodomy, sexual abuse, incest and endangering the welfare of a child. Included among the suspects were Vincent Fremgen, 28, and Ezra Fremgen, 25, the brothers of Ms. Fremgen.</p>
        <p>Brett Taylor, a lawyer for Mr. James, denied the charges in court yesterday. ''When all the evidence is in, this case will look a lot different,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The police, who had said on Wednesday that four children had been abused, said yesterday it appeared there were only three victims.</p>
        <p>They said that the two sisters, age 13 and 14, were victimized by all five adults, and that the 8-year-old boy was victimized by his father and by one of the uncles.</p>
        <p>All the sexual offenses took place in the Linden Street home, a cluttered, filthy apartment with stacks of trinkets, clothes, garbage and, in the bedrooms, pornography.</p>
        <p>While investigators said they believed that the sexual abuse went on for years, the charges cover numerous sexual offenses that prosecutors say took place between April 1 and June 30.</p>
        <p>Child welfare officials took notice of the household in July 1997 when someone reported the family to the state's child abuse telephone line. Child welfare workers reported that they found a filthy apartment with animal feces, and a child with lacerations on the body.</p>
        <p>They decided to try to keep the household together by offering intensive counseling services, but the caseworker finally ordered the three children put in foster care on Sept. 23, when it became clear that Ms. Fremgen and Mr. Robacker were not responding to the city's help.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 14, 1997, Judge Nora Freeman of Family Court decided to send the two girls home after the foster care agency, Pius XII, recommended that they return, city officials said.</p>
        <p>The agency made the recommendation because the charge of physical abuse had been discounted, leaving only a charge of neglect for keeping the children in a filthy house.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, city officials insisted that they had not wanted the children returned to the family, questioning why the judge and the agency had supported the return. But yesterday, court documents showed that the city actually approved of the girls' placement in the home as long as a housekeeper was there to help.</p>
        <p>The boy, who told court officials that he did not want to return to the Fremgen household, was sent to another foster mother. And the case finally unraveled when the boy told his new foster mother that he had been sodomized by Ezra Fremgen. The police arrested Mr. Fremgen on Tuesday and the others on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''The statements indicate that most knew what was going on and on occasion they observed each other,'' said a law enforcement official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. ''They appear to be very low-functioning people. It doesn't appear that they tried to hide it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
