<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back on the Offensive for City Charter Guru</title>
    <meta content="03PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Charters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarz, Frederick A O Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DD173EF930A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back on the Offensive for City Charter Guru</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Frederick A O Schwarz Jr, who eight years ago led commission that rewrote New York City's Charter, and who has roared back into public life with blistering attack on Mayor Giuliani's decision to try rewriting Charter to block a referendum on moving Yankee Stadium to Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EIGHT years ago, Frederick A. O. Schwarz Jr. took his celebrated family name and several shelves of civic accomplishments and quietly departed from New York City's public arena. He had just led the commission that rewrote the City Charter, and -- unlike his old boss, Mayor Edward I. Koch --  found it unnecessary to comment on how it was carried out or offer his momentary opinions on Mr. Koch's two successors.</p>
        <p>Reporters would seek comments about the Dinkins or Giuliani administrations, and he would politely beg off. Elected officials would try to enlist him in their temporal disputes, hoping his interpretation of the charter would bolster theirs, and he would say the thing spoke for itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EIGHT years ago, Frederick A. O. Schwarz Jr. took his celebrated family name and several shelves of civic accomplishments and quietly departed from New York City's public arena. He had just led the commission that rewrote the City Charter, and -- unlike his old boss, Mayor Edward I. Koch --  found it unnecessary to comment on how it was carried out or offer his momentary opinions on Mr. Koch's two successors.</p>
        <p>Reporters would seek comments about the Dinkins or Giuliani administrations, and he would politely beg off. Elected officials would try to enlist him in their temporal disputes, hoping his interpretation of the charter would bolster theirs, and he would say the thing spoke for itself.</p>
        <p>Privately, like many New Yorkers, he was deeply ambivalent about Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, delighted at the Mayor's success in reducing crime but worried about the reasons the administration was loath to release information about city government. But until this week, he held his tongue.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, with the release of a blistering letter on Monday, Mr. Schwarz has roared back into public life, furious over the Mayor's decision to try rewriting the charter to block a referendum on moving Yankee Stadium to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Writing to Peter J. Powers, the former First Deputy Mayor and chairman of Mr. Giuliani's hastily formed Charter Revision Commission, he said the attempt to rewrite the charter to the advantage of the mayoralty was a ''trivialization and politicalization of charter revision'' and represented ''awful government.''</p>
        <p>Many in and around City Hall reacted as if a stone colossus had come back to life and was rumbling menacingly in their direction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers declined to discuss the substance of the seven-page letter and criticized Mr. Schwarz for not informing him of it in advance.</p>
        <p>One anonymous official was quoted in The New York Times as saying that Mr. Schwarz, a Democrat, was acting politically. Paul A. Crotty, like Mr. Schwarz a former city corporation counsel and a member of Mr. Giuliani's panel, said his predecessor was simply trying to protect his handiwork.</p>
        <p>''He's very proud of the charter,'' said Mr. Crotty, now a group president with Bell Atlantic. ''It represents for him a careful balancing of interests, and he doesn't want it changed.''</p>
        <p>MR. SCHWARZ, whose family sold the eponymous toy store in the 1960's, has a courtly manner born of prominence and does not have to struggle to restrain himself at such suggestions. He said that his political involvement had been minimal (though he did give the maximum of $7,700 to Ruth W. Messinger's mayoral campaign), and that he had no problem with changes to the charter, as long as they were undertaken thoughtfully.</p>
        <p>''You can't fairly consider these issues without an extensive public process because charter commissions are not elected bodies,'' he said in his 40th-floor law office at the lofty firm of Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore, where he has been a partner on and off since 1969. ''If you haven't had a very extensive and open process, you're dealing with a blunt instrument in referenda that can be manipulated by money. And that makes the process incredibly important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarz, it seems fair to say, has a passion for process -- checks, balances, the visibly operating mechanism of government -- as a protector of the public good. Having given New York City mayors broader powers than the President or the governor to spend money and make policy, his commission also included several countervailing forces to watch over that power, the various monitors under which Mr. Giuliani chafes and has proposed changing.</p>
        <p>''This is in the nature of powerful people in executive jobs,'' he said, insisting he was not referring specifically to the present Mayor. ''With a few exceptions, they feel they can get it done, so they say, 'Why should I face criticism or second-guessing or new ideas?' And the great lesson of America is that we don't trust one individual to have so much power.''</p>
        <p>Though he has often represented some of the country's largest corporations at Cravath, Mr. Schwarz, known as Fritz to a wide group of friends, has an even longer streak of anti-authoritarianism, which he said he absorbed from the Kennedy era of vigorous civic involvement.</p>
        <p>At Harvard Law School in 1960, he led a protest against the local Woolworth's when black students were holding a famous sit-in at the Woolworth's in Greensboro, N.C. He spent a year in Nigeria helping apply its new constitution after years of colonialism, and he was chief counsel to Senator Frank Church's intelligence committee in 1975, investigating the F.B.I. and the C.I.A. He has worked with many local civic and charitable groups, and even those who disagree with him on the current matter are aware that it is difficult to assail him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarz, whose boyishly flyaway hair makes it hard to believe he is 63 with three children in their 30's, is the great-grandson of Frederick August Otto Schwarz, who founded the store in 1862. His family's only connection to the store is a license fee the current owners pay for the name, which goes to a charitable foundation for children. But as with city government, he feels obligated to drop by now and then to make sure things are running smoothly.</p>
        <p>''I've got a grandchild now,'' he said. ''I want to make sure it's still a quality store.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
