<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York and Wisconsin Will Defy Federal Directive to Provide Viagra Through Medicaid</title>
    <meta content="Y03DRU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impotence</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wisconsin</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DF173EF930A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York and Wisconsin Will Defy Federal Directive to Provide Viagra Through Medicaid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York and Wisconsin say they will defy new Federal policy that requires state Medicaid programs to pay for medically approved uses of Viagra, popular but expensive new impotence pill; directive, from Clinton Adm, prompts outcry from governors, who say they had not been consulted even though states pay more than 40 percent of Medicaid costs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two states, New York and Wisconsin, said today that they would defy a new Federal policy that requires state Medicaid programs to pay for medically approved uses of Viagra, the popular but expensive new impotence pill.</p>
        <p>The directive, from the Clinton Administration, prompted an outcry from governors, who said they had not been consulted even though states pay more than 40 percent of Medicaid costs. The National Governors' Association said Medicaid coverage of Viagra should be a state option, not a Federal mandate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two states, New York and Wisconsin, said today that they would defy a new Federal policy that requires state Medicaid programs to pay for medically approved uses of Viagra, the popular but expensive new impotence pill.</p>
        <p>The directive, from the Clinton Administration, prompted an outcry from governors, who said they had not been consulted even though states pay more than 40 percent of Medicaid costs. The National Governors' Association said Medicaid coverage of Viagra should be a state option, not a Federal mandate.</p>
        <p>In a letter to governors today, Nancy-Ann Min DeParle, administrator of the Federal Health Care Financing Administration, said state Medicaid programs must cover Viagra when it is medically necessary for treatment of male impotence.</p>
        <p>Robert R. Hinckley, a spokesman for the New York State Health Department, said: ''We disagree with what the Federal Government is saying. We have a responsibility to protect the health of Medicaid recipients. The Federal Government needs to get a better handle on potential complications that can arise from use of Viagra before it requires state Medicaid programs to cover it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinckley said New York officials were concerned about Viagra's interactions with other drugs and its effects on people with chronic conditions, including heart disease. The label for Viagra says it should not be used by people taking organic nitrates like nitroglycerin, which is often used to treat angina, or chest pain, caused by clogged arteries.</p>
        <p>Zenia Mucha, a spokeswoman for Gov. George E. Pataki of New York, a Republican, said tonight, ''The Federal Government should not be requiring New York or any other state to pay for Viagra until there is a better understanding of the impact this drug has on patients.''</p>
        <p>In Wisconsin, James Malone, a spokesman for the state's Department of Health and Family Services, said: ''We are not covering Viagra right now, and we don't intend to. We will resist being forced to cover it. We don't believe that Viagra is medically necessary. This Federal directive is ill advised and ill considered.''</p>
        <p>It is not clear how the disagreements will be resolved. They could end up in court if poor people press claims for the drug. Alternatively, the Clinton Administration could try to withhold Medicaid money from states that refuse to comply.</p>
        <p>Ms. DeParle said states could ''prevent abuse and misuse of Viagra'' by requiring prior approval for prescriptions or by limiting the number of refills or the number of pills in a prescription.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said they would monitor the use of Viagra and could halt coverage of the drug if evidence showed that it was being misused or abused. Donna E. Shalala, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, ''is greatly concerned about the potential for clinical or financial abuse of Viagra,'' Ms. DeParle said.</p>
        <p>The National Governors' Association estimated that today's directive would cost Federal and state agencies more than $100 million a year.</p>
        <p>Jennifer E. Baxendell, a health policy analyst at the association, said there had been ''virtually no consultation with states'' to assess the costs or implications of a nationwide mandate for Medicaid coverage of Viagra. States pay 43 percent of Medicaid costs, or roughly $73 billion of $170 billion last year.</p>
        <p>''Coverage of Viagra should be a state option, not a mandate,'' the governors' association said.</p>
        <p>Pfizer Inc., the maker of Viagra, says more than two million men have taken the sky-blue diamond-shaped pill since it was approved by the Food and Drug Administration on March 27. It is one of the most popular new prescription products in history.</p>
        <p>Mariann L. Caprino, a spokeswoman for Pfizer, said the company had requested Medicaid coverage in all states. As of early June, she said, 26 states covered Viagra, often with some restrictions. The other states did not cover it or were considering whether to do so, she said.</p>
        <p>The wholesale price of Viagra is $7 a pill, Ms. Caprino said, while the retail price at pharmacies ranges from $8 to $10 a pill.</p>
        <p>Ms. Caprino praised today's decision. Male impotence ''is a bona fide medical condition that has a tremendous impact on patients and their partners,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But disability rights advocates expressed outrage that the Government was requiring coverage of Viagra while allowing states to deny or cut back coverage of medical equipment needed by people with severe disabilities.</p>
        <p>Sheldon V. Toubman, a lawyer at the New Haven Legal Assistance Association, said, ''It's very disturbing that the White House would instruct states that they must cover this sex pill while allowing states to ration care for quadriplegics and people with cerebral palsy or Lou Gehrig's disease who need special medical equipment to keep them alive and to stay out of nursing homes.''</p>
        <p>Ms. DeParle predicted that a relatively small number of Medicaid recipients would qualify for Viagra. Women and children account for 90 percent of the 40 million Medicaid beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>Geralyn A. Lasher, a spokeswoman for the Michigan Department of Community Health, said: ''We are very disappointed with today's announcement from Washington. We are still looking at our options, to see if we have to cover Viagra. We estimate that it would cost us $14 million a year -- $14 million that we could spend on maternal and infant services or people with H.I.V.''</p>
        <p>In Utah, Michael J. Deily, the state Medicaid director, said the state initially allowed 10 Viagra pills a month for Medicaid recipients, then reduced the allowance to five pills and was now considering ''more stringent criteria'' for evaluating a patient's medical need for the drug.</p>
        <p>Technically, states do not have to cover prescription drugs under Medicaid, but all states do so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
