<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Upset in the Vanderbilts And a Title in the Mixed Pairs</title>
    <meta content="17card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/17/crosswords/bridge/17card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DA1F31F934A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Upset in the Vanderbilts And a Title in the Mixed Pairs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Upset in the Vanderbilts and a Title in the Mixed Pairs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, March 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Spring North American Championships here, the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams semifinals were played on Friday. The No. 4 seed (Lou Ann O'Rourke, Eric Greco, Geoff Hampson, Marc Jacobus, Norberto Bocchi and Giorgio Duboin) faced No. 25 (Piotr Tuszynski, Apolinary Kowalski, Farid Assemi, Nick Bykov, Srikanth Kodayam and Ed Wojewoda). The No. 7 seed (Christal Henner-Welland, Bjorn Fallenius, Roy Welland, Antonio Sementa, Cezary Balicki and Adam Zmudzinski) played No. 3 (James Cayne, Michael Seamon, Fulvio Fantoni, Lorenzo Lauria, Claudio Nunes and Alfredo Versace).</p>
        <p>The major upset in the quarterfinals was the defeat of the No. 1 seed -- Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Jeff Meckstroth, Eric Rodwell and Paul Soloway -- by the Tuszynski team. After being down by 31 international match points at halftime, Tuszynski rallied to win by 146 imps to 134.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Spring North American Championships in St. Louis, the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams semifinals were played on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the Spring North American Championships here, the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams semifinals were played on Friday. The No. 4 seed (Lou Ann O'Rourke, Eric Greco, Geoff Hampson, Marc Jacobus, Norberto Bocchi and Giorgio Duboin) faced No. 25 (Piotr Tuszynski, Apolinary Kowalski, Farid Assemi, Nick Bykov, Srikanth Kodayam and Ed Wojewoda). The No. 7 seed (Christal Henner-Welland, Bjorn Fallenius, Roy Welland, Antonio Sementa, Cezary Balicki and Adam Zmudzinski) played No. 3 (James Cayne, Michael Seamon, Fulvio Fantoni, Lorenzo Lauria, Claudio Nunes and Alfredo Versace).</p>
        <p>The major upset in the quarterfinals was the defeat of the No. 1 seed -- Nick Nickell, Dick Freeman, Bob Hamman, Jeff Meckstroth, Eric Rodwell and Paul Soloway -- by the Tuszynski team. After being down by 31 international match points at halftime, Tuszynski rallied to win by 146 imps to 134.</p>
        <p>The Rockwell Mixed Pairs was won on Wednesday night by Mildred Breed of Austin, Tex., and Richard Zeckhauser of Cambridge, Mass. They entered the last round more than a board behind Jane and Bob Teel of Birmingham, Ala., but scored 76 percent of the 182 match points available in that round to prevail by 2.09 match points.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal aided their run to the title. But first look only at the North hand. East passes, your partner opens one no-trump, 15-17 points, and West passes. How would you plan the auction?</p>
        <p>It would seem normal to respond two diamonds, a transfer bid showing at least five hearts, then to rebid three diamonds, promising at least four cards in that suit and game-forcing values. But Zeckhauser, an economics professor at Harvard who with Peter H. Schuck has just published a book with the interesting title ''Targeting in Social Programs: Avoiding Bad Bets, Removing Bad Apples,'' decided that he wanted to play in four hearts, even if his partner had only a doubleton in that suit.</p>
        <p>So he responded four diamonds, a Texas transfer. (Note that three no-trump has no chance after a spade lead, and that six diamonds unluckily fails when the trumps break 4-0. Also, if North had responded two diamonds, East would probably have overcalled two spades. Four spades doubled goes down only two for minus 500.)</p>
        <p>Against four hearts, West led the diamond jack. East, not knowing that South had only two hearts, decided to discard a spade instead of potentially ''wasting'' his natural trump trick and establishing dummy's diamond suit. (If East had ruffed, declarer would have had to guess to drop his heart queen to score an overtrick.)</p>
        <p>Breed, a full-time bridge player, won with her ace and played a heart to dummy's jack. East, after taking his queen, shifted to a spade. Declarer won with her ace, drew trumps and called for the club nine. When East went in with his queen, South ducked, playing a low club from her hand.</p>
        <p>Declarer ruffed East's spade return on the board, led a club to her jack, cashed the club ace, ruffed a club on the board and claimed an overtrick, losing only one heart and one club.</p>
        <p>Plus 650 scored 89 percent of the match points available on the board.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
