<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Versatile Lamb Makes Its Way Back to the Table</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDC1F3DF933A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Versatile Lamb Makes Its Way Back to the Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SPRING is the traditional time for lamb. A roast, scented with herbs and served with new potatoes, steamed young carrots and peas is one of the many highlights of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SPRING is the traditional time for lamb. A roast, scented with herbs and served with new potatoes, steamed young carrots and peas is one of the many highlights of the season.</p>
        <p>SPRING is the traditional time for lamb. A roast, scented with herbs and served with new potatoes, steamed young carrots and peas is one of the many highlights of the season.</p>
        <p>At many of the better butchers, ''genuine spring lamb'' is now becoming available, at higher prices than regular lamb. This label is applied to lamb less than six months old slaughtered from March to October. If it is very young - two to four months - it will have a more delicate flavor than other lamb. The flesh will be whitish pink, as opposed to rosy, and extremely tender. It makes wonderful roasts and chops.</p>
        <p>However, the quality of lamb in general has improved enormously in the last few years, in both supermarkets and butchers, as the demand grows and people discover its versatility. The inexpensive neck and shoulder have plenty of flavor and respond well to long, slow braising. A particularly good stew, especially if you are entertaining, can be made with shoulder or neck, braised Indian-style in yogurt with chilies, garlic, ginger and almonds. Potatoes and okra are added toward the end, so that you have a meal in one pot. This dish improves enormously upon being made a day in advance and reheated. It is good with basmati rice and mango chutney.</p>
        <p>A leg can be marinated for a few days in yogurt, garlic and spices so that the flesh becomes meltingly tender when it is roasted. Rib or loin chops are meatier than those from the shoulder - and more expensive - but they are superb grilled and served with a puree of red or yellow peppers, spring vegetables and a glass of red wine.  Grilled Lamb Chops With Red Pepper Sauce  Preparation time: 10 minutes.  Cooking time: 10 to 15 minutes  8 rib or loin lamb chops 1 inch thick  2 tablespoons olive oil  1 clove garlic, crushed  1 tablespoon fresh rosemary leaves Salt and freshly ground pepper  For the red pepper sauce:  4 red peppers, seeded and cut into quarters  1 clove garlic, coarsely chopped  2 shallots, coarsely chopped</p>
        <p>3/4 cup of chicken or veal stock, preferably homemade</p>
        <p>1/4 cup dry white wine or vermouth.</p>
        <p>1. Wipe the lamb chops dry with paper towels and rub them with oil and garlic. Sprinkle them with rosemary and salt and pepper and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Preheat broiler.</p>
        <p>3. Make the red pepper sauce. Combine the peppers, garlic, shallots, stock and wine in a saucepan and simmer, covered, for 10 to 15 minutes, or until the peppers are soft. Puree in a food processor, season to taste with salt and pepper and set aside.</p>
        <p>4. Meanwhile, grill the chops two inches from the heat until they are medium rare (about three minutes a side). The meat should feel slightly resistant when pressed with a finger. Serve on heated plates with the pepper sauce spooned on the side.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.  Lamb Stewed With Okra, Yogurt and Coriander  Preparation time: 15 minutes  Cooking time: 1 1/2 hours  3 pounds stewing lamb, cut up  2 tablespoons peanut or vegetable oil  1 large onion, coarsely chopped  1 1/2 cups plain yogurt  2 green chilies, seeded and coarsely chopped  2 cloves garlic, coarsely chopped  2 tablespoons fresh ginger root, chopped</p>
        <p>1/2 cup blanched almonds</p>
        <p>Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  1 tablespoon ground cumin  1 1/2 tablespoons ground coriander  1 1/2 pounds small red potatoes  1 pound okra, trimmed  2 to 3 tablespoons fresh coriander leaves, chopped.</p>
        <p>1. Wipe the pieces of lamb dry with paper towels. Heat the oil in the large, heavy casserole and brown the lamb pieces a few at a time. Pour off any fat. 2.</p>
        <p>* Meanwhile, combine the onion, yogurt, chilies, garlic, ginger and almonds in a food processor and grind till pureed. 3.</p>
        <p>* Return the lamb to the casserole and add the yogurt mixture. Season with salt and pepper and add the cumin and coriander. Cover and cook over low heat (you will probably need a heat pad) for one hour. Add the potatoes and okra and continue cooking for half an hour, or until they are tender. Sprinkle with fresh coriander just before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6-8 servings.  Roast Leg of Lamb, Marinated  Preparation time: 2 to 3 days unattended, 5 minutes attended  Cooking time: 1 to 1 1/2 hours  1 5- to 6-pound leg of lamb</p>
        <p>For the marinade:</p>
        <p>3/4 cup plain yogurt  1 small can flat anchovy fillets with their oil  2 cloves garlic, minced  1 teaspoon dry mustard  1 teaspoon thyme leaves</p>
        <p>Freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Trim away any loose fat from the lamb and wipe the leg dry with paper towels. Combine yogurt, anchovies, garlic, dry mustard, thyme and pepper in a food processor and puree until smooth.</p>
        <p>2. Coat the lamb with the mixture, make sure it is entirely covered, place in a dish and cover with foil paper and marinate, turning occasionally, in the refrigerator for two to three days.</p>
        <p>3. Preheat oven to 425 degrees. Roast the lamb for 12 to 15 minutes a pound, according to how you like it, on a rack.</p>
        <p>4. Remove the lamb from the oven and let it rest for a few minutes. Slice thin and arrange the slices on a heated platter. Pour the juices over the slices and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
