<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GROWING ECONOMY PRODUCES SURPLUS IN STATE BUDGETS</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710468"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D81338F935A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GROWING ECONOMY PRODUCES SURPLUS IN STATE BUDGETS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a fiscal turnaround that would have been all but unthinkable in the nation's statehouses just a few years ago, state budgets are swelling with revenue and nearly half the states have enacted election-year tax cuts in recent months.</p>
        <p>In state capitals from Boston to Phoenix, lawmakers who fought in 1991 and 1992 over how to fill huge, painful budget gaps instead battled this year over how to divide unexpected wealth. A growing national economy has largely been responsible, and not only for the surge in revenue: it has also helped to ease recession-era strains on the budgets, like welfare spending and Medicaid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a fiscal turnaround that would have been all but unthinkable in the nation's statehouses just a few years ago, state budgets are swelling with revenue and nearly half the states have enacted election-year tax cuts in recent months.</p>
        <p>In state capitals from Boston to Phoenix, lawmakers who fought in 1991 and 1992 over how to fill huge, painful budget gaps instead battled this year over how to divide unexpected wealth. A growing national economy has largely been responsible, and not only for the surge in revenue: it has also helped to ease recession-era strains on the budgets, like welfare spending and Medicaid.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the tax cuts so far are generally dwarfed by the tax increases enacted a few years ago to deal with the budget gaps, and in some cases they are small enough so as to be little more than symbolic.</p>
        <p>Many states, including New York, are expected to consider much larger tax cuts next year. And with revenue now outrunning projections in all but a handful of states, many lawmakers are also talking about using surpluses next year to raise state workers' salaries or to restore spending on programs they cut a few years ago.</p>
        <p>But amid the rush to divide up spoils that in some states are measured in the billions of dollars, many fiscal experts are warning that the brighter fiscal picture is temporary and, in some ways, even illusory. Nor is it uniform: California's fiscal picture, for example, could be charitably described as having improved in two years to severe from disastrous.</p>
        <p>Still, the current revenue boom is undeniable, and state tax coffers are growing far beyond the rate of inflation. Eighteen states had double-digit increases in revenue from sales taxes in the past year and 23 saw such increases in business taxes, according to a report released last week by the Center for the Study of the States at the Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government in Albany.</p>
        <p>In at least 22 states, the response this spring or summer was to cut taxes. At $649 million, New Jersey's cut was the largest of any state, said Steven D. Gold, the director of the center. Other large cuts per resident were in New York ($470 million), Arizona ($115 million), Georgia ($100 million) and New Mexico ($50 million). Seventeen other states, including Texas, cut taxes by lesser amounts this year.</p>
        <p>For nearly all the states, however, even larger amounts of money will almost surely be the subject of discussion next year. This has prompted caution from fiscal experts who warn that widespread tax cuts or spending increases could wind up proving catastrophic if the nation's economy begins another downturn.</p>
        <p>Another ominous factor on the fiscal horizon, they say, is the states' growing prison populations and the potentially huge cost of tough crime measures like the three-strikes-you're-out provisions adopted by 11 states in recent years and pending in a dozen others. Mixed Blessing for Governors</p>
        <p>For the nation's governors, the surge almost seems a mixed blessing. "The budgets are in better shape, there is no question," said Gov. Howard Dean of Vermont, a Democrat who is chairman of the National Governors' Association. "And because there were huge tax increases to plug these big holes a few years ago, the public has a deep concern about tax cuts now."</p>
        <p>But even as he promised to work for a tax cut if he was re-elected this fall, Mr. Dean was clearly concerned about going too far.</p>
        <p>"The proper thing to do is to put aside a contingency fund" for a future downturn, the Governor said. "But our Legislature in Vermont has not shown the discipline to indicate to me that they wouldn't just spend it. So the second-best choice is a tax cut."</p>
        <p>A similar thought was expressed by the chief fiscal official in Texas, John Sharp, the State Comptroller. Last Wednesday, Texas ended the first year of its two-year, $70.1 billion budget cycle. Asked in an interview for an accounting, Mr. Sharp said the state wound up the year with $2.1 billion more in its treasury than had been anticipated. Don't Tell the Legislators</p>
        <p>"The economy is roaring," the Comptroller said. "I want to say the state economy is doing well because I want people to read it, and it certainly is the truth. But I don't want legislators to read it because I want legislators to continue what they have been doing for the last three years, which is finding better ways to operate."</p>
        <p>In a year when 22 governors are up for re-election, including those in the nation's four most populous states, the political implications of the states' improving fiscal pictures could be enormous and, for them, positive.</p>
        <p>Then again, voters may prove oblivious to or skeptical of the positive news. After all, many may simply be hardened by images of the tax increases and budget slashing that incumbent governors oversaw earlier in their terms.</p>
        <p>A good example is New York, where Gov. Mario M. Cuomo presided over a $470 million tax cut last spring, mostly in business taxes. As he campaigns for a fourth term, he is plausibly able to talk about enacting future tax cuts ranging from $1 billion to $1.5 billion a year.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cuomo also remains the man who has presided over a series of unpopular fee and tax increases, the deferral of scheduled tax cuts, a doubling of state university tuition costs, cuts in popular state programs and a freeze in the salaries of state workers. And some of their unions, which have been instrumental in his rise to power, now refuse to endorse his re-election. Good News for Incumbents</p>
        <p>Still, tax increases tend to be the thing that enrages voters the most, and in virtually every state they are not an issue this fall. Simply put, that is good news for incumbents.</p>
        <p>In Texas, for example, Mr. Sharp, a Democrat who is up for re-election, cheerfully asserts: "There will not be a tax increase next session. Slam dunk, period."</p>
        <p>The more apropos question, in state capitals around the country, is how much of a tax cut to give the voters. To be sure, there are plenty of governors and legislators who insist that deep tax cuts represent a golden opportunity, a way to force state governments, even in flush times, to pare back to the essentials.</p>
        <p>The most far-reaching experiment with such a concept is in New Jersey, where Gov. Christine Todd Whitman, a Republican, was elected last year on a pledge to cut state taxes by 10 percent a year over three years.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gold, the director of the Center for the Study of the States, said that many states had done little to address long-term structural problems in their budgets and warned that this guaranteed painful deficits in the future, when the economy slowed.</p>
        <p>Equally important, "states have been passing the buck to local governments," Mr. Gold said, adding, "To some extent, this appearance of health at the state level is partly due to shifting fiscal stress to cities and counties and schools."</p>
        <p>Another advocate of caution is Hal Hovey, the editor and publisher of State Budget &amp; Tax News, a bimonthly report. The upturn in state revenue is striking, he conceded. Indeed, having published the 1992 issue entirely in red ink to dramatize the fiscal straits of the states, he put out an all-green-ink issue this summer.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hovey warned: "This big boom in revenues probably won't be sustainable. And for the states in general, it is my opinion that significant tax cuts are more dangerous than they have been in years."</p>
        <p>In a few cases, most notably in Mississippi, where revenue from sales taxes rose 15.4 percent this year, some of the gains cans be attributed to casino gambling. But that is an unreliable source of steady cash because an increasing number of states, including some close to Mississippi, are on the verge of legalizing casino gambling.</p>
        <p>In general, though, the surge in revenue is a direct result of the economic recovery. The budget picture looks strongest in the Rocky Mountain and Southeastern states, many of which weathered less turbulent fiscal times in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>In California, progress is measured best only by how the size of the state's problems has shrunk. Three years ago lawmakers were confronted with a potential budget gap of $14.3 billion, which was filled by a combination of spending cuts, borrowing, tax increases and shifting costs to local governments.</p>
        <p>Since then that gap has decreased by almost $3 billion a year; this year, in a $55 billion budget, lawmakers fought over filling a relatively manageable $5 billion hole, said Mac Taylor, deputy legislative analyst for the California Legislature.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Taylor noted that one risky assumption built into the current budget and the next one was that California would regain $3.6 billion in its lawsuit against the Federal Government over the cost of providing services to illegal aliens.</p>
        <p>California also offers a striking example of how spending on prisons puts pressure on the budget. In the last several years, the state has cut 5,000 employees in higher education, part of an overall plan for deep budget cuts. But those savings were more than wiped out by the addition of 8,000 workers to the budget for corrections officials. History Lesson in New York</p>
        <p>In other states, the overall economic recovery has been less than dramatic, but the states' fiscal condition has been aided by tough measures like those in New York, where the state work force was reduced by 10 percent during the recession.</p>
        <p>"The cost containment that the state did in those difficult years helped us to get to the point where now we can look at tax cuts, with the recovery of the economy, as a reasonable option," said Rudy F. Runko, the New York State budget director.</p>
        <p>But history offers an obvious caution. In the mid-1980's, during another economic boom, Governor Cuomo and legislative leaders in Albany agreed to nearly $5 billion in tax cuts. Before long, Mr. Cuomo was saying the cuts were too generous and was asking for tax increases; by 1991, he and the Legislature were staring at budget gaps of $4 billion or more.</p>
        <p>This time around, Mr. Runko said, another tax cut is feasible. But he urged that state officials move with prudence. "The Governor is saying these cuts must be affordable, without doing damage to essential state services," he said. "And they must not impact the local governments."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
