<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Labor Chief Asks Business For a New 'Social Compact'</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORPORATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SWEENEY, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3D61E39F934A35751C1A963958260" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Labor Chief Asks Business For a New 'Social Compact'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John J. Sweeney, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s new president, called yesterday for a new "social compact" between America's corporations and workers, saying he and the labor movement might forgo their rhetoric of confrontation if business adopted what he called a less greedy, more respectful attitude toward the people it employs.</p>
        <p>In what was billed as a major speech, Mr. Sweeney told 400 New York business  executives and civic leaders that companies were undermining the nation's prosperity by holding down wages and slashing their work forces at a time of record profits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John J. Sweeney, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s new president, called yesterday for a new "social compact" between America's corporations and workers, saying he and the labor movement might forgo their rhetoric of confrontation if business adopted what he called a less greedy, more respectful attitude toward the people it employs.</p>
        <p>In what was billed as a major speech, Mr. Sweeney told 400 New York business  executives and civic leaders that companies were undermining the nation's prosperity by holding down wages and slashing their work forces at a time of record profits.</p>
        <p>I want to build bridges between labor and management, so that American business can be more successful and American workers can share in the gains," he said.</p>
        <p>But while holding out an olive branch with one hand, Mr. Sweeney did a little table-pounding with the other, voicing the labor movement's frustration, even anger, with low wage increases.</p>
        <p>"Our problem is stagnant wages -- America needs a raise," he said. "We are going to take the fight to greedy employers who have been picking our pocket."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney, speaking at the New York Hilton to the Association for a Better  New York, a business-led civic group, said many American companies seemed to have dropped the practice of "raising the standards of living for working Americans, not just accumulating enormous wealth for a fortunate few."</p>
        <p>Referring to a sit-in that low-paid janitors held on a bridge in Washington in September, he said workers were so frustrated about low wages that many felt  like blocking bridges rather than building them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney, who had been president of the Service Employees International Union, was elected president of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations in October, after spearheading a drive to replace the federation's longtime president, Lane Kirkland, whom dissidents accused of doing far too little to invigorate a languishing labor movement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney's aides say that between now and the 1996 elections, he will focus his energies and speeches on attacking the growing wage gap between the rich and the rest of the country, and on pushing government, business and unions to do more to reduce that gap.</p>
        <p>The federation's officials say Mr. Sweeney's strategy of focusing on the wage gap has several goals: to heighten pressure on companies to be more generous in  wage settlements, to cause more Americans to warm up to the labor movement and to throw laissez-faire Republicans on the defensive. At the same time, these officials privately fault President Clinton, saying he has not done nearly enough to reduce wage inequities.</p>
        <p>"Since 1979," Mr. Sweeney said in his speech, "all of the income growth in our country has gone to the top 40 percent of households, and nearly all of that went to the top 20 percent.  Well, that isn't the way America built the world's  largest middle class and the world's strongest economy."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney said raising wages had become the leading political and economic  issue in the country, and he predicted that next year's elections would revolve  around who could offer the best ideas for creating jobs and increasing incomes.</p>
        <p>Playing on an unofficial motto of Mr. Clinton's 1992 campaign, "It's the economy, stupid," Mr. Sweeney said, "Look for smart candidates and their campaigns to hang signs in their headquarters with this slogan: 'It's wages, stupid.' "</p>
        <p>After citing a social compact articulated by President John F. Kennedy -- "A  rising tide lifts all boats" -- Mr. Sweeney noted that when Chase Manhattan and  Chemical Bank earlier this year announced a merger that would reduce their combined work force by 12,000, the price of their stock rose.</p>
        <p>"Does a rising tide now sink most ships, except for the luxury yachts?" he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney said it was unfortunate that American business no longer followed Henry Ford's practice of paying his workers enough so that they could afford to  buy the cars they built. He said car prices had risen 70 percent in the last decade, while family incomes had risen 40 percent.</p>
        <p>"Labor's victories can be yours too," he told the business executives. "With  decent paychecks, we can buy your products and services."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
