<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Expands Its Monitoring Of the Trash-Hauling Industry</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ORGANIZED CRIME</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAFIA (UNIONE SICILIANO) (BLACK HAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIED, JOSEPH P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0D61E39F934A35751C1A963958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Expands Its Monitoring Of the Trash-Hauling Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH P. FRIED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIED, JOSEPH P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the latest move to rid Long Island's garbage-hauling business of Mafia control, Federal prosecutors said yesterday that six companies with a "healthy share of the market" will come under Federal Court oversight, joining eight companies already under such supervision.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors and a court-appointed monitor said the growing court supervision of the business on Long Island had resulted in increased competition among hauling companies in Nassau and Suffolk counties and sharp drops in the cost of commercial-trash collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the latest move to rid Long Island's garbage-hauling business of Mafia control, Federal prosecutors said yesterday that six companies with a "healthy share of the market" will come under Federal Court oversight, joining eight companies already under such supervision.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors and a court-appointed monitor said the growing court supervision of the business on Long Island had resulted in increased competition among hauling companies in Nassau and Suffolk counties and sharp drops in the cost of commercial-trash collection.</p>
        <p>In one case they cited, a Seaford diner is now paying one-third what it previously paid to have its garbage carted away. In other instances, they said,  carting companies have offered prices that are half what the customer previously paid.</p>
        <p>The addition of the six companies to the year-and-a-half-old monitoring program is the latest effort by the authorities to curb mob domination of the private garbage-hauling business in the New York region.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani announced plans to create a commission that would regulate and license carting companies in New York City and would have the authority to audit their records, set maximum fees and investigate and  fingerprint their executives and employees. Last summer, a state grand jury brought racketeering and other charges against some of the largest garbage haulers in the city, accusing them of using violence to enforce a noncompetitive system.</p>
        <p>In the city, private companies pick up garbage at commercial sites while the  Department of Sanitation collects residential trash. On Long Island, private companies may pick up residential or commercial trash, depending on the municipality.</p>
        <p>The Rand Corporation has estimated that the mob-enforced, competition-stifling system of allocating customers on Long Island, which the court monitoring is intended to curtail, caused businesses to pay 50 percent more for commercial collections, and residential customers 15 percent more, than they would under a competitive system.</p>
        <p>The monitor for the Island, Michael G. Cherkasky, was appointed by Judge I. Leo Glasser of Federal District Court in Brooklyn as an outgrowth of a civil suit that Federal prosecutors brought against more than 40 companies hauling trash on Long Island. Litigation is pending to bring more than 25 additional companies under the monitoring.</p>
        <p>Zachary W. Carter, the United States Attorney for the Eastern District of New York, identified the six companies added to the program as MCM Sanitation, Enviro Carting, Enviro Recycling, Golden Eagle Disposals, Vinnie Monte's Waste Systems and VAM Management.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
