<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hundred Salutes to the Library</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="814013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DF1F39F934A35751C1A963958260" item-length="1305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hundred Salutes to the Library</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clearly, it was not just another night in the most literary of cities.</p>
        <p>Best-selling authors juggled pots and pans in the kitchen. Bleary-eyed manuscript readers mingled with tycoons whose main daily reading matter is stock tables. And from private midtown clubs to minimalist SoHo lofts to Upper East Side town houses, they all toasted a singularly New York institution, the New York Public Library.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clearly, it was not just another night in the most literary of cities.</p>
        <p>Best-selling authors juggled pots and pans in the kitchen. Bleary-eyed manuscript readers mingled with tycoons whose main daily reading matter is stock tables. And from private midtown clubs to minimalist SoHo lofts to Upper East Side town houses, they all toasted a singularly New York institution, the New York Public Library.</p>
        <p>The library has been uniting readers and writers one way or another, usually in the silence of its reading rooms, for 100 years now. But last night, at 100 "Tables of Contents" dinners organized to celebrate the centennial, there were no "quiet, please" signs, and no one checked whether the guests had any overdue  books.</p>
        <p>The dinners were as different as the library's own holdings. Some were formal, at stiff-upper-lip institutions like the New York Academy of Sciences on East 63d Street. Some were casual, in library patrons' homes. One, at the @ Cafe in the East Village, showed off not the acid-free pages of a just-accessioned book, but an electronic home page on the World Wide Web that came with photographs of the guests.</p>
        <p>And the one in the "private dugout" at Rusty Staub's restaurant, at 575 Fifth Avenue, at 47th Street, featured food that was decidedly unusual: bear claw consomme, Texas rattlesnake spring rolls, rosemary-skewered wild boar kebabs with roasted garlic tomato sauce, and a salad of Mexican cactus.</p>
        <p>But no matter what the menu, from West Indian to Cajun to Japanese, there were two common elements: champagne (from 130 donated magnums and 2 jeroboams),  and an 80-word toast written by Toni Morrison, the Nobel and Pulitzer Prize winner who is a member of the library's board.</p>
        <p>"The New York Public Library is more than brilliant, more, even, than major," the toast said. "What we celebrate tonight is its necessity. New York City is unthinkable without it."</p>
        <p>Pamela Banker, a partner in an interior design firm, said it was unthinkable  that she was in the same room as the author Joyce Carol Oates. But there they were, in the Park Avenue apartment of Louise Westergaard, a theatrical producer, and her husband, Stephen O'Neil.</p>
        <p>"It's just a fabulous mix, isn't it?" Ms. Banker said. "You couldn't put this party together if it wasn't for the library."</p>
        <p>The guests, who paid $350 apiece, had listed the five parties they wanted to  attend, in order of preference, on a reservation form. Some gatherings were limited to only six or eight people; the library struggled to give as many partygoers as possible their first choice to rub elbows with authors and, as it  turned out, about-to-be-authors. Lillian Vernon, the doyenne of the mail-order catalogue business, said that she had signed a contract to write her autobiography only hours earlier.</p>
        <p>Was the conversation witty? Sprinkled with knowing literary allusions? Well,  at least it was grammatically correct. Joanne Matthews, a guest at a dinner with a Cole Porter theme, asked the writer Brendan Gill, "Did you graduate Yale?"</p>
        <p>"Graduate from Yale," he corrected. "Remember the preposition."</p>
        <p>"I went to Wellesley," she replied. "I thought I had a good education."</p>
        <p>The author-turned-screenwriter Nora Ephron was listed as a special guest at "When Books Become Movies," but was a no-show. She was in Los Angeles casting her movie, "Michael," according to an assistant.</p>
        <p>"We knew from the beginning that she might not be able to make it," said Laura Yorke, who was host of the party with her husband, Dick Snyder, the former chairman of Simon &amp; Schuster, and their downstairs neighbor Lynn Nesbit, the literary agent.</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Ephron's family was well represented. Her husband, Nicholas Pileggi, the author of "Wiseguys" and "Casino," was there. So was her sister, Delia Ephron, a producer and screenwriter. Richard Price, who wrote "Clockers,"  was also on the guest list.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Yorke's father, Aaron Jones Yorke, was not, at least not at first. He marked his daughter's dinner as his first choice on the reservation form, only to be told by library officials -- apparently unaware of his relationship to Ms. Yorke -- that he would have to go somewhere else.</p>
        <p>"I called and said, 'He's my dad,' " Ms. Yorke said. That did the trick.</p>
        <p>Her guests arrived to the smell of smoke -- "someone forgot to open the flue," Mr. Snyder said -- and later Mr. Pileggi and the restaurateur Warner LeRoy disappeared to watch the New York Knicks-Chicago Bulls basketball game on  television in another room.</p>
        <p>This was the seventh time in 12 years that the library organized an evening of dinners, so it was no surprise that there were some familiar faces among the  hosts and hostesses, who donated the costs.</p>
        <p>"We gave this same party four years ago," said Kathy Greenberg, the wife of the chairman of the Bear, Stearns investment banking house, Alan C. Greenberg, as she put the finishing touches on Party No. 31. "Well, I hope not the same party. If the same 16 people walk in the door, that would certainly be strange."</p>
        <p>Sure enough, at least one guest had been there before: Mortimer Levitt, the owner of the Custom Shop clothing chain.</p>
        <p>This time, it turned out that Mr. Greenberg had invited a couple of guest performers: Bob Elliott, a retired physics teacher who is known as "Elliott the  Great," and Jerry Deutsch, a lawyer and accountant who has been doing illusions  with Mr. Greenberg for at least 30 years. Soon, coins and watches were vanishing and reappearing.</p>
        <p>"This is the kind of magic I like," Mr. Levitt said, "where it happens right  before your eyes."</p>
        <p>Other partygoers seemed to have mastered the magic of being in two places at  once. Carolyne Roehm's apartment was the setting for a party with the art critic Charles Michener as host. But Ms. Roehm, a designer, was around the corner in Bill Blass's apartment, where they were hosts at a celebration of Thomas Jefferson. Ms. Roehm called him the "quintessential polymath." Never mind that neither she nor Mr. Blass could explain exactly what a "polymath" was (it means  a person of great and diversified learning).</p>
        <p>"And to think I originally wanted to give a poker party," she said.</p>
        <p>She said that she had spent last year in Paris, where Jefferson was an Ambassador. But the the wines last night -- chardonnays and cabernet sauvignons  donated by the Monticello Vineyards -- were produced in the Napa Valley, not in  the Virginia vineyards that Jefferson fostered.</p>
        <p>There was chablis at Rosetta and Sam Miller's apartment on Central Park South. It seemed only appropriate: the Lady Chablis was the name of the transvestite party-crasher who figured in John Berendt's best seller, "Midnight  in the Garden of Good and Evil."</p>
        <p>Mr. Berendt flew in from Louisville, Ky., the latest stop on what he called "the longest, dullest book tour God ever created," and read several passages from the book. The reading was in a bedroom where the Millers had set up an altar-like corner, complete with votive candles.</p>
        <p>"We were trying to create some of the book's sinister quality," Mrs. Miller said.</p>
        <p>But unlike the parties chronicled in Mr. Berendt's book, no one brought a gun.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
