<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater in Review</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IVES, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BREEN, PATRICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KORDER, HOWARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN MATRE, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEDGES, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIVE VERY LIVE (ONE ACT PLAYS)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DF113EF93BA35752C0A964958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mel Gussow</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five Very Live  The Atlantic Theater 336 West 20th Street Manhattan Through Jan. 18 Five one act plays by contemporary American playwrights: David Ives, Patrick Breen, Howard Korder, David Van Matre and Peter Hedges; scenery by James Wolk; lighting by Howard Werner; production stage manager, Matthew Silver. Presented by the Atlantic Theater Company. WITH: Robert Bella, Ron Butler, Sarah Eckhardt, Steven Goldstein, Kristen Johnson, Mary McCann, Neil Pepe, David Pittu, Robin Spielberg and Damian Young.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five Very Live  The Atlantic Theater 336 West 20th Street Manhattan Through Jan. 18 Five one act plays by contemporary American playwrights: David Ives, Patrick Breen, Howard Korder, David Van Matre and Peter Hedges; scenery by James Wolk; lighting by Howard Werner; production stage manager, Matthew Silver. Presented by the Atlantic Theater Company. WITH: Robert Bella, Ron Butler, Sarah Eckhardt, Steven Goldstein, Kristen Johnson, Mary McCann, Neil Pepe, David Pittu, Robin Spielberg and Damian Young.</p>
        <p>In "Five Very Live," an anthology of unequal one-act comedies dealing with sociocultural matters, a troupe of eager young actors from the Atlantic Theater Company has ample elbow room to display its comic resourcefulness.</p>
        <p>Mary McCann and Robert Bella are the entire cast of David Ives's "Sure Thing," the first and by far the funniest of the comedies, a sharp-sighted take on contemporary mating habits. In this curtain-raiser, which was previously produced at the Manhattan Punch Line, a man approaches a cafe table and begins a round robin of small talk with a woman who is reading "The Sound and the Fury."</p>
        <p>His first maneuver fizzles, and, after the sound of a buzzer, he tries again. The buzzer keeps sounding and interrupting and the dialogue keeps changing, until the play becomes a virtuosic series of variations on a single theme. Moving from Faulkner to Woody Allen, Mr. Ives shifts degrees of aggressiveness and self-defensiveness, in 10 nimble minutes offering a thesaurus of the modes and mannerisms of the pick-up. Under Scott Zigler's direction, Ms. McCann and Mr. Bella are the deftest of reactors and counter-reactors.</p>
        <p>Later, Ms. McCann appears with Kristen Johnston, a hopeful hostess in Howard Korder's "Wonderful Party," another repeat from the Manhattan Punch Line. This is a raucous, one-note cartoon about hangers-on and gate-crashers, which finds some fun in the specifics of party giving (Ms. Johnston offers tropical drinks "with or without an umbrella"). The sketch reaches a climax when 20 uninvited guests crowd the apartment with a Babel of forced bonhomie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bella's showiest role is in the play that gives the anthology its title, David Van Matre's sophomoric sendup of tabloid television journalism. The actor plays a baseball star hounded from the game on unproven moral charges. Mr. Bella is amusing as the abashed athlete and Ms. McCann and Ron Butler radiate smugness as the anchors in charge of allegations and rumors.</p>
        <p>David Pittu holds the stage alone in Patrick Breen's whimsical "Call of the Wily." He plays Wily, the mischief-making coyote in cartoons. As interpreted by Mr. Pittu and as disguised in a seedy coyote costume by Kia Heath, Wily is a highly cultured sort. Standing at a bar, he soliloquizes like a Dudley Moore film character. The unanswered question of the moment is why does the coyote never capture the Road Runner?</p>
        <p>"The Age of Pie" by Peter Hedges closes the evening with farce turning into slapstick. This is a flat-handed attempt to write a play to end all plays about encounter groups. In this case, the therapy session leads to squabbles and, in the absence of a resolution, culminates with custard pies. Despite the slippery demands of the play, the actors perform with panache. Once again, humor derives less from the words of a playwright than from the exuberance of a community of actors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
