<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Minimalist; Taking a Different Tack On Fish and Chips</title>
    <meta content="18MINI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cod (Fish)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D9173FF93BA25751C0A96E958260" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Minimalist; Taking a Different Tack On Fish and Chips</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Bittman, in The Minimalist column, describes making crispy potatoes with cod fish; recipe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN one of my daughters was young, there was a time when her main passion in life was potatoes, especially crispy ones. It didn't matter how they were cooked -- as home fries, french fries or roasted. As long as they had that external crunch and internal mealiness, she was happy.</p>
        <p>For one special occasion, I produced the classic French dish, potatoes Anna, in which potatoes are thin-sliced, drenched in butter, carefully layered and roasted until golden -- the ultimate in crisp potato dishes. This was an error, of course; potatoes Anna is a pain to make and contains about a week's allotment of butter. Naturally, the demand was unrelenting thereafter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN one of my daughters was young, there was a time when her main passion in life was potatoes, especially crispy ones. It didn't matter how they were cooked -- as home fries, french fries or roasted. As long as they had that external crunch and internal mealiness, she was happy.</p>
        <p>For one special occasion, I produced the classic French dish, potatoes Anna, in which potatoes are thin-sliced, drenched in butter, carefully layered and roasted until golden -- the ultimate in crisp potato dishes. This was an error, of course; potatoes Anna is a pain to make and contains about a week's allotment of butter. Naturally, the demand was unrelenting thereafter.</p>
        <p>So in an attempt to make the effort more rational, I cut down on the butter, short cut the preparation time by enlisting the aid of the broiler during the last few minutes of cooking and -- to make life easier still -- decided to turn this one dish into something approaching an entire meal. In the last few minutes, before the potatoes were cooked through, I placed a thick fillet of fish on top of the potatoes. The result is what I call Emma's Cod, a simple weeknight dish that I now make routinely, and one that seems even to impress the occasional guest.</p>
        <p>The preparation can, of course, be made more complex. A teaspoon or so of minced garlic tossed with the potatoes is the most obvious elaboration, but chopped parsley, minced thyme leaves or even ground spices, like chili or curry powder, vary the dish nicely. You can also add other vegetables, but because most will throw off added water, the potatoes will not brown as well as they do when cooked solo.</p>
        <p>Cooking time is determined by thickness, of both the potato slices and the fish. If you have a mandoline (or a sharp knife and good cutting skills), aim for slicing the potatoes about one-eighth inch thick. This will allow them to cook through and begin to brown within 40 minutes or so. The cod or other fish should be about one inch thick; during the eight or so minutes it takes to cook through, the tops of the exposed potatoes will gain a fine crust, while the fish browns lightly.</p>
        <p>EMMA'S COD  Time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>4  or 5 medium potatoes, 2 pounds or more</p>
        <p>6  tablespoons extra virgin olive oil or melted butter</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1 1/2  pounds cod or other fillets, about 1-inch thick (skinned), in 2 or more pieces.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees. Peel potatoes, and cut them into slices about  1/8-inch thick (a mandoline comes in handy here). Toss the potatoes in an 8-by-12-inch or similar size baking pan with 4 tablespoons of the oil or butter. Season the potatoes liberally, spread them evenly and place the pan in the  oven.  2. Cook for about 40 minutes, checking once or twice, until the potatoes are tender when pierced with a thin-bladed knife and have begun to brown on top. Remove the potatoes from the oven. Turn on the broiler, and adjust the rack so that it is 4 to 6 inches from the heat source.  3. Top the potatoes with the fish, drizzle with the remaining oil or butter and sprinkle with some more salt and pepper. Broil until the fish is done, 6 to 10 minutes, depending on its thickness (a thin-bladed knife will pass through it easily). If at any point the top of the potatoes begins to burn, move the pan a  couple of inches farther away from the heat source.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
