<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reports of Saudi Price Cuts Depress Energy Contracts</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FUTURES/OPTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9163BF935A35755C0A966958260" item-length="361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reports of Saudi Price Cuts Depress Energy Contracts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Reuters</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Reports that Saudi Arabia reduced prices for its July oil exports to the United States by 40 cents a barrel from June levels sent energy futures traded at the New York Mercantile Exchange tumbling today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Reports that Saudi Arabia reduced prices for its July oil exports to the United States by 40 cents a barrel from June levels sent energy futures traded at the New York Mercantile Exchange tumbling today.</p>
        <p>Reports that Saudi Arabia reduced prices for its July oil exports to the United States by 40 cents a barrel from June levels sent energy futures traded at the New York Mercantile Exchange tumbling today.</p>
        <p>July crude settled down 46 cents, at $16.68 a barrel, after having fallen more than 70 cents earlier in the session. July gasoline dropped 1.76 cents, to 57.82 cents a gallon, and July heating oil ended 0.48 cent lower, at 47.11 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the reports that Saudi Arabia cut its prices for July crude to the Far East, Europe and the United States sent futures spiraling downward. But by late afternoon, traders began to doubt the Saudi cuts were as widespread as first speculated.</p>
        <p>Responsibility Denied</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia's Minister of Petroleum and Mineral Resources, Hisham Nazer, denied his country was responsible for the price slide.</p>
        <p>''Saudi Arabia promised OPEC on May 1 to abide by its quota,'' Mr. Nazer said in statement carried by the Saudi Press Agency. ''The whole world admitted it was keeping its promise, and it still adheres to it. Saudi Arabia has not changed its position.''</p>
        <p>On the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, pork bellies and live hogs climbed on talk of Soviet buying interest. Bellies posted 2-cent daily limit gains in the July contract, to 67.30 cents a pound. They also made limit gains for August and ended sharply higher for contracts expiring in other months.</p>
        <p>Market dealings were quiet but when talk reached the trading floor that the Soviet Union might buy meat if granted Government credits, prices soared.</p>
        <p>Indications that supplies of frozen pork bellies were dropping also supported the market. Traders and analysts estimated a 300,000- to 500,000-pound drop in supplies. After the close of trading, the Chicago Mercantile Exchange reported cold storage supplies dropped 931,000 pounds during the week ended last Saturday.</p>
        <p>Live hog futures moved in tandem with pork bellies to close sharply higher in most months. Forecasts for higher hog prices also aided the tone, traders said.</p>
        <p>Hogs closed from 0.525 cent to 1.375 cents higher, with the June contract up 0.525 cent, at 66.775 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>FUTURES/OPTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
