<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uphill Struggle to Adapt Wine to the World's Taste</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FUTURE ARTICLES WILL DISCUSS PORTUGAL, GERMANY AND THE NAPA VALLEY OF CALIFORNIA." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D9133AF935A35755C0A966958260" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uphill Struggle to Adapt Wine to the World's Taste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
      <dateline>MENDOZA, Argentina</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A WINE-BOTTLING line is noisy. As the bottles bump along the metal belt waiting their turn to be filled, they clank, rattle and crash into one another, setting up a terrible din.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A WINE-BOTTLING line is noisy. As the bottles bump along the metal belt waiting their turn to be filled, they clank, rattle and crash into one another, setting up a terrible din.</p>
        <p>A WINE-BOTTLING line is noisy. As the bottles bump along the metal belt waiting their turn to be filled, they clank, rattle and crash into one another, setting up a terrible din.</p>
        <p>On the major bottling line here at the Penaflor winery, Argentina's largest and one of the largest in the world, there is hardly any noise: the wine is being packed in one-liter cardboard boxes called tetrapacks.</p>
        <p>That particular bottling line says a lot about wine in Argentina. Of course, no one, not even here in the wine capital of the Southern Hemisphere, would put good wine in a plastic box. The Argentines are among the world's leading wine consumers but, for the most part, they have not been overly concerned about quality.</p>
        <p>Or at least, not until recently. For several years now, the Argentine wine business has been adapting - painfully - to the overworked adage that less is more.</p>
        <p>Here in this handsome city at the foot of the Andes, 600 miles west of Buenos Aires, wine production has always been described in gargantuan terms: three quarters of a million acres of grapes, an annual output of a half billion gallons of wine, and individual fermenting tanks with the capacity of 10 medium-size California wineries. ''I think we have 40,000 growers,'' said Domenico LoVecchio, the director of the San Telmo winery, ''but nobody knows for sure.''</p>
        <p>Most of the growers sell their production, either grapes or wine, to one of about a half-dozen huge wineries where it is blended and shipped.</p>
        <p>Much of this wine, probably 70 percent, even today is little more than vin ordinaire, simple table wine. But until recently, it was wine ideally suited to its principal market: Argentina itself. Argentina is the fifth-largest wine producer in the world after Italy, France, the Soviet Union and Spain, and, four years ago was fourth in wine consumption, with per capita consumption at more than 17 gallons a year.</p>
        <p>That figure has been dropping, partly because of the disastrous state of Argentina's economy - many people now cannot afford even the cheapest wine - and because, like elsewhere in the world, tastes are changing. Millions of Argentines, it appears, would rather consume soft drinks and beer than the indifferent wine of the criolla grape sold in five-gallon demijohns or in the nondescript tetrapacks. As a result, wineries have been closing and the industry is worried.</p>
        <p>But 10 years ago, a handful of farsighted wine makers, mostly based here in Mendoza, decided that the future was in exports. They began to develop the vineyards and the wine-making techniques that would gain them entry into the world's fine wine markets.</p>
        <p>There is no reason why Argentina should not be among the world's premium wine producers. Wine has been made here since the Jesuit missionaries arrived in the country in 1556. The criolla grape they brought with them is the basic wine grape of the country. Other Spanish missionaries took the grape into Mexico and the United States, where it is known as the mission grape.</p>
        <p>A hundred years ago, Italian immigrants who had grown grapes and made wine in Italy discovered the fertility of the high plains stretching away from this city in every direction. Within a few years, it was Argentina's favorite land for vineyards.</p>
        <p>Only now is the long effort beginning to show some success, many years after Chile, which went through many of the same problems, began to make its mark beyond its borders.</p>
        <p>Some of Argentina's problems are unique to Argentina. For 40 years, this potentially rich land has been a closed society; closed to innovation, cut off from modern technology and from contemporary political and economic ideas. For example, by law, Argentine products, if available, must be used in preference to better imports. And Penaflor labels its fine wine bottles by hand rather than to use a virtually unworkable domestic machine.</p>
        <p>Only after prolonged and costly battles with the bureaucracy were the big wineries here finally permitted to buy European or American presses and oak barrels for aging wine. Still the ravages of inflation are everywhere. What was meant to be one of the most beautiful wineries in the world, San Telmo, here in Mendoza, is a half-built monument to fiscal ineptitude, a partly finished architectural marvel sitting in a sea of mud, surrounded by rusting piles of building materials with which it was to have been finished 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>And yet, even San Telmo produces good wines, some of which can be found in the United States. ''We do the best we can,'' Sigifredo Alonso, San Telmo's president, said, ''and we look to the future.''</p>
        <p>The future looms large in the lives of Argentines, partly because the present has been bleak for so long. ''Argentina is a nation of unfinished dreams,'' someone once said.</p>
        <p>Carlos Pulenta is a director of Penaflor and president of Bodegas Trapiche, Penaflor's fine-wine subsidiary. ''The future for us is in export,'' he said. ''We must export or we will die.'' Dramatic stuff, but Mr. Pulenta, whose grandfather came from Ancona, Italy, to found Penaflor, seems to mean what he says.</p>
        <p>He has opened an importing company in New York and plans to do the same soon in London. He has invested heavily in the equipment needed to make and age fine wine and is converting thousands of acres of dull criolla and Pedro Ximenez grapes to chardonnay, malbec and cabernet sauvignon.</p>
        <p>For the moment, Trapiche fine wines are only a part of Penaflor's export mix. Bulk wine, millions of gallons of it, are sold to the wine and spirits government monopolies in Finland and other Scandinavian countries. Even major wine producers like France and Spain buy bulk wine from Penaflor. Grape juice concentrate by the shipload goes to Japan where it is made into wine. The country also exports other fruit juices and bottled water. In fact, olive oil brings in more hard currency than wine.</p>
        <p>Exporting wine is an uphill fight. The severely taxed Government has no money to spare for promotion, unlike neighboring Chile, where the Government has for almost a decade paid for a sophisticated marketing program for its wine and fruit exports.</p>
        <p>Argentina is also hampered by its unfamiliarity with the world wine market. One evening, in the Trapiche tasting room, someone opened a half-bottle of a 1983 cabernet sauvignon from Beaulieau Vineyards in California. The Argentine tasters were delighted. ''One day we will make a wine like this,'' one said. The one American present found the wine faded and oxidized.</p>
        <p>Until recently the preferred wine making style in both Chile and Argentina called for many years of aging in large oak casks, just the formula for producing heavy, oxidized wines. Here was a well-known American wine that seemed to conform to that style. Old traditions die hard.</p>
        <p>When the Italian wine makers came to Mendoza in the 19th century, they brought the best European grape varieties with them, including cabernet sauvignon. For some reason, malbec, which is the principal variety in Cahors but mostly a blending variety in Bordeaux, in Argentina makes a wine as good as and often better than cabernet sauvignon. Perhaps it resists oxidation more.</p>
        <p>In any event, Trapiche makes a malbec that is quite delicious, as does Navarro Correas, one of the most prestigious of the wineries here in Mendoza. Vilma Gutierrez, the chief wine maker at Navarro Correas studied for a time under Zelma Long, for many years the wine maker and now president of the Simi Winery in California.</p>
        <p>Two varieties that appear to have considerable promise are merlot and chardonnay. The best merlots seem softer and more harmonious, certainly more so than the cabernets, and avoid what tasters call the ''hotness'' associated with oxidation. The best chardonnays, Trapiche's among them, are fresh and clean. There seems to be no overwhelming need to age them in oak.</p>
        <p>Chenin blanc, produced in considerable quantity in Argentina is no better than it should be, and pinot noir is still pretty much in the experimental stage.</p>
        <p>In spite of the county's chaotic economic condition, progress continues here. Old vineyards are torn out and new grapes planted. New growing areas are opening up at higher elevations like Tupungato and in cooler climes like Rio Negro, 500 miles to the south. Techniques continue to be refined, better clones of grapes are developed, wine makers go abroad to study. The wines now in export markets show this improvement, particularly the whites. Excellent sparkling wines are being made here; wines that could compete with any other than champagne itself, if they were to be exported in some quantity.</p>
        <p>But there is a long way to go. Until the economy is brought into line, there is little likelihood that outside investors - or the Argentines who squirrel most of their income in Swiss banks - will put up the kind of capital needed to modernize the Argentine wine industry. And, given the current downturn in the world wine market, who can say it would be a wise investment if they did?</p>
        <p>For the wine fan, however, the Argentine wines are a whole new world to explore. And, given their remarkably low prices at the moment - mostly under $10 for the good wines - it can be a rather reasonable trip.</p>
        <p>Buying Them</p>
        <p>THE best endorsement for the Argentine wine may be the fact that Argentines drink almost all of it themselves.</p>
        <p>Argentine wines may not be readily available in your corner liquor store yet, but with a little effort you will find them.</p>
        <p>The best-known name is Bodegas Trapiche, the prestige export label of the huge Penaflor. The Trapiche Reserva line includes cabernet sauvignon, malbec, chardonnay and pinot noir, all costing about $5.99. San Telmo includes a cabernet sauvignon and a chardonnay at about $7.99. Navarro Correas offers a malbec, a syrah and a pinot noir in its Collecion Privada group, all at $8.99. Navarro's sauvignon blanc sells for about $7.50.</p>
        <p>Other labels to look for include Clos du Moulin, Fond de Cave, Comte de Valmont and Palmero, whose 1984 merlot, for about $6 is a solid bargain.</p>
        <p>Worth sampling, too, are the wines of Humberto Canale, which come from Rio Negro. The Canale Reserva line includes a semillon, a cabernet sauvignon and a merlot. Some stores may still have the 1978 cabernet for under $10, a wine well worth trying.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
