<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Look for a Fast Plane</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCORDE AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AIR FRANCE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PUTMAN, ANDREE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLESIN, SUZANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D81F30F934A15752C0A962958260" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Look for a Fast Plane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE SLESIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLESIN, SUZANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not the usual trip to the airport: no luggage to check in, no carry-on, no ticket. Just an intriguing invitation to see how Andree Putman, the French designer, had put her distinctive signature on the interior of the Air France Concorde.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Putman, known for the chic face lift she gave the Morgans Hotel 10 years ago, the redesign marked the culmination of years of Paris-New York-Paris forays. A frequent traveler on the supersonic airplane, she was in the habit of making a mental list of all the improvements she could make to the interior with just a flick of her minimalist wand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not the usual trip to the airport: no luggage to check in, no carry-on, no ticket. Just an intriguing invitation to see how Andree Putman, the French designer, had put her distinctive signature on the interior of the Air France Concorde.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Putman, known for the chic face lift she gave the Morgans Hotel 10 years ago, the redesign marked the culmination of years of Paris-New York-Paris forays. A frequent traveler on the supersonic airplane, she was in the habit of making a mental list of all the improvements she could make to the interior with just a flick of her minimalist wand.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, she was invited to join a competition to change the look of the Concorde. The other designers invited to submit proposals were Philippe Starck, Philippe Boisselier and Pierre Gautier-Delaye.</p>
        <p>"I thought I was dreaming, that it was a fairy tale," she said. "I've always thought of the Concorde as a magical object, a symbol, a miracle."</p>
        <p>But one that was not perfect.</p>
        <p>"I wanted to change everything," she said. "I realized how much I disliked the luggage racks, the colors, the shape of the seats."</p>
        <p>Bernard Bazot, Air France's vice president for commercial affairs in the United States, said it cost $1 million to redo the interiors of five of the fleet's seven Concordes (two are backups).</p>
        <p>On Tuesday morning at Kennedy International Airport, a group of visitors was invited to go to the boarding gate, breeze past security and walk single file onto the sleek, narrow Concorde.</p>
        <p>Ms. Putman pointed out the softer curve of the luggage compartments; the higher, rounded headrests in what she called "the spirit of Babar," a reference to the well-traveled elephant of children's storybook fame, and the new gray, navy blue and beige carpeting with its geometric frieze running the length of the two cabins. She said her intervention was "not about a spectacular gesture, but all in the details. I felt I had to have the courage to do so little."</p>
        <p>Suggesting the attention one may expect from the housekeeping staff in a great hotel, the immaculate white pique cotton headrest covers seemed to represent a kind of subliminal security blanket. "In small spaces, you become nervous," she said, adding that the covers go to the laundry right after the plane lands.</p>
        <p>In the lounge, lunch was being served. The subtle contrast between the soft beige linen napkins and the corrugated paper flatware envelope did not go unappreciated. Nor did the white china decorated with only an understated streak of bright blue. "The color of the New York skies we like so much," she said, getting ready to board the 1 P.M. flight to Paris.</p>
        <p>Au revoir.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
