<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Task in '92: Getting to Barcelona</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="5 DAYS TO BARCELONA -- Eleventh article of a series on the Summer Olympics" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED81030F933A15754C0A964958260" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Task in '92: Getting to Barcelona</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>BARCELONA, Spain, July 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as senior Olympic officials spent the days leading to the last four Summer Games urging countries to abandon threatened boycotts, they are at work attempting to have the largest group possible for the opening ceremonies of the Barcelona Olympics on Saturday.</p>
        <p>But this time, the circumstances are somewhat different. Those whom the International Olympic Committee is trying to get here actually want to participate. They include two or three teams from what was once Yugoslavia and even an I.O.C. member, Ivan Slavkov of Bulgaria, whose passport was lifted last week by the police in Sofia as he was about to board a plane for Barcelona.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as senior Olympic officials spent the days leading to the last four Summer Games urging countries to abandon threatened boycotts, they are at work attempting to have the largest group possible for the opening ceremonies of the Barcelona Olympics on Saturday.</p>
        <p>But this time, the circumstances are somewhat different. Those whom the International Olympic Committee is trying to get here actually want to participate. They include two or three teams from what was once Yugoslavia and even an I.O.C. member, Ivan Slavkov of Bulgaria, whose passport was lifted last week by the police in Sofia as he was about to board a plane for Barcelona.</p>
        <p>The Yugoslav question is expected to be solved by Monday, after a United Nations Security Council sanctions committee in New York reviews clarifications from the I.O.C. about how athletes from Yugoslavia, now comprising only the republics of Serbia and Montenegro, would participate in the Games. Renegotiating Sanctions</p>
        <p>Among the sanctions imposed on Yugoslavia for being the aggressor in the current fighting is the requirement that Spain and all other member countries of the United Nations deny Yugoslavs the right to compete internationally. The I.O.C. proposed resolving the issue by having the Yugoslav team of approximately 160 athletes compete as individuals under the Olympic flags.</p>
        <p>But after several discussions by the sanctions committee over the weekend, not all 15 members were satisfied the team would be depoliticized enough to grant Spain permission to allow it to join athletes from the 170 other nations expected for the Olympics. The committee wanted to know how the Yugoslavscould partake in team events and not be identified as a nation and how they would travel to Spain. The committee also asked for a list of athletes who would compete.</p>
        <p>Francois Carrard, the I.O.C. director general, said this afternoon that the I.O.C. response would be sent shortly and that he expected a resolutuon of the matter within 24 hours.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he indicated that countries that would replace Yugoslavia in team competitions if a political solution could not be found had been alerted. They include Iceland's men's handball team, Norway's women's handball team, Czechoslovakia's water polo team and the women's basketball team from Italy.</p>
        <p>"The fundamental point is the interpretation of 'representing,' " Carrard said at an afternoon news conference. "The Security Council wants to make sure this team, whatever form it takes, is not perceived as representing Yugoslavia."</p>
        <p>To that end, he said the team could be designated as the Independent Team, a neutral convenience like the one created for the athletes from 12 former Soviet Republics who are competing together on the Unified Team.</p>
        <p>Carrard disagreed that such a notion might be politically less persuasive in team sports. "It would be like five of us here playing together on a side," he said.</p>
        <p>Closely tied to any resolution of the Yugoslav situation is the prospect of participation by two other former Yugoslavia republics, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and Macedonia. They have petitioned the I.O.C. for inclusion but were told that the other Yugoslav issue must be settled first. It appears, however, that they would be accommodated in some form no matter what position the United Nations takes with Serbia and Montenegro.</p>
        <p>The major uncertainty with Bosnia and Herzegovina and with Macedonia is whether their athletes, about 15 from each republic, would compete as one team or two. In either case, Carrard said, no determination would be made until the I.O.C. knew if Yugoslavia was in or out.</p>
        <p>Slavkov's participation in the Olympics is dependent upon government authorities in Bulgaria, who so far have shown an unwillingness to let him attend. They claim he is under investigation for embezzlement and cannot leave the country until the issue is resolved.</p>
        <p>Slavkov, an I.O.C. member since 1987 and president of the national Olympic Committee, was deeply involved with the former Communist regime under Todor Zhivkov, his father-in-law, who was ousted three years ago. More than two years ago, Slavkov, 52, was charged with embezzling funds from the Olympic committee, but the case was dropped for lack of evidence.</p>
        <p>As a reform government has taken root in Bulgaria, new efforts have begun to examine activities of members of the old regime. Slavkov became one of dozens of officials who lost traveling privileges while investigations continue under a newly appointed prosecutor general, Ivan Tatarchev.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Juan Antonio Samaranch, the I.O.C. president, and other Olympic officials have interceded on Slavkov's behalf through the Bulgarian Foreign Ministry in Sofia and the embassy in Madrid, asking that he be allowed to attend the Games.</p>
        <p>"We are very shocked, very shocked to learn he has been refused to leave Bulgaria," said Carrard in language unusually strong for an I.O.C. official. "There is nothing new to justify this. We are shocked. This is a matter of human rights. It is most disturbing for the I.O.C. that this kind of restriction still persists in certain countries of Europe today."</p>
        <p>Slavkov was so shaken by his detention, he developed high blood pressure and spent three days in a hospital. He must return on Monday for another examination.</p>
        <p>"There is no problem, actually," he said tonight from his home in Sofia. "It is the stupidity from the chief prosecutor, the decision not to go out of the country. For more than two years, my case has been closed. Now, again, on the eve of the Games it is open. Obviously, this is a special case because of the Olympics. I have traveled for the last two years, and all the time, I came back to the country. So what is the problem?"</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICAN TO COMPETE</p>
        <p>JOHANNESBURG, July 19 (AP) -- A table-tennis player who was dropped from the South African Olympic team after failing a drug test has regained her spot, the South African Press Association said today.</p>
        <p>The decision to give Cheryl Roberts a reprieve was made late Friday during a special meeting of the National Olympic Committee, the association reported.</p>
        <p>Roberts tested positive for a banned stimulant on May 31, but sports officials said it was a rushed test and that Roberts had not been told she needed to declare if she was on medications. The stimulant is contained in medication prescribed for Roberts because of a head cold. She tested negative for drugs in a later test.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
