<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Trail, at Last, to the Big City</title>
    <meta content="26meat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/26/dining/26meat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1778533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kingston (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowen, Dana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applestone, Joshua</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Union Square Greenmarket</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Agriculture Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DC153FF935A15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Trail, at Last, to the Big City</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On the Trail, at Last, to the Big City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA BOWEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowen, Dana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joshua Applestone, who owns butcher shop in Kingston, NY, develops system for getting fresh local meat from small farmers to lucrative New York market; many farms are too small to supply steady flow of meat, so Applestone took over logistics of slaughtering and delivering meat to upscale restaurants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT his Greenwich Village restaurant, Mas, Galen Zamarra serves duck from Ulster Country, goat cheese from Connecticut, trout from the Neversink River in upstate New York. Even the cocktails are garnished with local fruit.</p>
        <p>But the first year he was open, in 2004, Mr. Zamarra didn't have a source for fresh local steak. So he served no steak at all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recently, a small group of farmers and entrepreneurs have come up with creative ways to get fresh local meat to the lucrative New York market by figuring out how to get the meat processed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT his Greenwich Village restaurant, Mas, Galen Zamarra serves duck from Ulster Country, goat cheese from Connecticut, trout from the Neversink River in upstate New York. Even the cocktails are garnished with local fruit.</p>
        <p>But the first year he was open, in 2004, Mr. Zamarra didn't have a source for fresh local steak. So he served no steak at all.</p>
        <p>Yet in a meadow beside a storybook barn a few hours north, Donald Leab tended a small herd of Black Angus that had exactly the grass-fed, corn-finished flavor Mr. Zamarra was looking for.</p>
        <p>The farmer didn't know the chef existed, and vice versa, so the meat was sold frozen for a fraction of its urban worth.</p>
        <p>In an era when chefs and shoppers are seeking out foods raised close to home, fresh meat feels like the final frontier. Aside from what you find in coolers at farmers' markets, it's still easier and cheaper to get fresh meat finished at gargantuan feedlots on the Great Plains than from nearby farms.</p>
        <p>But recently a small group of farmers and entrepreneurs have come up with creative ways to get fresh local meat to the lucrative New York market by figuring out how to get the meat processed.</p>
        <p>So many slaughterhouses have closed in recent years, because of increases in costs and the tightening of regulations, that farmers must wait for months and often drive 100 miles or more to have animals processed.</p>
        <p>''The slaughterhouses here are the biggest problem,'' said Joshua Applestone, 36, who opened a butcher shop in Kingston, N.Y., called Fleisher's two years ago and soon became a matchmaker between chefs and farmers like Mr. Zamarra and Mr. Leab on the side.</p>
        <p>It was that ''so close yet so far'' quandary that drove Mr. Applestone, a chef who was at the time a vegan, and his wife, Jessica, an author, to a career in cutting meat. Ms. Applestone had decided to indulge in the occasional rib-eye from farms she had visited and trusted, but couldn't find anyone who would sell her a single fresh steak.</p>
        <p>If they had a shop, they thought, they could sell the rib-eyes everyone wanted, as well as stock from bones, sausage from scraps, even soap from suet. For Mr. Applestone, the idea had nostalgic pull: his great-grandfather Wolf Fleisher had been a butcher in Borough Park, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''People told us we were crazy,'' Ms. Applestone said one busy afternoon in the shop, a place so old-fashioned it seems as if it should be experienced in black and white.</p>
        <p>When they started visiting farms they began to think that the doubters might be right. Most were too small to supply a steady flow of meat and were already overwhelmed by the logistics of processing. So the Applestones took over the logistics, booking weekly reservations with processing plants and arranging to have animals from several farms trucked in.</p>
        <p>''It makes it a lot easier,'' said Mr. Leab, whose family has owned Ioka Valley Farm in Hancock, Mass., since 1936. ''They take care of all of that.''</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Applestone who first took Mr. Leab's meat to New York City. (Mr. Leab now works with distributors in Boston too.)</p>
        <p>After Mr. Applestone fills his truck with fresh meat at a slaughterhouse he delivers the priciest pieces to places like Mas and Il Buco in Manhattan and less expensive cuts and hamburger meat to neighborhood places like Diner and Sparky's in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. Everything else is cut and sold in the shop, along with other products, like the farm-cured bacon that ultimately wooed him back to the camp of carnivores.</p>
        <p>Marty Broccoli, an agricultural economic developer for Oneida County, N.Y., estimated that New York State now has only half as many slaughterhouses inspected by the federal Agriculture Department as it did 20 years ago. (Federal inspection allows the sale of meat across state lines and to resellers.) At the same time there are more part-time farmers and back-to-landers raising animals for the booming natural and grass-fed meat market.</p>
        <p>The number of slaughterhouses was suddenly reduced again, by one, on Monday, when a fire destroyed Fresh Farms Beef in Rutland, Vt., which was booked through the fall with orders destined for city restaurants. Farmers and distributors that used Fresh Farms, including Fleisher's, scrambled to find other facilities.</p>
        <p>Steve Krut, executive director of the American Association of Meat Processors, said the shortage of slaughterhouses is a national problem. Over the past five years, 188 slaughterhouses, most of them small, withdrew from federal inspection or closed, leaving fewer than 1,000, Mr. Krut said.</p>
        <p>Even businesses like Niman Ranch, one of the most successful purveyors of naturally raised meats, are stymied. Bill Niman, the founder, lamented that the company might end relationships with small hog farmers in North Carolina because the slaughterhouse it was using cannot work with it anymore.</p>
        <p>Kathleen Harris, who owns Currytown Farm in Montgomery County, N.Y., sold the meat from her animals to chefs in New York until all three slaughterhouses she worked with closed two years ago. So largely with state agricultural development grants she helped start the Northeast Livestock Processing Service, which connects farmers looking for services like organic meat processing with suitable slaughterhouses, and handles details like scheduling.</p>
        <p>Without such services, said Rick Bishop, who is an owner of Mountain Sweet Berry Farm in Sullivan County, N.Y., and was until recently an agricultural extension agent, farmers often sell meat for half what chefs pay, sometimes at conventional meat auctions. (That means a rare bit of luck might get you a great local steak at Key Food.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop has been helping his neighbors by giving their meat a free ride on his vegetable truck to the Union Square Greenmarket, where he hands it off to the chefs who have ordered it. Realizing that this underground railroad of fresh local meat was more of a patch than a fix-it plan, Mr. Bishop applied for federal and state grants and private financing to build a new slaughterhouse in Liberty, N.Y., specializing in boutique meat. It is to open in spring 2007.</p>
        <p>Mario Batali wrote a letter of support for the grants, and Kurt Gutenbrunner, the chef at Wallsé and other restaurants -- and a member by marriage of a family of Austrian butchers -- is an adviser on the project.</p>
        <p>There will be temperature-controlled lockers where chefs can cure and age meat, and equipment to handle the carcasses of larger, more flavorful, heritage breeds, which most slaughterhouses turn away.</p>
        <p>The idea, Mr. Bishop said, was to create a prototype that other counties, even states, can employ. ''Ultimately, the Hudson Valley needs two or three,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the new slaughterhouses would have to meet chefs' fastidious demands, said Jennifer Small, an owner of Flying Pigs Farm in Sushan, N.Y., and a founder of Farm to Chef, a network of two dozen upstate farmers making weekly deliveries of products including fresh and frozen meat. Started with a government grant in 2004, it is now owned by chefs and farmers.</p>
        <p>''A lot of small slaughterhouses are sloppy,'' Ms. Small said. It's not uncommon, distributors say, for porterhouses to come back as hamburger meat or for oxtails to fall off the back of the truck. That is why Ms. Small and Fleisher's covet slaughterhouses like Hilltown Pork, a small family-run operation near Pittsfield, Mass., that works with a longtime country butcher, Ted Johnson.</p>
        <p>Because Fleisher's, like most butcher shops, isn't federally inspected, the Applestones can't butcher meat destined for restaurants. So they work with Mr. Johnson, who took them under his wing when they were learning to butcher, dividing carcasses into manageable cuts, known as subprimals, and giving chefs a crashcourse in butchering at their restaurants.</p>
        <p>''If you want to be a part of this sustainable agriculture and local livestock, you've got to learn how,'' said Dona Abramson, chef of the Bright Food Shop in Chelsea, uneasily carving a four-foot-long shoulder clod into flatiron steaks as Mr. Applestone watched.</p>
        <p>But Patrick Martins, a founder of Heritage Foods USA, which distributes naturally raised Kansas meat, said that having chefs butcher is not the answer. So when he decided this year to add fresh local meat to the line he sells to New York chefs, he joined up with Pat LaFrieda Wholesale Meats in the meatpacking district of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>They're an odd couple. Patrick LaFrieda III, 35, the president, said his father, Pat, who ran the business before him, was never interested in locally grown meat because there was already plenty of great-tasting western prime. ''But some of my customers have been asking about this stuff,'' Mr. LaFrieda said. Mr. Martins has whole carcasses shipped to LaFrieda, where old-school pros, with years of experience giving chefs what they want, go to work.</p>
        <p>Those chefs can be particular. ''They're like, 'We want a French rack with a big eye and a three-inch bone,' '' Mr. Martins said.</p>
        <p>Now that they can get it, he said, ''that's what's going to help local farms.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
