<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIVE QUESTIONS for PATRICK McGURN; The Shareholders at the Barricades</title>
    <meta content="25FIVE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/25/business/25FIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1273478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thomson Financial Securities Data</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Institutional Shareholder Services</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abelson, Reed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGurn, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">international_trade_and_world_market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Weyerhaeuser</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Navistar International Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Gabelli Asset Management Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">International Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DC1339F936A15751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIVE QUESTIONS for PATRICK McGURN; The Shareholders at the Barricades</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REED ABELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abelson, Reed</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patrick McGurn, director for corporate programs at Institutional Shareholder Services, unit of Thomson Financial, answers questions about the big issues in this year's proxy season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the proxy season heats up, shareholders are offering up a dizzying array of proposals. Many will not come to an actual vote, because some companies and investors will reach agreement on the issues, while others could end up the subject of spirited campaigns.</p>
        <p>The proposals range widely. One at AT&amp;T asks the company to review its involvement with a distributor of pornographic material for cable systems. Another, resolved at Navistar International last week,  asked the company to drop its poison-pill antitakeover defense. Shareholders voted nearly three quarters of the outstanding shares in favor of the proposal, filed by Gabelli Asset Management, a mutual fund company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the proxy season heats up, shareholders are offering up a dizzying array of proposals. Many will not come to an actual vote, because some companies and investors will reach agreement on the issues, while others could end up the subject of spirited campaigns.</p>
        <p>The proposals range widely. One at AT&amp;T asks the company to review its involvement with a distributor of pornographic material for cable systems. Another, resolved at Navistar International last week,  asked the company to drop its poison-pill antitakeover defense. Shareholders voted nearly three quarters of the outstanding shares in favor of the proposal, filed by Gabelli Asset Management, a mutual fund company.</p>
        <p>Many of the issues have been raised by shareholders before -- for example, the idea that directors should be elected every year, instead of in staggered classes.</p>
        <p>Patrick McGurn, the director for corporate programs at Institutional Shareholder Services, a unit of Thomson Financial that advises large shareholders on proxy matters, talked last week about what he sees as some likely highlights of the coming year. Institutional Shareholder Services, which this week is holding its annual conference on the proxy season, analyzes proxy votes at nearly 20,000 American and foreign companies each year.</p>
        <p>REED ABELSON</p>
        <p>Q. What are the big issues emerging in this year's proxy season? Any new twists on shareholder proposals?</p>
        <p>A. Issues include boards of directors, executive compensation, broadening into the larger issue of stock options and dilution. I'm also expecting a lot of activity on the social front, from the X-rated proposal at AT&amp;T to genetically modified foods to drug pricing. We're seeing more issues torn from the headlines by social activists.</p>
        <p>On the key governance proposals like repealing classified boards, there are no big twists and turns on those but support seems to be growing for them.</p>
        <p>We're seeing those proposals led by nontraditional activists -- not the public pension funds, not the unions -- but money managers.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you expect this season to be active? And do you expect any proxy battles?</p>
        <p>A. Incredibly so, in fact. The election of directors, for example, is no longer a routine voting event. You'll see scores of companies where there are efforts to withhold votes from candidates.</p>
        <p>As for proxy battles, I'm tracking more than three dozen real or threatened contests. That is very unusual. A handful is more the norm. There is the Weyerhaeuser-Willamette contest, for example, and Carl Icahn going at Visx. As we get closer to the meetings, we're likely to see settlements.</p>
        <p>Q. The unions have become increasingly involved in corporate governance. Are there any specific issues that they are particularly concerned about?</p>
        <p>A. They tend to offer pretty mainstream corporate governance proposals because they like the high voting support for them. They are changing the targets around a lot. The Service Employees International Union is targeting the REIT [real estate investment trust] industry on issues like board independence, classified boards and poison pills. So sectors ignored by mainstream investors can be targets.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there any activity concerning Internet boards? A recent study by Spencer Stuart suggests there is a lack of outsiders and diversity.</p>
        <p>A. If you believe the Spencer Stuart data, Internet boards are more insular, less independent. Companies are going to find that investors are not going to cut them any slack if those companies have substandard governance. We're seeing some proposals at the dot-com companies.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think companies are in for any surprises this season?</p>
        <p>A. The wild card is the reaction to the stock market. I think you're going to see a lot of small investors attending meetings, including employees who have been laid off.</p>
        <p>If some of the meetings early in the season are any indication, we could see some uprisings that are violent in the rhetorical sense. On executive pay, we've seen stories of companies forgiving loans and payouts for failures. You're going to see a lot of anger pour out on this.</p>
        <p>Some labor unions, and the state retirement system in Connecticut, are proposing to use pay-for-performance measures, real ones, to make sure pay is linked to performance. I expect greater support for these proposals. It could be a breakthrough year on that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
