<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Prayer Meetings Irritate a Town</title>
    <meta content="25PRAY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1273386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Milford (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chamberlain, Frances</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D91539F936A15751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Prayer Meetings Irritate a Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCES CHAMBERLAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chamberlain, Frances</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on zoning dispute, now in federal court, centering on family prayer meetings at home of Robert and Mary Murphy, parishioners at St Francis Xavier Catholic Church in New Milford, Conn; neighbors say home and driveway additions are aimed at expanding meetings and parking space; family contends its First Amendment rights are being violated; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Murphy family has been holding weekly prayer meetings in their New Milford home since 1994 with few complaints from their neighbors. Dozens of people often attend, and the street on those Sundays can fill with cars.</p>
        <p>But last year, when the couple began building an addition, along with an expanded driveway, some of their neighbors started to complain to the town, fearful that the couple was going to use the space for expanded meetings and the driveway to park more cars. The dispute is now in federal court in Bridgeport, where the town wants the family to comply with zoning laws and the couple will fight for what their lawyer says are their First Amendment rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Murphy family has been holding weekly prayer meetings in their New Milford home since 1994 with few complaints from their neighbors. Dozens of people often attend, and the street on those Sundays can fill with cars.</p>
        <p>But last year, when the couple began building an addition, along with an expanded driveway, some of their neighbors started to complain to the town, fearful that the couple was going to use the space for expanded meetings and the driveway to park more cars. The dispute is now in federal court in Bridgeport, where the town wants the family to comply with zoning laws and the couple will fight for what their lawyer says are their First Amendment rights.</p>
        <p>''I've had prayer groups in my own home. Lots of families do it,'' said Art Peitler, the mayor of New Milford. ''But when there are routinely 40 to 50 cars, with people, kids wandering off, the neighborhood was dumbfounded.''</p>
        <p>The couple, Robert and Mary Murphy of 25 Jefferson Drive, parishioners at St. Francis Xavier Catholic Church in New Milford, began to hold family prayer meetings at their home after Mr. Murphy became ill with pneumonia, and they eventually expanded them to include friends. Their son, Patrick, also a New Milford resident and the spokesman for his family, said the meetings are on Sundays, from 4:30 to 6:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''My family prays together,'' said Patrick Murphy. ''We say the rosary, but it's not a service, just friends and family.''</p>
        <p>Last summer, several of the neighbors who live in the Jefferson Drive cul-de-sac with the Murphys began to complain at Zoning Commission meetings.</p>
        <p>Carmine Montemurro, who has lived at 21 Jefferson Drive since late 1996, has found the Sunday traffic to be a nuisance.</p>
        <p>''At times, the whole street was lined with cars, both sides,'' he said. ''I've counted 40 cars at one time.</p>
        <p>''There are seven houses on this cul-de-sac, and sometimes the cars are parked beyond the next intersection,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Patrick Murphy said he finds the whole issue to be kind of odd.</p>
        <p>''''They never once called us,'' he said about his neighbors. ''They started to call police about cars parked in the street. The police came six times, but there was no noise issue and no problem with parking.'' The police department said last week that it has never issued tickets related to the meetings.</p>
        <p>The Murphy family started to build an addition onto their house last year.</p>
        <p>''People made assumptions,'' Mr. Murphy said. ''They claimed we were building a church, but we really built an addition that consists of a library, office, master bedroom and workout room. We even invited the zoning office to visit and see. We use our kitchen, family room and porch for prayer meetings.''</p>
        <p>''Without ever coming to us, one neighbor called the Archdiocese of Hartford and told them we were holding Mass here,'' Mr. Murphy added. ''They called the Health Department, fire inspector and building inspector. Then they went to a zoning meeting and wrote a letter to the mayor.</p>
        <p>''Friends of mine who attended the first zoning meeting were floored by the accusations,'' Mr. Murphy said. ''They said people were driving through fences and throwing rocks. What really happened was that a 4-year-old and her friend, playing with pebbles by the driveway, bounced a few stones into a neighbor's yard.''</p>
        <p>Mary Chalupsky of Milford began attending the prayer meetings in 1994. She said she is disturbed by the dispute and said the town is being myopic.</p>
        <p>''We pray for world peace and personal needs,'' she said about the meetings. ''The Catholic church is stocked with different kinds of devotions and prayers, we pray to the Blessed Mother, different novenas, we have music that helps to keep people in a state of prayer, and then, after about two hours, we stop and maybe have coffee together or share some food that others might have brought to share.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peitler, speaking a few days before a settlement hearing was scheduled in the chambers of a Waterbury judge earlier this month, predicted that the issue was probably heading toward a full court decision.</p>
        <p>''It's a pretty classic zoning issue, about what can or cannot take place in a residential area. You can have a church, but it needs a public hearing first,'' he said. ''It's not allowed to have large meetings, but something that a small neighborhood or cul-de-sac can handle.''</p>
        <p>The problem arose, Mayor Peitler said, because the retiring zoning officer had signed off on the building permit. The zoning board, he said, cannot now ask them to remove the structure.</p>
        <p>''The town can take no action regarding the building, just take action at the magnitude of the group and find a place that is suitable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''All the neighbors said they liked the Murphys, who are parishioners at a local Catholic Church,'' Mr. Peitler said. ''But when the building addition and parking lot plans were revealed, neighbors reacted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy said it is not a parking lot. The driveway is being expanded to circle the house to accommodate a handicapped entrance for his father, who has back problems, and for a basketball court, he said. To keep more cars off the street during prayer meetings, he said cars have been parking on the unfinished driveway.</p>
        <p>Once the new addition went up, neighbors began appearing at zoning meetings. In November, Thomas Byrne, the attorney for the Zoning Board, determined that regularly scheduled gatherings of a ''diverse group of people'' are not permitted in the family's residential zone.</p>
        <p>The Zoning Board followed up with a letter of violation, and then Kathy Castagnetta, the zoning enforcement officer, issued a cease-and-desist order in December. The Murphys sued. A few days before Christmas, a federal judge issued a temporary order halting Ms. Castagnetta's ban. At United States District Court in Bridgeport, both sides presented their cases and were ordered to meet with a judge in Waterbury and work on a settlement.</p>
        <p>Judge William Garfinkel officiated at the hearing, attended by lawyers for both sides, the town's zoning enforcement officer, some of the neighbors, and members of the Murphy family.</p>
        <p>Vincent McCarthy of New Milford, a friend of the Murphys and senior counsel for the American Center for Law and Justice, a Virginia-based organization that defends religious-rights cases, represents the family. He said the settlement hearings resulted in no deal, ''not even close.''</p>
        <p>''The mayor seems to be the force behind this,'' Mr. McCarthy said. ''We threatened to sue the mayor because he was going to deny the driveway permit when we already had it. We argued, and we have made offers to the town.''</p>
        <p>''Judge Holly Fitzsimmons in Bridgeport will now make a decision based on briefs,'' Mr. McCarthy said. ''She will probably render a decision within the next 60 days.'</p>
        <p>''I see this as a family that wants to have prayer with friends,'' he said. ''The only question is if people in residential areas can have prayer meetings. I think this violates their First Amendment rights and I feel confident about the outcome.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peitler said the meetings should be held somewhere else.</p>
        <p>''What started there has simply outgrown the setting,'' he said. ''It should be continued in a more suitable place, not continued on one acre.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
