<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Power to Choose Is Here, But Few Have Made a Move</title>
    <meta content="25ELEC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1273363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DA1439F936A15751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Power to Choose Is Here, But Few Have Made a Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, Robert A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on small number of Connecticut residents who have other energy company other than Connecticut Light and Power or United Illuminating since industry was deregulated in 1999; about 25 percent of customers who have switzhed have chosen so-called 'green' option offered by energy cooperative; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOEL N. GORDES of Colebrook still has a copy of a letter he wrote to a state newspaper in 1981 about the need to break up the electric utility monopoly in Connecticut. So last year, when the Connecticut Energy Cooperative began offering consumers their first choice in many decades about where to buy electricity, he signed up.</p>
        <p>''I've waited almost 20 years to do this, so I was more than pleased to be one of the first to sign up,'' Mr. Gordes said. ''It took long enough.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOEL N. GORDES of Colebrook still has a copy of a letter he wrote to a state newspaper in 1981 about the need to break up the electric utility monopoly in Connecticut. So last year, when the Connecticut Energy Cooperative began offering consumers their first choice in many decades about where to buy electricity, he signed up.</p>
        <p>''I've waited almost 20 years to do this, so I was more than pleased to be one of the first to sign up,'' Mr. Gordes said. ''It took long enough.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes also chose to sign up for a program in which the cooperative sells power that is generated by wind, water, or methane recovered from closed landfills, even though it cost him slightly more than if he had stayed with his current power provider, Connecticut Light and Power.</p>
        <p>''I went with the green option because I believe in it, and because I think over time it will be the more stable of the options,'' Mr. Gordes said.</p>
        <p>In the first year that Connecticut consumers have had a choice about where they buy power, about 1,100 have followed Mr. Gordes's example and chosen an energy company other than Connecticut Light and Power or, in the New Haven area, United Illuminating. About 25 percent of those customers who have switched have chosen the so-called ''green'' option with the cooperative, said Beryl M. Lyons, a spokeswoman for the State Department of Public Utility Control.</p>
        <p>''It's taking off slowly, but that's O.K.,'' Ms. Lyons said. ''The pace is about what we anticipated. It's tough to make a change to a brave new world, but it does seem to be moving.''</p>
        <p>The reason the pace has been slow is because when the state deregulated the industry in 1999, the law forced Connecticut Light and Power and United Illuminating to sell power at artificially low prices to residential users. The price, 5.5 cents per kilowatt hour at C.L.&amp;P. and 5 cents at United Illuminating, is so low that few companies said they can make money at that level. There is more profit selling to businesses.</p>
        <p>So, of the 21 companies that have been licensed to sell power in the state, most are concentrating on the commercial or industrial market and only three -- the cooperative, ABCD Electric in Bridgeport, and Green Mountain Power of Austin, Tex. -- have begun targeting residential consumers. The Connecticut Energy Cooperative, for example, charges 5.25 cents per kilowatt hour, with the price guaranteed through November (it can go up or down after that).</p>
        <p>All this is going to change on Jan. 1, 2004, when Connecticut has its second power revolution. That's when rates are expected to go up, not down. The state's rate cap will be lifted on that date and while more companies will be selling power in the state, and competition will increase, few officials said they believed any will be able to afford to consistently sell it for the low rates that consumers have now.</p>
        <p>''The price that we set guarantees losses for any newcomer who might be interested in selling electricity,'' said State Representative Demetrios S. Giannaros, a Democrat of Farmington and co-chairman of the State Legislature's Energy Committee. ''The problem is not today or tomorrow, the problem is what's going to happen on Jan. 1, 2004, when all price controls are lifted. If you don't have a competitive market by then, it's too late. We've seen all around the world huge price spikes when you deregulate and all you have in place is a regulated monopoly.''</p>
        <p>So consumers, who are already facing higher natural gas bills, may be in for a shock in a few years. Already, the power shortages in California are making consumers here nervous about deregulation, but while Connecticut may have problems of its own, it doesn't share California's.</p>
        <p>California power companies were prohibited from signing long-term contracts with electricity providers, because regulators saw it as increasing the costs. That has resulted in an uncertain supply. In Connecticut, regulators required long-term contracts, which stabilized prices and supplies.</p>
        <p>California also has not built any significant new sources of power in a decade because of zoning and environmental restrictions; Connecticut has a peak load of about 6,385 megawatts, and the capacity to produce 6,682 megawatts of power.</p>
        <p>''Except for the years that the Millstone nuclear plants were down, we've always been a net exporter of energy,'' Ms. Lyons said. ''And we have the ability to import as much as 2,000 megawatts of power from around the region.</p>
        <p>''I think in great measure, the situation in California has had a significant impact on whether people are willing to change suppliers in Connecticut,'' Ms. Lyons said. ''California keeps making the news, but in Pennsylvania restructuring is working out very well, and they have an adequate supply.''</p>
        <p>Guy R. Mazza, the state consumer counsel who supported deregulation, said just getting consumers to realize that they can change the company that provides electricity to their televisions and computers will take some time.</p>
        <p>''It's a change in the way that power is provided, and its not as easy a change for people to grasp as, say, the change we had in telecommunications, but I think it will eventually provide some benefit for consumers,'' Mr. Mazza said. ''A lot of people are going to wait until the last minute, but people are starting to switch, and I think as time goes by more people will realize they have a choice.''</p>
        <p>Frank J. Poirot, a spokesman for Northeast Utilities, the parent company of Connecticut Light and Power, said losing 1,100 of the company's 1.1 million customers has not had a noticeable impact on revenues. But he said even if a majority of customers switch, the company is going to survive, because deregulation has separated power sales from the transmission and distribution of power, which is C.L.&amp;P.'s business now. It sells electricity through Select Energy, its unregulated subsidiary.</p>
        <p>''We're an energy delivery company, and that will be a revenue stream that we always have as long as we have the power lines,'' Mr. Poirot said. ''And the state has pretty strict laws regarding transmission and distribution lines, to avoid what Connecticut and most other states experienced in the early days, which was parallel lines belonging to competing companies. In the early 1900's, legislators saw what a mess that could be so they passed laws that say only one company at a time can provide that service.''</p>
        <p>Under the energy deregulation plan adopted by the state, which went into effect in January 1999, Connecticut Light and Power must sell electricity at a price that is effectively 10 percent below its 1995 rates -- the ''standard offer'' in regulatory parlance -- until Jan. 1, 2004, at which point all restrictions will be lifted. The company's transmission and distribution charges and other costs make up about two-thirds of a consumer's monthly electric bill. Competition affects the other one-third, the generation component.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mazza, the consumer counsel, said he is not convinced that having a few companies offer electricity alternatives is what the legislature intended to accomplish with deregulation.</p>
        <p>''We definitely would like to see more companies come in,'' Mr. Mazza said. ''I wouldn't consider this to be a vibrant, competitive market right now, in particular for residential consumers. What you want to see is enough companies so that no one single one can exert market power.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mazza said the reason more companies aren't entering the Connecticut market is that the generation component of the electric price set in the standard offer is too low. Currently, it is 5.5 cents per kilowatt hour in the Connecticut Light and Power rate structure, which is the price that any other company coming in must beat; wholesale prices now are about 7 cents per kilowatt hour.</p>
        <p>He said Connecticut Light and Power is making a profit now, so there are ways of changing the calculations without raising the price people pay for power now. For instance, adjusting the transmission and distribution charge down the same amount as the generation charge goes up; the net effect on consumers would be zero, but alternative power companies would have more incentive to come in. Northeast Utilities' sale of the Millstone nuclear power plants in Waterford is expected to net the company $500 million, money that could also be used to reduce consumer bills, he said.</p>
        <p>Stephen J. Fabiani, vice president of Northeast's Select Energy subsidiary, said his company is marketing natural gas and electricity to large commercial and industrial users, but it is not targeting residential customers because the profit margins are so slim.</p>
        <p>''If the markets were really deregulated today, the price would initially be higher,'' Mr. Fabiani said. ''The standard offer is such a great deal because it's artificially low.''</p>
        <p>Robert A. Maddox, director of marketing for the Connecticut Energy Cooperative, said while competition is taking off slowly, he expected it will soon begin to gather momentum, particularly as smaller providers offer customers package deals. He expects the cooperative could ultimately capture about 10 percent of the market because of the convenience.</p>
        <p>''We can offer them electricity, fuel oil, natural gas, propane, and long distance telephone services,'' Mr. Maddox said. How about the Internet? ''It's coming, along with wireless phones, maybe home security systems, and so on.'' The problem is going to come on Dec. 31, 2003, when everyone realizes their bills are going to go up, and they start casting about for choices.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lyons of the public utilities control office said regulators are convinced that as the process moves forward, more people will look at their options, and there is still almost three years before the complete end of regulation.</p>
        <p>''Until they started getting solicited by the competitors, it may not hit people that they have a choice, but I think as you see more and more advertisements, people are going to look into it,'' Ms. Lyons said. ''If people know they have a choice and still sit back and wait a little longer, that's O.K. We would certainly urge people not to wait until the last minute, but they don't all have to all rush out and do it tomorrow.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
