<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRO BASKETBALL: N.B.A. Analysis; Knicks Are Shown How to Play in a Big Game</title>
    <meta content="03KNIC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/03/sports/basketball/03KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1571357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A. Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D91039F930A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRO BASKETBALL: N.B.A. Analysis; Knicks Are Shown How to Play in a Big Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nets-Knicks Series Could Be One-Sided Affair</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chris Broussard NBA Analysis contends that unlike New Jersey Nets, New York Knicks do not know how to win big games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fantasizing should stop: the thoughts of special postseason happenings at Madison Square Garden, the dreams of an upset victory over the defending Eastern Conference champion Nets in the first round.</p>
        <p>Friday night's Knicks debacle at Continental Arena proved that with or without Jason Kidd and Kenyon Martin, the Nets have one major series-turning advantage over the Knicks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On paper, Nets-Knicks would be a first-round playoff matchup to die for. But would it be competitive, as competitive as a glance at the teams lineups suggest?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fantasizing should stop: the thoughts of special postseason happenings at Madison Square Garden, the dreams of an upset victory over the defending Eastern Conference champion Nets in the first round.</p>
        <p>Friday night's Knicks debacle at Continental Arena proved that with or without Jason Kidd and Kenyon Martin, the Nets have one major series-turning advantage over the Knicks.</p>
        <p>They know how to win.</p>
        <p>Do the Knicks?</p>
        <p>Here's a hint: Nets 108, Knicks 83.</p>
        <p>While the Knicks spent the last few years laying on beaches during May, the Nets were outlasting Reggie Miller, Gary Payton and Paul Pierce in the playoffs, and learning in defeat against the Los Angeles Lakers and the San Antonio Spurs.</p>
        <p>Penny Hardaway, who helped Orlando reach the N.B.A. finals in 1995, knows how important those playoff experiences were to the Nets. And he knows how little understanding his Knicks teammates have when it comes to winning big games.</p>
        <p>''A lot of guys are not used to this situation,'' Hardaway said, trying to explain the Knicks' horrible showing under must-win circumstances. ''You have a few guys that have been to the finals, myself and Shandon Anderson, that have gone far in the playoffs. So you've got a lot of guys without a lot of experience on this team, even though we have a very good team. So you might put more pressure on yourself than normal and not be able to play your game. It's tough.''</p>
        <p>He described the problem the Knicks are facing this way: ''You can put so much pressure on yourself that you're playing so uptight that you're trying not to make a mistake and you're just making mistakes over and over again.''</p>
        <p>In other words, when games and playoff spots are on the line, the Knicks are cringing, and they allowed the Nets, who were without their top two players, to shoot 60 percent from the floor Friday night.</p>
        <p>While the Knicks were having anxiety attacks, the Nets, even when hampered by injuries, were sticking out their chests and strutting. That attitude alone would carry them past the Knicks in the metropolitan area's ideal first-round matchup, especially if Kidd and Martin are healthy.</p>
        <p>''They've been in the trenches,'' Hardaway said. ''They've been through the entire Eastern Conference two years in a row.</p>
        <p>''When times get tough, they just keep running their offense and know that eventually they'll break out of it. They don't fear anything.''</p>
        <p>Friday night, the Knicks seemed to fear contact. Instead of putting a body on the Nets in the lane, they stepped aside and watched them make layup after layup. Committing the cardinal sin against the Nets, the Knicks failed to get back on defense, allowing a transition game led by Lucious Harris to score 23 points, 11 more than the Nets have averaged this season without Kidd.</p>
        <p>The Knicks gave up more layups and dunks Friday night than a good defensive team does in a week's worth of games. Jefferson put Kurt Thomas on a poster with a monstrous windmill slam, Harris sauntered through the heart of the Knicks' defense for an uncontested finger roll and, on one possession, Jason Collins grabbed three offensive rebounds in a row over Nazr Mohammed.</p>
        <p>Late in the third quarter, after Tim Thomas scored on what could have been a momentum-turning transition layup, the Knicks allowed Richard Jefferson to convert a 3-point play three seconds later.</p>
        <p>The way to beat the Nets is to stop their transition game and make them play halfcourt basketball. It is hard to imagine the Knicks, who played such soft defense Friday night, dictating tempo in a series against the Nets.</p>
        <p>''Our defense was the worst I've seen in a long time,'' Knicks Coach Lenny Wilkens said. ''Our defense was horrendous. Of course it concerns me because this was a game that we needed and now we've got to make it up somewhere.''</p>
        <p>What the Knicks cannot make up for is their lack of know-how when it comes to pulling off victories. Allan Houston, Hardaway, Anderson, Kurt Thomas and Dikembe Mutombo have reached the N.B.A. finals. But Mutombo and Houston are hurt, and Anderson, Kurt Thomas and Hardaway are role players.</p>
        <p>Stephon Marbury has not experienced playoff success, and Tim Thomas played poorly for the Bucks last year in the final two games of the Nets' four games-to-two series victory in the first round. Vin Baker played his best ball for losing teams, and Mohammed has spent the past two years in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>One would think the Nets would be the team looking ahead, obsessed with the postseason, but the Knicks might have been the ones with improper focus Friday night.</p>
        <p>''They shouldn't have been,'' Wilkens said, when asked if his team was thinking ahead to the playoffs. ''You can't get caught up in that. Really, they shouldn't. Now if they did, that was a mistake. Hey, we're not in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks, tied for seventh place, are still on track to meet the Nets in the first round. Hardaway, despite knowing what he knows, said the Knicks will not concede defeat should they face off against the Nets. He hopes they learned Friday night what the Nets spent two postseasons learning.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, this type of whipping will make us mad enough to want to come back and redeem ourselves if we do meet,'' Hardaway said.</p>
        <p>Deep down inside, he probably knows better.</p>
        <p>N.B.A. Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
