<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who's the Man? Dave</title>
    <meta content="03davez" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/03/fashion/03davez.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060910T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1787315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Men's Health (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinczenko, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinetz, Erika</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Men, Love &amp; Sex: The Complete User's Guide (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Zinczenko, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D61E3EF930A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who's the Man? Dave</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who’s the Man? Dave</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIKA KINETZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinetz, Erika</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of David Zinczenko, editor in chief of Men's Health magazine, who has made career out of doling out advice to men about their guts, their athletic prowess and their health; is now sharing his insights with women in book Men, Love &amp; Sex: The Complete User's Guide for Women; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID ZINCZENKO is making his 17th appearance on the ''Today'' show, this time opposite Steve Schirripa -- who plays Bobby Bacala on ''The Sopranos'' -- on the subject of ''heavy men.'' Heavy as in large, overweight and lacking any evidence of abs, quads or tone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko, the editor-in-chief of Men's Health, is an expert on this topic, having written the 2004 best-seller ''The Abs Diet.'' He is trim, a welter to Mr. Schirripa's big heavy, and today he is dressed in a gray Prada suit and open-collar white shirt, with his hair carefully brushed to frame a face that might be described as ''handsome middle brother.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An editor uses the male viewpoint to build a franchise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID ZINCZENKO is making his 17th appearance on the ''Today'' show, this time opposite Steve Schirripa -- who plays Bobby Bacala on ''The Sopranos'' -- on the subject of ''heavy men.'' Heavy as in large, overweight and lacking any evidence of abs, quads or tone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko, the editor-in-chief of Men's Health, is an expert on this topic, having written the 2004 best-seller ''The Abs Diet.'' He is trim, a welter to Mr. Schirripa's big heavy, and today he is dressed in a gray Prada suit and open-collar white shirt, with his hair carefully brushed to frame a face that might be described as ''handsome middle brother.''</p>
        <p>He is sharing with Al Roker and Lester Holt the current wisdom that a little man flab may be a fine accessory for fall -- but, guys, you don't want to throw away those gym memberships.</p>
        <p>''Metrosexuality is dead,'' he declares. ''And good riddance to it. But let's be clear here: The trend is a tough calzone to swallow.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko (pronounced zinn-ZENK-oh) has made a career out of doling out advice to men, helping them muddle through their post-metrosexual worries about their guts, their athletic prowess and their health.</p>
        <p>His prime vehicle is Men's Health, a magazine with a circulation of almost 1.8 million -- up by more than 100,000 from when he took over in 2000 -- that has won readers and awards for its well-researched articles about men's lives.</p>
        <p>From that success has come the appearances on the ''Today'' show, where he is frequently trotted out (19 times and counting) as the spokesman for Everyman, combining cheerful quotability with extensive data culled in the interest of getting to know ''Him.''</p>
        <p>Now he is extending that franchise to women -- far more receptive to such information and more likely to buy books -- and sharing some of his insights in ''Men, Love &amp; Sex: The Complete User's Guide for Women.'' The book, which will be out this week, is full of pithy assessments about what men really want, such as:</p>
        <p>''What's the formula for what a man wants in a long-term relationship? How's this? Love us like you've know us for years; surprise us like you've known us for days.''</p>
        <p>And this: ''One unexpected naked strut: Priceless.''</p>
        <p>And: ''Say this: 'Let's slow down. I want to enjoy every single second.' Not: 'I need more foreplay.' ''</p>
        <p>''I've spent more than a decade channeling information for and about men,'' Mr. Zinczenko, 36, said in his ninth-floor office on Manhattan's East Side, not to far from the office yoga studio. ''I'm able to come and use this information, with the help of the research, to hand over the keys to the kingdom to women.''</p>
        <p>And why not? Women have Oprah, Candace Bushnell, Naomi Wolf. Who will speak for men?</p>
        <p>Dave will.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko's three-year relationship with an actress, Rose McGowan, made him a boldface name around New York. The couple has since parted but Mr. Zinczenko maintains a medium-high profile.</p>
        <p>''David himself has become a bit of a celebrity, and I don't mean that in a negative sense,'' said Martin Walker, a magazine consultant and the chairman of Walker Communications. ''He's identified with the magazine more so than the editors of any of the competitive books. He's on the 'Today' show with frequency, which creates buzz about the magazine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko balks at the celebrity label. ''I'm totally against the idea of a celebrity editor,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''If you asked 30 people walking down the street, 'Who is David Zinczenko?' no one would have any idea. I'm more than happy to make it about. '' He paused for the words to describe where the spotlight should shine. ''I'm trying to find something better to call it than 'the product.' ''</p>
        <p>But these days, the product and Mr. Zinczenko are nearly welded together. ''Dave is not the only editor-in-chief of a magazine who's not a particularly gifted line editor or copy editor or structural editor,'' said Denis Boyles, who worked at the magazine as an editor at large under Mr. Zinczenko's predecessors, Mike Lafavore and Greg Gutfeld.</p>
        <p>''What Dave is great at doing is what they have him doing,'' he said. ''Being that regular guy who represents the brand for all guys. He's as regular as you can get without being made of fiber.''</p>
        <p>As an interpreter of men for women, Mr. Zinczenko is far more optimistic than the Women-Are-From-Venus, Men-Are-From-Mars set. And if a guy is Just Not That Into You, Mr. Zinczenko is there to help.</p>
        <p>''You see, the truth is that men do share their feelings -- their fears, their desire, even their deepest secrets,'' he writes in ''Men, Love &amp; Sex'' (written with Ted Spiker). ''They've shared those feelings with me. And now I'm here to share their feelings with you.''</p>
        <p>Like Men's Health, the new book is less a thing of passion than of science. ''Men, Love &amp; Sex'' was based on a survey of 5,000 men and women, and its raw material -- sheaves of survey results -- is stacked in an unruly pile on the floor behind Mr. Zinczenko's desk.</p>
        <p>It is the research, Mr. Zinczenko says, that makes him different from other lifestyle and relationship authorities hawking their views on television and in print.</p>
        <p>''I've never suffered multiple concussions,'' he said. ''I've never had diabetes. I haven't contracted avian flu. But I'm still able to edit a magazine that covers those topics because the magazine and the staff, the team, draws on the best doctors and researchers and experts to support everything that appears in the magazine.</p>
        <p>''I brought that same approach to 'The Abs Diet' and to this book,'' he said. ''The last thing I'm interested in is subjecting readers to some riff based on my personal experience alone.''</p>
        <p>THE research credo has helped Men's Health speak with authority on what's on the minds of guys who don't care about celebrities and who think high fashion is a clean shirt.</p>
        <p>Since its debut in the late 1980's, the magazine has surpassed traditional men's books like Esquire and GQ by following the formula of best-selling women's magazines -- by catering to men's anxieties about their bodies and sexual performance. Cover headlines meant to grab a newsstand buyer by the throat -- which Mr. Zinczenko once described as ''mugging'' the passer-by -- are sometimes written before the articles.</p>
        <p>The latest cover promises, like many before it: ''More Sex, Better Sex'' and ''The Easy Way to Hard Abs!''</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Zinczenko, Men's Health won its first National Magazine Award (for personal service) in 2004, and was a finalist in three categories this year. Its cover price was raised to $4.50 in March, but it still trumps its rivals at the newsstand. And its overall circulation is higher than that of GQ, Details, Esquire, Men's Fitness, Men's Journal, FHM and Stuff.</p>
        <p>The magazine has drawn a growing number of luxury brands to its ad pages, including Canali, Porsche and Jaguar, though in the first seven months of this year it had 15 percent fewer ad pages than in the same period last year. Executives at Rodale, which publishes Men's Health, attribute the fall-off to the company's vulnerability to the slumping auto industry (Rodale does not accept advertising from tobacco or liquor companies).</p>
        <p>People who have worked with Mr. Zinczenko say he is smart and ambitious. Mr. Boyles also calls him transparent: ''You can almost see the wheels turning.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafavore, one of the founding editors of Men's Health, said: ''What he lacks in ability, he makes up for in charm.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko responded: ''I worked with these guys a long time ago. I know for sure the magazine has come a long way since the last millennium, and I like to think I have, too.''</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Zinczenko is testing his own knowledge about men and women in the dating world. ''I want to marry and have kids,'' he said. ''The things we all want.''</p>
        <p>His relationship with Ms. McGowan, who played Paige Matthews on the WB television series ''Charmed,'' ended a year and a half ago.</p>
        <p>''He's a guy's guy,'' Ms. McGowan said in an e-mail message. ''An overused term, but true nonetheless.''</p>
        <p>''When I met him, he was using Irish Spring to wash his face,'' she wrote. ''I'll admit to being pleasantly surprised.''</p>
        <p>She went on: ''He's amazingly well mannered, and it's not an act. David would be just as happy to talk to the guy who runs his parking garage as he would be speaking to an executive.''</p>
        <p>Dan Abrams, the new general manager of MSNBC, who shares a summer house with Mr. Zinczenko in Southampton, also called him a ''guy's guy.'' Healthy, too. ''He goes running a lot,'' Mr. Abrams said. ''Any time he eats something in the house, he looks at the calories on the back.''</p>
        <p>It was not always so.</p>
        <p>He was a fat child. ''My older brother would invite his friends over to spy on me while I ate lunch,'' Mr. Zinczenko wrote in Men's Health four years ago. '' 'Don't disturb the big animal,' he'd tell them. 'It's feeding.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko, who grew up in Bethlehem, Pa., and now lives in the West Village, said his parents divorced when he was 6. His mother, Janice Sobieski, was a ''typical single mom, working three jobs to make ends meet,'' he said. His father, who smoked, ate too much and exercised too little, died of a stroke at 52. (Mr. Zinczenko was having lunch with Art Cooper, the former GQ editor, at the Four Seasons in 2003 when Mr. Cooper suffered a stroke and died. It is a memory that Mr. Zinczenko recalls with tears in his eyes, explaining that it conjured memories of his father's death.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko entered the military after high school, serving in the Naval Reserve while he attended Moravian College in Bethlehem. After graduating from college, he parlayed a few opinion articles published in The Los Angeles Times into a job as an assistant editor at Men's Journal as it was starting up. In 1993, he accepted an offer to become an associate editor at Men's Health, and he was soon in charge of creating international editions of the magazine. He became editor-in-chief in 2000, at age 30.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zinczenko declined to reveal his salary, saying it is proprietary information of Rodale, a private company. Rodale seems pleased with its editor and his fusion with the brand. ''I don't think there's a reader of Men's Health who picks it up and does not feel they have a bit of a relationship to Dave through the magazine,'' said Steve Murphy, the chief executive of Rodale. ''That's good. It makes it real.''</p>
        <p>Before his appearance on the ''Today'' show with Mr. Schirripa, Mr. Zinczenko downed a glass of skim milk. Plenty of carbs and protein, he noted. Drink six ounces daily and you could reduce stroke risk by 50 percent, according to the September issue of Men's Health.</p>
        <p>It was raining, and after the 8:10 a.m. segment, Mr. Schirripa and Mr. Zinczenko splashed down the steps from the set. ''Steve,'' people called out from the crowd, and Mr. Schirripa held up the meat of his palm in a practiced wave.</p>
        <p>No one called for David. He had the Prada suit, the affable jokes, the informed preparation, the skim milk -- but Mr. Schirripa got the love. Mr. Zinczenko went back to the office, back to the numbers, back to the team.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 10, 2006, Sunday  An article last Sunday about Dave Zinczenko, the editor-in-chief of Men's Health who has built a franchise based on men's viewpoints, referred incorrectly to the rise in circulation from July 2000, when he took over, through the first half of 2006. According to the Audit Bureau of Circulation, the average paid monthly circulation has increased 226,000 to 1,856,000 from 1,630,000. The increase was not ''more than 100,000,'' which was the rise in average monthly circulation for the full years 2000 through 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 10, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about Dave Zinczenko, the editor-in-chief of Men's Health who has built a franchise based on men's viewpoints, referred incorrectly to the rise in circulation from July 2000, when he took over, through the first half of 2006. According to the Audit Bureau of Circulation, the average paid monthly circulation has increased 226,000 to 1,856,000 from 1,630,000. The increase was not ''more than 100,000,'' which was the rise in average monthly circulation for the full years 2000 through 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
