<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Beach, Fla.</title>
    <meta content="30Hours" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1787496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="36 HOURS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/36 Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D61F31F930A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Beach, Fla.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flash, a bounty of tanned skin and music where the Cuban roots are never far away: Hmm, sounds like South Beach, that hot southern tip of Miami Beach, Fla., where the party never ends and where the crowd ranges from hipsters holding court at the Raleigh Hotel pool to young families taking a leisurely bike ride along the beach promenade.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  1) TRANSCENDING TRENDS  Dip your (hopefully well-manicured) toes into the South Beach scene on Lincoln Road, the pedestrian shopping and dining street where everyone struts on weekend nights. In a town of fleeting trends and fickle tastes, this place stays popular, perhaps because it embraces all kinds of people. Check out the performance artist in platform shoes who sashays to hits from the 70's and 80's, the old guy who wears a large albino snake around his neck and the parade of the surgically enhanced. Then grab a table at Ice Box Cafe (1657 Michigan Avenue, 305-538-8448; www.iceboxcafe.com), just around the corner, where you can keep one eye on the decadent multitudes and the other on a display of decadent desserts. A local favorite, the Ice Box has what many Miami restaurants lack: creativity without over-the-top embellishment.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  2) DRINK ME  Move on down Lincoln Road to flashy Collins Avenue, hook a left and hit the Delano (1685 Collins Avenue, 305-672-2000; www.delano-hotel.com) for an essential Miami Beach experience. Yes, it has become a cliché, but an ever-elegant one, with at least as much oomph as newcomers like the Setai and the Victor. Enter with a flourish past the gauzy white curtains and Alice in Wonderland couches, head back to the palm-lined pool and order mojitos at the bar. If you are feeling profligate, choose an $18 glass of Champagne and drink it in the pool, at a candelabrum-topped table perched at the shallow, shallow (4 inches or so) end.</p>
        <p>Saturday  9 a.m.  3) WALKING ON SUNSHINE  Roll out of bed, put on large sunglasses and get yourself to South Pointe Park, a grassy expanse and promenade at the tip of South Beach that has become a town square of sorts. Gaze down Government Cut, the channel between the Atlantic and the Port of Miami, toward the fast-changing downtown skyline. After your stroll, stop in at Big Pink (157 Collins Avenue, 305-532-4700; www.bigpinkrestaurant.com), a nearby diner that has portions that would make any South Beach diet doctor shudder.</p>
        <p>11 a.m.  4) NOT QUITE THE SMITHSONIAN  Lose yourself in Miami's chic museum of miscellany, the Wolfsonian (1001 Washington Avenue, 305-531-1001; www.wolfsonian.org). This place is packed with artifacts that focus on the history of design from 1885 to 1945. Mitchell Wolfson Jr., an eccentric heir to a movie theater fortune and an obsessive collector, opened it in 1995 after acquiring mountains of quirky objects on his world travels. The collection of political propaganda -- not just posters but everyday items like a bomb-shaped cigarette lighter -- will jolt your sun-dazed brain.</p>
        <p>2 p.m.  5) SAND BETWEEN YOUR TOES  At last, it's time to hit the beach. There are plenty to choose from, all with their own take on life next to the Atlantic. In South Beach, along Ocean Drive, you'll see tourists in rented lounge chairs and the late-night party crowd -- multi-ethnic, barely clothed and sunbathing away a collective hangover. And the Art Deco lifeguard stands are always worth a look. Farther north, Orthodox Jewish couples like to stroll the boardwalk between 21st and 46th Streets; it's also the perfect spot for a morning jog. Haulover Park Beach, above Bal Harbour, draws local families with barbecue grills and kites, though its northern end is for nudists. If you're seeking solitude, try Bill Baggs Cape Florida State Park on Key Biscayne: it's secluded, with a historic lighthouse and ample dunes.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  6) LATINO FARE IN CORAL GABLES  Wander over to the lushly landscaped city of Coral Gables, which has its own thriving night life and a number of up-and-coming restaurants, including many that specialize in Argentine, Peruvian and other Latin American cuisine. At Cacao (141 Giralda Avenue, 305-445-1001; www.cacaorestaurant.com), the Venezuelan chef, Edgar Leal, puts a whimsical spin on traditional Latin fare. The dining room is elegant and softly lit, and the wine list, full of South American choices, is strong.</p>
        <p>11 p.m.  7) FUSION BY WAY OF FUNK  Back in South Beach, Saturday night is revving into high gear. You could hit the hotel bar scene or nightclub of the month, but brace yourself for obnoxious cocktail prices -- and attitudes. A refreshing alternative -- and one of the only spots to hear local bands -- is Jazid (1342 Washington Avenue, 305-673-9372; www.jazid.net), an intimate club on scrappy Washington Avenue. The dance floor gets hopping when one of the club's regular acts, Suénalo, plays its addictive fusion of Cuban son and rumba, Dominican hip-hop, Colombian cumbia and American funk.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  8) Paddle, Paddle, Splash!  The sun is dazzling, the sky uncommonly blue and the water -- everywhere you look -- beckons once more. This time, try kayaking in Biscayne Bay, on the western side of Miami Beach. At South Beach Kayak (1771 Purdy Avenue, 305-332-2853), you can rent a kayak and then paddle to Star and Hibiscus Islands, getting the best view in town of Shaquille O'Neal's house and other palatial (some say tacky) residences. This is also a fine way to study Miami's downtown skyline without having to dodge local drivers, though maniacs on water scooters pose their own challenges. You might also check out Monument Island, where a soaring but shabby obelisk stands in tribute to Henry Flagler, the oil baron who built a railroad to Miami in 1896, when it was still a swampy outpost.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  9) MEET ME AT THE BILTMORE  Assuming you've had enough views of the water, you won't regret returning to Coral Gables for the elaborate brunch at the Biltmore Hotel (1200 Anastasia Avenue; 305-445-1926; www.biltmorehotel.com). This Sunday extravagance is served in a Mediterranean-style courtyard where a fountain murmurs as a band slinks through ''Boy From Ipanema.'' It's where local families come for birthdays, anniversaries and other excuses to indulge. If you can move afterward, stroll through the hotel, built in 1926 and modeled after a tower in Spain. Then call it a weekend, and groan your way to the airport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flash, a bounty of tanned skin and music where the Cuban roots are never far away: Hmm, sounds like South Beach, that hot southern tip of Miami Beach, Fla., where the party never ends and where the crowd ranges from hipsters holding court at the Raleigh Hotel pool to young families taking a leisurely bike ride along the beach promenade.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  1) TRANSCENDING TRENDS  Dip your (hopefully well-manicured) toes into the South Beach scene on Lincoln Road, the pedestrian shopping and dining street where everyone struts on weekend nights. In a town of fleeting trends and fickle tastes, this place stays popular, perhaps because it embraces all kinds of people. Check out the performance artist in platform shoes who sashays to hits from the 70's and 80's, the old guy who wears a large albino snake around his neck and the parade of the surgically enhanced. Then grab a table at Ice Box Cafe (1657 Michigan Avenue, 305-538-8448; www.iceboxcafe.com), just around the corner, where you can keep one eye on the decadent multitudes and the other on a display of decadent desserts. A local favorite, the Ice Box has what many Miami restaurants lack: creativity without over-the-top embellishment.</p>
        <p>10:30 p.m.  2) DRINK ME  Move on down Lincoln Road to flashy Collins Avenue, hook a left and hit the Delano (1685 Collins Avenue, 305-672-2000; www.delano-hotel.com) for an essential Miami Beach experience. Yes, it has become a cliché, but an ever-elegant one, with at least as much oomph as newcomers like the Setai and the Victor. Enter with a flourish past the gauzy white curtains and Alice in Wonderland couches, head back to the palm-lined pool and order mojitos at the bar. If you are feeling profligate, choose an $18 glass of Champagne and drink it in the pool, at a candelabrum-topped table perched at the shallow, shallow (4 inches or so) end.</p>
        <p>Saturday  9 a.m.  3) WALKING ON SUNSHINE  Roll out of bed, put on large sunglasses and get yourself to South Pointe Park, a grassy expanse and promenade at the tip of South Beach that has become a town square of sorts. Gaze down Government Cut, the channel between the Atlantic and the Port of Miami, toward the fast-changing downtown skyline. After your stroll, stop in at Big Pink (157 Collins Avenue, 305-532-4700; www.bigpinkrestaurant.com), a nearby diner that has portions that would make any South Beach diet doctor shudder.</p>
        <p>11 a.m.  4) NOT QUITE THE SMITHSONIAN  Lose yourself in Miami's chic museum of miscellany, the Wolfsonian (1001 Washington Avenue, 305-531-1001; www.wolfsonian.org). This place is packed with artifacts that focus on the history of design from 1885 to 1945. Mitchell Wolfson Jr., an eccentric heir to a movie theater fortune and an obsessive collector, opened it in 1995 after acquiring mountains of quirky objects on his world travels. The collection of political propaganda -- not just posters but everyday items like a bomb-shaped cigarette lighter -- will jolt your sun-dazed brain.</p>
        <p>2 p.m.  5) SAND BETWEEN YOUR TOES  At last, it's time to hit the beach. There are plenty to choose from, all with their own take on life next to the Atlantic. In South Beach, along Ocean Drive, you'll see tourists in rented lounge chairs and the late-night party crowd -- multi-ethnic, barely clothed and sunbathing away a collective hangover. And the Art Deco lifeguard stands are always worth a look. Farther north, Orthodox Jewish couples like to stroll the boardwalk between 21st and 46th Streets; it's also the perfect spot for a morning jog. Haulover Park Beach, above Bal Harbour, draws local families with barbecue grills and kites, though its northern end is for nudists. If you're seeking solitude, try Bill Baggs Cape Florida State Park on Key Biscayne: it's secluded, with a historic lighthouse and ample dunes.</p>
        <p>8 p.m.  6) LATINO FARE IN CORAL GABLES  Wander over to the lushly landscaped city of Coral Gables, which has its own thriving night life and a number of up-and-coming restaurants, including many that specialize in Argentine, Peruvian and other Latin American cuisine. At Cacao (141 Giralda Avenue, 305-445-1001; www.cacaorestaurant.com), the Venezuelan chef, Edgar Leal, puts a whimsical spin on traditional Latin fare. The dining room is elegant and softly lit, and the wine list, full of South American choices, is strong.</p>
        <p>11 p.m.  7) FUSION BY WAY OF FUNK  Back in South Beach, Saturday night is revving into high gear. You could hit the hotel bar scene or nightclub of the month, but brace yourself for obnoxious cocktail prices -- and attitudes. A refreshing alternative -- and one of the only spots to hear local bands -- is Jazid (1342 Washington Avenue, 305-673-9372; www.jazid.net), an intimate club on scrappy Washington Avenue. The dance floor gets hopping when one of the club's regular acts, Suénalo, plays its addictive fusion of Cuban son and rumba, Dominican hip-hop, Colombian cumbia and American funk.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>10 a.m.  8) Paddle, Paddle, Splash!  The sun is dazzling, the sky uncommonly blue and the water -- everywhere you look -- beckons once more. This time, try kayaking in Biscayne Bay, on the western side of Miami Beach. At South Beach Kayak (1771 Purdy Avenue, 305-332-2853), you can rent a kayak and then paddle to Star and Hibiscus Islands, getting the best view in town of Shaquille O'Neal's house and other palatial (some say tacky) residences. This is also a fine way to study Miami's downtown skyline without having to dodge local drivers, though maniacs on water scooters pose their own challenges. You might also check out Monument Island, where a soaring but shabby obelisk stands in tribute to Henry Flagler, the oil baron who built a railroad to Miami in 1896, when it was still a swampy outpost.</p>
        <p>1 p.m.  9) MEET ME AT THE BILTMORE  Assuming you've had enough views of the water, you won't regret returning to Coral Gables for the elaborate brunch at the Biltmore Hotel (1200 Anastasia Avenue; 305-445-1926; www.biltmorehotel.com). This Sunday extravagance is served in a Mediterranean-style courtyard where a fountain murmurs as a band slinks through ''Boy From Ipanema.'' It's where local families come for birthdays, anniversaries and other excuses to indulge. If you can move afterward, stroll through the hotel, built in 1926 and modeled after a tower in Spain. Then call it a weekend, and groan your way to the airport.  36 HOURS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
