<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Ho-Ho-Kus; A Borough That Guards Its Traditions</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950305T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="741632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HO-HO-KUS (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHESLOW, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DE133DF936A35751C0A963958260" item-length="1792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Ho-Ho-Kus; A Borough That Guards Its Traditions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY CHESLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHESLOW, JERRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it is less than 20 miles from Manhattan and 2 miles from five major shopping malls in neighboring Paramus, the well-maintained 1.8-square-mile borough of Ho-Ho-Kus has changed little in the last 50 years.</p>
        <p>Most of its housing stock is turn-of-the-century or earlier. Its last major housing development, the Cheelcroft section, dates to the Great Depression, and a score of its houses are on the National or New Jersey Registers of Historic Places.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH it is less than 20 miles from Manhattan and 2 miles from five major shopping malls in neighboring Paramus, the well-maintained 1.8-square-mile borough of Ho-Ho-Kus has changed little in the last 50 years.</p>
        <p>Most of its housing stock is turn-of-the-century or earlier. Its last major housing development, the Cheelcroft section, dates to the Great Depression, and a score of its houses are on the National or New Jersey Registers of Historic Places.</p>
        <p>"Many people tell me we are right out of a Norman Rockwell painting," said Rusty Thompson, the borough historian and a councilwoman. "I guess you could say we're frozen in time."</p>
        <p>Reflecting an acquiescence to the nearby shopping malls, most of the businesses in Ho-Ho-Kus are either specialty or convenience establishments, including three banks, a video store, a florist, a couple of delis and five antiques shops. The 19th-century clapboard, Tudor and brick downtown business district spreads for six blocks around the intersection of Franklin Turnpike and Sheridan Avenue. Besides stores, it also has half a dozen two-story office buildings used by professionals such as doctors and lawyers.</p>
        <p>The borough's housing stock is almost exclusively single-family detached. The only exceptions are 10 small apartments above stores in the business district and the 24-unit Normandy Court condominium complex off West Saddle River Road, where prices range from about $ 400,000 for some three-bedroom units, up to $ 500,000 for some four-bedroom units.</p>
        <p>Only 15 houses are currently registered for sale in the Multiple Listing Service, with the most expensive ones on the east side of New Jersey Route 17, which bisects the borough from north to south. The listed homes range in price from $ 250,000 for a small, three-bedroom Tudor on Sheridan Avenue, a busy street in the western section, to $ 1.9 million for a large, six-bedroom, eight-bath ranch on four acres on Boiling Springs Road on the eastern side.</p>
        <p>"Anything priced at under about $ 400,000 goes very quickly," said Eleanor Portsmore, a sales associate with Abbott &amp; Caserta Realtors on Sycamore Avenue in Ho-Ho-Kus. Among the most sought after are the Cheelcroft homes, 50 mainly brick or flagstone Tudors and colonials on such streets as Gilbert Road or Sutton Drive, which sell for $ 300,000 to $ 450,000. They were built by Harold W. Cheel during and after the Depression. His widow, Helen S., still lives in one. A three-bedroom Cheelcroft home on Sheridan Avenue is now on the market for $ 315,000.</p>
        <p>"It's on a main road," said Mrs. Portsmore. "That same house one street over would sell for more than $ 380,000."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Portsmore said she could not accurately gauge the rental market because downtown apartments rarely become vacant. However, she said small, two-bedroom houses for $ 1,600 and $ 2,000 a month.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Sayers says he is disturbed that his children and those of other longtime residents cannot afford to move into the borough immediately after they marry. He says that buyers are willing to pay a premium because the borough has a negligible crime rate.</p>
        <p>"We have a 14-person police force that patrols around the clock, which is quite a lot for a small borough," Mr. Sayers said.</p>
        <p>LORI Lamb, who moved into the borough six years ago, also cites a low crime rate. She and her husband, John J., own a 22-room home on three and a half acres. Their home dates back to 1720 and is listed on the National Register of Historic Places.  "Although you know that crime is everywhere, I feel safe here," Mrs. Lamb said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lamb, a former airline hostess and model, and her husband, a real estate lawyer, have three children aged 5, 3 and 3 months. She said that her husband had lived in nearby Emerson, N.J.</p>
        <p>"My husband knew the area and wanted a large piece of property," she recalled. "We started negotiating for the house before we got married and got a call from the realtor when we were on our honeymoon in Germany that we had gotten it."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lamb called Ho-Ho-Kus "a friendly place where people reach out to you." She recalled offers of help that the Lambs had received from neighbors and the pastor of the Community Church, a Protestant Church and one of three houses of worship in the borough, just after they moved in six years ago.</p>
        <p>Like most residents of the borough, Mr. Lamb commutes to work. His office is in Montvale, N.J., a 20-minute drive. Many other residents are executives who work in New York City and use the borough's two park-and-ride lots near the train station in the commercial center of the borough.</p>
        <p>Some historians say the name Ho-Ho-Kus is a Leni Lenape Indian word that means "Red Cedar," for the dominant tree in the area when the first white settlers arrived in the late 17th century. Others interpret it as "Running Water," for the Saddle River and the Ho-Ho-Kus brook, which pass through the borough.</p>
        <p>Residents carefully guard their traditions, starting with the spelling of the borough's name. A book published in 1983, the 75th anniversary of the formal incorporation of the borough, includes a congratulatory note from President Ronald Reagan addressed to the "the Citizens of Ho Ho Kus." A note underneath the letter comments, "Look Ma, no Hyphens!!!"</p>
        <p>The first white settler to own property in what is now Ho-Ho-Kus was Albert Zaborowsky, who arrived from Poland in 1662. In 1790, one of Albert's descendants, John Zabriskie, built a private home on the corner of East Franklin Turnpike and Sheridan Avenue. That house later became a stagecoach stop and inn. Today, the brownstone and clapboard structure is Claude's Ho-Ho-Kus Inn, a highly regarded French restaurant, one of the borough's five restaurants.</p>
        <p>The arrival of the Ramapo and Paterson Railroad in 1850 started Ho-Ho-Kus's transformation from an agricultural center to a bedroom community of New York City. In 1870, the borough was put on the national map by the construction of what became the world-famous Ho-Ho-Kus Racetrack, a 23-acre track and fairground facility that was just west of what is now route 17. Horse and auto races took place at the track until 1938, when they were banned after a fatal accident. The area has since been developed for housing. When Route 17 was built in the 1930's, the residential character of Ho-Ho-Kus was preserved by a zoning ordinance that banned strip shopping centers from the highway in the borough.</p>
        <p>One of the oldest houses in the borough, The Hermitage, is now a state museum displaying 19th-century furniture and artifacts. The oldest part of the structure was built in 1747 and was visited by George Washington, Alexander Hamilton and the Marquis de Lafayette during the Revolutionary War. In 1782, Aaron Burr married its owner, the widow Theodosia Prevost. The museum is open from 1 to 4 P.M. on the first and third Sundays of each month and by special appointment.</p>
        <p>UNLIKE many other school districts in Bergen County, which have replaced aging facilities, Ho-Ho-Kus continues to upgrade its 1936 school building to meet local codes, said Dr. Debra Jackson, the superintendent of schools. Many of the floors of the Ho-Ho-Kus school are hardwood; its desks are older wooden ones, and the wires to link up the classroom computer network run on outside the building, rather than inside the walls.</p>
        <p>"The people here appreciate the woodwork and the fireplaces in the kindergartens," Dr. Jackson said. "It gives the school a nurturing, homelike atmosphere."</p>
        <p>The district serves kindergarten through eighth grades. High school students are sent to nearby Midland Park, an arrangement Mayor Sayers terms "unsatisfactory" because, he says, Midland Park High School is small and offers few electives. The Ho-Ho-Kus Board of Education is discussing possible alternatives.</p>
        <p>Computers are introduced in fourth grade, under a technology upgrade program now under way. Dr. Jackson said that next year they would be introduced in second grade. She added that she did not believe the youngsters were at a disadvantage compared to those in other districts who are given computer access in kindergarten.</p>
        <p>"In Ho-Ho-Kus most households have computers," she explained. "So the children are exposed to them in the home."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Jackson said that the students at Ho-Ho-Kus generally average in the 90th percentile on state-mandated achievement tests. As evidence of the quality of the school, she cites the 1989 Blue Ribbon for Excellence Award that it received from the Federal Department of Education at a White House ceremony. "We send a clear message that every child here gets a personal education," Ms. Jackson stated. "Our average class size is 18, but we have some classes with as little as 8 students."</p>
        <p>The borough also has a parochial school, St. Luke's Roman Catholic School, attached to St. Luke's Church.</p>
        <p>There is also a private school for severely learning disabled students ranging in age from 5 to 21. Tuition for the 100 students at ECLC, on Franklin Turnpike, is paid by the State Department of Education and local school districts.</p>
        <p>There are six parks, the largest of which is the 15-acre East Park off East Saddle River Road and Hollywood Avenue. It includes picnic facilities, walking trails and a section of the Saddle River, which residents use for trout fishing. On the Market 3-bedroom, 2-bath Tudor at 151 Sheridan Avenue, $ 250,000. 3-bedroom, 2-bath Tudor at 1 Van Dyke Drive, $ 389,000. 8-bedroom, 4-bath colonial on 5 acres at 873 East Saddle River Road, $ 1.75 million. GAZETTEER POPULATION: 4,080 (1995 estimate)</p>
        <p>AREA: 1.8 square miles.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN HOUSEHOLD INCOME: $ 92,000 (1995 estimate).</p>
        <p>MEDIAN PRICE OF ONE-FAMILY HOUSE: $ 385,000.</p>
        <p>TAXES ON MEDIAN HOUSE: $ 4,500.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN PRICE ONE YEAR AGO: $ 375,000.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN PRICE FIVE YEARS AGO: $ 359,000.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN PRICE OF 3-BEDROOM CONDOMINIUM: $ 420,000.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN PRICE ONE YEAR AGO: $ 420,000.</p>
        <p>MEDIAN RENT ON 2-BEDROOM HOUSE: $ 1,700.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC-SCHOOL EXPENDITURE PER PUPIL: $ 8,410.</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT: Mayor (Richard M. Sayers, Republican) elected to 4-year term; 6-member Council elected to 3-year terms.</p>
        <p>DISTANCE FROM MIDTOWN MANHATTAN: 18 miles.</p>
        <p>RUSH-HOUR COMMUTATION TO MIDTOWN: 40 minutes on Short Line Bus to Port Authority midtown terminal, $ 6.70 one way, $ 12.75 round trip, $ 49 for 10 trips; 45 minutes on New Jersey Transit train to Hoboken, $ 5.25 one way, $ 8 round trip, $ 142 monthly, then 10 minutes via PATH train, one way $ 1.</p>
        <p>ANDREWS SISTERS: In 1948, the Andrews Sisters launched a comical song called "Ho-Ho-Kus, N.J." with a visit to the borough. They thereby subjected Ho-Ho-Kus to good-natured national joking with lines that proclaimed, "It's lonesome in Passaic, but one town that takes the ca-ik is Ho-Ho-Kus, we'll sing until they choke us, 'bout Ho-Ho-Kus."</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 5, 1995, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 5 about living in Ho-Ho-Kus, N.J., referred incorrectly to St. Luke's school. It merged with two other parochial schools and is no longer at St. Luke's parish.  St. Luke's former school building is used by ECLC, a facility for learning-disabled students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 5, 1995, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 5 about living in Ho-Ho-Kus, N.J., referred incorrectly to St. Luke's school. It merged with two other parochial schools and is no longer at St. Luke's parish.  St. Luke's former school building is used by ECLC, a facility for learning-disabled students.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
