<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Israel, a Utopia Recedes</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="741698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ISRAEL PHILHARMONIC ORCHESTRA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHSTEIN, EDWARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D71431F936A35751C0A963958260" item-length="1350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Israel, a Utopia Recedes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHSTEIN, EDWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1934, IN PALESTINE, THE Polish violinist Bronislaw Huberman had a vision of an artistic utopia. In this paradise, he said in a lecture, no class would have an exclusive claim on mankind's highest esthetic achievements. Great art would be the birthright of all citizens. He envisioned a place where populism would mean a universal dedication to the sublime.</p>
        <p>Palestine could be such a place, he suggested, "the first country where we shall witness the miracle of an entire community culture." And the first step toward realizing that miracle was to create a new orchestra that would, in its performances, help create "One Great Spiritual Unity." "Let's work for Music in Palestine," he urged his audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1934, IN PALESTINE, THE Polish violinist Bronislaw Huberman had a vision of an artistic utopia. In this paradise, he said in a lecture, no class would have an exclusive claim on mankind's highest esthetic achievements. Great art would be the birthright of all citizens. He envisioned a place where populism would mean a universal dedication to the sublime.</p>
        <p>Palestine could be such a place, he suggested, "the first country where we shall witness the miracle of an entire community culture." And the first step toward realizing that miracle was to create a new orchestra that would, in its performances, help create "One Great Spiritual Unity." "Let's work for Music in Palestine," he urged his audience.</p>
        <p>So began the Palestine Symphony Orchestra, which later became the Israel Philharmonic Orchestra. Huberman's utopian visions were part of what inspired Arturo Toscanini to lead the orchestra's inaugural concert in 1936, declining all fees. Huberman arranged for the emigration of orchestral musicians from Germany, Poland, Austria and Hungary, saving them from the Nazis. The new orchestra played for the general public and in special workers' concerts, with ticket prices reduced by 80 percent. It became a cooperative, run by the players: a musical kibbutz, of sorts. Its ambition was to become a regional ensemble that would help bring peace to the Middle East; two weeks after the inaugural concert, Toscanini led the orchestra on its first foreign tour, to Egypt.</p>
        <p>The Israel Philharmonic will begin a two-week tour of the United States on Wednesday in Washington and play at Avery Fisher Hall on Feb. 12 and 13. Its utopian heritage is still important. But having come to realize that in contemporary culture, populism does not mean universal appreciation of high art, the orchestra is sternly schooling itself in the practicalities of the late-20th-century music business.</p>
        <p>Until its 50th anniversary, celebrated in 1987, the Israel Philharmonic, secure in its finances and confident of its future, could afford to be be complacent about its place in the artistic cosmos. Zubin Mehta was appointed music director for life in 1981. Subscriptions were jealously guarded by their possessors and passed on like family heirlooms. (In 1973, the waiting list for subscriptions contained some 2,000 names.) During its best years, the orchestra earned more than 90 percent of its budget through subscriptions and box office, a figure probably unmatched anywhere in the world. And there was no significant competition in Israel itself.</p>
        <p>But then, as one musician said recently, cable television came. Leisure activities changed. Over the decades, Israel itself became a modern state, one with more problems than most. Immigration made European culture less central. Artistic education was neglected. New Russian immigrants, meanwhile, created numerous chamber groups and orchestras throughout the country, tempting listeners who did not want to travel to Tel Aviv. As loyal subscribers began to die, no new generation stepped forward to take their place. Subscriptions fell from a high of 35,000 to 28,000 by 1990.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Avigdor Levin, a new financial officer, was hired to stop the slide.</p>
        <p>"We are reaching normalization," Mr. Levin wryly explained last fall. After surveying the damage, he pushed normalization even farther. The orchestra's first advertising campaign included bus posters in Hebrew proclaiming: "We are expanding the circle for you" and "The I.P.O. is for everybody."</p>
        <p>THE ORCHESTRA TRIED some of the techniques used in the United States, reducing the number of concerts in each subscription series and offering special privileges at the box office for subscribers. Mr. Levin has visited and consulted with the New York Philharmonic and the major orchestras in Philadelphia, Boston, Cleveland, Chicago and Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>The approach has begun to pay dividends. Since 1991, Mr. Levin said, 20,000 new subscribers have joined the orchestra, and the slippage has stopped. The average age of the audience, 63 in 1991, is now 55. Box office represents only 62 percent of the orchestra's budget, yet Mr. Levin boasts that last season, Mann Auditorium, the orchestra's home in Tel Aviv, was more than 90 percent full; this season, the figure is 95 percent.</p>
        <p>But the orchestra must continue its promotional pressure amid increasing competition.</p>
        <p>"The more competition the better," Mr. Levin insists. "Some subscribers who left us for other orchestras are coming back."</p>
        <p>Stiff new competition has come in particular from the new opera house in Tel Aviv, just a short walk from Mann Auditorium. It opened last October, with no participation by the Philharmonic. By one account, the Philharmonic's inquiries about becoming the orchestra for the New Israeli Opera were rebuffed. Shlomo Lahat, the former mayor of Tel Aviv, under whose aegis the building was constructed, told Mr. Mehta, he said, that involvement by the Philharmonic was not a good idea and that competition was good for the orchestra.</p>
        <p>"During the last few years," Mr. Lahat explained to me, "performances have not been at such a high level."</p>
        <p>Of course, added duties in the opera house would have entailed a radical expansion of the Philharmonic's roster and schedule, and many in the orchestra considered it impractical. But musicians' egos are still bruised over the opera company's complete lack of interest. Some express cautious hopes that a relationship will evolve over time. The situation is volatile at the moment; the company has become a center of controversy in the last three months, with revelations of the squandering of public funds in the construction of the building.</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic, meanwhile, scheduled three operas in concert this season and aggressively booked stars like Yevgeny Kissin, Jessye Norman, Yo-Yo Ma, Itzhak Perlman and Riccardo Muti. Although many artists, following Toscanini's lead, accept lower fees than usual or none at all, artistic costs rose by 30 percent this season because of the influx of big names.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin is lobbying for more help from the Israeli Government. Last season, the orchestra put 358,000 seats up for sale at its Israeli concerts -- more than half the tickets available for musical events in the entire country each year. Yet the state contributes just 11 percent of the orchestra's $14 million annual budget. Most other cultural institutions in Israel receive 30 to 40 percent of their funds from the Government. The Philharmonic's American tour is intended in part to keep the orchestra visible for future fund raising; 18 percent of its budget is now raised privately in Israel and the United States.</p>
        <p>While facing these pressures, the orchestra has undergone a gradual artistic evolution. Merrill Greenberg, an English-horn player who joined the orchestra in 1973, when many of the original members were still in place, described the "warm, rich, string playing" that came from old German and Polish instrumentalists. Like many ensembles in both Europe and the United States, the Israel Philharmonic has begun to shed such distinctive qualities, becoming a world-class professional ensemble with a modern, international sound.</p>
        <p>Uri Toeplitz, a flutist who was with the orchestra at its founding and has written a book about its history, said that in the 1930's and 40's, the "intensity of the Jewish playing gave the orchestra a special color." That color, he thinks, faded as the ensemble matured.</p>
        <p>"I am surprised sometimes that we were able to play as well as we did under Toscanini," Mr. Toeplitz said of the 1936 inaugural concert, "But the intensity came from the spirit of the times. Now we are more like any other orchestra."</p>
        <p>Some see this as a blessing.</p>
        <p>"We have a marriage going here," Mr. Greenberg said of Mr. Mehta's close involvment with the orchestra. Does the ensemble have a distinctive Israeli sound? "No, not yet," he replied. "But we're a young country. We're looking for it."</p>
        <p>The result will probably evolve not out of utopian esthetic visions but through the gritty experiences of contemporary Israeli life.  CLASSICAL MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
