<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jurors Doubted Scrushy's Colleagues</title>
    <meta content="02scrushy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/02/business/02scrushy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1684419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">HealthSouth Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scrushy, Richard M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6D61231F931A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jurors Doubted Scrushy's Colleagues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jurors Doubted Scrushy's Colleagues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KYLE WHITMIRE</byline>
      <dateline>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., July 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the end, the jury deciding the fate of HealthSouth's former chief executive, Richard M. Scrushy, focused on one issue: credibility. But it was not Mr. Scrushy's credibility they were thinking about -- he did not testify in his own defense. Instead, they wondered, could they believe the five former company executives who testified against him?</p>
        <p>''No one really corroborated one another,'' recalled one juror, Christopher Cooper, a 37-year-old computer technician at a local bank. ''Each one of them had a reason to hide something.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., July 1 - In the end, the jury deciding the fate of HealthSouth's former chief executive, Richard M. Scrushy, focused on one issue: credibility. But it was not Mr. Scrushy's credibility they were thinking about - he did not testify in his own defense. Instead, they wondered, could they believe the five former company executives who testified against him?.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the end, the jury deciding the fate of HealthSouth's former chief executive, Richard M. Scrushy, focused on one issue: credibility. But it was not Mr. Scrushy's credibility they were thinking about -- he did not testify in his own defense. Instead, they wondered, could they believe the five former company executives who testified against him?</p>
        <p>''No one really corroborated one another,'' recalled one juror, Christopher Cooper, a 37-year-old computer technician at a local bank. ''Each one of them had a reason to hide something.''</p>
        <p>The jury acquitted Mr. Scrushy on Tuesday of all 36 counts that had accused him of presiding over a $2.7 billion accounting fraud while running the HealthSouth national hospital chain. The Justice Department, legal experts had thought, appeared to have a strong case against Mr. Scrushy after all five of the company's former chief financial officers agreed to cooperate.</p>
        <p>Facing such a cadre of government witnesses during the five-month trial was a daunting challenge, one of Mr. Scrushy's lawyers, James Parkman III, said at a news conference after the verdict.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't go in with the idea that there were five of them,'' Mr. Parkman said. ''We had to go in and try to sell the idea that there was only one, and they acted together as one, acted together as a group, and therefore cut that number of five to one.''</p>
        <p>The one former executive they focused on was William T. Owens, who worked his way up at HealthSouth from assistant treasurer to chief financial officer and even served briefly as chief executive in 2002. The defense characterized him as a tax cheat who would lie to protect himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Owens, in cooperating with the government, had secretly recorded his conversations with Mr. Scrushy. But those recordings were often difficult to hear and ambiguous in meaning, jurors said.</p>
        <p>''I can't talk about the federal government, but a pocket recorder could have recorded better than what was on that tape,'' a second juror, Curtis Bender, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper, the juror, said that he thought another of the chief financial officers, Weston Smith, had been lying to protect his wife, whom some witnesses connected with the fraud. Mr. Cooper also said Mr. Owens hadtransferred many of his assets to his wife before making his plea deal.</p>
        <p>The jurors said the plea agreements, rather than strengthening the government's case, made the witnesses' testimony suspect. Before the trial, a federal judge had sentenced Michael Martin, another former chief financial officer, to six months of home detention. The defense characterized the sentence as excessively lenient, allowing Mr. Martin to sleep in his own bed, go to the store and even play golf.</p>
        <p>''They were fooling the public, fooling the stockholders, bankers, auditors,'' Mr. Bender said. ''They fooled a lot of people for a lot of years and got away with it -- that's what it seemed like.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bender, 54, a lineman for the Alabama Power Company, added that he could not conclude that Mr. Scrushy had known about the fraud. ''That's where the reasonable doubt came in,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Phoebe Ellsworth, a professor of psychology and law at the University of Michigan, said the case was somewhat analogous to one in which a co-defendant might testify in exchange for immunity. ''Jurors ask themselves why one guy should be taking all the heat and another guy should be taking very little.''</p>
        <p>One juror said he thought the prosecution's case was strong enough to convict Mr. Scrushy. But because the juror, Willis G. Vest, 63, was suffering from migraine headaches, he was replaced with an alternate.</p>
        <p>''To me, there was more than enough evidence and testimony, but people disagree,'' Mr. Vest said in an interview after the verdict. ''Almost every witness agreed with each other.''</p>
        <p>Initially, at least, some jurors agreed with Mr. Vest. The first vote taken by the jury was seven to five for acquittal, Mr. Bender said. After further deliberation, a second vote ended with only three holdouts for conviction. In a note to the judge, the jury said that it was deadlocked on all counts.</p>
        <p>The judge, Karon O. Bowdre of Federal District Court for the Northern District of Alabama, gave the jury a so-called Allen charge, a special set of instructions emphasizing the resources spent on the trial, with an encouragement to reach a unanimous decision.</p>
        <p>''I was feeling like we didn't do our job, that this was the easy way out,'' Mr. Bender said. ''But after she told us to go in there and try to reach a verdict, I was glad because now we could go in there and start deliberating.''</p>
        <p>After that, one juror changed his mind and Mr. Vest said he began to suffer from the migraine headaches.</p>
        <p>The lone remaining holdout, a female juror, whom her colleagues declined to identify, finally gave in during the last four days of deliberation. The final vote, on Tuesday, was unanimous for acquittal.</p>
        <p>''It is not surprising that one holdout would eventually agree with the others,'' Dr. Ellsworth said. ''If the other guy had stayed on it might have been a different story, but being a minority of one is very difficult.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bender said he went into the trial suspecting that Mr. Scrushy was guilty of violating the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, a law passed by Congress in the wake of the accounting scandals at Enron and WorldCom.</p>
        <p>''If he signed that paper, knowingly or not knowingly, I was thinking he was guilty; he's C.E.O. of the company,'' Mr. Bender said. ''But once we got into the courtroom and started reading what the law requires and not requires, it just blew my theory right out.''</p>
        <p>Shortly before his indictment was unsealed in 2003, Mr. Scrushy left a predominantly white suburban church to attend Guiding Light Church, a large, mostly black congregation in Birmingham. On weekends during the trial, he often preached and made donations at black churches in the area and was the host of a religious television program.</p>
        <p>Many of the ministers who appeared on the show also appeared in court, sitting behind the defense table. The jurors, however, insisted that that was never a factor in their deliberations. ''I was hoping that Birmingham would not make this into a black or white issue,'' Mr. Cooper said. ''His charitable donations had nothing to do with our decisions. I didn't know much about that until it was over.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bender said he nearly missed the birth of his granddaughter during the deliberations, and Mr. Cooper said he had to take a day off when his wife underwent knee surgery.</p>
        <p>Now back at work, Mr. Cooper and Mr. Bender said they tried to avoid any questions from co-workers about the verdict. Mr. Bender said some of his co-workers had asked why they let Mr. Scrushy go.</p>
        <p>''And then some said, 'What, they didn't have the evidence, right?''' Mr. Bender said. ''And I said, 'Yep.'''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
