<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deep, Painful Descent of Tokyo Stocks</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="648286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NIKKEI STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TOKYO STOCK EXCHANGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED71738F93BA35752C1A965958260" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deep, Painful Descent of Tokyo Stocks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Nov. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Japanese stock market having taken another steep dive in the last two weeks and share prices in the fourth year of a deep overall decline, dissatisfaction over the Tokyo Stock Exchange's policies is growing.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the market's drop, analysts say, are the nation's persistent recession, plummeting corporate profits, a mounting toll of bad loans by banks and the near-abandonment of stocks by small investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Japanese stock market having taken another steep dive in the last two weeks and share prices in the fourth year of a deep overall decline, dissatisfaction over the Tokyo Stock Exchange's policies is growing.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the market's drop, analysts say, are the nation's persistent recession, plummeting corporate profits, a mounting toll of bad loans by banks and the near-abandonment of stocks by small investors.</p>
        <p>The stock market has been perceived as so unattractive that although Americans have been pouring tens of billions of dollars into mutual funds that invest overseas, only a trickle of that money has come to Japan. That is surprising, given that Tokyo has the second-largest market in the world, after the New York Stock Exchange. The Power of Fear</p>
        <p>But some experts say that outmoded attitudes at the Tokyo Stock Exchange, a meddlesome Government and inadequate order systems have contributed to the lack of confidence. In particular, experts say, the exchange's policies have kept frightened individual investors away, and that absence has inhibited recovery.</p>
        <p>The exchange says it is trying to help, but admits it has had little success. "Increasing individual participation is the main concern of the Tokyo Stock Exchange at the moment," said Yoshiaki Kaneko, who left the Finance Ministry to become the exchange's managing director later this month. "That will contribute to stability in the market. What we're trying to do is increase the attraction of the stocks themselves."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaneko said, for instance, that the exchange is urging companies to increase their stingy dividends, reduce the minimum number of shares an investor must purchase and provide better information about their finances. Companies, though, have been in no mood to comply.</p>
        <p>The problems have been highlighted in recent weeks by one of the largest new listings of a company in a decade. On Oct. 26, the Government-controlled East Japan Railway, known as JR East, made its debut. The listing had been postponed for more than a year and had been eagerly awaited, as officials hoped to use the offering both to raise cash and give the market a psychological lift.</p>
        <p>By most accounts, though, it became a fiasco that helped send the market on its latest plunge. In the less than two weeks since, the Nikkei index of 225 issues has lost more than 8 percent of its value.</p>
        <p>The Government sold half of the four million shares in the giant railroad at an auction that put the price at 380,000 yen a share, the equivalent of $3,518. Some criticized the auction process, because it left more than 10,000 individual investors each owning just one share.</p>
        <p>When the shares were formally listed, individual investors who had been frustrated with their meager allotments bid lustily for more. The exchange could not deal with the orders, and so could not set a price until nearly 40 minutes after it closed for the day. The price was then put at 600,000 yen each.</p>
        <p>Some thought that looked too good. The next morning, the small investors whom the Government and the exchange had been hoping to attract as stable, long-term stockholders placed waves of sell orders. The exchange suspended trading that day and the next, making it difficult for most of those who wanted to take profits to do so.  A Four Years</p>
        <p>The price of JR East shares has steadily fallen since, to 485,000 yen on Friday, the equivalent of $4,491. The Nikkei index closed Friday at 18,590.46 points.</p>
        <p>[ The Nikkei index gained 21.60 points in trading Monday morning, to 18,612.06 at midday, up 0.12 percent. ]</p>
        <p>Since the end of 1989, despite occasional upswings, the Nikkei has lost more than half its value from its peak -- more than $3 trillion.</p>
        <p>The Tokyo Stock Exchange blamed its computer systems for the halts in trading, and this angered some experts. The major brokerage houses never criticize the Tokyo exchange in public, since it is regarded as virtually an arm of the powerful Finance Ministry -- which provides the exchange's top executives. But they came as close as they could when they issued a statement saying they had asked the exchange to insure that such foul-ups do not recur.</p>
        <p>"In my view, the exchange has not been innovative enough in developing its technology," said Shoichi Royama, dean of the economics department at Osaka University and an expert on financial markets. "The problems with JR East are just symptoms. I'm not astonished."</p>
        <p>The problems and the subsequent decline in the value of both JR East and the general market have embarrassed the Government and the exchange. Not least, this has complicated efforts by public companies and brokerage houses to reopen the exchange to more new issues.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, the Finance Ministry decreed a near-halt to new listings on the Tokyo exchange, in one of many failed attempts to lift stock prices. It was hoped that a successful JR East listing would once again permit the market to receive a steady flow of new issues.</p>
        <p>In 1989, for instance, before the decline began, Japanese companies raised 5.8 trillion yen from new offerings on the Tokyo exchange, the equivalent of $53.7 billion. Last year, the figure fell to four billion yen, or $37 million, and will be higher this year largely because of the JR East offering.</p>
        <p>"I'm sure there is some concern about the computer problems -- no doubt about it," Mr. Kaneko said. "But we are still analyzing the situation."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
