<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off to U.S., Japanese Pack Words, Like 'Police!'</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="581957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANGER, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D8143FF933A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off to U.S., Japanese Pack Words, Like 'Police!'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANGER, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Jan. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 7 o'clock on Sunday nights, television viewers across Japan tune in to see the latest disaster to befall Hyota, a hapless Japanese traveler trying to survive in America with the English he learned in Japan's public schools. He was recently wandering the streets of Tombstone, Ariz., in search of a security guard.</p>
        <p>"I am looking for guardo-man," he said, reaching for one of the thousands of terms Japan has borrowed from abroad and turned into something halfway between English and Japanese.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 7 o'clock on Sunday nights, television viewers across Japan tune in to see the latest disaster to befall Hyota, a hapless Japanese traveler trying to survive in America with the English he learned in Japan's public schools. He was recently wandering the streets of Tombstone, Ariz., in search of a security guard.</p>
        <p>"I am looking for guardo-man," he said, reaching for one of the thousands of terms Japan has borrowed from abroad and turned into something halfway between English and Japanese.</p>
        <p>"I don't know him," answered a man eating an ice-cream cone on a park bench. A young mother, approached with the same question, clutched her baby and scurried away. A teen-ager asked if he was seeking a "gay man," and another directed him to a gardener.</p>
        <p>By this time the studio audience of "Kyosen's Unusable English," which parodies the failure of Japan's schools to teach its students how to communicate, was roaring with nervous laughter at their countryman's plight.</p>
        <p>These days shows like "Unusable English," which started only three months ago and has soared in the ratings, are playing a vital new role in Japan: they are becoming something of a national survival course for Japanese preparing to wander out of the safe cocoon of their own country.</p>
        <p>Suddenly the airwaves are filled with programs to teach street lingo to a nation that grew up reading stiff passages from English-language textbooks that might get you into the University of Tokyo but are of little use warding off a hustler at Kennedy Airport.</p>
        <p>Not all of Japan's fears are centered on the United States. In the last week or so, Japanese women living in South Africa and Australia were slain, and a bus full of Japanese tourists in Egypt was fired upon. Television commentators noted that Japanese increasingly seem like natural targets -- rich, conspicuous and unaccustomed to looking over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>After a number of Japanese workers were taken hostage in Iraq at the beginning of the Persian Gulf war, there was a surge in corporate programs to make executives aware of the dangers of international travel, but they did not last long.</p>
        <p>A similar flurry occurred after the kidnapping of several Japanese executives in the Philippines. What is new is the popularity of a weekly television program on coping with the dangers of a visit to America and a rapid increase in survival courses, most aimed at visitors to the United States. Crime Is Expected</p>
        <p>Japanese have always viewed a visit to America with a mixture of fascination and terror: In a recent poll conducted by The New York Times, CBS News and Tokyo Broadcasting System, 69 percent of Japanese responding said they thought they were "very likely" or "somewhat likely" to be the victim of a crime during a visit to the United States.</p>
        <p>But the image of America as a place where unsuspecting, cash-laden Japanese are as tempting a target as clay pigeons was reinforced like never before after the slaying of a 16-year-old Japanese foreign exchange student in Louisiana in October. The student was killed when he didn't understand the meaning of the word "Freeze!" shouted by a man wielding a gun.</p>
        <p>The account of Yoshihiro Hattori's killing, after he approached the wrong house in search of a Halloween party, has fed a long-held image here of America and become the source of at least two new movements: one to ban guns in the United States, and the other to arm Japanese with survival language for their ventures abroad.</p>
        <p>. Two weeks ago the youth's parents, Masaichi and Mieko Hattori, presented the United States Ambassador to Japan, Michael H. Armacost, with some of the million signatures they had collected in a petition calling for the removal of guns from American homes.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Japanese newspapers and magazines have been filled with features about how Americans keep guns at home, something that is illegal in Japan. (The very few who own guns in Japan -- where the homicide rate is one-eighth that in the United States -- are required by law to keep them stored at a police station.)</p>
        <p>But another result of what has come to be known as the "freeze case" is a rash of crash courses in "defensive English."</p>
        <p>"People are really desperate," said Mieko Hikosaka, a Tokyo teacher who with two friends organized street-language seminars that attracted more than 700 people. Mrs. Hikosaka, who lived in New York for several years, covered what she terms "useful expressions" like "Get him!" "Stop him!" and "Police!"</p>
        <p>"I realized that I needed to do this when another high school teacher told me that he did not know 'freeze' had another meaning other than what you do with food," she said.  Tongue-Tied in Class</p>
        <p>Though every Japanese student gets six years of English instruction, almost all of it is a grammar-laden preparation for the university entrance exams. Students say they are so fearful of making a mistake in class that they dare not speak at all, and quickly focus on passing the test rather than communicating.</p>
        <p>"Japanese people have such a fear of English that they cringe even if asked simple directions by a foreigner on the street."</p>
        <p>Hideyuki Sumii, the co-producer of the "Unusable English" program, said problems were compounded by the way the Japanese language twists and then assimilates English words like "mansion," which is the term Japanese use to describe a small apartment. Trying to rent a mansion in America, it turns out, is a surprisingly expensive proposition.</p>
        <p>"People get lulled into thinking that they can actually communicate when in fact they are making fools of themselves," Mr. Sumii said.</p>
        <p>But sooner or later, the topic always returns to self-protection. More than ever before, seminars on how to avoid getting conned, mugged or worse on American shores are a big draw. The Government has turned out safety films to warn Japanese of the hazards they face abroad, and companies now show their employees videos on topics like how to spot a good neighborhood in Los Angeles from a gang-ridden one.</p>
        <p>"It turns out it's pretty easy," a Mitsubishi executive said recently, mocking the naivete of some of the warnings. "The good blocks have a lot of big empty buildings that we Japanese paid too much for. On the bad blocks everything's burning."</p>
        <p>But if part of the problem is lack of language skills, the country got another role model this week with the announcement that Masako Owada would marry Japan's Crown Prince, Naruhito. Miss Owada has spent much of her life in the United States and Britain, and her English is so good that many Japanese say it is a bit intimidating. Starting this week, the 29-year-old former diplomat is traveling with what many Japanese think is an essential item for ventures overseas: a team of stern-faced bodyguards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
