<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. to Name Its Own to Board</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="581947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TULIS, MARK S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUARLES, PEARL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOCHBERG, AUDREY G (ASSEMBLYWOMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GALEF, SANDRA R (ASSEMBLYWOMEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DF1F3CF933A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. to Name Its Own to Board</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE early suggestions of bipartisan cooperation, leaders of the Republican Party, which controls the Board of Legislators, plan to name two of their own to fill vacant seats on the Board at its meeting tomorrow. The two seats, formerly held by Democrats, are in predominantly Democratic districts.</p>
        <p>The 8 Republicans and 1 Conservative control the 17-member Board, but last fall the Board's chairman, Stephen P. Tenore, surprised political observers and encouraged Democrats by announcing he would consider candidates from both parties to fill the two vacancies. The seats had been occupied by Sandra R. Galef of Ossining and Audrey G. Hochberg of Scarsdale, who were elected to the State Assembly in November. After redistricting as a result of the 1990 census, the Eighth Legislative District, formerly represented by Ms. Hochberg, was redrawn to include a 45 percent minority population.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE early suggestions of bipartisan cooperation, leaders of the Republican Party, which controls the Board of Legislators, plan to name two of their own to fill vacant seats on the Board at its meeting tomorrow. The two seats, formerly held by Democrats, are in predominantly Democratic districts.</p>
        <p>The 8 Republicans and 1 Conservative control the 17-member Board, but last fall the Board's chairman, Stephen P. Tenore, surprised political observers and encouraged Democrats by announcing he would consider candidates from both parties to fill the two vacancies. The seats had been occupied by Sandra R. Galef of Ossining and Audrey G. Hochberg of Scarsdale, who were elected to the State Assembly in November. After redistricting as a result of the 1990 census, the Eighth Legislative District, formerly represented by Ms. Hochberg, was redrawn to include a 45 percent minority population.</p>
        <p>"I said I wouldn't rule out anyone," Mr. Tenore reiterated last week, but he added that the Democrats couldn't agree on a candidate in time for him to present their choice to his party's executive committee. "There just wasn't a clear decision on the Democratic side as to who they would support," he said. 'That's a Moot Point'</p>
        <p>Calling Mr. Tenore's remarks "preposterous" and "total hypocrisy," Dennis Mehiel, the County Democratic Party chairman, said: "If Mr. Tenore wants to appoint a Democrat to one of two clearly Democratic seats, the decision rests with the Board of Legislators, not with the Republican executive committee. Mr. Tenore is simply a tool of the Republicans."</p>
        <p>Mr. Tenore refused to say whether he would have supported a Democratic nominee had the Democrats agreed on one. "That's a moot point," he said, adding, "On Monday, the Democrats will say they all agree, but that doesn't help, on Monday. The Republicans needed a decision."</p>
        <p>Last week, Anthony J. Colavita, the County Republican Party chairman, said party leaders had not supported Mr. Tenore's proposal to share the seats with the Democrats. "It was possible," Mr. Colavita said, but he added, "There was no support for it among party leaders or among legislative leaders." Morning Session Scheduled</p>
        <p>The full Board will vote on the nominees when it holds its first 1993 legislative session tomorrow morning. If the Republicans support their party's candidates, as is expected, the new legislators will include the New Castle Town Supervisor, Mark S. Tulis, and Pearl C. Quarles of New Rochelle, president of the Westchester Black Women's Political Caucus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tulis, a lawyer, has been a member of the New Castle Town Council for the last six years, first serving two years as a councilman and now completing his second term as Supervisor. Mrs. Quarles, who narrowly lost a race for a seat on the New Rochelle City Council 10 years ago, served 8 years on the city's school board, becoming its first black president in 1977.</p>
        <p>If the two Republican nominees are confirmed as legislators, both will be making sacrifices to assume their new positions. Mrs. Quarles will relinquish her job as a staff assistant in the Finance and Administration unit of the county's Department of Social Services.</p>
        <p>By giving up his position as Supervisor, Mr. Tulis leaves the choice of his replacement to the four remaining members of the Town Council, all Democrats. The Council, he said, is also likely to replace Bette Spriggs, the deputy town supervisor and a Republican appointed by Mr. Tulis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tulis said that if he had run for the Board of Legislators in a special election he would not have had to give up the Supervisor's post if he lost the legislative race. 'The Lines Are Very Clear Now'</p>
        <p>The Board of Legislators is debating a proposal to hold special elections to fill vacant seats on the Board, a proposal that is likely to be approved by the Board soon and sent to county voters in a referendum in November. If approved, special elections would be held beginning in 1994.</p>
        <p>Last week, debate about the proposal and the candidates was pushed to the sidelines while both parties traded blows, with Democrats claiming they should never have trusted their power-hungry colleagues across the aisle and Republicans insisting they had tried to be fair to a Democratic Party in disarray, whose leaders were unable to agree on a candidate.</p>
        <p>"I didn't believe it in the first place," said Judy A. Shepard, a Democratic legislator from Yorktown, when she learned that Mr. Tenore was supporting two Republicans rather than candidates from both parties.</p>
        <p>Two additional Republicans will give the Republican Party 11 seats on the 17-member board, one short of the 12 votes needed to approve budget appropriations. "All this talk about cooperation is over, and the lines are very clear now," Ernest D. Davis, a Democrat from Mount Vernon, said, adding that the Republicans would have difficulty obtaining that 12th vote. "When the time came for the Republicans to be fair, they weren't," Mr. Davis said, adding, "We'll act accordingly."</p>
        <p>Upon learning of the Republican leaders' decision, Mrs. Galef said: "We've been had. This is another example of Steve Tenore saying one thing and doing another." She was referring to last year's political uproar when Mr. Tenore defeated her bid for Board chairman by one vote.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Galef was widely expected to become Board chairwoman when in November 1991 the Democrats won a majority of seats on the Board for the first time in history. But Suzanne R. Swanson, a Conservative elected to the Board on the Democratic line, threw her support to Mr. Tenore in a move that Democrats said was calculated to give Republicans control of the Board.</p>
        <p>Once he assumed the chairmanship, Mr. Tenore moved quickly to mollify Democrats and establish harmony on the Board. He offered four committee co-chairmanships to the Democrats, insured that proposals from both parties reached the floor and adopted some Democratic suggestions for change, including changes in the 1993 budget.</p>
        <p>He continued that effort to reach consensus among the Democrats before a meeting of the Republican executive committee last Monday night, Mr. Tenore said. The effort ended in a conference call he arranged from his Florida vacation home with Herman Keith, the Democratic minority leader, and with Mr. Davis, the deputy minority leader, a few hours before the Republican Party meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tenore said he asked Mr. Keith if the Democrats had someone they could agree on and was told by Mr. Keith that they did not. That, Mr. Tenore said, left him unable to present a Democratic candidate to Republican leaders that evening. "We needed a decision," Mr. Tenore said. Cross-Endorsement Rejected</p>
        <p>When told about the telephone conversation, Mr. Mehiel said: "No one asked Mr. Tenore to appoint a Democrat, because we understand majority rule. He raised the issue and made the offer, positioning himself as not so partisan." That, Mr. Mehiel added, "is the defining issue."</p>
        <p>Mark P. Weingarten, executive director of the Westchester County Democratic Party Committee, said, "The Democratic caucus hadn't met before that phone call, so, of course, there could be no agreement on the candidates."</p>
        <p>Republicans, Mr. Weingarten said, needed to insure their control of the Board. Their opponents, led by Mr. Colavita, the County Republican Party chairman, had proposed one possibility: a bipartisan slate approved by both parties, but only if Democrats would cross-endorse that slate in the legislative elections scheduled for November.</p>
        <p>"The Republican Party contacted us and suggested cross-endorsement," Mr. Weingarten said. "That would mean the total disenfranchisement of the voters," he said. "Of course, we refused." Two Democratic Candidates Named</p>
        <p>Late last week, the Democrats announced the names of their two candidates for the Board: Lois T. Bronz, a former seven-term Greenburgh Town Councilwoman, and Dr. Bruce Gilchrist, the New Castle Town Supervisor from 1986 to 1989.</p>
        <p>At the end of the week, some Democrats remained hopeful that their Republican colleagues would support a bipartisan slate. "How the vote goes remains to be seen," Ms. Shepard said. "The question is whether Republicans will vote as they have been told or how they believe."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
