<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton to Ask Billions More In Spending for the Military</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="728734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY PERSONNEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERRY, WILLIAM J (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEHL, DOUGLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDC1E30F931A35751C1A962958260" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton to Ask Billions More In Spending for the Military</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEHL, DOUGLAS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to quiet Republican criticism that the military is underfinanced, President Clinton held a Rose Garden ceremony today to announce that he would seek a $25 billion increase in military spending over the next six years.</p>
        <p>With Defense Secretary William J. Perry and the Joint Chiefs of Staff at his side, Mr. Clinton outlined plans to improve readiness and to support military personnel. Among the purposes of the new money, he said, will be the troops' annual cost-of-living pay increases that Congress has already authorized into the next century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trying to quiet Republican criticism that the military is underfinanced, President Clinton held a Rose Garden ceremony today to announce that he would seek a $25 billion increase in military spending over the next six years.</p>
        <p>With Defense Secretary William J. Perry and the Joint Chiefs of Staff at his side, Mr. Clinton outlined plans to improve readiness and to support military personnel. Among the purposes of the new money, he said, will be the troops' annual cost-of-living pay increases that Congress has already authorized into the next century.</p>
        <p>In addition to that $25 billion, Mr. Clinton said, he will ask Congress for an emergency increase in this fiscal year's Pentagon budget to help cover the costs of operations in Haiti, in Kuwait, in Bosnia and off the Cuban coast. Administration officials said later that this emergency request would total about $2 billion.</p>
        <p>Senior Administration officials said Mr. Clinton's plan was recognition of a need to improve the readiness and the quality of life of military forces, which have been stretched so thin that the Pentagon last month conceded that 3 of 12 Army divisions were not at peak readiness levels.</p>
        <p>But the Administration officials also acknowledged that the timing and the staging of today's event reflected a view that Mr. Clinton must do more to head off what has been a strong line of Republican attack: that cuts in military spending since he took office almost two years ago have left American forces incapable of carrying out their declared mission of fighting two major conflicts at once.</p>
        <p>"We ask much of our military," the President said in presenting his initiative, "and we owe much to them."</p>
        <p>Republican Congressional leaders described the plan as a welcome and important first step. Senator John McCain, an Arizona Republican who is among his party's most influential figures in military matters, called it "the first sign of recognition on the part of this Administration that this nation's military readiness and ability to defend its vital national interests in the world is in question."</p>
        <p>But Senator McCain and his fellow Republicans said the initiative was insufficient to heal what they called deep wounds in American military might. They said they would fight to halt the decline in the Pentagon budget, which has plunged to $252 billion a year from $281 billion since Mr. Clinton took office and would decline further, even under the President's new plan, before spending rises again later in the decade.</p>
        <p>"This is a hemorrhage that needs a tourniquet," said Senator Robert C. Smith, a New Hampshire Republican who is a member of the Senate Armed Services Committee, "and the President is offering a Band-Aid."</p>
        <p>The $25 billion in new spending that Mr. Clinton called for today would not reverse the current decline in the military budget until the 1998 fiscal year, a turnaround point he had previously set. It would postpone its largest budget increases until the turn of the century, and over the next four years would provide only $2.5 billion a year -- about 1 percent of the Pentagon budget -- over existing plans for military spending.</p>
        <p>At a White House briefing after the announcement, Deputy Defense Secretary John Deutch pronounced the plan sufficient to allow the Pentagon to close a budget shortfall that had threatened to force deep cuts in weapons systems.</p>
        <p>But Republicans immediately questioned Mr. Deutch's arithmetic. They said that even if his assumptions of low inflation were correct, and even given weapons systems cuts that he said still lay ahead, it would be impossible to make up a budget gap that the Administration estimates will total $48 billion over the next six years.</p>
        <p>"We have a readiness problem now, and we will have a readiness problem after the President's initiative is implemented," said Representative Floyd D. Spence, the South Carolina Republican who is preparing to become chairman of the House Armed Services Committee in the new Congress.</p>
        <p>A promise to restore military spending is a central feature of House Republicans' "Contract With America," which they have pledged to carry out once they take control next month. Representative Newt Gingrich, set to become Speaker of the House, has led a chorus of Republican attacks accusing Mr. Clinton of cutting military spending too deeply.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clinton, who has sought for the last two years to hold the line against the deeper military cuts sought by some Democrats, said today that it was "not right" to see his request for an increase in spending as an acknowledgement that his critics were correct.</p>
        <p>"We have seen the military, frankly, have to deal with an amazing number and variety of unanticipated challenges," he said. "They have done so with great skill, but now they need the support that I think we ought to give them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
