<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jewish Right, Arab Left</title>
    <meta content="19FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Affairs" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="909943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Foreign Affairs"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1F3FF93AA25751C0A961958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jewish Right, Arab Left</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <dateline>CASABLANCA, Morocco</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column on failure of Arab intellectual left to reconcile itself to Israel, even though Arab regimes have; cites absence of most Arab intellectuals from debate over future of Palestinian state (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu signed the Hebron withdrawal accord it signaled a fundamental split on the Jewish right in Israel. Those who argued that for religious, nationalist or security reasons Israel must never cede one inch of the West Bank were left behind, as a large segment of the Jewish right joined the land-for-peace camp, creating a broad new center. Now the only debate left in Israel is not whether there will be a Palestinian state in the West Bank, but what size will it be: A size 15 wide, a size 10 narrow, or a size 7 small?</p>
        <p>The answer to that question will depend, in part, on whether the split on the Jewish right will be mirrored now by a split on the Arab left. Up to now the Arab intellectual left, as well as the unions of Arab doctors, lawyers and writers, have refused to reconcile themselves to Israel, even though their regimes have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu signed the Hebron withdrawal accord it signaled a fundamental split on the Jewish right in Israel. Those who argued that for religious, nationalist or security reasons Israel must never cede one inch of the West Bank were left behind, as a large segment of the Jewish right joined the land-for-peace camp, creating a broad new center. Now the only debate left in Israel is not whether there will be a Palestinian state in the West Bank, but what size will it be: A size 15 wide, a size 10 narrow, or a size 7 small?</p>
        <p>The answer to that question will depend, in part, on whether the split on the Jewish right will be mirrored now by a split on the Arab left. Up to now the Arab intellectual left, as well as the unions of Arab doctors, lawyers and writers, have refused to reconcile themselves to Israel, even though their regimes have.</p>
        <p>For the first time a tiny split in the Arab left is opening, but it has a long, long way to go before it becomes a politically significant movement that could really influence the debate in Israel. This week some important Arab media, such as Al-Mussawar magazine, the widely watched television show featuring Egypt's Hamdi Qandil and even leftist newspapers like Al-Ahali have been filled with this budding debate: Was it proper for Arab intellectuals, led by Egypt's Lutfi al-Kholi and Abdel Moneim Said, to take part in a recent dialogue with centrist Israeli intellectuals in Copenhagen? The Arab intellectual left had previously decreed that only a dialogue with non-Zionist Israelis was legitimate.</p>
        <p>But those who went to Copenhagen argued that it has not been the boycott of Israel by Arab intellectuals that has brought the Palestinians their first chunks of land from Israel. Rather it was the pressure first of the Palestinian uprising and then of the Israeli peace movement. Therefore if Arab intellectuals really want to help Palestinians, they will engage directly with the peace forces in Israel, even the Likud, and try to nurture the land-for-peace lobby there. The Nobel Prize-winning Egyptian author Naguib Mahfouz told Al-Ahram: ''Accusing those who participated $(in Copenhagen$) of treason is nonsense. I support the advocates of peace on the Arab side getting in touch with the advocates of peace in Israel. This is a patriotic act.'' Added Mohammed Sid Ahmed: ''Negating Israel is impossible. What is possible is to change Israel.''</p>
        <p>But this is still a minority view. I just participated in a roundtable discussion with 50 Moroccan professors at King Hassan II University in Casablanca, and I heard attacks on Israel that were so bitter I finally said to them: ''I feel as if I've entered a time warp and woken up at an Arab League meeting in 1960.'' For these Moroccan intellectuals, Hebron didn't exist, Oslo didn't exist, Yasir Arafat was misguided. They spoke from the heart about the ''rape of Arab land'' that the Jewish state represented. Qadri Hifni, an Egyptian expert on Israel, summed up their mindset in Al-Mussawar, saying: ''The cultural domain is the last bastion of normalization. Let us $(intellectuals$) be careful. If boycotting Israel would hurt it, let's maintain that strategy.''</p>
        <p>These hard-line Arab intellectuals seem to be seeking not Israeli withdrawals, but Israeli atonement. They want an ideological victory, they want an apology, they want the Jews to stand up and say, ''Sorry, we never should have built a state here.'' Further complicating the picture is a new element: Some Arab intellectuals today seem to be either intimidated by the rising influence of Islamic fundamentalists or fascinated by their power, and would like to mobilize it. Mohammed Imara, a leading Egyptian Islamist, argued that the role of the Arab intellectual was ''to nourish the memory of our nation about the entirety of its rights until the balance of power can be corrected.''</p>
        <p>Even those Arab intellectuals ready to engage Israelis today do so on the assumption that Israel will return to the 1967 lines. But the real debate in Israel will not be whether to return 100 percent of the West Bank, but whether to return 40 to 50 percent or 80 to 90 percent. I'm not sure even the most dovish Arab intellectuals are ready to take sides in that debate. In that sense, Ali Salem, a prominent Egyptian writer, may be right when he said: ''The call for a dialogue with the peace camp in Israel is justified, but it came too late.''</p>
        <p>Foreign Affairs</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
