<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Stage as King's County: Another 'Richard' Opens</title>
    <meta content="25RICH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Richard II (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFD6143EF936A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Stage as King's County: Another 'Richard' Opens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. J. R. BRUCKNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruckner, D J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D J R Bruckner reviews Pearl Theater Cop production of Richard II; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richards are dropping all over town these days. It started a couple of weeks ago with Richard III, wiped out in a Moonwork production at the Stella Adler Conservatory downtown. Both he and Richard II have been dispatched in Theater for New Audiences' presentations in midtown. Now Richard II buys it at the Pearl Theater Company's home on St. Mark's Place. All have drawn sizable audiences.</p>
        <p>Given that the plays involved are Shakespeare's most pointed political examinations of legitimacy in government, it is enough to make one wonder whether Americans are not more worried about their own situation than current polls suggest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richards are dropping all over town these days. It started a couple of weeks ago with Richard III, wiped out in a Moonwork production at the Stella Adler Conservatory downtown. Both he and Richard II have been dispatched in Theater for New Audiences' presentations in midtown. Now Richard II buys it at the Pearl Theater Company's home on St. Mark's Place. All have drawn sizable audiences.</p>
        <p>Given that the plays involved are Shakespeare's most pointed political examinations of legitimacy in government, it is enough to make one wonder whether Americans are not more worried about their own situation than current polls suggest.</p>
        <p>The Pearl's ''Richard II'' is the most familiar-looking of the productions: customary staging, Elizabethan costumes, no gimmicks. But Shepard Sobel, the director, has shifted the focus from Richard the man to the play's sharp political arguments in a way that makes this version appear more tough-minded than most. Here the tumult of the early scenes -- duels, banishments, confiscations and wars -- is only a buildup to the intense political debates of the last two acts.</p>
        <p>Richard still has all those elaborately metaphorical speeches that have made actors covet the role for 400 years, but they are subdued enough in this performance to seem reasonable, if self-justifying assertions, overheard amid the clamor of the usurpers of the throne and their opponents. (And because so much attention is shifted to the men struggling for power, all of them seem more shifty and sinister than usual.)</p>
        <p>Even two moments of gallows humor strengthen the impression that the political stakes are enormous: first, Act IV's scene in Parliament in which the nobles accusing one another of treason raise so many challenges to duels that the floor is littered with gloves, and one duke, having no gloves left, whips the gorget from his throat and slams it down as a gage; second, the argument between the Duke and Duchess of York, in the presence of the new King, Bolingbroke, about whether their son should be hanged.</p>
        <p>Altogether, the production is a forceful reminder, without pushing and prodding the audience, that there was good reason for governments under two monarchs in Shakespeare's time to be deeply concerned when this play was presented.</p>
        <p>Not unexpectedly in a repertory company, individual performances vary widely and sometimes distractingly. And there is a serious general defect: not a single phrase in this entire play is prose, but in this production there are hardly half a dozen lines together that anyone would recognize as poetry. Why does it seem so difficult for Americans to train actors to speak in measured cadences? In a play as richly wrought as this one, failing to do so risks losing the meaning of what the characters say.</p>
        <p>RICHARD II</p>
        <p>By William Shakespeare; directed by Shepard Sobel; stage manager, Lisa Ledwich; sets and costumes by Murell Horton; lighting by Stephen Petrilli; sound by Robert Murphy; properties, Karin Bagan; production manager, Tony Rust. Presented by the Pearl Theater Company. At 80 St. Mark's Place, East Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Bradford Cover (King Richard II).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
