<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tell Me What Street Compares With Mott Street</title>
    <meta content="12BERMANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001203T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1246893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berman, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diner, Hasia R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lower East Side Memories: A Jewish Place in America (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D91E30F931A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tell Me What Street Compares With Mott Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Berman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berman, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Berman reviews book Lower East Side Memories: A Jewish Place in America by Hasia R Diner; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lower East Side Memories</p>
        <p>A Jewish Place in America.</p>
        <p>By Hasia R. Diner.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 219 pp.</p>
        <p>Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $27.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lower East Side Memories</p>
        <p>A Jewish Place in America.</p>
        <p>By Hasia R. Diner.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 219 pp.</p>
        <p>Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $27.95.</p>
        <p>THE Jewish Lower East Side took root as early as the 1820's in the area that is now Chinatown, grew in the 1840's as a result of the German immigration and, beginning in the 1880's, blossomed into something enormous owing to masses of East European Jews, who came fleeing for their lives from the pogroms and miseries of the Czarist empire. By 1910, the Lower East Side, with half a million Jews, had become the largest and most densely populated Jewish neighborhood America has ever seen. And then, by the 1940's, the East Side Jews, having grown less poor and more Americanized, went streaming out of the wretched old tenements in search of the large green pasture known as the rest of the United States, and the neighborhood began to shrink. You might suppose that Jewish history on the Lower East Side had pretty much reached an end.</p>
        <p>But not so. The old Jewish neighborhood merely entered into a curious new phase, of which Hasia R. Diner, a professor of American Jewish history at New York University, has now made herself the historian. The neighborhood declined in real life while it rose in legend. Jews poured out and books poured in; instead of crowds of people, crowds of memory. The neighborhood was simultaneously abandoned and sacralized. Diner points to a children's book from 1951, ''All-of-a-Kind Family,'' by Sydney Taylor, as a sign of the new phase. The book described Jewish little girls who spend their afternoons at the public library and nibble greasy Jewish foods and speak in English to their Yiddish-speaking parents and generally live the life of the old Jewish neighborhood, in a highly scrubbed version -- just at the moment when the actual, unscrubbed neighborhood was fading into oblivion. And ''All-of-a-Kind Family'' was just the beginning.</p>
        <p>By the 1960's, literary critics and book publishers were rediscovering all kinds of novels that had been written about the old East Side many years before and had then been forgotten -- books by Abraham Cahan, Anzia Yezierska, Michael Gold and Henry Roth, which went on to enjoy a bigger success in paperback revival than had ever been theirs when originally published. Museums put on Lower East Side exhibitions. Historians produced major books. In 1976, Irving Howe brought out his masterpiece of historical writing, ''World of Our Fathers.'' There were romance novels. Hollywood brought out sentimental movies.</p>
        <p>The counterculture of the 1960's and 70's, in its Jewish enthusiasms, produced ''The Jewish Catalog,'' featuring everything you could possibly want in order to pursue a satisfying existence as a Jewish immigrant of 1910. Lower East Side kitsch began to appear on the walls of Jewish restaurants. And there was more. As Diner shows, synagogues and Jewish summer camps from as far afield as Texas and California began to stage re-enactments of Lower East Side life, where Jewish children would dress up like immigrants of long ago and pretend to speak Yiddish under a replica of the Statue of Liberty. And in those several ways, through the concerted action of highbrow critics, lowbrow critics, serious historians, schlock historians, Hollywood sentimentalists, hippies and summer camp counselors, the impoverished old neighborhood gradually lifted off the asphalt plane of past reality and went floating into the upper ether of the American Jewish imagination.</p>
        <p>The old neighborhood came to represent the early history of the American Jews as a whole and not just the people whose ancestors actually did live there. The neighborhood represented the hardships of immigration. And it represented, perhaps still more vividly, a Jewish world that seemed to have disappeared irretrievably into the past as soon as the East Siders or their children had achieved sufficient American success to move away.</p>
        <p>But how did the East Side manage to acquire so many meanings -- as ''the emblem,'' in Diner's phrase, ''of American Jewish history?'' The East Side was, in its day, the largest of the immigrant Jewish districts in America. But Diner points out that a good many Jewish immigrants ended up in Boston, Baltimore, Philadelphia and Los Angeles too. Chicago's Jewish zone contained some 200,000 people in the years after World War I, on streets that were no less colorful and exotic than any downtown peddler block in Manhattan. American Jews looking for roots could hardly gaze back on their ancestral homes in Europe, given the horrors of the Old World. But Diner does wonder why, in creating their legend, the American Jews refused to concede even a smidgen of mythic meaning to some of those other perfectly reasonable American neighborhoods or even to the Jewish districts of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>She offers several explanations, and the chief of them points to Manhattan's role as a center of both American publishing and American social reform. Journalists and do-gooders of a century ago, in their concern with immigration and poverty, found it natural and easy to direct their attention to the bedraggled East Side, which gave the neighborhood a celebrity that no other district could claim. And celebrity mutated into myth, eventually. Diner must be right about that. But her explanation tends to gloss over some neighborhood achievements that never did have anything to do with New York publishing or the curiosity of other people.</p>
        <p>Is it impolite, in this hour of stock market ecstasy, to mention that one of those achievements, back in the old days, had to do with socialism? The political imagination of the old East Side was dominated in some degree by the German Social Democratic Party and its American admirers, and when the East Side socialists grew sufficiently strong, they went about building an impressive series of institutions, some of which still survive. Diner says that after the neighborhood had gone into decline, the remaining Jews tended to be elderly and poor -- people who had been left behind in the flight uptown and to the suburbs.</p>
        <p>But, on the contrary, a large number of the remaining Jews lived and still live in a long strip of low-rise and high-rise socialist housing cooperatives along Grand Street and East Broadway -- nicely constructed, cheap housing for Jewish trade unionists and their families, some of the buildings fairly drab, others quite cleverly designed, with an artistic flair and brilliantly executed murals. It is true that in the year 2000 the last of these old cooperatives have begun to shed their socialist commitment in order to permit apartment sales on the open real estate market. Yet socialism made Grand Street grand, in its day. And when the modern American Jews look back at the old East Side through a veil of tears, aren't they looking back on a set of ideals, too, and on a passion for social justice that managed to thrive in the semi-European streets of New York for a good many years?</p>
        <p>I don't want to put too much emphasis on my own left-wing political nostalgias or on any other single feature of the modern Jewish myth of the old East Side. For there is something mysterious and profound in the phenomenon that Diner has described, the elevation of a grimy neighborhood into a golden legend -- a shadowy hint of Jewishness that goes deeper than anything that is allowed either by her explanations or by mine. The feeling that today's Jews are but pale reflections of a truer, authentic Jewish life; the feeling that Jewish greatness did once exist, but it was long ago; the feeling that some distant place and not the here-and-now was and is the authentic Jewish home -- those feelings do somehow spring up irrepressibly in the Jewish soul. The impulse doubtless begins with a religious yearning for the Jerusalem of ancient times. But it is a more than religious impulse. The Sephardic Jews of North Africa and the eastern Mediterranean have spent centuries pining for the lost Jewish life not just of ancient Judea but of medieval Spain.</p>
        <p>In a classic memoir of modern Jewish life, ''Out of Egypt,'' Andre Aciman recalls how his family fled the Arab revolution in Egypt only to end up engulfed by nostalgic yearnings for any number of other places -- for the Alexandria they had left behind, for Paris, for New York and even, of course, for Israel, where the family had never been. And so, if the modern American Jews, in gazing back on the tenements of downtown New York, have come up with one more exotic site to locate their Jewish yearnings, it is not just because America's Jews have left their traditions behind, but also because America's Jews have not left their traditions behind. As the French historian Pierre Nora nicely puts it, ''To be Jewish is to remember being Jewish.''</p>
        <p>Hasia Diner's book is short -- too short, because she fails to cite all kinds of cultural artifacts that have helped create the modern myth of the Jewish East Side. Then again, the book is not short enough, because of a sloppy tendency on her part to say, for example, on one page, ''The Lower East Side has become fixed in American Jewish memory as the site from which a singular story has been told,'' and, on another page, ''The Lower East Side came to be the place about which they told their stories,'' and, on still another page, ''The story of the Lower East Side has become almost universally understood to be synonymous with the story of Jewish life in America.'' And so forth, until you get a little impatient. Her book is not especially profound, philosophically speaking, and not especially acute as a work of cultural criticism. Her descriptions tend to make a single blur out of a masterwork like Howe's ''World of Our Fathers'' and a second-rate children's book like ''All-of-a-Kind Family.'' And yet, in her wanderings around the old East Side, Diner, the inspired historian, has found her way to a particular intersection that no one else has located quite so precisely. She has stumbled on the exact place where cultural identity, historical myth and geographical location run together, in a tangle of traffic and honking horns -- a strangely emotional place, as anyone can discover even now by turning a corner in the old neighborhood and suddenly noticing the remnant Hebrew letters on a rust-colored wall, or the brick shell of an old wrecked synagogue, symbols that seem much too deep and weighty ever to be deciphered.</p>
        <p>Paul Berman is the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968'' and the editor of ''Blacks and Jews.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 3, 2000, Sunday  A map of the Lower East Side of New York, published on Nov. 12 with a review of ''Lower East Side Memories: A Jewish Place in America,'' by Hasia R. Diner, carried a misattribution from the book. The map originated in ''The Promised City,'' a 1962 book my Moses Rischin, not with the 1939 ''W.P.A. Guide to New York City.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 3, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A map of the Lower East Side of New York, published on Nov. 12 with a review of ''Lower East Side Memories: A Jewish Place in America,'' by Hasia R. Diner, carried a misattribution from the book. The map originated in ''The Promised City,'' a 1962 book my Moses Rischin, not with the 1939 ''W.P.A. Guide to New York City.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Berman is the author of ''A Tale of Two Utopias: The Political Journey of the Generation of 1968'' and the editor of ''Blacks and Jews.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
