<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for a Respite</title>
    <meta content="12SUN1$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/12/opinion/12SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1246744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDD1338F931A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for a Respite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says any speculation about what awaits the next president and Congress must start with reality that Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush, two candidates with very different personalities and visions, produced evenly divided electorate; says next president will face a mandate problem that will force him toward tactics different from those of recent winners</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beleaguered citizens trapped in the war zone of an endless presidential election may find it hard to believe, but come Jan. 20 either George W. Bush or Al Gore will take office. We thought it might be useful to leap ahead and take a look at what awaits a new president and Congress. Any speculation must start with the reality that two candidates with very different personalities and visions produced an evenly divided electorate. Similarly, Democratic and Republican legislative candidates offering very different approaches to domestic issues led to a House and Senate with only a slight edge for the G.O.P. One question that hovers over all this is what kind of Washington the public really wants. Another is whether all this conflict and division will set the stage for ceaseless partisan conflict or inspire a new search from moderates on both sides for a bipartisan balance point.</p>
        <p>Many worry that the bitterness of the presidential contest will hang over whichever candidate wins the electoral vote. One hopeful sign -- a bare one -- was the Gore campaign's decision Friday to dial back its threats of litigation over the Florida results. The Bush campaign blustered unattractively about retaliatory ballot challenges in other close states, and yesterday sought a federal court injunction to prevent a manual recount in some Florida  counties. We have declared our strong preference for a prompt, dignified, non-litigious resolution to the presidential election. But however or whenever the end comes, the questions remain about what kind of political world we will all inhabit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beleaguered citizens trapped in the war zone of an endless presidential election may find it hard to believe, but come Jan. 20 either George W. Bush or Al Gore will take office. We thought it might be useful to leap ahead and take a look at what awaits a new president and Congress. Any speculation must start with the reality that two candidates with very different personalities and visions produced an evenly divided electorate. Similarly, Democratic and Republican legislative candidates offering very different approaches to domestic issues led to a House and Senate with only a slight edge for the G.O.P. One question that hovers over all this is what kind of Washington the public really wants. Another is whether all this conflict and division will set the stage for ceaseless partisan conflict or inspire a new search from moderates on both sides for a bipartisan balance point.</p>
        <p>Many worry that the bitterness of the presidential contest will hang over whichever candidate wins the electoral vote. One hopeful sign -- a bare one -- was the Gore campaign's decision Friday to dial back its threats of litigation over the Florida results. The Bush campaign blustered unattractively about retaliatory ballot challenges in other close states, and yesterday sought a federal court injunction to prevent a manual recount in some Florida  counties. We have declared our strong preference for a prompt, dignified, non-litigious resolution to the presidential election. But however or whenever the end comes, the questions remain about what kind of political world we will all inhabit.</p>
        <p>To state the obvious, this would be a good time for all sides, including the leadership of Congress, to step back and think about delivering something that even those voters caught up in the heat of the moment would probably welcome -- an easing of the recrimination and warfare in American politics.</p>
        <p>The harbingers are admittedly not great in  Congress. Under the Senate majority leader, Trent Lott, Republicans have been willing to tolerate shrinkage of their Senate majority as the price of maintaining a reflexive ideological ferocity. Even now, faced with the possibility of a tie in the Senate, Mr. Lott has stuck to his old ways by joking tastelessly about the possibility of lightning striking Hillary Rodham Clinton before she joins him in the Capitol. As Tom Daschle, the minority leader, said, the Senate rules are such that nothing can be done in that body without cooperation across the aisles. That is doubly true if this turns out to be a Senate that has 50 Democrats and 50 Republicans, and the vice president has to be called in to break ties. These factors, plus Mr. Lott's bellicosity, make it unlikely that the Senate could spark a new comity.</p>
        <p>Prospects may be better in the House, where the G.O.P. clings to the thinnest majority since the 1950's. The speaker, Dennis Hastert, has leadership potential if he can break free of fire-eaters like Tom DeLay. Last session, he worked with President Clinton and the Democrats on issues including trade with China.</p>
        <p>But the best chance for real progress will be the White House, notwithstanding that half of the voters will be unhappy with whoever moves in. Mr. Gore or Mr. Bush would have to try to govern from the center. On some issues, it will be difficult to find a middle ground. But the precarious equilibrium created by voters in Congress has also created an opportunity. Mr. Bush may have seen this possibility before the election when he said he would be the kind of president who would work with Democrats to bring about Medicare reform, a prescription drug benefit and an overhaul of Social Security. Mr. Gore was more combative, but as a senator from Tennessee he reached out to Republicans on foreign policy issues. And he has the experience to practice the almost forgotten presidential skill of charming the opposition.</p>
        <p>The next president will face a mandate problem that will force him toward tactics different from those of recent winners. President Reagan used his 1980 landslide to push an ambitious program of tax cuts, and he picked up the support of Democrats who either agreed with him or were scared to defy him. Although receiving only 43 percent of the popular vote in 1992, President Clinton was perceived as having a mandate on health care until his legislative effort hit the skids for lack of consultation with Congress. One test for the next president will be to consult with key members, no matter what obstacles Mr. Lott and like-minded battlers may erect.</p>
        <p>Our guess is that whoever wins the White House, the public will let him try to lead despite lingering unhappiness over the election. From Woodrow Wilson to John F. Kennedy to Mr. Clinton, American presidents have won pluralities and gone on to lead effectively if they communicated with the public and worked with Congress. After the spectacle of events in Florida last week, Americans should be ready for a respite from the fratricidal politics of the last several years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
