<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slimmer Carbonara</title>
    <meta content="15MINI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MINIMALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pasta</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/The Minimalist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pasta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DA1131F936A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slimmer Carbonara</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Bittman describes making a vegetarian spaghetti carbonara; recipe for spaghetti with zucchini and mint (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE excitement once associated with the first appearance of the true summer vegetables like tomatoes, cucumbers and corn has been diminished by their year-round presence in the markets. This, of course, is thanks to the fact that it's always summer somewhere and that long-distance shipping has become inexpensive and efficient.</p>
        <p>Still, nothing beats real seasonal produce, which is by definition local and therefore more likely to be fresher and tastier. And zucchini, among the first and most prolific of the midsummer vegetables, is at its peak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE excitement once associated with the first appearance of the true summer vegetables like tomatoes, cucumbers and corn has been diminished by their year-round presence in the markets. This, of course, is thanks to the fact that it's always summer somewhere and that long-distance shipping has become inexpensive and efficient.</p>
        <p>Still, nothing beats real seasonal produce, which is by definition local and therefore more likely to be fresher and tastier. And zucchini, among the first and most prolific of the midsummer vegetables, is at its peak.</p>
        <p>One of the best and most unusual uses for zucchini is as a substitute for meat in a kind of vegetarian spaghetti carbonara. Carbonara -- named for the charcoal producers who worked for weeks on end in the woods and depended on long-keeping ingredients for cooking -- was, for many Americans, one of the first pasta dishes they ate that was not swimming in tomato sauce. Tossed with egg, crisp bacon or pancetta and loads of Parmesan, it was a revelation. Since then, spaghetti carbonara has become something of a symbol for over-the-top pasta.</p>
        <p>Made with zucchini, the dish becomes a little less fat-laden. But because the backbone of the sauce remains eggs and Parmesan, it is still rich -- and quite delicious.</p>
        <p>This is one of those pasta sauces that can be put together in just about the time it takes to boil a gallon of water. And although there is almost no technique involved, there are a few points worth making:</p>
        <p>Be sure to cook the zucchini enough to brown it a bit, which will enhance its flavor.  The eggs will cook fully from the heat of the pasta. But if this makes you at all nervous, do the final tossing of eggs, cheese and pasta in the cooking pot, over the lowest heat.</p>
        <p>Use top-quality hard cheese, since its flavor will dominate. Genuine Parmigiano-Reggiano is probably best, but a good hard pecorino is nice in this dish, too.</p>
        <p>Mint is the herb of choice; its fresh taste is the most unusual aspect of this preparation. But you can substitute parsley or basil.</p>
        <p>SPAGHETTI WITH ZUCCHINI AND MINT  Time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>Salt to taste  3 tablespoons olive oil  3 or 4 small zucchini, about a pound, washed, trimmed and cut into slices  1/8 to  1/4 inch thick  Freshly ground black pepper to taste  2 eggs  1 cup freshly grated Parmigiano-Reggiano cheese  1 pound spaghetti, linguine or other long pasta</p>
        <p>1/2 cup roughly chopped mint, parsley or basil.</p>
        <p>1. Salt a large pot of water, and bring it to a boil over high heat. Put the olive oil into a 10- or 12-inch skillet over medium-high heat. A minute later, add the zucchini, and cook, stirring only occasionally, until very tender and lightly browned, 10 to 15 minutes. Season with a little salt and a lot of pepper.</p>
        <p>2. Beat the eggs and  1/2 cup of the cheese together. Add the pasta to the boiling water, and cook until it is tender but firm. When it is done, drain it, and combine it immediately with the egg-and-cheese mixture, tossing until the egg is cooked. Add the zucchini, and toss again. Taste, and add more salt and pepper if necessary.</p>
        <p>3. Toss in the herb, and serve immediately, passing the remaining cheese at the table.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>THE MINIMALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
