<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southern Bombing Fugitive Is Seen in North Carolina</title>
    <meta content="Y15BOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rudolph, Eric Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EFDC1E31F936A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southern Bombing Fugitive Is Seen in North Carolina</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal authorities say Eric Robert Rudolph, suspect in bombing of Alabama abortion clinic, emerged from woods of western North Carolina a week ago, took large amount of food and pickup truck from residence before abandoning truck and vanishing once more; will double team of agents pursuing Roberts; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After five and a half months in hiding, the man wanted in the bombing of an Alabama abortion clinic emerged from the woods of western North Carolina last week, took a large amount of food and a pickup truck from a residence, and then abandoned the truck and vanished once more, the Federal authorities said today.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Andrews, N.C., this afternoon, Federal investigators said the team of agents pursuing the man, Eric Robert Rudolph, would be more than doubled from its previous size of 35. Bloodhounds have also been tracking him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After five and a half months in hiding, the man wanted in the bombing of an Alabama abortion clinic emerged from the woods of western North Carolina last week, took a large amount of food and a pickup truck from a residence, and then abandoned the truck and vanished once more, the Federal authorities said today.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Andrews, N.C., this afternoon, Federal investigators said the team of agents pursuing the man, Eric Robert Rudolph, would be more than doubled from its previous size of 35. Bloodhounds have also been tracking him.</p>
        <p>''We think we have the resources that we will find him,'' said Woody Enderson, the F.B.I. agent who directs the multiagency Southeast Bombing Task Force.</p>
        <p>The sighting, last Thursday, was clearly the most encouraging lead in a search that has taken investigators across hundreds of miles of mountainous terrain since Jan. 29, when a bomb exploded outside the New Woman All Women Health Care Center in Birmingham, Ala.</p>
        <p>The bombing killed an off-duty policeman who was working as a security guard at the clinic and seriously wounded a nurse. Witnesses saw a man acting suspiciously shortly after the explosion, and the North Carolina license plate on the man's truck was traced to Mr. Rudolph.</p>
        <p>''This is a pretty significant step forward,'' Mr. Enderson said, ''because we now know for sure that he's in this area and that we are able to focus in on a much smaller area than we have before.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudolph, a 31-year-old carpenter with ties to extremist religious groups, is also wanted for questioning in three bombings in the Atlanta area in 1996 and 1997, including the explosion at Centennial Olympic Park on July 27, 1996. That explosion killed one woman and wounded 111 other people. Seven people were wounded in two explosions on Jan. 27, 1997, outside a building housing an abortion clinic in a suburb north of Atlanta, and five were wounded in a bombing at a gay nightclub in midtown Atlanta on Feb. 21, 1997.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Rudolph has been formally charged only in the Birmingham bombing, forensic evidence suggests that he may have been responsible for the Atlanta bombings as well, investigators have said. In May, the Federal Bureau of Investigation placed Mr. Rudolph on its list of the 10 most-wanted fugitives and offered a $1 million reward for information leading to his arrest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Enderson said the man identified as Mr. Rudolph appeared on Thursday evening at a residence near Nantahala Lake, not far from where Mr. Rudolph once lived. Mr. Enderson said the fugitive had taken a blue 1977 Nissan pickup truck from the occupant of the residence, whom he did not identify. He said Mr. Rudolph had also taken a large amount of food from the resident, possibly enough for five or six months.</p>
        <p>The authorities said the resident had given a description that enabled them to produce a new sketch of the previously clean-shaven Mr. Rudolph, showing him thinner, bearded and his hair in a ponytail. He was last seen wearing camouflage fatigues, a camouflage jacket, and gloves, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Enderson declined to say specifically whether the resident knew Mr. Rudolph.</p>
        <p>''Keep in mind that pretty much in this whole area, people know each other,'' he said. ''The extent of the association I'm not going to discuss.''</p>
        <p>A law-enforcement official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said the resident, described as the owner of a health food store, did not report the truck as stolen until several days after it was taken. It was found, broken down and abandoned, about noon on Monday at the Bob Allison Campground, part of the Nantahala National Forest, the official said. The official said the authorities had found a note inside the truck explaining whom it belonged to, and they identified the handwriting on the note as Mr. Rudolph's.</p>
        <p>The official said the truck apparently was not at the picnic area 18 hours before it was found, meaning that Mr. Rudolph has less than a day's head start on his pursuers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Enderson said his team had been energized by the sighting of Mr. Rudolph. And he sounded reassured by the discovery that Mr. Rudolph had apparently spent the last five months in the hills of western North Carolina. Officials had long said they assumed that Mr. Rudolph, an avid outdoorsman who has been described as a survivalist, was hiding in the familiar woods near his home.</p>
        <p>''We've said all along that we had strong reason to believe that Eric Rudolph was in this area, had not left this area, that he was alive, that he was acting alone,'' Mr. Enderson said. ''We still believe that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
