<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top of Lineup Spurs Comeback by Florida</title>
    <meta content="02MARL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/02/sports/baseball/02marlins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Marlins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Marlins</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Francisco Giants</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DE173CF931A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top of Lineup Spurs Comeback by Florida</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top of Lineup Spurs Comeback by Florida</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florida Marlins defeat San Francisco Giants, 9-5, to tie National League division series, 1-1; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Juan Pierre, the Marlins' leadoff hitter, completed his first postseason game on Tuesday by going without a hit and failing to reach base for one of the few times this season, the veteran Lenny Harris approached him in the visitors' clubhouse at Pacific Bell Park and again at the team's hotel off Union Square. Harris, whom Florida acquired in August as a bench player and motivational speaker, reminded Pierre why he had been so successful over 162 games and wondered why he had tried to change for one game.</p>
        <p>Pierre opened Wednesday's game against the Giants with a single to right field, and the Marlins, led by his speedy presence atop the lineup, rallied for a 9-5 victory. It tied the three-of-five-game National League division series at a game apiece heading to Game 3 in Florida on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Marlins, led by Juan Pierres speedy presence atop the lineup, rallied to beat the Giants, 9-5, in Game 2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Juan Pierre, the Marlins' leadoff hitter, completed his first postseason game on Tuesday by going without a hit and failing to reach base for one of the few times this season, the veteran Lenny Harris approached him in the visitors' clubhouse at Pacific Bell Park and again at the team's hotel off Union Square. Harris, whom Florida acquired in August as a bench player and motivational speaker, reminded Pierre why he had been so successful over 162 games and wondered why he had tried to change for one game.</p>
        <p>Pierre opened Wednesday's game against the Giants with a single to right field, and the Marlins, led by his speedy presence atop the lineup, rallied for a 9-5 victory. It tied the three-of-five-game National League division series at a game apiece heading to Game 3 in Florida on Friday.</p>
        <p>''It felt good to get that first hit,'' Pierre said. ''From there, I continued to roll.''</p>
        <p>A record crowd of 43,766 packed Pac Bell, surpassing the one here Tuesday and hoping that Barry Bonds and the Giants would again roll over the wild-card Marlins.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Marlins came back from 4-1 and 5-4 deficits and negated the advantage San Francisco had taken in Game 1, when Jason Schmidt fired a three-hit shutout and prevented Pierre and Florida's No. 2 batter, Luis Castillo, from reaching base in a game for just the seventh time this season.</p>
        <p>''If they don't get on, we're in trouble,'' Marlins Manager Jack McKeon said.</p>
        <p>Pierre said, ''I know I went to bed last night thinking about it.''</p>
        <p>Pierre had mostly slapped his way to 204 hits and a .305 batting average this season, and he had stolen 65 bases. On Tuesday, Harris noticed he was swinging harder to keep up with Schmidt's 95-mile-an-hour fastball. Reverting to form, Pierre went 4 for 5 with a steal in Game 2, scored three runs and drove in three.</p>
        <p>''I just tried to tell him, be patient,'' Harris said. ''You had 200-something hits this year. Do what got you here. The guy's throwing 90 miles an hour. He thought he had to swing harder because he was throwing hard. If he keeps doing what he's been doing, he'll be successful.''</p>
        <p>McKeon, 72, said Pierre was like a son to him, and who wouldn't want a leadoff hitter who is perpetually on base and a threat to run and can catch nearly everything hit toward the gaps in center?</p>
        <p>After San Francisco scored three times in the fourth for a 4-1 lead, the Marlins responded with three runs off Giants starter Sidney Ponson in the fifth, Pierre scoring the tying run on Ivan Rodriguez's two-out single.</p>
        <p>Pedro Feliz opened the Giants' fifth with a triple and scored on J.T. Snow's single, again giving San Francisco the lead, 5-4. But the Giants did not score again that inning after McKeon intentionally walked Bonds to load the bases with one out and Carl Pavano retired Edgardo Alfonzo and Benito Santiago on pop-ups.</p>
        <p>Juan Encarnacion led off the sixth for the Marlins with a homer off reliever Joe Nathan, and Florida added two more runs with two out on a wind-aided double by Pierre that fell on the warning track when right fielder Jose Cruz tripped in the corner. The Marlins had a 7-5 lead and, finally, some control over the game.</p>
        <p>The fog did not lift until late this afternoon, replacing the glare in the outfield with whipping winds, like those that blew Pierre's double from foul territory past Cruz. Giants Manager Felipe Alou lamented that the elements were not kind to his team, but he stopped as he walked out of the interview room after the game, reminding reporters of the Marlins' hit total and acknowledging that there was little defense for it.</p>
        <p>The teams that combined for six hits and two runs in Game 1 used 14 pitchers in Game 2. Florida had 15 hits, only two for extra bases.</p>
        <p>Pavano led a fleet of Marlins relievers to shut down the Giants. After starter Brad Penny and reliever Rick Helling allowed five runs in four and a third innings, five Florida relievers shut out San Francisco for four and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>Alou took over a team that went to the World Series a year ago, and during the regular season the Giants beat the Marlins in five of six games. Many Marlins, like Pierre and McKeon, are experiencing their first postseason; rallying to win today should eliminate any doubt that they can beat the Giants.</p>
        <p>''It sure helps a lot,'' Harris said. ''We have a bunch of young kids here that were disappointed from the way we lost yesterday. But I told them things are going to happen like that. That's what the playoffs are all about. Playing against the National League champions, things like that are going to happen. Stay above yourself and do the things that got you here. I think today these guys responded well. That's what they did. They did the little things.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
