<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Men Are Manly and So Are Bears</title>
    <meta content="26EDGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bears</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mamet, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tamahori, Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baldwin, Alec</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">linson, art</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Edge, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD1F3BF935A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Men Are Manly and So Are Bears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews film The Edge, written by David Mamet, directed by Lee Tamahori and starring Anthony Hopkins and Alec Baldwin; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles Morse (Anthony Hopkins) is a brilliant billionaire with a nice airplane, a beautiful trophy wife (Elle Macpherson) and a spectacular Alaskan hunting lodge rented as the setting for his latest birthday celebration. According to ''The Edge,'' a barbed, great-looking adventure film written cannily by David Mamet and directed with verve and fury by Lee Tamahori (''Once Were Warriors''), all this is very, very bad. It's soft. It's empty. It's complacent. In terms of manly accomplishment, it can't compare with the thrill of battling a hungry bear.</p>
        <p>Enough of the fashion world, which lionizes Charles's wife, Mickey, as a superstar model; enough of the theoretical knowledge that Charles gleans from books. ''The Edge'' has something quite a bit more rugged in store. And so Mr. Mamet gleefully constructs what is, pardon the expression, a gnawing tension between Charles and Bob Green (Alec Baldwin), the cagey fashion photographer who resents Charles's wealth and seems to covet his wife. Meanwhile, Mr. Tamahori brings on Bart, whose credits include television's ''Grizzly Adams.'' Mr. Hopkins, whose creative collaboration with Bart goes back to ''Legends of the Fall,'' has called him ''the John Wayne of bears.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charles Morse (Anthony Hopkins) is a brilliant billionaire with a nice airplane, a beautiful trophy wife (Elle Macpherson) and a spectacular Alaskan hunting lodge rented as the setting for his latest birthday celebration. According to ''The Edge,'' a barbed, great-looking adventure film written cannily by David Mamet and directed with verve and fury by Lee Tamahori (''Once Were Warriors''), all this is very, very bad. It's soft. It's empty. It's complacent. In terms of manly accomplishment, it can't compare with the thrill of battling a hungry bear.</p>
        <p>Enough of the fashion world, which lionizes Charles's wife, Mickey, as a superstar model; enough of the theoretical knowledge that Charles gleans from books. ''The Edge'' has something quite a bit more rugged in store. And so Mr. Mamet gleefully constructs what is, pardon the expression, a gnawing tension between Charles and Bob Green (Alec Baldwin), the cagey fashion photographer who resents Charles's wealth and seems to covet his wife. Meanwhile, Mr. Tamahori brings on Bart, whose credits include television's ''Grizzly Adams.'' Mr. Hopkins, whose creative collaboration with Bart goes back to ''Legends of the Fall,'' has called him ''the John Wayne of bears.''</p>
        <p>This madly scenic film, photographed in splendid Canadian wilderness settings by Donald M. McAlpine, begins more or less innocently with a fashion shoot, as Mickey and entourage arrive at the lodge in search of a pristine setting. Mr. Tamahori, whose specialty is the domestic powder keg, knows how to invest even these benign moments with plenty of menace. There's something about Mickey's gaiety at Charles's surprise party. Something about how she gives him a pocket watch engraved ''From the luckiest woman in the world.'' Something about the way Bob gives him a knife.</p>
        <p>Next day, under the stewardship of the crusty Peckinpah veteran L. Q. Jones as the lodge's proprietor, Mickey is posing with feathers and arrows in her coiffure and an arrowhead hanging as an earring. But Bob, a purist, seeks deeper authenticity. He wants to find the Indian who posed in one of the proprietor's pictures, and so he and Charles and an assistant named Stephen (Harold Perrineau) go off for a short hop on their seaplane. Then the plane goes down and suddenly it's survivalist time. Cue Bart.</p>
        <p>There's no need to worry that Mr. Mamet is on foreign territory with this action premise. ''The Edge'' succeeds ably in blending his famously acerbic dialogue with nerve-racking adventure scenes. Surveying the glorious wilderness, Bob remarks that this experience is changing his perspective: ''Little different from the fashion world. Little different from snortin' coke off the girls' hipbones.''</p>
        <p>Charles, calmly: ''In what way?''</p>
        <p>''Charles, you know, you're starting to loosen up,'' Bob tells him appreciatively. ''That's my report.''</p>
        <p>Despite the levity, someone in the film does quite graphically become the bear's breakfast. And Bob and Charles engage in a wild fight, one that ends with the two men lying exhausted on a carcass, huffing and puffing in almost postcoital contentment. ''All my life I wanted to do something unequivocal,'' Charles declares, which is much of the film's point.</p>
        <p>''The Edge'' also enjoys the power games that keep the rich man and his wife's admirer on their respective toes.</p>
        <p>''Never knowing who your friends are, never knowing what people value you for,'' muses Bob, another many-shaded Mamet schemer captured craftily by Mr. Baldwin. ''Must be tough.''</p>
        <p>Charles, no less shrewd and played with marvelous sang-froid by Mr. Hopkins, has another way of looking at it: ''Never feel sorry for a man who owns a plane.''</p>
        <p>And so, while Charles demonstrates his prowess at making a compass from a leaf and paper clip or a fishing lure from his birthday watch, Bob zeroes in on the essence of their rivalry. Pure Mametese and words to live by, since the aloof tycoon (a la ''The Game'') is Hollywood's latest endangered species: ''Now it's the broad, now it's the boodle, and nothing is safe.''</p>
        <p>''The Edge'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes profanity and bear-related gory violence in the wild.</p>
        <p>THE EDGE</p>
        <p>Directed by Lee Tamahori; written by David Mamet; director of photography, Donald M. McAlpine; edited by Neil Travis; music by Jerry Goldsmith; production designer, Wolf Kroeger; produced by Art Linson; released by 20th Century Fox. Running time: 120 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Anthony Hopkins (Charles Morse), Alec Baldwin (Bob Green), Elle Macpherson (Mickey Morse), L. Q. Jones (Styles), Harold Perrineau (Stephen) and Bart (the Bear).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
