<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Madrid Journal; Eyes Are on Banker: His on Politics?</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="564391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONDE, MARIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONDE, MARIO (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D7133AF933A15753C1A964958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Madrid Journal; Eyes Are on Banker: His on Politics?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his slicked-back dark hair, elegant suits, matador physique and reputation for ruthlessness, Mario Conde became a role model for an entire generation of young Spaniards who believed that finance was the way to the top in the new Spain of the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>A decade earlier, political or academic careers were still the fashion. But by 1988, when Mr. Conde became president of the Banco Espanol de Credito, a money fever had seized Spain. Only 37 years old at the time, the high-profile banker was seen as proof that the country had changed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his slicked-back dark hair, elegant suits, matador physique and reputation for ruthlessness, Mario Conde became a role model for an entire generation of young Spaniards who believed that finance was the way to the top in the new Spain of the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>A decade earlier, political or academic careers were still the fashion. But by 1988, when Mr. Conde became president of the Banco Espanol de Credito, a money fever had seized Spain. Only 37 years old at the time, the high-profile banker was seen as proof that the country had changed.</p>
        <p>Today, the shine has gone off Spain's boom. The peseta lost 10 percent of its value against the German mark last month, business confidence has been shaken and many highly paid young brokers and financial operators are beginning to wonder what the future holds for them.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Conde continues to fascinate Spaniards. Some deride him as the personification of the get-rich-quick mentality that has now tumbled the economy into trouble. Others look to him as a Ross Perot-like outsider who, at the right moment, could step in to save Spain from its politicians. 'Never Attracted' by Politics</p>
        <p>Sitting in the quiet elegance of his bank's head office, he once again brushed aside the widely held view that his secret ambition is to become Prime Minister. "For the last five years, people have been saying that sooner or later I will enter politics," he said. "It has never attracted me."</p>
        <p>"For a time, there was a big difference in the polls between the Socialist Government and the conservative opposition and some journalists would write about me," he added. "But now the Socialists are losing points and the conservatives are gaining in the polls, so it's not even logical."</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, more than any other Spanish businessman, he continues to maintain a high public profile, albeit carefully managing his image. While gossip magazines follow the night-time antics of Spain's "beautiful people," Mr. Conde appears in photographs alongside the likes of Pope John Paul II and former Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain. The Democratic Way</p>
        <p>More significant, he is not shy about voicing opinions on the country's affairs. After Denmark rejected a new treaty on European union in a referendum in June, for example, he said Spaniards should also vote on the treaty rather than simply watch its ratification by Parliament.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Felipe Gonzalez dismissed the suggestion, but after France ratified the treaty by the narrowest of margins in a referendum last month, Mr. Conde felt vindicated.</p>
        <p>"What's being proposed in Europe is a path to political union, and people didn't know this," he said. "Nor did they in France. Isn't it democratic to ask their opinion?"</p>
        <p>Now he is needling the Government for promising that despite the peseta's weakness, Spain will be among the first countries to adopt a single European currency. "It's nice to say this, but is it realistic?" he asked. "Isn't it more logical to say, if it involves great risks to the economy to achieve this in two or three years, why not take a little longer?"</p>
        <p>What perhaps most feeds suspicions of Mr. Conde's political ambitions is his interest in communications. Although his name has been associated with many publications, he said Banesto invested only in a newspaper that is now defunct, El Independiente, and holds shares in El Mundo as a collateral for a $800,000 loan. A Business Decision</p>
        <p>But this summer, in a joint venture with Rupert Murdoch and a Spanish entrepreneur, Antonio Asencio, he took control of Antena 3, one of the country's new commercial television channels. And since then, his many enemies have held up some of the station's programs as evidence that it is furthering his political agenda.</p>
        <p>"We made an entirely business decision to be part of Antena 3," he said. "We have to deal with the real Spain. And in it, communications companies are important and earn money. But that's not being in politics unless you think of everything as politics. And in that sense, you can influence politics from a major company or a bank."</p>
        <p>Certainly, it was as a banker that he first won headlines. Born into a modest Galicia family, he went to the Banco Espanol de Credito, which is known as Banesto, from careers as a Government lawyer and a pharmaceutical industry executive. But he immediately made his mark by fighting off a hostile takeover and soon followed up by filling the bank's board with his own supporters.</p>
        <p>In 1990 he separated Banesto's industrial holdings from the bank and placed them in a new corporation, but his plan to sell shares in London and New York in what was advertised as "1 percent of Spain's gross domestic product" fell through when Iraq invaded Kuwait. Since then, he has begun selling off some of the bank's non-financial assets.</p>
        <p>For his critics in the press and the Government -- his relations with the Economy Minister, Carlos Solchaga, have always been tense -- the best way that Mr. Conde could be buried politically, of course, would be for his bank to slide into trouble. And only this month, Madrid newspapers were speculating about a new rebellion brewing inside Banesto's board. 'There'll Be Plenty to Do'</p>
        <p>Mr. Conde lighted his fourth cigarette of the interview and waved his hand dismissively. "There's nothing to that," he said. "But journalists have to find something to write. Look, when an economy goes into crisis, banks always reflect it. But Spanish banks are well capitalized, and I think we'll have fewer problems than banks in some other countries."</p>
        <p>So will he be satisfied with simply getting richer? "Thanks to the luck of life, I have earned more than enough. My objective is to run the bank group efficiently. So, you'll say, 'Yes, that's fine for a while, but the day will come when this isn't enough.' Well, yes. On that day, there'll be plenty to do."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
