<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Rumson, N.J.;Abundant Space, And on the Water</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="829099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUMSON (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHESLOW, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDB1539F932A25751C0A960958260" item-length="1611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Rumson, N.J.;Abundant Space, And on the Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY CHESLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHESLOW, JERRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FLANKED by the Shrewsbury and Navesink Rivers and just a mile west of the Atlantic, Rumson has been a magnet for wealthy New York financiers for more than a century.</p>
        <p>In the 1890's, bankers and industrialists like Jacob Schiff built estates of  dozens of acres and commuted by boat across New York Bay to lower Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FLANKED by the Shrewsbury and Navesink Rivers and just a mile west of the Atlantic, Rumson has been a magnet for wealthy New York financiers for more than a century.</p>
        <p>In the 1890's, bankers and industrialists like Jacob Schiff built estates of  dozens of acres and commuted by boat across New York Bay to lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>At the time, Rumson Street was the showplace of New Jersey," said Mayor Charles Callman. "People would drive here just to get a look at the beautiful estates, with their large houses and spectacular gardens."</p>
        <p>Today, the natural beauty of the 5.2-square-mile Borough of Rumson continues  to attract Wall Street bankers many of whom commute to the Monmouth County community on an Express Navigation ferry from the nearby Highlands to Pier 91 just north of the South Street Seaport. The one-way fare is $11. The 1990 census showed that a third of all houses in Rumson were valued at more than half a million dollars and a third of all households had six-figure annual incomes. Among the more expensive homes are several built by well-known architects, including Stanford White.</p>
        <p>Fewer than two dozen houses are under construction, with all but a handful being marketed for more than $700,000. The largest property in Rumson, a 30-acre estate complete with 32-room mansion, outbuildings and stables, is on the market for $3.95 million.</p>
        <p>THE profile of the couples moving in here is that they are in their 30's and  40's with one or two children," said P.J. Rotchford, Manager/Broker at Gloria Nilson Realtors in Rumson.</p>
        <p>"They know that Manhattan is not where they want to raise their children and  can afford something special."</p>
        <p>Among the newer residents are Christopher J. Evans, his wife, Deborah, and their 3-year-old daughter. They moved to Rumson from Manhattan in December 1992  because, Mr. Evans said, he "has a thing about being on the water." Their home is a renovated Dutch colonial on three quarters of an acre, backing up to the Navesink River.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans says he likes the fact that Rumson has large properties, keeping congestion down.</p>
        <p>"Many people buy a summer home and use it on weekends or their wives and kids stay in the Hamptons while they spend the week in Manhattan and go home for the  weekend," said Mr. Evans, a 37-year-old Wall Street money manager. "My goal was  to have just one house, but it had to be in a recreational environment."</p>
        <p>MAYOR Callman is quick to point out that many houses are available for less than $150,000. Most are tiny, turn-of-the-century converted bungalows or capes on small lots on streets like Meadowbrook Road, Maplewood Road or Ward Lane in an area known to old-timers as Cartontown, perhaps because of the small size of its bungalows. Some of the original owners of those homes worked on the large estates prior to World War I, according to George Moss, a borough councilman and local historian.</p>
        <p>There are no cookie-cutter neighborhoods in Rumson. On many streets throughout the borough, small ranches, capes and colonials that sell for $200,000 to $300,000 are next to larger, custom homes on more than an acre that  sell for a million dollars or more. Mr. Moss attributes this to the way in which large, turn-of-the-century estates were broken up.</p>
        <p>"After World War I, the men came home from overseas, where they learned that  there was a future beyond serving the owners of the large estates," Mr. Moss said.</p>
        <p>"So the large estates lost their source of inexpensive labor and found it impractical to keep so much land. So they started dividing the land and selling  off parts of it for construction. That process continues to this day. Therefore, you have mansions near small houses."</p>
        <p>There are only 40 condominium town houses in the borough. They are in a complex called Rumson Park, off River Road. The two-bedroom units with one-car garages sell for $165,000 to $180,000, Mr. Rotchford said.</p>
        <p>By far the most famous resident of Rumson is the singer Bruce Springstein, who has a brick-and-wood mansion with turrets on five acres off Rumson Road.</p>
        <p>The house is shielded from prying eyes by large artificially created hills of earth.</p>
        <p>There are three small business districts within a quarter of a mile of each other on River Road, a main thoroughfare that links the borough to Red Bank. They contain the usual complement of banks, boutiques, delicatessens, bagel shops and hairdressing salons.</p>
        <p>There is also a wide variety of restaurants, including Barnacle Bill's and Hook, Line and Sinker, both of which serve seafood, Fromagerie (continental), Briody's (American), Val's Tavern (Italian) and What's Your Beef, a steakhouse.</p>
        <p>The Rumson Market, similar to an old general store, is a gathering place for  locals. No neon lights are permitted in the borough, making many of the business establishments barely distinguishable from local houses.</p>
        <p>The only apartments in the borough are over some of the stores in the business districts and are designated as nonconforming. Rents are about $750 a month for two bedrooms.</p>
        <p>FOR supermarket shopping, residents go to neighboring Red Bank, Fair Haven or Little Silver. The closest large mall is the Monmouth Mall in Eatontown, six miles southwest.</p>
        <p>No one knows for sure what the name Rumson means. One old story, vehemently denied by Mr. Moss, is that the borough land was bought from the Leni Lenape Indians in the late 17th century for "some rum." The name may be a shortened version of the Indian name for the area, Narrumsum, which appears on a deed of sale of the land by the 11 Indians to a group of Englishmen from Long Island on  April 7, 1665, for L359.</p>
        <p>Rumson was mostly a farming community with a few large estates until 1870, when a drawbridge was built across the Shrewsbury River, linking Rumson to the Borough of Sea Bright and convenient boat travel to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>This set off a wave of estate building by New York society.</p>
        <p>AMONG the institutions founded by the residents of the estates was the Sea Bright Lawn Tennis and Cricket Club on Rumson Road in 1877, just four years after tennis was introduced to the United States. The club, which has 15 courts, is listed in the National Register of Historic Places and has been designated by the Department of the Interior as a National Historic Landmark.</p>
        <p>The club has a two-year waiting list for membership. The initiation fee is $4,500 per family, with an annual fee of $650 per player.</p>
        <p>Also in the borough is the Rumson Country Club off Ward Avenue, which includes an 18-hole golf course and tennis courts.</p>
        <p>Other recreational facilities include the five-acre Victory Park, donated to  the borough in 1920 by Bertram H. Borden, an estate owner and former president of the board of education.</p>
        <p>The park, off River Road, has two tennis courts, a basketball court and a large gazebo, which is sometimes used for concerts.</p>
        <p>The largest park is the 23-acre Meadow Ridge Park off Ridge Road. It has two  baseball diamonds, two soccer fields, a tot lot and walking paths.</p>
        <p>In addition, according to Mayor Callman, the Navesink and Shrewsbury Rivers offer some of the finest fishing in New Jersey, including striped bass, bluefish and flounder.</p>
        <p>Rumson's children attend the Deane-Porter School from kindergarten through third grade, followed by the ForrestdaleSchool for grades four to eight, which share a campus on Forrest Avenue. According to the New Jersey State Report Card, the district spent 10 percent less than the state average of $7,738 per student  last year but paid 10 percent more per teacher in salaries.</p>
        <p>"We are trying to attract the best and the brightest teachers from across the country," said the Superintendent of Schools, Dr. Jack Woodbury. "We want them to be good examples for our students. That's one of the best ways to build lifelong learners."</p>
        <p>Both Forrestdale and Deane-Porter have25-computer laboratories and at least one computer per classroom. According to Dr. Woodbury, all graduates of Forrestdale are proficient in the use of both I.B.M.-compatible and Macintosh computers.</p>
        <p>On last year's New Jersey State Early Warning Tests, Forrestdale eighth graders scored seventh highest of the 640 schools in the state. The students also take the Educational Records Bureau Test, which is used mainly by wealthier districts and private schools.</p>
        <p>IN almost all subjects, Rumson students from grades three to eight exceeded the average scores of other public schools and matched those of most independent schools.</p>
        <p>From Forrestdale, the students go on to the 650-student Rumson-Fair Haven Regional High School, which sent more than 95 percent of its 130 graduating seniors to higher education last year.</p>
        <p>There is one parochial school, the Roman Catholic Holy Cross School on Rumson Road, for kindergarten through eighth grade. There is also a nonsectarian private school, the Rumson Country Day School on the corner of Ridge Road and Bellevue Avenue, for the same grades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
