<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>"I wonder what's on the PC tonight."</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERACTIVE (TWO-WAY) TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKOFF, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DC1739F93BA35756C0A962958260" item-length="3044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>"I wonder what's on the PC tonight."</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKOFF, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO know Dana Law is to know that the future of television may be a lot gloomier than powerful cable-industry figures like John Malone and Gerald Levin have been saying. And that the future of the personal computer industry may be a lot brighter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Law, 40, who makes his living as a magician and a psychic, spends a lot of time in front of the tube in his house in El Cajon, near San Diego. He gets the latest news and weather, sends and receives electronic mail, shops and checks travel guides to find out where to eat out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO know Dana Law is to know that the future of television may be a lot gloomier than powerful cable-industry figures like John Malone and Gerald Levin have been saying. And that the future of the personal computer industry may be a lot brighter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Law, 40, who makes his living as a magician and a psychic, spends a lot of time in front of the tube in his house in El Cajon, near San Diego. He gets the latest news and weather, sends and receives electronic mail, shops and checks travel guides to find out where to eat out.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Law's tube is not a television. It's a computer, hooked to the local cable system. "It runs like the wind now," he said. "It's amazing what's available. And I'm getting sound and pictures that I wasn't getting before."</p>
        <p>A few years ago Mr. Law might have seemed unusual. Now, however, there are millions of Americans like him, and the number is growing fast. They are people who can operate their personal computer as effortlessly as they can drive a car, who are as comfortable with a computer as with a television set. And they are people who would rather spend their time in front of a PC than a TV.</p>
        <p>Such people are giving pause to the big-name companies in a variety of industries that have gambled with much fanfare that it is the television, not the personal computer, that will be the portal to the many "interactive" services already here or on the horizon. Among those services are home shopping, video games that can be played with someone elsewhere, electronic mail, video conferencing, and news and information retrieval.</p>
        <p>These companies, including Time Warner, Tele-Communications Inc., AT&amp;T, Viacom, US West and Bell Atlantic, have invested a lot of money and credibility in dozens of field tests of interactive television in places like Queens, N.Y., Orlando, Fla., and Alexandria, Va. Now, almost overnight, they are realizing that the personal computer may be the place to be.</p>
        <p>"For interactive applications the personal computer is going to win," said Nicholas Negroponte, director of the Media Laboratory at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, which receives financing from both the personal-computer and television industries.</p>
        <p>The argument of the companies betting on television as the best way into the American home is simple: Almost everyone has a TV, and almost everyone is far more comfortable using a TV than a PC. Sounds like the argument buggy makers made after the Model T was introduced 85 years ago.</p>
        <p>But just as improvements on the automobile made it far more appealing and affordable, advances on the personal computer are making it much easier to operate, much more useful and much less expensive. For example, the newest generation of personal computers have chips powerful enough to run video with the resolution and lack of jerkiness of a television picture.</p>
        <p>So ubiquitous and familiar will the personal computer become, particularly among younger Americans, that it will soon be the most indispensable tool in the information age, says the economist George Gilder. As a result, many communications, computer and entertainment companies are reversing course and scrambling to invest in interactive services that can be used on the personal computer instead of -- or at least as well as -- on the television.</p>
        <p>For example, Tele-Communications, the largest cable operator, has joined with Microsoft, the largest software company, to test software that allows a personal computer access to data bases over TCI's cable network.</p>
        <p>Viacom, the cable and entertainment giant, is developing multimedia games and educational programs that will blend the interactivity of a CD-ROM with the format of an MTV or a Nickelodeon. For example, personal computer users might someday tap into the cable network to receive video games on a pay-per-use or subscription basis, or tune in to interactive television programs that permit the viewer to take the role of one character and change the outcome as the show progresses. And in its Castro Valley, Calif., trial of interactive services, Viacom now plans to experiment not only with television but also with the personal computer.</p>
        <p>These companies are joining many computer, software and information companies that have already recognized the potential of the PC for interactive services and are rushing to capitalize on it. Later this year Microsoft plans to release a new version of its Windows operating system that will simplify the process of connecting personal computers to cable and telephone networks. The Intel Corporation plans to introduce next month a modem that hooks a personal computer to cable-television lines and allows PC users to receive information from the cable network more than 2,000 times faster than through a conventional telephone modem. And in San Diego, Prodigy, the nation's largest on-line computer service, has tapped into the high-capacity local cable lines, allowing it to offer customers like Mr. Law not only text but sound, pictures and, soon, video.</p>
        <p>Now that personal computers can offer video of television quality, many software publishers expect to announce entertainment and educational products to be delivered over cable networks and phone lines to PC users. Microsoft is developing interactive programs including ones that allow home banking and the gathering of sports statistics. And early next year, Prodigy, in cooperation with the ESPN cable network, plans to offer its users video clips of sports highlights.</p>
        <p>For investors, the implications are obvious. Personal computer makers like I.B.M., Compaq and Apple all stand to gain, as do chip makers like Intel and Motorola and software companies offering educational or entertainment programs, like Microsoft, Broderbund and Electronic Arts. Companies with a big stake in developing the devices for interactive television, including Silicon Graphics, General Instrument and Scientific-Atlanta, stand to lose. And other companies that committed money and time to experiments in interactive television stand to be embarrassed.</p>
        <p>The advantage enjoyed by the personal computer over the television may not last beyond the next few years, however. There is much debate about what the "home information appliance" will look like a decade from now. One view -- call it the Ronco Dicer Slicer Approach -- is that a single device combining all the attributes of a computer and a television will emerge. It will have a high-definition screen and a controller that is a cross between a remote-control wand and a keyboard.</p>
        <p>But there is an increasingly accepted school of thought that there will someday be not one but many devices in the home. Like kitchen appliances today, information appliances a decade from now will each have a different function. The personal computer and the TV will both be so affordable that the average family will think nothing of having one or more of each, as well as other information appliances, like smart telephones.</p>
        <p>But for now, at least, it is the personal computer, not the television, that is becoming an increasingly powerful magnet. The TV Vision</p>
        <p>The vision of interactive television, as espoused by executives like Mr. Malone of Tele-Communications Inc.  and Mr. Levin of Time Warner, is of a futuristic version of the cable-converter box atop the family TV. It would bring into the home an avalanche of new services -- any movie, any time; video games that would allow many players in many places; home shopping and banking; electronic mail and information services. It would be easily operated even by the technically unsophisticated by means of a simple wand that could act like an existing remote-control device or like a personal- computer mouse.</p>
        <p>Everything from the box atop the TV, known as a set-top controller, to giant computers that would distribute the services over the cable network has had to be designed, and is now being tested in various communities.</p>
        <p>Among the most passionate defenders of this vision are executives at Time Warner, which has tested such a system in Queens and plans another test for Orlando, Fla., starting this fall, and at Silicon Graphics Inc., which is designing the set-top controller for Time Warner. They argue that entertainment viewed on the television, not other services offered on the personal computer, will be the driving force that brings interactivity to most Americans.</p>
        <p>"How many American homes even have a den for the personal computer?" said Ed McCracken, chairman of Silicon Graphics. "At a personal computer you sit there and do things and the computer reacts. In the entertainment world the television does things and you react to it. This is going to be about entertainment." The PC Vision</p>
        <p>But now this vision is being challenged by the growing realization that desktop computers and their networks are no longer the realm of scientists and hobbyists. More than 5 million people in this country will be subscribing to commercial on-line services by the end of the year, up from 3.9 million last year, according to Jupiter Communications, a New York market-research firm.</p>
        <p>The Internet, the network that connects on-line services as well as students, scientists and Government employees, is growing even more quickly, and now counts 20 million computers worldwide -- roughly the number of homes viewing last week's most popular TV show, "Seinfeld."</p>
        <p>Executives at Intel point out that almost 30 percent of the nation's homes already have personal computers, a figure that will rise to well above 50 percent by the end of the decade. And 52 percent of the homes with incomes between $50,000 and $100,000 a year have PC's, as well as 65 percent of homes above $100,000, according to Link Resources, a market-research firm in New York.</p>
        <p>Even computer industry executives say they have been surprised by how rapidly the personal computer is being adopted in the home. "We in the computer industry thought our business was in corporations," said Avram Miller, vice president for business development at Intel. He said that last year 45 percent of the personal computers with Intel chips were shipped to homes rather than businesses and that revenue from the sale of personal computers surpassed that from color televisions in the United States.</p>
        <p>Also favoring the personal computer is the advantage it currently enjoys over the television in what it can offer. Most of the services envisioned for interactive television, like home shopping and information retrieval, are already available over the personal computer from on-line services like Prodigy, Compuserve and America On-Line. And they are becoming easier to use, thanks to the addition of point-and-click controllers and improvements in on-screen graphics.</p>
        <p>The computer has other advantages, too. It has a display screen that offers higher resolution than the television screen, which has been locked into the same resolution for more than five decades and is unlikely to change before the end of the century. This means that the personal computer can produce higher-quality video.</p>
        <p>Also, the computer is easier to read on than a television. People are generally about 18 inches from their computer screens, as opposed to 9 feet from a TV. Many interactive services require a lot of reading.</p>
        <p>Those differences mean that, while the television holds the advantage for watching programs and movies as a family, the personal computer is better for just about everything else.  The Price Factor</p>
        <p>Interactive television may have another Achilles heel -- cost. In its trial in Orlando, Time Warner will use a set-top box that costs the company $5,000 apiece. For a similar trial in Castro Valley scheduled by Viacom, AT&amp;T's Bell Laboratories has developed a box that will cost $4,000 apiece.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the main cost of connecting a personal computer to the local cable or phone system is a special modem. Companies including Zenith that sell this device are charging about $400. But that price will soon come down to around $100, about the cost of a conventional modem, said Scott Kurnit, an executive vice president at Prodigy.</p>
        <p>The cable companies say that the trials are strictly to demonstrate the feasibility of interactive television and that set-top controllers will fall rapidly in price before they hit the market, making them affordable to the average cable customer within three years.</p>
        <p>But many critics of interactive television doubt that the price will drop so quickly.</p>
        <p>These critics also question whether interactive television can be financed by revenues from the sale of movies, which is what its proponents are counting on to finance the construction of more sophisticated systems that offer more services. "Everyone is talking about video-on-demand as the 'killer app' for interactive television," said Robert Alexander, a New York consultant, "but I don't think that stands up."</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander estimated that it would cost $100 billion to deploy an advanced electronic network to most American homes. That works out to about $1,000 per home, although even that number will seem optimistic at least until 1996 or 1997.</p>
        <p>He then assumed that the price per movie in the interactive television trials would be $1 to $4, generating an hourly rate of 50 cents to $2 per hour, of which the cable operator would clear 25 cents to $1.</p>
        <p>Then he estimated that the cable industry would require a 15 to 20 percent return on its investment. If that is true, it would require $20 billion in revenue, equal to 20 to 80 billion hours of movies on demand.</p>
        <p>If the figure were 50 billion hours, that would work out to about 500 hours per household -- 10 hours per week, or 5 movies a week for every household in the country.</p>
        <p>"It's not disloyal to say that this kind of activity is simply not in the cards," Mr. Alexander said. "Something besides movies-on-demand will have to pay for the new networks." Cable Disappointments</p>
        <p>The new openness toward the personal computer can also be attributed to the collapse of some big mergers between cable and telephone companies that shared a vision of interactive television. Among those broken deals: the TCI-Bell Atlantic merger, and the Cox Enterprises-Southwestern Bell combination.</p>
        <p>"As a result of the failure of the mergers, people who have content are looking to the 'den' solution rather than the 'living room' solution," said Mitchell Kapor, the software developer, referring to the den as the room where the PC is often found.</p>
        <p>One more reason that prospects for the personal computer are brighter is that the cable industry has been slowing its investment in the modernization of its networks, an upgrade that is more necessary for interactive television than for interactive personal computing. Last week, for example, Time Warner said it would cut capital investment by $100 million. Tele-Communications said in February that it would delay $500 million in new spending until the Government clarified its regulatory position.</p>
        <p>The disadvantages of interactive TV have led to a new willingness among many companies to consider the computer. "If we have customers using PC's we intend to serve them," said Robert Thompson, senior vice president at Tele-Communications.</p>
        <p>This new awareness shows in many recent industry moves.</p>
        <p>In recent months Tele-Communications has drawn nearer to Microsoft, a company with a "PC-centric" view of the world. The two companies, which last year came close to creating a company with others including Time Warner that would produce software for the set-top controller, are now jointly exploring Microsoft's technology for both personal computing and interactive television.</p>
        <p>And now that the Pentium chip from Intel and the Power PC chip from I.B.M., Motorola and Apple allow personal computers to run television-quality video, a number of companies are planning to bring out entertaining or educational software that offers sound and video.</p>
        <p>For example, 20th Television, a subsidiary of Rupert Murdoch's Fox Inc., recently dispatched a top executive, Matt Jacobson, to lead an effort to develop interactive programming for Delphi, the parent company's on-line personal computer service, which Mr. Murdoch bought last year.</p>
        <p>Prodigy has taken a particularly strong interest in linking the personal computer to cable systems. In the company's trial in San Diego, subscribers who link their PC's to a cable system can get Prodigy almost 70 times faster than it comes into their homes by a telephone modem. Combined with the more powerful personal computers available, this means that Prodigy customers can now receive sound and video.</p>
        <p>Prodigy recently decided to introduce the cable connection commercially. Before the end of the year it will be available in 12 cities. (The company wouldn't name them.) Other Ventures</p>
        <p>Entrepreneurs are also leaping toward interactive services over the computer. For example, last year Carl Malamud, a Washington computer network expert, introduced Internet Talk Radio. Each week, with the sponsorship of computer and software companies, Mr. Malamud broadcasts a half-hour radio show. People who use powerful computer work stations can listen to Mr. Malamud's program, which includes news and interviews from the computer industry and which is broadcast "digitally" as ones and zeroes over a computer network and then converted to sound on the computer.</p>
        <p>Last week Mr. Malamud went a step farther and added video that can be viewed on computer work stations tapping into the Internet. "The future isn't 500 channels coming out of cable TV," he said. "It's going to be a personal computer that will be used in ways the cable companies never thought of."</p>
        <p>At least one television personality has also jumped from television to personal computing. Adam Curry, a "video jock" on Viacom's MTV channel, established an address on the Internet last year that offers a newsletter, music and videos.</p>
        <p>Last month Mr. Curry left MTV to devote himself entirely to the new personal computer medium. In a letter announcing his resignation last week he said that the Internet "is surpassing all traditional media, with its ever increasing global audience; the power is unlimited, and it's in the hands of the people, finally!"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
