<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Return to Amherst and the Pioneer Valley</title>
    <meta content="16ADOB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="686016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FRUGAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Frugal Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2D61131F93BA35756C0A962958260" item-length="2558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Return to Amherst and the Pioneer Valley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SPANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SPRING in the Pioneer Valley of central Massachusetts is a glorious affair; almost all the trees bear lacy pink and white flowers, and you cannot step out of doors without smelling their perfumes. Or so I recalled, having spent my student years at Mount Holyoke, one of the colleges - Amherst, Smith, Hampshire, and the University of Massachusetts are the others - situated around the town of Amherst, a veritable New England Oxford. I had often contemplated returning is the valley to sample the season's pleasures, but had been deferred by the price. Renting a car from New York for three days costs almost $200, and even if you take the train to Springfield for a mere $51 round trip, you need to rent a car to reach the Five College Area. Amtrak offers service to Amherst as well, but the train, on its way to Montreal, stops in town at 2:40 A.M., and leaves for New York at 1:15 A.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SPRING in the Pioneer Valley of central Massachusetts is a glorious affair; almost all the trees bear lacy pink and white flowers, and you cannot step out of doors without smelling their perfumes. Or so I recalled, having spent my student years at Mount Holyoke, one of the colleges - Amherst, Smith, Hampshire, and the University of Massachusetts are the others - situated around the town of Amherst, a veritable New England Oxford. I had often contemplated returning is the valley to sample the season's pleasures, but had been deferred by the price. Renting a car from New York for three days costs almost $200, and even if you take the train to Springfield for a mere $51 round trip, you need to rent a car to reach the Five College Area. Amtrak offers service to Amherst as well, but the train, on its way to Montreal, stops in town at 2:40 A.M., and leaves for New York at 1:15 A.M.</p>
        <p>Last month, though, I called the Peter Pan bus company and learned that the round-trip fare between New York and Amherst is $37.95, with about 10 departures a day. The Amherst Chamber of Commerce helped me find a small local concern called North Amherst Motors where I reserved a car for $29.95 a day, and provided me with a list of lodging options, including the venerable Lord Jeffery Inn right on the town common, with 50 handsomely appointed rooms that rent for $80 to $120. As I was looking for something less expensive, I called several bed and breakfasts in the area and booked three nights in three different private homes for $40 to $65. Then I packed jeans, turtlenecks and clogs - if I could no longer be mistaken for a student, I could at least try to blend in - and boarded the bus at the Port Authority Terminal.</p>
        <p>It was pouring rain, and the trip north via New Haven, Hartford and Springfield was a boring four and a half hours long; but the bus driver treated his passengers like a brood of dizzy chicks, making sure everyone made the right connections. I spent much of the trip remembering how, as a very green freshman, I approached the area for the first time, also on a Peter Pan bus. As we neared Northampton (our first stop in the Five College Area), I saw fingers of dingy snow on the flanks of Mount Tom, crocuses in the mud at the bus stop and yellow-green coronas around the budding trees. Clearly, high spring was several weeks away; still, the interseasonal sogginess seemed a sign of life and raised another memory from my freshman year, that star of English Lit !, Cheucer, and a professor who delighted in reading aloud from ''The Canterbury Tales.''</p>
        <p>I was trying to remember what comes after ''When that April with his shoures soote'' as the bus stopped alongside Amherst Common. The gently sloping greensward is bordered by the gracious edifices of Amherst College, which was founded in 1821 by, among others, Noah Webster and Samuel Fowler Dickinson, grandfather of Emily.</p>
        <p>Both the town and the college were named for Lord Jeffrey Amherst, as his first name is usually spelled in reference books.</p>
        <p>A British Army general, he is said by some accounts to have devised a plan to decimate the Indian tribes of New England by infecting them with smallpox.</p>
        <p>Lord Amherst never visited the town and is hardly dearly beloved.</p>
        <p>Standing in a puddle, gazing at the mist-shrouded campus on the hill, I felt gratified to see that little had changed since the days when, with a heart full of trepidation, I used to come to Amherst for mixers. After a 10-minute walk through a neighborhood of lovely turn-of-the-century homes northwest of the campus where the poets Eugene Field and Robert Frost once lived, I arrived at the door of the Lincoln Avenue Bed and Breakfast, a capacious yellow Victorian with a broad front porch. There was no sign out front, and no one at home except a cat, though I had been told the owner would be there. The door, however, was unlocked, so I entered, a little like Goldilocks. Inside I found spotless polished wood floors, two front rooms almost completely devoid of furniture and a stack of business cards indicating that besides running a B &amp; B, the mistress of the house taught yoga and practiced acupressure, presumably in the empty rooms.</p>
        <p>Hoping that there was more furniture in a bedroom upstairs, I left my bag and ventured back into the rain.</p>
        <p>I had a cappuccino and a slice of pumpkin bread for about $2.50 at a college hangout on the common called Bonducci's Cafe, noting that the students still favored the Lands' End look with holes. Then I cut a damp swath across the common, stopping at the Robert Frost Library, 750,000 volumes strong and one of the few modern buildings on campus, where I collected a Five College Calendar of Events and studied it. It was never too late to avail myself of the valley's cultural riches, I decided.</p>
        <p>The Mead Art Museum, 200 paces beyond the library, came at the right price - free. It lies beside mighty Stearns Steeple, bereft of the church it pinnacked when it was built in 1873 (the church was demolished to make way for the museum); at intervals no one seems to be able to predict, chimes still resound from the steeple in memory of the college's Civil War dead. The museum is notable for its early American painting, for a protrait of a rather wan Lord Jeffery Amherst, by Sir Joshua Reynolds and the gorgeously paneled Rotherwas Room, built in 1611 in Herefordshire, England, and carted across the Atlantic for the Long Island Jacbean-style mansion of Herbert Lee Pratt, an Amherst benefactor.</p>
        <p>THE college's Museum of Natural History just to the south of the gallery (admission free) also bears the Pratt name, and is a pleasantly old-fashioned place, with glass-topped wooden display cases, two aquariums humming in the background and not a soul around when I visited. There I found three petrified dinosaur eggs and a topographical model of the valley, showing the low Holyoke Range to the south of Amherst, the great oxbow of the Connecticut River near Northampton, and a bit of the hill country stetching up toward New Hampshire and Vermont.</p>
        <p>As darkness fell, I returned to my B &amp; B and met the people who lived there, Bonnie Novakov-Lawlor, barefoot and wearing a floor-length dress, her husband, Larry, a set designer and painter, and their young son, Josh. Bonnie showed me to my pretty room at the front of the house on the third floor, with a single sleigh bed, rocking chair, small desk and lace-curtained window. The large, immaculate bathroom, which I shared with two other guests, was several steps away, and had a clawfoot tub (with shower) and skylight: a terrycloth robe was provided to ease my passage down the hall. The place was homey - I could smell dinner cooking and hear the family at the table - and made me feel ike a grad student who had rented a room for the semester.</p>
        <p>I had dinner at Boltwood's Tavern in the Lord Jeffery Inn, less expensive than the hotel's formal dining room. A nicely presented grilled tuna steak and glass of California Merlot cost $19 with tip. However, I found better and more economical fare later at several of Amherst's cafes and ethnic restaurant, like Paradise of India on Main Street, where a heaping lunchtime portion of chicken biryani cost $5.25. Several doors down is the Black Sheep Cafe, a casual, woody place, with old Joni Mitchell songs piped in, delicious hazelnut coffee and a begulling pastry case. And at Bell's Pizza, near the University of Massachusetts, I was happy to learn that the tuna grinders (submarine sandwiches) are just as good as they used to be, not to mention just as cheap (about $3).</p>
        <p>That night I attended a concert called Women's Singing Traditions of New England in Buckley Recital Hall at Amherst for $12. It was nicely done, and the product of considerable ethnographic research, as the program explained, with female singers performing traditional music brought to this country by immigrants from French Canada, Bulgaria, Ireland, Greece, Portugal and Africa. But during the concert my eyelids drooped, and later I wished I had caught the ''Five by Scorsese'' film program across campus instead.</p>
        <p>The next day was devoted to touring, beginning with a job past Emily Dickinson's handsome brick homestead on Main Street (open by appointment), where I peeped in the window sacrilegiously, but caught no sight of the reclusive poet's ghost. After a nondescript breakfast at my B &amp; B, Larry was kind enough to give me a lift to North Amherst. Motors, where I collected my ear, drove back to campus and took a tour of the college, led by an exuberant sophomore named Amanda, with wire-rimmed spectacles. The rest of the group consisted of a serious-looking young woman who had just been accepted by Amherst and her parents. As we traipsed across campus, I noted the new computer center and the bike path that leads all the way to Northampton, and learned that Amherst, which went coed in 1976, has a student body of 1,600, now about equality divided between the sexes.</p>
        <p>After the tour I browsed through the shops in the center of town, including the Jeffrey Amherst Bookstore, with a whole floor-to-ceiling shelf of volumes on Emily Dickinson, and stopped in at the Allen House Victorian Bed and Breakfast on Main Street, a B &amp; B in a Stick-style Victorian home built in 1886. The Allen House, which has five bedrooms, all with private baths, was full when I called earlier in search of a room, which I really regretted once I saw the inn's hand silk-screened wallpaper, cherrywood maniels and glorious late 18th-century antiques, among them an Eastlake bed in which I yeared to sleep.</p>
        <p>And I ended the day with a visit to my alma mater, Mount Holyoke, in the hamlet of South Hadley, about 10 miles south of Amherst. Founded in 1837, it is the oldest women's college in the country, with a handsome campus designed by Fredrick Law Olmsted. There I paused by the grave of the founder, Mary Lyon, and thought about tender scenes from my past.</p>
        <p>I spent the night at the Northfield Country House, about 20 miles north of Amherst along Route 63, an idyllic country road perfect for biking. The B &amp; B is a fieldstone and brown-shingle manor house secluded on a hilltop above the peaceful little town of Northfield. It has seven bedrooms that share four baths, a yawning stone fireplace in the living room and massive chestnut beams. My room had a double bed with a quilt spread and white wicker furniture, and the proprietor was graciousness itself, serving me a full breakfast the next morning and telling me about the hill towns' love affair with contra dancing, traditional line dances.</p>
        <p>After leaving, I toured two of the 13 restored Colonial-era homes in Old Deerfield Village, bought a pair of shoes in Northampton, took in the Monets, Picassos and Seurats at the Smith College Museum of Art, and strolled among the luxuriant greenery at Smith's Lyman Plant house. Exhausted, I bedded down in another B &amp; B, called The Knoll, in the little town of Florence, just west of Northampton. Surrounded by 16 acres of farmland and forest, it was a peaceful spot, and my doubled-bedded room was comfortable, but I liked the tub in the bathroom down the hall best - it was so long I could stretch out in it fully. During my 13 hours at the Knoll, I took two baths.</p>
        <p>Really, though, I should have stayed in Amherst all three days of my visit, preferably at the Allen House; that way, I could have avoided renting a car by taking the free Five College bus that runs around the valley during the academic year. My lodging bill would have been roughly the same, about $175 for three nights, as would meals and entertainment, which cost me under $100 for three very full days; but my transportation expenses would have been $37.95 rather than $113. And I should have gone in May, just to smell that thickly perfumed air.</p>
        <p>But I'm not complaining: I still have my memories.</p>
        <p>The bottom line in Amherst</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>Peter Pan, a member of the National Trailways Bus System, (800)237-8747, offers a round-trip rate between New York and Amherst of $37.95.</p>
        <p>Amtrak, (212)582-6875, has train service to Amherst from New York for $52 round trip, and to Springfield from New York for $51 round trip.</p>
        <p>Getting Around</p>
        <p>The Five College Bus System operates during the academic year along four different routes between Mount Holyoke in South Hadley; Hampshire College, the University of Massachusetts, Amherst and Smith College in Northampton. No fare is charged and anyone can use it. For schedules, call (413)588-5806.</p>
        <p>Free, student-led tours of the Amherst College campus begin at the Office of Admissions, (413)542-2328. From May 31 to Sept. 2 they will be offered from Monday to Friday at 10 A.M., noon, 2 and 4 P.M.</p>
        <p>North Amherst Meters, 78 Old Sunderland Road, North Amherst, (413)549-2880, has a fleet of rental cars that include compact models renting for $29.95 a day, not including tax or insurance. The first 100 miles a day are free, with a charge of 20 cents a mile for each additional mile.</p>
        <p>Valley Bicycles, 319 Main Street, Amherst, (413)256-0880, rents bikes by the half day ($10), day ($18), weekend ($35) and week ($60).</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The Amherst Area Chamber of Commerce, 11 Spring Street, Amherst, Mass. 01002, (413)253-0700, is open Monday to Friday from 9 A.M. to 3:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>I can supply information on accommodations as well as area attractions and restaurants.</p>
        <p>The Alien House Victorian Bed and Breakfast, 599 Main Street, Amherst, Mass. 01002, (413)253-5000, has five rooms with private baths. Full breakfast and afternoon tea. Rates from $45 to $105.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Avenue Bed and Breakfast, 242 Lincoln Avenue, Amherst, Mass. 01002, (413)549-0517, has three bedrooms with a shared bath. The room rate is $65, with breakfast.</p>
        <p>Northfield Country House, 181 School Street, Northfield, Mass. 01360, (413)498-2692, has seven bedrooms that share four baths.</p>
        <p>Rates from $50 to $80, with a full breakfast.</p>
        <p>The Knoll Bed and Breakfast, 230 North Main Street, Florence, Mass. 01060, (413)584-8164, has three rooms that share two baths. Single $45, double $55 and $60.</p>
        <p>Berkshire Bed &amp; Breakfast Homes, (413)268-7244, is a reservation service that offers B &amp; B style accommodations in private homes in western Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Rates vary from $45 to $185 a night. It charges an $8 booking fee.</p>
        <p>S.S.</p>
        <p>FRUGAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
