<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Markets; Doing Business in Eastern Europe</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD103AF930A15751C1A966958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Markets; Doing Business in Eastern Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Fuerbringer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Based on just the numbers, American businesses have been cautious, if not timid, about setting up shop in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>American companies were responsible for only 3 percent of the acquisitions made by foreigners in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union during the first three quarters of this year, and only 14 percent of the joint ventures, according to a study by KPMG Peat Marwick and Bloc Magazine, which covers business developments in the area. This left the United States in third place, behind Germany, with 59 percent of the acquisitions and more than 38 percent of the joint ventures, and France, with 13 percent and 18 percent, respectively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Based on just the numbers, American businesses have been cautious, if not timid, about setting up shop in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>American companies were responsible for only 3 percent of the acquisitions made by foreigners in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union during the first three quarters of this year, and only 14 percent of the joint ventures, according to a study by KPMG Peat Marwick and Bloc Magazine, which covers business developments in the area. This left the United States in third place, behind Germany, with 59 percent of the acquisitions and more than 38 percent of the joint ventures, and France, with 13 percent and 18 percent, respectively.</p>
        <p>Some critics argue that Americans are missing an opportunity. But others contend that the environment in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union is still too difficult to operate in. Laws are unclear, distribution is difficult and, most important, getting profits home, especially from the Soviet Union, is a nettlesome problem.</p>
        <p>In addition, the political outlook is still very uncertain, a point driven home last week by the unexpected resignation of Eduard A. Shevardnadze, the Soviet Union's Foreign Minister. In a speech to a stunned Congress of People's Deputies, Mr. Shevardnadze sounded a warning about his country's future that could only give investors more reasons to stay away. "A dictatorship is approaching," he said. "No one knows what this dictatorship will be like, what kind of dictator will come to power and what order will be established."</p>
        <p>But the numbers also show -- as do some other major joint venture negotiations that are still in progress -- that of all the difficult investment environments that American companies might choose, they seem to prefer the biggest and most difficult, the Soviet Union, risk and all.</p>
        <p>Of the 34 American joint ventures begun this year in what had been the Communist bloc, 15 are in the Soviet Union. The American participants include Warner Brothers, Arthur Andersen, Ernst &amp; Young, Bechtel Group, Honeywell, Gillette, U S Sprint and Otis Elevator.</p>
        <p>And if the Soviet Union can avoid a descent into anarchy, five other major American companies are waiting to set in motion the largest group venture to date.</p>
        <p>These are the five members of the American Trade Consortium -- Chevron, Archer-Daniels-Midland, RJR Nabisco, Eastman Kodak and Johnson &amp; Johnson. Their point man is James R. Giffen, chairman of the Mercator Corporation, the consortium's merchant bank. The consortium has been working for years to design a deal that would allow its members to bring their profits out of the Soviet Union. So far, without a project in operation, they have spent about $120 million.</p>
        <p>While they are wary of the shifting political situation, Mr. Giffen and executives at several of the member companies said that some agreements have been signed and others will be ready to be completed early next year. RJR Nabisco has joined with the Eritsky factory in Leningrad to make Winston cigarettes and expects to begin manufacturing in the first half of next year. Another agreeement has been reached for a biscuit plant outside Moscow.</p>
        <p>The key to the entire venture is Chevron. It is working on a joint production deal with the Soviets on the Tengiz field, northeast of the Caspian Sea. Containing an estimated 25 billion barrels of oil, the field is the Soviet Union's largest discovery in 25 years. A Chevron spokesman said the company is in the final stages of negotiation.</p>
        <p>The other four companies will be making products to be sold in the Soviet Union, allowing them to tap a vast market while bringing to the public many of the consumer goods that the Soviets lack. These products would be sold for rubles, which normally would make such a venture unattractive.</p>
        <p>But the dollars that the Soviets will earn from selling their share of the oil from the Chevron joint venture will be used to turn the ruble profits of the other four companies into dollars that can be taken home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giffen, who has just returned from the Soviet Union, is not put off by the troubled transition process going on there. Indeed, he said the problems Mr. Gorbachev is facing were to be expected.</p>
        <p>But as he described the difficulties of making deals in the Soviet Union, and the uncertain road ahead for the Gorbachev Government, he sounded like he was trying to warn prospective investors away from any Soviet joint venture now.</p>
        <p>"You don't want to be there this week or next week," he said, when asked if this were the case. But he added, "If you ask me if I am worried about Gorbachev, my answer is, 'No.' There is nobody who can take his place.</p>
        <p>"The trick of this whole thing," he continued, "is the fact that we have not gone forward with any of these joint ventures and that we won't go forward until we can minimize the risk as much as possible."</p>
        <p>But he allowed there is an outcome that could scotch the consortium's plans. "We designed this to operate in a planned economy, a market economy and a transition economy," he said. "What it can't operate in is instability."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
