<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rambo Christmas for the Kids</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIOLENCE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, MARY E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HOME ALONE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1E3DF930A15751C1A966958260" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rambo Christmas for the Kids</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary E. Mitchell; Mary E. Mitchell is a writer.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, MARY E</byline>
      <dateline>NEWTONVILLE, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The other night, I saw a Christmas movie in which a little boy leaves a church and goes home and shoots two men in the genitals and face.</p>
        <p>Since it was described to me as a family movie, we brought the children along. They heard the little boy's family call him a disease, an incompetent and a jerk. They saw the mother exile the child to a dark attic after he told her he was frightened of the attic. They watched five healthy overfed kids snivel, gripe and tease and insult each other, while residing in a mansion filled with VCR's, sports equipment, toys, silver and priceless antiques.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The other night, I saw a Christmas movie in which a little boy leaves a church and goes home and shoots two men in the genitals and face.</p>
        <p>Since it was described to me as a family movie, we brought the children along. They heard the little boy's family call him a disease, an incompetent and a jerk. They saw the mother exile the child to a dark attic after he told her he was frightened of the attic. They watched five healthy overfed kids snivel, gripe and tease and insult each other, while residing in a mansion filled with VCR's, sports equipment, toys, silver and priceless antiques.</p>
        <p>The movie is called "Home Alone" and while it may sound like "Christmas on Elm Street," it's billed as a comedy. At the box office, it's trumping "Rocky V," grossing millions and nearly breaking records for opening weekend revenues. Kids, drugged by the powerful spirit of Christmas, are standing in line every night with their mommies and daddies to see it.</p>
        <p>And I'm trying to understand why "Home Alone" doesn't scare the pants off them.</p>
        <p>A boy's mother discovers, while applying lipstick in her first-class plane seat, that she's forgotten to bring her son along on the trip. The father, hearing the news, throws up his hands when they land in Paris, then goes to his hotel to freshen up. The film's metaphorical Saint Nick, a nice old man with a beard, saves the boy -- after the lad has shot, torched, fried and cut two burglars -- by bashing the burglars' faces with a heavy shovel.</p>
        <p>The action is interspersed with shots of Christmas creches and lovely, soft snowfalls. But violence is what the movie is about -- violence that would make Rambo blush. Against the backdrop of John Williams' beautiful original music, we learn that home is not where the hearth is but where the hot iron is. Indeed, a hot iron falls hard on the face of a man whose thuggish sidekick later threatens to chew a boy's fingers off, one at a time. In "Home Alone," violence is a chuckle. Abandonment is amusing. Cruelty is a boffo part of modern family life.</p>
        <p>It's filled with Christmas lights and pine wreaths, but there's no peace on earth or good will toward men. Call me old-fashioned, but I believe that some things should stay old-fashioned -- and Christmas movies is one of them.</p>
        <p>When I was a kid, things came out good for everyone in Christmas stories: Rudolph and the dentist-elf tamed the Abominable Snowman; the Grinch found his heart at the edge of a steep cliff; a senile angel restored Jimmy Stewart's will to live. Nothing like this happens in "Home Alone," and I scratched my head the whole way home, wondering why the movie is such a smash.</p>
        <p>How can a Christmas story stray so far from the formula and still be so successful? Even Bill Murray, while butchering "A Christmas Carol" several years ago in "Scrooged," ended it all nicely in a burst of comic generosity. When I brought my kids to see that movie, it was still possible to leave with a tear in my eye, our arms linked together as we walked to the car.</p>
        <p>Not so with "Home Alone." I left this movie with a bad taste in my mouth and it wasn't the Milk Duds. Why were we tittering nervously about shooting and burning and child neglect?</p>
        <p>Do parents often forget their kids? my younger child asked on the way out. I looked into her sweet brown eyes, not so sure I wanted her to hear the truth. No, honey, I finally told her, they only do that if it sells tickets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
