<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At AIDS Conference, a Call to Arms Against 'Runaway Epidemic'</title>
    <meta content="Y29VIRU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piot, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D9153FF93AA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At AIDS Conference, a Call to Arms Against 'Runaway Epidemic'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Participants at 12 World AIDS Conference in Geneva, Switzerland, urge national leaders to muster political courage to carry out strong prevention programs to stop global epidemic; UN AIDS program director Peter Piot warns world is facing runaway epidemic of AIDS; says time has come to embrace new realism and urgency in efforts to overcome complacency about human immunodeficiency virus (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pleas for national leaders to muster the political courage to carry out strong prevention programs to stop the global epidemic of AIDS were sounded at the opening of the 12th World AIDS Conference here today.</p>
        <p>Saying that the world is facing a ''runaway epidemic'' of AIDS, Dr. Peter Piot, the head of the United Nations AIDS program, told the conference that ''it is time to embrace a new realism and a new urgency in our efforts'' to overcome complacency about human immunodeficiency virus, which causes AIDS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pleas for national leaders to muster the political courage to carry out strong prevention programs to stop the global epidemic of AIDS were sounded at the opening of the 12th World AIDS Conference here today.</p>
        <p>Saying that the world is facing a ''runaway epidemic'' of AIDS, Dr. Peter Piot, the head of the United Nations AIDS program, told the conference that ''it is time to embrace a new realism and a new urgency in our efforts'' to overcome complacency about human immunodeficiency virus, which causes AIDS.</p>
        <p>''This epidemic is out of control at the very time when we know what to do, and what to do now,'' Dr. Piot said in pointing to areas in Africa where one in four adults is infected with H.I.V.</p>
        <p>Other speakers said there was clear and increasing evidence that condoms for men and women, sex education, public information campaigns, short courses of drugs to reduce mother-to-child transmission of H.I.V, needle exchange programs for users of injectable drugs and other measures can prevent H.I.V.</p>
        <p>The condom for women, speakers said, was giving women more choice in protecting themselves against H.I.V. More than 18 million such  condoms have been sold since 1992. The United Nations has negotiated a program in which four million condoms for women were sold in developing countries last year at a cost of 50 to 90 cents, compared with $2 to $3 in the United States.</p>
        <p>Scores more millions of condoms for men have been sold to combat H.I.V. since the AIDS epidemic was discovered in 1981.</p>
        <p>Such preventive measures have slowed down H.I.V. infection rates in developed countries and a few developing countries like Senegal, Thailand and Uganda.</p>
        <p>But, ''Why is it, despite our efforts, that 16,000 people a day are still getting H.I.V. when the infection is preventable?'' Dr. Piot asked. ''It's a collective failure of the world.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ruth Cardoso, the wife of the President of Brazil, said that ''the AIDS epidemic is a global public health priority.''</p>
        <p>''Governments everywhere must be called upon, once and for all, to stop adopting the self-defeating attitude of downplaying the problem's urgency and to take on the fight against AIDS as a major priority,'' Dr. Cardoso said.</p>
        <p>Brazil ranks fourth on the United Nations' list of infected countries,  with 580,000 adult carriers of H.I.V. AIDS is Brazil's second-leading cause of death in people ages 20 to 49,  Dr. Cardoso said. In Brazil, she heads a government-civilian program to combat poverty and social ostracism.</p>
        <p>Ruth Dreifuss, the Swiss Minister of Interior, Health and Social Affairs, said, ''The benefits of targeted prevention campaigns far exceed their supposed negative effects.''</p>
        <p>''Sex education and the promotion of condoms among young people works and does not lead to an increased number of sexual partners,'' Ms. Dreifuss said.</p>
        <p>Drug users have access to free needle exchange programs in Switzerland, and Ms. Dreifuss said that  that had drastically reduced the sharing of needles, a source of H.I.V. transmission. She also said that 87 percent of the Swiss population supported such measures.</p>
        <p>Critics pointed to the United States Government's lack of financial support for needle exchange programs, which researchers have shown to be effective in reducing H.I.V. infections. In April, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, Donna E. Shalala, endorsed the use of needle exchanges but declined to give  communities Federal money to run such programs.</p>
        <p>Asked about the discrepancy between the scientific findings and the Clinton Administration policy on needle exchange programs, Dr. Helene Gayle, who heads the AIDS program at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, said: ''We all know that science should be the basis of our policy. But it's not a perfect world. People in policy roles juggle a lot of things. Needle exchange is a complex issue in a complex world.''</p>
        <p>Financing for prevention has not kept pace with the epidemic, and in some cases has actually declined as the number of people affected by H.I.V. has increased, Dr. Peter Lamptey, who heads an AIDS program for Family Health International in Research Park Triangle, N.C., said at a separate meeting on AIDS prevention here today.</p>
        <p>With more than 13,200 scientists, health workers, government officials and representatives of anti-AIDS groups registered on the first day, the world conference is the biggest such meeting since the first was held in Atlanta in 1985.</p>
        <p>More than 10 million people have become infected with H.I.V. since the last AIDS conference in Vancouver in 1996. About half are under age 25.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
