<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani as Usual</title>
    <meta content="08MARC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muhammad, Khalid Abdul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D9123EF93BA3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani as Usual</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis contends that New York City Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani was upholding his image as pugnacious leader by supporting New York City Police Department for storming stage at Harlem youth rally and concluding that speech of its chief organizer, Khalid Abdul Muhammad, was inflammatory and riot police had no recourse but to act (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To hear Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani tell it yesterday, the largest and best Police Department in the country simply had to storm a stage at a Harlem youth rally on Saturday. The concluding speech of its chief organizer, a peripheral preacher of hate named Khallid Abdul Muhammad, was so inflammatory -- ''telling people to shoot and kill police officers'' -- that the riot police had no recourse but to slap down their face guards and seize the spotlight.</p>
        <p>Very few have dared to champion the words and actions of Mr. Muhammad, who has vanished in a puff of anti-Semitic exhaust. But that has not absolved Mr. Giuliani from criticism. Some believe that the Mayor's defense yesterday -- which also included a now customary attack on the news media -- obfuscates what they say is at the root of the rally's ugly denouement: the imposition of Mr. Giuliani's will upon any activity that he finds distasteful or not in keeping with his quality-of-life vision for the City of New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To hear Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani tell it yesterday, the largest and best Police Department in the country simply had to storm a stage at a Harlem youth rally on Saturday. The concluding speech of its chief organizer, a peripheral preacher of hate named Khallid Abdul Muhammad, was so inflammatory -- ''telling people to shoot and kill police officers'' -- that the riot police had no recourse but to slap down their face guards and seize the spotlight.</p>
        <p>Very few have dared to champion the words and actions of Mr. Muhammad, who has vanished in a puff of anti-Semitic exhaust. But that has not absolved Mr. Giuliani from criticism. Some believe that the Mayor's defense yesterday -- which also included a now customary attack on the news media -- obfuscates what they say is at the root of the rally's ugly denouement: the imposition of Mr. Giuliani's will upon any activity that he finds distasteful or not in keeping with his quality-of-life vision for the City of New York.</p>
        <p>They argue that the city's abrupt ending of the rally -- so startling that it prompted several minutes of minor violence -- did not occur in a vacuum. Since the Mayor began his second term in January, a growing number of judges and constitutional lawyers have complained that his policies infringe on First Amendment rights; this latest event seemed to be only one in a series. And given the taunts that Mr. Muhammad gleefully directed at Mr. Giuliani in recent weeks, particularly after a Federal appeals court upheld his right to hold the rally, few expected the Mayor to cede to him the last angry word.</p>
        <p>Andrew G. Celli Jr., a civil rights lawyer, called it ''classic Giuliani.''</p>
        <p>But others use the phrase ''classic Giuliani'' as a compliment. Polls indicate that the Mayor remains very popular, suggesting a public validation of those aggressive policies that civil libertarians find so troubling. Although the public's reaction to the  police action Saturday has not yet been measured, one frequent critic, the City Council Speaker, Peter F. Vallone, said that the Mayor had responded properly to a dangerous situation. And, as the Mayor points out, for all the angry words not one person was seriously injured.</p>
        <p>For several months preceding the rally, the Giuliani administration sought to block the rally called the  Million Youth March -- if not from the city entirely, then at least from Harlem, and at least from taking place on Labor Day weekend. Its primary argument was that there were not enough officers on a holiday to handle an event that its organizers said would take up 12 hours and 29 city blocks (estimates that later proved ridiculously out of whack). At the same time, the administration was fighting, and often losing, assorted other free-speech battles.</p>
        <p>It blocked taxi drivers from crossing the 59th Street Bridge on the pretext that they planned to bring city traffic to a halt, then refused to allow more than 20 drivers to assemble for a protest of stricter taxi regulations -- all in violation of constitutional rights, a Federal judge later ruled. It imposed licensing regulations on sidewalk artists and on newsstands that Federal judges found to be too broad. It barred city employees from talking to reporters, which a Federal appellate court ruled infringed on the First Amendment rights of the employees. And it set crowd limits for events on the steps of City Hall, limits that critics say were selectively enforced.</p>
        <p>Taken individually, the incidents might have represented nothing more than different interpretations of law and municipal governance. Taken collectively, the mayor's critics say, they suggest systematic suppression. Then, as if to punctuate the point, there came a phalanx of police officers on Saturday to storm a stage at a rally that until then had been so peaceful that no arrests had been made.</p>
        <p>''It's consistent with his myopic and vindictive, restrictive view of the  First Amendment,'' said Norman Siegel, who as director of the New York Civil Liberties Union is rarely  in the good graces of City Hall. ''He's now not just complaining about New York magazine doing a satire of him, or cabbies coming over the 59th Street Bridge, or people gathering on the steps of City Hall. He's now trying to trample on traditional First Amendment rights to protest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegel is a familiar critic of the Mayor's. But he was particularly exercised by Saturday's scuffle because, like reporters covering the rally, he was less than 100 feet from the stage when Mr. Muhammad was ending the rally with his melange of love and hate, peace and violence.</p>
        <p>Contrary to the Mayor's version of those final moments, Mr. Muhammad did not tell people to ''shoot and kill police officers.'' Instead, he demonstrated his rich experience as a hatemonger by cleverly urging retaliation only if provoked -- a fine point to some, an essential point in the arena of protected free speech. Pointing out the cocoon of police surrounding the event, he turned the officers into props for his disturbing soliloquy. ''If anyone attacks you,'' he said at one point, ''already decide who will be the ones to disconnect the railing where you are and beat the hell out of them with the railing.''</p>
        <p>It was rhetoric like this that Mr. Giuliani later said prompted the police to mount the stage -- only seconds after Mr. Muhammad had ended his tirade with the oddly paternal ''Go home to your families'' -- and pull the plug, prompting a melee that, while brief, will long linger in the communal memory of Harlem.</p>
        <p>''The police handled it superbly,'' Mr. Giuliani maintained yesterday. ''They couldn't possibly have done a better job. The lack of violence is really truly attributable only to the police, given the invocations to violence, the fact that it ended in the last 10 minutes with a call to kill police officers.''</p>
        <p>There is healthy debate among former police officials and crowd-control experts as to whether the police acted properly, given their extensive training to deflate, rather than inflate, confrontations, and to ignore taunts, no matter how hateful. There is also debate as to whether Mr. Muhammad's words were akin to yelling ''Fire!'' in a movie theater. No one expects such a shout in a theater; everyone expected Mr. Muhammad to talk trash, just as they would expect Carol Channing to belt out ''Hello, Dolly.''</p>
        <p>''I think that a lot of people knew that Muhammad and some of the other leaders were going for gross exaggeration,'' said Sheldon S. Leffler, chairman of the City Council's Public Safety Committee. ''I don't think the comments he made at close to 4 o'clock were sufficient grounds for the police to move forth.''</p>
        <p>David A. Paterson, the state Senator from Harlem, said that while Mr. Muhammad should be charged with inciting to riot -- putting at risk the very youth he said he wanted to help -- the Giuliani administration is also to blame for underestimating the people of Harlem. ''Even when Muhammad exhorted the crowd to violence, some cheered but all ignored him,'' he said. ''This did not deserve a police deployment as though a riot was already in progress.''</p>
        <p>According to accounts by witnesses, this much is true: the throwing of chairs, bottles and fists happened only after the police took the stage and pulled the plug. That thought left Mr. Celli wondering about timing.</p>
        <p>''What would have happened if the police had not reacted 30 seconds after the deadline?'' he asked. ''If they had waited 30 minutes, Khallid Muhammad would have looked like just another insane soapbox speaker.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Giuliani only bolstered his image as a ''classic'' -- however you want to take that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
