<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bellwether District, Clues to Lewinsky's Impact</title>
    <meta content="Y08OHI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strickland, Ted (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFDB123EF93BA3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bellwether District, Clues to Lewinsky's Impact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>PORTSMOUTH, Ohio, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ohio's Sixth Congressional District is considered national bellwether, which is why Republicans and Democrats are watching Rep Ted Strickland's re-election campaign so closely; Strickland, a Democrat, has won his seat, then lost it, then regained it, in three very close races; it is precisely kind of district Republicans would like to take to pad their uncomfortably narrow majority of 21 in House of Representatives, and Democrats need to hold onto if they are to have chance of winning majority of their own; thus far, there are few overt signs that Monica S Lewinsky matter will bedevil Strickland, although there is enough unease that he and other Democrats are willing to openly scold President of their own party before Election Day; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Ted Strickland sat in the back seat of the Ford Explorer, with its air-conditioner set up high, waiting for the start of the River Days parade, which has been the highlight of the Labor Day weekend in this Ohio River town as long as anyone can remember.</p>
        <p>''In a normal year,'' he said, ''I would have had two or three months of hand-to-hand combat by now, but so far this year, there's been almost no campaign. I spent most of my time this summer doing Congressional work.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Ted Strickland sat in the back seat of the Ford Explorer, with its air-conditioner set up high, waiting for the start of the River Days parade, which has been the highlight of the Labor Day weekend in this Ohio River town as long as anyone can remember.</p>
        <p>''In a normal year,'' he said, ''I would have had two or three months of hand-to-hand combat by now, but so far this year, there's been almost no campaign. I spent most of my time this summer doing Congressional work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Strickland, a 57-year-old Democrat, won his seat in 1992 on his fourth try. He lost it in 1994, then took it back in 1996. Each of the last three races has been a gasper, with the winner taking 51 percent, the loser 49, making this district, the Ohio Sixth, something of a national bellwether. Presidential races have been close, too, with George Bush winning by 2,720 votes in 1992 and Bill Clinton by only 4,488 in 1996.</p>
        <p>This is precisely the kind of district that the Republicans would like to take to pad their uncomfortably narrow majority of 21 in the House of Representatives, and the Democrats need to hold onto if they are to have a chance of winning a majority of their own.</p>
        <p>The race here has an additional significance as well. This is also the kind of religious, straitlaced district both parties will watch to measure the import of President Clinton's relationship with the former intern  Monica S. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Thus far, there are few overt signs that the Lewinsky matter will bedevil Mr. Strickland, although there is enough unease that he and other Democrats are willing to openly scold a President of their own party before Election Day.</p>
        <p>At this stage in the campaign, at least, local issues are the dominant concern. But the flames of partisan passion have not truly begun burning here in the rolling hills of the Sixth, a lovely if economically forlorn region stretching east along the river from the exurbs of Cincinnati for more than 150 miles to Marietta, the oldest town in the Midwest, which was founded in 1788. People are talking about the heat -- it was over 100 degrees this weekend -- and not about the campaign.</p>
        <p>Lieut. Gov. Nancy Hollister, 48, the Republican nominee, is a more than presentable candidate, a moderate, a supporter of limited abortion rights, with roots in the region.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Hollister had to fight a nasty primary against four more socially conservative rivals, including Frank A. Cremeans, who beat Mr. Strickland in 1994 and lost to him in 1996. That emptied her campaign treasury. After a summer of fund-raising, she has only about $200,000 on hand, but Mr. Strickland has more than twice that.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hollister trails in the polls, by as much as 10 points in one, by a smaller margin in others. Both candidates expect a tight finish.</p>
        <p>''I always run as if I'm a thousand votes behind,'' she said in an interview this afternoon, sitting cross-legged on the floor of her Marietta living room. ''All I have to do is convince people that the less government, the better. My opponent tries to dip into the Federal goodies bag for the district, but I would deliver Federal dollars directly to the localities for them to spend.''</p>
        <p>The two candidates disagree on how to reform school financing after a court decision declaring the present system unconstitutional. They talk about jobs, which have been a problem hereabouts for decades; Portsmouth alone has lost shoe factories and a steel mill, and with them half its population. The median family income is the lowest in the state, at $21,761 a year.</p>
        <p>But what of Mr. Clinton and Ms. Lewinsky?</p>
        <p>Some Ohio Democrats, including Mr. Strickland, have openly criticized the President. Representative Marcy Kaptur of Toledo denounced him in a speech last week for having dragged the nation and his family through ''a year of deceitful melodrama'' and told The Cleveland Plain Dealer that even resignation would not constitute adequate atonement. More subtly, Mary Boyle, the party's Senate candidate, produced a video that showed her with Hillary Rodham Clinton and Senator John Glenn, whom she hopes to succeed, but not with Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I like this man personally,'' Mr. Strickland said. ''I've supported him on most issues. But not many people get to be President, and not many people are as smart as he is. What a waste! He has endangered everything he's worked for and I've worked for. His Presidency might actually end prematurely.</p>
        <p>''I'm amazed and very sad and disappointed, like my constituents, and angry, too. But people's anger is not out of control yet, and I don't think it will affect the way they vote this fall. But it might; it could.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Strickland, a former Methodist minister who still greets male acquaintances with an evangelical ''how are you doing, my brother?'' is also a graduate psychologist. In his former occupation as a counselor at a local prison, he said, he had ''encountered all kinds of behavior.'' But he had nonetheless been astounded, he added, ''by the risks the President took, the repetition, even when his actions had already got him in trouble, again and again.''</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Hollister, she said Mr. Clinton had ''violated the code of ethics and behavior you have to hold yourself to as a public official.'' At the moment, the Lewinsky case is not entering into many voting decisions here, she said, but by October, she suggested, ''things may look different.''</p>
        <p>Debby Allard, the editor of The Portsmouth Times, said that because Mr. Strickland had spoken out against Mr. Clinton's behavior, ''I can't see many people at all around here punishing Strickland for the President's sins.''</p>
        <p>The situation could have been worse for him if Mr. Cremeans had won the Republican primary, local people say. He has a strong appeal to the religious right -- the former head of the Christian Coalition, Ralph Reed, was an adviser for a time -- and he might have been better able to stir up socially conservative voters on the Clinton issue.</p>
        <p>This is an old-fashioned world with traditional values, less inclined to live and let live than Cincinnati and other big Ohio cities. The big River Days parade, for example, was a page from a simpler past, with homemade costumes and floats, fire engines, Model T Fords, Model A Fords, high school bands and an American Legion honor guard. The one truly contemporary note was the names of the cheerleaders who rode on long flatbed trucks: Bethany and Tiffany, Lindsay and Brittany, Courtney and Ashley, with nary a Jane or a Mary in sight.</p>
        <p>What worries him, Mr. Strickland said, is a low turnout in November. With most people prosperous, with continuing cynicism about politics and with no crisis abroad, voters might stay at home, and that would help Ms. Hollister, the Congressman suggested. The best solution, he said, would be ''for Clinton to go for broke, cast aside this excessive caution, set inspiring goals.''</p>
        <p>But few in Washington see much chance of that, and many think Mr. Strickland's fears of a low turnout will be realized. In a study earlier this year, Curtis Gans of the Center for the Study of the American Electorate predicted a ''sharply reduced'' turnout compared with 1994, and suggested it was likely to hurt Democrats because of disproportionately heavy participation by more highly paid voters, who tend to be Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Strickland has done what he can to insulate himself against adversity. He works hard at the minutiae of constituent service, returning each weekend to the district, plying the byways of an area without a city of more than 25,000 people.</p>
        <p>Always a fairly centrist Democrat, Mr. Strickland has inched far further to the right in the last two years. He was one of only 15 Democrats to vote to end the income tax by 2003; he backed a constitutional amendment banning flag-burning, and he opposed the President on several trade issues. That has led Ms. Hollister to accuse him of lacking principle and bowing to electoral expediency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
