<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Dept. Expert on Croatia Resigns to Protest Policy in Balkans</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENOCIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALKER, STEPHEN W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER, WARREN M (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE113DF937A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Dept. Expert on Croatia Resigns to Protest Policy in Balkans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saying he could no longer countenance a policy that he believes legitimizes aggression and genocide in Bosnia, the State Department's specialist on Croatia resigned today, bringing to four the number of officials who have quit in the last year to protest the United States' Balkan policy.</p>
        <p>In a two-page letter to Secretary of State Warren Christopher, the official, Stephen W. Walker, said Washington's failure to take a harder line against the Bosnian Serbs had resulted in hundreds of thousands of casualties and undermined vital United States interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saying he could no longer countenance a policy that he believes legitimizes aggression and genocide in Bosnia, the State Department's specialist on Croatia resigned today, bringing to four the number of officials who have quit in the last year to protest the United States' Balkan policy.</p>
        <p>In a two-page letter to Secretary of State Warren Christopher, the official, Stephen W. Walker, said Washington's failure to take a harder line against the Bosnian Serbs had resulted in hundreds of thousands of casualties and undermined vital United States interests.</p>
        <p>"A dangerous precedent is being set," he wrote. "Genocide is taking place again in Europe, yet we, the European Community and the rest of the international community stand by and watch."</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker, who has worked in the Foreign Service for eight years, was the desk officer for Croatia in the office for Eastern European affairs. His resignation was the third this month by an official involed in Bosnia policy.  Role of Technician</p>
        <p>As a desk officer, Mr. Walker, 30, was one of the department's foremost technical experts on Croatia. But he ranked rather low, and was relied on mostly to produce information and recommendations to be used by senior officials to develop policy.</p>
        <p>As a candidate for President, Mr. Clinton said he would take a more vigorous stance against what he termed Serbian aggression in Bosnia. But in recent months, his Administration has said it would support virtually any resolution of the war acceptable to all the parties, even one that allows the Serbs and Croats to keep land they had taken by force.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago Jon Western, an official investigating war-crime accusations against Serbs, resigned, saying United States policy was not tough enough. In early August, Marshall Freeman Harris, the desk officer responsible for monitoring the war in Bosnia, quit. Last August, George Kenney, the deputy officer on the Yugoslavia desk, also resigned. All three men were middle- to low-level policy analysts; all said Administration policy was rewarding ethnic cleansing. Motives Were Questioned</p>
        <p>In April, 12 State Department officers signed a petition protesting the policy on Bosnia, and last winter two of the department's top experts gave Mr. Christopher a 30-page dissent drawn up during the Bush Administration protesting Washington's actions in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Harris resigned, State Department officials characterized him as a young officer who was frustrated at being left out of the formulation of policy. That reaction caused a fair amount of resentment in the European bureau, where feelings against the Bosnia policy run strong, and on Aug. 13 Mr. Christopher met with several dozen of the dissenters in an effort to clear the air.</p>
        <p>Today Michael McCurry, the State Department spokesman, termed Mr. Walker's decision "an honorable form of protest."</p>
        <p>Asked what he felt the resignation indicated, Mr. McCurry said: "I think it tells you what the Secretary himself has said on numerous occasions: this is a frustrating, terrible problem in which answers are not easy to come by. And it's just as frustrating for the Secretary as it is for people at the country-desk-officer level who work on the problem."</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview today, Mr. Walker said: "There is widespread support in the department for doing more, and widespread frustration within the Department with our policy. It's very difficult to find people within the department who support our policy. It's evident not only in these resignations, but also within the hallways."</p>
        <p>In his letter, Mr. Walker urged the Administration to arm the Muslim-dominated Bosnian Government and to act to preserve Bosnia within its origninal borders, guarantee the rights of all people and punish all war criminals and states that violate international law and principles.</p>
        <p>The United States has backed each of these goals. But Mr. Walker called Washington's support half-hearted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
