<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Lines Drawn For Major Struggle Over Rent Control</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="576055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DC1238F930A25751C1A964958260" item-length="1744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Lines Drawn For Major Struggle Over Rent Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"RENT control is like a drug," said Jim Whelan, Atlantic City's Mayor. "Once you're on it, it's very difficult to get off it."</p>
        <p>In the two decades since New Jersey's municipalities began enacting rent-control ordinances in large numbers, local officials have become increasingly disenchanted with the laws that limit rent increases. They say that rent control, which exists in 119 communities, has shifted an increasing share of the tax burden onto residential and commercial property owners and led to the deterioration of rental housing in many areas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"RENT control is like a drug," said Jim Whelan, Atlantic City's Mayor. "Once you're on it, it's very difficult to get off it."</p>
        <p>In the two decades since New Jersey's municipalities began enacting rent-control ordinances in large numbers, local officials have become increasingly disenchanted with the laws that limit rent increases. They say that rent control, which exists in 119 communities, has shifted an increasing share of the tax burden onto residential and commercial property owners and led to the deterioration of rental housing in many areas.</p>
        <p>But few municipal officials are willing to express their opposition to rent control on the record. "There are a lot more tenants than there are landlords," Mr. Whelan said. And those tenants represent votes.</p>
        <p>Landlord and tenant groups, however, have been anything but bashful about presenting their positions and battling for advantage. For example, landlords have helped persuade many communities to adopt some form of vacancy decontrol, softening their rent ordinances by allowing an owner to charge higher rates for a controlled apartment after it has been vacated.</p>
        <p>And in recent months, both sides of the rent-control issue have begun gearing up for a major confrontation next year.</p>
        <p>A 600-member taxpayer association has sprung up in Hudson County with the express intent of persuading officials to modify or eliminate rent controls. "We're going to make our presence felt at every board meeting of every city in this county," said Robert G. Sacks, the group's president.</p>
        <p>Last month, a bill that would exempt all new multifamily housing from local rent controls passed unanimously in both houses of the Legislature. The bill extends for five years an expired five-year exemption for such properties.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, advocates of tenant rights are planning their own countermoves. "We know the attack is coming," said Phyllis Salowe-Kaye, president of the New Jersey Tenants Organization, based in Hackensack. To meet what she called "a major mobilization to get rid of rent control," her group is organizing a statewide voter registration drive and a series of forums on tenants' rights.</p>
        <p>Ms. Salowe-Kaye and other supporters of rent control say controls to protect tenants from rent-gouging landlords are needed as much as ever, if not more, particularly in light of New Jersey's dismal economy and chronic high unemployment.</p>
        <p>"The fact is that landlords have made a bunch of gains in the past few years with vacancy decontrol," Ms. Salowe-Kaye said. Currently 85 municipalities with rent-control ordinances have some form of vacancy decontrol. She is also concerned, she said, that the Republican-dominated Legislature will attempt to "get rid of" rent control. Traditionally, she said, Republicans have been less sensitive to tenant issues than Democrats.</p>
        <p>Opponents of rent control say it has caused an unfair tax shift in many municipalities. Because landlords' rental income is limited, they can often persuade officials to reduce the assessed value of their property, which lowers their real-estate taxes. As a result, the remaining owners of single-family homes and commercial properties end up paying a higher proportion of the municipal taxes.</p>
        <p>Opponents also charge that rent control has led to the deterioration of rental housing in many areas because landlords who receive below-market rents for their apartments are more likely to cut corners on maintenance and capital improvements.</p>
        <p>Rent control has also inspired some landlords and tenants in controlled apartments to strike illegal, clandestine agreements under which tenants pay higher rents than the law permits.</p>
        <p>While several municipal officials interviewed for this article expressed opposition to rent control, they spoke only on condition of anonymity. One local official in northern New Jersey said that in his municipality, "Rent control is killing the tax base."</p>
        <p>A municipal rent-board administrator in the southern part of the state referred to rent control as "a tax on the immobility of real estate." He said any attempt to set pricing controls on a local supermarket, for example, would be met by "the supermarket picking up and moving to the next town." Such an option, he said, is not available to property owners.</p>
        <p>Only Mr. Whelan was willing to go on record. "I'm one Mayor who's not afraid to say that I have reservations with rent control," he said. "I'm not sure that it works, I think it has helped deplete our rental stock, and I think it is a strong disincentive to investment."</p>
        <p>Yet officials are of two minds. "If you repeal rent control, you create havoc," Mr. Whelan said. "You end up having a lot of people who can't afford to live where they're living." Neighborhood Stability Seen</p>
        <p>Ms. Salowe-Kaye of the tenants' organization would be the first to agree. "Rent control lets people who can't afford to buy homes know that they can stay in their apartments for a reasonable rent," she said. "Strong rent control means you get stability in a neighborhood."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sacks, the head of the newly formed Hudson County Taxpayers Association and a Jersey City real-estate agent, said his group intended to bring pressure on communities to repeal their rent ordinances.</p>
        <p>"People who own rent-controlled buildings are not making any money," he said, "so they have a choice: they either walk away from their buildings or they fight. One of the ways to fight is to appeal their taxes.  And in case after case they're successful."</p>
        <p>But cities still need the same amount of money in their budgets to provide necessary services, Mr. Sacks said, adding: "So who picks up the burden? The guy who owns a one-family house. The people who are living almost scot-free in rent-controlled apartments are living off the fat of the land. They're freeloading off the community, and it's unfair."</p>
        <p>Ms. Salowe-Kaye said her tenants' organization would combat efforts to derail rent control. "We are starting a major education process, a huge voter registration drive statewide," she said, "and we're going to do a series in January of regional educational forums for tenants on tenants' rights." Formula for Increases</p>
        <p>Most rent-control ordinances establish a base rent for each apartment in a building and then allow set increases each year. Those increases range from as little as 2 percent a year to as much as 7 percent.</p>
        <p>Some ordinances allow for direct "pass-throughs" to tenants for expenses like real-estate taxes and for surcharges covering such expenses as heat and water. Many communities permit landlords to apply for rent increases if they can prove that the controlled rents they receive are causing them financial hardship.</p>
        <p>Joseph Pojanowski, a Ramsey Councilman and a lawyer who often represents landlords before local rent and tax boards, said such hardship provisions typically do not work.</p>
        <p>"In order to get a hardship increase, some towns have formulas that are impossible to achieve," he said. "It is a hardship in itself to file the appeal."</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said, landlords forced to charge artificially low rents often attempt to cut their losses by trimming expenses rather than engaging municipalities in protracted legal battles.</p>
        <p>"They take the easier road," Mr. Pojanowski said. "They eliminate preventive maintenance, they let their buildings get run down, and they file tax appeals." And that, he said, depreciates the quality of existing housing stock in a municipality. 'Three Elements' of Control</p>
        <p>Proponents of rent control, however, say that rent-control ordinances allow honest landlords to make a fair return on their investment while providing them with the ability to maintain their buildings properly.</p>
        <p>"Rent control has three elements," Ms. Salowe-Kaye said. "Yearly increases, hardship increases and capital improvements." If landlords really wants to fix up buildings, she said, they can get more rent. "But where landlords have milked the property for years and years," she said, "surely the repairs that are necessary are not going to be covered."</p>
        <p>Supporters of rent control also challenge the proposition that controls have led to a shifting of tax burdens to owners of private homes and commercial real estate.</p>
        <p>"What we found is that tax shifts tend to be universal," said Mitchell Kahn, executive director of the Bergen County Housing Coalition and professor of social work and social policy at Ramapo College.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kahn said he had recently conducted a survey of all 70 Bergen County municipalities to determine whether towns with rent control had greater tax shifts than those without.  He discovered, he said, that rent control had no discernible effect on shifting taxes, and that "even towns that had no apartments had tax shifts."</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Joseph W. Hottendorf, executive vice president of the Hudson County Board of Realtors, said his dissection of the tax history of an area of Bayonne had yielded a different result.</p>
        <p>"We took one of Bayonne's three wards and looked at every apartment building in that ward," Mr. Hottendorf said. Using assessments made during a citywide revaluation in 1991, he said, he found that the assessed values of the 66 apartment buildings in the ward had decreased by 12.1 percent.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Hottendorf said, the assessments on single-family homes increased by 32.25 percent.</p>
        <p>"I know what that says to me," Mr. Hottendorf said. "It says the politicians want fewer people to be affected by tax increases, so the small homeowner gets affected but not the tenants in the apartment buildings." Decontrol as 'Safety Valve'</p>
        <p>The only real "safety valve" for rent control, said Dr. George Sternlieb, professor emeritus of city planning at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, is vacancy decontrol. In addition to allowing landlords to increase their rental income without raising the rents of existing tenants, he said, vacancy decontrol also acts as a catalyst for better building maintenance.</p>
        <p>"It's in the owner's best interest to improve the building because he wants the new rent to be as good as possible," he said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Whelan described how some landlords and tenants behave in towns with no vacancy decontrol when the disparity between the controlled rent and the market rent becomes great.</p>
        <p>"They cheat; that's what they do," he said, referring to the practice of landlords' and tenants' entering into clandestine rental agreements for rents that exceed the rent-control limits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
