<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At P.S. 115, Urban Reality Is Only Pushed Aside</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DILLON, SAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANNING, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE173DF934A15752C0A965958260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At P.S. 115, Urban Reality Is Only Pushed Aside</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DILLON, SAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton thrilled Public School 115 with her lightning visit yesterday, but minutes after her departure, students were back in mourning for a teacher who may have been murdered, and the principal was worrying that more school ceilings will collapse.</p>
        <p>Though it appeared that the First Lady wanted to make an upbeat point about volunteer action -- she chose P.S. 115 to honor an innovative tutoring program there -- her one-hour tour of the crowded Washington Heights school became a surprise brush with urban violence and decay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton thrilled Public School 115 with her lightning visit yesterday, but minutes after her departure, students were back in mourning for a teacher who may have been murdered, and the principal was worrying that more school ceilings will collapse.</p>
        <p>Though it appeared that the First Lady wanted to make an upbeat point about volunteer action -- she chose P.S. 115 to honor an innovative tutoring program there -- her one-hour tour of the crowded Washington Heights school became a surprise brush with urban violence and decay.</p>
        <p>It came one week after school authorities reported the disappearance of a longtime teacher, Patricia Manning, whose body was found by the police in her Queens apartment, her head bloodied. The police are investigating her death as a possibile homicide, though other causes have not been ruled out.</p>
        <p>"It was good that Mrs. Clinton came here when she did, because morale was very low," said Graciela Navarro, who coordinates bilingual education at the school. "It cheered us up, but now we'll go back to mourning."</p>
        <p>Indeed, in the hours after Mrs. Clinton's visit, the mood in the school faded from exhilaration into renewed grief over Ms. Manning's death. Students, teachers and parents milled through the school's office wearing their best clothing, donned for the First Lady's visit, and black ribbons distributed by parents in memory of Ms. Manning.</p>
        <p>"We're all just destroyed by Ms. Manning's death, but Mrs. Clinton's visit came just at the right moment," said George Tomka, the school principal. "Out of tragedy comes hope."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton visited P.S. 115 as a way of lauding volunteer tutors who work with the school's children one day a week. But students like Ariel Diaz, 8, believed the First Lady had come because of Ms. Manning's death.</p>
        <p>"She picked this school 'cause she is helping us feel better when we feel sad," he said. "I miss my teacher, Ms. Manning."</p>
        <p>"I cry when my teacher tells me about Ms. Manning, so Mrs. Clinton comes to make me feel better," Ariel added. "I think she knows that somebody killed Ms. Manning, and she has to find the polices and tell them to find the robbers that killed her."</p>
        <p>Colleagues last saw Ms. Manning at school on Jan. 13. When she failed to call after several days of absence, Mr. Tomka said he phoned the police Jan. 19.</p>
        <p>"We think she was murdered -- though we're not sure," Mr. Tomka said. Her death had no apparent connection to the school, he said.</p>
        <p>Lieut. John Shatinski, the detective squad commander in the 113th Precinct, said that the medical examiner has not yet ruled on the case. Ms. Manning was a "very private person" who confided little, even to relatives, and that has made the investigation difficult, he said.</p>
        <p>P.S. 115, situated on West 177th Street, is among the city's most crowded schools, with 1,400 students jammed into a structure built for 1,000. Before Mrs. Clinton's visit, custodians and teachers worked feverishly to give it a spit-and-polish shine. But the Gothic 1913 building is crumbling, and Mrs. Clinton was not given a complete tour.</p>
        <p>She did not see, for instance, the hole in the auditorium ceiling, four feet in diameter, left when hundreds of pounds of plaster crashed to the floor recently after a water leak.</p>
        <p>"Water is seeping in all over this school," Mr. Tomka said. "And my letters to the school board authorities about it go unanswered."</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Clinton stood in the area on the floor above the collapsed ceiling, Isabel Horwitz, a teacher, said she and others became concerned. "We were all afraid she would fall through," she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton was protected by about 40 police officers and school security guards, in addition to the Secret Service, Mr. Tomka said.</p>
        <p>Three students were killed in drug-related violence in the streets outside the school about four years ago, he said, and in November 1990, Antonio Otero, 23, the custodian, was attacked inside the school by teen-agers who beat him with a bat, dislocating his arm.</p>
        <p>"I'm glad everything went good for Mrs. Clinton here," Mr. Otero said, "because the neighborhood around here is terrible."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
