<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foster Care Director Quits After Purchases of Luxury Items</title>
    <meta content="08foster" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/08/nyregion/08foster.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1803246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DD1E3FF93BA35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foster Care Director Quits After Purchases of Luxury Items</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Foster Care Director Quits Over Purchases of Luxury Items</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The executive director of one of the city's midsize foster care agencies resigned after an audit by the city's comptroller's office found that she had spent tens of thousands of dollars at luxury retailers.</p>
        <p>The audit showed that the executive director, Lelar Floyd, used the agency's corporate credit card to spend $71,000 for clothing, shoes and jewelry at high-end retailers including Saks Fifth Avenue and Neiman Marcus -- even though the city criticized her for similar behavior in 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The audit showed that the executive director, Lelar Floyd, used the agency’s corporate credit card to spend $71,000 at high-end retailers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The executive director of one of the city's midsize foster care agencies resigned after an audit by the city's comptroller's office found that she had spent tens of thousands of dollars at luxury retailers.</p>
        <p>The audit showed that the executive director, Lelar Floyd, used the agency's corporate credit card to spend $71,000 for clothing, shoes and jewelry at high-end retailers including Saks Fifth Avenue and Neiman Marcus -- even though the city criticized her for similar behavior in 1997.</p>
        <p>Ms. Floyd, who ran Concord Family Services in Brooklyn, made these purchases, which she said in an interview were for the benefit of foster children, even as the agency was $4 million in debt and had significant trouble documenting that it had provided basic services to children, the audit said.</p>
        <p>Over the past 15 years, several other similar community-based agencies have lost city contracts for various reasons including poor performance or mismanagement. The audit that discovered Ms. Floyd's purchases also found that Concord had poor recordkeeping and financial management.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Ms. Floyd said that all the purchases were made to benefit foster children in her agency's care and that for the total used for some of the more expensive items -- which included a $425 blazer -- she had donated $1,000 of her own money.</p>
        <p>Ms. Floyd said that the clothing allowances for children in foster care were woefully inadequate.</p>
        <p>Last year, the city said that it was putting on review the 10 agencies with the combined lowest scores on the city's annual performance evaluations, including many of these remaining community-based agencies.</p>
        <p>Concord, which currently contracts with the city to provide foster care for more than 300 children, was not one of those reviewed. The agency had a ''very good rating'' on its most recent annual evaluation by the city.</p>
        <p>Still, the audit criticized both the city's Administration for Children's Services and Concord's board of directors for exercising lax oversight. ''Several issues that required the board's oversight either were not discussed or were only discussed in a cursory manner and not resolved,'' the report stated.</p>
        <p>Before the audit was released in June, Phillip R. Scott, chairman of Concord's board of directors, defended the board by telling the city comptroller that the board took its obligation to oversee Concord's operations very seriously.</p>
        <p>Sharman Stein, a spokeswoman for children's services, said her agency had no comment on Ms. Floyd's departure, but said children's services ''did refer some issues regarding Concord'' to the city's Department of Investigations.</p>
        <p>Joffrey H. Hill, a lawyer from Union, N.J., who is representing Concord's board of directors, confirmed that the board accepted Ms. Lloyd's resignation on Oct. 27, but said the board would have no further comment on the matter.</p>
        <p>Ms. Floyd has been Concord's executive director since 1992. A report on April 10, 1997, by the Department of Investigations found that Ms. Floyd had been using a corporate card to make purchases at retailers including Saks and Eileen Fisher.</p>
        <p>According to that report, at the time Ms. Floyd justified such purchases by saying ''it was necessary to teach the children 'quality shopping.' ''</p>
        <p>The Department of Investigations recommended that children's services give ''serious consideration'' to terminating its contracts with Concord.</p>
        <p>Children's services did its own investigation and decided to maintain the contracts.</p>
        <p>Ms. Floyd said that she was never made aware that investigators thought her actions might be serious enough to warrant termination of contracts.</p>
        <p>City Comptroller William C. Thompson Jr. undertook a new audit of Concord that covered the fiscal year 2004.</p>
        <p>The audit found that the agency had ''appropriately managed'' $6.6 million in money it had received for foster care contracts from the city.</p>
        <p>Yet it also found ''weaknesses'' in the agency's documentation of its care of foster children and of certain ''excessive'' expenditures.</p>
        <p>The audit was also critical that the agency was functioning with $4 million in debt and showed little capability in managing it finances.</p>
        <p>In addition, the audit said that of 46 case files it had culled at random from Concord's files, 4 contained no original notes and 30 did not have required notes that indicate whether children in foster homes have been visited.</p>
        <p>Ms. Floyd said that the debt was accumulated in part because of failures by children's services to make reimbursements that they were obligated to make.</p>
        <p>The incomplete case files were hardly limited to Concord or unusual, she added, and occurred because of a high turnover of caseworkers.</p>
        <p>''It is a systematic problem in the field,'' she said. ''A lot of other agencies have the same problems.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
