<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lone Voice For Regulation At the F.C.C.</title>
    <meta content="30COPP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/30/business/30COPP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1427940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Copps, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Copps, Michael J.</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Powell, Michael K</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DB1438F933A0575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lone Voice For Regulation At the F.C.C.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Lone Voice for Regulation at the F.C.C.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Michael J Copps, lone Democrat on Federal Communications Commission, and sole member concerned about maintaining regulation of nation's broadcasters and telephone companies; he urges caution on deregulation of media ownership favored by fellow commissioners; cites need to defend public interest by encouraging diversity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a steel band, Michael J. Copps would play the violin.</p>
        <p>The lone Democrat at the top of the Federal Communications Commission, Mr. Copps has sounded a broad regulatory theme at a time when his other colleagues are playing a deregulatory trio. His views, attuned to what for decades was the mainstream approach to regulation of the nation's broadcasters and telephone companies, are now seen by his colleagues as out of step with the new economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael J. Copps has sounded a broad regulatory theme at a time when his other colleagues are playing a deregulatory trio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a steel band, Michael J. Copps would play the violin.</p>
        <p>The lone Democrat at the top of the Federal Communications Commission, Mr. Copps has sounded a broad regulatory theme at a time when his other colleagues are playing a deregulatory trio. His views, attuned to what for decades was the mainstream approach to regulation of the nation's broadcasters and telephone companies, are now seen by his colleagues as out of step with the new economy.</p>
        <p>As Michael K. Powell, the F.C.C. chairman, and his two Republican colleagues have begun a process to relax a host of rules -- most notably the regulations that limit the size of the nation's largest media conglomerates -- Mr. Copps has been the only member of the commission to urge caution and voice appreciation for the existing rules. Alone among the commissioners, he has promoted those rules as vital for encouraging diversity of voices, local programming and consumer choice.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Copps who is 62 and a historian by training, has spoken to trade groups and others about the historic and legal significance of regulating ''in the public interest'' and the need to keep or restore a host of rules that the other commissioners have generally opposed or been silent about. Some of his top priorities -- preserving the concentration rules, encouraging affirmative action in the workplace at media outlets, and maintaining tough accounting oversight of the telephone giants -- have little support at the rest of the agency.</p>
        <p>But he also has an important political patron, Senator Ernest F. Hollings, Democrat of South Carolina, for whom he once worked and who now heads the relevant committees that oversee the F.C.C. and set its budget. Should the full Congress come under Democratic control after the election, Mr. Copps may gain considerable influence in slowing down Mr. Powell's deregulatory push, particularly since Mr. Powell's alliance with the two other Republicans at the agency, Kathleen Q. Abernathy and Kevin J. Martin, is fragile.</p>
        <p>''There is the potential here to remake our entire media landscape, for better or for worse, for a long time to come,'' Mr. Copps said in an interview in his office last week. ''The stakes are incredibly enormous.''</p>
        <p>By law, no more than three members of the agency can be from the same political party. Because of partisan wrangling in the Senate, the five-person commission has one vacancy. That has left Mr. Copps a frequent dissenter.</p>
        <p>His views and dissents are seen by some members of the commission as quaint -- relics of the Progressive and New Deal eras that Mr. Copps specialized in when he was a history professor at Loyola University of the South. They argue that his admiration for a broad-based ''public interest'' approach to regulating the marketplace is no longer relevant in the Internet Age, which they see as a time when value of regulations should be measured by a precise economic cost-benefit analysis.</p>
        <p>But outside the agency, Mr. Copps has been widely praised by a motley group of consumer organizations, labor unions, small broadcasters and conservative groups who see him as their only ally at the F.C.C. Telecommunications law leaves significant discretion to the regulators to act ''in the public interest,'' and Mr. Copps's supporters see his campaign to apply a broad and historic formulation of that standard as heartening at a time when his colleagues are taking a narrower view in an effort to phase out the government's role in favor of the marketplace.</p>
        <p>L. Brent Bozell III, the conservative columnist, former top aide to the former presidential candidate Patrick Buchanan and founder of the Parents Television Council, says Mr. Copps is ''a voice in the wilderness'' in his effort to curtail sex and violence on the airwaves.</p>
        <p>''Copps, more than anyone else in a leadership position at the F.C.C., is concerned with the degradation of culture and the messages directed at children,'' Mr. Bozell said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bozell said that when he met with Mr. Powell, the head of the agency, he was told that the commission ''doesn't receive a lot of complaints'' about the issue. ''There is this fear at the F.C.C. about Hollywood and an unwillingness to take a stand,'' Mr. Bozell said. ''Copps has, and I applaud him for it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Copps has also had support from Mr. Bozell's major target, the artistic community in Hollywood, for urging the commission not to roll back a series of rules that have limited the size of the nation's largest media companies.</p>
        <p>''He understands that to have very few people control so much media is a dangerous thing for democracy, whether it is on the extreme right or extreme left,'' said Victoria Riskin, president of Writers Guild of America West, which represents 8,500 writers in television, film and news. The guilds representing virtually all of the creative talent in Hollywood have unified against Mr. Powell's efforts to rewrite the rules.</p>
        <p>The review of the ownership rules is the most important issue now before the F.C.C. Earlier this month, the commission announced its intention to reconsider the rules, partly because Mr. Powell has been skeptical of them and partly because a federal appeals court has questioned the justification for some of them.</p>
        <p>The current rules restrict a newspaper from owning a TV station in the same city. They prevent a media conglomerate from owning two television networks. They prohibit a network from owning stations that broadcast to more than 35 percent of the nation's homes. They restrict a broadcaster from owning two television stations in the same market unless there are at least eight other competitors. And they restrict a company from owning more than eight radio stations in the same market.</p>
        <p>Within the F.C.C., Mr. Copps's influence is limited. He has asked that the agency conduct a series of nationwide hearings on the ownership rules and collect evidence by reaching out to a variety of interested parties, from artists to minority broadcasters. When representatives from unions and consumer groups made a similar request at a meeting with Kenneth Ferree, a close F.C.C. colleague of Mr. Powell's and the head of a task force now studying the rules, Mr. Ferree was said by several participants to have dismissed the idea as ''an exercise in foot-stomping.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Copps disagrees.''It's not foot-stomping, it's pulse-taking,'' he said. ''We're talking about redrawing the landscape in ways that can't be undone. We need to hold hearings in some of the media markets and talk to a cross section of stakeholders and see what this will do to issues of diversity and localism and voices and choices.''</p>
        <p>Though his accent has a distinctly Carolina lilt, Mr. Copps is a native of Milwaukee. His family moved in 1959 to Spartanburg, S.C., where he attended Wofford College. Intending to become a lawyer, he changed his mind after falling under the spell of a history professor. He earned his doctorate in American history at the University of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>After teaching for four years at Loyola, Mr. Copps came to Washington in 1970 to be a low-level assistant to Senator Hollings. He rose to become Mr. Hollings's chief of staff.</p>
        <p>''I was glad to have somebody that erudite,'' Mr. Hollings said. Mr. Copps is now playing a vital role at the F.C.C., Mr. Hollings said, because Mr. Powell and the rest of the commission have taken such a narrow view of the public interest.</p>
        <p>''This fellow said it was a nebulous standard and you cannot categorize it,'' Mr. Hollings said, referring to a statement Mr. Powell once made about the public interest standard. ''He is gung ho on market forces. He is a guy who believes there should be no regulation. That's how he approaches regulation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Copps left Mr. Hollings's staff in 1985 be a lobbyist, first for Collins &amp; Aikman and then for the American Meat Institute. For most of the Clinton administration he served at the Commerce Department, rising in 1998 to become the assistant secretary for trade development. Last year, at the urging of Senator Hollings, he was appointed a commissioner by President Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Copps says his views reflect his strong admiration for the progressives -- from Theodore Roosevelt and Woodrow Wilson to Franklin D. Roosevelt -- and his devotion to their ideals is in plain sight. Adorning his commission office are wall-sized campaign posters from earlier times. One, a 1932 campaign placard, features two pictures with the phrase: ''Roosevelt &amp; Garner -- End Prohibition.'' Another sports a picture of Harry S. Truman and his favorite slogan: ''The Buck Stops Here.''</p>
        <p>Asked about a poster of Calvin Coolidge, he replied, ''You have to be bipartisan in Washington.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
