<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Lottery Asks for New Bids</title>
    <meta content="MB234359" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1428046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Addenda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC1538F933A0575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Lottery Asks for New Bids</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have been developments involving challenges to the awarding of two lottery accounts.</p>
        <p>The California Lottery Commission is asking four finalists in a review for its account, a five-year contract with total billings of $125 million, to submit new bids for the media part of the assignment. The rebidding came at the request of one finalist, the Los Angeles office of DDB Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, which protested a decision in July to award the account to a team composed of two agencies owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies, the San Francisco office of Foote, Cone &amp; Belding and the Los Angeles office of Initiative Media.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have been developments involving challenges to the awarding of two lottery accounts.</p>
        <p>The California Lottery Commission is asking four finalists in a review for its account, a five-year contract with total billings of $125 million, to submit new bids for the media part of the assignment. The rebidding came at the request of one finalist, the Los Angeles office of DDB Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, which protested a decision in July to award the account to a team composed of two agencies owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies, the San Francisco office of Foote, Cone &amp; Belding and the Los Angeles office of Initiative Media.</p>
        <p>The new bids will mark the third time the commission is reviewing the account. The Interpublic team was selected after an earlier protest by the incumbent agency, the Los Angeles office of Grey Worldwide, part of the Grey Global Group, which challenged a decision last year to shift the account to DDB Los Angeles. The agencies submitting new bids for the media duties will be DDB Los Angeles; Grey; the Interpublic team; and another Interpublic agency, the Los Angeles office of McCann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Tierney Communications in Philadelphia is withdrawing a protest made in March with the Pennsylvania Department of Revenue, challenging a decision by the department to shift the Pennsylvania lottery account, with billings estimated at $18 million, to Marc USA in Pittsburgh from Tierney.</p>
        <p>Tierney, which has handled the lottery account for 25 years, complained that the review process had been confusing and flawed. In a letter sent to the department, Tierney executives said they had decided their chances of successfully challenging the shift were small and they wanted to focus on remaining clients. Tierney is part of the Partnership division of Interpublic.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
