<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hundreds Are Lost As Crowded Ferry Capsizes Off Haiti</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="591195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FERRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D81639F93AA25751C0A965958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hundreds Are Lost As Crowded Ferry Capsizes Off Haiti</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti, Feb. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of passengers aboard a badly overloaded Haitian ferry are believed to have drowned when the vessel sank off the country's southern peninsula early Wednesday, officials said today.</p>
        <p>The Haitian authorities and United States Coast Guard officials said the victims, passengers on a regularly scheduled ferry linking remote areas of the peninsula with the capital, Port-au-Prince, could number 1,500 or more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of passengers aboard a badly overloaded Haitian ferry are believed to have drowned when the vessel sank off the country's southern peninsula early Wednesday, officials said today.</p>
        <p>The Haitian authorities and United States Coast Guard officials said the victims, passengers on a regularly scheduled ferry linking remote areas of the peninsula with the capital, Port-au-Prince, could number 1,500 or more.</p>
        <p>They said the sinking was unconnected with the recent exodus of boat people that has seen more than 40,000 Haitians try to flee the country since a violent army coup overthrew the elected President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, in September 1991.</p>
        <p>Survivors said the the rusty, 150-foot triple-decker vessel, the Neptune, sank before dawn in a heavy rainfall several hours into the overnight journey to Port-au-Prince from Jeremie, an isolated town near the western end of the southern peninsula. By this evening, 141 people had either floated to shore alive or had been rescued at sea.</p>
        <p>Because of Haiti's bad roads and scant telephone network, news of the accident did not reach Port-au-Prince until early today, more than 24 hours after the sinking, when bodies began washing onto beaches around the southern towns of Mirogoane and Petit-Goave.</p>
        <p>The officer who supervises United States Coast Guard activities in Haiti, Comdr. Larry Mizell, said the Coast Guard was alerted to the sinking shortly after 7 this morning and immediately dispatched a plane over the zone between the southern peninsula and the island of La Gonave, where the sinking occurred.</p>
        <p>Commander Mizell said that two Coast Guard ships were headed for the area to help in rescue efforts. Because of the delay in discovering the tragedy, however, few other survivors are expected, officials said. More Passengers Than Tickets</p>
        <p>With most roads nearly unusable, and no fuel available in the country for small aircraft, the Neptune had become Jeremie's only serviceable link with the outside, making weekly runs to Port-au-Prince.</p>
        <p>As they pieced together spotty reports on the Neptune's sinking, officials said it appeared that 800 tickets had been sold for the 180-mile run this week. They said that the rickety vessel typically loaded up with huge stacks of charcoal, agricultural produce and livestock at Jeremie's simple concrete wharf before the passengers boarded.</p>
        <p>Often, several officials said, the number of passengers far exceeded the number of tickets sold, leading to speculation that as many as 2,000 people may have been aboard the ship.</p>
        <p>"This is a boat that we've seen many times," Commander Mizell said. "The passenger load can vary anywhere between 500 and 2,000 people on any given day depending upon what else they are carrying and what is going on."</p>
        <p>The ferry's captain, Benjamin St. Clair, was one of the survivors. In an interview with Radio Metropole, a private Haitian station, he said that passengers began to panic as the ship took on water in a driving rain. The shifting of the frightened passengers rocked the vessel back and forth, he said, causing it to capsize.</p>
        <p>With the aid of floating debris, Captain St. Clair was able to make it to shore, along with about 60 passengers. Owners Feared a Hijacking</p>
        <p>The Neptune's regularly scheduled Tuesday trip to the capital had been suspended for several weeks until last week, officials said, largely because the owners feared Haitians trying to reach the United States would hijack the vessel. Boats seized on the seas by the Coast Guard are routinely destroyed and their passengers returned to land.</p>
        <p>A Haitian military official reached by telephone in Jeremie said the Neptune had been unusually crowded because of the pent-up demand among those who had been waiting weeks for the ferry service to resume.</p>
        <p>"No one will ever know how many people were aboard that boat," said the official, who spoke on condition of anonymity. "But I have never seen it so full of people."</p>
        <p>Since mid-January, the United States Coast Guard has kept more than 20 of its ships in international waters off Haiti to prevent a resurgence of boat people trying to reach the United States. It has estimated that one-third or more of those setting out aboard crudely build and often overloaded wooden boats since the exodus began may have died in accidents at sea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
