<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Size Is in the Eye of the Architect</title>
    <meta content="19REM.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="AT THE GALLERY WITH: Rem Koolhaas" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE GALLERY WITH: Rem Koolhaas"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Rem Koolhaas</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lehmann Maupin (Gallery)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iovine, Julie V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koolhaas, Rem</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D81E3AF93AA2575AC0A960958260" item-length="1470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Size Is in the Eye of the Architect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE V. IOVINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Iovine, Julie V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with the Dutch architect Rem Koolhaas, who is in New York to oversee completion of the new Lehmann Maupin gallery in SoHo, his first American project; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MR. EXTRA-LARGE has done something very small for his first project in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Dutch architect Rem Koolhaas was in town this week, overseeing the completion of Lehmann Maupin, a new gallery he has designed in SoHo, to open on Oct. 3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MR. EXTRA-LARGE has done something very small for his first project in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Dutch architect Rem Koolhaas was in town this week, overseeing the completion of Lehmann Maupin, a new gallery he has designed in SoHo, to open on Oct. 3.</p>
        <p>By his standards, the 3,500-square-foot storefront gallery, at 39 Greene Street (near Grand Street), is minuscule. Mr. Koolhaas is usually associated with somewhat larger projects, like ''redesigning Holland,'' which is how he describes his theoretical Point City/South City plan of 1993. Or his master plan for Euralille, a 469-acre international communications, financial, transportation and entertainment hub in northern France. Or the recently commissioned master plan for Universal City, a 415-acre theme park and corporate complex in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>And he is one of a few star architects being favored for an expansion at the Museum of Modern Art.</p>
        <p>A boost to his international reputation has been the publication (30,000 copies sold so far) of his manifesto-tome, ''S, M, L, XL'' (Monacelli Press). Its release was the heaviest publishing event of 1996, figuratively and literally (the 1,376-page book weighs 6 pounds). The Museum of Modern Art had a one-man show of his work last year. And students flock to his occasional courses on urban planning at Harvard and Rice Universities. Such is the life of an architectural cult figure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koolhaas, 52, is himself impressively scaled, at over six feet tall. He has the penetrating glare of Yul Brynner, only he still has some hair. In print, he has a tendency to make pronouncements that are either bombastically absurd (''Architects will be the last for whom the apples fall'') or inspiringly blunt (''Imagine the whole architectural profession is run through a shredder and only tiny fragments of plankton are what remain, the question is can you work with that plankton?'').</p>
        <p>He fearlessly embraces the grimmest realities of the built world -- the snaking highways, abandoned rail yards, sprawling edge cities -- making them the foundations for his urban makeovers and geometry-defying architectural forms.</p>
        <p>''Rem is one of the first strong, positive voices in architecture in a long time,'' said Lars Lerup, the dean of architecture at Rice University. ''What Rem says is: 'Learn how to live with the dirty reality, and make something great out of it. Stop dabbling in form, and be part of what's going on in the world.' He makes a spectacle of architecture, and everyone who gets sucked up in his vision feels enthused.''</p>
        <p>Last Saturday morning at the gallery, a construction site still strewn with orange-juice cartons nearly three weeks before its opening, Mr. Koolhaas embodied dour Dutch chic, looking terminally depressed but geeky-suave in black slacks and a short-sleeved blue shirt. He stood with one of the gallery's founders, David Maupin, and pointed through the building's rear windows to a patch of blue sky in a cleft between buildings, where, the architect said, you would be able to see ''clear to Miami,'' if only the back of the building opposite were painted white. Mr. Maupin vowed to look into it.</p>
        <p>But there was still no escaping it: Mr. Koolhaas's first work in the United States is modest. His staccato phrases reverberated: The new gallery is ''an unstable situation''; it ''reeks of process''; he is creating ''a device allowing modifications and adjustments'' that, bless him, is ''not completely sterile.'' Actually, all he has done is to add two 16-foot-tall wall sections on rollers to a SoHo-style warehouse space, dividing the sky-lighted rear from the front.</p>
        <p>Why did he agree to such a small-scale project? ''I do big and small with equal interest,'' he said. ''It's all about planning, whatever the scale.''</p>
        <p>As to how such a heavy-gun architect came to design the gallery, Mr. Maupin, whose partner is Rachel Lehmann, said, ''It all happened in such an organic, natural way.'' The two men met at a gallery, Mr. Maupin said. ''I arranged for Rem to visit some artists' studios, and soon we were talking about a gallery space. Then it was more like getting design advice from a friend.''</p>
        <p>This breezy version of events belies some 20 years during which Mr. Koolhaas considered, turned down, competed for or lost opportunities to build in the United States. Mr. Koolhaas shrugs off those years.</p>
        <p>''The 1980's were not good for my kind of architecture,'' he said. ''Post-modernism and the Reaganite excesses did not attract me.'' He said he and his company, O.M.A., the Office for Metropolitan Architecture, were ''more drawn to commissions that have an effect on relationships in the city or impact conditions, which is what's interesting about the gallery.''</p>
        <p>As a planner, he works with the messy reality of modern cities, without retreating from the chaos and building gemlike forms. In a gallery, there is tension between architecture and art. Which one will dominate?</p>
        <p>''No one believes that architecture can do anything to make art come alive,'' he said. So, he is taking his cue from the life around him by designing a space where artists can paint on the plywood floors, alter the ceiling, move walls. In turn, he said, he will continue to ''condition the space'' for future exhibitions.</p>
        <p>The inaugural show, ''Moving Structures,'' will include a life-size sculpture of an elevator by Richard Artschwager and voice-activated light bulbs by Tony Oursler. The design issue will be whether to open or close the sliding walls, to make the space feel either ''claustrophobic'' or ''free.'' Mentally, however, Mr. Koolhaas has already moved on by busily imagining other more ''extreme'' conditions, like arranging a pitch-dark background for something like the photographer Cindy Sherman's vomit series or creating what he calls ''an astringent, authoritarian circulation'' (i.e., obstacle course) for the amusement of jaded gallery-goers. The only sacred space, he agreed, with prompting from Mr. Maupin, will be the sales office.</p>
        <p>The discreet maneuverings at the gallery don't give much of an indication of the powerhouse intellect that is Mr. Koolhaas's hallmark. The closest glimpse of that is available at local bookstores, where one can inspect, perchance to lug home, ''S, M, L, XL,'' his $75 magnum opus. In classic manifesto style, it reads as if it were written at break-neck speed over many years. ''Bigness is ultimate architecture,'' it exclaims in overscale capitalized type in a passage that goes on for 20 pages. It is a graphic mille-feuilles (in fact, Bruce Mau, the Canadian graphic designer, shares top billing on the title page with Mr. Koolhaas and O.M.A.).</p>
        <p>The book layers project descriptions upon dream-book passages, glossaries, reveries, news clips and more. If it weren't so heavy, one might expect to see it fluttering in the wind like the pamphlets dropped from biplanes by the Italian Futurist F. T. Marinetti in the early 1900's.</p>
        <p>The effect is intimidating. How does one read the thing? Any way you want, suggests its author. ''Some read a tiny fraction every day, some read it nonstop, some start at the rear,'' he said. ''There are as many ways to read it as there are people. And that's how it was conceived.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koolhaas's 1978 book, ''Delirious New York'' (reissued last year by Monacelli), with its visionary take on Manhattan's ''culture of congestion,'' was equally celebrated, and easier to read. But his fixation with skyscrapers has long since peaked. ''What I find most suspenseful now is the relationship between virtual space and real space,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a battleground, and architecture will be forced to prove its credibility,'' he said. At the same time, he foresees virtual reality superimposing concrete reality with anything the viewer wants to see, thus liberating architecture from what he calls ''obligations it doesn't want to perform anymore, like iconography and ornament.''</p>
        <p>In a tour de force of consistent reasoning, Mr. Koolhaas brings the conversation back to the little gallery. Like it, the architecture of the future will be more about offering flexible conditions than in building definitive forms, he believes. But what will it all look like?</p>
        <p>''I have no idea,'' said Mr. Koolhaas, who had been practicing creative simultaneity himself by double-booking his afternoon schedule. ''But I'm deeply interested,'' he added reassuringly, dashing off to his next appointment, already under way.</p>
        <p>AT THE GALLERY WITH: Rem Koolhaas</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
