<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Set for Abortion Vote Amid a Furor Over Just How Rare a Late-Term Method Is</title>
    <meta content="19ABOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDA1F3AF93AA2575AC0A960958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Set for Abortion Vote Amid a Furor Over Just How Rare a Late-Term Method Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News conferences are held on eve of hotly contested House vote to enact ban on kind of late-term abortion by advocates on each side; groups also preview new television advertisements and predict that issue will be decided by handful of votes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of a hotly contested House vote to enact a ban on a kind of late-term abortion, advocates on each side today held dueling news conferences, previewed new television advertisements and predicted that the issue would be decided by a handful of votes.</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion lobbyists said two recent newspaper articles had given them a significant last-minute boost in their fight to overturn President Clinton's veto of the ban, which Congress approved earlier this year. The articles -- in The Washington Post, and The Record of Hackensack, N.J. -- suggested that the procedure was not so rare as the President and abortion rights advocates had said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of a hotly contested House vote to enact a ban on a kind of late-term abortion, advocates on each side today held dueling news conferences, previewed new television advertisements and predicted that the issue would be decided by a handful of votes.</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion lobbyists said two recent newspaper articles had given them a significant last-minute boost in their fight to overturn President Clinton's veto of the ban, which Congress approved earlier this year. The articles -- in The Washington Post, and The Record of Hackensack, N.J. -- suggested that the procedure was not so rare as the President and abortion rights advocates had said.</p>
        <p>The procedure -- which anti-abortion groups call partial birth abortion and doctors call intact dilation and extraction -- is one of several methods used to abort a fetus after 20 weeks of gestation. No one knows exactly how often it is performed, because neither the Federal Government nor state governments require that it be reported.</p>
        <p>But the articles, published this week, suggested that the procedure was used as many as several thousand times a year, rather than 500 as had been estimated by abortion rights groups.</p>
        <p>The articles, which the National Right to Life Committee and other anti-abortion groups are widely distributing, also said the procedure  was used in many cases on healthy women with healthy fetuses in their second trimester of pregnancy, not exclusively in the third trimester for women whose lives are endangered.</p>
        <p>''That information has helped minimize any attrition we might have suffered and made it more difficult to flip'' on the issue, said Representative Charles T. Canady, the Florida Republican who sponsored the House bill to ban the procedure. ''It's created an environment in which it's more difficult to switch.''</p>
        <p>It takes a two-thirds vote to override a veto, or 290 House members if all are voting, and the last vote on the bill was 286 to 129, with one member voting present. Representative Christopher H. Smith, a New Jersey Republican who is a leading anti-abortion voice in the House, predicted victory but by the barest of margins.</p>
        <p>The Senate is expected to uphold the veto. But even so, Republicans expect to capitalize on the issue in the elections. Bob Dole, the Republican Presidential nominee, told a convention of the Christian Coalition last week that if elected he would sign a bill banning the procedure.</p>
        <p>Representative Nita M. Lowey, a New York Democrat, said Republicans were using the issue as a back-door method of attacking Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court decision that legalized abortion a quarter-century ago.</p>
        <p>''They know they can't get rid of Roe v. Wade with a club,'' Ms. Lowey said, ''but they can chip away at it.''</p>
        <p>One House member who opposes the ban said his camp might be losing because the issue was not one that many members were willing to risk losing elections over, especially with the Senate likely to sustain the veto. And among those who support the ban are Representatives Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri and David E. Bonior of Michigan, the top two members of the House Democratic leadership.</p>
        <p>Abortion rights advocates acknowledged that the number of such abortions might have been understated but said the procedure was nonetheless rare.</p>
        <p>''I think yes, the numbers are greater than we originally thought,'' said Vicki Saporta, executive director of the National Abortion Federation. ''But it's still a very, very rare procedure.''</p>
        <p>In any case, Ms. Saporta said, ''the numbers don't matter, because that's not the point.''</p>
        <p>. ''The point,'' she said, ''is who makes the decision.''</p>
        <p>In the procedure, a physician partly extracts the fetus from the uterus, feet first, then suctions the brain and spinal fluid out of the skull before collapsing the skull so that the fetus can be entirely removed.</p>
        <p>Abortion rights advocates maintain that the other main late-term method, in which the fetus is dismembered rather than removed intact, is not as safe.</p>
        <p>The article in The Record, on Sunday, quoted doctors at a clinic in Englewood, N.J., who were not otherwise identified, as saying their clinic alone performed as many as 1,500 intact-dilation-and-extraction abortions a year.</p>
        <p>No one at the clinic, Metropolitan Medical Associates, was willing to discuss the report in detail today. One official there, who would not give her name, said in a brief telephone interview that the doctors had been misquoted. But she declined to say how.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the clinic did in fact perform 1,500 of the procedures a year, she said, ''We have no comment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
