<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Leaders, Private Schools</title>
    <meta content="15FREE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1191917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freedman, Samuel G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DB1F3EF936A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Leaders, Private Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Samuel G. Freedman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freedman, Samuel G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Samuel G Freedman Op-Ed article argues that if Harold Levy, interim chancellor of New York City schools, wants to oversee public education in city, he should put his daughter and son in public schools, instead of elite private school on Upper East Side (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Harold Levy, the interim chancellor of New York City schools, has made it known that he wants to be appointed permanently, he needs to answer one question: Will he send his children to public school?</p>
        <p>His own behavior raised this issue.  Just hours after being named interim chancellor last January, Mr. Levy visited his old elementary school in Washington Heights. As the child of German Jewish refugees, he began his education at P.S. 189. And in one of those classic stories of the city schools, he eventually rose to the Ivy League and became a corporate lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that Harold Levy, the interim chancellor of New York City schools, has made it known that he wants to be appointed permanently, he needs to answer one question: Will he send his children to public school?</p>
        <p>His own behavior raised this issue.  Just hours after being named interim chancellor last January, Mr. Levy visited his old elementary school in Washington Heights. As the child of German Jewish refugees, he began his education at P.S. 189. And in one of those classic stories of the city schools, he eventually rose to the Ivy League and became a corporate lawyer.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levy's return to his alma mater looked more strategic than sentimental. By posing for photos with the school's current pupils, many of them immigrants from the Dominican Republic, he was telling the public that he cares about public education -- after all he was a product of it.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Levy boasts many excellent bona fides for the job. During his brief time in office, he has pressed state legislators for increased financing, demanded greater accountability by administrators and insisted that teachers transferred to other schools disclose their often-critical job-performance records. Before taking his current position, he served on the state Board of Regents and led a task force studying public-school facilities.</p>
        <p>But there is one bothersome fact: His two children attend an elite private school on Manhattan's Upper East Side. If Mr. Levy wants to oversee public education on more than a stopgap basis, then he should put his daughter and son in the public schools. The same standard should hold for anyone else with school-age children who is considered by Mayor Giuliani and the Board of Education for the chancellorship.</p>
        <p>I do not begrudge any parent the right to enroll a child in private school. My wife and I considered several private schools before sending our children to a public school in Manhattan. I particularly empathize with working-class families who scrape together the  money for parochial schools, which are often the only affordable alternative to the city's worst public schools.</p>
        <p>But when a private citizen chooses to become a public figure, the decision to send children to a private school has an effect far outside the home. Mr. Levy is essentially declaring the public schools unfit for his own children. If  is named permanent chancellor and does not move them to public schools, could there be a more destructive symbol for public education?</p>
        <p>Nor can a chancellor who spends about $35,000 a year on tuition honorably oppose publicly funded vouchers for impoverished children. Shouldn't those students enjoy a comparable choice?</p>
        <p>The issue here is not Harold Levy the individual; it is the phenomenon he represents. There is a chasm between the public stance many liberals take on education and the private decisions they make. Al Gore, who is running for president as the protector of public schools against vouchers, sent his own children to private schools. And how many of New York City's leaders send their children to public schools? Not many, according to a report by The Daily News; those paying tuition include Mark Green, the public advocate, Mayor Giuliani and Al Sharpton.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers would surely look askance at a police commissioner who used private guards or at a Transit Authority director who never took the subway. Why should the standard of enlightened self-interest be set any lower in the realm of public education?</p>
        <p>Samuel G. Freedman, a journalism professor at Columbia, is the author of ''Small Victories: The Real World of a Teacher, Her Students and Their High School.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Samuel G. Freedman, a journalism professor at Columbia, is the author of ''Small Victories: The Real World of a Teacher, Her Students and Their High School.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
