<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Representatives Urge Military To Respond to Sexual Assaults</title>
    <meta content="04ASSA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/04/politics/04assault.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemetson, Lynette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D81231F937A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Representatives Urge Military To Respond to Sexual Assaults</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Representatives Urge Military to Respond to Sexual Assaults</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE CLEMETSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clemetson, Lynette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of Congress, responding to Army report citing 25 percent increase in sexual assault claims within ranks, urge military leaders to make immediate, concrete changes in how cases are handled in every branch of armed forces; report cites lack of integrated prevention and response policies, poor response by commanders to claims of assault and insufficient support for victims (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to an Army report citing a 25 percent increase in sexual assault claims within Army ranks in the last five years, members of Congress on Thursday urged military leaders to make immediate, concrete changes in how these cases are handled in every branch of the armed forces.</p>
        <p>The report, released on Thursday, intensified debate at a hearing of a subcommittee of the House Armed Services Committee that had initially been called to respond to a Defense Department report on the issue released last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers were responding to an Army report citing a 25 percent increase in sexual assault claims within Army ranks in the last five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to an Army report citing a 25 percent increase in sexual assault claims within Army ranks in the last five years, members of Congress on Thursday urged military leaders to make immediate, concrete changes in how these cases are handled in every branch of the armed forces.</p>
        <p>The report, released on Thursday, intensified debate at a hearing of a subcommittee of the House Armed Services Committee that had initially been called to respond to a Defense Department report on the issue released last month.</p>
        <p>The Army report's findings echoed many of those in the Defense Department report, citing problems like a lack of integrated prevention and response policies, poor and inconsistent response by commanders to claims of assault, and insufficient support for victims. The report also highlighted more specific problems, including a backlog in the processing of DNA evidence.</p>
        <p>In response to testimony from military leaders, the subcommittee's chairman, Representative John M. McHugh, Republican of New York, said the issue had reached ''a crisis point,'' noting that the military had produced 18 major studies on sexual assault in the last 15 years.</p>
        <p>''How do we begin to reassure women that we are serious this time?'' Mr. McHugh asked. ''How do we convey a sense of sincerity and genuine purpose?''</p>
        <p>Testifying before the subcommittee, Reginald J. Brown, assistant secretary of the Army for manpower and reserve affairs, said sexual assault ''degrades our mission readiness by devastating our ability to work effectively as a team.'' He said that while current Army programs dealt effectively with sexual harassment, sexual assault was addressed only ''to a minor extent.''</p>
        <p>An overview of the report, submitted by Mr. Brown in written testimony, also stated that commanders did not routinely report claims to military police and investigators, and that reported claims were often incomplete. Current laboratory resources for testing DNA evidence in criminal assault cases are insufficient, the report found, and the Army lacks a system to collect and analyze data on sexual assaults.</p>
        <p>The committee also heard testimony from William Navas, Mr. Brown's counterpart in the Navy, and Michael Dominguez, who holds the same position in the Air Force.</p>
        <p>Several times during the hearing, contradictions and points of confusion among panelists gave some indication of the challenges the military still faces in addressing the problem.</p>
        <p>The Army report indicated an increase in sexual assault cases to 822 in 2003 from 658 in 1999. It showed an increase in reported cases of rape over the same period to 469 from 356. But David S.C. Chu, under secretary of defense for personnel and readiness, cited a Defense Department report released in February that showed a decline in sexual assaults of female soldiers from 6 percent to 3 percent from 1995 to 2002.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chu attributed the discrepancy to a difference in the wording of questions in the two reports and said the Army findings should not be cited to reflect a trend.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Army said after the hearing that while the raw numbers of cases have increased, the percentage in relation to the Army's total population has decreased because of a growth in both the active and reserve forces.</p>
        <p>Another dispute surfaced in an exchange between Representative Loretta Sanchez, Democrat of California, and Ellen Embrey, deputy assistant secretary of defense for force health protection and readiness, who headed the Defense Department's sexual assault task force.</p>
        <p>In response to a question about access to abortion for rape victims who became pregnant, Ms. Embrey said military personnel in Defense Department facilities were not authorized to perform abortions unless the life of the mother was in danger.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sanchez and Mr. McHugh both jumped in to stress that, by law, victims had a right to abortion, provided that the patient paid for the procedure herself. A Defense Department spokesman, later clarified that the representatives were correct.</p>
        <p>Army officials said they had already made some changes, like the addition this year of more information about sexual assault in basic and advanced training for enlisted personnel and in courses for officers.</p>
        <p>Mr. McHugh said many of the steps being taken were encouraging, but added, ''There is a long path between encouragement and final achievement.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
