<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Track Announcer, History Is the Payoff</title>
    <meta content="04TV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/04/sports/sportsspecial/04tv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Park Race Track</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durkin, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Durkin, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDF1331F937A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Track Announcer, History Is the Payoff</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Track Announcer, History Is the Payoff</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Belmont Park track announcer Tom Durkin prepares to call Belmont Stakes and for chance to be immortalized if Smarty Jones wins Triple Crown; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten minutes before yesterday's first race at Belmont Park, a steeplechase, Tom Durkin was trying to learn who these horses were. Durkin, the track announcer at Belmont, rarely calls steeplechases. It will not be long remembered, not like tomorrow's Belmont Stakes, which Durkin will call.</p>
        <p>His attitude is, heck, this is no problem. ''I'm a trained actor,'' he said, standing in the glass-enclosed announcer's booth that overlooks the finish line from the highest point at the track.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten minutes before yesterday's first race at Belmont Park, a steeplechase, Tom Durkin was trying to learn who these horses were. Durkin, the track announcer at Belmont, rarely calls steeplechases. It will not be long remembered, not like tomorrow's Belmont Stakes, which Durkin will call.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten minutes before yesterday's first race at Belmont Park, a steeplechase, Tom Durkin was trying to learn who these horses were. Durkin, the track announcer at Belmont, rarely calls steeplechases. It will not be long remembered, not like tomorrow's Belmont Stakes, which Durkin will call.</p>
        <p>His attitude is, heck, this is no problem. ''I'm a trained actor,'' he said, standing in the glass-enclosed announcer's booth that overlooks the finish line from the highest point at the track.</p>
        <p>Durkin's race-by-race ritual of memorization is twofold. The first is coloring the jockeys' silks next to their entries in his program. The second seems, upon observation, like a prayer for creativity, or at least, accuracy. He recites each name, repeatedly, until they're as familiar as family.</p>
        <p>''Naughty Prince, Naughty Prince,'' he said, making it sound a little like a children's fairy tale, then continued, ''South by Gosh, South By Gosh, Cherokeeinthehills, Cherokeeinthehills, Sur La Tete, Sur La Tete, Serazzo, Sur La Tete, Foretold, Serazzo, Serazzo.'' And on and on, first at a canter, then faster and louder, then in a near whisper, until they left his mouth woven as they would be in a race.</p>
        <p>At 1 p.m., Durkin flipped the switch that turned on the public address system, said, ''They're off!'' and his call was as informed as if Naughty Prince and Sur La Tete were in tomorrow's Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>Durkin, 53, calls the races at Belmont, Aqueduct and Saratoga, but most notably, he is the voice of the Triple Crown for NBC. If Smarty Jones wins the Belmont Stakes, Durkin's call will be the first in 26 years to be connected to a Triple Crown winner, like Chic Anderson is to Secretariat. Anderson described him as moving like a ''tremendous machine'' in his final strides during the 1973 Belmont.</p>
        <p>''I try assiduously to avoid those thoughts,'' he said. ''They do nothing but take you out of your focus. If I screw it up, it'll be on my tombstone.'' He added: ''It's so easy to make a mistake. I'm not particularly confident, but the calls need to sound confident.''</p>
        <p>He is, of course, more familiar with Smarty Jones and the other horses entered in the Belmont than he was with the steeplechase horses. To Durkin, the story is not just Smarty Jones, and whether he can win the Triple Crown. ''It's like Odysseus,'' he said. ''After 26 years, he is still trying to get home. He's had this journey, and the Triple Crown has faced a lot of factors the gods have placed in Odysseus's way.''</p>
        <p>In the five-act Belmont scenario that Durkin has sketched out, but which can be discarded if Smarty Jones stumbles, he nears home at the five-eighths pole. ''He'll be a minute from home, but it's really 26 years and a minute,'' he said. ''I never refer to time left, but I may here.''</p>
        <p>Durkin lives a few hundred yards from the edge of Belmont, in a Floral Park house that he shares with his 21-year-old cat, and assorted friends who spend extended time there. He is, or has been, he said, a goofball, a class clown, a natural performer (his first, and best, role at St. Norbert College was Tartuffe, the religious hypocrite, in Molière's satire) and a man of immoderate tastes. He vacations from January to April in Panzano, a village south of Florence, where, he said, his ultimate annual goal ''is to get bored.''</p>
        <p>''Moderation is for people who lack commitment, O.K.?'' he said, with a smile.</p>
        <p>He is a burly man, his red hair nearly all gone gray, his round face seemingly ready to burst into boisterous laughter at any moment. His denim pants have no choice but to surrender to gravity.</p>
        <p>He went to an art auction the other day, and yesterday, a woman he met there for the first time called him in his Belmont perch to ask for tickets to tomorrow's race.</p>
        <p>He keeps two books in his Belmont booth: a dictionary and the choreographer Twyla Tharp's ''The Creative Habit,'' where he finds wisdom that he annotates by writing, ''This means you'' and ''Huge.''</p>
        <p>He is a race-caller at the peak of his profession -- calling the Triple Crown and the Breeders' Cup -- yet he prefers horses from many furlongs away.</p>
        <p>''I gotta tell you,'' he said. ''I don't like being around them. They're a little scary. Have you been up close to them? I'm allergic to the straw or the horses, and if I'm around them for a half-hour, my eyes turn crimson. I'm just not a horse person.''</p>
        <p>But, he said, ''Eh, so far, not a problem.''</p>
        <p>One day at Santa Anita, where NBC was televising the Breeders' Cup, the producer, David Michaels, said to Durkin, ''Let's go down to shed road.''</p>
        <p>As Michaels recalled it, ''Tom said, 'I'm not going.' I said, 'What do you mean?' And he said, 'I don't like horses.' I said, 'What?'''</p>
        <p>Like Michaels, Steven Crist, publisher of The Daily Racing Form, praises Durkin's ability to quickly assess race dynamics. ''He has a great ability to intelligently see a race developing,'' Crist said. ''He can pick up a move when a horse is fifth coming around a turn, and when leaders are tiring.''</p>
        <p>Durkin has almost always wanted to call races, which may be an odd career choice when at age 10 or 11, but it meets his innate desire to perform.</p>
        <p>''There's only one other performer at the track: the bugler,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow, he will perform, but will not overdramatize. He is not preparing a phrase for the highlight ages if Smarty Jones wins.</p>
        <p>He will walk to the track, toting his laptop, take the elevator to his roost and do his memory exercises. Sometime after 6 p.m., he will attach his binoculars to an eye-high brace, and gently move the powerful glasses to his left to watch the Belmont Stakes field, then push them aside to watch, without magnification, the horses come down the stretch.</p>
        <p>''This cannot be embellished,'' he said. ''All I have to say is, 'He won the Triple Crown.'''</p>
        <p>Or not.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
