<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Search for Defense Chief Narrows to Pentagon Deputy</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="663585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERRY, WILLIAM J (DEPUTY SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D61230F931A15752C0A962958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Search for Defense Chief Narrows to Pentagon Deputy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton has focused his search for a new Defense Secretary on William J. Perry, the current Deputy Secretary, and will weigh his decision over the weekend, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry, a 66-year-old former engineering professor who is widely respected in Congress and at the Pentagon, met with Mr. Clinton alone this morning in what White House officials called a "warm" session.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton has focused his search for a new Defense Secretary on William J. Perry, the current Deputy Secretary, and will weigh his decision over the weekend, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry, a 66-year-old former engineering professor who is widely respected in Congress and at the Pentagon, met with Mr. Clinton alone this morning in what White House officials called a "warm" session.</p>
        <p>"It's safe to assume that Bill Perry is now the front runner," said a senior White House official, who said the two men discussed broad issues concerning the Defense Department. "They had a good session, but Clinton has not made a hard decision."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry would bring a diverse and distinguished background as an entrepreneur, Government official and high-technology visionary. As Deputy Defense Secretary, he has been responsible for the daily business of the Pentagon, and he traveled last year to Russia to discuss that nation's conversion of military factories to commercial industries.</p>
        <p>Some Administration officials argue that Mr. Perry might not have the well-polished political skills or the weighty reputation to deflect anticipated Republican attacks on national security issues.</p>
        <p>After Bobby Ray Inman's surprising withdrawal as the nominee on Tuesday and Senator Sam Nunn's rejection of the job, Administration officials said Mr. Clinton was leaning in favor of the safe and sound, though unspectacular, choice of Mr. Perry.</p>
        <p>"In Perry, they have someone who can do the job and do it very well," Harold Brown, the Secretary of Defense during the Carter Administration, said in a telephone interview today. "Stars often flare out."</p>
        <p>President Clinton will consider possible choices to head the Pentagon during his weekend at Camp David, and an announcement could come as early as Monday, White House officials said.</p>
        <p>"He'll spend some time on it," the White House spokeswoman, Dee Dee Myers, told reporters today. "He will over the course of the next few days until the process is completed."</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff, Thomas F. McLarty 3d, has been heading the search, along with Vice President Al Gore and Mr. Clinton's national security adviser, Anthony Lake.  Process of Elimination</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry appears to have emerged as the consensus choice more through a process of elimination than through the kind of aggressive recruiting campaign that attracted Mr. Inman, however briefly, to the job.</p>
        <p>Senator Nunn and Warren B. Rudman, a former Republican Senator from New Hampshire, took themselves out of the running. Norman Augustine, the Martin Marietta Corporation chief, was also described as a candidate, though White House officials said they had made "no effort to reach out to him." But he too let it be known that he was not interested.</p>
        <p>Some House Democrats have urged the White House to settle on a compromise that would delay the appointment of a new Secretary until the end of the year, and allow the current Defense Secretary, Les Aspin, to put into place the first year of the Pentagon's ambitious new war-fighting strategy for the future. But a White House official said this option was a "fairly outside long shot."</p>
        <p>"That leaves Bill Perry as the last man standing," said one senior Pentagon official, adding that Mr. Perry would be an excellent choice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry received strong support today from influential senators.</p>
        <p>"Bill Perry would be an excellent man," said Senator Jim Exon, a Nebraska Democrat who is a senior member of the Armed Services Committee. "If Perry were the choice, we would be extremely well served."</p>
        <p>Senator Nunn, the Georgia Democrat who heads the Armed Services Committee, also has a long and close relationship with Mr. Perry that dates to when Mr. Perry served as the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Development under President Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>In that position, Mr. Perry overcame resistance within the Pentagon and in Congress to develop the laser-guided bombs and F-117 Stealth fighter that played instrumental roles in the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry, who served two years in the Army beginning in 1946, also has experience as an entrepreneur and executive in the military industry. In 1964 he was a founder of E.S.L. Inc., a military electronics company, and left there as its president to work at the Pentagon.  Advised Soviet Officials</p>
        <p>After his stint in the Carter Administration, Mr. Perry became a managing director of Hambrecht &amp; Quist, Inc., an investment banking concern in San Francisco that specializes in technology issues. He later served as chairman of Technology Strategies and Alliances, a management consulting company, and a director of the Center for International Security and Arms Control at Stanford University, where he worked with former Soviet military officials on how to convert their military industries to commercial uses.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Perry's major challenges since his return to the Pentagon under Mr. Aspin was to overhaul the cumbersome and costly system the military uses to buy its new weapons and spare parts.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Perry's initial optimism about changing an acquisition and research system that spends about $100 billion a year has given way to frustration in the face of resistance from an industry and a military wary of changes that some officers believe could hurt combat readiness.</p>
        <p>When Congress returns from its recess next week, though, it will take up legislation addressing ways to streamline the purchasing process.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
