<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NATO's Cousin Organization Will Meet on Crisis</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="378380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IRAQ-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-KUWAIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERSIAN GULF</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTERN EUROPEAN UNION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF143CF932A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NATO's Cousin Organization Will Meet on Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Aug. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Amid criticism that they have not yet developed a coherent response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, key Western European governments are to meet here Tuesday under the auspices of a little-known defense organization that has long been overshadowed by NATO.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Amid criticism that they have not yet developed a coherent response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, key Western European governments are to meet here Tuesday under the auspices of a little-known defense organization that has long been overshadowed by NATO.</p>
        <p>Amid criticism that they have not yet developed a coherent response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, key Western European governments are to meet here Tuesday under the auspices of a little-known defense organization that has long been overshadowed by NATO.</p>
        <p>The Western European Union, as it is known, comprises nine countries that are members of both the European Community and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization. But unlike NATO, which can operate only in Europe and North America, the Western European Union has no geographical restrictions on its activities.</p>
        <p>''This is our main appeal today,'' an official of the organization said. ''Our charter says we can respond to threats to peace 'in whatever area this threat should arise' as well as to threats to our economic stability. It's tailor-made for the current crisis.''</p>
        <p>With both foreign and defense ministers expected to attend Tuesday's session, experts said the organization aimed to coordinate European naval activities in the Persian Gulf and to provide a political umbrella for governments wary of becoming involved militarily in the crisis.</p>
        <p>After the meeting, foreign ministers of the 12-nation European Community - the nine nations of the Western European Union plus Greece, Ireland and Denmark - are also to meet here to discuss the fate of some 7,700 Community citizens who are trapped in Iraq and Kuwait.</p>
        <p>While working together diplomatically, however, Western European nations have so far failed to develop a common military strategy, with Britain alone in joining the United States in an international force protecting Saudi Arabia and only France also sending naval reinforcements to the gulf.</p>
        <p>Several governments nonetheless now seem willing to act more forcefully. The Netherlands today ordered two frigates to the gulf. Warships sent by Italy and Belgium to the eastern Mediterranean may also move into the gulf if given the green light by the Western European Union.</p>
        <p>Belgium said any decision to send its three minesweepers into the gulf would depend on the Western European Union's stand.</p>
        <p>Spain, which is allowing American aircraft to use United States bases in its territory to refuel on their way to Saudi Arabia, has already alerted several warships in expectation of the Paris meeting. Portugal and Luxembourg, the remaining members of the organization, have so far not disclosed their plans.</p>
        <p>Bonn Won't Send Warships</p>
        <p>BONN, West Germany, Aug. 20 (Reuters) - West Germany will not send any warships to the Persian Gulf because such action would violate its Constitution, Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher said today.</p>
        <p>He told reporters that Chancellor Helmut Kohl and Government and party leaders had agreed unanimously that a military operation in the gulf region would be contrary to the Constitution, which bars West Germany from sending warships on combat missions outside NATO's area.</p>
        <p>But he said the meeting, which included the opposition's candidate for chancellor, Oskar Lafontaine, favored a constitutional amendment to allow West German forces to go to the gulf as part of a United Nations force.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
