<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Republicans Maintain Control of the Senate</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="567909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 ELECTION: NEW YORK STATE -- THE NEW YORK LEGISLATURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD1E3FF937A35752C1A964958260" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Republicans Maintain Control of the Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After spending more for a state legislative seat than any other candidate in New York history, the majority leader of the State Senate, Ralph J. Marino, last night comfortably fended off a vigorous challenge that had threatened his standing as the most powerful Republican in state government.</p>
        <p>At the same time, several Republican colleagues of Mr. Marino in the Senate also appeared to have beaten back Democratic challengers and thus preserved the G.O.P.'s 27-year grip on the Senate, but with the strong possibility that the party's majority would be diminished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After spending more for a state legislative seat than any other candidate in New York history, the majority leader of the State Senate, Ralph J. Marino, last night comfortably fended off a vigorous challenge that had threatened his standing as the most powerful Republican in state government.</p>
        <p>At the same time, several Republican colleagues of Mr. Marino in the Senate also appeared to have beaten back Democratic challengers and thus preserved the G.O.P.'s 27-year grip on the Senate, but with the strong possibility that the party's majority would be diminished.</p>
        <p>As of 12:45 A.M. today, Republicans, who now hold a 35-to-26 edge in the chamber, were ahead in at least 32 races and seemed likely to win at least one other.</p>
        <p>Overall, Democratic hopes of riding the Clinton-Gore coattails to victory in the local State Senate races were, in most cases, crushed.</p>
        <p>In one bitterly contested race in Queens pitting two incumbents against each other, a Republican Senator, Frank Padavan, defeated his Democratic opponent, Jeremy S. Weinstein. With 77 percent of the precincts counted, Mr. Padavan had 60 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>In another hotly contested race, in the Hudson Valley, with 90 percent of the precincts counted, a Republican incumbent, Joseph R. Holland, led a Democrat, Diana Hess, a former utility-company executive and soap-opera star, by 56 percent to 44 percent.</p>
        <p>In the conservative southwestern corner of the state, a surprisingly close race emerged as Nancy Gay Bargar, the Democratic challenger, was leading by a single percentage point over the Republican incumbent, Jess Present, with about 90 percent of the precincts counted. Mr. Present was hurt as 9 percent of the voters turned to John W. Hasper, a Republican Assemblyman whose name appeared on the Conservative line even though he had endorsed Mr. Present after losing the Republican primary.</p>
        <p>Democrats also were on the verge of winning an open seat in the Rochester area. Marino Talks Tough</p>
        <p>A fiery Mr. Marino declared victory around 11 P.M. at his headquarters in Jericho, L.I., and offered a blunt retort to two conservative anti-tax groups that had also spent heavily to denigrate his record in Albany. "To hell with Pack-Up, to hell with Change-NY," he said, referring to the groups by name. And he pledged to lead an effort to revitalize his party as it approaches the 1994 gubernatorial election.</p>
        <p>At 12:45 A.M. today, with 34 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Marino had captured 60 percent of the vote in his race against James F. Gaughran,</p>
        <p>a Suffolk County legislator. Mr. Gaughran had conceded after early returns showed him losing even in precincts of his hometown of Huntington.</p>
        <p>In the Assembly races, while final totals were not available, Democrats appeared assured of winning at least 88 of the 95 seats they hold now, and probably several more.  High-Visibility Race</p>
        <p>The race involving Mr. Marino was clearly the most watched among the contests for the 211 seats in the State Legislature -- 150 in the State Assembly and 61 in the Senate.</p>
        <p>As the majority leader of the Senate, which has been in G.O.P. hands since 1965, Mr. Marino is the most powerful Republican in state government.</p>
        <p>It is extremely rare for a legislative leader to face any serious opposition in a re-election bid, and indeed the last time one actually lost was in 1978 when the Assembly Speaker, Stanley Steingut of Brooklyn, was upended in a Democratic primary by an insurgent, Murray Weinstein.</p>
        <p>As of Oct. 19, which was the most recent mandatory filing at the State Board of Elections, Mr. Marino had spent $560,000 and Mr. Gaughran $80,000, with both men expected to add tens of thousands of dollars to those totals by the end of the campaign.</p>
        <p>On top of that, Mr. Gaughran benefited from the $185,000 spent in a highly unusual campaign, an effort against Marino led by an anti-tax conservative group that calls itself Pack-Up, for the Political Action Committee to Kick Out Unproductive Politicians. The campaign, listed in elections filings as an "educational effort on Ralph Marino's record," consisted of a flood of radio commercials excoriating Mr. Marino for approving billions of dollars in tax increase and deferred tax cuts during his tenure in Albany.</p>
        <p>The drama over Mr. Marino's plight played against the backdrop of Democratic hopes that the Clinton landslide in New York state would help the party do what it had failed to do for almost three decades: take back the Senate from the Republicans.</p>
        <p>But history, and the realpolitik of incumbency-protection politics in Albany, suggested all along that the Democrats' battle would be very much an uphill one.</p>
        <p>The Democrats needed to pick up 5 seats to take control.</p>
        <p>But the G.O.P., which controlled the reapportionment process in the Senate this year, drew new district lines to maximize their advantages. That made it even tougher for the Democrats to win new seats than in 1990, when a similar push for a Democratic victory failed miserably, and the Republicans actually picked up a seat.</p>
        <p>And because the laws of political gravity in Albany push money toward expected winners, the Republicans held an overwhelming advantage in fund raising as well this year. The New York State Republican Senate Campaign Committee, the chief funnel to G.O.P. candidates, has received about $1.2 million in contributions for this campaign, almost 10 times what the Democrats got.</p>
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, consumed with campaign work on behalf of the Clinton-Gore ticket and for the economic-development bond act that he proposed, had little time for specific campaigning for Democratic Senate candidates.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cuomo, angrily dismissing suggestions that he doesn't mind having the Republican-led Senate around as a whipping boy, urged voters in general to back Democratic candidates for the Senate.</p>
        <p>With the Democrats in firm control of the Assembly, Mr. Cuomo and Democratic lawmakers repeatedly pledged that if the Democrats won the Senate, New Yorkers would quickly see passage of a range of legislation routinely blocked by the G.O.P.: stiffer environmental protections, a ban on assault weapons, changes in allocation of school aid and an overhaul of New York's infamously arcane election laws.</p>
        <p>In the Assembly, while there were a handful of close races, and reapportionment virtually guaranteed the election of several new black and Hispanic lawmakers, there was virtually no suspense about the overall outcome: the Democrats, who now have a 95-to-55 edge and controlled redistricting in their house, all along were expected to maintain their overwhelming majority.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 ELECTION: NEW YORK STATE -- THE NEW YORK LEGISLATURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
