<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes Slowing Down Can Really Get Hectic</title>
    <meta content="Y07ITAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/07/international/europe/07ITAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1398477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Greve Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greve (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saturnini, Paolo (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Slow Food</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EED9173DF934A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes Slowing Down Can Really Get Hectic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sometimes Slowing Down Can Really Get Hectic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>GREVE, Italy</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paolo Saturnini, mayor of Greve, Italy, is founder of International Network of Slow Cities; he describes slow city as one that preserves its architectural heritage, typical dishes and inherited customs; five Italian cities belong, and 40 more want to join; Greve's effort to bring back something of its past has produced commercial boom, helped by tourists who now crowd its cafes; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since Paolo Saturnini declared this old market town, in the heart of Chianti country, a slow city, life has never been so hectic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saturnini, 52, has been mayor of Greve for 13 years, and his inspiration came from the Slow Food movement that arose in the 1980's to oppose fast food and its values of homogeneity, impersonality and haste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since an old Italian market town in the heart of Chianti country declared itself a slow city two years ago, life has been busier than ever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since Paolo Saturnini declared this old market town, in the heart of Chianti country, a slow city, life has never been so hectic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saturnini, 52, has been mayor of Greve for 13 years, and his inspiration came from the Slow Food movement that arose in the 1980's to oppose fast food and its values of homogeneity, impersonality and haste.</p>
        <p>When McDonald's began to open in Italian cities, Slow Food proponents set up tables in the street in front and served traditional dishes like pasta in meals lasting hours. Next came long lunches, a movement in Tuscany that fosters old-style lunches, stretched out over hours, with traditional dishes that often take as long to prepare as unhurried diners take to consume them.</p>
        <p>If Slow Food and long lunches, Mr. Saturnini reasoned, why not slow cities?</p>
        <p>''Cities are becoming all uniform; they are losing their identity, their souls,'' Mr. Saturnini lamented in a recent conversation. In commerce, he added, chain stores triumph, creating sameness in food and customs. ''It's a negative uniformity,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A slow city, by contrast, would preserve its architectural heritage, typical dishes and inherited customs. So two years ago, Mr. Saturnini founded the International Network of Slow Cities. Today, five Italian cities belong, and 40 more want to join.</p>
        <p>But Greve -- once known for little more than being the birthplace of the explorer Giovanni da Verrazano -- now finds itself with little time to slow down.</p>
        <p>''Everyone's running,'' complained Alessandra Molletti, Mr. Saturnini's assistant, taking time to show a visitor around, since the mayor's calendar was full. Being a slow city, she said, ''is a two-edged benefit -- it helps us live better, but it's also commercially useful.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Saturnini says he wants to leave his son something of his grandparents, Ms. Molletti explained, and in a world full of uniformity, Greve finds that individuality sells well. So like much of Tuscany, Greve is thriving selling its uniqueness. Unemployment has been replaced by a labor shortage, and while the young once emigrated for jobs, they are returning. Ms. Molletti is an example: a native of the region, she spent eight years working in the theater in New York, before settling in Greve.</p>
        <p>Stefano Falorni never left. For eight generations, his forebears ran the pork store on the main piazza. But Italy's opening to the rest of Europe, which led other local butchers to import pork from the Netherlands and beef from Denmark, nearly drove the Falornis out of business.</p>
        <p>So five years ago, Mr. Falorni, now 55, revived a near-extinct race of local free-ranging hogs to produce salami and ham. Now, Mr. Falorni employs 40 people raising the distinctive black and white hogs and producing meat products. Local restaurants feature pasta with meat sauce from the hogs, and tourists fill his store. The meat is shipped throughout Europe, and orders come from as far as Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>''We put our soul in this salami,'' Mr. Falorni says, tugging at a bushy moustache. ''Not just pork.'' Asked whether he found time for long lunches, he confessed he usually sneaks off for a sandwich.</p>
        <p>Greve's backwardness, he said, became an asset. His competitors, he went on, ''are outside biting their nails, while we're making money.''</p>
        <p>For decades after World War II, Ms. Molletti said, the people of Greve, like so many Italians, sought modernity in neon signs to replace old hand-painted ones, and aluminum front doors, rather than wood. Now Mr. Saturnini campaigns against neon and aluminum. He urges store owners to put out flower boxes of geraniums, and rewards with diplomas those who paint their facades. He has banned big hotel chains, like Sheraton, and sought to instill a taste for tradition in the young by asking school cafeterias to serve the kind of bread soup their grandmothers used to cook, and teachers to take their pupils on field trips to the grape harvest to learn about wine.</p>
        <p>Of course, no one here mistakes this return to past ways with the real thing, whose main features were poverty and unemployment.</p>
        <p>Sandro Checcucci, 35, ran a quiet wine bar until two years ago. Then, local investors, including Mr. Falorni, restored a block of quaint wine cellars that had stood unused for 30 years. They installed one of Tuscany's biggest wine shops and hired Mr. Checcucci to run it. Now, streams of visitors taste the 1,100 Tuscan wines that Mr. Checcucci offers. In place of unemployment, he said, ''we now lack workers, especially in the tourist season.'' The 15- to 20-year olds often leave, tired of the quaintness, he said, though many return in search of work. What's missing now, he added, is ''social life -- not jobs.''</p>
        <p>Still, Rossella Rossi, who runs the 10-room hotel on the piazza, said there was no mistaking the new Greve with the town of her youth. Around Greve, fields once terraced with grape and olives that were tended by hand are now sloped to allow for tractors and other mechanized equipment, Ms. Rossi, a woman in her 30's, said. ''Where the bookstore is, there was a greengrocer,'' she said, ''and a poultry shop where they now sell souvenirs.''</p>
        <p>''It's developed,'' she added. ''But it has lost that aspect of genuineness.''</p>
        <p>Greve Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
