<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daniel Hopes to Show Age Is Just a State of Mind</title>
    <meta content="07LPGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/07/sports/golf/07LPGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1398535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mcdonald's Lpga Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daniel, Beth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Daniel, Beth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DC143DF934A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daniel Hopes to Show Age Is Just a State of Mind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Daniel Hopes Age Just a State of Mind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, Del., June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Beth Daniels hopes to break record for oldest woman golfer to win major championship with win at McDonald's LPGA Championship, at 45 years old; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The oldest woman golfer to win a major championship was Babe Zaharias, who captured the 1954 United States Open at the age of 43 years 7 days. Beth Daniel can break the record by nearly three years with a victory at this week's McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>The 45-year-old Daniel signaled that she would be a contender today when she shot a four-under-par 67 in the opening round of the $1.5 million tournament, the second major of the season. Daniel's only major victory among the 32 titles in her career came at the L.P.G.A. Championship in 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beth Daniel can break the record for the oldest woman golfer to win a major at the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship, but Karrie Webb leads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The oldest woman golfer to win a major championship was Babe Zaharias, who captured the 1954 United States Open at the age of 43 years 7 days. Beth Daniel can break the record by nearly three years with a victory at this week's McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>The 45-year-old Daniel signaled that she would be a contender today when she shot a four-under-par 67 in the opening round of the $1.5 million tournament, the second major of the season. Daniel's only major victory among the 32 titles in her career came at the L.P.G.A. Championship in 1990.</p>
        <p>Daniel was the leader in the clubhouse at the DuPont Country Club, but she was a shot behind Karrie Webb, who was on the course with three holes left when play was suspended shortly before 6 p.m. because of lightning. Webb, who won this tournament last year, does not have a victory this season and is ranked 21st on the money list.</p>
        <p>Annika Sorenstam, who ranks first on the money list and who posted her fourth victory of the year last week, shot a one-under-par 70. Sorenstam was at three under par with four holes to play, but she had two bogeys, which was uncharacteristic for the 31-year-old Swede, who won the season's first major, the Kraft Nabisco Championship.</p>
        <p>Daniel had two decent rounds at the Kraft Nabisco in late March, but she shot a 75 in the third round and finished tied for 14th. Daniel said today that she was more upset with what was repeatedly said on television about her age.</p>
        <p>''It really bugged me that they kept saying on TV the whole weekend, 45-year-old Beth Daniel for birdie from 10 feet, 45-year-old Beth Daniel teeing off,'' she said. ''That was like my new first name; Beth was like my middle name. That really kind of bugged me because, really, what is age? Age is a state of mind. You have guys on the PGA Tour that are in their 40's winning tournaments. Why can't you have women 45 years old winning golf tournaments?''</p>
        <p>Daniel would like to imitate Betsy King and Juli Inkster, who are also among the leaders in this tournament, by winning an event in her 40's. Five of King's 34 victories have come after her 40th birthday and Inkster has three victories in her 40's, including one in this tournament two years ago. King and Inkster were at two under par when play was suspended with 72 players still on the course. King had three holes left and Inkster five.</p>
        <p>Daniel has not played well in recent years. She last won a tournament in 1995, four years before she became the 16th player to be inducted into the L.P.G.A. Hall of Fame. But she has been playing well this season thanks primarily to an improvement in her putting. Daniel started using a long putter two years ago, and it is starting to pay dividends this year.</p>
        <p>Daniel made six birdies today, one from 40 feet and another from 60, on greens that were extremely fast. She also had two bogeys.</p>
        <p>''I putted extremely well,'' Daniel said, ''but I'm also pleased with the way I played over all. I tried to play smart golf and I managed to do that for the most part. I also had good control of my irons and, as I said before, I putted extremely well. I've been playing golf since I was 6, but I started using the long putter two years ago and it's like learning a new skill.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
