<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hollywood Film Chain's Latest Link</title>
    <meta content="18holl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/18/movies/18holl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1797950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Sam Mendes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Mendes, Sam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Foxx, Jamie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6D71E30F93BA25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hollywood Film Chain's Latest Link</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hollywood Film Chain’s Latest Link</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, the director Sam Mendes collected his ''director of the year'' prize at a star-studded but still otherwise obscure, untelevised gala called the Hollywood Awards, two weeks before his film ''Jarhead'' was even released. ''I'm very fond of giving awards to movies you've never seen,'' he joked to a knowing audience of filmmakers, actors and studio executives.</p>
        <p>This time around, the estimable Mike Medavoy is being named ''Hollywood producer of the year'' in connection with what might have been the Oscar campaign for ''All the King's Men'' -- had the film not turned into one of the biggest disappointments of his storied career. The Oscar winner Eric Roth will be named ''Hollywood screenwriter of the year'' even though his only film of 2006, ''The Good Shepherd,'' doesn't open until mid-December and is still being edited. And the production designer John Myhre, a two-time Oscar winner, is being similarly honored, though his movie ''Dreamgirls'' won't come out until Christmas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hollywood Film Festival didn’t exist, so Carlos de Abreu invented it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, the director Sam Mendes collected his ''director of the year'' prize at a star-studded but still otherwise obscure, untelevised gala called the Hollywood Awards, two weeks before his film ''Jarhead'' was even released. ''I'm very fond of giving awards to movies you've never seen,'' he joked to a knowing audience of filmmakers, actors and studio executives.</p>
        <p>This time around, the estimable Mike Medavoy is being named ''Hollywood producer of the year'' in connection with what might have been the Oscar campaign for ''All the King's Men'' -- had the film not turned into one of the biggest disappointments of his storied career. The Oscar winner Eric Roth will be named ''Hollywood screenwriter of the year'' even though his only film of 2006, ''The Good Shepherd,'' doesn't open until mid-December and is still being edited. And the production designer John Myhre, a two-time Oscar winner, is being similarly honored, though his movie ''Dreamgirls'' won't come out until Christmas.</p>
        <p>All of these dubious honors -- not to take anything away from the honorees themselves -- will be handed out on Monday night at the Hollywood Awards, in what has become the first mandatory stop on the flashbulb-and-red-carpet-lined moving sidewalk of self-congratulation that is the awards season. Primarily seen as a publicity vehicle for late-year releases, the awards show and its promoters have lately made pretensions to Oscar oracling: Jamie Foxx won the ''breakthrough actor of the year'' prize for ''Ray'' in 2004, after all, and Paul Haggis and his ensemble cast were honored for ''Crash'' four months before it won best picture.</p>
        <p>Still, the story behind this peculiar Hollywood extravaganza is emblematic of some aspects of the town itself: dreamt up almost overnight, built on facades more than foundations and, at bottom, a money-making enterprise.</p>
        <p>The architect and chief financial beneficiary of it all is Carlos de Abreu, a Portuguese-accented P. T. Barnum who once worked in intelligence on what he called ''the wrong side'' of the African National Congress for colonial Mozambique, flew jets in its air force and marketed Cartier watches to rich Americans before quitting his job to study film at the University of California, Los Angeles, and marrying Janice Pennington, then a model on ''The Price Is Right.''</p>
        <p>Together the two set about finding ways to help novices enter the film industry while making a buck themselves. They started a screenplay competition in 1991, hoping to attach themselves to any winners that were produced. In 1996 they founded the Hollywood Film Festival, after learning to their surprise that the name wasn't yet taken, Mr. de Abreu said.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview Mr. de Abreu said he had been working for more than a decade to ''bridge the gap between established Hollywood and emerging talent,'' and cited a screenwriting how-to book of which he is a co-author and an Internet bulletin board for screenwriters he set up.</p>
        <p>In Mr. de Abreu's retelling, he had an awards show in mind all along, but was urged by friends to try a film festival. So he created both. Yet while the awards show now looms large on the industry's fall calendar, and while the Hollywood Film Festival has turned up discoveries like the director Craig Brewer, it is still not a rival to independent film festivals like Sundance, Telluride or the New York Film Festival. Its premieres are also not the cream of the crop: last year's opening feature was the action-comedy ''Kiss Kiss, Bang Bang.'' This year's is the family film ''Flicka.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, unlike those and many other film festivals -- and even the Golden Globes, whose organizers give away millions of dollars to charity -- Mr. de Abreu's business, including both the film festival and the awards show, is anything but a nonprofit enterprise. He declined to reveal its revenues but insisted he was not getting rich: his Mercedes, he said, is 16 years old.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Abreu said he did once establish a philanthropy called the Hollywood Film Foundation, but that it was no longer active. Asked why, he said: ''I don't have time for everything.''</p>
        <p>No doubt, Mr. de Abreu has been busy raising his game since his first festival in 1997. (The New York Times was a sponsor of the festival in its early years but is no longer involved.) And he has proven a canny marketer. To attract A-listers early on, he staged the awards show in August, when few if any industrywide events compete for celebrities' time; in 2002, he moved it to October, at the start of the Oscar-campaign preliminaries. Today he packs a ballroom at the Beverly Hilton, honoring not only industry players but also international films, chosen by a jury, and American popcorn movies, chosen by a Web poll.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Abreu also hired the publicity powerhouse PMK/HBH, which steered some of its own clients to attend and lent the fledging awards show credibility by association, and signed Paula Wagner, Tom Cruise's producing partner and a former top talent agent, as his co-chair. While PMK no longer handles Mr. de Abreu's press, Ms. Wagner continues to urge her industry peers to make appearances at the awards show or contribute films to the festival, several industry executives said. Pat Kingsley, head of PMK/HBH, and Ms. Wagner both declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Abreu said he viewed his ''of-the-year'' honors as lauding a body of work; Mr. Medavoy, for one, is turning out five movies this year, not just ''All the King's Men.'' Mr. Roth said he had agreed to be honored partly because it put him in good company -- Robert Towne once accepted it, too -- and partly because he hoped it would help Universal promote ''The Good Shepherd.'' Robert De Niro, who directed the film, is to present Mr. Roth with his honor.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Abreu has honed his own tricks, of course, for enticing top stars and industry people to participate -- the starry ensemble of ''Bobby,'' somewhat predictably, is being honored en masse -- and for getting major film companies to help foot the bill. (Tables for 10 run from $10,000 to $25,000, though Mr. de Abreu said his honorees, presenters and all the independent filmmakers are admitted free.)</p>
        <p>To no one's objection, Mr. de Abreu's awards show spreads the wealth. Every major studio has at least one film represented, from Universal, with six honors, to Warner Brothers, with two.</p>
        <p>Executives at three studios, who demanded anonymity lest they be revealed as resentful, cowardly and spendthrift, complained that Mr. de Abreu had proved himself adept at manipulating even reluctant studios into participating, often by signing up their stars and filmmakers before approaching the company -- especially those embarking on a sales blitz for a forthcoming movie or a campaign for an Oscar contender. Once the talent is tagged for an honor, studio executives said they felt obligated to get on board.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. de Abreu said he always plays fair. Films and filmmakers are honored whether their studios buy into the show or not, he said, and his awards-picking process is ''transparent'' -- though he declined to identify anyone involved, other than his wife, Ms. Wagner and himself.</p>
        <p>More to the point, he asked that his industry awards not be measured by others' standards. ''They're not competing,'' he said. ''There is no contest. Our organization could be you and me. We're trying to celebrate film.''</p>
        <p>A surer sign of Mr. de Abreu's concern for film over the bottom line may be his reluctance to sell the show's broadcast rights. He said he has had offers but rejected them rather than drop some of the ''below-the-line'' categories of awards, like makeup and costume design.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, he added, ''We may change our mind.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
