<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Terror in the Air, and Frantic Rescue From the Sea</title>
    <meta content="25HIJA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19961127T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="891961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mitsamouli (Comoro Islands)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ethiopian Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Comoros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DB133DF936A15752C1A960958260" item-length="1472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Terror in the Air, and Frantic Rescue From the Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</byline>
      <dateline>MITSAMOULI, Comoro Islands, Nov. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hijacked Ethiopian Airlines jet runs out of gas and crashes into sea just off Mitsamouli, Comoro Islands, narrowly missing hotel; 123 of 175 people aboard are believed dead; hotel quickly sends out its scuba boats, one of which carries eight French doctors, to rescue survivors; two of hijackers survive crash and are in custody; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When two passengers burst out of their seats and ran up the gangway to the cockpit, Hiwot Tadesse, a flight attendant, thought they were having a fight. When a third followed them, holding something in his gloved hands, she knew the plane was being hijacked.</p>
        <p>''I pushed back my trolley and told the other girl to stop serving drinks,'' she said today. ''The terrorists said for everyone to be seated. They said they had explosives and they were going to blow up the airplane.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When two passengers burst out of their seats and ran up the gangway to the cockpit, Hiwot Tadesse, a flight attendant, thought they were having a fight. When a third followed them, holding something in his gloved hands, she knew the plane was being hijacked.</p>
        <p>''I pushed back my trolley and told the other girl to stop serving drinks,'' she said today. ''The terrorists said for everyone to be seated. They said they had explosives and they were going to blow up the airplane.''</p>
        <p>That moment of confusion was the start of a terrifying four-hour ride that ended in the death of more passengers than in any other previous hijacking. The bodies have not all been recovered, but 123 of the 175 aboard are believed to have died Saturday when Ethiopian Airlines Flight 961 shot over the airport and a resort hotel on this volcanic island in the Indian Ocean and, flying almost silently because it was out of fuel, turned sharply and fell into the sea.</p>
        <p>The Boeing 767 struck the water once, bounced and then smashed nose first, breaking into three pieces. The airplane crashed only 500 yards from the shore, just missing a class of scuba-diving students on their first dive.</p>
        <p>$(In Washington, a State Department spokesman said that four Americans were on the plane and that three were among the 52 survivors, including the American Consul General in Bombay, Franklin P. Huddle, and his wife, Shania. The spokesman, Christopher Bush, said he could not release any other information about the American passengers.</p>
        <p>$(He said the State Department was sending investigators to the Comoros, including agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, because air piracy abroad is a Federal crime if there are American passengers on board.$)</p>
        <p>The pilot's ability to ditch the airplane just in front of the Galawa Beach Hotel but not on it may have saved many more lives. The airplane seemed to be heading straight for the hotel, witnesses said, when it suddenly pitched to the right, missing the building and crashing into the water.</p>
        <p>And the quick thinking of the director of water sports, who immediately radioed in all her scuba boats, one of which carried eight French doctors, may have helped save the passengers and crew members who got out of the crash alive.</p>
        <p>The survivors described being trapped underwater in their seats with the waves pitching the wreckage of the fuselage to and fro, the bodies of dead passengers brushing against them as they struggled to undo their seat belts.</p>
        <p>Many who were barely hurt in the crash suffered cuts on their hands and legs as they crawled through twisted metal in the half-sunken wreckage to reach holes where they could see sunlight.</p>
        <p>Hotel scuba instructors who dived into the wreck described bodies trapped in their seats, sometimes held in by the life vests they had put on when the captain said they were going down.</p>
        <p>Passengers who escaped said they clung to sections of the fuselage screaming for help as the plane rocked in a sea of dismembered bodies, wreckage and floating pieces of luggage and clothes.</p>
        <p>''It is a miracle for me,'' said Nagin B. Surti, 55, a passenger from Bombay, India, where the flight originated. Mr. Surti, who emerged with only scratches and a cut hand when he climbed the overhead rack and squeezed out of a hole in the airplane said, ''I had made my last prayer saying, 'Please, God, we are your human beings, please.' ''</p>
        <p>He said he did not know what happened to a friend he was traveling with, but he shook his head, showing little hope.</p>
        <p>Officials say they do not yet know the hijackers' motive, but two of them survived the crash and are in jail here. Early reports said they boarded the plane at Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, commandeered it about 20 minutes later, persuaded the pilot that there were 11 hijackers on board and demanded to be taken to Australia.</p>
        <p>The flight, bound for Nairobi, Kenya, and then across Africa to Ivory Coast, did not have enough fuel to fly to Australia, the pilot says he told the hijackers, but they insisted on going in any case.</p>
        <p>Two flight attendants who survived, Mrs. Tadesse and Yeshimebete Gebremeskel, 36, said the hijackers beat the co-pilot and pushed him out of the cockpit. They said the hijackers spoke English, French and Amharic, Ethiopia's main language.</p>
        <p>''But it wasn't fluent,'' Mrs. Tadesse said. ''It was like a neighbor country.''</p>
        <p>One of the hijackers sat in the co-pilot's seat and played with the control stick like a child, she said, making the plane dip dangerously several times. It was only in the last few minutes of the flight that the co-pilot forced his way back into the cockpit and took back his seat, she said.</p>
        <p>Both the co-pilot and the pilot survived, though the pilot has a head injury, hospital workers said.</p>
        <p>For the passengers, the hours in flight were a nightmare. They were told only that they had been hijacked and should stay seated. On a flight that was supposed to be over Africa, they could see the ocean below.</p>
        <p>One hijacker stayed in the first-class compartment, glaring at the passengers to keep them in their seats.</p>
        <p>''He let us feed the children,'' Mrs. Tadesse said.</p>
        <p>When he would look down one aisle, she said, she would let passengers along the other aisle sneak to the bathroom or get a sandwich.</p>
        <p>When the airplane ran out of fuel at 3:20 P.M. (7:20 A.M. Eastern time Saturday), Caroline Fotherby, 34, the hotel's manager for water sports, was in her beach clubhouse, having decided at the last minute to do some paperwork instead of going diving.</p>
        <p>''I heard a plane approaching, but not loudly,'' she said. ''Then there was a crash. First I thought it was thunder, but it was sunny. Then I thought it was the volcano here, but then my staff screamed 'Emirates!'  I turned round and saw the wing of a plane sticking out of the water, and a tail just a stone's throw from one of my dives in progress.''</p>
        <p>Emirates, she explained, is the name of an airline that flies to the island twice a week.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fotherby immediately called the hotel nurse and all her instructors by radio, and they rushed to the site in high-speed rubber boats, grabbing survivors where they could. A glass-bottomed cruise boat pushed off the beach and brought a dozen more survivors to shore.</p>
        <p>The nurse set up a clinic in an open-air restaurant and the eight vacationing French doctors and two from South Africa worked for hours in their bathing suits, saving lives.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fotherby said she saw one decapitated body, and others with severe injuries, as the living were treated in the restaurant and the dead were piled on top of old sheets and linens on the beach.</p>
        <p>Despite a traffic jam of vehicles crowding the island's narrow coast road, the injured were eventually all transferred to the run-down hospital in Moroni, the capital, where many lay on iron beds, eight to a room.</p>
        <p>$(Arun Mehen, airport manager at  Sahar International Airport in Bombay, said 42 of the passengers began their flight in Bombay, including 19 Indians, 9 Sri Lankans, 9 Nigerians and 3 Americans. Aviation officials in Nairobi said 8 Israelis, 7 Britons, 4 French citizens, 3 Italians and a Hungarian were among the passengers.</p>
        <p>$(The dead included Mohamed Amin, 53, a photographer who helped alert the world about the 1984 famine in Ethiopia, and his colleague Brian Tetley, 61, The Associated Press reported, quoting airline officials.$)</p>
        <p>The Comoros Government has declared 48 hours of mourning.</p>
        <p>Tonight, at the Galawa Beach Hotel, there was a full moon over the Indian Ocean. In its light, the tail section of the airplane could be seen, nestled on a reef. A crew of police officers and laborers worked to attach a cable so the tail would not drift off before the arrival of a salvage ship from the French island of Reunion.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 27, 1996, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the crash of an Ethiopian Airlines plane into the Indian Ocean misstated its ranking among air disasters in which a hijacking was involved. With the death toll revised yesterday to 125, this crash was the second worst involving a hijacked aircraft, not the worst; 128 people died in 1990 when a hijacked plane crashed in Guangzhou, China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 27, 1996, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the crash of an Ethiopian Airlines plane into the Indian Ocean misstated its ranking among air disasters in which a hijacking was involved. With the death toll revised yesterday to 125, this crash was the second worst involving a hijacked aircraft, not the worst; 128 people died in 1990 when a hijacked plane crashed in Guangzhou, China.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
