<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Says Trade Pat Will Aid U.S. Economy</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="587702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME APPLIANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL TRADE COMMISSION (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DF1031F930A35751C0A965958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Says Trade Pat Will Aid U.S. Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first comprehensive assessment of the North American Free Trade Agreement by a Federal agency has found that the pact will help overall American economic output and employment slightly, while producing job losses in the auto, household appliance and apparel manufacturing industries.</p>
        <p>The study by the International Trade Commission, an independent Federal agency, buttresses claims made for the agreement by the Bush Administration and rebuts some of the criticism from labor unions and some members of Congress who have predicted huge job losses. First Independent Evaluation</p>
        <p>The study, to be made public later this week, has been awaited on Capitol Hill and at the White House as the first independent evaluation of the pact's merits. It was sent to the Senate Finance and the House Ways and Means Committees Monday night, and a member of Congress allowed a reporter to examine it this afternoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first comprehensive assessment of the North American Free Trade Agreement by a Federal agency has found that the pact will help overall American economic output and employment slightly, while producing job losses in the auto, household appliance and apparel manufacturing industries.</p>
        <p>The study by the International Trade Commission, an independent Federal agency, buttresses claims made for the agreement by the Bush Administration and rebuts some of the criticism from labor unions and some members of Congress who have predicted huge job losses. First Independent Evaluation</p>
        <p>The study, to be made public later this week, has been awaited on Capitol Hill and at the White House as the first independent evaluation of the pact's merits. It was sent to the Senate Finance and the House Ways and Means Committees Monday night, and a member of Congress allowed a reporter to examine it this afternoon.</p>
        <p>The report provides little ammunition for critics who have called for extensive renegotiation of the agreement.</p>
        <p>If approved by Congress, the trade agreement would eliminate -- over the next 15 years -- virtually all import-export barriers among the United States, Canada and Mexico.</p>
        <p>President Clinton promised during the campaign to negotiate three side agreements covering workers' rights, environmental issues and import surges, but said that he would not renegotiate the half-foot-thick basic text of the agreement. But Mickey Kantor, the United States trade representative, muddied that issue at his Senate confirmation hearing on Jan. 19, when he said that he hoped to address the sugar industry's concerns through one of the side agreements.</p>
        <p>The free-trade pact is one of several large trade issues facing the Clinton Administration. Also today, Senator Max S. Baucus, the Montana Democrat who heads the Senate Finance Committee's trade panel, introduced legislation to revive the expired Super 301 law, which had set a fixed schedule of Administration action against foreign countries that trade unfairly, as opposed to indefinite negotiation. The law expired at the end of 1990.</p>
        <p>President Clinton endorsed Super 301 during the election campaign, and it is expected to become law this year. Mr. Baucus also introduced a measure today that would allow domestic industries to force the Federal Government to take action if foreign governments appear to break commitments in past trade pacts.</p>
        <p>Also today, a Congressional aide said that the Administration was reviewing with Congress whether to seek a limited renewal of the so-called fast-track legislation, which allows the President to submit trade agreements to Congress for expedited consideration with no amendments allowed. The Administration is considering a six-month renewal for multilateral agreements -- such as the 112-nation world trade pact now being negotiated in Geneva -- and a four-year extension for bilateral and regional agreements.</p>
        <p>The International Trade Commission's report concluded that if the North American pact was approved by Congress, employment would eventually drop by up to 5 percent in the automotive and apparel industries and up to 15 percent in the major household appliance, glass and ceramic tile industries. The report attributed the job losses to extra competition from Mexican imports and the construction of new factories there.</p>
        <p>But the study estimated that compared with employment forecasts without the agreement, total employment with the agreement would gradually rise by up to eight-hundredths of a percentage point in the United States, up to six-tenths of a percentage point in Canada and up to 6.6 percent in Mexico. The American auto parts, computer, industrial machinery and textile industries would gain jobs.</p>
        <p>The commission's report also projected that the long-term effect would be to increase annual economic output by up to three-tenths of 1 percent in the United States, by up to five-tenths of 1 percent in Canada and by up to 16.2 percent in Mexico.</p>
        <p>Economic studies have consistently predicted that the pact would have the greatest effect on Mexico because its economy is only one-twentieth of the size of the United States economy, and because Mexico already relies heavily on trade with the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
