<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marchibroda's Second About-Face</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="577777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INDIANAPOLIS COLTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BALTIMORE COLTS (DEFUNCT FOOTBALL TEAM)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCHIBRODA, TED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDF163CF933A15751C1A964958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marchibroda's Second About-Face</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The word greatest has rarely (ever?) been applied to the Colts since their infamous 1984 getaway to Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>But now they have their chance: to equal the greatest one-season turnaround in National Football League history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The word greatest has rarely (ever?) been applied to the Colts since their infamous 1984 getaway to Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>But now they have their chance: to equal the greatest one-season turnaround in National Football League history.</p>
        <p>To add to the intrigue, the man who helped establish the record is back at the helm. He would be Ted Marchibroda, who took over a Baltimore Colts team that had gone 2-12 in 1974 and led them to a 10-4 mark in '75.</p>
        <p>Now Marchibroda is running the Colts in Indianapolis, 13 years after he was dismissed. They were 1-15 last year and are 7-7 this season. No team has ever gone from a one-victory season to the playoffs the next year, but the Colts have a chance.</p>
        <p>"This one has been under much more difficult circumstances than the 1975 Colts," said Marchibroda. "We opened up the season with our No. 3 quarterback." In fact, the Colts have used four quarterbacks this year: Jeff George, Mark Hermann, Jack Trudeau and Tom Tupa. George, whom Marchibroda lifted in midgame against the Jets last Sunday, starts today against the Cardinals in the Hoosier Dome.</p>
        <p>"Turnarounds are more difficult now because the game has become so complex, especially if you're a young team and you want to teach them a new system," said Marchibroda.</p>
        <p>The Colts have tied the Cowboys for the most triumphs following a one-victory year. The '89 Cowboys went 1-15 and followed that with a 7-9 record.</p>
        <p>"Sure, I've talked to them about the playoffs," Marchibroda said about his players. "But I told them not to lose focus. That's what's kept us going the last few weeks: not looking ahead."</p>
        <p>What would have lured Marchibroda back to head coaching from the safety of Buffalo, where he had been the respected offensive coordinator of a team that went to the last two Super Bowls?</p>
        <p>"You always want to return," said Marchibroda. "You can't turn down the head job."</p>
        <p>Following are the clubs that improved by eight games: Act Now. Smile Later.</p>
        <p>Steve Gutman and Wellington Mara gave passionate speeches at the league meetings early last week in favor of settling with the union. There has been no labor agreement for five years.</p>
        <p>Gutman, who keeps a low profile as Jets' president, does most of his talking behind closed doors. According to someone who was in the meeting room, Gutman exhorted the league's negotiators to make a deal to promote stability.</p>
        <p>The alternative, Gutman said, was to continue what he described as the current chaotic situation.</p>
        <p>His co-tenant, Mara, the Giants' president, told his peers that the timing was right. He said they should seize the moment by making a deal with the union -- and not wait for a judge's decision, which could result in total free agency and the end of the college draft.</p>
        <p>It had been a quiet season without instant replay -- until Dallas quarterback Troy Aikman was hit in the end zone last Sunday, fumbled the ball and lost the ball game. The Cowboys contended that he was struck while his arm was coming forward, which would have made it an incomplete pass; the officials ruled otherwise, giving the Redskins a touchdown on a fumble recovery.</p>
        <p>The game was the only one last week to which the league brought a replay official and replay gear. Although replay is dead, the N.F.L. has continued to have an experimental replay game of the week to consider its use in the future.</p>
        <p>The league's director of officiating, Jerry Seeman, was not at the game, but said afterward the replay was inconclusive and thus he would not have overturned it.</p>
        <p>But Jack Reader, the assistant head of officials, was there, acting in the imaginary capacity of replay referee. And Reader told John Madden that he would have overruled the call.</p>
        <p>Still, overruled or not, the Cowboys' owner, Jerry Jones, said he remained opposed to instant replay, a position echoed by his coach, Jimmy Johnson. It doesn't appear that the instant-replay proponents will get the three-quarters vote they need to bring it back in its present form. Unless, that is, something outrageous happens in the playoffs or the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>MARTY GLICKMAN retires from more than 50 years of broadcasting next Saturday after doing the radio play-by-play of the Jets-Saints game. He got around even more than the legendary Gladys Goodding, who played for the Dodgers, the Knicks and the Rangers. She was the organist. Glickman broadcast Knicks, Rangers, football Giants, Dodgers and Jets.</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
