<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Horse Racing;   Allies and Foes of Sports Betting</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="376079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRIST, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D61131F937A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Horse Racing;   Allies and Foes of Sports Betting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Crist</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRIST, STEVEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Is widespread legal sports betting inevitable or preventable?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Is widespread legal sports betting inevitable or preventable?</p>
        <p>Is widespread legal sports betting inevitable or preventable?</p>
        <p>The two sides of the issue were argued here Sunday at the Jockey Club Round Table, Saratoga's annual gathering of industry poobahs. The horse racing industry is debating that question in earnest these days because the answer will dictate racing's response and, perhaps, its future.</p>
        <p>The industry nationwide is in a similar position to New York's two decades ago, when legislators decided to institute off-track betting. The New York tracks, fearing OTB as a competitor, shunned the idea, hoping it would fail. Instead, OTB succeeded but under the operation of a massive statewide bureaucracy that has been fighting the tracks' interests ever since.</p>
        <p>The industry does not want to make the same mistake, but also is leery about welcoming a new form of betting that might steal away many customers.</p>
        <p>Advocating prevention here Sunday was James Heffernan, former president of the New York Racing Association and now the president of the American Horse Racing Federation, a national lobbying group. Heffernan pointed to the success last year of Kentucky racing interests, who effectively squelched a plan to base a state lottery on the results of basketball and football games. Noting that state lotteries have taken an estimated 11 percent of racing's business away, Heffernan asked why the sport should do anything but fight another competitor.</p>
        <p>''Legalized sports betting is not inevitable,'' he said. ''If it did come, the tracks would not get a monopoly. The states will inevitably use the huge distribution networks already in place for lotteries.''</p>
        <p>Ed Bowen, editor of The Blood-Horse, a weekly trade magazine published by the Thoroughbred Owners and Breeders' Association, said that sports betting was a cinch to proliferate, given the needs of state treasuries to raise more money. Rather than be left on the outside looking in, he suggested, racing should consider sports betting ''a threat but also an opportunity.'' He said sports betting operated by the tracks would be the ideal way to get more sports fans interested in racing.</p>
        <p>Bowen also noted that it is hypocritical of racing's leaders to make allies of the sports officials who are railing about the immorality of betting on a sporting contest, since horse racing itself is a game of betting on a sporting contest.</p>
        <p>Both speakers made sense, while missing a key point.</p>
        <p>The idea that racing can squelch sports betting seems unrealistic. Sports betting is currently legal only in Nevada, which handled $1.4 billion in bets last year, and experts estimate that illegal bookmakers handle $40 billion more a year, more than three times the national racing action. It is only a matter of time before state legislators begin arguing that they, rather than organized crime, should reap the proceeds.</p>
        <p>Given that, racing should get whatever piece of the action it can, but Heffernan is probably correct that the tracks will not enjoy an exclusive franchise. There are more than 10,000 lottery-ticket outlets in New York state, as opposed to only 300 OTB shops and fewer than a dozen tracks. Why would the state so severely limit the points of sale?</p>
        <p>Bowen argued that sports betting ultimately would help racing because bettors exposed to both types of gambling would find racing the superior challenge. This may be true in a sporting and intellectual sense, and racing does offer the careful, hard-working professional handicapper a realistic chance of beating the game.</p>
        <p>But the main reason that people bet more illegally on football and basketball games than they do legally on horse races is a simple matter of odds. The ''vigorish'' on sports bets -the amount that the bookmaker holds as his guaranteed profit - is only 4.54 percent. For every $220 a bookie takes in, he pays out $210. A bettor who bets $500 a week will on average lose less than $25 a week, which may make it an affordable hobby.</p>
        <p>Race tracks, however, take a minimum of 18 percent - nearly four times as much - and as much as 25 or even 36 percent on trifectas and Pick-6's. A $500 a week bettor will lose about $100 a week or $5,000 a year. After a few years of that, he decides that the game is too tough, and starts thinking about taking the Redskins plus 4 1/2 points instead of betting the daily double at Saratoga.</p>
        <p>To have any chance of competing with illegal bookmakers, state-sponsored sports betting would have to have a similar takeout of about 5 percent. Now, if Belmont Park had a betting window with a 5 percent takeout on football bets and a 25 percent takeout on horse-race bets, which one would have the longer line?</p>
        <p>Every study ever commissioned proves that when tracks give more money back to the customers, the customers bet more, and the track and the state treasury eventually come out ahead. Yet no track in the country is actively seeking a reduction of the takeout. Track managers say it is an unrealistic goal. Such defeatism could prove fatal.</p>
        <p>Racing may be sitting on a short-term boom. Off-track betting and simulcasting are spreading around the country and drawing new customers in. Once such betting machinery is in place, though, it is inevitable that it will someday be selling tickets on basketball games as well as horse races. Unless racing stops taking four times as much money out of every bet as the illegal sports bookies do and the legal ones will, the racing game stands little chance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
