<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 9-Pound Mac Clone</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="376027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL COMPUTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">OUTBOUND SYSTEMS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD91639F937A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 9-Pound Mac Clone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER H. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: APPLE Computer Inc. has given its blessing to a small Colorado company that makes a nine-pound Macintosh-compatible portable. The rival portable machine, called the Outbound Laptop System, is made by Outbound Systems Inc. of Boulder. It is smaller, lighter and - if you already own a Macintosh Plus or SE - less expensive than Apple's own Mac Portable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: APPLE Computer Inc. has given its blessing to a small Colorado company that makes a nine-pound Macintosh-compatible portable. The rival portable machine, called the Outbound Laptop System, is made by Outbound Systems Inc. of Boulder. It is smaller, lighter and - if you already own a Macintosh Plus or SE - less expensive than Apple's own Mac Portable.</p>
        <p>APPLE Computer Inc. has given its blessing to a small Colorado company that makes a nine-pound Macintosh-compatible portable. The rival portable machine, called the Outbound Laptop System, is made by Outbound Systems Inc. of Boulder. It is smaller, lighter and - if you already own a Macintosh Plus or SE - less expensive than Apple's own Mac Portable.</p>
        <p>Apple and Outbound officials declined to give the specific terms of their agreement, but the effect is that Outbound, phone (303) 786-9200, can now sell a Macintosh clone without fear of legal reprisal Earlier, Apple had asserted that the Outbound system violated Apple's intellectual property rights, since it is built around a proprietary Macintosh ROM (read-only memory) chip that is physically removed from a Macintosh Plus or SE computer and transferred to the Outbound portable.</p>
        <p>The ROM chip, which can be thought of as the DNA of the machine, contains the special operating instructions that control all of the basic operations of the Macintosh. Because it uses the Macintosh ROM, the Outbound can run all Macintosh software with 100 percent compatibility.</p>
        <p>Until now, Apple has vigorously challenged any company that has attempted to make a Macintosh workalike. In contrast, the ROM of the original I.B.M. PC has been cloned and used by hundreds of companies over the years. I.B.M.-compatible portables have advanced so far that four-pound ''notebook'' computers with hard disks, high-resolution screens and powerful chips are widely available for $4,000 or less.</p>
        <p>The Mac Portable, which weighs 15.5 pounds with a hard disk, will not fit on a lap, has a dim screen and costs $4,799 to $5,499, even after a $1,000 price cut earlier this year.</p>
        <p>''The Mac Portable, in relation to other portable machines, has not done well,'' said JoeAnn Stahel, president of the Dallas-based market research firm StoreBoard, a subsidiary of the Computer Intelligence Company of La Jolla, Calif. Apple's endorsement of the Outbound system may be a stop-gap measure to bolster the overall Macintosh-compatible portable market until Apple can develop a decent laptop of its own, she said.</p>
        <p>There is some question whether the Outbound machine is really a Mac clone, and even if it is really a computer. Outbound describes the 9.2-pound device, which costs $2,999 to $3,999 depending on options, as an extension to the Macintosh Plus and SE. To use the Outbound, the owner must first have the Mac.</p>
        <p>A dealer must install a special card in the Mac, connect it to the Outbound, and then ''lobotomize'' the Mac by transferring its ROM chip to the Outbound. After that, the user can attach and detach the units at will. When they are attached to one another on a desktop, the Mac and the Outbound function as one machine, using the Outbound's faster 16-megahertz microprocessor instead of the Mac's slower 7.83 MHz one.</p>
        <p>The combined units also take advantage of the Outbound's memory and disk storage (a 1.44 megabyte floppy diskette ''superdrive'' or an optional 40-megabyte hard disk) in addition to what the Mac already has.</p>
        <p>Then, when the user wants to go on the road, the Outbound system can be disconnected from the Mac, becoming a fully functional, battery-powered portable. The battery life is twp to three hours. The illuminated screen is 640 by 400 pixels, or picture elements, as against 512 by 342 on the Mac Plus or SE.</p>
        <p>The Outbound keyboard, typically not used when the two systems are docked on the desktop, goes with the portable on the road. It sends signals to the computer not by cable, but by infrared signals. Also, the keyboard uses an intriguing pointing device called the Isopoint instead of a mouse, although a conventional mouse can be attached as an option.</p>
        <p>The Isopoint is a pencil-like object just below the space bar. Rolling it up and down moves the cursor up and down; sliding it left and right moves the cursor left and right, and pressing it works like the button on a mouse.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL COMPUTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
