<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Daneyko's Night, Devils Fail to Sustain the Emotion</title>
    <meta content="10DEVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/10/sports/hockey/10DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1549601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Daneyko, Ken</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DE1730F933A25752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Daneyko's Night, Devils Fail to Sustain the Emotion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Daneykos Night, Devils Fail to Sustain the Emotion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Jan. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tampa Bay Lightning defeats New Jersey Devils, 4-1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils scored on their first shot, and Ken Daneyko Night was off to a flying start.</p>
        <p>Then the electricity on a special night left Continental Arena, literally, and the Tampa Bay Lightning scored three third-period goals to beat the stumbling Devils, 4-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils are 2-4-2-1 in their last nine games, and Fridays game honoring Ken Daneyko, their defenseman who retired last summer, served as another downer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils scored on their first shot, and Ken Daneyko Night was off to a flying start.</p>
        <p>Then the electricity on a special night left Continental Arena, literally, and the Tampa Bay Lightning scored three third-period goals to beat the stumbling Devils, 4-1.</p>
        <p>The pregame ceremony honoring Daneyko, the Devils' longtime defenseman who retired last summer, had been hampered by a malfunctioning microphone.</p>
        <p>Then the start of the second period was delayed for 15 minutes. A transformer in nearby Totowa, N.J., shorted out, causing a power surge at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The capacity crowd of 19,040 could have lived with those glitches had the Devils (20-10-9-1) won the game.</p>
        <p>They were booed after Martin Brodeur allowed two goals in a nine-second span in the third period.</p>
        <p>''From power outages to bad microphones, it was one of those nights,'' Devils Coach Pat Burns said.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay (18-15-6-1) had taken a 2-1 lead on Cory Stillman's goal 1 minute 22 seconds into the third period off a nice pass from center Brad Richards.</p>
        <p>The Devils, playing without defenseman Scott Stevens, who was out with flulike symptoms, then gave up goals to Dave Andreychuk at 6:38 and Fredrik Modin at 6:47.</p>
        <p>''I think what I'm mad about is that we kind of gave up,'' Patrik Elias said.</p>
        <p>The Devils have lost two games in a row for the first time since Oct. 22, their fifth game of the season. They are 2-4-2-1 since a 5-2 victory Dec. 19 over Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''We'll get out of it eventually,'' Brodeur said. ''You just don't want it dragging around too long.''</p>
        <p>Daneyko was honored in a brief ceremony before the opening face-off. He promised he would keep his remarks short, and he did.</p>
        <p>He thanked his family, his coaches, his teammates and the fans. The capacity crowd booed when it became apparent that his No. 3 sweater would not be retired.</p>
        <p>He received a painting from the team and a wide-screen television from his teammates, and he handled a malfunctioning microphone in stride.</p>
        <p>''I never in my wildest dreams thought I would play 20 years, let alone with one team,'' Daneyko said in a news conference before the ceremony.</p>
        <p>The red carpet that had been rolled out for Daneyko's ceremony had barely been rolled back up when Devils center Scott Gomez scored on the first shot of the game.</p>
        <p>It sailed over the left shoulder of Tampa Bay goaltender John Grahame at 1:28 for Gomez's fifth goal. Gomez had not scored in the previous seven games.</p>
        <p>The Devils had two breakaways before the game was six minutes old. But Elias flubbed his shot, and Brian Gionta missed his. Tampa Bay then rustled up some energy.</p>
        <p>''They're a team that gets in your face real quick,'' Burns said.</p>
        <p>Devils defenseman Brian Rafalski broke his stick on a shot, and Rafalski smothered a shot by the Lightning right wing Martin St. Louis at the Devils' end.</p>
        <p>But St. Louis, who will be a starter in the N.H.L. All-Star Game, poked the puck free and beat Brodeur with one minute left in the first period. The Devils went downhill from there.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of the night, you don't want to lose,'' Rafalski said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
