<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford or Honda, New or Used, He Wants to Sell It</title>
    <meta content="16MYER$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="965428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Used Cars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Autonation Usa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Rent-A-Car</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alamo Rent-A-Car Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huizenga, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DB113DF935A25753C1A961958260" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford or Honda, New or Used, He Wants to Sell It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN R. MYERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R</byline>
      <dateline>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wayne Huizenga is founder of Autonation chain of used-car marts, where salesmen are 'guides' and consumers are considered 'guests'; in just one year of operation, he has built 15 Autonation used-car marts from scratch with lots size of six Manhattan blocks, while buying 200 new car dealerships and National and Alamo rental agencies; he wants to link together every aspect of auto business in ways that bring untold benefits to consumers and untold profits to him; photos (Special Section, Cars)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF every car salesman, especially every used-car salesman, were honest, sensitive, patient, fair, tactful and caring, then Wayne Huizenga's whole plan to revolutionize the $700 billion business of buying cars wouldn't stand a chance.</p>
        <p>But as a founder of the Autonation chain of used-car marts and the nation's largest seller of new cars as well, Mr. Huizenga (pronounced HI-zing-uh) is betting that the chance to buy a car with no haggling will have limitless appeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF every car salesman, especially every used-car salesman, were honest, sensitive, patient, fair, tactful and caring, then Wayne Huizenga's whole plan to revolutionize the $700 billion business of buying cars wouldn't stand a chance.</p>
        <p>But as a founder of the Autonation chain of used-car marts and the nation's largest seller of new cars as well, Mr. Huizenga (pronounced HI-zing-uh) is betting that the chance to buy a car with no haggling will have limitless appeal.</p>
        <p>Fixing the car sales business could prove far more complicated than building WMX, the nation's largest trash hauler, and Blockbuster, the largest video-store chain, which is how Mr. Huizenga earned most of his billion-dollar-plus fortune.</p>
        <p>While executives at his Republic Industries holding company admit they are still learning how to steer their new business,  Mr. Huizenga has roared off at 90 miles an hour. In just one year of operation, he has built 15 Autonation used-car marts from scratch with lots the size of six Manhattan blocks, while buying 200 new car dealerships and the National and Alamo rental agencies.</p>
        <p>His vision: beyond the factory gates, link together every aspect of the auto business, new or used -- selling, buying, leasing, financing, renting, repairing -- in ways that bring untold benefits to consumers and untold profits to him.</p>
        <p>Many in Detroit cheer the prospect of more efficient distribution and improved service. But some auto makers, long used to telling dealers what cars to sell and on what terms, fear the rise of the first dealer powerful enough to challenge them.</p>
        <p>By the end of 1999, Mr. Huizenga plans to have a presence in the nation's 50 largest markets with 90 Autonations, each surrounded by clusters of new-car dealers, which will operate under their own names.  His full-speed approach may be a product of character, but it's also an effort to beat out  other new, publicly traded companies bent on expansion.</p>
        <p>''We want to have the best Ford dealer and the best Chevy dealer and the best Toyota dealer in every market,'' he said during a recent interview at a penthouse office suite here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huizenga says that through volume and corporate ownership, he can trim $1,000 -- in advertising, inventory and interest charges, reconditioning costs and the like -- off the cost of the average used car.</p>
        <p>He has hired a manager from the Saturn plant in Spring Hill, Tenn., to bring assembly-line techniques to the refurbishing of used cars. At a reconditioning center near here, cars are routed to about half a dozen different lines, depending on how much body work they require, with other lines for mechanical repairs. Fixing up cars so they don't need return trips to reconditioning centers is among the lessons his company is still learning, Mr. Huizenga said.</p>
        <p>At age 59, H. Wayne Huizenga, who founded his empire with a single garbage truck, remains burly and determined.</p>
        <p>In South Florida, he already possesses the visibility Ted Turner has in Atlanta or Donald J. Trump has in New York, largely because he owns three professional sports teams here: the Florida Marlins, the Florida Panthers and the Miami Dolphins.</p>
        <p>To most challenges, he has blunt and ready answers. An eventual recession? ''That's when the strong get stronger,'' he said, his narrow, blue eyes narrowing further. ''There would be a lot of dealers that want to sell.''</p>
        <p>Efforts by Toyota and now Honda to curb his purchases of their dealers? ''The bigger, more sophisticated manufacturers recognize that this is an advantage to them,'' he said, describing how closer ties to dealers like him can help auto makers know which models to produce.</p>
        <p>But changing car dealer culture will take more than money. For one, Mr. Huizenga's company will have to teach salespeople, called ''sales guides,'' a new language.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to call it a 'lot' and a 'deal,' '' said Lynn Fernandez, a manager at the first Autonation, near Fort Lauderdale.  ''It's an 'outdoor display area' and a 'transaction.' You're not an 'up,' as in 'next up,' you're a 'guest.' ''</p>
        <p>The showroom includes a snack bar and a shop with auto supplies and Autonation shirts and caps. Shoppers can leave their children in a monitored playroom, then scan the inventory on touch-screen computers. They can print out a page of data, including a picture and location for each car, then roam the outdoor display area by themselves or with a sales guide in a golf cart.</p>
        <p>Greg Meurrens and Yolanda Ramos were peeking inside a late-model Toyota Tacoma and other light trucks when a salesman -- make that a sales guide -- rolled by on a cart. ''Need some help?'' he asked. When they shook their heads, he rolled on.</p>
        <p>At other dealerships, Mr. Muerrens said, ''they're on top of you.'' He bent his knees and clawed the air to imitate a wild, hungry animal. ''Here they ask. You can think before you say anything.''</p>
        <p>But the more he thought, the less certain he became about buying: ''$26,490?'' he asked, looking at the sticker in the Tacoma's window. ''That's a lot of money.''</p>
        <p>''For the year and model, you could probably get it cheaper,'' Ms. Ramos said. ''That's why I would want to try to bargain.''</p>
        <p>OTHERS who were beginning their hunt for a car at Autonation were far from sure it would end there. Frank and Helen Bonfiglio printed out sheet after sheet to find reasonably priced midsized cars for a daughter in New Paltz, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''This is a good place to start,'' Ms. Bonfiglio said. ''You can get a sense of what the inventory is, what prices would be.'' But the Bonfiglios said they might send their printouts to their daughter, and let her shop in her own town.</p>
        <p>In taking the used-car business corporate,  Mr. Huizenga's leading rival accuses him of imitating.</p>
        <p>''They've been doing this for about nine months, and we've been doing it for six years,'' said W. Austin Ligon, the president of Circuit City's Carmax used-car chain.</p>
        <p>Carmax offers services comparable to Autonation's, but with lower prices, Mr. Ligon said, citing Wall Street studies to support him. Since the first Carmax opened in 1993, the chain has doubled in size annually, to 17 by the end of this year, as fast as  staff members can be trained, Mr. Ligon added.</p>
        <p>Instead of becoming the Wal-Mart of the car market, Mr. Ligon predicted that Mr. Huizenga would become the Robert Campeau, whose flamboyant, and hellbent, purchases of the nation's major retailers a decade ago ended up in bankruptcy courts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huizenga points out that his company's finances remain strong and disagrees  that Carmax is beating him on price, especially considering Autonation's refurbishing and other services. ''When we put $400, $500 or $600 into a car, it's a different car,'' he said. ''You could charge a little extra, if you could explain it to the consumer.'' He says  his plans for linking the industry's elements are far broader than Carmax's. As an example, he said trade-ins at his new-car dealerships would give him a better supply of used cars than Carmax could find.</p>
        <p>If Autonation aims to reinvent used-car sales, Mr. Huizenga's new-car dealers are more traditional. The Maroone (pronounced ma-ROON-ee) Auto Plaza that he bought, along with Michael Maroone's other South Florida dealerships for $216.7 million in February, looks like a couple of airport terminals linked by a long, four-level garage. Maroone ranks first in the nation in sales of Isuzus, and at least third in Dodges, fourth in General Motors over all and fifth in  Chevrolets, with several other divisions selling a variety of vehicles, even garbage trucks.</p>
        <p>Sales people at the dealership attribute their success to long-term relationships. They frequently make as many as 30 calls a day to achieve the 8 to 10 required contacts from computer-generated lists of past customers who might be ready for new cars, current customers who came to shop but didn't buy or recent customers who might appreciate the follow-up.</p>
        <p>MR. Huizenga wants Maroone and his other new-car dealers to introduce no-haggle pricing. Otherwise, he regards the Maroone operations as so exemplary that he has chosen Mr. Maroone to run his company's new- and used-car sales.</p>
        <p>Though they are far from unanimous, industry experts said Mr. Huizenga could at least provide a jolt to an industry much in need of one. ''It will be the first time someone has put all the pieces of the business together,'' said Martin L. Anderson, who teaches management at Babson College in Wellesley, Mass. ''He will be able to cut a lot of costs out of the system and offer a lot more choice.''</p>
        <p>These, Mr. Huizenga affirmed, are his long-term goals. His short-term advice is embodied in the way he says goodbye. His parting words are ''Buy a car.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
