<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$89 Million Provides Instant Gratification</title>
    <meta content="16NLCS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="965569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="LEAGUE CHAMPIONSHIP SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Marlins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7D6153FF935A25753C1A961958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$89 Million Provides Instant Gratification</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Oct. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles National League champion Florida Marlins as team prepares to play Cleveland Indians in World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a giddy entourage surrounding him, H. Wayne Huizenga, owner of the Florida Marlins, tumbled out of the visitors' dugout at Turner Field almost an hour after the Marlins had eliminated the Atlanta Braves on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The stands were empty, the lights dimmed; there was nobody around. Every kid's dream. Huizenga and his friends, wearing Champagne-soaked T-shirts over their shirts, ties and sweaters, did what every kid would have done. They took a victory lap around the bases, in joyously loud disorder, the fastest among them stumbling across home plate, the slowest making the trek with a cane, Huizenga in the middle of the pack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a giddy entourage surrounding him, H. Wayne Huizenga, owner of the Florida Marlins, tumbled out of the visitors' dugout at Turner Field almost an hour after the Marlins had eliminated the Atlanta Braves on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The stands were empty, the lights dimmed; there was nobody around. Every kid's dream. Huizenga and his friends, wearing Champagne-soaked T-shirts over their shirts, ties and sweaters, did what every kid would have done. They took a victory lap around the bases, in joyously loud disorder, the fastest among them stumbling across home plate, the slowest making the trek with a cane, Huizenga in the middle of the pack.</p>
        <p>The Marlins' route to the National League title, from their birth as an expansion team in 1993, was as circuitous as the path of some of those circling the bases. They will play host to Cleveland in Game 1 of the World Series on Saturday, sending to the mound the rookie Livan Hernandez, who struck out 15 Braves in winning the crucial fifth game on Sunday. They have come this far in only their fifth year of existence, the fastest ascent of any expansion team, which suggests a straight line from top to bottom.</p>
        <p>But the Marlins, in fact, have had a strange five-year history, seemingly adopting and then discarding organizational strategies as quickly as their fretful manager, Jim Leyland, changes pitchers in the late innings.</p>
        <p>Entering the National League the same season as the Colorado Rockies, the Marlins were once considered the more conservative of the two franchises. While the Rockies immediately filled their roster with older, more established players, Florida's strategy for the 1992 expansion draft was to pluck young prospects. They wanted to stockpile their own farm system, develop players, establish a base of talent they thought would eventually propel them to the top of the National League East standing. The Marlins also concentrated on acquiring Latin American players to appeal to the heavily Spanish-speaking population around Miami.</p>
        <p>However, the Marlins' selections in the expansion draft provided little long-term dividend. Jeff Conine, selected from the Kansas City Royals, is the only current member of the Marlins acquired in that draft.</p>
        <p>The Marlins won 64 games in their first season and drew more than three million fans. But while the Rockies quickly established themselves as an exciting offensive team that hit a lot of home runs, the Marlins were a work in progress. Interest in them in South Florida waned somewhat in 1994, when the Marlins went 51-64 before the labor wars between owners and players wiped out the rest of that season.</p>
        <p>Huizenga was considered among the strongest hawks during the owners' fight with the Players' Association. As it turned out, the struggle seemed to hurt the Marlins more than most teams. Dave Dombrowski, the club's general manager, once said, ''Baseball stopped being the happening thing to do'' in South Florida.</p>
        <p>Colorado continued to fill its ball park and qualified for the playoffs in 1995; the Marlins, on the other hand, drew only 1.7 million in 1995, and the team continued to play sub-.500 baseball. The same trend continued in 1996, with the Marlins' season-ticket base plummeting to 12,000, a nearly 50 percent drop from Florida's first year.</p>
        <p>Fed up with the slow decline, Huizenga became determined to alter the team's direction after the 1996 season. The Marlins tried and failed to sign Albert Belle, offering the free-agent outfielder $10 million per season. But they did land a handful of other stars, signing Bobby Bonilla to a four-year, $23.3 million deal, pitcher Alex Fernandez to a five-year, $35 million contract and Moises Alou to a five-year, $25 million deal; in all, the Marlins spent $89 million on free agents. In addition, they gave Leyland a $7.5 million contract to manage, and gave Gary Sheffield a $60 million extension. If it worked for George Steinbrenner and the Yankees, Huizenga's logic seemed to be, then it would work for the Florida Marlins. ''We feel with this team,'' Leyland said at the time, ''we have a chance.''</p>
        <p>But the strategy did not work, at first. Rather than abandoning the beaches and flocking to Pro Player Stadium, South Floridians' interest in the Marlins was lukewarm in the first months of the 1997 season. The team did not perform to expectations, either -- Sheffield fell into a slump from which he never really emerged, and the Marlins struggled to fight off the pesky Mets.</p>
        <p>His patience at an end, Huizenga announced in June that he was selling the team. ''We have lost money every year,'' he said at the time. ''The simple answer is, we are not willing to sustain the losses.'' Leyland, suddenly thrust into the same sort of unstable situation he left behind in Pittsburgh, decided he would move his family back north. The Marlins, it seemed, were unraveling, and as with many other baseball franchises, there were rumors the team would be relocated.</p>
        <p>The Marlins began playing better, however. They clinched a wild-card playoff berth, finishing second to the Braves in the N.L. East, and soon Huizenga was running around the bases at Turner Field with his friends. Interest in the Marlins has never been higher, their season-ticket base is sure to increase. And what of the sale? ''We'll have to think that thing through later,'' Huizenga said in the Marlins' clubhouse, through streams of Champagne. Like the victory lap, yet another 90-degree turn for the Marlins' franchise.</p>
        <p>LEAGUE CHAMPIONSHIP SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
