<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="07FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2D9153EF934A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Warning of Chaos in Russia Unless Political Fights End  Viktor S. Chernomyrdin warned on national television that Russia has entered a fiscal nosedive and that further political squabbling could lead to social chaos, on the night before Russia's Parliament was to vote again on whether to confirm him as the country's Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Floods Ravage Bangladesh  More than 20 million homes in Bangladesh have been swamped by monsoon season flooding that has lasted almost two months, twice as long as other recorded floods. The waters have inundated more than half of the country, killed more than 520 people, shut down roads, damaged more than 4,000 schools and wiped out a big portion of the rice crop.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Warning of Chaos in Russia Unless Political Fights End  Viktor S. Chernomyrdin warned on national television that Russia has entered a fiscal nosedive and that further political squabbling could lead to social chaos, on the night before Russia's Parliament was to vote again on whether to confirm him as the country's Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Floods Ravage Bangladesh  More than 20 million homes in Bangladesh have been swamped by monsoon season flooding that has lasted almost two months, twice as long as other recorded floods. The waters have inundated more than half of the country, killed more than 520 people, shut down roads, damaged more than 4,000 schools and wiped out a big portion of the rice crop.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Embassy Bombing Arrests  Investigators have arrested two more suspects in the bombing of the United States Embassy in Tanzania and have made significant progress in determining how the bomb was made and taken to the embassy, Federal Bureau of Investigation and local police officials say. The arrests came in the same week that agents investigating the simultaneous attack on the American Embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, began focusing on a Muslim businessman from the Comoros Islands.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Eternal Leader in North Korea  North Korea announced that it had revised its Constitution to make its former ''Great Leader,'' Kim Il Sung, the country's ''eternal President.'' President Kim's son Kim Jong Il, the country's longtime ''Dear Leader,'' will in effect be head of state, as chairman of the National Defense Commission. The action leaves North Korea without a living President.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Rice Cost Threatens Indonesia  Experts are warning that the dramatic increase in the price of rice in Indonesia is the biggest threat to stability in the country, as it struggles to regain its political and economic footing. Food riots have already erupted in parts of eastern Java and could spread to major cities like Jakarta.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>I.R.A. Leader on Disarming  Gerry Adams, the leader of the political wing of the Irish Republican Army, said that he could not guarantee that the I.R.A. would agree to disarm during talks in the new Northern Ireland Assembly. But last week, Mr. Adams, the president of Sinn Fein, had emphasized that sectarian warfare was a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Nonaligned Countries Meet  Delegates from 113 countries held a summit meeting last week in the South African coastal city of Durban. The chief issues the delegates were said to have discussed were not those topping the Clinton-Yeltsin agenda in Moscow; in fact, the Congo war eclipsed planned talks. It was the 12th meeting of the nonaligned movement, founded as a forum for nations that are neither pro-American nor pro-Soviet.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-12</p>
        <p>Republicans Optimistic About Midterm Elections  As they take to the trail this Labor Day for the traditional opening of the fall campaigns, Republican and Democratic candidates say the Lewinsky matter, a jittery stock market and tumult abroad have thrust them into the most unsettled, and unpredictable, election season in years. The uncertainty has already altered the calculations of Republicans, who say they have the most to gain, particularly from President Clinton's difficulties. By contrast, Democrats find themselves on the defensive.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Surge in Union Strikes  The recent strikes at Northwest Airlines, General Motors, Bell Atlantic and U S West represent the biggest surge in major walkouts in years and, industrial relations experts say, point to a new aggressiveness on the part of the nation's labor unions. Even though union membership is slipping and the economy is slowing, the experts say, unions have grown bolder because of the tight labor market, more combative union leadership and the teamsters' gains in last year's U.P.S. strike.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Federal mediator sent negotiators for Northwest Airlines and its striking pilots home, asking them to redouble efforts to end the nine-day strike, which has grounded Northwest's nearly 1,700 daily flights.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Panel Seeks Broad Powers  The Judiciary Committee, headed by Representative Henry J. Hyde, Republican of Illinois, is seeking sweeping powers never granted to a House panel, as it prepares to accept the report from the Whitewater independent counsel, Kenneth W. Starr. The committee will review President Clinton's conduct in the Lewinsky matter and House Democratic and Republican leaders will try to resolve the debate over exempting the committee from many House rules.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>President Clinton's personal behavior remains Topic A on Capitol Hill since he admitted to having had an inappropriate relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky, a former White House intern, and lying about it.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Hiring Bonuses for Teachers  Long accustomed to being supplicants within the labor force, candidates for public-school teaching jobs -- especially in special education, math and science -- are being put in the decidedly unfamiliar position of being wooed with financial sweeteners. In Baltimore this summer, prospective special education teachers were in such demand that those with just a year's experience were offered the starting salaries of four-year veterans. In Massachusetts, nearly 200 of the promising rookie teachers who apply to work in the commonwealth's schools next year will receive $20,000 signing bonuses.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>High Price of Gas in Texas  A citizens movement to protest the high price of gasoline has become the hottest political issue in El Paso, drawing in state officials and becoming entangled with a contentious proposal to open a pipeline from the Gulf Coast -- a kind of cavalry charging to the rescue.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Swissair Flight Recorder Is Found in Nova Scotia  Divers found one of the two flight data recorders from Swissair Flight 111 on a rocky stretch of sea bottom littered with debris and three major pieces of wreckage of the MD-11. The discovery in Peggy's Cove, Nova Scotia, raised hopes that investigators would soon know why the plane crashed offshore last week, killing everyone aboard, after a pilot reported smoke in the cockpit. No additional remains of the 229 victims were identified, nor were large numbers of victims found. But officials were clearly relieved that a Navy diving tender, the Sechelt, had found one of the plane's two ''black boxes.'' The box was brought ashore, where technicians immersed it in fresh water and sealed it for immediate shipment to a Transportation Safety Board laboratory in Ottawa. Also, the medical examiner said that the victims' remains were simply in poor condition and DNA analysis could not be performed on all of the remains, so some would be frozen until lawyers and ethicists could decide what to do.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Harlem Rally Under Dispute  Khallid Abdul Muhammad, the chief organizer of a weekend youth rally in Harlem, was the focus of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's stepped-up defense of police officers who stormed the stage at a the rally on Saturday. The Mayor gave conflicting explanations for the police action. First he said the rally's organizers had flouted a court-ordered deadline for ending the rally. Later he said the police moved in when Mr. Muhammad began inveighing against them. Organizers and community leaders in Harlem accused the city of using excessive force and threatened to sue.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Focus on Upstate Voters  In the upper corridors of New York State, these final days before the Sept. 15 primary are treating Democratic voters to the spectacle of three quintessential New York City politicians striving for votes by grasping for ties that stretch beyond the five boroughs and their suburbs. They face a beguiling challenge: how to connect to the voters of western, central and northern New York, who are generally skeptical and often feel as shunted to the margins politically as they are geographically.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Shift Seen in Yankees' Goal  Hideki Irabu was a Cy Young award candidate in May, a possible All-Star in June. Now he is in jeopardy of being dropped from the Yankees' rotation and, eventually, from their playoff roster. He gave up six runs to the Chicago White Sox and the Yankees lost 6-5. They have lost 10 of their last 18 games; they must win 17 of their last 22 to pass the mark of 116, set by the 1906 Chicago Cubs. But their focus seems to have shifted to the playoffs.</p>
        <p>D6</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Microsoft Suit Strategies  With the filing of witness lists on Friday night, the Government and the Microsoft Corporation offered the first glimpse of their courtroom strategies in the historic antitrust trial scheduled this month. The Government will portray Microsoft as an information-age monopolist and Microsoft plans a defense with one conspicuous absence -- William H. Gates, the company's chairman.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Start-Ups Suffer Market Jitters  If the market falls further and looks as if it will not bounce back, investments by venture capitalists and public stock investors in small technology companies will slow, bankers and investors say. But for now, there is still a lot of money poised to be invested in promising new start-up companies involved in information technology and the Internet.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A14-15  Akira Kurosawa  One of the handful of truly important directors that the cinema has produced, was 88. He personified Japanese movies -- his work includes ''Seven Samurai'' and ''Rashomon'' -- to most of the world.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Frances Hamerstrom  The author, conservationist and wildlife biologist, who discovered a passion for observing nature as a young girl in Boston and pursued that passion throughout her life, was 90.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Kirk O'Donnell  The lawyer and lobbyist for a leading Washington law firm and the former chief aide to former Speaker Thomas P. O'Neill Jr., was 52.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17  Editorials: Helping Kosovo's displaced; more jobs, less security; Brent Staples on remedial education at CUNY.  Columns: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
