<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking a Higher Authority</title>
    <meta content="09BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/09/books/09BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1390687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Publishers Weekly</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D81230F93AA35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking a Higher Authority</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeking a Higher Authority, Readers Flock to Spiritual Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold Making Books column on increase in number of religious books being published; religious book publishers increased their presence at recent booksellers' convention in New York and Publishers Weekly reports that religious titles, for first time, topped its annual lists of best-selling fiction and nonfiction in 2001; some recent titles noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most assertive aspect of book publishing these days seems to be the selling of the incorporeal: connectedness to God, wellness, perfection of the spirit. This wave has been building for a while now, but two recent events showed that it has become a tsunami.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, among the most visible exhibitors at the booksellers convention in New York was Tyndale House Publishers, the Christian publishing house. Some mainstream publishers, including Random House Inc., scaled down from past conventions, and Penguin Putnam didn't even show, but many who attended were struck by how publishers of religious books had clearly increased their presence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most assertive aspect of book publishing these days seems to be the selling of the incorporeal: connectedness to God, wellness, perfection of the spirit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most assertive aspect of book publishing these days seems to be the selling of the incorporeal: connectedness to God, wellness, perfection of the spirit. This wave has been building for a while now, but two recent events showed that it has become a tsunami.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, among the most visible exhibitors at the booksellers convention in New York was Tyndale House Publishers, the Christian publishing house. Some mainstream publishers, including Random House Inc., scaled down from past conventions, and Penguin Putnam didn't even show, but many who attended were struck by how publishers of religious books had clearly increased their presence.</p>
        <p>And last month Publishers Weekly, the industry's trade journal, reported that religious titles were at the top of its annual lists of both best-selling fiction and nonfiction for 2001, the first time ever. The numbers were huge. ''The Prayer of Jabez'' (Multnomah Publishers) by Bruce Wilkinson, based on an obscure prayer by an Old Testament figure, sold some eight million copies. (Now his wife, Darlene Wilkinson, is out with ''The Prayer of Jabez for Women.'')</p>
        <p>''Desecration'' (Tyndale), the ninth in the ''Left Behind'' series of apocalyptic novels by Tim LeHaye and Jerry B. Jenkins, sold nearly three million copies, more than John Grisham's Christmas book. (Tyndale had its own sort of apocalypse when Mr. LeHaye switched congregations and signed a four-book deal with the Bantam Dell Publishing Group for a different series, reportedly for $45 million.)</p>
        <p>Clearly something is up in the loosely defined inspirational genres. The books range from the serious Christian, Jewish and Buddhist (and lately some Muslim) works through New Age buckle-down about self-help to stuff that would embarrass P. T. Barnum. For many readers apparently, these books bring a kind of religion to those who don't want a traditional one. Whatever, secular publishers are into it heavily.</p>
        <p>So what's out there? A small sampling: ''What Would Buddha Do at Work?'' (Ulysses Press/Barrett-Koehler) by Franz Metcalf and B. J. Gallagher Hateley answers questions like what the great teacher would do if he were bored in the office. Simon &amp; Schuster has Phillip C. McGraw's best-selling ''Self Matters.'' Putnam has Kent M. Keith's ''Anyway: The Paradoxical Commandments,'' one of which cautions that even though ''people are illogical, unreasonable, and self-centered, love them anyway.''</p>
        <p>There's also the inspirational book ''The Right Words at the Right Time'' by Marlo Thomas and Friends (Atria Books), the friends being famous people who each tell how the right words, etc., brought about a crucial turning point in their lives. Then there's more studious work, like ''A New Religious America: How a 'Christian Country' Has Become the World's Most Religiously Diverse Nation'' (Harper San Francisco), by Diana L. Eck, a professor of comparative religion at Harvard.</p>
        <p>Why this new burst of popularity? The quick and glib answer is 9/11. When the world is turned upside down by uncontrollable violence, people tend to look inward, at themselves, not at the usual. Altie Karper, editorial director of Schocken Books, Knopf's imprint for Jewish works, said that after great disasters, ''you can't look to logic to find answers to things that are illogical.''</p>
        <p>But 9/11 only accelerated, at least for secular publishers, what had clearly started to emerge before. Michelle Rapkin, who next month becomes director of Doubleday's religious publishing, said that the desire for these books ''was there and started snowballing in 1999 before the millennium.'' She added: ''People really started to think about what was going to happen. Many literally thought about the end of world. The 'Left Behind' series had been a huge success, and that built a platform for these kinds of books to cross over into the regular market after they'd been selling in Christian market.''</p>
        <p>Then came 9/11, which, Ms. Rapkin said, ''pushed everyone to a place where they started feeling maybe it was time to think of things more important than career and retirement funds.'' Where everyone went, publishers naturally followed, and now there are few major publishing houses without spiritual or religious imprints. Paul Foster, publisher of John Wiley &amp; Sons' imprint Jossey-Bass, said, ''There seems to be a lot of personal soul searching, a trend that started about 10 years ago.'' To help in the search, he now plans to publish 40 new titles a year, he said.</p>
        <p>Some books within these categories are sublime and some not so. Mitch Horowitz, senior editor at Tarcher/Putnam, said: ''Books are neutral. You use them like credit cards for a good purpose or to run up bills. Their value depends on what the reader brings to them. People buy these books for what they can do for them personally, not for the rest of the world.''</p>
        <p>If that's the case, it doesn't matter much whether the reading is sublime or nonsense. ''Eat more to weigh less'' sounds absurd, for instance. Tarcher plans to publish about 40 new titles a year, and ''if they are done intelligently and approached intelligently, then these books on philosophy and psychology and religion and self-help can be helpful,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There are special book clubs for these genres. One Spirit Book Club, a division of the Book-of-the-Month Club, started in 1995 with 20,000 members and now has more than 400,000. Patricia Gift, its editor in chief, said this about its growth: ''People have more time to think about their lives, and many people are no longer attached to traditional religion. A huge number of the disaffected turn to Buddhism and some to shamanism, and into self-help and improvement.''</p>
        <p>It would seem that religious books and their interconnection with wellness and self-help will continue to be a growth product. Wendy Carlton, the Putnam editor of its ''Conversations With God'' books, said the writer, Neale Donald Walsch, put it this way, ''I'm a regular guy who made lots of mistakes, and God spoke to me and can speak to you, but you have to listen.'' She added, ''And that was a broader appeal to lots of people than even traditional religion.''</p>
        <p>What's happening apparently is that many of these books, no matter how airy they seem, are anchoring people to a new sort of spirituality without making them face the intellectual challenge of the liturgical. If the book is replacing the church for many, what's coming next from publishing? Something on the order of Chesterton's ''St. Francis of Assisi'' or Thomas Merton's ''Seven Storey Mountain''? Not likely. Probably some form of God for dummies.</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
