<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hornets Face Home-Court Disadvantage</title>
    <meta content="09HORN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/09/sports/basketball/09HORN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1390808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charlotte Coliseum</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Charlotte (Nc)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Charlotte Hornets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Orleans Hornets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Charlotte</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Charlotte Hornets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD61330F93AA35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hornets Face Home-Court Disadvantage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hornets Face Home-Court Disadvantage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C., May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charlotte Hornets will face New Jersey Nets in Game 3 of Eastern Conference semifinals at home in Charlotte Coliseum, where fan attendance is far below league average as Hornets prepare to move to New Orleans; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having been a part of the National Basketball Association for nearly 40 years, Paul Silas knows that players garner energy, intensity and adrenaline from raucous home crowds. So when asked today what type of fan turnout he expected for Game 3 of the Charlotte Hornets' Eastern Conference semifinal series against the Nets, Silas responded with hope rather than reason.</p>
        <p>''Probably about 23,000 strong,'' Silas, the Hornets' coach, said with a grin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hornets' impending move to New Orleans has resulted in essentially a boycott of the team's home games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having been a part of the National Basketball Association for nearly 40 years, Paul Silas knows that players garner energy, intensity and adrenaline from raucous home crowds. So when asked today what type of fan turnout he expected for Game 3 of the Charlotte Hornets' Eastern Conference semifinal series against the Nets, Silas responded with hope rather than reason.</p>
        <p>''Probably about 23,000 strong,'' Silas, the Hornets' coach, said with a grin.</p>
        <p>Laughs broke out all around. For Silas will be delighted if half that number shows up at the Charlotte Coliseum on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The Hornets led the league in home attendance in eight of their first nine seasons, including every season from 1990-91 to 1996-97.</p>
        <p>''Every night it was like Michael Jordan was playing,'' said 35-year-old Craig Caudle, a lifelong Charlotte resident who worked as an usher at the Coliseum from 1990 to 1993.</p>
        <p>But the club's impending move to New Orleans, which is expected to be ratified by the league's Board of Governors on Friday, has turned the once-bustling arena into a relative ghost town on game nights -- and left the Hornets without much of a home-court advantage.</p>
        <p>With tarp covering the top four or five rows of the arena, the Hornets averaged a league-worst 11,286 fans this season. Many observers said the nightly count was inflated.</p>
        <p>The excitement of playoff basketball -- and, in the Hornets' case, a legitimate chance to advance to the N.B.A. finals -- has done nothing to change what is essentially a fan boycott.</p>
        <p>In Game 1 of their first-round series with the Orlando Magic, with 19,925 seats available, the Hornets drew 9,505 fans. Game 2 attracted 10,323 spectators. Things were so bad that up-to-date playoff merchandise was not even being sold in the arena.</p>
        <p>Sporty Jeralds, the coliseum manager, said he expected roughly the same turnout for Thursday's game. A team spokesman said that new merchandise would be available.</p>
        <p>Having a successful team in a basketball-crazed region drawing high school crowds -- on national television, no less -- has to be embarrassing for the N.B.A. But even the league's officials understand the fans' actions.</p>
        <p>''I can understand that in that circumstance a fan might not want to come,'' said Russ Granik, the league's deputy commissioner. ''It's a little bit uncomfortable, but again, it's just a fact of life, and I think you've got to give the Hornets' players and Paul Silas a lot of credit to be able to perform at the level they have. I think people understand that the attendance isn't a reflection of N.B.A. basketball, just a reflection of the current situation.''</p>
        <p>Much of the city continues to pull for the Hornets, while at the same time refusing to support the club's two owners, George Shinn and Ray Wooldridge, who are held in mass disdain in Charlotte.</p>
        <p>Neither owner was available for comment.</p>
        <p>''We care for the players and the coach, and we're all rooting for the Hornets, but people don't want to give any money to owners who've basically abandoned our city,'' Mayor Pat McCrory said in a telephone interview. ''I personally am rooting for the Hornets. I'd love to have the Charlotte Hornets' name permanently written on the N.B.A trophy.''</p>
        <p>Earlier in the season, some players said they felt more at home on the road, and their record supported their claim.</p>
        <p>Just 21-20 in Charlotte, the Hornets built an impressive 23-18 record away from home. They are the only team in the league that won more road games than home games.</p>
        <p>That was one reason Charlotte's Game 1 and Game 2 losses at Continental Arena were so disheartening. Deep inside, the Hornets, who won both of their home games in the first round, know they play their best basketball in opposing buildings.</p>
        <p>While some teams would feel comfortable coming home, even down by 2-0, the Hornets have no such luxury.</p>
        <p>''It's been tough on everybody,'' Charlotte forward P. J. Brown said. ''I just think the fans, ourselves, the organization, everybody, wants this thing to end, because it's really been such a bad thorn in everybody's side this whole year.</p>
        <p>''But tomorrow we need to go out and play hard and well and not worry about who's in the stands.''</p>
        <p>The city's love affair with the Hornets began to sour early in the 1997-98 season, when fans started to grow weary of Shinn's refusal to pay top dollar to the Hornets' best players. His strategy of trading away stars instead of paying them had cost Charlotte such popular players as Alonzo Mourning and Larry Johnson, building blocks on a team that potentially was one of the league's best.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 25, 1997, the first ripple was felt when the Hornets' 10-season sellout streak of 364 games was broken. The off-the-court problems of Derrick Coleman, Anthony Mason and also Shinn, who won a civil suit filed by a woman who accused him of forcing her to have sex, further soured the fans' taste for the team. Then Glen Rice, and eventually Eddie Jones, were traded away.</p>
        <p>When Wooldridge bought a percentage of the club in 1999 and immediately began talking about the need for a new arena, the public became angrier. By the 2000-1 season, the average attendance, once as high as 24,042, was down to 15,010. Wooldridge and Shinn applied for relocation to Memphis last season. Soon thereafter city officials agreed to use public money to build a new arena.</p>
        <p>But McCrory put the decision to a referendum. He says the state Legislature forced him to, while the league says a referendum was unnecessary. In any event, when the referendum failed last June, the team was all but gone.</p>
        <p>''Most of the fans out in the community say they don't have anything against us,'' Brown said. ''They say they enjoy our play and how we work in the community. But they have some hard feelings against our ownership, so all I can do is kind of shrug my shoulders. All I can do is go out and be a professional and do the things I can do. That's all anybody can ask of anyone.''</p>
        <p>Now, all Silas is asking is for the fans to show up. After all, the N.B.A. is leaving the city for a long time, if not forever.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
