<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle-Tested Spartans Best Boston College</title>
    <meta content="07jimmyv" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/07/sports/ncaabasketball/07jimmyv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1723098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jimmy V Classic (College Basketball)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Michigan State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Joseph's College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Kansas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDE1031F934A35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle-Tested Spartans Best Boston College</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Battle-Tested Spartans Best Boston College</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michigan State University defeats Boston College, 77-70, in Jimmy V Classic; St Joseph's College defeats Kansas University, 70-67; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mystery seems to have been solved. Boston College's undefeated record was a mirage.</p>
        <p>Facing its first true test of the young season, No. 6 Boston College failed last night in the Jimmy V Classic at Madison Square Garden, losing to No. 14 Michigan State, 77-70.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing its first true test of the young season, No. 6 Boston College failed in the Jimmy V Classic at Madison Square Garden, losing to No. 14 Michigan State.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mystery seems to have been solved. Boston College's undefeated record was a mirage.</p>
        <p>Facing its first true test of the young season, No. 6 Boston College failed last night in the Jimmy V Classic at Madison Square Garden, losing to No. 14 Michigan State, 77-70.</p>
        <p>In the first game of last night's doubleheader, Kansas fell to 3-4 with a 70-67 loss to St Joseph's.</p>
        <p>The Eagles entered the game with a 6-0 record, but they had feasted on a soft schedule that included games against Dartmouth, Shawnee State, Buffalo, Drake and an Oklahoma State team that had lost to Northwestern State. For the most part, they had proved nothing.</p>
        <p>Michigan State, meanwhile, was taking the opposite approach. Last night's game was its third this season against a top-10 team. The Spartans lost to No. 8 Gonzaga in triple overtime and beat No. 9 Arizona in overtime. More battle-tested than the Eagles, they took over midway through the second half while showing everybody they are a lot tougher test than Shawnee State.</p>
        <p>''It's too early for this to be a huge step for us,'' Michigan State Coach Tom Izzo said. ''The good news is that we didn't play great, but we found a way to win.''</p>
        <p>The Spartans were clinging to a 2-point lead when a Craig Smith basket with 14 minutes 41 seconds left in the game made the score 41-39. But Michigan State responded with a 13-2 run to pad its lead. With a 3-pointer from Maurice Ager with 9:07 to go, Michigan State had a 57-44 lead and Boston College's hole was too deep.</p>
        <p>Boston College was done in by a sizzling second-half effort from Michigan State, which shot 77.3 percent while scoring 51 points.</p>
        <p>''That was due to a number of factors,'' Boston College Coach Al Skinner said. ''One is our lack of size. Foul trouble was another. There was great execution on their part. But there's no question that we didn't defend the way we needed to.''</p>
        <p>Ager led Michigan State (6-2) with 22 points and Paul Davis had 18. Jared Dudley was the leading scorer for Boston College with 23 points</p>
        <p>By all appearances, it is going to be a long and uncharacteristic season in Lawrence, Kan. The unranked Jayhawks, their roster decimated from a season ago, do not have anywhere near the talent and experience everyone has come to expect from one of college basketball's most successful programs.</p>
        <p>''I would say this has been a little bit more frustrating for the guys and for the staff because we haven't experienced much success,'' Coach Bill Self said. ''Last year, we got off to a great start and we won every game in the last four minutes. The difference is experience. Now, we're losing those same games.''</p>
        <p>Kansas has lost its four leading scorers (Wayne Simien, Keith Langford, J. R. Giddens, Aaron Miles) from last season's team that went 23-7 and beat St. Joseph's, 91-51. The Jayhawks start three sophomores, a freshman and a senior. Predictably, much of this season has been a struggle. Kansas's three victories have come against a trio of unheralded opponents -- Idaho State, Western Illinois and Division II Chaminade.</p>
        <p>This is the first time that Kansas is under .500 seven games into the season since 1971, and the Jayhawks could be on their way their first sub. 500 full season since 1982-83.</p>
        <p>Chet Stachitas, a senior forward and one of the few holdovers from the 2003-4 team that was undefeated during the regular season, led St. Joseph's (4-1) with 27 points. That tied a career high. Stachitas made 9 of 12 shots, including 6 of 9 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>The Hawks took their first lead of the game with 17:42 left in the second half when Abdulai Jalloh connected on a 3-pointer to put his team in front, 38-37. St. Joseph's increased its lead to 47-42 on a 3-pointer by Stachitas with 14:27 left. Stachitas kept hitting just about everything, scoring 17 second-half points.</p>
        <p>With 17.6 seconds to go, Stachitas hit just one of two free throws, which left his team clinging to a 70-67 lead. The freshman Micah Downs had a chance to tie the score for Kansas when taking a 3-pointer from the left wing with time running out, but it was off the mark. Ahmad Nivins grabbed the rebound, and St. Joseph's had its biggest victory of the season.</p>
        <p>Kansas' problems included a dismal free throw shooting night. The Jayhawks shot 32 percent (6 for 19) from the line and missed all four free-throw attempts in the final five minutes.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
