<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Singh's Late Error, Perry Takes The Bay Hill</title>
    <meta content="21GOLF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/21/sports/golf/21golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1658871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bay Hill Invitational (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hack, Damon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perry, Kenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Perry, Kenny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D71E3CF932A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Singh's Late Error, Perry Takes The Bay Hill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Singh's Late Error, Perry Takes the Bay Hill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., March 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenny Perry wins Bay Hill Open (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh stood in the middle of the last fairway at the Bay Hill Invitational with a 7-iron, waggling it for the right feel, staring into the green expanse at his target. In three holes, under a darkening sky Sunday, Singh had taken Kenny Perry's three-shot lead and whittled it to none.</p>
        <p>Singh sent his shot skyward and leaned hard into the club, following the ball's flight as it dropped short of the 18th green, bounced off a rock and landed in a lake fronting the green. Singh's knees buckled as his chance at victory drowned in murky water, lifting Perry to his eighth career PGA Tour victory and first since 2003, when he won three times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh's knees buckled as his chance at victory drowned in murky water, lifting Kenny Perry to his eighth career PGA Tour win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vijay Singh stood in the middle of the last fairway at the Bay Hill Invitational with a 7-iron, waggling it for the right feel, staring into the green expanse at his target. In three holes, under a darkening sky Sunday, Singh had taken Kenny Perry's three-shot lead and whittled it to none.</p>
        <p>Singh sent his shot skyward and leaned hard into the club, following the ball's flight as it dropped short of the 18th green, bounced off a rock and landed in a lake fronting the green. Singh's knees buckled as his chance at victory drowned in murky water, lifting Perry to his eighth career PGA Tour victory and first since 2003, when he won three times.</p>
        <p>Singh's error brought moans from onlookers who had expected nothing less than perfect execution. Count Perry and Singh among the surprised.</p>
        <p>''I'm shocked,'' said Perry, who finished with a two-putt par on No. 18 for a two-under 70 and a total of 12-under-par 276, two shots better than Singh (69) and Graeme McDowell (66). ''It looked liked it was going next to the hole.''</p>
        <p>Singh said: ''It was a good shot, I just hit the wrong club. The wind shifted on me. The air is getting a little heavier, and the wind is kind of turning a bit.''</p>
        <p>He narrowly missed out on victory for the second consecutive week. At the Honda Classic last Sunday, Singh lost to Padraig Harrington in a playoff when he lipped out a 30-inch putt for par.</p>
        <p>''I play aggressive, and I went for the flag,'' Singh said. ''I just came up a little short.''</p>
        <p>Despite finishing tied for second, Singh supplanted Tiger Woods as the No. 1 player in the world after Woods finished tied for 23rd. Woods was among 40 players who finished the third round Sunday because a storm suspended play Thursday.</p>
        <p>Woods carded a two-over 74 on Sunday morning and then shot an even-par 72 in the afternoon to finish 11 shots behind Perry.</p>
        <p>''It was a frustrating week,'' Woods said. ''I didn't really have it, didn't putt well, didn't hit the ball all that great. Consequently, I wasn't in contention.''</p>
        <p>The race for No. 1 could change hands several times this season. Ernie Els is ranked third, and Phil Mickelson is fourth.</p>
        <p>''Being No. 1 is really just a number, because the wins take care of themselves,'' Woods said. ''If you win a bunch of tournaments each and every year, consistently, the rankings will just follow.''</p>
        <p>Singh was surprised to hear he had regained the top ranking.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think I got it back,'' he said with a laugh. ''Well, big deal. I lost the golf tournament.''</p>
        <p>Singh entered the final round three shots behind Perry and quickly pulled to two back when Perry bogeyed the first hole. As the final holes neared, Singh started to put pressure on Perry.</p>
        <p>Singh made a 15-footer for birdie on No. 15. On No. 16, a par-5, he closed the gap to one shot when he spun a wedge to a foot and tapped in for birdie. Perry could manage only par.</p>
        <p>Perry and Singh knocked their tee shots on the 219-yard, par-3 17th to the back fringe. From 60 feet, Perry hit his chip firm, sending it 8 feet past the hole. He lined up the return putt, released the blade and watched the putt lip out, leaving him with a bogey.</p>
        <p>When Singh dropped his 4-foot par putt in the center of the cup, Perry was caught.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I was a little nervous, I don't know,'' Perry said.</p>
        <p>But Singh made the pivotal mistake, on the 441-yard 18th hole, a par-4 that plays into the wind. When Singh hit into the water, Perry hit his approach shot to the fat part of the green, two-putted for par and the victory and slipped into the blue blazer that Arnold Palmer gives his tournament champion.</p>
        <p>Perry, who is from Franklin, Ky., also received $900,000 and a sword for his mantle.</p>
        <p>He has also won Jack Nicklaus's Memorial tournament and Ben Hogan's Colonial, two of the more prestigious events on Tour. Perry dedicated his victory to Norman Head, his former swing coach, who has Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>Perry said he was not sure where the victory would take him, but his immediate plans included driving up to Ponte Vedra Beach, Fla., site of the Players Championship. Singh had invited Perry, among several golfers, to attend a party at his home Monday night.</p>
        <p>Did Singh rescind the invitation after Perry beat him?</p>
        <p>''No,'' Perry said. ''He said, 'See you tomorrow.'''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
