<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hospital Chief Stepping Down After a Year</title>
    <meta content="21SINA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/21/nyregion/21SINA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medical Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mount Sinai Medical Center (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York University Medical Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mount Sinai School of Medicine (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berns, Kenneth I (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">David, Kenneth L (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medical Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medical Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Mount Sinai Medical Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4D91131F932A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hospital Chief Stepping Down After a Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leader of Troubled Hospital Stepping Down After a Year</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Kenneth I Berns, chief executive of New York's Mount Sinai Medical Center, is resigning barely one year after assuming post; will remain on staff as professor; will be replaced by Dr Kenneth L Davis, who is currently dean of medical school; up to 500 health care workers will be laid off in hospitalwide shakeup; change is widely viewed as final refutation of 1998 merger with New York University Medical Center (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barely a year after taking office on a pledge to restore the Mount Sinai Medical Center to economic health, its chief executive, Dr. Kenneth I. Berns, is leaving his post, and up to 500 health care workers will be laid off in a hospitalwide shake-up, administrators said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The job cuts, which will take effect within the next few weeks, come on top of the loss of about 430 positions already cut over the last year, as the hospital -- long one of the nation's premier teaching hospitals and an imposing presence on Manhattan's Upper East Side -- has struggled with problems in its finances, its administration and its medical reputation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Kenneth I. Berns, who pledged to restore Mount Sinai Medical Center to economic health, is leaving his post as chief executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barely a year after taking office on a pledge to restore the Mount Sinai Medical Center to economic health, its chief executive, Dr. Kenneth I. Berns, is leaving his post, and up to 500 health care workers will be laid off in a hospitalwide shake-up, administrators said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The job cuts, which will take effect within the next few weeks, come on top of the loss of about 430 positions already cut over the last year, as the hospital -- long one of the nation's premier teaching hospitals and an imposing presence on Manhattan's Upper East Side -- has struggled with problems in its finances, its administration and its medical reputation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Berns, a 64-year-old geneticist who was recruited to Mount Sinai from the University of Florida, will remain on the staff as a professor of genetic research in the medical school. He will be replaced by Dr. Kenneth L. Davis, 56, who is currently the dean of the medical school. Dr. Davis, who has been at Mount Sinai since 1979, will remain dean and add Dr. Berns's responsibilities to his own.</p>
        <p>Mount Sinai has more than 11,000 employees.</p>
        <p>''We deeply appreciate the leadership that Dr. Berns has provided over the last year,'' said Peter W. May, the medical center chairman, ''and we are pleased that he will be a part of Mount Sinai's research efforts.''</p>
        <p>A hospital spokesman, Dr. Gary Rosenberg, said that while the change was not Dr. Berns's idea, he was involved in discussions of the reorganization and was not being removed for poor performance.</p>
        <p>''He was party to the discussion and he fully agreed'' that his best contribution would be in his own research specialty, Dr. Rosenberg said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Berns could not be reached for comment; a woman in his office said he was attending an event off campus.</p>
        <p>Administrators said the leadership change and the job cuts reflected two deep but very different problems at Mount Sinai.</p>
        <p>Reducing the staff, the administrators said, is part of a yearlong reorganization process to help stem steep financial losses, which are partly the result of rising costs from insurance, drugs and emergency preparedness, especially after the terrorism attacks of Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>The change in administration, they said, addresses the core nature of the institution. In many ways it represents the final refutation of the merger with N.Y.U. Medical Center in 1998, which is widely regarded within the hospital industry, and within Mount Sinai, as a failure.</p>
        <p>The merger separated the medical school and the hospital, a change that also separated the functions of research and patient care. Under Dr. Davis, they will once again be reunited under one head, as they were for most of Mount Sinai's history.</p>
        <p>''This will really bring the medical school and hospital into a unified position, where we were before the merger,'' Dr. Rosenberg said. ''After the merger they were separately administered, and that didn't work.''</p>
        <p>Mount Sinai is certainly not alone among New York hospitals in facing money troubles. Industry experts say those problems are likely to deepen this year as the fiscal crisis in Albany ripples out, especially through proposed cuts in reimbursement under the Medicaid system, which helps hospitals care for the poor.</p>
        <p>For Mount Sinai, though, the struggle has been harder and longer. The death early last year of a partial-liver donor from an infection, partly because of what investigators said was inadequate medical supervision, led the state to order the hospital to suspend transplants for six months. At the same time, the hospital began closing clinics, laying off workers and imposing new cost controls in hopes of containing its financial losses.</p>
        <p>Hospital industry experts said the job cuts announced yesterday, while partly reflecting Mount Sinai's specific situation, could very likely be echoed at other hospitals in the months ahead as losses continue across the industry.</p>
        <p>''This is evidence that the concern about the financial stress being felt by New York City hospitals is real,'' said James R. Tallon Jr., the president of the United Hospital Fund, a research and philanthropic group based in Manhattan. ''It certainly demonstrates that in the hospitals, we're dealing with both smoke and fire.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
