<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mauve-ing of America</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="430748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERIOR DESIGN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANTWELL, MARY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEWART, MARTHA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STODDARD, ALEXANDRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED81E3DF934A25750C0A967958260" item-length="2088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mauve-ing of America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Cantwell; Mary Cantwell is on the editorial board of The Times. She has recently completed a memoir of small-town life.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANTWELL, MARY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martha Stewart. Alexandra Stoddard. Simply to say their names is to recall a dear friend -- I will call her Jane -- for whom living well was much more than the best revenge. It was the Only Thing. No supermarket bar of soap made its way into her bathroom, nor did she ever make a meal out of an end of salami, a heel of French bread and last night's leftover wine. I have, we all have. Jane would have thought it a descent into the gutter.</p>
        <p>One morning, having stayed overnight on the pullout couch in her living room, I awoke to find her sipping coffee, her eyes fixed on a sun-struck bowl of white roses. "I am having," she said, referring to the 19th-century flower painter, "a Fantin-Latour moment." Martha Stewart and Alexandra Stoddard, the latter in particular, are very big on the Fantin-Latour moment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martha Stewart. Alexandra Stoddard. Simply to say their names is to recall a dear friend -- I will call her Jane -- for whom living well was much more than the best revenge. It was the Only Thing. No supermarket bar of soap made its way into her bathroom, nor did she ever make a meal out of an end of salami, a heel of French bread and last night's leftover wine. I have, we all have. Jane would have thought it a descent into the gutter.</p>
        <p>One morning, having stayed overnight on the pullout couch in her living room, I awoke to find her sipping coffee, her eyes fixed on a sun-struck bowl of white roses. "I am having," she said, referring to the 19th-century flower painter, "a Fantin-Latour moment." Martha Stewart and Alexandra Stoddard, the latter in particular, are very big on the Fantin-Latour moment.</p>
        <p>"And afterward, what is more fun than to put your hat away in a scented, flowered chintz hatbox?" Alexandra asks in "Daring to Be Yourself," one of her many books. Several things probably, but why cavil? Take the time to contemplate the chintz, caress the tissue paper and there it is. A Fantin-Latour moment.</p>
        <p>If I am somewhat slow to formally introduce Martha Stewart and Alexandra Stoddard, it is because I find it hard to believe they need an introduction. Not when the one has memorialized her days and nights on Turkey Hill Road in eight books, four videos and a new magazine; and when the other, who also believes that life can be beautiful, has said so in nine books, a magazine column and, this year, a newsletter. Martha Stewart, in fact, no longer needs a last name. Several weeks ago, at an antiques show, I found an acquaintance buying yard after yard of old ribbons with which to wrap presents. "Aha," I said "you've been reading Martha. . . ." My lips had scarcely formed an S before she squawked: "No, no, I did it first.</p>
        <p>Before</p>
        <p>Martha!"</p>
        <p>Martha Stewart produced her first book in the 1980's, and Alexandra Stoddard was delivered of her first in the 70's. But it is the 90's that is their decade. If Erica Jong's Isadora Wing reflected a certain Zeitgeist, so they reflect another. It's cookie time! Home and hearth time! Time to slip into something more comfortable.</p>
        <p>Martha Stewart is a product of Nutley, N.J., a hometown as familiar to her fans and followers as Saint-Sauveur-en-Puisaye is to Colette's. "It seems like yesterday, that early Christmas morning when I crept down the chilly oak staircase in our family home in Nutley" . . . "The family car left Nutley, N.J., each morning as Father went to his salesman's job" . . . "My first 'catered' party was a breakfast of heroic proportions for the Nutley High School football team."</p>
        <p>If it was Sido and Sido's house that made Colette a writer, so it was life in Nutley -- with the Victory garden that was her father's joy and the mother who served 10 different vegetables and five fresh fruit desserts at Sunday dinner and the little brothers and sisters with whom she baked and decorated and made presents -- that made Martha what she is today. America's own Goddess of Housekeeping. The faith symbolized by Martha Stewart, however, is as far from broom, dustpan, mop and Sani-Flush as Mouton-Rothschild is from Welch's grape juice. Instead, it celebrates hens that lay blue eggs and gardens in which "everything grows bigger than life," meals reminiscent of Emma Bovary's wedding feast and dining tables done up to the nines. And its shrine is a restored 19th-century farmhouse on Turkey Hill Road in Westport, Conn., a monument to money, upper-middle-class taste and compulsive attendance at every antiques shop, consignment shop and tag sale in southern Connecticut. Maybe the entire United States.</p>
        <p>See Martha make blinis, cut heart shapes out of cucumber slices, construct a croquembouche. Hear her purr "this looks</p>
        <p>great</p>
        <p>. . . isn't that</p>
        <p>cute</p>
        <p>. . . I</p>
        <p>love</p>
        <p>that cookie . . . these parsnips are</p>
        <p>perfect</p>
        <p>." The candles are lighted, the guests arrive, the Depression glass looks like a million bucks. Elsewhere, ignorant armies are clashing. But not here, not at Turkey Hill Farm. Nor at your house either, not if you follow the rituals.</p>
        <p>Alexandra Stoddard shares Martha's Seven Sisters hair style (minus the part), the same plushy landscape (she was raised in Westport) and the same air of Vassar '62. And, like Martha Stewart, she is more than eager to talk about herself and her family. Their husbands' names are reassuringly bankerish -- Peter for Alexandra and the since-divorced Andrew for Martha -- and their daughters' rather grand. Alexandra has Alexandra and Brooke; Martha has Alexis. Both are unapologetically affluent. Neither, thank God, is a poor-mouth.</p>
        <p>Although Alexandra is an interior decorator ("Recently I chose for a couple's penthouse living room, dining room and hall . . . a Fuller O'Brien Fulcolor Free Spirit Yellow") and a mine of paint, rug and furniture tips, her Fantin-Latour moments are sometimes less the fruits of the flesh than of the spirit. She quotes all-stars like Rilke, Kierkegaard, Shakespeare, Goethe, the Book of Common Prayer and Bill Moyers, along with friends named Cathy and Gwen and Louise, and always to the same end. "Each of us must become impassioned, finding meaning and self-fulfillment in our own life's journey," she says at the beginning of "Alexandra Stoddard's Living Beautifully Together." Actually, she says it in one way or another in all her books.</p>
        <p>That her readers are true believers is clear from her sales (often the hard-cover and paperback versions of the same books are selling simultaneously) and, above all, from their letters -- not only by what is said but by what it's said upon. Many of her correspondents appear to have listened hard to "Does the lining color in the envelope speak to you? The embossing? The hand-painted borders where the colors have definition?" Out of a pile of 30, for instance, only 3 had the plain American flag stamp. The other stamps had been bought for their looks, and nine of them said LOVE. One letter was typed, the rest handwritten -- sometimes elaborately so -- and the writing paper was variously pink, peach or flowered. One woman had used two menu-size greeting cards printed with enormous bouquets. A Fantin-Latour moment indeed.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the purest expression of the fans' belief in Alexandra, however, is in a letter in the first issue of her newsletter, "Beautiful Living Companion." A Colorado woman writes: "One of the first things I did after reading 'Living a Beautiful Life' was purchase a heavy crystal decanter for our orange juice. I get a feeling of satisfaction every time I open the refrigerator and see it on the shelf." I, for one, cannot sneer at the sentiment, not when I find squeezing oranges with my 1930's English pottery squeezer close to a religious experience.</p>
        <p>Martha's Fantin-Latour moments, like my epiphany with the squeezer, often emerge from the joy the workman takes in the right tools. U-pins, for making a Christmas wreath out of the neighborhood greenery, are "really great." "This laundry rack just works wonderfully" as a place upon which to toss spun sugar. Cookies never stick if one uses "this really nice baking paper." A pouncer brush is swell for stenciling. Natural sponges are wonderful for decorating both wrapping paper and cookies. As for that spun-sugar tossing, Martha does it with a truncated whisk. Her invention.</p>
        <p>Although Alexandra warns that "all this emphasis on money and acquisition can increase our sense of insecurity and lower our self-esteem," she sometimes sounds like a contributor to Harper's Bazaar's legendary, long-ago "Why Don't You" column. "After summering with the in-laws in Maine, you've discovered you need more privacy with your immediate family. So you quietly look for a cozy house to rent in the country where you and your spouse can enjoy your weekends with the children." . . . "Don't analyze why something speaks to you -- whether it is a painting, a chandelier, a piece of antique jewelry, a tablecloth, a Windsor chair or a lavender dress. It is meant to be yours. Act." . . . "The white trousers go from a dock in the South of France to dinner in the Berkshires to Bermuda and back home by the fire with a cashmere sweater. . . ." Never mind. That the reader is no more apt to be summering at Bar Harbor than she is to toss carmelized sugar over a laundry rack is irrelevant. It's the possibility that exhilarates.</p>
        <p>"To read Martha in bed is to feel like you've been tucked in, and to read Alexandra anywhere is like listening to verbal Muzak," says a devotee of both. "And when the wind blows chill, you want to pull a warm cozy magazine over your ears."</p>
        <p>The magazine she has in mind is Victoria, three years old and a paean to a presumably gentler age. As the circulation of women's service magazines slump, so that of Victoria soars -- 806,000 at last count. Here there are no nasty bosses and nastier underlings, no problematic orgasms and thunder thighs. Here are women dressed to resemble Cheryl Campbell in "The Shooting Party" and Maud when the black bat, night, has flown, and silver tea services sparkling in firelight. Roses spill their petals onto polished mahogany, homemade marmalade glistens in its glass, a bed that might have done for Rhett and Scarlett beckons. Victoria is all, and more, the service magazines were before they got in step with the times. Victoria is determinedly out of step, which surely accounts for that 806,000 in circulation.</p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, an article about Roseanne Barr in a recent issue of a service magazine that details the oft-told tale of how she and her current husband once consummated their love in the bathroom of a yogurt shop. A few pages later, Dr. Ruth, in prose as high-pitched as her voice, urges us not to take sex so seriously and advises "risky business." She is reminded of a couple who sneaked a quickie in a changing hut after a swim and . . . the reader pauses, an image of Roseanne and Tom in the bathroom in unsettling juxtaposition with one of herself and her beloved struggling out of damp swimsuits. Small wonder if she turns to Victoria with its "A Cozy Place for Armchair Dreams" and "By Firelight -- A Romantic Dinner, an Afternoon Reverie." So pretty, so pleasant, so</p>
        <p>restful</p>
        <p>. And so evocative of the good life as it's lived by Martha Stewart and Alexandra Stoddard.</p>
        <p>But Martha and Alexandra are not restful. "Watching Martha making a gingerbread house," the devotee says, "is a lot like watching a Jane Fonda video. You may not want to do that stuff yourself, but you're glad somebody is." Making the charts, arranging the folders and doing the lists that Alexandra suggests will get you through the day would kill a week. But while it is easy to poke fun at their relentless energy, at the make-work implicit in Martha's tendency toward overkill (heart-shaped Melba toast, for example) and at Alexandra's passion for continual audits of one's life, it's also to miss the point of all that activity. Embellishing the cave is an ancient preoccupation -- look at Lascaux -- and so is attempting to bring order out of chaos.</p>
        <p>A LONG TIME AGO, I SAW A photograph of a linen cupboard in which the sheets and towels had been neatly stacked and tied up in ribbons. I was living in my third "married" apartment then, and for the first time had such a cupboard. Should I?</p>
        <p>I didn't, because I am a lazy woman and bad at tying bows. But I remember being tempted, and why. Ordering my linens into ranks would have been a form of defense in a world I found disorderly. There was not, is not, a thing to be done about pestilence, death and the bad dreams that sneak up on us when we're not sleeping. But I would have had that cupboard, that proof positive that I could make tidy my minuscule corner of the universe. Seeing Wamsutta, Martex and Cannon neat and cozy in their ribbons might even have afforded me a Fantin-Latour moment.</p>
        <p>We enter this world naked, we leave this world naked. But as long as we are in residence, Martha Stewart and Alexandra Stoddard will make sure we are dressed. Not in clothes necessarily, although Alexandra has a lot of tips about those, too, but in Fantin-Latour moments. "Seek wonderful smells. . . . When you sit by a warm fire study the flames," Alexandra advises. "At the end of the day, no matter who we are or what we do," Martha says, "we want to go home." Thousands, more likely millions, of American women hang on to their every word. In the age of Athena, Demeter is getting rich.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
