<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christopher Takes Syrian Response to Rabin</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISRAEL-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-SYRIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SYRIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER, WARREN M (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DB1738F934A25756C0A962958260" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christopher Takes Syrian Response to Rabin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, May 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Indirect peace negotiations between Israel and Syria gathered momentum today as Secretary of State Warren Christopher brought Syria's response to an Israeli peace plan to Jerusalem after having pressed Damascus to flesh out additional details.</p>
        <p>Eager to avoid any misunderstandings in the fragile negotiations, Mr. Christopher delayed his flight from Damascus to Israel by six hours today so he could get Syria's Foreign Minister, Farouk al-Sharaa, to clarify parts of the Syrian counterproposal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Indirect peace negotiations between Israel and Syria gathered momentum today as Secretary of State Warren Christopher brought Syria's response to an Israeli peace plan to Jerusalem after having pressed Damascus to flesh out additional details.</p>
        <p>Eager to avoid any misunderstandings in the fragile negotiations, Mr. Christopher delayed his flight from Damascus to Israel by six hours today so he could get Syria's Foreign Minister, Farouk al-Sharaa, to clarify parts of the Syrian counterproposal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher reported no specific progress from his meetings with Mr. Sharaa and President Hafez al-Assad, but he said he was pleased that Syria remained seriously engaged in peace efforts.  High Stakes for Both Sides</p>
        <p>"We are at the beginning of a very serious process that involves high stakes for both countries," he said. "My job is to try to make sure that we understand each other as well as possible and not leave uncertainties."</p>
        <p>American officials said Mr. Assad had presented a comprehensive counterproposal that covered issues like normalization, timing, security arrangements and Israeli withdrawal from the Golan Heights, which Israel captured in the 1967 war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher met late tonight in Jerusalem with Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin to discuss Mr. Assad's response. The Syrian radio reported today that Mr. Christopher would return to Damascus this week, but American officials said no such decision had been made final.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials said today that Syria appeared to be signaling slightly more flexibility in the peace talks. They pointed to an article today in Al Hayat, a London-based Arabic newspaper, which laid out a five-part Syrian formula to step up the peace talks.</p>
        <p>Citing Syrian officials, the newspaper said Syria wanted Israel to cancel its annexation of the Golan Heights and recognize Syrian sovereignty over that area. The plan also said that Israel should voice its readiness to withdraw from the Golan in the future and that Syria and Israel should discuss security arrangements on both sides of the border.</p>
        <p>Lastly, Syria would show a willingness to discuss other questions involving relations, including normalization, embassies and trade.</p>
        <p>There remains a major difference over Syria's call for a total and rapid Israeli withdrawal from the Golan. Prime Minister Rabin has indicated a willingness to close many Israeli settlements there, but he continues to oppose full withdrawal. In addition, Israel proposed a phased withdrawal over several years. No Breakthrough Seen</p>
        <p>A senior American official said the talks were "not on the brink of a breakthrough." He said Syria and Israel had no plans to resume direct peace talks, which broke off in late February. Mr. Christopher's work as a mediator "will give more of a push to the direct negotiations when they resume," he said.</p>
        <p>Coinciding with Mr. Christopher's visit to Damascus, The Syria Times, an official newspaper, ran an article saying that most American newspapers were under Jewish influence, that Jews often distorted facts to mislead the public and that Jews unduly intervened in American education, research and culture. As evidence of Jewish influence, the newspaper said that "30 percent of Protestant bishops in the United States are Jews who did not quit Judaism."</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher asked the American Ambassador in Damascus, Christopher Ross, to complain to Syrian officials about the article.</p>
        <p>American and Israeli officials said other articles in the Syrian press had been more positive. Tishrin, an official Syrian paper, suggested on Sunday that Damascus would accept Israeli withdrawal from the Golan over a "reasonable and acceptable" time period. Israeli officials said that signaled a change from Syria's usual demand for immediate withdrawal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
