<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Magazines Follow Baby Boomers Into the Garden</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="741803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAGAZINES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARMODY, DEIRDRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D9173BF935A35751C0A963958260" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Magazines Follow Baby Boomers Into the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEIRDRE CARMODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARMODY, DEIRDRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few years ago, in the course of his travels around the country, Douglas Jimerson, the garden editor of Better Homes and Gardens, became puzzled as to why people were beginning to refer to their lawns and backyards as rooms.</p>
        <p>"Rooms?" he wondered. Then the light went on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few years ago, in the course of his travels around the country, Douglas Jimerson, the garden editor of Better Homes and Gardens, became puzzled as to why people were beginning to refer to their lawns and backyards as rooms.</p>
        <p>"Rooms?" he wondered. Then the light went on.</p>
        <p>"These were people in their 40's and 50's and it didn't take much to figure out who is in their 40's and 50's now," he said. As baby boomers "put finishing touches on the inside of their houses," he said, "the logical place for them to turn their attention to was outside."</p>
        <p>This week, the first issue of Home Garden hits the stands, with Mr. Jimerson as editor in chief. Filled with tips on how to grow roses in hard places, make topiary or design a potting shed, Home Garden is one of several new magazines to respond to the surge of interest in gardening among baby boomers. Home Garden, like its older sibling, Better Homes and Gardens, is published by the Meredith Corporation of Des Moines.</p>
        <p>Gardening has become a $22 billion business, with the bulk of the money -- an average of $400 a year -- spent by 30- to 49-year-olds with annual incomes of more than $50,000, according to a 1993 survey by the National Gardening Association. People with incomes of $100,000 spend twice as much.</p>
        <p>Andrew Cook, who owns de Van Koek, a supplier of high-end, hand-forged gardening tools, has seen his business grow an average of 125 percent a year since he started it five years ago.</p>
        <p>Allen Lacy, a writer of gardening books and a former gardening columnist for The Wall Street Journal and The New York Times, started Homeground, a 16-page quarterly newsletter for gardeners, in 1993. Although subscriptions are a steep $38 a year, Mr. Lacy said subscribers were renewing at a 60 percent rate, which is considered high in the magazine industry. Most of the newsletter's 1,000 subscribers come from high-income areas like the Upper East Side of Manhattan, Georgetown and Darien, Conn.</p>
        <p>And Country Living Gardener, introduced by Hearst magazines in 1992 as a spinoff of Country Living magazine, has just increased its publishing schedule from twice a year to four times a year. It also increased the circulation guaranteed to advertisers to 500,000 from 450,000.</p>
        <p>The surge of interest is not only evident in print. Virtual Garden, a Time Inc. on-line service that made its debut on the Internet in October, is being tapped into 35,000 times a week. Among other things, the service enables viewers to use an interactive gardening encyclopedia that provides endless lists of plants and information on such titillating subjects as how to triple-till your soil.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the first of the gardening magazines to be aimed squarely at the most affluent baby boomers was Garden Design. The magazine, with a circulation of 50,000, had been published since 1981 by the American Society of Landscape Architects. It was acquired last year by Meigher Communications, a company formed specifically to cater to aging baby boomers with substantial incomes.</p>
        <p>The magazine was redesigned under a new editor in chief, Dorothy Kalins, a former editor in chief of Metropolitan Home during the 1980's, and a new publisher, Joe Armstrong, a former publisher of Rolling Stone. They made the magazine more elegant and lavish, and reintroduced it in April with a circulation of 50,000.</p>
        <p>S. Christopher Meigher 3d, a former head of magazine development at Time Inc. who is president and co-founder of Meigher Communications, said Garden Design was expected to achieve profitability in one year. Its circulation is now 150,000.</p>
        <p>The magazine, which appears six times a year, has a hefty cover price of $5. (Home Garden, which is published six times a year, has a cover price of $3.99 and Country Living Gardener has a cover price of $3.50.) Subscriptions are $24 a year.</p>
        <p>But what Mr. Meigher and Mr. Armstrong are most proud of is the list of prestigious advertisers in Garden Design, including Saks Fifth Avenue, Godiva, Cadillac, Ralph Lauren and Rolex.</p>
        <p>This roster represents a breakthrough. For years, high-income advertisers neglected gardening magazines, which had to rely instead on ads from suppliers of garden equipment and fertilizers.</p>
        <p>Valerie Muller, executive vice president of DeWitt Media, an advertising agency, said the entry of Home Garden into the market this week would give a lift to the newly established category.</p>
        <p>"I am thrilled that the category is developing because I think it is a natural one," she said. "I like it when things are not force-fed to the public. It is so rare when we see customer needs being addressed instead of just someone wanting to make some money."</p>
        <p>Garden Design's readers have a median age of 43 and a median household income of $71,000, while those of Home Garden have a median age of 42 and a median household income of $57,000.</p>
        <p>Dorothy Kalins, editor in chief of Garden Design, describes her magazine as "embodying the baby boomer ideology: intensely personal, a little spiritual, sophisticated but very, very approachable."</p>
        <p>For Catherine Westerberg, publisher of Home Garden, Garden Design compares with her publication this way: "It's kind of like Oscar de la Renta ball gowns to our Anne Klein ready to wear."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
