<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wonder Of Metness: Day at Shea</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB173FF933A25757C0A966958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wonder Of Metness: Day at Shea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Finally, it was time for what Robert Derbabian calls ''the wonder of Metness.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Finally, it was time for what Robert Derbabian calls ''the wonder of Metness.''</p>
        <p>Finally, it was time for what Robert Derbabian calls ''the wonder of Metness.''</p>
        <p>Never mind the uncertainty of the 32-day lockout and the emptiness of more than a month without idyllic dispatches from the sunny South describing ball players stretching and shagging flies and smacking fungoes. Never mind the endlessness of labor negotiations and the hugeness of players' megabuck salaries. Never mind that to experience the wonder of Metness, Mr. Derbabian had to experience the madness of Metness, which involved elbowing his way onto a standing-room-only subway car.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, all was forgiven. The moment he saw the blue-and-gray colossus of Shea Stadium, the memories came back: Dwight Gooden's one-hitter in 1985. The season tickets a friend gave up when the Mets let Keith Hernandez go. Even the 1980 lineup, ''when they were nothing.''</p>
        <p>The No. 7 train stopped at the Willets Point-Shea Stadium station, brakes squealing. Mr. Derbabian said he had a case of opening-day butterflies. And then he disappeared in a sea of blue-and-orange caps, blue-and-orange warmup jackets, blue-and-orange sweatshirts. Gloria Barnes, a bartender from Astoria, Queens, wore her Mets earrings.</p>
        <p>No Yankee Pinstripes Here</p>
        <p>There were some people in pinstripes - not the Yankee kind - but the worries of winter and of the workplace seemed so far away.</p>
        <p>''Fans have short memories,'' Mr. Derbabian said. ''The lockout was a joke. The owners started that whole thing by paying what the players wanted. Nobody complains when Sinatra makes a ton of money. But once the game starts, nobody thinks about anybody's salary.''</p>
        <p>And no one was thinking about preseason headaches, like the Howard Spira-George Steinbrenner matter and that other New York team, the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spira pleaded not guilty last week to trying to extort money from Mr. Steinbrenner, the volcanic Yankees' owner. Mr. Steinbrenner has acknowledged paying Mr. Spira $40,000. Mr. Spira has said the money was for information to ''destroy'' Dave Winfield. Mr. Steinbrenner has said that he wanted the information to help settle a dispute concerning his contributions to the Winfield Foundation.</p>
        <p>Cashen Doing His Thing</p>
        <p>''My dad is a diehard Yankee fan,'' Mr. Derbabian said. ''He doesn't care about Steinbrenner. I care that he ruined a great team. Wilpon and Dou bleday just let Cashen do his thing.''</p>
        <p>For some on Mr. Derbabian's train, yesterday was a first. Joshua Cohen - ''six and a half, I think'' - had never seen a season opener before, but he had some idea of what to expect: His father, Dan Cohen, a psychologist, said they had been to Shea for one game last year.</p>
        <p>''Dad! Dad! I can't remember the score!'' said Joshua, adding that he has 4,685 baseball cards at home -nearly 10 percent of them emblazoned with Darryl Strawberry's picture. ''It was the Reds and the Mets.''</p>
        <p>It was also Mayor David N. Dinkins's first opening day as mayor. He left the game at the top of the fifth, when the score was tied 3-3, to go back to City Hall to perform a marriage ceremony, his first since taking office. He officiated for Paula Walker, 37, assistant news director of WNBC-TV, and Roosevelt Madison, 33, a freelance television makeup artist and fashion model.</p>
        <p>Nasty, Brutish and Long</p>
        <p>''Beautiful,'' the Mayor said after his trip to Shea. ''Lots of hits. Excellent seats, of course. The sun was shining. The grass was green. The sky was blue.''</p>
        <p>For some, though not Mr. Dinkins, the trip to Shea was nasty, brutish, and anything but short. Chris Donnelly of Schenectady, N.Y., got up at 9 P.M. Sunday, worked the midnight shift at the Post Office there, then caught a 9 A.M. train to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I got about 5 minutes of sleep on the train,'' he said, wide awake at game time.</p>
        <p>Some who did not have so many miles to go still had problems on the way to Shea. One No. 7 train was stopped in Long Island City, Queens, for 15 minutes for what the train crew said was track work.</p>
        <p>The train was delayed again, at the 74th Street station in Jackson Heights. The train crew said the holdup was a passenger who had gotten sick and needed to be helped off. The fans, anxious about missing the first pitch, groaned.</p>
        <p>Eventually the train got going again, arriving at Shea just in time for Howard Johnson's home run in the bottom of the first.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
