<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Council's Meter Plan Restores Free Sunday Parking</title>
    <meta content="28meter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/28/nyregion/28meter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050729T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1690626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">City Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDA103FF93BA15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Council's Meter Plan Restores Free Sunday Parking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City Council's Meter Plan Restores Free Sunday Parking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS CONFESSORE; Colin Moynihan and Jim Rutenberg contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The City Council voted overwhelmingly yesterday to eliminate metered parking on Sundays, restoring to New Yorkers a treasured privilege whose loss has been much lamented in the two years since it was sacrificed to bring added revenue to the city's depleted treasury.</p>
        <p>The Council's decision touched off an unusually bitter debate with Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who attacked the legislation as naked election-year pandering, and whose transportation commissioner, Iris Weinshall, told the Council in testimony yesterday that it had chosen to ''put both pedestrians and motorists at risk,'' a charge that infuriated many Council members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The City Council's decision sparked an unusually bitter debate with Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who attacked the legislation as naked election-year pandering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The City Council voted overwhelmingly yesterday to eliminate metered parking on Sundays, restoring to New Yorkers a treasured privilege whose loss has been much lamented in the two years since it was sacrificed to bring added revenue to the city's depleted treasury.</p>
        <p>The Council's decision touched off an unusually bitter debate with Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who attacked the legislation as naked election-year pandering, and whose transportation commissioner, Iris Weinshall, told the Council in testimony yesterday that it had chosen to ''put both pedestrians and motorists at risk,'' a charge that infuriated many Council members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg vowed to veto the legislation, but mayoral aides acknowledged that they would likely not have the necessary votes to defeat an almost certain override. The vote in favor of the bill was 43 to 1.</p>
        <p>The legislation will most likely prove popular with city residents, some of whom seemed ecstatic yesterday that they would no longer have to dart out of church to feed the meter or scrounge for quarters on a Sunday morning instead of sleeping in.</p>
        <p>''I think that's great. I think that's about time,'' said Jerry Barber, 34, as he parked his car on Montague Street in Brooklyn Heights. Mr. Barber, who works seven days a week as a security consultant, said he had heard reports of the change yesterday morning and was grateful for it. ''The city bleeds us of cash. It's time to give the working man a break.''</p>
        <p>Patsy Grant, 53, a jazz singer from East New York, said, ''It's crazy trying to park on Sundays when everybody's off work.'' Almost every cost involved in owning a car has gone up, she noted. ''It would be great to relax on Sunday and not worry about that $150 ticket.''</p>
        <p>Legislation to suspend metered parking on Sundays was first proposed in 2003 by Councilman Vincent J. Gentile, not long after the meters in his Brooklyn district became active on Sundays. ''As time went on, more and more meters became active, and so more and more constituents came to object,'' said Mr. Gentile, who cosponsored the final version of the measure with Councilman Hiram Monserrate.</p>
        <p>''Everything needs a break one day a week -- even parking meters,'' the Council speaker, Gifford Miller, said at a press conference in City Hall, appearing with Mr. Gentile and Mr. Monserrate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gentile said the measure would cost the city about $12 million a year in lost revenue, which he described as ''a drop in the bucket.''</p>
        <p>But during testimony before the Council's Finance Committee yesterday morning, Commissioner Weinshall criticized the bill and the Council in unusually strong terms, saying that the meters served as an important tool for managing both traffic and the availability of parking spaces.</p>
        <p>''The purpose of meters, regardless of which day they are in effect, is to turn over parking spaces so that more customers and other individuals can gain access to a particular parking spot in busy commercial areas,'' said Commissioner Weinshall, who said that fewer than half of city meters were active on Sundays.</p>
        <p>High turnover, she added, made it easier for motorists to find parking spaces and reduced illegal parking in bus stops and at fire hydrants, enhancing public safety.</p>
        <p>''So where does that leave us?'' she asked. ''The Council wants to make it more difficult for New Yorkers to find parking.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg also criticized the Council and Mr. Miller, who is running for mayor.</p>
        <p>''This will take away the ability for people to go to church on Sunday morning; this will take away the ability for people to go to stores and shop on Sunday mornings, because people will just leave their car the whole day,'' the mayor said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg and his aides appeared caught off guard by the legislation's swift move through the Council. The Finance Committee held a hearing yesterday morning and passed the bill by a vote of 14 to 1. Before lunchtime, the mayor's aides said they doubted that the bill would come up for a vote the same day.</p>
        <p>The mayor also contrasted the bill's rapid passage with the sweeping noise-pollution bill his administration had drafted in consultation with the Council -- the last major piece of legislation on the mayor's first-term agenda -- which is stalled.</p>
        <p>''You know, it's fascinating, in an election year the City Council can hold one hearing and come up with a piece of legislation, whereas the noise bill that we've tried to get passed for one year doesn't seem to be able to get to a vote.''</p>
        <p>In a clear dig at the speaker, who is more than 25 years his junior, Mr. Bloomberg said, ''We need some adults who will vote for things that will really make a difference in this city and not just pandering -- and hopefully the City Council will realize that they are really doing damage to those people who they profess to help.''</p>
        <p>The change came as especially good news to a particularly dedicated class of New Yorkers -- those nomadic car owners who brave the city streets year after year without the benefit of a driveway or garage space to call their own.</p>
        <p>''I think it's something we really need,'' said Paul Engel, a 70-year-old Upper West Sider who makes window coverings and draperies. Mr. Engel referred to himself as a ''professional parker,'' having owned a car in the city for 40 years, without a permanent spot to park, and getting a mere five tickets.</p>
        <p>''You have churchgoers, restaurants, movies, merchants. All will benefit. It's very difficult to run out every hour to put quarters in the meter when you're in the movies or eating dinner.''</p>
        <p>He pondered for a moment.</p>
        <p>''It will bring in Jerseyites,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 29, 2005, Friday  An article yesterday about a New York City Council vote to abolish metered parking on Sundays citywide referred imprecisely to the status of the city's meters in 2003, before free Sunday parking was curtailed. At the time, 6,400 of New York's 73,200 metered spaces required payment seven days a week; the city's action increased that number to 32,100, where it remains today. 1/3 1/3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 29, 2005, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a New York City Council vote to abolish metered parking on Sundays citywide referred imprecisely to the status of the city's meters in 2003, before free Sunday parking was curtailed. At the time, 6,400 of New York's 73,200 metered spaces required payment seven days a week; the city's action increased that number to 32,100, where it remains today. 1/3 1/3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
