<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Constellation of Advisers and Others Starts Updating Résumés</title>
    <meta content="28react" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/28/nyregion/28react.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1690633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TURNING POINT IN ALBANY: REACTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McKeon, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cahill, John P</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gargano, Charles A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5D9103FF93BA15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Constellation of Advisers and Others Starts Updating Résumés</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Constellation of Advisers and Others Starts Updating Résumés</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER and RAYMOND HERNANDEZ; Al Baker reported from Albany for this article, and Raymond Hernandez from Washington.</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, July 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki's announcement on Wednesday that he would not seek a fourth term sent shudders through the influential circle of lobbyists, consultants and aides whose fortunes have been linked to his for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>From the State Capitol to Wall Street and Washington, the legions of Republicans who came of age in the Pataki era and helped shape New York government and politics suddenly felt the political ground shift beneath their feet, prompting many to wonder what lay ahead for them. In a flurry of activity, résumés were dusted off and conference calls placed, and some held out hope that the journey of their main political benefactor would not end now but would continue to the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, July 27 - Gov. George E. Pataki's announcement on Wednesday that he would not seek a fourth term sent shudders through the influential circle of lobbyists, consultants and aides whose fortunes have been linked to his for more than a decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki's announcement on Wednesday that he would not seek a fourth term sent shudders through the influential circle of lobbyists, consultants and aides whose fortunes have been linked to his for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>From the State Capitol to Wall Street and Washington, the legions of Republicans who came of age in the Pataki era and helped shape New York government and politics suddenly felt the political ground shift beneath their feet, prompting many to wonder what lay ahead for them. In a flurry of activity, résumés were dusted off and conference calls placed, and some held out hope that the journey of their main political benefactor would not end now but would continue to the White House.</p>
        <p>''I think there are a lot of great things ahead for him, so I feel nothing but optimism,'' said Michael McKeon, a former aide who typifies the path followed by many people who owe their success to the governor. Mr. Pataki hired Mr. McKeon when he was a reporter for an upstate newspaper, vaulted him through his inner circle to the post of communications director and saw him go off on his own to become a leading political consultant at Mercury Public Affairs.</p>
        <p>For many others, there was the reality of losing the center around which their world has orbited.</p>
        <p>One associate of Mr. Pataki's took stock as news that the governor was leaving sunk in around Albany. ''Are there a whole host of people up in Albany who are now going to be concerned about making the mortgage payments in 2007? Absolutely,'' said the associate. ''But there are a whole host of Democrats who were in the same boat when Cuomo left, and they managed to survive.''</p>
        <p>For the governor's part, he left his aides with words of encouragement at his news conference in the Capitol. He ended it by pledging to use the rest of his time in office to make the state ''better, safer, cleaner and stronger'' than before. ''Let's not waste a day,'' he said. ''Let's get back to work.'' Applause filled the room. Some shouted.</p>
        <p>As they filed out into a crowded hallway, many of the governor's top aides were ebullient. Some said they felt motivated to find creative ways to solidify his achievements, now that they are free of the usual political restraints in place when a governor is seeking re-election.</p>
        <p>Many said it was too soon to start thinking about anything beyond the end of the governor's term, though they admitted that those thoughts would not be far off.</p>
        <p>''It will start to creep into the psyche of all of us; you know: 'What happens to me?''' said John F. Cape, the governor's budget director, who said it would be the fifth consecutive gubernatorial farewell he had seen.</p>
        <p>''But,'' he added, ''my assumption is we'll all be too busy to think about it.''</p>
        <p>Up the hallway, John P. Cahill, who has served in a series of senior posts in the Pataki administration and was appointed in May as the governor's new development chief in Lower Manhattan, was holding court with reporters. After he praised Mr. Pataki, he was asked about his own plans, which he said were to ''continue to work for the governor as long as he will let me.'' He did not say where that might be.</p>
        <p>Nearby, Charles A. Gargano, the chairman of the Empire State Development Corporation, considered his future without a Governor Pataki.</p>
        <p>''Me?'' he said. ''I collect unemployment,'' he said with mock concern, and laughed. Then he turned serious, acknowledging that there were many people in the Pataki administration, speechwriters, budget analysts and others facing a variety of changes.</p>
        <p>''The outside world is waiting for them,'' Mr. Gargano said.</p>
        <p>As the day wore on, many Republican political figures said they were not surprised by the decision and saw reason for hope. The governor had bowed out early enough to give the party a chance to rally behind a replacement.</p>
        <p>John J. Faso, one of the governor's close allies in the State Assembly who went on to become an Albany lobbyist, said it is too early ''to speak of him as though he is gone,'' noting that there is still plenty Mr. Pataki can do in his remaining time in office.</p>
        <p>Alfonse M. D'Amato, the former senator and confidant of Mr. Pataki's who played a crucial role in his 1994 victory, said Mr. Pataki was ever mindful of the network of loyalists he would be leaving behind. ''I think he had a sense of obligation he felt towards them,'' he said. ''I think that was one of the reasons he took so long to make his decision.''</p>
        <p>TURNING POINT IN ALBANY: REACTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
