<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. LEADERSHIP ANNOUNCES ACCORD ON TAX REDUCTION</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="770657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (SPEAKER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D61F3FF930A15755C0A963958260" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. LEADERSHIP ANNOUNCES ACCORD ON TAX REDUCTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republican leaders in the House and Senate struck a deal tonight to cut a variety of income and investment taxes by $245 billion over the next seven years, the final element of a compromise blueprint for balancing the Federal budget by 2002.</p>
        <p>Speaker Newt Gingrich and the Senate majority leader, Bob Dole, announced the tax and budget agreements tonight, ending three weeks of off-and-on haggling between their offices and Congress's ranking tax and budget officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Republican leaders in the House and Senate struck a deal tonight to cut a variety of income and investment taxes by $245 billion over the next seven years, the final element of a compromise blueprint for balancing the Federal budget by 2002.</p>
        <p>Speaker Newt Gingrich and the Senate majority leader, Bob Dole, announced the tax and budget agreements tonight, ending three weeks of off-and-on haggling between their offices and Congress's ranking tax and budget officials.</p>
        <p>Aides said that the final proposal called for spending of about $12 trillion over the next seven years, just under $1 trillion less than is currently assumed. It would also reduce projected "discretionary" spending -- on roads, education, the environment and other programs without fixed spending formulas -- by $190 billion through 2002, and increase projected military spending by about $34 billion during that period.</p>
        <p>Two of the biggest and fastest-growing entitlement programs, Medicare and Medicaid, would also get major reductions in their rates of spending growth, although their budgets would continue to rise.</p>
        <p>After the agreements were announced, the White House chief of staff, Leon E. Panetta, said that the Republicans were going about their budget balancing in the "wrong way" and that their plans apparently called for "extreme cuts in Medicare and unwise cuts in education to pay for tax cuts to those who don't need them." His remarks echoed earlier White House rumblings of a possible veto if tax and spending cuts were judged unacceptable.</p>
        <p>As a practical matter, the agreements reached tonight are less important as fiscal documents than as political symbols. The House and Senate took their biggest steps toward erasing the deficit in May, when they approved separate proposals to bring the Government to fiscal balance, and this compromise is devoted to eliminating what were mostly small differences between the two plans.</p>
        <p>Both chambers are expected to give their final approval to the new budget outline before Congress adjourns for the July 4 holiday. That, in turn, would give Congress's committees the directions they need to write detailed spending and tax plans for the 1996 budget this summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich called the agreements "another historic step in bringing the Federal budget into balance" and added, "After decades of reckless spending, we are committed to making Government leaner, more efficient and cost effective."</p>
        <p>But by no means does the accord insure that the Republican vision of a budget will become law. President Clinton has virtually promised to veto any budget containing deep reductions in the rate of spending on Medicare and Medicaid as well as deep cuts in taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton entered the budget-balancing competition himself last week, offering his own 10-year plan plan that included a tax cut of $111 billion. Mr. Gingrich said tonight that the President's proposal had "created an environment that made it easier" to reach an accord, but that the plan had never been seriously considered on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>The $245 billion deal on taxes effectively splits a very big difference between the Senate and House versions of the budget resolution, one that had seemed to threaten the prospects for any agreement at all.</p>
        <p>House Republicans voted nearly unanimously in April for a package of tax cuts totaling $350 billion over seven years and mainly intended to benefit families and investors. The Senate's more cautious Republicans, fearful that a package of that scale would undermine any plan to erase the deficit, voted in May to set aside $170 billion for tax reduction, but to be spent only if and when it could be proven that the Federal budget was headed toward fiscal balance.</p>
        <p>The compromise announced tonight lifts elements from both positions. The $245 billion in tax cuts includes the principal breaks sought by the House, including a $500-per-child tax credit for taxpaying families and reductions in the capital-gains rate. The proposal would halve the current capital gains rate of up to 28 percent for private investors and cap the corporate rate at 25 percent. These provisions, if enacted, presumably would take effect sometime before the 1996 elections.</p>
        <p>Other provisions could attack the so-called marriage penalty by giving a credit to couples whose taxes increase because of matrimony, create a tax-free retirement savings account for nonworking spouses, offer credits to adopting parents, reduce the alternative minimum tax for corporations and give small businesses more favorable tax treatment for deducting investments.</p>
        <p>The critical word, however, is "could." The actual mix of tax cuts, while heavily influenced by the Republican leaders and the budget committees, will be determined by the House and Senate tax-writing committees in legislation to be written this fall.</p>
        <p>One provision that seems destined to change is the House's proposal to extend the full $500-a-child tax credit to households earning up to $200,000 per year, gradually phasing out at a ceiling of $250,000. Democrats had attacked that as a giveaway to the rich. Negotiators said tonight that the full credit was likely to begin phasing out at incomes of $95,000 or even less.</p>
        <p>But in other respects, the $245 billion package is roughly what the House had haggled for in the last week, and far more than the Senate wanted. The $170 billion that senators had reserved for tax cuts was based on experts' predictions that a balanced budget could bolster the economy and produce a so-called fiscal dividend of that size; to reach $245 billion, legislators will have to find more economic benefits or cut spending further.</p>
        <p>As compensation, senators won the House's promise that no tax cuts would take effect until the Congressional Budget Office certified that spending reductions were locked in and sending the budget toward balance.</p>
        <p>As many as a dozen of the Senate's 54 Republicans, many of whom wanted no tax cut at all, had expressed grave doubts about supporting such a hefty package. But their resistance collapsed in recent days.</p>
        <p>The compromise on taxes promises to produce one unintended and unwanted effect: a crush of major political and fiscal decisions in late September, just as the fiscal year is ending and the budget battle between Mr. Clinton and the Republicans reaches its climax.</p>
        <p>Republicans had already elected to postpone enactment of major changes in the Medicare program until September, just before those changes will be folded into a vast package of spending and taxing proposals that is the core of the budget.</p>
        <p>But by requiring the Congressional Budget Office to certify that the budget has enough money to pay for a tax cut, Republican leaders have effectively postponed action on a tax package until September as well.</p>
        <p>The two sides agreed to reduce projected spending on the fast-growing Medicare program by $270 billion over seven years, about $8 billion less than the House had sought, but almost $25 billion more than the Senate wanted. Medicaid would lose $180 billion from projected spending through 2002, splitting the difference between the two proposals.</p>
        <p>The Senate also gave in to House demands to sharply cut spending on one of the more popular and politically sensitive Federal benefits: subsidized loans for college and graduate-school students.</p>
        <p>The House had proposed to cut $12.5 billion from the loan program by 2002, mostly by requiring students to assume the interest costs of loans during their years in school.</p>
        <p>The Senate had fought the House proposal, but in the agreement announced tonight, spending on student loans would fall $11 billion from current projections through 2002.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
