<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upheaval in the East: Rumors;   Whispered No Longer, Hearsay Jolts Bucharest</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="314178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUMANIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CEAUSESCU, NICOLAE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DD1E30F937A35752C0A966958260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upheaval in the East: Rumors;   Whispered No Longer, Hearsay Jolts Bucharest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</byline>
      <dateline>BUCHAREST, Rumania, Jan. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Rumors and conspiracy theories, once the spice of this Balkan city's romantic reputation, have crept back to life here, spreading old-fashioned intrigue through the hotel lobbies and coffee shops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Rumors and conspiracy theories, once the spice of this Balkan city's romantic reputation, have crept back to life here, spreading old-fashioned intrigue through the hotel lobbies and coffee shops.</p>
        <p>Rumors and conspiracy theories, once the spice of this Balkan city's romantic reputation, have crept back to life here, spreading old-fashioned intrigue through the hotel lobbies and coffee shops.</p>
        <p>Released from the enforced silence of the old Government, many people here are unhappy with the amount of information they are getting from the new provisional Government. A result is a heavy flow of unconfirmed facts and even wilder theories to animate Rumanians' suspicions.</p>
        <p>Today, at the first news conference by a ranking military official, the First Deputy Minister of Defense was asked whether 30,000 die-hard rebels had dug into a bunker in the Carpathian Mountains, and whether a fleet of getaway ships was waiting for them in the Black Sea. The official, Gen. Vasile Ionel, dismissed both reports as fanciful.</p>
        <p>Another Government spokesman was asked to comment this week on reports that the wife and children of the new Rumanian President, Ion Iliescu, had been killed. Those too were denied.</p>
        <p>Wave of Conspiracy Theories</p>
        <p>Many details of what happened during the fall of Nicolae Ceausescu's Government and the rise of the Council of National Salvation are still unclear, not surprisingly, given the level of emotion, fear and confusion here two weeks ago. But now, new, often elaborate conspiracy theories are added to the mix, of which the grandest holds that the new Government invented - even manufactured - the threat of a band of crazed and deadly Ceausescu loyalists to consolidate power.</p>
        <p>There are no facts to support such a theory, but they have taken on life in the absence of verifiable facts to support the Government's assertions. A week after the street fighting ended, the Government has still not produced documentation for its casualty figure of 60,000 or the number of captured guerrillas - leaving local and foreign observers to make their own guesses. More detailed accounts of the shootings now emerging suggest that a number of people were killed by nervous and poorly trained soldiers.</p>
        <p>The television and the press still operate as organs of the Council of National Salvation. As a result, many Rumanians still turn to foreign broadcasts for information and analysis unobtainable locally.</p>
        <p>Yet, as the revolution recedes in time, some memories seem to grow fresher. A young man today repeated word-for-word the conversation overheard on Dec. 22, the day Mr. Ceausescu fled, in which one general told another to call in the Cuban troops.</p>
        <p>Mythology Spread by Fear</p>
        <p>Even now, certainties linger that Arabs were among the renegade members of the Securitate who battled Government troops until last week.</p>
        <p>Like the rumor that the Securitate had poisoned the water supply in the western Rumanian city of Timisoara, some of the tales in circulation are part of the mythology, fed by fear, that enveloped the Ceausescu regime.</p>
        <p>Even now, as facts come out of once-secret files - maybe especially now -people are ready to believe the worst, like the report that Mr. Ceausescu had a deaf, mute one-armed bodyguard who was seen emptying his gun into a crowd.</p>
        <p>But already some of the suspicions are directed at the new Government, which is being closely watched for any signs of abusing the power it has inherited.</p>
        <p>Extended Holiday for Students</p>
        <p>Tonight, in the corridor of the Hotel Intercontinental, temporary headquarters for the foreign press and hence a magnet for people with theories and tips, a young woman blurted out the latest rumor, that the Government had set a Jan. 5 deadline for the registration of new parties. ''Maybe it hasn't been announced, but that doesn't mean it isn't true,'' she said with great urgency.</p>
        <p>Distrust is a legacy common to one-party states, and Rumania's long servitude under Mr. Ceausescu has made people particularly alert to the possibility of traitors in their midst.</p>
        <p>As they were complaining openly about the new Government to a member of the foreign press in the hotel lobby - once three sufficient reasons for arrest - a group of young men suddenly dropped their voices when a tall man walked by. ''We think he is from the Securitate,'' said one man. ''And that he is here spreading disinformation.''</p>
        <p>Today, after a three-day New Year's holiday - in which even the newspapers, with their new-found freedom, did not publish - people returned to work, jamming the subway and trolley cars. Because of their sacrifices during the revolution, university students were given another two weeks off.</p>
        <p>But flags with holes cut in the middle - where the symbol of the last 40 years of Communist rule has been removed - still fly on subway cars and rooftops, and by the small shrines lighted by candles that mark places where people were killed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
