<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sinister Tales From a Sleepy Town Grip France</title>
    <meta content="Y23FRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/23/international/europe/23FRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1499224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Toulouse Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transsexuals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Toulouse (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Noe (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Monde (French Newspaper)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baudis, Dominique</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alegre, Patrice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transsexuals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Languedoc-Roussillon/Toulouse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D6143BF930A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sinister Tales From a Sleepy Town Grip France</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sinister Tales From a Sleepy Town Grip France</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>TOULOUSE, France, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>All of France is spellbound by tales of rape and murder emanating from quiet city of Toulouse, where two unidentified prostitutes say that former Mayor Dominique Baudis joined in sadomasochistic orgies at lake house in nearby Noe and ordered murder of transvestite who secretly videotaped proceedings; Baudis denies charges and suggests that people he has alienated in pornography industry are out to detroy him, or that local newspaper is bent on revenge; detectives learned about prostitutes by questioning Patrice Alegre, psychopath who was sentenced to life in prison for five killings year ago; media frenzy surrounding story includes articles by staid daily Le Monde, which ran detailed but thinly sourced article with lurid charges for which there is no hard evidence; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever the truth, the tales of rape and murder emanating from this quiet city in southern France are impossible to ignore.</p>
        <p>Two prostitutes say that the former mayor joined in sadomasochistic orgies and that he ordered the murder of a transvestite who secretly videotaped it all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever the truth, the exotic tales of rape and murder emanating from a quiet city in southern France are impossible to ignore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whatever the truth, the tales of rape and murder emanating from this quiet city in southern France are impossible to ignore.</p>
        <p>Two prostitutes say that the former mayor joined in sadomasochistic orgies and that he ordered the murder of a transvestite who secretly videotaped it all.</p>
        <p>The former mayor denies the talk outright, and suggests that people he has alienated in the pornography industry are out to destroy him, or that a local newspaper is bent on revenge.</p>
        <p>With France spellbound, what may be the most remarkable aspect of the scandal is the alacrity with which the national news media have lent credence to the word of the two prostitutes, who have not been identified. The overgrown scope and exotic details of their story seem more fitting for a Gothic novel than a sleepy town.</p>
        <p>The undeniable facts are few, and involve a string of buried bodies, dating back about a decade ago. They proved to be the victims of a Toulouse psychopath named Patrice Alègre, who was sentenced to life in prison for five killings a year ago.</p>
        <p>A group of detectives, thinking that Mr. Alègre was responsible for more murders, continued to interrogate him and were periodically rewarded with tips about unsolved crimes. While investigating one of those crimes -- the 1992 murder of a woman in a seedy local hotel -- the police came across the prostitutes.</p>
        <p>They contend that Mr. Alègre acted as a pimp for a handful of municipal government officials, including the mayor at the time, Dominique Baudis, and an assistant prosecutor, Marc Bourrague. Both of them, the prostitutes say, engaged in sadomasochistic orgies at a lakeside house outside Toulouse. At least three women were killed during the sessions, the prostitutes say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alègre lent support to the prostitutes' allegations, saying that Mr. Baudis had ordered him to kill a transvestite who videotaped the orgies.</p>
        <p>According to the two prostitutes, Mr. Alègre strangled yet another prostitute to keep her from talking. Both prostitutes said they were present at that murder, at a Toulouse hotel in 1992. That makes them potentially liable for prosecution, possibly as accomplices, giving the women an incentive to concoct a story that deflects blame.</p>
        <p>As a measure of the media frenzy that surrounds the story, even the staid daily Le Monde ran a detailed but thinly sourced article contending that the new owner of the lake house stripped a bloodstained carpet from a room nicknamed ''the chapel,'' where the orgies are alleged to have taken place. The paper reported that the police found marks on the wall, and theorized that they were left by iron rings attached ''at the height of a child or of a person crouching or on all fours.'' It even reported that witnesses in nearby villages recalled hearing baroque music and cries from the house late at night and that the police were convinced that people sacrificed animals there.</p>
        <p>There is no hard evidence for any of this, and the house's new owner denounced the report the next day.</p>
        <p>The two prostitutes' versions of the story are themselves riddled with contradictions, but they include enough verifiable details that they cannot be dismissed without serious investigation. One of the prostitutes, for example, was able to draw a map of Toulouse's judicial building, correctly identifying, according to her lawyer, the office of the assistant prosecutor where she says sex acts took place.</p>
        <p>''It would have been impossible'' for her to know where that office was unless she had been there, said the lawyer, Georges Catala, in an interview here this week. He said his client also described a tattoo on the assistant prosecutor's shoulder. So far, the prosecutor is not talking.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor's lawyer, Laurent de Caunes, insisted in a interview that the prostitutes had reasons to invent their tale and that Mr. Alègre's allegations were the product of a diseased mind.</p>
        <p>''Alègre is a pervert who destroys life with pleasure,'' Mr. de Caunes said. ''And this has given him the means while in prison, where he has nothing else to do, to destroy more lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baudis was once a television personality and is Toulouse's most famous son. He was elected mayor when his father retired from the job in 1983 and he gave up the job in 2001. He was later appointed head of the national government's media watchdog organization, in Paris.</p>
        <p>Many people find it unlikely that a man so recognizable would risk indulging in bizarre group sex with the lower rungs of Toulouse society.</p>
        <p>But much of the French news media have argued that Mr. Baudis has not made a plausible defense. He tried to pre-empt the scandal by appearing on national television in May. He said he was innocent and suggested that unidentified people were conspiring to destroy him because of his efforts to restrict the late-night broadcast of pornography on television.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baudis' reputation was further shaken when a magazine published the transcript of a phone conversation, picked up by a police wiretap, between a Parisian madam and a suspected prostitute; in it, she said she saw Mr. Baudis regularly.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Baudis' defense appears forced, Mr. Alègre's allegations, and those of the prostitutes, seem doubtful. For one thing, Mr. Alègre initially denied the allegations and changed his story only after being confronted with the prostitutes' account several times.</p>
        <p>One of the prostitutes has now been arrested for arranging false testimony from another person.</p>
        <p>Toulouse Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
