<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Files of the Boston Archdiocese, a Problem Priest's Dossier</title>
    <meta content="Y06PRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/06/national/06PRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1446257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foley, James D (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDD133BF935A35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Files of the Boston Archdiocese, a Problem Priest's Dossier</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Files of the Boston Archdiocese, a Problem Priest's Dossier</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Dec. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Records released by lawyers suing Boston Archdiocese show that Rev James D Foley, who was ordained a Roman Catholic priest in 1960, had affairs with three women, at least two of them married and in their late teens; Foley fathered two children with one of women and was present when she overdosed; more than 30 years later, Foley, 69, remains a priest in archdiocese (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. James D. Foley broke his vow of celibacy soon after he was ordained a Roman Catholic priest in 1960. Church records say he had affairs with three women, at least two of them married and in their late teens.</p>
        <p>Father Foley fathered two children with one of the women and was present when she overdosed, according to records released today by lawyers suing the Boston Archdiocese in the case of a priest accused of molesting several boys. The records do not specify what the woman ingested, but they indicate Father Foley left her even though she had begun to faint. He returned to call 911, but the woman died.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOSTON, Dec. 5  The Rev. James D. Foley broke his vow of celibacy soon after he was ordained a Roman Catholic priest in 1960. Church records say he had affairs with three women, at least two of them married and intheir late teens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rev. James D. Foley broke his vow of celibacy soon after he was ordained a Roman Catholic priest in 1960. Church records say he had affairs with three women, at least two of them married and in their late teens.</p>
        <p>Father Foley fathered two children with one of the women and was present when she overdosed, according to records released today by lawyers suing the Boston Archdiocese in the case of a priest accused of molesting several boys. The records do not specify what the woman ingested, but they indicate Father Foley left her even though she had begun to faint. He returned to call 911, but the woman died.</p>
        <p>More than 30 years later, Father Foley, 69, remains a priest in the archdiocese. When church officials learned in 1993 of his possible connection to the woman's death, Father Foley was sent for treatment then returned to a restricted ministry at St. Joseph's Church in Salem, barred from one-on-one interaction with women. He is a member of the archdiocese's presbyteral council, a priests' panel which advises Cardinal Bernard F. Law.</p>
        <p>The Foley file, primarily memoranda and letters between archdiocesan officials, is part of some 12,000 pages of records on 65 priests that a state court ordered the archdiocese to turn over to lawyers in the lawsuit. The lawyers are trying to show a pattern of negligence in the way the archdiocese deals with priests accused of abuse or other crimes.</p>
        <p>One plaintiffs' lawyer, Roderick MacLeish Jr., said he was concerned that Father Foley was still in ministry. Today, the lawyers referred the case to the state attorney general and local law enforcement agencies. The attorney general's office said they would examine the records.</p>
        <p>A woman answering the phone at Father Foley's parish today referred all calls to the archdiocese. An archdiocesan spokeswoman did not return phone calls.</p>
        <p>In other files, Cardinal Law and his aides displayed a solicitous attitude toward priests accused of abuse, letting them remain in parishes without restriction. But in the Foley case, archdiocesan officials seemed to struggle more with how to deal with the priest.</p>
        <p>In 1994, the Rev. John B. McCormack, who is now bishop of Manchester, N.H., wrote about the Foley case that ''Cardinal Law thinks that this man should not be in pastoral ministry due to potential scandal. His remark is that this man should spend his life in a monastery doing penance.''</p>
        <p>The file contains records of Father Foley's affairs in the 1960's, but suggests that Cardinal Law's archdiocese became aware of them and the woman's death during a routine evaluation to see if Father Foley's parish assignment should be extended in 1993. Father Foley told archdiocesan officials about the death, according to one memo.</p>
        <p>Father Foley's records also show he had several psychiatric breakdowns in the 1960's and was briefly hospitalized. There are no allegations that he abused children.</p>
        <p>After sending Father Foley for treatment in 1994, archdiocese officials seemed to wrestle with his future.</p>
        <p>In May 1994, Father McCormack wrote that Father Foley was ''highly at risk.'' But a few months later, Father McCormack wrote that he believed Father Foley could serve in ministry ''if he increases his understanding of himself and is more able to manage his needs for intimacy and dependency.''</p>
        <p>The archdiocese first agreed to allow Father Foley to live in a rectory and celebrate Mass, then let him be an associate pastor with monitoring, therapy and the provision ''that he not enter any situation with women where there is the potential to be compromised.''</p>
        <p>Since then, the only record of a problem occurred in 1996, when, according to a memo, Father Foley was hospitalized after a ''psychotic episode'' in which he experienced ''delusions of grandeur''and ran red lights, ''thinking they were red only for other people.''</p>
        <p>In 1998, the archdiocese upheld his position as associate pastor, keeping the restrictions in place.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
