<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gabelli Settles Investor Suit for $100 Million</title>
    <meta content="05mario" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/05/business/05mario.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gabelli Group Capital Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabelli, Mario J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mancheski, Frederick J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlmutter, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D61E3FF936A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gabelli Settles Investor Suit for $100 Million</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gabelli Settles Investor Suit for $100 Million</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mario J Gabelli settles long-running legal battle with early investors Frederick J Mancheski and David M Perlmutter; agrees to pay more than $100 million; lawsuit claimed Gabelli prevented them from selling stake in Gabelli Group Capital Partners at fair market value; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mario J. Gabelli, the famed money manager, settled a long-running legal battle yesterday with his first investor, agreeing to pay him and another early investor more than $100 million.</p>
        <p>The settlement comes after years of back-and-forth about the value of the investment in Mr. Gabelli's mutual fund empire and after a barrage of accusations that he had looted the company and breached his fiduciary duty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mario J. Gabelli, the famed money manager, settled a long-running legal battle yesterday with his first investor, agreeing to pay him and another early investor more than $100 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mario J. Gabelli, the famed money manager, settled a long-running legal battle yesterday with his first investor, agreeing to pay him and another early investor more than $100 million.</p>
        <p>The settlement comes after years of back-and-forth about the value of the investment in Mr. Gabelli's mutual fund empire and after a barrage of accusations that he had looted the company and breached his fiduciary duty.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit had been brought by Frederick J. Mancheski, 79, who was Mr. Gabelli's first investor in 1976, and David M. Perlmutter, a former lawyer for Mr. Gabelli.</p>
        <p>Both men contended that Mr. Gabelli had prevented them from selling at fair market value their stake in his private company, Gabelli Group Capital Partners, the controlling shareholder of Gamco Investors, which is Mr. Gabelli's publicly traded mutual fund company.</p>
        <p>Throughout the fight, a spokesman for Mr. Gabelli had described the lawsuit as meritless and at one point called it ''tantamount to greenmail,'' suggesting that the men were trying to ''reap huge additional gains at the expense of the other shareholders.''</p>
        <p>But in late March, the judge in the case issued a partial summary judgment in favor of the two investors. The judge, Linda S. Jamieson of New York State Supreme Court in White Plains, also said, ''There are allegations made against Mr. Gabelli that trouble this court.''</p>
        <p>The settlement ends a nasty legal fight for Mr. Gabelli, who also faces problems in another case.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department announced in March that it would pursue civil fraud claims against Mr. Gabelli, arguing that he orchestrated a scheme to deceive the Federal Communications Commission in its auctions of wireless spectrum licenses several years ago. He has denied the accusations.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, Mr. Gabelli said that Mr. Mancheski and Mr. Perlmutter would receive about 2.1 million Gamco shares worth about $80 million, which would correspond with their stake in Gabelli Group Capital Partners.</p>
        <p>Additional cash compensation, worth more than $20 million, is also expected to be paid as part of the deal, though the details of that part of the settlement could not be learned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabelli had contended that the two men's shares were restricted and could be sold only back to the company at book value, which the two men suggested was an artificially depressed price, probably below $50 million.</p>
        <p>''We're pleased with the outcome of this matter, which resolves the issue in a way that allows us to move forward and directly aligns Mr. Mancheski's and Mr. Perlmutter's interests with those of Gamco,'' Mr. Gabelli said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mancheski said: ''I'm also very pleased to have reached this agreement. I hope to see further growth in the value of Gamco Investors as I become a major shareholder directly in Gamco Investors.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
