<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Momix's Relentless Quest to Laugh at the Logic of Gravity</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOMIX DANCE TROUPE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4DD133BF933A05751C1A962958260" item-length="410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Momix's Relentless Quest to Laugh at the Logic of Gravity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was golden oldie time for Momix on Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater (175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea), where the irrepressible group performs through Sunday afternoon. The well-staged program of 13 short pieces included some of the most beautiful-looking and funniest pieces created by Moses Pendleton, Cynthia Quinn and collaborators over the company's 13-year history. The selection also said a lot about Momix itself.</p>
        <p>The best of the classics is still Alan Boeding's oddly poignant "Circle Walker," a solo set to music by Yas Kaz, in which a man moves about the stage inside and beside an object that looks and behaves like a giant gyroscope. Propelled by the rolling sculpture, created by Mr. Boeding, Terry Pexton's body flipped and spiraled eerily through space in a slow-motion breakdown of Momix-style gymnastics, unaffected here by gravity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was golden oldie time for Momix on Wednesday night at the Joyce Theater (175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea), where the irrepressible group performs through Sunday afternoon. The well-staged program of 13 short pieces included some of the most beautiful-looking and funniest pieces created by Moses Pendleton, Cynthia Quinn and collaborators over the company's 13-year history. The selection also said a lot about Momix itself.</p>
        <p>The best of the classics is still Alan Boeding's oddly poignant "Circle Walker," a solo set to music by Yas Kaz, in which a man moves about the stage inside and beside an object that looks and behaves like a giant gyroscope. Propelled by the rolling sculpture, created by Mr. Boeding, Terry Pexton's body flipped and spiraled eerily through space in a slow-motion breakdown of Momix-style gymnastics, unaffected here by gravity.</p>
        <p>The sculpture briefly becomes a companion when Mr. Pexton beckons and it approaches. But man as heroic mover is the overall theme of the solo, a dance that would seem, like much of the Momix repertory, to be a natural for the 1996 Olympic Games in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>There is a similar poignancy to "White Widow." Ms. Quinn, who brings a much-needed warmth to the repertory, dangles and then sweeps across the stage hanging from a rope in the solo, to music by Julee Cruise. Her head is shorn, and her elbows, knees and flexed feet are much in evidence. This is not the graceful superwoman -- the impervious she-bird -- that one might expect.</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn's "When We're Alone," a ballroom duet for a live woman and a mannequin man, has all the delightfully jaundiced romance of Marianne Faithfull's singing of "Penthouse Serenade," to which the dance is set. It is also a fairly obvious and familiar one-line joke until the magical surprise ending, when the man spins atop the woman's raised arm.</p>
        <p>That obviousness is a problem for Momix, which too often gives in to its most sophomoric impulses in its humor and the play of shapes for which the company is known. Too many moments come perilously close to kitsch. There is a purity to the opening moments of "Brain Waving," when a rope stretched across the front of the stage "dances" with loopy, antic wit, wit that was missing from too much of the rest of the program. And Momix owes an uncomfortably large debt -- most evident in "Medusa" -- to Alwin Nikolais.</p>
        <p>The company also included Brian Sanders, Erin Elliott and Solveig Olsen.  DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
