<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'What Would You Do as Senator?'</title>
    <meta content="18TEXT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/18/nyregion/18text.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1620227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">O'grady, Marilyn F (Dr)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Howard D (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schumer, Charles E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mills, Howard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D6153AF93BA25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1191" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'What Would You Do as Senator?'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Excerpts from the Debate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from TV debate among Sen Charles E Schumer, State Assemblyman Howard Mills and Dr Marilyn F O'Grady (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the debate among candidates for a United States Senate seat in New York. The debate featured the incumbent, Charles E. Schumer, a Democrat; State Assemblyman Howard Mills, the Republican candidate, and Dr. Marilyn F. O'Grady, the Conservative Party candidate. The moderator was Bill Ritter of WABC-TV Channel 7.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- I want to be specific now with all three of you. Are we doing enough to protect this city? Do we have enough money to do it? And what would you do as senator? ...</p>
        <p>MR. MILLS -- The issue gets to one of the critical issues in this campaign, and that is the effectiveness of the incumbent. Senator Schumer has just demonstrated what he's very good at: talking about problems, outlining issues. What he's not good at is effective delivering for New York. It's a fact that right now New York ranks below Wyoming on a per capita basis in homeland security monies. It is the job of the Congress to get the monies for New York. The senator has tried to blame the Bush administration. It is the Congress that appropriates the money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the debate among candidates for a United States Senate seat in New York. The debate featured the incumbent, Charles E. Schumer, a Democrat; State Assemblyman Howard Mills, the Republican candidate, and Dr. Marilyn F. O'Grady, the Conservative Party candidate. The moderator was Bill Ritter of WABC-TV Channel 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the debate among candidates for a United States Senate seat in New York. The debate featured the incumbent, Charles E. Schumer, a Democrat; State Assemblyman Howard Mills, the Republican candidate, and Dr. Marilyn F. O'Grady, the Conservative Party candidate. The moderator was Bill Ritter of WABC-TV Channel 7.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- I want to be specific now with all three of you. Are we doing enough to protect this city? Do we have enough money to do it? And what would you do as senator? ...</p>
        <p>MR. MILLS -- The issue gets to one of the critical issues in this campaign, and that is the effectiveness of the incumbent. Senator Schumer has just demonstrated what he's very good at: talking about problems, outlining issues. What he's not good at is effective delivering for New York. It's a fact that right now New York ranks below Wyoming on a per capita basis in homeland security monies. It is the job of the Congress to get the monies for New York. The senator has tried to blame the Bush administration. It is the Congress that appropriates the money.</p>
        <p>And I think that Senator Schumer should explain why it is that as the senior United States senator, he has allowed us to rank below Wyoming on a per capita basis. All homeland security monies should be allocated on a risk-assessment basis. Period. It should not be normal pork-barrel spending as usual. And we need a senator who can effectively deliver the monies for New York. We're not getting enough. And it is the responsibility of the senator of the State of New York to get that done for the people of New York.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Senator Schumer, do you want to respond to that?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- The bottom line is that we do need a better allocation. We've worked hard. And in fact, just in this last homeland security bill, Senator Clinton and I got a fund past the Senate, Democrats and Republicans, that would give New York a very fair share. In the earlier days, the first year, we got a good share. Second and third it slipped, mainly because the administration was not fighting for us. But I'll tell you, we're going to get those funding back.</p>
        <p>And one other point, getting 20 billion [dollars] for New York City, that was a huge undertaking. If we do better in the homeland security we'll get about 200 million a year. It would take a hundred years to equal the 20 billion. ...</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- President Bush, who is something of a state's rights advocate, has proposed a federal constitutional amendment calling for a ban on same-sex marriages. If you're re-elected, would you support or oppose such an amendment? And why?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- I've already opposed such amendment and let me tell you why. First, I am against -- I believe that marriage should be between a man and a woman. That's my personal belief. That is the belief that I think every church, synagogue, mosque, any other religious institution should not be forced by the state to decide who should be married. It should be up to them. And so I voted, for instance, for DOMA, which is called the Defense of Marriage Act, which said that one state didn't have to recognize another state.</p>
        <p>But I also believe ... that the rights that the state gives should be neutral on this issue. So for instance, if a same-sex couple wanted hospital visitation rights, I'd be for that. If a same-sex couple wanted to file a tax return or have a will, I'd be for that. That's called civil unions. And while I'm against gay marriage, I believe that we should have civil unions. ...</p>
        <p>MR. MILLS -- I actually agree with Senator Schumer largely on this issue. I do support the federal Defense of Marriage Act. I do believe that marriage is between a man and a woman and that it should be kept that way. And I would fight to keep it that way. It is a critical cultural, religious concept in our society. I do support civil unions, and I do support equal rights minus the use of marriage for same-sex couples.</p>
        <p>This is an issue that really highlights why I am being criticized by some in this campaign. My opponent, Mrs. O'Grady, is really in this race for really only two reasons. No. 1, that I support a woman's right to choose. And No. 2, that I do support same-sex couples having rights, minus the right of marriage. But I do agree that the Defense of Marriage Act was good legislation. I would support it. Marriage is between a man and a woman. And I will do everything that I can as a United States senator to keep the law that way. But we do have to express tolerance and support for same-sex couples as well.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Thank you, assemblyman. Dr. O'Grady?</p>
        <p>DR. O'GRADY -- Well, I support the concept of a constitutional amendment to define marriage as between a man and a woman. I think this is the proper way to do this. I don't -- Senator Schumer wants to circumvent the legislative process. And that by doing a constitutional amendment, that would be a legislative -- allowing the people to decide this issue. ...</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- These are yes and no questions. There's no time limit except that it's yes or no. My questions will be much longer than the answers. In the city of New York there is a huge debate right now over whether to build a stadium on the West Side of Manhattan for the New York Jets. Do you favor or oppose -- I shouldn't say that, it's yes or no -- do you favor building such a facility? Dr. O'Grady?</p>
        <p>DR. O'GRADY -- No.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Senator Schumer?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- I think we have to do other things first. A lot of these questions can't be answered ----</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Is that a no or a yes?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- Yes or no. That is, build the No. 7 line first.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Hold on. Yes or no?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- Build the No. 7 line first.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Assemblyman Mills?</p>
        <p>MR. MILLS -- Yes, I do.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- All right, thank you. If you are elected or re-elected in November, do you plan to serve a full term? Dr. O'Grady?</p>
        <p>DR. O'GRADY -- Yes.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Senator Schumer?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- I love being senator. I intend ----</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Is that a yes or a no?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- The only thing on my radar screen is to be a good senator.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Is that a yes or no?</p>
        <p>MR. SCHUMER -- But I never say never.</p>
        <p>MR. RITTER -- Assemblyman Mills?</p>
        <p>MR. MILLS -- Yes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
