<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Internet advertisers face a new enemy: people who click on ads with no intention of buying.</title>
    <meta content="18NEWC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/18/technology/18newcon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041019T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1620191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="New Economy"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeller, Tom Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Internet Advertising Bureau</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D8153AF93BA25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Internet advertisers face a new enemy: people who click on ads with no intention of buying.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Each Technology Advance, a Scourge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Zeller Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeller, Tom Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet advertisers face click fraud, in which scam artists, automated scripts and even underhanded competitors click on their ads with no intention of buying, running up fees advertisers pay to host sites; it is nearly impossible to pin down precisely how widespread click fraud has become; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF there is any single axiom of the digital age, it must be this: for every advance, there is a scourge.</p>
        <p>E-mail has spam. The Web has pop-up windows and spyware. Even the market infant, Internet telephony, has analysts bracing for an onslaught of what is been called ''Spam Over Internet Telephony,'' (or ''spit,'' of course).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Internet advertisers face a new enemy: people who click on ads with no intention of buying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF there is any single axiom of the digital age, it must be this: for every advance, there is a scourge.</p>
        <p>E-mail has spam. The Web has pop-up windows and spyware. Even the market infant, Internet telephony, has analysts bracing for an onslaught of what is been called ''Spam Over Internet Telephony,'' (or ''spit,'' of course).</p>
        <p>It should come as no surprise, then -- and some might say it is a bit of poetic justice -- that online advertisers are becoming acquainted with their own special plague: click fraud.</p>
        <p>The variations are many, but it essentially works like this: merchants typically pay a fee to the sites that play host to their ads whenever those ads are clicked by a visitor.</p>
        <p>In an ideal world, the visitor, now transported to the advertiser's Web site, hangs out for a spell, examines the wares and eventually makes a purchase. In click fraud, those clicks that the advertiser is paying for are not coming from potential customers, but from scam artists, automated scripts, and even underhanded competitors.</p>
        <p>''It's really any click initiated on a cost-per-click ad that is made without there being a possibility of a legitimate site-visit or a transaction to occur,'' said Jessie C. Stricchiola, the president of Alchemist Media, a California company that helps advertisers recoup cash lost to the practice. ''It's a really serious problem for the advertisers it affects.''</p>
        <p>It is nearly impossible to pin down precisely how widespread click fraud has become. John Squire, the vice president for product marketing for Coremetrics, which provides consulting and Web analysis for online merchants like Eddie Bauer, OfficeMax and CompUSA, estimated that his company's clients are spending approximately $10 million a year on fraudulent clicks. That is, they are spending about $10 million on consumers that don't exist.</p>
        <p>Other companies -- usually ones that are feverishly peddling their own solutions to the problem -- say that as much as 50 percent of cost-per-click advertising dollars are spent on fraudulent clicks.</p>
        <p>The practice has been around for years, but it is gaining wider attention as the online advertising market continues to grow rapidly. According to a survey released last month by the Internet Advertising Bureau and PricewaterhouseCoopers, online advertising revenues in the United States have been growing steadily over the last two years, and now stand at $2.4 billion.</p>
        <p>And given the advent of affiliate programs from companies like Google and Yahoo, with its Overture Services, the opportunities to engage in click fraud have become even more widely dispersed.</p>
        <p>Affiliate arrangements allow third-party Web sites to display context-sensitive advertisements pushed to them by the larger players. When visitors click those ads, the third-party site gets a share in the revenues.</p>
        <p>It didn't take long, then, for shady affiliates to figure out that artificially driving up the click rate on those ads could enhance the commission checks that are doled out to them by their patron networks.</p>
        <p>The Times of India reported last spring that a growing number of housewives, college students and other people in need of some extra cash were being hired in New Delhi to sit in front of a computer and click on advertisements.</p>
        <p>Other rings of phantom clickers have been reported in China, Nigeria and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more often, sneaky affiliates will deploy scripts or software that will robotically click the ads, mimicking visitors and scooping up revenues.</p>
        <p>One offshore Web site peddling false-click software reminds small Web publishers that the big companies command lots of advertising dollars because their sites have millions of visitors.</p>
        <p>''But what if your site doesn't have that traffic?'' the company asks. The solution: Use their program to ''simulate that traffic.'' The advertiser, the site's owners say, will think you're ''a hell of a Webmaster!''</p>
        <p>Most striking of all, perhaps, is the third variety of click fraud, in which overheated merchants click on a competitor's ads as a way of devaluing the competitor's campaign and depleting the rival's advertising accounts.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes it just makes people feel good to know they're costing their competitors money,'' Ms. Stricchiola said.</p>
        <p>Each click, after all, has a price.</p>
        <p>''And therein lies a very large flaw'' in the cost-per-click model, Ms. Stricchiola said. ''It shouldn't happen and the fact that that it is happening is wrong,'' she said, adding that it is only a matter of time before the practice, which appears to occupy murky legal territory with little or no specific regulatory language addressing it, ends up in court.</p>
        <p>The largest networks -- Yahoo's Overture, Google, FindWhat.com -- are understandably cautious not to overstate the extent of click fraud. But they all deploy fairly sophisticated tactics to combat the practice. Watchdog programs monitor the incoming clicks and sniff out unusual activity -- sudden spikes, for instance, or repeated clicks from the same location. And each has a staff dedicated solely to detecting and rooting out click fraud before it hollows out their business model.</p>
        <p>''Click fraud has been something that we have faced since the beginning,'' said Salar Kamangar, the director of product management at Google. ''It's an ongoing issue.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Google thought the problem serious enough to mention in a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission this year before the company's initial public offering.</p>
        <p>''We are exposed to the risk of fraudulent clicks on our ads,'' the document said. ''We have regularly paid refunds related to fraudulent clicks and expect to do so in the future. If we are unable to stop this fraudulent activity, these refunds may increase.''</p>
        <p>It is unlikely that the boom in online advertising could be stalled solely by click fraud, experts say, but the race between cheaters and the cheated in the pay-per-click universe is almost certain to continue.</p>
        <p>The histories of spam, spyware and, one presumes, spit, show that new mutations and workarounds tend to evolve quickly, requiring new monitoring techniques to catch them.</p>
        <p>''As with anything electronic, the perpetrators get a little more crafty as time moves along,'' said Karen Yagnesak, a spokeswoman for FindWhat.com. ''We try to stay a few steps ahead of them.''</p>
        <p>New Economy</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 19, 2004, Tuesday  The New Economy column in Business Day yesterday, about online merchants who pay excessive cost-per-click fees to sites because of fraud artists, automated scripts or underhanded rivals, referred imprecisely to advertising revenues in a survey by the Internet Advertising Bureau and PricewaterhouseCooper. The figure for the first six months of 2004 was $4.6 billion; the $2.4 billion figure was for the second quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 19, 2004, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The New Economy column in Business Day yesterday, about online merchants who pay excessive cost-per-click fees to sites because of fraud artists, automated scripts or underhanded rivals, referred imprecisely to advertising revenues in a survey by the Internet Advertising Bureau and PricewaterhouseCooper. The figure for the first six months of 2004 was $4.6 billion; the $2.4 billion figure was for the second quarter.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
