<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hot-Shooting Sales Scores 46 for UConn</title>
    <meta content="22WOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES: WOMEN'S BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Connecticut</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D7143EF931A15751C1A961958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hot-Shooting Sales Scores 46 for UConn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>LAKELAND, Fla., Dec. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut defeats Stanford, 94-78, in women's college basketball; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Connecticut 94, Stanford 78</p>
        <p>One number jumped out at Nykesha Sales today as she peered at a sheet of statistics. ''I can't believe I took 27 shots,'' said Sales, a University of Connecticut guard, smiling sheepishly.</p>
        <p>Another number jumped out at everyone else. Sales scored a school-record 46 points -- the most by a Division I women's player this season -- as the Huskies wore down Stanford, 94-78, in the Elite 4 Holiday Classic at the Lakeland Civic Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Connecticut 94, Stanford 78</p>
        <p>One number jumped out at Nykesha Sales today as she peered at a sheet of statistics. ''I can't believe I took 27 shots,'' said Sales, a University of Connecticut guard, smiling sheepishly.</p>
        <p>Another number jumped out at everyone else. Sales scored a school-record 46 points -- the most by a Division I women's player this season -- as the Huskies wore down Stanford, 94-78, in the Elite 4 Holiday Classic at the Lakeland Civic Center.</p>
        <p>The victory, in a matchup of the two women's programs with the most victories over the last three seasons, left Connecticut, ranked third in the Associated Press poll of reporters, at 10-0, and No. 12 Stanford at 2-4.</p>
        <p>Sales made 18 shots, including a career-high 6 3-pointers, and 4 of 6 free throws in eclipsing Kerry Bascom's school record of 39 points.</p>
        <p>''I think she was trying out for the circus with some of those shots,'' Stanford Coach Tara VanDerveer said. ''The basket was big for her today. She took over the game.''</p>
        <p>One of Sales's baskets came when she unintentionally banked the ball off the backboard on a spin move. That pulled Connecticut into a 58-58 tie early in the second half.</p>
        <p>''I knew when she made that, it was her day,'' said Huskies guard Rita Williams, who contributed 6 timely steals and 14 points. ''I felt she had a game like this in her. I'd been waiting for it to come out.''</p>
        <p>Sales, a senior who is a candidate for the United States national team, scored 19 points in the first half. Stanford, meanwhile, went ahead by 30-19 and, behind center Heather Owen's 11 points, held on for a 44-42 halftime lead.</p>
        <p>But Sales, who recently overcame mononucleosis, became almost unstoppable in the second half. She sank 10 of her 12 shots after the intermission, including one long fadeaway that ended with her on the floor, smiling incredulously.</p>
        <p>Sales searched hard for words in trying to explain her game.</p>
        <p>''I never really shot that many times,'' she said. ''I guess something good is going to happen if you shoot that much and you're making a lot of them. I just know I shot a lot more jump shots than usual.''</p>
        <p>UConn Coach Geno Auriemma said he had seen Sales take flurries of shots before because she could think of nothing else to do, and she had not been happy about it.</p>
        <p>''But today, the look on her face was one of confidence,'' Auriemma said. ''That told me we should run more stuff for her, and we did. Of her 27 shots, on 23 or 24 she did exactly what she wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Sales scored 11 straight points and 20 of her team's 25 points during a crucial part in the second half, as the Huskies took charge. From 64-64 with about 10 minutes left, it was mostly all UConn.</p>
        <p>A 3-pointer by Amy Duran broke the deadlock and Sales produced the next 7 points as the Huskies' bulge grew to 8.</p>
        <p>Still, all is not perfect with the Huskies. Their sophomore starting center, Paige Sauer, fouled out of the game with 18 minutes left. She was a nonfactor, with 2 points and no rebounds, and Auriemma fretted that she was pressing to be an adequate replacement for the all-American Kara Wolters, now a professional player.</p>
        <p>''I told her afterward, 'We showed here we can win without you,' '' Auriemma said. ''I said, 'So just go out and play your game. Don't worry about being a star. We have enough stars.' ''</p>
        <p>Particularly one named Nykesha Sales.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES: WOMEN'S BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
