<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Black Brother-Sister Duo Pursue Olympics</title>
    <meta content="17SKII$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1177201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SKI REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alpine Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lloyd, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horton, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horton, Suki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alpine Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4D61031F934A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Black Brother-Sister Duo Pursue Olympics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lloyd, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles black US skiers Andre Horton and his sister Suki; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Almost any time he's skiing -- on any slope anywhere -- the Alaskan downhiller Andre Horton seldom sees another black person on the mountain. If he does, that other skier is probably the only other African- American besides himself out there that day. Despite years of ski racing, the realization still gives Horton pause.</p>
        <p>''I think, that guy must be lonely,'' Horton said in a recent telephone interview. ''I see him, and I think he must be the only one there. But then, sometimes I'm the only one there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Almost any time he's skiing -- on any slope anywhere -- the Alaskan downhiller Andre Horton seldom sees another black person on the mountain. If he does, that other skier is probably the only other African- American besides himself out there that day. Despite years of ski racing, the realization still gives Horton pause.</p>
        <p>''I think, that guy must be lonely,'' Horton said in a recent telephone interview. ''I see him, and I think he must be the only one there. But then, sometimes I'm the only one there.''</p>
        <p>Rather than letting the numbers bother him, however, Horton turns reality around. ''It's the position I've been given,'' he said about his ski-racing career. ''It's a strong position to be in, because I know I can have a big impact on others.''</p>
        <p>The 20-year-old Horton, and his 17-year-old sister, Suki, are primed to become the first African-Americans on the United States Ski and Snowboard Team. But for both athletes, who grew up near ski slopes in Anchorage and are the children of two schoolteachers -- Elsena, an expert downhill skier who is white, and Garry, who is black -- the dream is still at least a season away.</p>
        <p>Both Andre and Suki are being nudged in that direction with financial and moral support from the National Brotherhood of Skiers. With a membership of 14,000, the brotherhood is the largest skier organization in the country for African-Americans. As for how many black skiers there are in the United States, no one knows. But the number is apt to be a fraction of the country's estimated 15 million skiers.</p>
        <p>Schone Malliet, the Hortons' ski coach and a member of the brotherhood, has a theory about that. ''While the number of skier visits is flat over all in the industry,'' Malliet said, ''the number of African-Americans probably is increasing because the discretionary income of blacks is increasing.''</p>
        <p>To underscore the brotherhood's intention to prepare a skier for world-class competition, the Hortons are attending the brotherhood's racefest this week. Billed as the Pontiac-GMC Annual Meeting Challenge Cup 2000, the event at Copper Mountain, Colo., brings members together for 11 days of racing and slopeside entertainment.</p>
        <p>For Suki Horton, an appearance there is no small task. Last Dec. 10, she injured a knee while skiing at Jackson Hole, Wyo. Surgery and a rehabilitation schedule means she will not be able to ski again this season. But she's showing up at Copper anyway.</p>
        <p>It was a blow to the young Suki, who at 15, was the first black to make the skiing ans snowboarding development team, the precursor to full ski team entitlement. It was a milestone that gave her as good a chance as anyone to become the first black Olympic skier from the United States.</p>
        <p>And so why is it that no African- Americans have made the ski team? ''TV really influences us,'' Suki said. ''Yet kids in the city never even see skiing. Beyond that, not many blacks are living in resort areas because they don't want to be that one black skiing down the mountain. But it has to start somewhere.''</p>
        <p>Getting a black American on the United States Ski Team may be on the horizon. But how soon it comes about is another question. Skier rankings are important, but so far, neither of the Hortons have enough points to make the grade.</p>
        <p>''We've worked with the National Brotherhood, and we're trying to move that along,'' Tom Kelly, spokesman for the skiing and snowboarding group in Park City, Utah, said recently. ''A number of skiers have come close. Andre and Suki are particularly notable, and we hope that will happen.''</p>
        <p>Andre is racing with a Western regional team this year. Last month, he was first and second in two downhill races at the Doug Smith Memorial in Big Mountain, Mont. He figures that if he can be among the top five in at least three events this season in the Super Series, part of the North American circuit, he can qualify for the United States Development Team next year.</p>
        <p>''If I make the national team, hopefully it will be with a low profile,'' he said. ''It wouldn't be like being a Tiger Woods with all the national attention. But I would like to be a role model. I'm up for the task, even though I know it won't be easy.''</p>
        <p>MOGULS</p>
        <p>The summer version of the Goodwill Games has turned into a winter one with the first event beginning today at Lake Placid, N.Y. More than 400 athletes from 22 countries will compete in the four-day series, which includes Alpine, cross-country and freestyle skiing events, plus jumping and Nordic combined. Other Olympic-class disciplines include snowboarding, luge, speedskating, figure skating and bobsled.</p>
        <p>THE SKI REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
