<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD81F3CF93BA35751C0A964958260" item-length="361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball</p>
        <p>COMMISSIONER'S OFFICE -- Suspended Gilberto Reyes, Montreal Expos catcher, for 60 days for violating his aftercare program and baseball's drug policy. American League</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball</p>
        <p>COMMISSIONER'S OFFICE -- Suspended Gilberto Reyes, Montreal Expos catcher, for 60 days for violating his aftercare program and baseball's drug policy. American League</p>
        <p>BOSTON RED SOX -- Agreed to terms with Luis Rivera, shortstop, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Agreed to terms with Jerry Browne, second baseman, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK YANKEES -- Agreed to terms with Greg Cadaret, pitcher, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND ATHLETICS -- Agreed to terms with Mike Moore, pitcher, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Agreed to terms with Roberto Alomar, second baseman, on a three-year contract, and David Wells, pitcher, and Manuel Lee, infielder, on one-year contracts. National League</p>
        <p>CHICAGO CUBS -- Agreed to terms with Mark Grace, first baseman, to a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI REDS -- Agreed to terms with Chris Sabo, third baseman, on a one-year contract, and Ted Power, pitcher, on a minor-league contract.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES DODGERS -- Agreed to terms with Juan Samuel, infielder, on a one-year contract. Football  Arena Football</p>
        <p>AFL -- Announced that New York City has been awarded an expansion franchise for the 1993 season. Professional Spring Football League</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON MARAUDERS -- Named Daniel Lounsbury offensive coordinator; Angelo Ortiz equipment manager; John McGuire video director; Adam Gold director of sales; and Lisa Neely marketing assistant. Claimed Randell Holmes, linebacker, off waivers from the Arkansas Miners. World League of American Football  OHIO GLORY -- Named Joe Viadella running backs coach and Barry Pettyjohn and Mike Dunlevy intern coaches.</p>
        <p>SACRAMENTO SURGE -- Named Bob Moran wide receivers coach and Jim Miblack assistant coach. Hockey  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>BOSTON BRUINS -- Traded Craig Janney, center, and Stephane Quintal, defenseman, to the St. Louis Blues for Adam Oates, center.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA FLYERS -- Traded Tony Horacek, left wing, to the Chicago Blackhawks for Ryan McGill, defenseman.</p>
        <p>SAN JOSE SHARKS -- Traded Tony Hrkac, center, to the Chicago Blackhawks for a conditional selection in the 1993 entry draft.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
