<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="11FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1407391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DF1330F932A25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Retreats on Demands For Immunity in War Court  The Bush administration, criticized for demanding immunity for American peacekeepers from the new International Criminal Court, proposed a compromise that would exempt its troops and officials for one year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Retreats on Demands For Immunity in War Court  The Bush administration, criticized for demanding immunity for American peacekeepers from the new International Criminal Court, proposed a compromise that would exempt its troops and officials for one year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Quarreling Over 9/11 Clues  American officials say the German police and intelligence agencies missed signals about the Sept. 11 attacks, failed to push to unravel the plot and, more recently, refused to arrest men suspected of being accomplices of the conspirators. German officials say the Americans withheld information from them then, and sometimes still do.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>U.S. Faults Israel on Closure  The White House criticized Israel for shutting down the East Jerusalem office of Sari Nusseibeh, a moderate Palestinian leader who has urged a halt to suicide bombings.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Britain Eases Pot Law  The government Britain said it would relax laws on marijuana, keeping the drug illegal but making private use in small amounts no longer subject to arrest.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Coca Spraying Plan Imperiled  An American law enacted in January threatens to disrupt a Bush administration strategy, and possibly even halt, to increase the aerial spraying of drug crops in Colombia with herbicides. A provision in the law requires that the program to eradicate coca crops in Colombia must meet the same standards that would apply if the herbicides were being sprayed in the United States.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Europe to Tackle Subsidies  The European Commission approved proposals to overhaul a system of farm subsidies that make up almost half of its budget, but the plan faces strong opposition from France, the system's leading beneficiary.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Argentina Orders Arrests  A judge ordered the arrest of Gen. Leopoldo Galtieri, Argentina's former military dictator, and more than 30 other military officers accused of ordering or participating in the kidnapping, torture and execution of members of a left-wing rebel force during the ''dirty war'' in Argentina more than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-21</p>
        <p>Pilots Should Be Armed, The House Votes Decisively  The House voted, 310 to 113, to let airline pilots carry guns in their cockpits, a move that the new Transportation Security Administration said six weeks ago it would not allow. The idea of arming pilots faces opposition in the Senate, though a proposal similar to the House bill has gained some support there.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Congress began shaping a Homeland Security Department substantially different from the Bush plan's.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>The government has managed to deport most of the Sept. 11 detainees at the center of lawsuits challenging the secret detention policy.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>A State Department inquiry found that 71 people got fraudulent visas from the United States Embassy in Qatar in 2000 and 2001, in some cases for bribes of more than $10,000.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Colon Cancer Bill Advances  A Senate panel voted to require all private health insurance plans in the United States to pay for screening tests to detect colon cancer in people who are 50 or older or have a high risk of developing the disease.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Aid to Black Farmers Sought  The Congressional Black Caucus demanded that the secretary of agriculture do more to promote the civil rights of black farmers and ensure that they receive agriculture loans as easily as other farmers.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Reassessing the 'Digital Divide'  A coalition of civil rights and policy groups challenged a Commerce Department finding that two programs intended to help narrow the gap between people who do and do not have access to computers and Internet technology should be dropped. The groups said a study re-examining the data Commerce used showed that while there was some narrowing, ''significant divides still exist'' along income, racial and geographic lines.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>No Change in Cost Overruns  Cost overruns for large public works projects remained mostly constant for most of the last century, a study in the Journal of the American Planning Association said.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Georgia Ex-Sheriff Guilty  Sidney Dorsey, 62, was convicted of masterminding the murder of his successor, who was gunned down after winning election on a promise to rid the department of corruption.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Giuliani Divorce Feud Ends Just as Trial Begins  The divorce case of former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Donna Hanover ended with an out-of-court settlement in which Ms. Hanover, a television personality and actress, will get $6.8 million tax free and custody of the couple's two children.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>9/11 Tapes Finally Played  Fire officials were allowed to listen to radio transmissions among firefighters at the trade center, but only after first signing an agreement with federal prosecutors not to discuss their contents publicly. The tapes may be used as evidence at the conspiracy trial of Zacarias Moussaoui.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-8</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Reading Scores Fall Sharply  The proportion of New York State middle-school students passing the state's reading and writing test dropped well below the passing levels of four years ago, except in affluent suburban school districts.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Earliest Trace of Human Origins  French scientists in central Africa have uncovered a seven-million-year-old skull of the earliest known member of the human family.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Knee Surgery's Value Doubted  Arthroscopic surgery for pain and stiffness from osteoarthritis worked no better than a procedure in which surgeons pretended to operate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Recommendations on Cloning  President Bush's bioethics advisers said a four-year moratorium would allow for more public debate.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Sunken PT 109 Is Found  Robert D. Ballard said he had located John F. Kennedy's wartime boat.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-13</p>
        <p>Tougher Corporate Penalties  The Senate endorsed broad criminal penalties for corporate officers who cheat investors or harm employee pensions. The House has passed a bill that carries no criminal penalties.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Sets Loan Conditions  The government gave conditional support to a $900 million loan guarantee that US Airways is seeking for $1 billion in private financing. The guarantee is the second granted to a carrier since Sept. 11, and it is the largest.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The Bear Market Worsens  The S.&amp; P. 500 and the Nasdaq sunk to their lowest levels since 1997. The S.&amp; P. 500 fell 32.36 points, or 3.4 percent, to 920.47; the Dow plunged 282.59 points, or 3.11, to 8,813.50; and the Nasdaq lost 35.11 points, or 2.54 percent, to 1,346.01.</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>$76.7 Million for a Rubens  A recently rediscovered Rubens was sold at Sotheby's in London for the third-highest price for a painting at auction and the highest auction price ever for an old master painting.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Hormone therapy woes; the wrong target; freezing time.  Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
