<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Begonias and Beyond: A Voice For the Tropical Forests</title>
    <meta content="04CONV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/04/science/earth/04CONV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1397671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A CONVERSATION WITH: RUTH KIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Tropical Botanical Gardens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiew, Ruth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreifus, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Conversations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D9133AF937A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Begonias and Beyond: A Voice For the Tropical Forests</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Begonias and Beyond: A Voice for the Tropical Forests</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA DREIFUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dreifus, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Ruth Kiew of Singapore Botanic Gardens and expert on tropical begonias who is in US to speak on fate of South Asia's endangered tropical forests and to accept David Fairchild Medal for Plant Exploration from National Tropical Botanical Gardens; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The soft-spoken woman shaking off a monumental case of jet lag at a Manhattan apartment one recent morning was Dr. Ruth Kiew, 56, the keeper of the herbarium and library of the Singapore Botanic Gardens, and one of the world's great experts on tropical begonias.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kiew had traveled to the United States to speak on the fate of South Asia's endangered tropical forests and also to accept the botanic equivalent of the Nobel Prize: the David Fairchild Medal for Plant Exploration from the National Tropical Botanical Gardens, an American group dedicated to plant preservation and discovery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Ruth Kiew discusses her expeditions in Borneo and her passion for the begonia. And she warns too many species are being lost before they are even found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The soft-spoken woman shaking off a monumental case of jet lag at a Manhattan apartment one recent morning was Dr. Ruth Kiew, 56, the keeper of the herbarium and library of the Singapore Botanic Gardens, and one of the world's great experts on tropical begonias.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kiew had traveled to the United States to speak on the fate of South Asia's endangered tropical forests and also to accept the botanic equivalent of the Nobel Prize: the David Fairchild Medal for Plant Exploration from the National Tropical Botanical Gardens, an American group dedicated to plant preservation and discovery.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kiew (pronounced cue) was being honored in part for her many explorations into remote areas of Malaysia, where she searched for new species of begonias and African violets. While rain and mud and leeches had never deterred her, Ruth Kiew, at first glance, seemed somewhat overwhelmed by the rigors of her trip from Singapore.</p>
        <p>''People always say that the jet lag from Asia to North America is serious,'' she said in an accent of her native Britain, ''but this was formidable!''</p>
        <p>Over coffee, Dr. Kiew regained her equilibrium and chatted about the plants and flowers that are her passion.</p>
        <p>Q. Martin Wells, the British zoologist, once said that his area of study had become obsolete because most biology students were so focused on cells and proteins that they couldn't recognize a whole animal if they encountered one. Is there a similar problem in botany?</p>
        <p>A. It's a problem at European universities. Not so much in the tropics. At European universities, the cutting edge tends to be more in the laboratory and on the technical side, more into molecular biology. At the same time there, my specialty, taxonomy, has come to be considered very old-fashioned. What a taxonomist does is to classify and name new species. Somehow, there's the impression that taxonomy is an old subject, that there's nothing interesting there to do anymore. Yet in the developing part of the world, there aren't enough trained taxonomists to identify all the plants we are discovering. As you know, we don't yet have an inventory of all the species.</p>
        <p>Q. Why is taxonomy an important part of getting an inventory of all the world's species?</p>
        <p>A. Because the scientific name is the key to everything we know about a plant. It's like databasing. After you find something, you just go into your computer, call up that name, and everything that's known about it will appear. But if you've got a plant and you don't know its name, there's absolutely no knowledge about it at all. Even a geneticist or a microbiologist needs to know the name.</p>
        <p>So the importance of taxonomists is that they can put the correct name to the right plant. And as I say, there aren't enough taxonomists. At the moment, people can still manage. There are still enough taxonomists over age 50 working. But when these pass on, there won't be enough young people coming up.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you fall into this un-chic profession of naming plants?</p>
        <p>A. I had a very inspirational lecturer when I was at Cambridge, E. J. H. Corner, who had developed a theory to explain how this tremendous diversity of plants evolved in the tropics. Also, I come from a scientific family. My father was a botanist; my mother, a biology teacher. My mother encountered quite a lot of prejudice when she was a student at Cambridge. In the 1930's, women couldn't get a full degree there. They could only be ''affiliated'' with the university. So my mother did not have the opportunity to pursue a Ph.D. She eventually went into teaching. Because of this, both my parents were very keen that my sister and I have equal opportunities.</p>
        <p>In the 1960's, when my chance to go to the tropics came, I asked my parents for their advice and my father's immediate reaction was, ''Every botanist needs to spend time in the tropics.'' He didn't say, ''Oh, that's going to be too difficult for a woman.'' So I went in 1969. I was only going to stay for a year. But I married a biologist I met there who studied frogs, had children, got divorced and, of course, never left.</p>
        <p>Q. What was your impression of the Malay world when you first arrived there?</p>
        <p>A. It was all completely new. The flora was bigger and brighter than anything in Europe. I had read about these things in books, but to see these specimens and the diversity, was incredible. One hectare of land -- a hundred meters by a hundred meters -- had about one hundred different tree species on it.</p>
        <p>And then the forests were so very majestic, on a much bigger scale than anything I'd encountered.</p>
        <p>Q. Was it difficult for a Western woman to function in the territory you studied in Borneo?</p>
        <p>A. I'd say, on the whole, there was a kind of positive discrimination. Or maybe it was just how people responded to me, especially when I was out in the field looking for new flowers and plants. I remember once I was on a six-week expedition for the Royal Geographical Society, and we were being led by porters from the Penan people. I was always the slowest in our group. But whenever I lagged behind, there would be some Penan person lurking behind a tree, making an excuse that he needed a cigarette or a rest. It is their credo to take care of the weakest one. I seemed to be that.</p>
        <p>Q. Your specialty is tropical begonias. Why devote oneself to begonias?</p>
        <p>A. My specialty is herbaceous plants. Begonias are one of those. I was looking for a research topic. Most of the taxonomists are actually attached to forestry departments. So that you see the forest trees are really quite well studied. But nobody was working on herbaceous plants. So this was a field that was waiting for somebody to work on it. And herbaceous plants, because they were on the ground, were accessible. I didn't need tree-climbing assistants to help me; I could take samples myself.</p>
        <p>Q. In your search for new varieties of begonias, you've found them in some really odd places, haven't you?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. Once a friend once came back from what was probably the most expensive resort in Malaysia with a new begonia. She noticed them growing in a creek there. So we had a great deal of fun turning up in all our jungle clothing and showing their nature guide how he can make sure that further development doesn't cause damage. We also took samples for the Botanical Gardens so that there would be backup of the rare flower.</p>
        <p>Q. Did you find any new plants on your Royal Geographical Society trip in Borneo?</p>
        <p>A. Any area one goes to in Borneo will have something new to be discovered. In an area the size of this living room, you might find 200 to 300 different plants, many of them existing only on the spot where they were growing. One bulldozer in a small area can condemn them to extinction.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you answer people who say that it doesn't matter if we lose a plant that is endemic to a small area that hardly anyone sees?</p>
        <p>A. Man should not destroy what it cannot create. I worry that the forest is going faster than it can be studied. I don't have to mention the new medicines, herbs, fruits and foods that are still to be discovered and what important resources they could be.</p>
        <p>You know, concern about biodiversity has a high media profile, but what you mostly hear about are animals being lost. Plants seem to have less charisma than tigers and elephants. I hoping that with this Fairchild Prize I can draw some more attention toward the plight of tropical forests.</p>
        <p>Q. One of the things you do back home is to give a beekeeping course to Malay women. Why beekeeping?</p>
        <p>A. I give a course on the flowers that are food for bees, yes. This is one of the things a botanist can do. It's for a development project to provide income for Malay women. If you can get cash to the women, it will go to the children. Well, when this started no one knew what the bees that they were domesticating ate. So I began to examine the little baskets on the bees' legs and look at the nectar in their stomachs to figure it out.</p>
        <p>Q. What have you learned about the diet of the Malay bees?</p>
        <p>A. That coconut was the best honey source. The women are now producing a wonderful coconut honey that's delicious with coffee, which they sometimes also grow.</p>
        <p>Q. Will your children be following in the family tradition by making careers in science?</p>
        <p>A. No. My daughter has always been interested in creative writing, and my son, when he was 9, said, ''I'm not going to be a biologist when I grow up because I want a nice car.'' He's now a currency trader.</p>
        <p>A CONVERSATION WITH: RUTH KIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
