<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="04OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/04/science/04OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1397670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Butterflies and Moths</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wasps (Insects)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elk</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snowmobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Io (Moon)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jupiter</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montana State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Michigan Technological University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snowmobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Butterflies and Moths</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D9133AF937A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ants' Demolition Derby</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Observatory column: Researchers in Britain and Japan, in study published in journal Nature, find that parasitic wasps secrete long-lasting chemicals on parasitic butterfly larvae that make host ants more aggressive, first attracting them to caterpillar and then repelling them; ants then turn on each other, and, thus distracted, cannot defend themselves against egg-laying wasps; researchers from Montana State and Michigan Technological Universities, in study published in journal Conservation Biology, conclude that elk and wolves exposed to snowmobiles have higher levels of hormones caused by stress; photos from Galileo spacecraft's final flyby of Jupiter's moon Io show many new volcanoes, cliffs and plume vents; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ants' Demolition Derby</p>
        <p>A community can be at its most vulnerable when its members quarrel among themselves, allowing an enemy to exploit the infighting to its own advantage. (There is a reason, after all, that the aphorism ''United we stand'' starts springing up everywhere in times of trouble.)</p>
        <p>What is true for people is also true for ants, apparently, according to a study by researchers in Britain and Japan. Only with ants, the same enemy that exploits the infighting is causing it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week's column includes items on insect infighting, the negative effects of snowmobiles on wildlife and Jupiter's moon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ants' Demolition Derby</p>
        <p>A community can be at its most vulnerable when its members quarrel among themselves, allowing an enemy to exploit the infighting to its own advantage. (There is a reason, after all, that the aphorism ''United we stand'' starts springing up everywhere in times of trouble.)</p>
        <p>What is true for people is also true for ants, apparently, according to a study by researchers in Britain and Japan. Only with ants, the same enemy that exploits the infighting is causing it.</p>
        <p>The researchers studied a convoluted relationship among two parasitic species, a wasp and a blue butterfly, and a European ant, Myrmica schencki. The ants serve as hosts to the butterfly larvae, protecting them in their final development stages, fooled by similarities in behavior and chemistry between the caterpillars and the ants' own larvae. But the caterpillar itself can be a host to the wasp, which given the chance will lay its eggs in it.</p>
        <p>How does the wasp get that chance? The researchers, whose work was reported in the journal Nature, found that the wasps secrete chemicals on the caterpillar. These chemicals, which had previously been unknown, make the ants more aggressive, first attracting them to the caterpillar and then repelling them. After being repelled, they turn on each other as a wave of panic travels through the colony. Distracted, the ants then cannot defend against the egg-laying wasp.</p>
        <p>The researchers found that the chemicals are long-lasting, creating an aggressive response among ants for nearly two months after being secreted. The chemicals may provide an alternative to poisons and repellents as a method of controlling ants, the researchers suggest.</p>
        <p>Elk Snowmobile Syndrome</p>
        <p>The issue of whether snowmobiles should be allowed in national parks often focuses on noise and pollution and how they affect other people who use the parks for quieter forms of winter recreation like cross-country skiing.</p>
        <p>But the effects on wildlife are a concern, too. Since wolves and elk do not attend public hearings, however, it has been difficult to gauge their reaction to snowmobiling in places like Yellowstone.</p>
        <p>Now, researchers from Montana State and Michigan Technological Universities have provided some measure of the effects on wildlife. Writing in the journal Conservation Biology, they show that elk and wolves exposed to snowmobiles have higher levels of hormones caused by stress.</p>
        <p>The researchers measured the hormones, called glucocorticoids, in elk feces from Yellowstone and wolf feces from Yellowstone, Voyageurs National Park in Minnesota and Isle Royale National Park in Lake Superior. They found that elk hormone levels were higher in snowmobile season than immediately afterward. With wolves, hormone levels were higher in Voyageurs, where snowmobiles are allowed, than in Isle Royale, where they are not.</p>
        <p>The Yellowstone samples, from a part of the park where snowmobiles are prohibited but wheeled vehicles are allowed, showed intermediate levels.</p>
        <p>Populations of elk and wolves in the areas studied are stable, so snowmobiling does not appear to have a direct physical effect on the wildlife. But elevated stress hormones can cause reproductive and other problems, the researchers say, so measuring hormones could provide warning of more severe effects to come.</p>
        <p>A Photogenic Moon</p>
        <p>The Galileo spacecraft's final flyby of Jupiter's moon Io in January may have fizzled; the craft went into standby mode because of radiation. But earlier photos of Io have just been released, and they are spectacular.</p>
        <p>The images, from flybys last year, show many new volcanoes, bringing the number of known ones to 120. Other photos, at www.jpl.nasa.gov/images/io, show cliffs and plume vents.</p>
        <p>Galileo will do one last non-imaging flyby of a small moon in the fall and will then be sent crashing into Jupiter in 2003.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
