<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Tops Japan to Earn Date With Surprising Australia</title>
    <meta content="01HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ATLANTA: DAY 13 -- BASKETBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="868911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ATLANTA: DAY 13 -- BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moran, Malcolm</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DA143FF932A3575BC0A960958260" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Tops Japan to Earn Date With Surprising Australia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moran, Malcolm</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US defeats Japan, 108-93, in quarterfinals of women's Olympic basketball tournament; Australia defeats Russia, 74-70, in other quarterfinals match; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The day after the Australian men proclaimed the greatest basketball victory in their nation's history in reaching the Olympic semifinals, the women completed a joyful matching set. They earned a rematch with the United States and a chance for a first basketball medal by eliminating Russia from medal contention with a 74-70 overtime quarterfinal victory this afternoon.</p>
        <p>As the former Soviet Union and the restructured Unified Team, the Russians once set a standard in the international women's game. But for the first time since women's basketball was introduced in 1976, a Russian team will leave an Olympic tournament without a medal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The day after the Australian men proclaimed the greatest basketball victory in their nation's history in reaching the Olympic semifinals, the women completed a joyful matching set. They earned a rematch with the United States and a chance for a first basketball medal by eliminating Russia from medal contention with a 74-70 overtime quarterfinal victory this afternoon.</p>
        <p>As the former Soviet Union and the restructured Unified Team, the Russians once set a standard in the international women's game. But for the first time since women's basketball was introduced in 1976, a Russian team will leave an Olympic tournament without a medal.</p>
        <p>The United States, which won the 1984 tournament boycotted by the Soviet Union and repeated as champion in 1988, advanced with a 108-93 victory over Japan earlier this afternoon behind Lisa Leslie's American Olympic record 35 points. Australia and the United States will meet at 5 P.M. Friday. In their preliminary round meeting, the Americans won, 96-79. ''We always fancied ourselves a shot at the U.S.A.,'' said Tom Maher, the Australia coach. ''We don't think that has changed.''</p>
        <p>On the way to an undefeated record in its 52-game pre-Olympic tour, the United States defeated Russia by a point in Chicago last month.</p>
        <p>Players did not shake hands at the end of Russia's defeat today, a game in which Robyn Maher, Australia's starting guard, suffered a broken hand and several confrontations took place in the final minutes. Yelena Baranova, who grabbed 21 rebounds, blocked 6 shots and scored 13 points in defeat, suggested that the narrow exhibition victory had a bearing on this tournament. ''I think that perhaps the United States became intimidated by our play in Chicago and pitted us against Australia to get us out of the running,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Vadim Kapranov, the Russia coach, said that the 23 fouls called against his team, compared with 13 for Australia, became a decisive factor. ''It was a physical game, but the referees were against us,'' Kapranov said. ''The Olympic spirit should be present in the game, but it was overshadowed by the referees.''</p>
        <p>His region will still have a stake in the semifinals. Ukraine, which has two starters that played for the gold-medal winning Unified Team in Barcelona, defeated Italy, 59-50, tonight. Yelena Zhirko scored 15 points with 15 rebounds and 4 steals. Ukraine will play Friday against Brazil, a 101-69 victor over Cuba tonight.</p>
        <p>In the United States victory, Katrina McClain, who scored 18 points, tied her American record of 16 rebounds. Teresa Edwards had 12 assists, 3 fewer than the record she set earlier in the tournament.</p>
        <p>Japan, the fourth place team in Group A and without a player taller than 6 feet, made 47 percent of its shots, including 13 3-point shots. That was the highest percentage and most 3-pointers the Americans have allowed in their six victories here. ''I wish we would have done a little better job taking away the 3-point shots,'' said Tara VanDerveer, the United States coach.</p>
        <p>Despite the problems with its perimeter defense, the Americans were never threatened. Leslie made 16 of 21 shots and had 8 rebounds and 4 assists. ''Tara tells me, 'When it's time to score, score,' '' Leslie said, '' 'and when it's time to pass it, pass it.' '' Aki Ichijo and Mikiko Hagiwara led Japan with 22 points each.</p>
        <p>Australia will at least equal its best previous Olympic performance, a fourth-place finish in 1988. Irina Sumnikova, Russia's 5-foot-9-inch point guard, had 5 assists, 4 turnovers and 10 points while playing with a protective bandage on her left hand and wrist. Still, Russia, the second place team in Group A with a 4-1 record, had a 7-point lead with 16 minutes 40 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>Michele Timms, the 5-5 Australian point guard, scored 6 of her 10 points in the next 3:47, with the third of three jump shots bringing her team within 2 points. Australia took a 64-62 lead on a layup and foul shot by Michelle Brogan with 1:56 to play in regulation time. But Baranova tied the game with a jumper with 16 seconds to go.</p>
        <p>Sandy Brondello, a substitute guard, replaced the injured Maher at the foul line with 4:24 to go in overtime and made 5 of 6 free throws for a total of 13 points.</p>
        <p>Brondello's free throws with 2:18 to go gave Australia a 71-68 lead. Baranova blocked a shot by Whittle and made a layup at the other end to bring Russia within a point with 54 seconds to go. But Brogan made a pair of free throws with 39.2 seconds to play, and Rachael Sporn deflected a pass for Baranova, leading to a jump ball with 5.8 seconds to go.</p>
        <p>''It was a good hit-out,'' said Sporn, who had 9 points and 6 rebounds. ''A very physical game. I didn't realize there were so many emotions in a game of basketball, but I guess overtime does that to you.''</p>
        <p>ATLANTA: DAY 13 -- BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
