<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Japan, Brutal Comics for Women</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="806878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMIC BOOKS AND STRIPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DB1739F936A35752C1A963958260" item-length="1485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Japan, Brutal Comics for Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE who thinks of Japanese women as innocent, repressed or prim should pick up a copy of Amour magazine.</p>
        <p>This is a comic book for women, the distaff equivalent of the comics that the mobs of pinstriped salarymen read on the train to work every morning. Those are  notorious for depicting sexual violence, aptly symbolized by a comic called "Rape-Man" that was finally extinguished because it glorified rape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE who thinks of Japanese women as innocent, repressed or prim should pick up a copy of Amour magazine.</p>
        <p>This is a comic book for women, the distaff equivalent of the comics that the mobs of pinstriped salarymen read on the train to work every morning. Those are  notorious for depicting sexual violence, aptly symbolized by a comic called "Rape-Man" that was finally extinguished because it glorified rape.</p>
        <p>So what's in the women's comics?</p>
        <p>Sexual violence, particularly rape. The December issue of Amour, for example, has 316 pages of comics. Of them, 90 contain rape scenes -- though it is a bit difficult to count, because usually a woman is depicted eventually enjoying what starts out as a rape.</p>
        <p>"Men read these kinds of comic books, so why shouldn't women as well?" asked  Yayoi Watanabe, a demurely dressed woman who draws the comics. "Women seem to be starting to say, 'Hey, we lust, too,' and 'We're also thinking of porn and promiscuity.' "</p>
        <p>Yet to American sensibilities, the magazines are not erotic, just sick. The drawings focus on pain and violence and, by American standards, could scarcely be more offensive. What is most unsettling about the "ladies' comics" -- as they are known in Japanese -- is that they seem to glorify rape.</p>
        <p>A few recent examples:</p>
        <p>*The first story in the November issue of Amour depicts a young man who kidnaps a young couple, strips them and ties them up, and then rapes and sexually tortures them repeatedly with various devices. The woman decides she</p>
        <p>likes being raped.</p>
        <p>*A story in the December issue of Cute depicts Saori, a young "office lady" whose boyfriend turns out to be a psychopath and serial rapist and killer. Saori so loves him that she lures young women to be attacked by him.</p>
        <p>*A young housewife in the December issue of Amour is raped by a man who introduces her to sadism and masochism. The housewife enjoys the experience and  begins to visit him every day.</p>
        <p>"Women don't want to be raped," Miss Watanabe said, when pressed on the point, "but women can be aroused by imagining it. That's true of me, too."</p>
        <p>Perhaps there is an analogy with mystery and crime novels: Agatha Christie and Elmore Leonard fans do not necessarily yearn to be killed. Yet there remains the paradox that the growing independence of Japanese women is reflected not in stories of assertive women, but rather of passive women being brutalized.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes we carry stories where the woman takes the initiative, and those kinds of stories have their fans," said Masafumi Mizuno, editor of Amour. "But most readers seem to prefer when women are in a passive position."</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Mizuno is the editor, most of the artists writing for Amour and  other ladies comics are women.</p>
        <p>Solid Sales</p>
        <p>These magazines are not found in the average woman's shoulder bag, but neither are they a tiny fringe of the market. Amour, which is six years old, claims a circulation of 400,000, and its readership may be several times that since copies are often passed around among friends.</p>
        <p>Amour is the best-selling "ladies' comic," but there are many titles available: Taboo, Cute, Scandal, Love and others. One is titled "I Wanna Be Your Dog" and depicts a naked woman groveling on all fours.</p>
        <p>Publishers say the buyers are overwhelmingly women, mostly in their 20's and  30's, and the ads are all for women's products. While the content is fairly similar to men's comics, there is a tad more plot development in the female version. The stories typically run 20 to 40 pages, with several comic panels per page, and in the ladies' comics the protagonists normally have their clothes on  for the first few pages.</p>
        <p>Japanese feminists are critical of the ladies' comics, but they are more concerned by the far greater number of similar books for men.</p>
        <p>Yoko Hayashi, a lawyer, offered a feminist critique in noting that the publishing houses are controlled by men. "The authors are women, but they are controlled by the publishers," she said.</p>
        <p>Mariko Mitsui, a former politician who is also an active feminist, said she is particularly disappointed by ladies' comics because they underscore that many young women do not really want to be liberated.</p>
        <p>"They want to escape independence, and so for them to be raped seems better"  than negotiating their own sexual encounters, Ms. Mitsui said.</p>
        <p>In reality, Japanese can be as outraged by rape as anyone. That is shown by the current uproar over the rape of a 12-year-old girl in Okinawa, allegedly by  three American servicemen. Yet by and large Japan is a far safer country than America, and there is probably less fear of rape in Japan. This coupled with sometimes fantastical drawings featuring blond Japanese (not unusual in pop-culture depictions here) perhaps makes the violence in comics seem less threatening.</p>
        <p>Fantasy as a Vent</p>
        <p>"I think Japanese comics in general are a playing out of the subconscious,"  said Frederik L. Schodt, an American who has written a book about Japanese comics. "Maybe they fill a role similar to dreaming. You work out your stress, explore fantasies, and then you go back to work and your normal life."</p>
        <p>"In terms of sexual fantasies, people are not so constrained by political correctness," Mr. Schodt said. "In Japan, women can fantasize more easily about  things that they might feel guilty about in the U.S."</p>
        <p>Chie Miya, a 35-year-old housewife who draws for Amour and other ladies' comics, says the rapists in men's comics are often "greasy, middle-aged men," while in ladies' comics the attackers are always dashing young men. "So readers  don't really take it as a rape," she said. "They see it as an assault by a person whom they are attracted to but whom they could not have as a partner in real life."</p>
        <p>The overall comic industry in Japan has been suffering a bit, and some of the ladies' comics have gone out of business. But others have gained ground, and one hot trend has been to include racy letters supposedly written by readers.</p>
        <p>A letter attributed to a 20-year-old "office lady" in Love Experience magazine describes how she was changing to go home late one evening when her boss burst into the dressing room. He handcuffed her and raped her, and her conclusion is: "I felt an ecstasy that I never had before."</p>
        <p>Gays for Girls</p>
        <p>One of the themes in ladies' comics, particularly those aimed at younger readers, is romances between gay men. Paradoxically, perhaps, these are less graphic and more sentimental than the male-female sexuality depicted in most comic books.</p>
        <p>One explanation may be that for teen-age girl readers just becoming aware of  their own sexuality, sensualism between two boys is erotically engaging without  being personally threatening.</p>
        <p>Ladies' comics have encountered some criticism in Japan, and there's been a modest effort in Parliament to tighten controls. But in fact they have been easing; pubic hair depictions used to be banned but are now tolerated, and drawings aim to be explicit and shocking.</p>
        <p>The ladies' comics are only one aspect of Japanese female assertiveness that  seems discordant to Americans. Another is the young women who are exceptionally  prim in the office and then after work strut in revealing clothes on stages in discos.</p>
        <p>"Women are eager for new experiences," argues Miss Watanabe, the comic artist. "They're looking for something beautiful, something enjoyable, something that feels good."</p>
        <p>In any case, there is no doubt that times are changing. Until the American occupation of Japan after World War II, kisses were not even allowed in films; the first on-screen kiss came in 1946, and the actor and actress were so anxious about it that they put a piece of gauze between their lips.</p>
        <p>"My mother's generation is very different," added Miss Watanabe, who said her mother is 60 and that she herself is "over 30." "My Mom seems to feel that even  opening the covers of the comic books is disgusting. She knows that I'm writing  something like this, but she won't tell her relatives or neighbors what kind of  comics I write."</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
