<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Booming Colorado Weighs Its Future</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="806907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLORADO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ASPEN (COLO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOULDER (COLO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLORADO, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Boulder</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Aspen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DB1739F936A35752C1A963958260" item-length="1367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Booming Colorado Weighs Its Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>ASPEN, Colo. Nov. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lighting a small, makeshift flamethrower in his cluttered kitchen, Hunter S.  Thompson pointed to imaginary Boeing 737's flying overhead and ranted, "Greedheads, greedheads."</p>
        <p>Not confining pyrotechnics to his mountainside home, the irascible journalist is rallying Aspenites to vote on Tuesday against a proposal to widen and strengthen this remote resort town's airport runway to accommodate long-haul jets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lighting a small, makeshift flamethrower in his cluttered kitchen, Hunter S.  Thompson pointed to imaginary Boeing 737's flying overhead and ranted, "Greedheads, greedheads."</p>
        <p>Not confining pyrotechnics to his mountainside home, the irascible journalist is rallying Aspenites to vote on Tuesday against a proposal to widen and strengthen this remote resort town's airport runway to accommodate long-haul jets.</p>
        <p>Executives of the Aspen Skiing Company complain that the number of skiers here has remained flat over the last 20 years. For Mr. Thompson and his fellow slow-growth advocates in this town of 6,000, that is just fine.</p>
        <p>It is an attitude that is spreading like a dry pine forest fire in Colorado,  one of the fastest-growing states in the Rocky Mountains, the region with the fastest economic and population growth in the nation. On Tuesday, slow-growth initiatives will be on the ballot in Aspen and at least five other Colorado boom towns.</p>
        <p>"It's not in my children's interest to have six million people living in Colorado," said Richard A. Lamm, referring to predictions of a population about  double that when he was Governor in the early 1980's. "We don't want Denver to become one big Los Angeles of the Rockies."</p>
        <p>The slow-growth movement is taking hold as memories fade of the Rockies' bitter recession of a decade ago, a bust triggered by falling oil and gas prices. With Colorado's economy increasingly diversified, many economists believe that the state may be breaking a century-long boom-and-bust cycle.</p>
        <p>Today, only 1 percent of Coloradans work in the energy field. More now work in telecommunications than energy. Denver is the capital of nation's cable television industry. Further spurring job growth there are a new international airport and a mutual fund industry whose portfolio has grown tenfold, to $50 billion, in five years.</p>
        <p>In the first half of the 1990's, Colorado's annual population growth ran at triple the nation's rate of 1 percent a year, though it has tapered off to only  double the national rate today. With quality of life increasingly important for  white-collar workers, Denver now offers four major sports teams, a revitalized downtown and easy access to wilderness areas.</p>
        <p>In this environment, more and more Colorado communities feel they can give themselves the luxury of shutting the door.</p>
        <p>In Boulder, where job growth has run at three times population growth, turnout was light last week for a pro-growth rally billed as "a taste of unemployment."</p>
        <p>Stephen M. Pomerance, a City Council candidate who helped found a residents group called Slow Growth, said that unemployment was not a realistic fear for most residents. "In Boulder, we have 85,000 jobs for a city with 95,000 people," he said.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Boulder residents are to vote on an initiative to cut annual commercial construction in half over the next five years. Sensing a ground swell of support for curbs, Boulder's City Council voted in September to adopt a compromise measure, to cut commercial construction by 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Boulder has been so attractive to investors that during the first nine months of this year companies scrambled to win permits for one million square feet of commercial construction, double the annual average of previous years.</p>
        <p>To some, Boulder's ballot proposal represents the second shoe dropping. In 1976, Boulder became the first city in Colorado to put caps on housing construction, though it left commercial development untouched.</p>
        <p>"The result is that we now have 40,000 people commuting into Boulder every day," said Paul Danish, a Boulder county commissioner, who pushed for the residential curb 20 years ago. Predicting victory for the commercial curb on Tuesday, he said, "You spend your day looking up someone's tailpipe -- and then  you say get it out of my life."</p>
        <p>The slow-growth movement is strongest in Boulder and other affluent western suburbs of Denver.</p>
        <p>In nearby Golden, home to Coors beer, residents are to vote Tuesday on an initiative to limit housing construction to 1 percent of current square footage. Offering views of Rocky Mountain foothills, this onetime territorial capital of  15,000 people saw housing construction growth of 3.2 percent in 1994.</p>
        <p>Similar limits are to be voted on Tuesday in three other west Denver suburbs: Broomfield, Lafayette and Longmont.</p>
        <p>In Utah, another fast-growing Western state, voters in Midway and St. George  on Tuesday will consider limits on building permits.</p>
        <p>From 1991 to 1994, Arizona and Colorado each experienced about 11 percent population growth, fastest after Nevada and Idaho.</p>
        <p>To some, the West's anti-bulldozer movement is elitist.</p>
        <p>"We have a whole generation of people who believe that only worms should move dirt," said Philip M. Burgess, president of the Center for the New West, a Denver-based study group. "Growth management can degenerate into enclave development. It backfires because it raises prices, it reduces choice."</p>
        <p>For some, Colorado's current economic slowdown and the state's history of boom and bust should be enough for communities to keep doors open to new investment.</p>
        <p>"It wasn't that long ago -- in the mid-80's -- that we had a collapse, the bottom fell out of the energy industry, the bottom fell out of the high-tech industry," warned Kenneth N. Hotard, senior vice president of the Boulder Area Board of Realtors. "We already see companies looking elsewhere."</p>
        <p>Alexander E. Bracken, a spokesman for Boulder's largest private employer, the Ball Aerospace and Technologies Corporation, said of his city's slow-growth initiative: "We hope that it will be defeated. This initiative would make it very difficult for us to grow."</p>
        <p>Coloradans have consistently refused to adopt statewide growth controls or plans.</p>
        <p>In Denver today, Gov. Roy Romer, a Democrat, led a symposium on "smart growth." "It is not realistic to build a wall around your state and to stop growth," he said in an interview on Thursday.</p>
        <p>He defined "smart growth" as taking advantage of the population's high level  of education to provide well-paying jobs with benefits. Colorado ranks third nationwide in the portion of its population who are high school and college graduates.</p>
        <p>Here in the mountain towns of Pitkin County, where unemployment is nearly nonexistent, slow-growth advocates suspect that expansion of Aspen's airport is  really a Trojan horse for "industrial tourism."</p>
        <p>"They want an industrial, cruise-ship economy here," said Tim Mooney, a realtor and ski instructor, who wore a button showing the black silhouette of a Boeing 737, stamped with a red international stop symbol.</p>
        <p>"We're in a box canyon at 7,900 feet -- there are only so many resources here," Mr. Mooney continued, his voice rising. "If the ski company thinks they can ratchet up their business by 10 percent a year, they are going to ratchet down the environment by 10 percent a year."</p>
        <p>Down the street, the Aspen Mayor, John S. Bennett, was also skeptical. "One of Aspen's greatest assets has been lack of accessibility," reflected Mr. Bennett, a Yale graduate who owns a French restaurant here, Pour La France. "A bigger airport with heavy, metal jets, flying in from Las Vegas -- I fail to see how it makes Aspen a better community."</p>
        <p>Today, newspapers brimmed with advertisements, paid for by the Aspen Skiing Company and other businesses that profit from the ski trade, favoring airport expansion. On Friday, over a breakfast served by a French waiter at a ski company hotel, company executives grumbled that only "elitists" were against permitting landings by Boeing 737's.</p>
        <p>"People who oppose this are second-homeowners who come in on private jets --  they are financially bullet-proofed," said Robert A. Maynard, the ski company president. "Why, we even heard someone say, 'Only nerds fly 737's.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
