<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restructuring of Medicare and Medicaid Will Affect the Low-IncomeElderly Twice</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="806927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGED</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS ANDBUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MEDICAID</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MEDICARE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEIN, ESTHER B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EEDB1739F936A35752C1A963958260" item-length="1765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restructuring of Medicare and Medicaid Will Affect the Low-IncomeElderly Twice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ESTHER B. FEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEIN, ESTHER B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doris Brisson lives on the outskirts of poverty in Mesquite, Tex. She is 66 years old and gets Social Security payments of $512 a month, food stamps worth $20 a month and she barely makes the rent on a one-room apartment that she says  gives cozy a bad name.</p>
        <p>When it comes to her health care, Mrs. Brisson relies not only on Medicare, the medical program for people over 65, but also on Medicaid, which covers many  of the nation's impoverished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doris Brisson lives on the outskirts of poverty in Mesquite, Tex. She is 66 years old and gets Social Security payments of $512 a month, food stamps worth $20 a month and she barely makes the rent on a one-room apartment that she says  gives cozy a bad name.</p>
        <p>When it comes to her health care, Mrs. Brisson relies not only on Medicare, the medical program for people over 65, but also on Medicaid, which covers many  of the nation's impoverished.</p>
        <p>While Congress has grappled with vast overhauls of the nation's two giant health care programs independently, for Mrs. Brisson, and for as many as five million other elderly poor people, the programs are nearly indivisible. To maintain their precarious existences, they depend on both.</p>
        <p>Together, the anticipated growth of the programs would be sliced by more than $440 billion in seven years under Republican legislation that passed last month  and that President Clinton has threatened to veto.</p>
        <p>Republicans maintain that by giving states more flexibility on spending their Medicaid dollars and by directing older people into cost-conscious managed care  plans, the Government will save money while improving health care and reducing costs for people like Mrs. Brisson.</p>
        <p>But numerous health care experts and advocates for the poor say that the financially pressed and often frail elderly, vulnerable to cuts in both programs, will become the legislation's most pathetic victims. Studies have shown that nearly a million older Americans living in poverty stand to lose some of their health coverage if these changes become law.</p>
        <p>"For them it's a double whammy," said Ron Pollack, Executive Director of Families U.S.A., an advocacy group. "They could lose Medicaid eligibility at a time when the Medicare expenses that Medicaid used to cover for them are going up. If they couldn't afford them before, how will they afford them now?"</p>
        <p>In Mrs. Brisson's case, Medicare pays for her doctor visits, but her premium, co-payments to her doctor and her annual deductible are now covered under a special Medicaid program. The program, the Qualified Medicare Beneficiary program, or Q.M.B., has required since 1990 that states pay those Medicare costs for beneficiaries who are barely above the poverty line, which is about $7,400 for a single person and about $10,000 for a couple.</p>
        <p>But neither program covers medicine. Mrs. Brisson is supposed to be taking medication for high blood pressure, arthritis and depression. She has the prescriptions in her purse, next to the wallet that has too little money to fill them.</p>
        <p>"Right now, what I can't get free from the doctor, I do without," said Mrs. Brisson, who has had trouble getting full Medicaid benefits after a recent move  from Colorado to Texas. "By the end of the month I'm begging dinner invitations  from friends. If anybody asks me to spend one more dollar for my health care, well, I guess I'd just have to quit going to the doctor altogether."</p>
        <p>The Republican Medicare plan raises beneficiaries' co-payments, deductibles and premiums and encourages them to join cost-saving managed care plans. By signing on for such a plan, the Republicans argue, older people with limited resources would no longer have to pay a portion of each doctor visit or a minimum amount before their benefits kicked in.</p>
        <p>The Medicaid plan, meanwhile, ends mandatory benefits for the very poor and gives states fixed grants that they would decide how to divide among their neediest residents. Whether states would put as much money as the Federal Government now requires into covering gaps in the Medicare coverage for the elderly poor is very much an open question.</p>
        <p>"Even if you had a combination of Mother Teresa and Albert Einstein administering these programs, the proposed cuts are so deep that needy people will lose eligibility," said Stan Dorn, managing attorney for the National Health Law Program, a public interest law center in Washington and Los Angeles that focuses on low-income health issues.</p>
        <p>Being forced to cut back on the medical attention they get, Mr. Dorn said, will have deadly consequences for the elderly poor. "The death certificate may say 'cause of death: heart attack,' " he said, "but the real cause will be Medicaid and Medicare cuts."</p>
        <p>Republicans said that given the spiraling costs of Medicaid and Medicare, they had no choice but to find a way to rein in expenses.</p>
        <p>"We are opening up Medicare to the new medicine of the 90's," said Mike Collins, a spokesman for the House Commerce Committee. "States and managed care  providers are going to give better care at lower costs to our needy seniors."</p>
        <p>But a study by the Urban Institute, a Washington-based research group, found  that even assuming that state governments achieve a higher level of cost efficiency in their managed care programs, nearly a million poor older Americans could lose their Medicaid eligibility in the next seven years.</p>
        <p>Another report by Project HOPE, a Washington think tank that studies health issues, found that nearly 60 percent of people eligible for Medicaid's Q.M.B. program did not receive benefits because they did not know about the program or  did not realize they qualified.</p>
        <p>But as the economic situation for poorer older Americans declines, experts warn that more of them will be forced to seek protections, like those now offered under the Q.M.B. program. But while the Republican plan mandates that states set aside a certain portion of their Medicaid block grants to cover premiums for this group, it does not require that all the poor elderly be covered.</p>
        <p>Each state would decide who it considers poor within the elderly population and how to distribute money among them. Currently, people with incomes up to 20  percent above the poverty level automatically qualify for Medicaid-subsidized premiums.</p>
        <p>Under the Republican plan, states would have to cover only premiums, not deductibles or co-payments. And the amount they would be required to reserve for the premiums is far too little, critics say. It amounts to 90 percent of what they spent on this program from 1993 to 1995, when most of those who were eligible did not participate.</p>
        <p>Health care experts also note that managed care plans are not available to more than nine million Medicare recipients because companies have not set up businesses where they live. But Mr. Collins of the House Commerce Committee said that the Republican leadership is "confident that markets will spring up" when the new plan becomes law.</p>
        <p>The Republicans, he said, envision a scenario in which Medicare beneficiaries are courted by managed care plans eager for their business. As the competition increases, he said, the plans will recruit good doctors, offer a wide range of services and even give financial incentives to the elderly to join, knowing that if they do not, people will go elsewhere.</p>
        <p>But while managed care companies are technically required by law to accept anyone who is eligible for Medicare, companies have a way of skewing their marketing to attract more stable and robust people whose care costs the least and increases profits most, said Lani Sanjek, associate executive director of the New York Statewide Senior Action Council. They hold recruiting seminars, for example, at times and places that are inconvenient or inaccessible to the disabled.</p>
        <p>What is more, advocates said, the Republican plan does not provide either a framework or a budget for monitoring the quality of managed care programs.</p>
        <p>"No standards have been established, let alone implemented," said Diane Archer, executive director of the Medicare Beneficiaries Defense Fund. "A lot of the elderly are too sick, too frail and too ill-equipped to make an informed choice under these circumstances. As this plan stands, the elderly poor are in danger of higher personal costs or significantly less health care."</p>
        <p>Many of these people are already rationing their own health care, doing without medications, like Mrs. Brisson, so that they can afford meals, or are visiting doctors only in an emergency to avoid co-payments they cannot afford.</p>
        <p>In Flushing, Queens, Irma Valentine, a former waitress, visits her doctor, because the cost is covered by Medicare. She takes her blood pressure and cholesterol prescriptions because they are covered by Medicaid, for which she is fully eligible because she is below the poverty level. But she does without arthritis pain killers and hemorrhoid medications because neither program covers those.</p>
        <p>"I'm 80 years old and I'm barely making it," said Mrs. Valentine, who volunteers time at the Self-Help Senior Center in Latimer Gardens, the public housing project where she lives, in exchange for warm meals. "I'm miserable and  I'm scared. If they ask me to give up any more, what would I take it away from?  From nothing?"</p>
        <p>What Orpha Andrukite hears about the plans debated in Washington has not reassured her that the coverage she now gets is safe. If she does fall off the Medicaid rolls, she says, she might as well "fall off the face of the earth."</p>
        <p>She is 70, and after working more than 30 years as a practical nurse, she now lives on $484 a month in Social Security benefits and $17 in food stamps in an apartment in southeast Washington.</p>
        <p>Until now, she has been covered by Medicare, with Medicaid picking up her out-of-pocket expenses, including most of the costs of the seven prescriptions she takes for a variety of illnesses, among them diabetes, osteorheumatoid arthritis and spasms. But if she is asked to spend any of her own money, she said, she will have to cut out the pills or the doctor visits.</p>
        <p>She already owes money to her daughter and a friend from North Carolina who two years ago slaughtered a cow and brought 100 pounds of meat up to Ms. Andrukite on account. The meat is now gone, she said, but the debt remains.</p>
        <p>"I'm already borrowed out, living on the edge," she said. "If they want to get another dollar from me, they may as well just come get me altogether."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
