<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Like a Real Candidate, Tanner Falls Flat in Hollywood</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="146344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOME BOX OFFICE (HBO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARMETZ, ALJEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUDEAU, GARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TANNER (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D91130F93BA25756C0A96E948260" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Like a Real Candidate, Tanner Falls Flat in Hollywood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALJEAN HARMETZ, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARMETZ, ALJEAN</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, May 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Democratic Presidential candidate Jack Tanner came to Hollywood recently for the usual purpose - to raise money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Democratic Presidential candidate Jack Tanner came to Hollywood recently for the usual purpose - to raise money.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Presidential candidate Jack Tanner came to Hollywood recently for the usual purpose - to raise money.</p>
        <p>The movie industry, which is generally apathetic this year about the real Presidential candidates, was equally unmoved by the fictional one. Almost no one showed up for the fund-raising party.</p>
        <p>Tanner, the dark horse, is a creation of Garry Trudeau, the Pulitzer Prize-winning cartoonist who draws ''Doonesbury.'' The liberal Democratic candidate is played by Michael Murphy in a series of half-hour programs directed by Robert Altman and presented by Home Box Office.</p>
        <p>Carrying his own suit bag, against the advice of his campaign managers, Tanner moves with the primaries from state to state, interacting with such real candidates as Bob Dole in New Hampshire. In future episodes, Tanner will be interviewed by Linda Ellerbee and share bagels and philosophy with Bruce Babbitt, the former Arizona Governor, who warns Tanner not to make the same mistakes he did in running for the Presidency. The Hollywood fund-raising episode will be broadcast on June 6, the eve of the California primary. Ignored by Hollywood Stars</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Altman says the ABC correspondents David Brinkley and Sam Donaldson have asked to interview Tanner, Hollywood didn't rush to join the fun. The only well-known actor at the Beverly Comstock Hotel, where the cocktail party was shot last week, was Rebecca De Mornay, the co-star of ''Risky Business,'' and Ms. De Mornay is engaged to a member of the cast, Richard Cox.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't get any name actors,'' said Mr. Altman. ''Their agents wouldn't let them come. Sue Mengers was horrified.'' He was referring to the head movie agent at William Morris. '' 'All our actors are working,' she said. I said, 'On a Sunday?' ''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Trudeau, the original idea of ''Tanner'' was ''to let the audience feel they're eavesdropping, to create a sense of authenticity by observing the process, to follow campaign culture in all its tribal rites - not to make a topical movie about 1988.''</p>
        <p>In the Hollywood episode, as elsewhere along the campaign trail, Jack Tanner is beset by ''the small moments of humiliation that pile up during the day,'' Mr. Trudeau said. ''The Hollywood party is a party by and for the young. Jack, who has presented himself as a generational candidate and prides himself on knowing the names of the Beatles, has to be briefed about the actors and doesn't even know what movies they were in. After all, the Beatles were 20 years ago. Jack has a look of befuddlement, like he's visiting Tibet.'' 'Never Had So Much Fun'</p>
        <p>''Jack is a decent guy who gets in over his head,'' said Mr. Murphy of his character. ''His basic decency is what I have to protect. More than with any other character I've ever played, if the audience doesn't like him, they won't watch. Tanner isn't corrupted, but he comes out of the process less naive.''</p>
        <p>''I've never had so much fun in my life,'' Mr. Altman, the director of ''M*A*S*H,'' said of ''Tanner.'' ''It's two-thirds scripted and one-third found art.''</p>
        <p>The encroachment of reality in the show was originally accidental but has since been nurtured. When Tanner hands out campaign buttons to real Tennessee politicians, the buttons carry a proper union inscription because that's the first thing politicans look for. ''Everybody just accepts it when I'm at a shopping center and I say, 'Hi, I'm Jack Tanner, I'm running for President,' '' said Mr. Murphy. ''I guess they get so used to people hustling them. And one woman said, 'We see stuff for you on television we don't see for other candidates.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman said: ''CNN wanted to cover us, and I said, 'Fine, but we'll shoot you, too. We'll be in your picture. You'll be in our picture.' I think in terms of filling in the squares, like a cartoon. Like a political cartoon -and hopefully as educational - we are disclosing a process that people are generally not aware of.''</p>
        <p>During one of the two California episodes, Jack Tanner is coached by Dorothy Sarnoff, who has taught numerous real candidates how to appear charming on television. Tanner thus gets his image polished in the land of polished images.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
