<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nets Look Rested, Not Rusted, After Layoff</title>
    <meta content="07nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/07/sports/basketball/07nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1730160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Picker, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Orlando Magic</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DF1F30F934A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nets Look Rested, Not Rusted, After Layoff</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Nets Look Rested, Not Rusted, After Layoff</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Jan. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets defeat Orlando Magic, 113-106; photos (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lengthy layoff can be dangerous for an N.B.A. team on a hot streak. Rust and complacency can settle in during the time off.</p>
        <p>The Nets seemed confident that it would not happen to them, even though they entered Friday's game against the Orlando Magic coming off a six-day break and owning an eight-game winning streak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets showed more signs of rest than rust as they defeated the Magic for their first victory of 2006 and their ninth consecutive triumph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lengthy layoff can be dangerous for an N.B.A. team on a hot streak. Rust and complacency can settle in during the time off.</p>
        <p>The Nets seemed confident that it would not happen to them, even though they entered Friday's game against the Orlando Magic coming off a six-day break and owning an eight-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>They showed more signs of rest than rust as they defeated the Magic, 113-106, at Continental Arena for their first victory of 2006 and their ninth consecutive triumph.</p>
        <p>''It was kind of like we didn't miss a beat tonight,'' said Jason Kidd, who had the 69th triple-double of his career with 16 points, 13 assists and 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Once again, the usual suspects led the way for the Nets (18-12).</p>
        <p>Vince Carter scored a game-high 31 points and added 5 assists. He has scored at least 21 points in every game of the streak. Richard Jefferson added 15 points and 4 assists. And Kidd's performance gave him more triple-doubles than 22 N.B.A. franchises, passing the Denver Nuggets.</p>
        <p>''My objective was to get out and try to run and speed the game up as fast as we could so that we could get that rust off,'' Kidd said. ''As much as we simulated or had great practices, it's a little bit different when you get out there in a game.''</p>
        <p>It helped that the Nets were playing the Magic (12-18), which had lost its previous two games by a combined 33 points. Still, Grant Hill had an early impact, scoring 14 points in the first half. He was inactive for the Magic's last game, on Wednesday in Toronto, with a strained groin muscle. The injury flared up shortly after halftime, and he played only about two minutes in the second half.</p>
        <p>Dwight Howard, Orlando's sensational second-year player, picked up the slack, finishing with 19 points and 14 rebounds. But it was not enough as the Nets' defense tightened with Hill on the bench.</p>
        <p>''Our defense has been the reason why we've been winning,'' Kidd said.</p>
        <p>The streak is the Nets' longest since they won a franchise-best 14 games from January to February 2004. The Nets had not played since a victory against the Atlanta Hawks on Dec. 30.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of how much time we have off, our approach shouldn't change,'' Carter said. ''It was just great to see.''</p>
        <p>The Nets treated the break as if it were something they had earned. It gave players like Jason Collins, who had a sprained right ankle, a chance to become healthy.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Coach Lawrence Frank rejected the notion that the break came at a bad time for the Nets. ''It's a unique thing to have this many days off in the course of a regular season,'' he said. ''But I think it's something that was a positive thing for us.''</p>
        <p>The Nets looked out of sorts on one of their first possessions, missing four shots despite getting offensive rebounds after the first three misses. But they took a 16-8 lead midway through the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Carter gave the Nets a 30-27 lead at the end of the quarter when he made a buzzer-beating 3-pointer from 32 feet. The Nets went into halftime with a 55-47 lead on 11 points from Carter, 10 from Nenad Krstic and 9 from Kidd. Six Nets ended up with 10 or more points.</p>
        <p>When Carter made an 18-foot jumper a minute into the second half, the Nets had a 10-point lead, their first double-digit advantage of the game. Clifford Robinson hit a 3-pointer at the end of the third quarter to give the Nets an 83-63 lead.</p>
        <p>One play in the third quarter summed up the Nets' night, as three players made quick passes to get the ball to Jefferson, who dunked.</p>
        <p>''I think that epitomizes the way we want to play,'' Jefferson said. ''Everyone touching the ball, everyone making the extra pass and everyone pushing the break.''</p>
        <p>The Magic cut the lead to 99-91 with about two minutes left when Hedo Turkoglu made a 3-pointer. But the Nets hit 12 consecutive free throws when the Magic repeatedly fouled them in the final 38 seconds.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>An acrobat doing back flips collided with one of the referees, Jim Clark, moments before the start of the third quarter Friday night. The game was delayed about five minutes as a medical team tended to Clark on the court. The quarter started with two officials before Clark returned with five minutes remaining.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
