<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Morgan Library Chooses Familiar Face for Its Next Chief</title>
    <meta content="24morg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/24/arts/design/24morg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pierpont Morgan Library</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minneapolis Institute of Arts</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DF1630F937A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Morgan Library Chooses Familiar Face for Its Next Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Morgan Library Chooses Familiar Face for Its Next Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four months after Charles E. Pierce Jr. announced plans to retire as director of the Morgan Library &amp; Museum, the institution's board has named a familiar face as his successor: William M. Griswold, who was a curator at the Morgan for six years and is now director and president of the Minneapolis Institute of Arts. He assumes the post in early 2008.</p>
        <p>A specialist in Italian master drawings, Mr. Griswold, 46, left the Morgan in 2001 to become the associate director for collections at the J. Paul Getty Museum and served briefly as acting director there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William M. Griswold, the director and president of the Minneapolis Institute of Arts, was a curator at the Morgan for six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four months after Charles E. Pierce Jr. announced plans to retire as director of the Morgan Library &amp; Museum, the institution's board has named a familiar face as his successor: William M. Griswold, who was a curator at the Morgan for six years and is now director and president of the Minneapolis Institute of Arts. He assumes the post in early 2008.</p>
        <p>A specialist in Italian master drawings, Mr. Griswold, 46, left the Morgan in 2001 to become the associate director for collections at the J. Paul Getty Museum and served briefly as acting director there.</p>
        <p>He became the director and president of the Minneapolis Institute in July 2005. While there he has overseen the completion of a 113,000-square-foot expansion designed by the architect Michael Graves and a $100 million capital campaign to help finance the addition and bolster the museum's endowment funds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griswold said that he thought long and hard about leaving the Minneapolis Institute after such a short time, but that his heart has always been at the Morgan. ''I know this is the right move for me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although the Morgan trustees were prepared to embark on an international search to find a replacement for Mr. Pierce, who has led the institution for 20 years, and there were several recommended candidates, ''right from the start we were hoping Bill would come back,'' said S. Parker Gilbert, president of the Morgan's board. ''He understands the challenges the library faces.''</p>
        <p>All the same Mr. Griswold will find the Morgan very different from the institution he left in 2001. In April 2006 it opened a widely acclaimed addition by the Italian architect Renzo Piano that united its three buildings on Madison Avenue at 36th Street with a light-filled atrium and increased its exhibition space by 75 percent.</p>
        <p>Now that the novelty of the $106 million expansion and renovation has worn off, Mr. Griswold will have to map out strong programming to keep the public coming back.</p>
        <p>''That's what's exciting,'' Mr. Griswold said in a telephone interview from Minneapolis. Although he said it would be premature to discuss specific ideas, he suggested that one of his priorities would be to maximize the impact of the Morgan's world-class collections, which include drawings by masters like Leonardo, Rubens and Degas and ancient Near Eastern seals to a rare Gutenberg Bible, medieval treatises and hundreds of letters from George Washington and Thomas Jefferson.</p>
        <p>Especially high on his list, he said, is expanding the museum's collection of art, music and literature from the 20th and 21st centuries. He is also interested in beefing up performances and lectures in the Morgan's new 280-seat concert hall.</p>
        <p>''The Morgan's identity as a museum is more apparent than ever,'' he said, ''and the great building is more accessible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Griswold said he also hoped to organize loan shows of every description. ''I do envision the Morgan as being an extremely lively place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He received a doctorate from the Courtauld Institute of Art in London and then went straight to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1988, working as an assistant and later associate curator of drawings. In 1995 he moved to the Morgan, where he headed the department of drawings and prints.</p>
        <p>He organized some acclaimed exhibitions there, including ''Master Drawings From the Hermitage and Pushkin Museums'' in 1998, which attracted tens of thousands of visitors, and ''Pierre Matisse and His Artists'' in 2002.</p>
        <p>Next came the Getty Museum post. In 2004, when Deborah Gribbon resigned as the Getty's director, he became acting director and was viewed as the leading candidate to run the museum.</p>
        <p>The Getty was then in deep turmoil. Ms. Gribbon had clashed with the head of the museum's parent trust, and there was a growing impression in the art world that the trust had diminished the museum's clout.</p>
        <p>Six months into his tenure as acting director, Mr. Griswold withdrew his name from the list of candidates being considered as Ms. Gribbon's successor. Later that year he took the job as director and president of the Minneapolis Institute of Arts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gilbert, of the Morgan's board, said of Mr. Griswold's return: ''When he left, we were sorry to see him go. It's really a homecoming.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
