<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fehr Expects Agreement On Testing Before Spring</title>
    <meta content="08UNIO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/08/sports/baseball/08union.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5D71231F93BA35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fehr Expects Agreement On Testing Before Spring</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fehr Expects Agreement on Testing Before Spring</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, Dec. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donald Fehr, the executive director of the Major League Baseball Players Association, confirmed Tuesday that the union and the owners were moving toward a stricter agreement on drug testing.</p>
        <p>Fehr took a brief break from the annual players meetings at a resort hotel to announce that the executive board of the union had authorized the chief negotiators of the players association to continue working to reach an agreement with Major League Baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donald Fehr, the executive director of the M.L.B. Players Association, confirmed that the union and the owners were moving toward a stricter agreement on drug testing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Donald Fehr, the executive director of the Major League Baseball Players Association, confirmed Tuesday that the union and the owners were moving toward a stricter agreement on drug testing.</p>
        <p>Fehr took a brief break from the annual players meetings at a resort hotel to announce that the executive board of the union had authorized the chief negotiators of the players association to continue working to reach an agreement with Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>Although Fehr said the changes would be related to the various substances covered by testing and the frequency of the tests, he did not offer specifics or provide a timetable for completing the deal. He said the players were ready to try to have the changes completed before spring training.</p>
        <p>A major league official involved in the discussions said the agreement would include more tests, some during the off-season; harsher penalties; and tests for steroids and substances with steroid-like effects. The official said the deal should be in place by spring training.</p>
        <p>''The public and the fans are always among the players' highest concerns,'' Fehr said. ''We have to negotiate an appropriate agreement. I think we will. I don't think it will take an extended time.''</p>
        <p>Rob Manfred, baseball's executive vice president for labor relations and human resources, said in a telephone interview: ''We think it's a very positive step that the players are prepared to move forward in this area. Candidly, I share Don's optimism on the ability to get something done fairly soon.''</p>
        <p>The collective bargaining agreement runs through 2006, but the players and the owners have been discussing possible amendments to the drug-testing policy. After reports of grand jury testimony from Barry Bonds and Jason Giambi regarding steroid use became public, the talks have intensified and will continue next week. Fehr said the players had always intended to discuss steroids during their meetings.</p>
        <p>When Fehr was asked why the union had agreed to make changes in the basic agreement for the first time, he did not cite as reasons the statements by Bonds and Giambi, as reported in The San Francisco Chronicle last week. Instead, he spoke about being realistic and recognizing the need to make the policy stronger.</p>
        <p>Fehr said the drug testing currently in place had shown ''pretty significant positive effects.'' After 5 percent to 7 percent of the tests were positive in survey testing in 2003, Fehr said there was a major reduction in positive tests in 2004. He would not divulge the percentage, but he said he believed the current program, which was agreed to in 2002, would have demonstrated its effectiveness.</p>
        <p>''Having said that,'' Fehr said, ''that doesn't mean it can't be done better. That doesn't mean improvements can't be made. That doesn't mean you shouldn't try and go further if, after further consideration, that makes the most sense. And that's hopefully what we're going to do.''</p>
        <p>Typically, the players would seek something in return for doing something like relenting on a stricter standard for drug testing, but Fehr said, ''This is not being approached as a traditional economical issue.''</p>
        <p>His comments seemed to indicate that the players also feel steroid use has become such an explosive matter that testing needs to be strengthened.</p>
        <p>If the players and owners were to adopt the drug-testing system used in the minor leagues, players would be subjected to four unannounced tests a year, including some in the off-season. The testing would cover steroids and related substances. The punishments would be more severe than the current ones, with the first positive test incurring an unpaid 15-game suspension and the suspensions rising to 30 games, 60 games and one year. If a player tested positive a fifth time, he would be suspended permanently.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to categorize those discussions,'' said Fehr, when asked if the sides were talking about a policy comparable to the minor league one. ''I think everybody knows the kinds of issues we're talking about.''</p>
        <p>Fehr said he spoke with Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, who has criticized baseball's drug testing, and said he would talk to him again this week. They have known each other for more than 25 years and Fehr mentioned how they had discussed the merits of having a major league franchise in Phoenix in the late 1980's. McCain has said he will propose legislation in Congress if baseball does not have a new program by next month.</p>
        <p>While Fehr said he and Commissioner Bud Selig disagreed with McCain's stance on legislation, he said, ''Hopefully, the issue is not going to be alive'' in January. ''It'll be clear we're moving in the direction that is appropriate,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Fehr said all of the pertinent discussions about drug testing and steroids were completed at Tuesday's meeting, which was attended by more than 40 players. Hotel security refused to allow reporters on the premises, citing the need to protect the guests. But when the union scheduled a news conference, the hotel allowed 60 reporters and photographers on the grounds.</p>
        <p>Fehr met with the news media for 23 minutes in a conference room before returning to the meetings. He turned down an invitation to appear on the ''Today'' show on Wednesday, explaining that he would be attending another round of player meetings. Like so many people in and out of baseball, Fehr said he was hoping for a resolution on stricter testing.</p>
        <p>''I don't know exactly what the time frame would be,'' he said. ''I hope it's not going to take long.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
