<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Know It All</title>
    <meta content="21BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/21/fashion/21BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1628906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Penelope</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ettus, Samantha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Viswanathan, Neeraja</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Experts' Guide to 100 Things Everyone Should Know How to Do, the</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Street Law Handbook, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prostitution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DA113FF932A15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Know It All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Know It All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Penelope Green</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Penelope</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Penelope Green reviews books The Experts' Guide to 100 Things Everyone Should Know How to Do edited by Samantha Ettus and The Street Law Handbook: Surviving Sex, Drugs and Petty Crime by Neeraja Viswanathan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE EXPERTS' GUIDE TO 100 THINGS EVERYONE SHOULD KNOW HOW TO DO  Edited by Samantha Ettus  Clarkson Potter, $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE STREET LAW HANDBOOK  Surviving Sex, Drugs, and Petty Crime  By Neeraja Viswanathan  Bloomsbury, $15.95.</p>
        <p>EXPERT advice -- along with the careers of experts to dispense it -- has been a publishing success story at least since the 16th century, when 100 years' worth of printing practice yielded not just Bibles and the collected works of William Shakespeare but also a flurry of how-to manuals. I know this only because there's a how-to history, ''How to Do It: Guides to Good Living for Renaissance Italians,'' by Rudolph M. Bell, a history professor at Rutgers (University of Chicago Press, 2000), which traced the history of those giving advice about everything -- from the proper handling of adolescents (who in the 16th century were considered such until the age of 28) to how to conceive a girl (tie a string around one testicle) -- and in so doing revealed much about the concerns of middle-class Renaissance families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE EXPERTS' GUIDE TO 100 THINGS EVERYONE SHOULD KNOW HOW TO DOEdited by Samantha Ettus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE EXPERTS' GUIDE TO 100 THINGS EVERYONE SHOULD KNOW HOW TO DO  Edited by Samantha Ettus  Clarkson Potter, $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE STREET LAW HANDBOOK  Surviving Sex, Drugs, and Petty Crime  By Neeraja Viswanathan  Bloomsbury, $15.95.</p>
        <p>EXPERT advice -- along with the careers of experts to dispense it -- has been a publishing success story at least since the 16th century, when 100 years' worth of printing practice yielded not just Bibles and the collected works of William Shakespeare but also a flurry of how-to manuals. I know this only because there's a how-to history, ''How to Do It: Guides to Good Living for Renaissance Italians,'' by Rudolph M. Bell, a history professor at Rutgers (University of Chicago Press, 2000), which traced the history of those giving advice about everything -- from the proper handling of adolescents (who in the 16th century were considered such until the age of 28) to how to conceive a girl (tie a string around one testicle) -- and in so doing revealed much about the concerns of middle-class Renaissance families.</p>
        <p>Five hundred years later, ''The Experts' Guide to 100 Things Everyone Should Know How to Do,'' put together by Samantha Ettus, founder of Ettus Media Management, a public relations company, is its own cultural Rorschach, as well as being a good read and utterly useful.</p>
        <p>We've got babies to diaper (ask the parents of the most famous sextuplets, Becki and Keith Dilley), car oil to be changed and flags to fly. We've got lipstick to apply (ask Bobbi Brown) and hands to wash. We're busy and dirty and shy and tired; we're insecure about our manners and our jobs, but we don't know how to listen (ask Larry King) or make our beds.</p>
        <p>Anthony M. Masiello, mayor of Buffalo, and a darn funny guy, grades snow like an Eskimo, from ''fluffy light'' to ''frozen solid'' and suggests using teenagers to shovel, instead of your middle-aged body.</p>
        <p>Morris Reid, principal of an advocacy company and a former aide to Ron Brown when he was secretary of commerce, can teach you how to make conversation. He points out that you don't have to be the smartest person in the room and that such knowledge can be liberating. Look to politicians to see people who can command a group without being afraid of sounding unintelligent. Shaking hands is Letitia Baldrige's territory. If you teach your kids to do so, she coaxes, you're contributing to the socialization of America.</p>
        <p>Tim Sullivan, writing when he was president of match.com, suggests, perhaps predictably, taking an online approach to asking someone on a date, reminding would-be Cyranos always to use spell-check. A good kiss, says Barbara De Angelis, author of 13 books on relationships, means no drooling. Swallow when necessary, she exhorts.</p>
        <p>Amy Alkon, also known as the Advice Goddess, can come stay with me anytime. Her advice on how to be a good houseguest -- be neat, be quiet, leave soon -- flows from this essential truth.</p>
        <p>''People are annoying,'' she writes. ''All people. Including you, me and Jennifer Aniston. Like the rest of us, you're loud, messy, demanding and unsightly, with numerous irritating habits, which degenerate from irritating to excruciating the longer you're around.''</p>
        <p>Nearly as practical as Ms. Ettus's ''Experts' Guide'' is Neeraja Viswanathan's lawyerly guide to sex, drugs and petty crime. She's a New York lawyer who has practiced corporate litigation and criminal defense. She's got a sharp tongue and a lot of trenchant answers for those who crave more legal advice than is on offer from ''Law &amp; Order.''</p>
        <p>It's good to know that thongs are sometimes O.K. on a beach, but not in an office supply store, and that mooning is outlawed in all 50 states. In fact, in Michigan, you don't have to be seen to be charged. Intent to moon is offense enough. (Well, it's more like an existential principle: if a man moons in a car and nobody sees him, is it a crime? Yes, if he's in Michigan.) It's also helpful to know that you won't be charged for having sex in your own house if you keep the shades down, and if you pay your spouse to have sex with you the exchange is not considered prostitution, except maybe in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>California is probably the best place to be caught smoking a joint (first-time offenders are automatically sent to rehab and given probation). Las Vegas and Miami are probably the worst. The amount of drugs on your person -- whether a marijuana seed or an ounce of cocaine -- has no effect on the charge of possession, contrary to popular belief. And selling fake drugs carries the same penalty as an attempt to sell the real stuff.</p>
        <p>Ms. Viswanathan's best lesson? A gentle prod to consider a career switch if you find yourself breaking the law -- and getting caught -- often.</p>
        <p>And meditate, dear reader, on the words of Linda Cobb, host of the cable show ''Talking Dirty With the Queen of Clean,'' and one of the 100 experts in ''The Experts' Guide'':</p>
        <p>''To stain is human, to remove it, divine.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
