<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You, Too, Could Write a Poem</title>
    <meta content="21ORRL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/21/books/review/21ORRL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1628704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orr, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heninian, Lyn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Best American Poetry 2004, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Best American Poetry 2004 (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DE1F3CF932A15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You, Too, Could Write a Poem</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Best American Poetry 2004': You, Too, Could Write a Poem</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Orr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Orr reviews book The Best American Poetry 2004, edited by Lyn Hejinian; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BEST AMERICAN POETRY 2004</p>
        <p>Edited by Lyn Hejinian.</p>
        <p>278 pp. Scribner Poetry. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The idea of poetry as a community activity is the best thing about the Best American Poetry series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BEST AMERICAN POETRY 2004</p>
        <p>Edited by Lyn Hejinian.</p>
        <p>278 pp. Scribner Poetry. $30.</p>
        <p>It's autumn again, the time of year when small gnats mourn among the river sallows, when the oven bird says the early petal-fall is past, when the wind moves like a cripple among the leaves -- and when some beleaguered editor attempts to cobble together 250 or so pages of new poetry that will pass muster with shoppers at Barnes &amp; Noble. Yes, it's time again for ''The Best American Poetry,'' the legendary series that is now in its 18th edition, including Harold Bloom's ''Best of the Best'' version from 1997. As poetry fans know, each edition offers all of the finest poetic moments of the past year, so long as they come in the form of one poem each by around 70 writers of varying skill, as chosen by an editor who is a famous poet with favors to trade and axes to grind. In the past, this simple yet elegant formula has produced such editorial highlights as Bloom's assault on the selections made by Adrienne Rich (''of a badness not to be believed''), the appearances of several editors' spouses, the appearances of many editors' buddies and the inclusion of poems by John Ashbery or Donald Hall in nearly every volume, including the one compiled by John Ashbery himself (l'état, c'est moi!).</p>
        <p>The editor this time is Lyn Hejinian, who seems to represent a departure for the series (not where Ashbery's concerned, though; you'll find him here between ''Arnold, Craig'' and ''Bang, Mary Jo''). Hejinian is a Berkeley professor often identified with American ''experimental poetry,'' a phrase that serves as a catchall for an assortment of avant-gardists who take their cues from Gertrude Stein, Ezra Pound, some lesser known modernists, various French theorists and the Language poetry movement of the 1970's and 80's. These writers embrace fragmentation and the deliberate use of nonsense, they generally resist traditional forms (unless they're using them in untraditional ways) and they often think of themselves as opposing a ''mainstream'' poetry culture that supposedly remains devoted to moist lyric epiphanies. Considering that the Best American series is about as mainstream as poetry gets, it's tempting to view Hejinian's editorship as a signal that the guerrilla fighters are now riding into town to become sheriffs.</p>
        <p>There are several problems with this picture, though, and the first is one that has long troubled American poets: for the average, engaged reader (the Best American's target audience), even fairly accessible poems can be maddeningly arcane. The second problem, which is related to the first, is that in the poetry world, even the insiders are outsiders. As it happens, poets who could reasonably be called ''experimental'' are currently sitting in Chancellors' seats at the Academy of American Poets, occupying faculty lounges from Buffalo to Berkeley, and of course, editing the Best American Poetry. To the extent there's a Poetry Establishment, these writers have been as much a part of it as anyone else for decades now.</p>
        <p>Still, not all parts view the whole the same way. For poets, the notable distinction of this Best American edition will be that it contains nothing from such traditional sources as Poetry, The Paris Review or The Yale Review, and is instead chock-full of work from newer magazines like SHINY and POOL and No: A Journal of the Arts. To put the adventurousness of this editorial decision in perspective, however, consider that the circulation of Pool is approximately 1,000; for The Yale Review it's 7,000; and for Cat Fancy it's 240,000. And if this year's editor has scorned The Paris Review, she hasn't exactly passed up the known for the unknown: of the 75 writers here, 41 have previously appeared in a version of ''Best American Poetry,'' a typical ratio for the series.</p>
        <p>As for the poems themselves, they run the usual gamut from very good to slightly dull to what-were-you-thinking, with a few more in the latter two categories than usual. Hejinian has favored assertively avant-garde writing but made an effort to include writers from other camps as well -- Kim Addonizio, John Hollander and Robert Pinsky, for example. The poems range from 22 words (Carl Rakosi) to 13 pages (Fanny Howe); they are, as you might expect, rarely written in traditional forms (Frederick Seidel's disturbing ''Love Song'' is an exception); and they're often more interested in peculiar surface effects ('' 'Let's be logical.'/ Your panties.'') than in constructing a reliable voice. This is poetry short on anecdote, long on implied quotation marks. And while much of the work is preoccupied with the idea of playfulness, the best poems are the ones that actually know how to play. Consider Olena Kalytiak Davis's moody and engaging ''You Art a Scholar, Horatio, Speak To It,'' a 29-couplet poem that begins:</p>
        <p>You say you walk and sew alone?</p>
        <p>I walk and sew alone.</p>
        <p>You say you gape and waver?</p>
        <p>I am mostly dizzy, most open-mouthed.</p>
        <p>You say you taste it with each dish?</p>
        <p>I drink it and I spit it up.</p>
        <p>You say it lays you face-down?</p>
        <p>I kiss the dirt.</p>
        <p>Oni Buchanan's macabre poem ''The Walk'' and Aaron Fogel's ''337,000, December, 2000'' are similarly vivid and unforced.</p>
        <p>When the poems here are less successful, it's often because a preprogrammed wonkiness has prevented them from offering us the challenge they'd like to make. Instead, the poem will fall upon its own cutting edge in a way that recalls the uncomfortable moment in ''The Matrix Reloaded'' when it becomes obvious that beneath the supercool trench coat of Morpheus beats the heart of a very nerdy man. This is a persistent problem for self-consciously avant-garde writing. One of the most heralded experimental poems is Michael Palmer's ''Sun'' (''The Best American Poetry 1989''), which includes such observations as ''For a dollar I will have text with you and answer three questions.'' Don't trust the Oracle, Neo; she's been reading way too much Barthes.</p>
        <p>Which leads to the question we ask every year: Could this really be the ''best'' poetry in America? Like the previous editors in this series, Hejinian has her doubts: ''Certainly no single poem in this volume is definitive,'' she writes, ''not of 'bestness,' nor of what's 'American,' nor of 'poetry.' '' Anyone who thinks about these concepts for more than two seconds realizes this is true, if only because poetry has never distributed its ''bestness'' equally among 75 writers in a given year. What this series really stands for isn't excellence, aesthetic or otherwise, but the idea of poetry as a community activity. ''People are writing poems!,'' each volume cries. ''You, too, could write a poem!'' It's an appealingly democratic pose, and it has always been the genuinely ''best'' thing about the Best American series. The only problem is that poetry isn't really an open system; it's a combination of odd institutions, personal networks, hoary traditions, talent and blind luck. It's both an art and a guild, in other words. And if basic participation is possible for anyone with a heartbeat and a laptop, the requirements for the deluxe plan -- the true ''Best American'' plan, if you will -- are obscure to all but a handful. The negotiation between what we now call the ''best'' and what we'll later call the ''great'' never ends; each year, ''The Best American Poetry'' offers a new compromise, and each year the truce is broken, the sides are marshaled, and the old argument begins again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
