<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leave the Senate Behind</title>
    <meta content="21RGLROSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/21/opinion/opinionspecial/21RGLrosen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1628802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rosen, Hilary</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DB133FF932A15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leave the Senate Behind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leave the Senate Behind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HILARY ROSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosen, Hilary</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Clinton appears to have decided to run for Senate again. Presumably, she has been persuaded that a 2006 re-election campaign will not harm her possible bid for the presidency in 2008. But some Democrats, including me, think she shouldn't run for re-election.</p>
        <p>A Clinton senatorial campaign is likely to be the most bruising and high-stakes race of 2006. The Republicans will put everything they have into attacking Mrs. Clinton, knowing that whatever damage they can inflict will pay dividends for them in 2008. They will try to wrap a liberal skin around her so tightly that it will be impossible for her to emerge from it a year later, when she would be campaigning for the White House. And remember: a Democratic senator from New York has to take lots of liberal positions to keep the base happy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Hillary Clinton's goal is to run for president in 2008, she shouldn't run for the Senate in 2006.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Clinton appears to have decided to run for Senate again. Presumably, she has been persuaded that a 2006 re-election campaign will not harm her possible bid for the presidency in 2008. But some Democrats, including me, think she shouldn't run for re-election.</p>
        <p>A Clinton senatorial campaign is likely to be the most bruising and high-stakes race of 2006. The Republicans will put everything they have into attacking Mrs. Clinton, knowing that whatever damage they can inflict will pay dividends for them in 2008. They will try to wrap a liberal skin around her so tightly that it will be impossible for her to emerge from it a year later, when she would be campaigning for the White House. And remember: a Democratic senator from New York has to take lots of liberal positions to keep the base happy.</p>
        <p>All this is especially frustrating because Senator Clinton is not such a liberal. This is the woman who supported her husband's push for the welfare-reform legislation that was vehemently opposed by her mentor, Marian Wright Edelman of the Children's Defense Fund. Knowing that it would anger the liberals, she nevertheless chose a moderate path. And contrary to the perception that she favored a government takeover of the health-care system, she has worked to expand the eligibility for existing coverage to more families and children.</p>
        <p>Indeed, her experience with health-care reform helped teach her that most people prefer incremental change to ambitious overhauls. Those who are paying attention know that her approach to helping the economy of upstate New York is dominated by Republican-like tax-credit and loan-guarantee proposals for employers that create jobs -- not proposals to increase old-fashioned government job grants. And she has shown a willingness to compromise and to work with Republicans in the Capitol. Her Senate colleagues view her as a congenial and shrewd politician. Her speeches are not fiery, moralistic or ideological but filled with pragmatic reasoning.</p>
        <p>She is pro-choice -- and so are most people in the country. But she can talk about social issues in a way most Democrats can't. When she speaks about gay and lesbian issues, for instance, she sounds like a middle-American mom searching for the right way to be fair and inclusive without feeling uncomfortable. That is an attitude many in America share right now.</p>
        <p>What's more, she doesn't need to create a platform for her moral values. She already has one. One that balances faith -- an uncontrived faith -- and politics. With no patience for political correctness, she knows how to relate to people across a broad spectrum of beliefs. In short, she comes across as the moderate Midwestern Methodist she is.</p>
        <p>Senator Clinton's campaign in 2000 was a lesson in the value of star wattage. But it also showed how she operates. She didn't begin by announcing what she could do for her constituency as a senator. She shared some core values and then went on a listening tour. It was a smart and modest instinct.</p>
        <p>If there were ever a time that Democrats need to listen to Americans, it is now. That's why Senator Clinton should spend the next two years in the Senate burnishing her foreign policy credentials and staking out some good territory in the increasingly right-wing Republican Senate.</p>
        <p>Then she should leave the Senate behind.</p>
        <p>Instead of getting tangled up in what would probably be a costly, contentious, toxic race, she should get out in the heartland to connect with voters. If she gives the American people the attention she gave New Yorkers, they will see a woman who has the spirit needed to get though difficult times -- and the vision to be a leader.</p>
        <p>Don't get me wrong. If Hillary Clinton has decided to run for re-election because she loves being the senator from New York, she can and should win. She has worked hard for New Yorkers and deserves re-election. But if her goal is to run for president in 2008, she shouldn't run for the Senate in 2006. Politicians with higher ambitions often stay in political office to make sure they have a platform for their ideas. That rule doesn't apply to Senator Clinton. She doesn't need to be in the Senate in 2007 to get attention -- from donors or from anyone else.</p>
        <p>There will be other Democrats who may vie for leadership as we approach 2008. John Edwards, Bill Richardson, Evan Bayh, Howard Dean, maybe even Al Gore or John Kerry. But many people are counting on Mrs. Clinton. And she needs to be prepared. Instead of running, she should walk -- across America.</p>
        <p>Hilary Rosen, the former chief executive of the Recording Industry Association of America, is a political commentator for CNBC and a Democratic strategist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Hilary Rosen, the former chief executive of the Recording Industry Association of America, is a political commentator for CNBC and a Democratic strategist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
