<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Trends Come and Go, A Swiss Tradition Endures</title>
    <meta content="17wedineWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1790595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/OSSINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brasserie Swiss (Ossining, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denitto, Emily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DC1231F934A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Trends Come and Go, A Swiss Tradition Endures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY DeNITTO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Denitto, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Emily DeNitto reviews Brasserie Swiss restaurant in Ossining, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VERENA and Rolf Baumgartner have been married for 34 years and have run Brasserie Swiss for nearly 29. One imagines that entering the Ossining restaurant is like visiting their home, with its upright piano against one wall, pictures of Switzerland everywhere and soft yodeling playing in the background.</p>
        <p>It is a comfortable, friendly place and -- this is the key to its appeal -- emphatically untrendy. There is no chocolate lava cake or the latest take on pan-seared sea bass. Instead, you'll find authentic, delicious interpretations of traditional Swiss favorites. The menu and décor may not have changed in decades, but both are presented with care and love.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VERENA and Rolf Baumgartner have been married for 34 years and have run Brasserie Swiss for nearly 29. One imagines that entering the Ossining restaurant is like visiting their home, with its upright piano against one wall, pictures of Switzerland everywhere and soft yodeling playing in the background.</p>
        <p>It is a comfortable, friendly place and -- this is the key to its appeal -- emphatically untrendy. There is no chocolate lava cake or the latest take on pan-seared sea bass. Instead, you'll find authentic, delicious interpretations of traditional Swiss favorites. The menu and décor may not have changed in decades, but both are presented with care and love.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baumgartner, the chef, thinks about each dish as a whole. So the Wiener schnitzel comes with a slice of lemon, a curl of anchovy creating a bowl around its edge to hold in a spoonful of capers. The tender piece of veal (not pork, as you'll find at many restaurants) is perfectly fried and lovely on its own, but combine it with the rest and the tastes hit a whole new level.</p>
        <p>Wiener schnitzel, lamb chops and bratwurst (excellent, from a Colorado butcher) are accompanied by crisp rösti -- a kind of hash browns -- made only with Idaho potatoes. Geschnetzeltes (strips of veal in a cream sauce) and jagerschnitzel (pork chops in brown sauce) come with spaetzle, which are tiny, light pastalike dumplings that help cushion the food and amplify its flavors.</p>
        <p>These days, most entrees are accompanied by an array of late summer vegetables. Yellow squash, zucchini, carrots, cauliflower, broccoli and green peppers are sautéed together. But it's the red cabbage side that nearly steals the show. Mr. Baumgartner marinates the cabbage in balsamic vinegar and red wine with apples and seasonings, then mixes it with garlic and onions sautéed in duck fat. The result is a sweet, savory, rich pleasure that could stand as a dish on its own.</p>
        <p>Lighter fare is available -- broiled salmon was a recent special and shrimp côte d'azur (shrimp in a tomato and garlic sauce over rice) and sole almandine are on the regular menu. A complimentary salad is also served before each entree, with a vinaigrette dressing made with an unlikely but welcome hint of curry. But the heartier offerings make the biggest mark, starting with the appetizers. Raclette valeisanne (a kind of potato and cheese mini casserole) and snails bourguignon were complex and wonderful. Onion soup came covered in melted, slightly browned Gruyère. Creamed herring salad was a favorite among the cold hors d'oeuvres.</p>
        <p>Even the desserts are best when richest. Chocolate mousse, made with a hint of rum, was cloudlike, with chunks of chocolate mixed in. Apple strudel had a flaky pastry and fragrant filling that included walnuts and white raisins. Cherries marinated in sweet wine were a terrific take on the Swiss classic.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baumgartner is the hostess and she's an enthusiastic interpreter of Swiss culture. Ask her about the large Alpine horns on the walls or about Swiss culinary preferences and she will have stories to tell. When the kitchen slows down, her husband comes out to the dining room and makes a point of visiting every table, happy to answer questions or just say hi.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's outside could use fresh paint and there are times when a mustiness can invade the food as well (twice in recent weeks, the rolls were stale and a piece of carrot cake, made off premises, was dry). And in keeping with its old-school charm, Brasserie Swiss does not make a great cup of cappuccino or even American-style coffee. Sanka is available. But I wouldn't have it any other way. The restaurant makes you think about how food can transport you to a different time and place. The trip to Brasserie Swiss is fun, and more often than not, satisfying.</p>
        <p>Brasserie Swiss</p>
        <p>118 Croton Avenue  Ossining  (914) 941-0319</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- A 70's time warp, with dark paneled walls and a separate old-school bar.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Mostly older couples and families with a connection to Switzerland.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Full service. The wine list is compact and mainly European with a few California brands. Prices range from $22 to $65 a bottle.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch entrees, $10 to $18.50; dinner entrees, $18.50 to $42.50 (for cheese fondue for two).</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Raclette valeisanne, snails bourguignon, Buendnerfleisch, herring salad, bratwurst, wiener schnitzel, lamb chops, capon, jagerschnitzel, chocolate mousse, apple strudel, coupe cherry swiss.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch, Tuesday to Friday, noon to 2:30. Dinner, Tuesday to Saturday, 5:30 to 10:30 p.m.; Sunday, 4 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Reviewed Sept. 17, 2006</p>
        <p>DINING/OSSINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
