<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinching Proves No Cinch as the Mets Are Derailed Again</title>
    <meta content="17mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1790895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D81331F934A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinching Proves No Cinch as the Mets Are Derailed Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, Sept. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 100 dedicated souls parked themselves behind the Mets' dugout before batting practice and screamed as if they were trying to make more noise than the 7 train. They shouted for David Wright, Carlos Beltrán and several others, shouts that were really pleas for the Mets to make history.</p>
        <p>What those fans wanted to witness was the Mets rumbling past the Pirates to clinch a National League East division that has been under their control for months. Once the inevitable occurred, the Mets and their eager fans could spend the next two weeks dreaming about a memorable October.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 100 dedicated souls parked themselves behind the Mets' dugout before batting practice and screamed as if they were trying to make more noise than the 7 train. They shouted for David Wright, Carlos Beltrán and several others, shouts that were really pleas for the Mets to make history.</p>
        <p>What those fans wanted to witness was the Mets rumbling past the Pirates to clinch a National League East division that has been under their control for months. Once the inevitable occurred, the Mets and their eager fans could spend the next two weeks dreaming about a memorable October.</p>
        <p>That inevitability, that official stamp, will have to wait at least one more day as the Pirates defeated the Mets, 3-2, and made sure their Champagne would continue chilling at PNC Park. It was another anxious, frustrating night for the Mets, one more night of putting a long-awaited celebration on hold.</p>
        <p>In a season that has lacked much recent drama because the Mets have been in first place for 164 consecutive days, there was some drama Saturday night. But the Pirates supplied it. Ronny Paulino's two-out double against Aaron Heilman kissed the left-center-field fence in the ninth inning and drove in Joe Randa from first base for the winning run.</p>
        <p>Instead of the Mets dancing by the mound and celebrating a division title that will soon be theirs, the Pirates mobbed Randa at the plate and celebrated their 62nd victory as if it pushed them into the postseason.</p>
        <p>All the Mets needed for the past two days was a victory against a team with one of the worst records in baseball or a loss by the Philadelphia Phillies and they would have become the first major league team to reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernández was superb for seven innings, but the Mets were baffled by two left-handed rookies who have a combined 11 appearances in their careers. Tom Gorzelanny and Shane Youman tamed the Mets on two runs in seven innings to match Hernández's effort.</p>
        <p>Carlos Delgado doubled in a run in the first, but Jason Bay countered with a bases-empty home run against Hernández in the second. The Pirates took a 2-1 lead in the fourth as Bay singled, stole second and scored on Ryan Doumit's single. The Mets tied the score in the fifth on Delgado's second run-scoring hit. The score stayed tied until Paulino's 400-foot double against Heilman.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph was relaxed before the game and mused that the Mets might not clinch the division until they returned to Shea Stadium for an eight-game home stand that begins Monday. If the Mets lose to Pittsburgh on Sunday and the Phillies win again, the clinching would undoubtedly happen next week at Shea.</p>
        <p>Beltrán was so uninterested in what the Phillies were doing on Saturday that he did not even realize they had an afternoon game.</p>
        <p>''They're playing today?'' Beltran said. ''Are they winning? Losing?''</p>
        <p>Because the Fox affiliate here showed the game between the Yankees and the Boston Red Sox, the Phillies-Astros game was not on the three televisions in the Mets' clubhouse, the two in the weight room or the one in the manager's office. The Mets were mostly interested in the college football game between Notre Dame and Michigan.</p>
        <p>As the Mets have moved toward a postseason spot, Pedro Martínez has been one of their most vital players, but right now he is their biggest question mark. For the Mets to be as formidable as they can be, Martínez must be productive, not unpredictable.</p>
        <p>He needed 68 pitches to get nine outs against the Pirates in a 5-3 loss Friday, a troublesome outing that caused him to bury his face in a towel in the dugout. Martínez, who had not pitched since Aug. 14 because of a strained right calf, said he was ''about to snap and let it all out.'' He was still upset Saturday.</p>
        <p>''I won't watch that game ever again,'' Martínez said.</p>
        <p>Martínez had said that the two starts he had remaining would be enough to enable him to be ready for the postseason. But he acknowledged that he needed to accomplish a lot in those outings.</p>
        <p>''Three innings is not enough to try to go seven in the first game in the playoffs,'' Martínez said. ''So you have to build the stamina, you have to get command of your pitches, you got to feel stronger.''</p>
        <p>When Randolph was asked if Martínez had had has enough time to get comfortable for the postseason, the answer was interesting.</p>
        <p>''I hope so,'' Randolph said. ''Pedro is very unique. You really can't put him in any kind of category or the normal way people do things. Guys like him, who am I to say he won't be ready in two starts?</p>
        <p>As long as Martínez's calf is fine and he is otherwise healthy, Randolph said he would remain the No. 1 starter for the playoffs. Presumably, that means Martínez could get bruised twice more and he would still be on the mound for the Mets' first playoff game in six years.</p>
        <p>A few minutes after Martínez ended an interview with reporters, the final score of the Phillies' game emanated from one TV. The Mets did not react. They were reading newspapers, playing video games and watching college football. They were getting ready to win the division. They will try again on Sunday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
