<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travel Advisory; Deals and Discounts</title>
    <meta content="28SHELL2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/03/travel/03deals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1509026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siano, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DC1E39F930A3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travel Advisory; Deals and Discounts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Deals and Discounts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH SIANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siano, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deals and Discounts column on fall vacation packages in US (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the summer vacation season moves into fall, vacationers have a choice of offers in various regions of the country.</p>
        <p>WYOMING ON HORSEBACK -- Through Sept. 7, the 129-room Teton Mountain Lodge in Jackson Hole, Wyo., has a four-night package aimed at would-be cowpokes. For $365 a person and up, it includes four nights in a one-bedroom suite with a fully equipped kitchen, a one-hour horseback ride into Grand Teton National Park, tickets to the Jackson Hole Rodeo and dinner at the Bar J Chuckwagon featuring live Western music. This price is based on four people in a room and includes all taxes; (800) 801-6615 or www.tetonlodge.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the summer vacation season moves into fall, vacationers have a choice of offers in various regions of the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the summer vacation season moves into fall, vacationers have a choice of offers in various regions of the country.</p>
        <p>WYOMING ON HORSEBACK -- Through Sept. 7, the 129-room Teton Mountain Lodge in Jackson Hole, Wyo., has a four-night package aimed at would-be cowpokes. For $365 a person and up, it includes four nights in a one-bedroom suite with a fully equipped kitchen, a one-hour horseback ride into Grand Teton National Park, tickets to the Jackson Hole Rodeo and dinner at the Bar J Chuckwagon featuring live Western music. This price is based on four people in a room and includes all taxes; (800) 801-6615 or www.tetonlodge.com.</p>
        <p>FREE NIGHT IN MIAMI -- The Four Seasons Hotel Miami is scheduled to open Oct. 1, and as an introduction, it will provide three nights lodging for the cost of two, from Oct. 15 to Jan. 31; availability is limited. Rates at the 221-room hotel will start at $325 a night. The hotel, on Brickell Avenue, overlooks Biscayne Bay, and has three pools, a fitness club and a spa; (800) 332-3442 or www.fourseasons.com/miami.</p>
        <p>EXTRAS ON OAHU -- The recently refurbished Waikiki Parc Hotel in Honolulu has a Parc Sunrise Bonus Package that includes a rental car, parking and full buffet breakfast for $199 a night, with a promise of an ocean view. The car is a compact from Dollar, with pickup and return at the airport; gasoline, insurance and hotel taxes extra. The offer is available to Dec. 25. The 297-room hotel has a heated rooftop pool and exercise room; (800) 422-0450 or www.waikikiparc.com.</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND BY SAIL -- Four New England cruises on the Arabella, a 160-foot schooner with 20 staterooms, are being sold at two-for-one prices for last-minute bookings. Trips are Aug. 14 to 19, Aug. 28 to Sept. 2, Sept. 12 to 17 and Sept. 18 to 23. All trips are from Newport, R.I., and all but the last include stops at Martha's Vineyard, Nantucket and Cuttyhunk Island. The last departure is a wine-tasting trip along Rhode Island, Connecticut and Long Island. Rates for two are $999 or $1,299 with the discount. Contact Classic Cruises of Newport at (800)395-1343 or www.cruisearabella.com. Similar discounts (at higher base prices) are available for Caribbean sailings on Dec. 21 to 27, Jan. 11 to 17 and other dates.</p>
        <p>FLOATING ON LAKE POWELL -- For those who can travel from Aug. 25 to Nov. 1, Lake Powell Resorts and Marinas is giving those who rent houseboats for four days or more a choice: free use of an 18-foot powerboat or 25 percent off the rent al price. The lake, on the border of Utah and Arizona, has almost 100 major redrock canyons to explore. Four-day rentals are $2,924 to $4,342 before the discount. Restrictions apply. Information: (888) 486-4665 or www.lakepowell.com.</p>
        <p>JOSEPH SIANO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
