<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Primary Credit Goes To 49ers' Secondary</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON REDSKINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DC1F3AF930A25752C0A967958260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Primary Credit Goes To 49ers' Secondary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Jan. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he was done explaining the intricacies of the play that may have saved the day for the San Francisco 49ers, Johnny Jackson stopped, looked up slowly at a questioner and finally smiled.</p>
        <p>Would he be fined, someone wanted to know, for being out of position on the interception that ruined a third-quarter drive today by the Washington Redskins?</p>
        <p>Jackson shook his head.</p>
        <p>"I hope not," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he was done explaining the intricacies of the play that may have saved the day for the San Francisco 49ers, Johnny Jackson stopped, looked up slowly at a questioner and finally smiled.</p>
        <p>Would he be fined, someone wanted to know, for being out of position on the interception that ruined a third-quarter drive today by the Washington Redskins?</p>
        <p>Jackson shook his head.</p>
        <p>"I hope not," he said.</p>
        <p>It isn't likely. Jackson dulled what looked like an important march by the Redskins. Rather than a touchdown, they wound up with nothing. Rather than a comeback victory, they left with a 28-10 loss to the 49ers, who advanced to the conference title game next week at Candlestick Park. End-Zone Heists</p>
        <p>Jackson's interception was the first of two end-zone heists by the 49ers in the second half that dashed Washington's attempts at a rally. In the fourth quarter, Darryl Pollard took away a pass intended for Ricky Sanders, who slipped on a corner pattern. And on the Redskins' next drive, with time quickly running down, Eric Davis, a reserve left cornerback, prevented Gary Clark from a touchdown catch with a dive in the corner of the end zone to knock away the ball.</p>
        <p>But those three plays did not necessarily represent the kind of day it actually became for the 49ers' secondary. Although they intercepted three Mark Rypien passes, the Washington quarterback still threw for 361 yards, completing 27 of 48. Art Monk had 10 receptions for 163 yards. Clark caught 6, Sanders 4.</p>
        <p>"Give their offense all the credit," Pollard said. "It was like playing against us. They've got three great receivers, and their quarterback can get the job done. When we got a bye and had to practice against ourselves all week, it was probably the best thing that could have happened."</p>
        <p>Still, the secondary was what kept the Redskins helpless as the afternoon grew late. No play might have been more important than Jackson's, since it came with the Redskins behind, 21-10, and needing to score with less than seven minutes left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Jackson, who conceded later that he should have been elsewhere, found himself chasing an uncovered Monk into the corner of the end zone on a third-down play. Rypien's throw was short, and Jackson, who usually plays only when the 49ers use five defensive backs, cut in front for a diving interception.</p>
        <p>"The ball was snapped, and I looked and saw the tight end block and the quarterback start to roll out," Jackson said. "Monk went to the corner, and I was just fortunate to get out there. He was open for a second, and I'm not sure Rypien saw me at all. That's what caused me to go out there."</p>
        <p>It may have crippled the Redskins' momentum, too. A touchdown would have cut the deficit to 4 points. Instead, when they saw the ball again, there were just 42 seconds remaining in the third quarter, and they were still behind by 11.</p>
        <p>"It might have been the turning point," Jackson said. "They were driving on us. It had to hurt them a little, but they're a good team. We knew they weren't going to quit."</p>
        <p>But if they didn't then, they might have folded emotionally after Pollard's interception. It came with the Redskins at the San Francisco 15-yard line with a first down. There were still 12 minutes left in the game.</p>
        <p>Sanders, though, slipped as he began his corner route, and Pollard was there -- alone -- to make the catch. It was simple, really. 'I Had My Eyes on It'</p>
        <p>"I can't count the times we've seen them try that play," said Pollard, a starter at cornerback. Was he fearful he might drop the ball?</p>
        <p>"The last thing on my mind was dropping it," he said. "I watched it come into my lap all the way. I had my eyes on it."</p>
        <p>The defensive play by Davis appeared open to question since he might have been called for pass interference on Clark. But there was no flag.</p>
        <p>"I didn't think it was a catchable ball," Davis said. "I turned and looked, and then he threw the ball. It was over both our heads. Maybe that's why they didn't call it. I was just going for the ball like he was."  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
