<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dialing for Data</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRODIGY (ELECTRONIC INFORMATION AND HOME SHOPPING SYSTEM)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D91730F931A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dialing for Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME OF the best new educational software does not come in a box. It comes over the telephone lines.</p>
        <p>Using a personal computer, a modem and a standard telephone line, a parent or teacher can tap into information services for a rich assortment of software at minimal cost. Several such systems, including Compuserve, Dialog, America Online and Genie, offer features for children as well as adults. But the best in terms of educational as well as dollar value is the Prodigy Information Services on-line network.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME OF the best new educational software does not come in a box. It comes over the telephone lines.</p>
        <p>Using a personal computer, a modem and a standard telephone line, a parent or teacher can tap into information services for a rich assortment of software at minimal cost. Several such systems, including Compuserve, Dialog, America Online and Genie, offer features for children as well as adults. But the best in terms of educational as well as dollar value is the Prodigy Information Services on-line network.</p>
        <p>The software needed to gain access to Prodigy costs about $30 at most major software stores, and versions are available for DOS and Macintosh computers. Then, for $12.95 a month, or $9.95 a month if purchased a year at a time, a Prodigy user has unlimited access to educational programs, news services, research data bases, games and other information sources that can keep children and their parents occupied for hours a day. The programs reside in Prodigy's computers in White Plains, N.Y., and the user taps into those computers using the modem.</p>
        <p>However, because of a technology called packet switching, it does not necessarily require a long-distance telephone call to connect to Prodigy's computers. In most larger cities Prodigy can be reached by calling a local access number. Users in smaller towns may have to call long distance -- but only to the nearest big city. Wide Range of Choices</p>
        <p>Once connected, the user's computer lights up with colorful graphics and a wide assortment of choices, the following among them:</p>
        <p>"Reading Magic Library," created for Prodigy by Tom Snyder Productions. Essentially an electronic storybook, with text and colorful graphics on each "page," "Reading Magic" is intended to be a collaborative effort of parents and their children. Indeed, as with all of Mr. Snyder's highly regarded software, this one uses clever plot twists and lots of puns that will hold everyone's attention.</p>
        <p>Familiar stories such as "Hansel and Gretel" are recast for today's readers. The children leave home because the parents are too busy to play with them, and they wander into the woods. There they stumble upon a house made of television sets, inhabited by a robot named Switch. The protagonists are hypnotized by television, until Gretel discovers a secret room -- a library -- and breaks the spell by reading a book.</p>
        <p>At several points readers decide how the story will unfold. Should Hansel follow Switch into the video game room, or should he stay with Gretel? Should the children go into the woods, or should they take a raft down the river?</p>
        <p>A new "Reading Magic" title is added to Prodigy each month.</p>
        <p>"Where in the World Is Carmen Sandiego," an on-line version of the popular PC program, written specifically for Prodigy. In this adventure Carmen Sandiego is the head of an international crime organization called V.I.L.E. that steals important, or sometimes just plain odd, national treasures.</p>
        <p>Because electronic books and games can be "published" more quickly than conventional books, Prodigy's "Carmen" is very topical. For example, during the Wimbledon tennis tournament a V.I.L.E. henchman might steal the net from Center Court ("A Net Loss," the headlines say). New games are added regularly. Geography Lessons</p>
        <p>In the course of tracking down Carmen's dacoits, the young detective must travel from city to city gathering clues, which are interspersed with geography and cultural lessons. Many teachers have observed that regular "Carmen" players know far more about geography than their parents -- assuming that their parents don't play.</p>
        <p>"Nova," an electronic version of the popular Public Television program, tailored to the needs of younger students. Just as the television show explores topics of interest in both science and nature, Prodigy's "Nova" allows children to explore a wide variety of topics. Their new knowledge is tested with on-line quizzes.</p>
        <p>Other selections include an on-line encyclopedia that can be of use in research projects, a political data base that helps children understand the upcoming election issues, a Weekly Reader section that encourages children to write their own stories, trivia games and a "clubhouse" with which youngsters nationwide can exchange electronic messages.</p>
        <p>Beyond the educational games and resources, Prodigy offers the latest national and international news, plus electronic articles on various issues. There is also an electronic mail service that allows users of Prodigy to send and receive messages among themselves. Many schools have made use of the electronic mail feature to coordinate projects with other schools. Several Drawbacks</p>
        <p>There are several drawbacks to Prodigy. Using it, for example, can tie up a telephone line for hours at a time. And the "call waiting" telephone feature offered in many areas must be disabled, because an incoming call generates a "click" that disrupts computer data transmissions. Disabling call-waiting is simple -- just dial *70 (star seven zero) at the start of the call. The service is automatically restored at the end of the call.</p>
        <p>Also, Prodigy includes paid advertising on each screen, a practice that allows the overall cost of the service to be kept low. Many parents and teachers, however, are concerned about exposing children to advertising in an educational setting. A second-grade teacher at my local school addresses the issue by having the class discuss the merits and the demerits of advertising before students use Prodigy.</p>
        <p>Because it has color graphics on each screen, Prodigy takes much longer to move from one screen to the next than do other on-line services. Using a faster modem helps, but faster modems are more expensive and not all local access telephone numbers will support the higher speeds.</p>
        <p>For information on tapping into Prodigy call Prodigy Information Services Inc. at 1-800-PRODIGY (1-800-776-3449).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
