<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Muddle of Insider Trading Regulation</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSIDERS INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISCH, JILL E (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE1638F937A15752C1A967958260" item-length="386" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Muddle of Insider Trading Regulation</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Insider Trading With Impunity?" (Forum, Oct. 27) states that the result in United States v. Chestman is incongruous because the defendant was found guilty of violating Securities and Exchange Commission Rule 14e-3, which prohibits trading with information of a forthcoming tender offer, but not guilty of general insider trading. The article says the anomalous decision is the result of Congressional and S.E.C. reluctance to define insider trading.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Insider Trading With Impunity?" (Forum, Oct. 27) states that the result in United States v. Chestman is incongruous because the defendant was found guilty of violating Securities and Exchange Commission Rule 14e-3, which prohibits trading with information of a forthcoming tender offer, but not guilty of general insider trading. The article says the anomalous decision is the result of Congressional and S.E.C. reluctance to define insider trading.</p>
        <p>The problem is not that simple. Traditional insider trading liability is based on the theory that an insider may not trade on nonpublic information because such trading compromises the insider's fiduciary obligations to the corporation. Many who traded on inside information, however, were not traditional corporate insiders. To deal with this, courts began to articulate an alternative basis for insider trading liability. The misappropriation theory considers a trade fraudulent if the trader obtains or uses information in breach of any relationship of trust and confidence. In the Chestman case, the Government sought to prove that Keith Loeb, a son-in-law of Ira Waldbaum, violating a relationship of trust and confidence with his wife by tipping his broker, Robert Chestman, about a forthcoming tender offer for Waldbaum Inc. The Government sought to predicate Mr. Chestman's liability not on a breach of the traditional corporate insider's duty but on Mr. Loeb's breach of this spousal duty.</p>
        <p>Misappropriation theory creates a legal fiction -- that the evil connected with insider trading is the harm it inflicts on the source of the information. Many observers, however, condemn insider trading for damaging market integrity or cheating investors.</p>
        <p>Is insider trading fraudulent if it does not involve a breach of duty? The court never dealt explicitly with the question of whether insider trading without a breach of duty is fraudulent. Clearly, Congress could enact a statutory definition of insider trading eliminating the requirement of a breach of duty. Less clear is whether, in the absence of such a breach, trading on nonpublic information is wrong. Congress continues to struggle with that question. JILL E. FISCH  New York, Nov. 7  The author is an associate professor at Fordham University School of Law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
