<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; The Right Thing</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="639975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOMALIA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOMALIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERBERT, BOB</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC133BF933A25753C1A965958260" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; The Right Thing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERBERT, BOB</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton is swimming in treacherous political waters with his latest Somalia policy. Another combat disaster in Mogadishu -- the loss of a large number of Americans, the taking of additional hostages -- would present an enormous threat to his Presidency.</p>
        <p>The conciliatory moves yesterday by the factional leader Mohammed Farah Aidid give the President some space in which to breathe, but not much. In Somalia, there are no guarantees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton is swimming in treacherous political waters with his latest Somalia policy. Another combat disaster in Mogadishu -- the loss of a large number of Americans, the taking of additional hostages -- would present an enormous threat to his Presidency.</p>
        <p>The conciliatory moves yesterday by the factional leader Mohammed Farah Aidid give the President some space in which to breathe, but not much. In Somalia, there are no guarantees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's standing with the American public, along with his entire domestic and foreign policy agenda, would be jeopardized by the sight of a few more bodies being dragged through the streets by a jeering crowd, or a few more frightened prisoners videotaped in captivity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has a lot to lose. So he is showing considerable courage by continuing the nation's attempt to do the right thing by Somalia.</p>
        <p>The United States has a responsibility in Somalia, and it outweighs the question of whether abandoning that country would send the wrong message around the world. The U.S. contributed to Somalia's troubles.</p>
        <p>At various times during the cold war both the U.S. and the former Soviet Union saw Somalia, a largely rural, nomadic country on the Indian Ocean and Gulf of Aden, as a place of strategic importance. The Somalis were courted, but instead of roses, the beloved was given heavy armaments.</p>
        <p>Among the weapons that went to the Somalis (along with training in how to use them) were recoilless rifles, armored personnel carriers, tanks, anti-aircraft guns, rocket launchers and surface-to-air missiles.</p>
        <p>Randall Robinson, the executive director of TransAfrica, a research and advocacy organization, said: "Those policies, first from the Soviets and then from us, have contributed to the wreckage of Somalia. Somalia has enough arms to outfit a major army. Twenty-five years ago it had none."</p>
        <p>Ultimately the weapons from the cold-war superpowers fell into the hands of Somali warlords and were used in the furious factional fighting that reduced the country to anarchy.</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Robinson: "When people want to know what happened to Somalia, I say, 'We happened to Somalia.' "</p>
        <p>It was, of course, the American public's reaction to the agony of starving Somalis that led to the hunger relief efforts. But beyond the humanitarian impulse, there was something appropriate about the United States moving in a substantial way to help Somalia.</p>
        <p>For the most part, that effort is working. Nearly a million lives have been saved, which is extraordinary. As President Clinton pointed out on Thursday, life is "returning to normal" in most of Somalia. "Crops are growing. Markets are reopening. So are schools and hospitals. Nearly a million Somalis still depend completely on relief supplies, but at least the starvation is gone. And none of this would have happened without American leadership and America's troops."</p>
        <p>There were blunders, and the loss of American and Somali lives in Mogadishu is a tragedy. The President's shift in policy is an effort to avoid further blunders and at the same time prevent the progress already made from being undermined.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has made it clear that the United Nations will not be calling the shots for U.S. troops faced with the threat of combat and that General Aidid will not be frozen out of attempts to negotiate a political solution.</p>
        <p>It should have been obvious from the beginning that the general would have to be dealt with -- not because he was a good guy, but because he was a legitimate leader of a large number of Somalis. It was never the proper role of the U.N. or the U.S. to favor one Somali faction over another, or to impose a solution by force.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton understands that his plan is vulnerable on a number of fronts. General Aidid, for example, could decide to lie low until the Americans leave in a few months. He or others could use guerrilla or terror tactics to exploit the lack of support among Americans for any further involvement in Somalia.</p>
        <p>The risk to President Clinton is great. But there is something noble about a large and powerful country saving a million lives in a small and troubled one. Six months is not too long a time to invest in the possibility that a more lasting solution can be found.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
