<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dish to Go Up, Over Protest</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="639938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CLINTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTENNAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNET (TV STATION) (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWE, MARVINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DE143BF933A25753C1A965958260" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dish to Go Up, Over Protest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVINE HOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOWE, MARVINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what Channel 13 thought was an act of good will, the station recently wrote to neighbors advising them that part of West 58th Street would be temporarily closed. The public television station, which planned to construct and install a satellite antenna on the roof of its headquarters at 356 West 58th Street, expected some annoyance for the inconvenience.</p>
        <p>But the reaction was anger. Both neighbors and Community Board 4, citing the continuing debate over the risk of radiation exposure from such technology, last week sent letters to city, state and Federal officials protesting the antenna.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what Channel 13 thought was an act of good will, the station recently wrote to neighbors advising them that part of West 58th Street would be temporarily closed. The public television station, which planned to construct and install a satellite antenna on the roof of its headquarters at 356 West 58th Street, expected some annoyance for the inconvenience.</p>
        <p>But the reaction was anger. Both neighbors and Community Board 4, citing the continuing debate over the risk of radiation exposure from such technology, last week sent letters to city, state and Federal officials protesting the antenna.</p>
        <p>The board of the Colonnade Condominium, a 46-story building adjacent to the station, also sent a letter, to the Federal Communications Commission. Citing "significant health concerns," the board asked the agency to reconsider its approval of Channel 13's antenna or to require an environmental study.</p>
        <p>"We're concerned about the possible impact of the radiation on the health of people who live next door and across the street," said Tim Gay, who heads Community Board 4's quality-of-life committee.</p>
        <p>William F. Baker, the president of Channel 13, said the station resists doing an environmental study because tests on a similar commercial antenna in Connecticut "showed more radiation in a kitchen with a microwave." He pointed out that all television networks have such antennae in midtown Manhattan, "and we're the last to get one."</p>
        <p>In the wake of a national debate over radio frequency exposure, the Federal agency is considering a revision of its guidelines that would make them more stringent. But officials said that this is not expected to affect Channel 13's project, which has already been approved.</p>
        <p>Construction of the 26-foot satellite dish, to be installed on the roof of the station's 25-story building, is expected to be completed by the end of October. The station wants to link up to Telstar 401, an A.T.&amp;T. satellite scheduled to be launched in November.</p>
        <p>Among other things, the new technology is intended to provide viewers with access to additional programs from other PBS stations as well as better reception. For 15 years, Channel 13 has operated a satellite dish in Vernon Valley, N.J., 40 miles northwest of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Melvin Ming, the chief administrative officer for Channel 13, said the antenna beam would be directed to the southwest, "above the horizon, with no building in its path." Robert Cleveland, an environmental scientist with the F.C.C., said the signals would be specifically directed to the satellite and would not expose people to radiation "unless they got into the main beam." He added that this was "highly unlikely," given the direction of the beam. MARVINE HOWE  CLINTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
