<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviews/Film; The War of the Sexes</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONVICTION, THE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DC1E39F930A25756C0A962958260" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviews/Film; The War of the Sexes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a time when Marco Bellocchio was mentioned in the same breath as Bernardo Bertolucci. But that was a couple of decades ago when they were among the wild young things of the Italian film industry. Today Mr. Bellocchio is best known in the United States for his X-rated 1985 film, "Devil in the Flesh," and his latest work is not likely to raise his profile. "The Conviction," a 1990 film opening today at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, takes topical, explosive issues -- rape, sexual harassment, power plays between the sexes -- and reduces them into a forgettable puff of hot air.</p>
        <p>The film begins in a promising, if calculated, way. An ordinary-looking young woman named Sandra (Claire Nebout) finds herself locked in a museum overnight. A handsome architect named Lorenzo (Vittorio Mezzogiorno, who died in January) has intentionally stayed behind as well. When he begins to rape her, at first she fights back. Then she freezes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a time when Marco Bellocchio was mentioned in the same breath as Bernardo Bertolucci. But that was a couple of decades ago when they were among the wild young things of the Italian film industry. Today Mr. Bellocchio is best known in the United States for his X-rated 1985 film, "Devil in the Flesh," and his latest work is not likely to raise his profile. "The Conviction," a 1990 film opening today at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, takes topical, explosive issues -- rape, sexual harassment, power plays between the sexes -- and reduces them into a forgettable puff of hot air.</p>
        <p>The film begins in a promising, if calculated, way. An ordinary-looking young woman named Sandra (Claire Nebout) finds herself locked in a museum overnight. A handsome architect named Lorenzo (Vittorio Mezzogiorno, who died in January) has intentionally stayed behind as well. When he begins to rape her, at first she fights back. Then she freezes.</p>
        <p>From that point on, the film takes one ludicrous turn after another. Shamed by her own coldness, Sandra invites Lorenzo to have sex she will enjoy. She does this by taking off her clothes and posing in an odalisque position in front of the museum's paintings, while they both expostulate about art and life.</p>
        <p>Then Sandra drags Lorenzo into court. On the witness stand, she actually says, "He has a force of character that drives a woman to sexuality even if she doesn't want it." He wishes. So, it seems, do Mr. Bellocchio and his co-author, the psychoanalyst Massimo Fagioli. They regard Sandra as an authentic woman rather than a male fantasy out of Freud by way of D. H. Lawrence.</p>
        <p>Soon the film shifts its attention to the prosecuting attorney, a man whose lover complains about his lack of passion. The prosecutor is played by Andrzej Seweryn with an unchanging look -- a furrowed brow and staring eyes -- that makes him look catatonic. Eventually he goes to the rapist for advice, wondering, "How do you lose your head for a woman?" Don't even ask about the scene in which the prosecutor stumbles across a peasant who looks and acts as if she were inhabited by the ghost of Anna Magnani.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bellocchio obviously intends the sly references and stylized nature of this film, but he couldn't possibly have intended it to be this much of a howler. Relations between the sexes are complicated, but rarely as lunatic as they are made to seem here. The Conviction  Directed by Marco Bellocchio; screenplay by Massimo Fagioli and Mr. Bellocchio, in Italian, with English subtitles; director of photography, Giuseppe Lanci; edited by Mirco Garrone; music by Carlo Crivelli; production designer, Giantito Burchiellaro; producer, Pietro Valsecchi; released by International Film Circuit. At the Joseph Papp Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village. Running time: 92 minutes. This film is not rated. Lorenzo Colajanni . . . Vittorio Mezzogiorno Sandra Celestini . . . Claire Nebout Giovanni Malatesta . . . Andrzej Seweryn Monica . . . Grazyna Szapolowska</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
