<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baylor Coach Bliss Resigns; Violations Discovered</title>
    <meta content="09BAYL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/09/sports/ncaabasketball/09BAYL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baylor University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Viv</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bliss, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanton, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dennehy, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dotson, Carlton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baylor University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bliss, Dave</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dennehy, Patrick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sloan, Robert B Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DA1231F93AA3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baylor Coach Bliss Resigns; Violations Discovered</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Baylor Coach Bliss Resigns; Violations Discovered</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baylor University basketball coach Dave Bliss and athletic director Tom Stanton resign in response to allegations that Baylor knew of student-athlete drug use and violated financial aid requirements, just days after body of former player Patrick Dennehy was found; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after attending the funeral of the basketball player Patrick Dennehy, Baylor Coach Dave Bliss resigned yesterday because of National Collegiate Athletic Association violations discovered by the university.</p>
        <p>Baylor's athletic director, Tom Stanton, also resigned, and Robert B. Sloan Jr., the university's president, announced that Baylor would report infractions involving financial aid and drug testing to the N.C.A.A. and impose immediate penalties on the basketball program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after attending the funeral of player Patrick Dennehy, Dave Bliss resigned. Baylor University's program will be placed on probation for two seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after attending the funeral of the basketball player Patrick Dennehy, Baylor Coach Dave Bliss resigned yesterday because of National Collegiate Athletic Association violations discovered by the university.</p>
        <p>Baylor's athletic director, Tom Stanton, also resigned, and Robert B. Sloan Jr., the university's president, announced that Baylor would report infractions involving financial aid and drug testing to the N.C.A.A. and impose immediate penalties on the basketball program.</p>
        <p>Sloan said the team would be placed on probation for two seasons and would not play in postseason tournaments in 2004.</p>
        <p>''I'm the head coach and I'm accountable for everything that goes on in my program,'' Bliss, 59, said yesterday in a news conference on the Baylor campus in Waco, Tex. ''I accept that responsibility. I intend to cooperate fully as the inquiry continues. I'll do whatever I can to make things right.''</p>
        <p>Accusations of improprieties in the program arose after Dennehy was reported missing on June 19. Dennehy's former teammate Carlton Dotson was arrested July 21 after he confessed to shooting Dennehy, according to the Waco police arrest warrant. Dennehy's body was found July 26. He was buried Thursday in San Jose, Calif. Bliss, Stanton and Sloan attended the funeral service.</p>
        <p>Dotson is being held in Maryland awaiting extradition to Texas.</p>
        <p>During the search for Dennehy's body, his father, Patrick Dennehy Sr., questioned how his son paid for tuition, expenses and a car while he was not on scholarship. Dennehy sat out last season after transferring from New Mexico. Others said some players were involved in drug use and possibly failed drug tests.</p>
        <p>The accusations prompted Sloan to form an investigation committee that included three Baylor law professors and a lawyer from Austin. The committee began work the same week Dotson was arrested and Dennehy's body was found.</p>
        <p>''The investigative committee and I have determined there have been serious or major violations,'' Sloan said.</p>
        <p>Sloan said two athletes received money for tuition that came from a third party. Sloan did not name the students or the third party, but said Bliss had ''admitted involvement in these infractions.''</p>
        <p>Sloan also said the investigation revealed that staff members neglected to follow procedures for reporting failed drug tests. Drug testing will now be conducted outside the athletic department, Sloan said.</p>
        <p>The university has not formed a search committee to find a new athletic director or coach. It is also uncertain whether the assistant coaches Doug Ash, Brian O'Neill or Rodney Belcher will be retained.</p>
        <p>Sloan said the investigation would continue and could involve more violations and penalties.</p>
        <p>''I think the community is shocked and saddened,'' Sammy Citrano, the owner of George's Restaurant in Waco, said last night in a telephone interview. ''Dave is a very respected man in our community and in our town. He's one of the best coaches to ever come to Baylor.''</p>
        <p>Bliss has a 526-328 career record in 28 seasons as a college coach, including stops at Oklahoma, Southern Methodist and New Mexico. He was 61-57 in four seasons at Baylor, taking over a program that was at the bottom of the Big 12. He recruited several transfers and junior college players, including Dennehy and Dotson.</p>
        <p>The resignation by Bliss was little consolation to Dennehy's stepfather, Brian Brabazon, who had been critical of the coaching staff. Family members said they believed that the coaches ignored Dennehy's concerns about being threatened and they said the staff was slow to act when Dennehy failed to show up for a required class on June 16. Bliss has said he was not aware of any threats.</p>
        <p>''That's really not where our concern has been,'' Brabazon said of the resignation in a brief telephone interview last night. ''None of this is going to make Patrick less dead. I can't wait to find out what happened. I don't blame anyone except Carlton. But maybe if these infractions didn't happen, our son would be alive.''</p>
        <p>Brabazon said he spoke briefly with Bliss and Stanton at Thursday's memorial, but there was no mention of a possible resignation.</p>
        <p>''It's unbelievable, but at the same time it's believable,'' he said. ''It's unbelievable because I shook their hands and they didn't say anything about it. It's believable because I've heard about everything that's gone on in the Baylor basketball program.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
