<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Headquarters Seizes Carpenters' Union Over U.S. Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JAVITS, JACOB K, CONVENTION CENTER (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED BROTHERHOOD OF CARPENTERS AND JOINERS OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PULLEY, BRETT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Javits, Jacob K, Convention Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D71731F931A25757C0A963958260" item-length="309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Headquarters Seizes Carpenters' Union Over U.S. Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRETT PULLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PULLEY, BRETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The labor union representing carpenters at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center was seized by its international office earlier this week, in response to rising concern over the local's finances and operations.</p>
        <p>Citing activity "detrimental to the welfare of the members," the international president of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America placed its Bronx-based Local 17 under trusteeship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The labor union representing carpenters at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center was seized by its international office earlier this week, in response to rising concern over the local's finances and operations.</p>
        <p>Citing activity "detrimental to the welfare of the members," the international president of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America placed its Bronx-based Local 17 under trusteeship.</p>
        <p>The president of the international, Sigurd Lucassen, stopped short of saying the action was related to recent allegations of mob corruption within the carpenters union in the New York area, but in a prepared statement Mr. Lucassen did say that he was in contact with a Federal investigator monitoring the activity of the union in the region.</p>
        <p>The Bronx local and some of its members have come under increased scrutiny in recent weeks as investigators and public officials have focused on allegations of organized crime operations by labor unions that operate inside the convention center.</p>
        <p>A Federal investigator charged last month that a small, preferred pool of Local 17 members have benefited from the lucrative contracts at the Javits center, violating a Federal consent decree that requires that the work be spread out among the union's members.</p>
        <p>Anthony Fiorino, the carpenters union official in charge of hiring the union members for work at the Javits center, is the focus of a hearing into charges that he has used his job to act as an agent for organized crime. Mr. Fiorino is supposed to hire workers from all of the 17 locals in the New York area, according to the consent decree.</p>
        <p>The union's international office, based in Washington, said that Roger Perron, an international union representative, would supervise a reorganization of Local 17 and would be given "full authority to appoint or remove officials."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
