<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many in City Summer School Won't Go On to Next Grade</title>
    <meta content="01school" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/01/nyregion/01school.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1786772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3D91E3EF932A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many in City Summer School Won't Go On to Next Grade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Many in City Summer School Won’t Go on to Next Grade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than half of the public school students urged to attend summer school for failing to meet Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's stiff promotion criteria will be forced to repeat a grade this coming year because they were unable to raise their scores enough on exams.</p>
        <p>The mixed results for the 13,751 third, fifth and seventh graders raised questions about the cost-effectiveness of the summer program created to help them. Forty-six percent of third graders and 41.3 percent of seventh graders who attended the program, called Summer Success Academy, improved their exam scores sufficiently to qualify for the next grade. Fifth graders fared slightly better, with 54.4 percent who attended the sessions scoring high enough to move on to the sixth grade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mixed results for the 13,751 third, fifth and seventh graders raised questions about the cost-effectiveness of the summer program created to help them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than half of the public school students urged to attend summer school for failing to meet Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's stiff promotion criteria will be forced to repeat a grade this coming year because they were unable to raise their scores enough on exams.</p>
        <p>The mixed results for the 13,751 third, fifth and seventh graders raised questions about the cost-effectiveness of the summer program created to help them. Forty-six percent of third graders and 41.3 percent of seventh graders who attended the program, called Summer Success Academy, improved their exam scores sufficiently to qualify for the next grade. Fifth graders fared slightly better, with 54.4 percent who attended the sessions scoring high enough to move on to the sixth grade.</p>
        <p>The five-week summer academy, with a budget of $33 million, served 11,595 students this year. The City Council has estimated that the summer program costs about three times what the city spends per student during the regular academic year, on a per-week basis.</p>
        <p>City officials said the results represented a substantial improvement by the students who attended summer school. They said that the mayor's policies had both put an end to social promotion, in which students moved to the next grade without meeting academic requirements, and prompted many more children to work hard in summer school.</p>
        <p>''If you look at seventh grade, especially, that's a really good story,'' said Jennifer Bell-Ellwanger, the city's testing director. She noted that 28.3 percent of seventh graders whose scores were too low for promotion in the spring raised their scores in August. Last year, before the mayor's promotion rules applied to that grade, only 13.5 percent raised their scores, she said.</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, the president of the city teachers' union, however, said the results were unimpressive and seemed little changed from less expensive summer school programs through the years. ''You are basically seeing what we had historically seen in terms of summer school results,'' she said. ''Half the kids pass, and half the kids don't pass.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg created the summer program in 2004 after imposing new rules barring the promotion of third graders who failed to show basic competency on standardized reading and math tests. The rules were expanded to include fifth graders in 2005 and seventh graders this year. Mr. Bloomberg credited the policy with helping to lift scores.</p>
        <p>This year's results, released yesterday by the city's Department of Education, were discouraging for third graders. Last year, 54.9 percent of third graders who attended summer school raised scores and were promoted, compared with 46 percent this year. Fifth graders did better with 54.4 percent promoted, up from 42.9 percent last year.</p>
        <p>Critics say that the mayor's promotion policy relies too heavily on exams and that resources should be focused on remedial programs during the regular academic year when attendance is markedly better.</p>
        <p>The city's efforts to enforce Mr. Bloomberg's promotion rules were complicated this year by sweeping changes in the testing system. New York State, which previously had administered annual English and math tests in fourth and eighth grades, adopted new tests for grades three through eight to comply with the federal No Child Left Behind law.</p>
        <p>The state exam results have yet to be released, frustrating some parents and educators who are beginning the school year without knowing how well students did the previous year.</p>
        <p>The lack of scores has also delayed Chancellor Joel I. Klein from setting performance targets for more than 300 principals who agreed to demonstrate high progress in exchange for greater autonomy.</p>
        <p>The state English test was given in January; the math test in March. The state had long warned that results would be later than usual because of extensive technical work required to calibrate the scoring of the new examinations.</p>
        <p>New York City, which had previously given its own exams in third, fifth, sixth and seventh grades, at first planned to administer its own tests to enforce the mayor's rules. But after parents objected to the double testing, the city and state struck a deal in which the city calculated preliminary scores to make promotion decisions.</p>
        <p>The city then used its own exams to test students at the end of summer school in August. State officials said they expected the full English exam results to be released in mid-September and the math scores to follow by the end of the month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
