<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Trail of Estrogen And a Mirage of Youth</title>
    <meta content="05KOLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/05/books/05KOLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1502134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolota, Gina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seaman, Barbara</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Greatest Experiment Ever Performed On Women, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Seaman, Barbara</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Greatest Experiment Ever Performed on Women (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6DF1F3AF936A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Trail of Estrogen And a Mirage of Youth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On the Trail of Estrogen and a Mirage of Youth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gina Kolota reviews book The Greatest Experiment Ever Performed On Women: Exploding the Estrogen Myth by Barbara Seaman; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GREATEST EXPERIMENT EVER PERFORMED ON WOMEN  Exploding the Estrogen Myth  By Barbara Seaman  332 pages. Hyperion. $24.95</p>
        <p>Dr. Susan Hendrix, a gynecologist at Wayne State University in Detroit, recently saw a new patient, a middle-aged woman who, it turned out, had been taking double the normal dose of hormone therapy for menopause. Dr. Hendrix asked her why and she said she had had terrible hot flashes and needed the hefty amount. Then, Dr. Hendrix told me, the truth came out: the woman thought the extra estrogen would help her look younger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barbara Seaman's lively and impassioned manifesto, while not always distinguishing between good science and anecdote, certainly makes her point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GREATEST EXPERIMENT EVER PERFORMED ON WOMEN  Exploding the Estrogen Myth  By Barbara Seaman  332 pages. Hyperion. $24.95</p>
        <p>Dr. Susan Hendrix, a gynecologist at Wayne State University in Detroit, recently saw a new patient, a middle-aged woman who, it turned out, had been taking double the normal dose of hormone therapy for menopause. Dr. Hendrix asked her why and she said she had had terrible hot flashes and needed the hefty amount. Then, Dr. Hendrix told me, the truth came out: the woman thought the extra estrogen would help her look younger.</p>
        <p>I have a feeling that would have been no surprise to Barbara Seaman, whose book ''The Greatest Experiment Ever Performed on Women'' takes on the estrogen industry. Her lively and impassioned manifesto, while not always distinguishing between good science and anecdote, certainly makes her point. The advertising and promotion of estrogen have invested the hormone with an allure that goes far beyond medical evidence.</p>
        <p>That effect was hard to miss last year when many women and gynecologists rejected findings from the Women's Health Initiative, a large and rigorous federal study on hormone therapy in menopause. It found that there were health risks with Prempro, a popular combination of estrogen and progestin, that were not balanced by benefits.</p>
        <p>Some women said they could never give up the pills, not because they needed them for severe menopause symptoms but because they were convinced that estrogen prevented wrinkles or because it staved off mental fogginess -- benefits that have never been demonstrated and are highly questionable. Some women and doctors said the risks found in the Women's Health Initiative study -- over a five-year period, one woman out of 100 who took the hormones had a disabling stroke, a heart attack, or breast cancer -- were too small to worry about.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seaman, a journalist and women's health advocate, has followed the estrogen trail for decades, collecting anecdotes and asking piercing questions. She confronted Robert Wilson, for example, a doctor whose 1966 book, ''Feminine Forever,'' was quietly sponsored by an estrogen maker, Ayerst Laboratories, and helped establish many of the estrogen myths.</p>
        <p>''At 50,'' Dr. Wilson stated, women taking estrogen ''still look attractive in sleeveless dresses or tennis shorts.''</p>
        <p>''How do you know,'' Ms. Seaman retorted, ''that it isn't from the tennis?'''</p>
        <p>In her new book Ms. Seaman takes on all forms and uses of estrogen, including birth control pills, the subject of her previous book, ''The Doctors' Case Against the Pill.'' Her thesis is that estrogen's benefits tend to be asserted, not proved, and whenever a benefit evaporates on examination, another arises to take its place.</p>
        <p>Yet, as much as I enjoyed reading Ms. Seaman's book, I kept finding myself thinking, yes, but.</p>
        <p>Yes, but she tends to hold estrogen critics to a looser standard than she does estrogen promoters. For example she quotes a Canadian doctor at 1970 Senate hearings on birth control pills saying that he noticed ''a striking increase in a rare chromosomal defect known as triploidy among the babies of women who conceive within six months of going off the pill.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Seaman never tells us that this is not scientific evidence, nor is it true that studies found that pill use leads to this birth defect. In fact, this is exactly the sort of anecdote that Ms. Seaman rightfully scorns when it is used to praise estrogen.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seaman correctly stresses that some of the hoped-for benefits of estrogen therapy are, at this point, just wishful thinking. That includes using estrogen to prevent Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>Yes, but why does she then undermine some of her credibility by implying that estrogen can cause neurological problems? As ''evidence'' she quotes a woman who thinks it happened to her: ''I could not articulate. Lost words, couldn't finish sentences. My case was extreme, but with the stopping of HRT, I'm better.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Seaman excoriates large drug companies for promoting unproven benefits of estrogen. Yes, but why does she then hold her fire on other treatments, like ''natural'' estrogen and progesterone and even testosterone, which were never subjected to large rigorous scientific studies for use in menopause?</p>
        <p>This credulity extends beyond prescription drugs and includes methods of avoiding Alzheimer's disease (keep active) and fractures (try tai chi, a Chinese balance training exercise that is, Ms. Seaman says ''particularly effective''). She asserts that it ''has been evaluated scientifically'' and shown to improve balance, prevent falls, and to provide ''enhancement of one's cardiovascular system''</p>
        <p>Maybe. But there is no good evidence that keeping active prevents Alzheimer's. As for tai chi and fractures, if there is such stellar evidence, it would be nice if Ms. Seaman would let us know what it is and who, besides the authors of a book on tai chi, is convinced by it.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, maybe the intense marketing of estrogens needs this book as a counterweight. When I was reading it, I saw an advertising supplement in The New York Times Magazine, with an article called ''Perimenopause: Before Your Period Ends.'' There is no author, no sponsor mentioned, just the small print ''advertisement'' at the top of the page.</p>
        <p>Here is some of what it says:</p>
        <p>''Five to 10 years before menstruation ends, when a woman is in her mid-30's to early 40's, estrogen levels diminish. Women can suffer from hot flashes and night sweats, vaginal dryness'' and, the article implies, can age overnight. ''Age spots and wrinkles appear as skin loses its elasticity.'' ''Weight gain is often common,'' and even if they do not gain weight, ''women often find that body shape changes, bulking up around their middles.'' There are psychological problems, ''irritability, mood swings and depression.''</p>
        <p>The solution? I'm sure that Ms. Seaman will not be surprised to learn that it includes estrogen -- in the form of low-dose birth control pills, and hormone therapy for menopause, either ''for a few years or indefinitely.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
