<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art(?) to Go: Museum Shops Broaden Wares, at a Profit</title>
    <meta content="T10SHO$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dobrzynski, Judith H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6D6153CF933A25751C1A961958260" item-length="2261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art(?) to Go: Museum Shops Broaden Wares, at a Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH H. DOBRZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dobrzynski, Judith H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American museums have been hawking merchandise ever since Metropolitan Museum of Art began selling etchings in 1871, but increasingly, objects you would never expect to find in museums are being sold alongside art books and reproduction sculptures; trend horrifies art purists; museum stores bring in as much as quarter of money museums earn, outstripping admissions, membership and other revenue-producing activities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rodin had pasta first. Now Warhol has pasta, too. Monet has Provencal soup, olive oil and absinthe. Rauschenberg has no food, but he has dinner plates.</p>
        <p>The topic is not lunch, but what's for sale in museum stores. American museums have been hawking merchandise for more than 125 years, ever since the Metropolitan Museum of Art began selling etchings in 1871. But increasingly, objects you'd never expect to find in the nation's cultural cathedrals are being sold right alongside the art books and note cards and reproduction sculptures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rodin had pasta first. Now Warhol has pasta, too. Monet has Provencal soup, olive oil and absinthe. Rauschenberg has no food, but he has dinner plates.</p>
        <p>The topic is not lunch, but what's for sale in museum stores. American museums have been hawking merchandise for more than 125 years, ever since the Metropolitan Museum of Art began selling etchings in 1871. But increasingly, objects you'd never expect to find in the nation's cultural cathedrals are being sold right alongside the art books and note cards and reproduction sculptures.</p>
        <p>The trend horrifies art purists even as it delights consumers in search of a different gift this holiday season or a little bit of culture to take home. So what if the connection is tenuous? Museum stores bring in as much as a quarter of the money museums earn, outstripping admissions, membership and other revenue-producing activities.</p>
        <p>The store at the Whitney Museum of American Art, where ''The Warhol Look/Glamour Style Fashion'' is on view, sells Campbell Tomato Soup watches, Campbell Soup cans stuffed with crayons and pasta shaped like lips from Warhol's 1950's ink drawing, ''Lips.'' Merchandise for the Brooklyn Museum of Art's ''Monet and the Mediterranean'' exhibition includes soup mixes and bottles of olive oil that have no link with the art or the artist, save their association with the Mediterranean, too.</p>
        <p>And visitors to the ''Best Dressed: 250 Years of Style'' exhibition at the Philadelphia Museum of Art will find red tomato-flavored pasta in the shape of boots and bustiers in the museum store, not far from the green spinach-flavored pasta that looks like Rodin's ''Thinker,'' leftovers from the ''Rodin and Michelangelo'' exhibition last spring.</p>
        <p>Those six-ounce pasta packages, labeled ''Food to Think About,'' are causing even more stir in the art world because they were dreamed up by the trend-setting Philadelphia museum, which created several hotly debated items for its 1996 Cezanne retrospective, most notably, bright yellow baseballs emblazoned with Cezanne's signature. Never mind that no one knows whether Cezanne ever heard of the great American pastime. The museum sold 8,750 balls for $9.50 each.</p>
        <p>Baseballs, pasta and who knows what else are now turning up in other museums.</p>
        <p>''The reason we make these products is so that we relate to everyone,'' said Stuart D. Gerstein, the Philadelphia museum's director of wholesale and retail operations.</p>
        <p>Perhaps. But the bigger reason for this unabashed commercialism is simple economics.</p>
        <p>At a time when money from government sources is declining and the largesse of corporations, foundations and private donors comes with many strings attached, art museums are looking for new ways to pay for mundane expenses like electricity and security. Some are increasing general admission fees or imposing fees for special exhibitions. Others are organizing exhibitions from their permanent collections to lend to smaller institutions and charging them for the privilege.</p>
        <p>And just about every museum is looking to squeeze more money from the store. Even the wealthiest, the Getty Museum: when the doors of its new $1 billion complex in Los Angeles are thrown open to the public on Dec. 16 the main store will occupy 1,700 square feet, five times the space occupied by the old museum store in Malibu, and there will be three satellite shops elsewhere in the building. The museum expects sales to reach $5 million in the first year and $1 million in profits.</p>
        <p>Unlike general retailers, museum stores enjoy their profits tax-free as long as their products are somehow related to the museum -- an edge that rankled with other retailers a few years ago. Now, ''most stores have accepted it and gone onto something else,'' said Isaac Lagnado, president of Tactical Retail Solutions, a consultant in New York. Even rival businesses like the Museum Store, the big chain that sells museum-related goods in shopping malls, are not grumbling, partly because they buy or license many of their products from the museums.</p>
        <p>Around the country, museum stores are undergoing a metamorphosis. Many have started spicing up their merchandise mix, sometimes hiring managers from the retailing industry to do it. They have shed their old ideas of what is appropriate, to the dismay of some art lovers.</p>
        <p>''I'm in favor of museum shops;  I'm in favor of the appropriate use of reproductions,'' said Nicholas Fox Weber, a cultural historian. ''But you don't take a great image and put it on a tote bag. It takes people away from the real issues of looking at art.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weber declined to muster a reaction to the very idea of artistic macaroni. But the critic Deborah Solomon did. Before actually reviewing the Rodin exhibition for The Wall Street Journal last April, she chastised the museum for going too far with ''Thinker'' pasta.</p>
        <p>Yet given the financial environment museum stores are unlikely to be stopped by carping. Membership surveys taken by the Association of Art Museum Directors and the American Association of Museums show that profits from museum stores contribute 18 to 26 percent of a museum's earned income, topping all other sources.</p>
        <p>At the Metropolitan Museum, one in five visitors leaves with a bag in hand. Total revenues from its 39 stores in the United States and overseas in the fiscal year through June 39 came to $87.4 million, up slightly from five years ago.</p>
        <p>And though most museums will not disclose store profits, Mr. Lagnado said, ''these stores do well.'' A new survey, taken by the Museum Store Association, found that the average gross profit margin is 48 percent, some 10 points above that of respected department stores.</p>
        <p>There's little wonder, then, that since 1992, while gallery space at 185 of the nation's largest museums increased by 3.3 percent, the space devoted to museum stores jumped 28.7 percent. Retailing managers have more room to offer more goods and to be creative about them.</p>
        <p>''What's happening is that more and more museum administrators are paying attention to the gift shop,'' said Rena Zurofsky, a veteran of store management at four art museums, including the Metropolitan and the Brooklyn Museum. ''And what retailing managers are hearing from them is not just a question of revenues or profits. It's 'Why don't I see in our shop what they have in that shop?' '' Ms. Zurofsky is now chief of retailing at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>At the same time, administrators now know that some people come to museums specifically to shop, and then maybe hit the galleries. The Museum Store Association survey shows that 97 percent of art museum stores are outside the admission barriers. ''Twenty years ago, we were loathed as much as we were loved,'' Ms. Zurofsky said. ''Now we're welcomed not only because of the money we bring in, but also because we draw people in.''</p>
        <p>Museums have also learned that shoppers can help spread the art gospel simply by carrying bags decorated with a logo. That is why more and more museums are offering products with their brand name. T-shirts and tote bags printed with museum logos, already common, have been joined by baseball caps that allow people to broadcast their cultural loyalties just as they do their favorite teams.</p>
        <p>Using Playthings As Links to Art</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Museum of Art put its own name as well as Cezanne's on each baseball, and its ''Thinker'' pasta included shapes of the museum's classical facade as well as Rodin's sculpture. The new Getty store will offer rubber toys modeled on the tram that delivers people to its doors and chunks of travertine marble, a material used throughout the six-building complex, labeled ''The Getty Center'' ($4.95 to $6.95, depending on size).</p>
        <p>In a twist on the brand-name strategy, the Metropolitan recently expanded the role of its unofficial mascot, William, a faience hippopotamus well known to fans of the Egyptian galleries. He has already appeared in the museum store as a print, a ceramic sculpture, a T-shirt and a tie. Now he is a stuffed toy ($13.95) and a Christmas ornament, and is  featured on a new T-shirt and tie. William may never rival Mickey Mouse in reach, but the intent to capitalize on a friendly, familiar image is unmistakable.</p>
        <p>This search for the new is spreading fast. Come February, the Cleveland Museum of Art will be peddling angel-shaped pasta for its ''Vatican Treasures: Early Christian, Renaissance and Baroque Art From the Papal Collections'' exhibition. For its current show, ''When Silk Was Gold,'' an exhibition of ancient Asian textiles, the Cleveland museum is selling silk robes ($150).</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, museumgoers can find stuffed animals, needlepoint kits, rugs, refrigerator magnets, cookbooks, umbrellas, soaps, furniture, playing cards, kites, candles, clothing, razors in the shape of frogs and mermaids and, of course, loads of jewelry. Computer mouse pads and screen savers are popular.</p>
        <p>Smart museums have found that they can spread their business more evenly through the year, instead of relying on the boost they get during December gift-buying, by offering  merchandise keyed to special exhibitions. At the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, the ubiquitous museum mug has been finessed by the Robert Rauschenberg dinner plate. The Whitney Museum sells bongo drums -- salt and pepper shakers, really ($30) -- made for its 1996 ''Beat Culture'' exhibition. And Museo del Barrio offers a baseball cap promoting its current ''Taino'' pre-Colombian art exhibition.</p>
        <p>But even among items that have become old hat, like scarves and neckties, the number of selections is growing, with motifs from Klimt, Mondrian, Ingres, to name a few, or the image of an entire painting.</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia museum even sells temporary tattoos of artworks ($2) from its collection. ''Our idea is that people are walking around with art on their bodies that is not good, and we're giving them good art to wear,'' said Mr. Gerstein, citing tattoos of van Gogh's ''Sunflowers'' as an example.</p>
        <p>Not every institution is succumbing to the trend. About 80 percent of the merchandise available at the Museum of African Art in Manhattan is authentic craft work from Africa. And the Museum of Modern Art, which plans to double its store space to 24,000 square feet when the museum is expanded in a few years, intends to stick with its strategy of offering distinctive, upscale objects.</p>
        <p>''We will not put rubber-stamp images on every product we can get our hands on,'' said James D. Gundell, the new president of MOMA Retail, who was brought in this year from Bloomingdale's. Instead, he wants to tap artists to develop objects especially for the Modern.</p>
        <p>M.V.P.: Renoir Or van Gogh</p>
        <p>But only a few museums seem to have the luxury of peddling class, not mass. Mr. Gerstein, from the Philadelphia museum, defends the choice. ''Our audience is changing, and we are looking for new ways to educate the public and promote the building and promote the collection,'' he said. In fact, he is so happy with the Cezanne baseball sales that he has a new one, an ''Artists All-Star'' baseball with 15 signatures by the likes of Renoir, Homer and van Gogh.</p>
        <p>He defends the pasta equally adamantly. ''You can make 'Thinker' pasta, put it in a bowl and tell your kids about Rodin and 'The Thinker,' '' he argued. And he parries questions about good taste with humor: ''The pasta tastes good.''</p>
        <p>More seriously, he added: ''I don't look at things as being not tasteful. I look at it as a matter of quality.'' He said that Philadelphia was also producing items that should appeal to more sophisticated tastes, like a series of CD's with musical selections that artists might have listened to. Among them are ''Music, Russia and  Kandinsky,'' with folk songs, cafe music and orchestral music from 1914 to 1921, and ''Music, Portraits  and Picasso,'' with ballet, jazz and Catalonian folk music as well as classical French pieces.</p>
        <p>That does not appease Mr. Weber, the cultural historian, who wishes that more museum stores offered local handicrafts and honest reproductions. ''I think you want something that will perpetuate the exhibition so that you can take it home with you and be reminded of it on a Sunday morning sometime,'' he said. He regrets his own decision, as director  of the Albers Foundation, to allow the Guggenheim to use an Albers painting on a tie a few years ago.</p>
        <p>At the Metropolitan, John Curran, the vice president for merchandising activities, is taking neither side. The Met, he said, will never do baseballs or pasta, though it has baseball caps ($18). But, he added, some museums have little choice.</p>
        <p>''How should museums stay open: should we raise taxes or raise admissions?'' he said. ''The most democratic thing to do is to let museums help themselves. No one is twisting anyone's arm to buy these things, and taste is a very subjective thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
