<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Presence in Gulf Is Denounced in Iran</title>
    <meta content="T10ISLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iran-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Persian Gulf</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khamenei, Ali (Ayatollah)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D9153CF933A25751C1A961958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Presence in Gulf Is Denounced in Iran</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>TEHERAN, Iran, Dec. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iran opens world Islamic conference with harsh denunciation of West, urging Muslim countries to resist what it calls 'persistent and cunning enemies' led by US and Israel; Ayatollah Ali Khamenei says US and its military presence in Persian Gulf is main threat to security in region; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iran opened a world Islamic conference today with a harsh denunciation of the West, urging Muslim countries to resist what it called ''persistent and cunning enemies'' led by the United States and Israel.</p>
        <p>The country's supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, told his guests that the main threat to security in the region was not his own Islamic Government, as many in the West assert, but ''the poisonous breath'' of the United States and its military presence in the Persian Gulf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iran opened a world Islamic conference today with a harsh denunciation of the West, urging Muslim countries to resist what it called ''persistent and cunning enemies'' led by the United States and Israel.</p>
        <p>The country's supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, told his guests that the main threat to security in the region was not his own Islamic Government, as many in the West assert, but ''the poisonous breath'' of the United States and its military presence in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>The address was bound to unsettle Saudi and other gulf leaders who since the Iranian revolution of 1979 have remained wary of Iranian intentions and now rely for their security on American protection. It must also have rankled Egypt and Jordan, who by making peace with Israel have established close bonds with Washington.</p>
        <p>But though Iran's President later offered more conciliatory remarks, Ayatollah Khamenei's inaugural seemed to signal Iran's intention as host of the three-day meeting to drive home a message that Islam itself is under attack.</p>
        <p>''Today, global arrogance gains hope and strength through creating discord and disunity in this front,'' the Ayatollah said. ''Is it not time to bolster and strengthen this rank in our favor?''</p>
        <p>The address was met with no more than polite applause within a circular conference hall built at the foot of the snow-dappled Elburz Mountains to house the heads of state and top officials who have assembled here for the first meeting of the 55-member Organization of the Islamic Conference in three years.</p>
        <p>But the 45-minute address by the conservative cleric put on center stage some of the hard-line views that still carry great weight within powerful sectors of Iranian society eight years after the death of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, who inspired the revolution that established Iran as the world's first Islamic republic.</p>
        <p>To underscore the gravity with which it intended the Ayatollah's address to be received, the Iranian Government circulated copies of the remarks in glossy pamphlets that included translations from Persian into English, Russian, French and Arabic.</p>
        <p>In his address, the Ayatollah labeled as Iran's most dangerous critics ''the Zionists, the notorious global Zionist media, and the agents of arrogance, in particular the Americans.''</p>
        <p>And he complained that ''Western materialistic civilization is directing everyone toward materialism while money, gluttony and carnal desires are made the greatest aspirations.''</p>
        <p>President Mohammed Khatami, whose overwhelming victory in elections last spring has helped give Iran a gentler face, later characterized relations between Islam and the West in warmer terms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khatami, who is also a cleric, said Islamic civil society and its Western counterpart were ''not necessarily in conflict and contradiction in all their manifestations and consequences.</p>
        <p>''This is why we should never be oblivious to judicious acquisition of the positive accomplishments of the Western civil society,'' Mr. Khatami said.</p>
        <p>But Ayatollah Khamenei has emphasized since the election that it is he, and not the President, who wields control over foreign policy and most other matters of state. And because it was he, rather than Mr. Khatami, who chose to inaugurate the conference this morning, the most powerful impression left by the proceedings was his message of defiance.</p>
        <p>The Ayatollah chose not to single out Arab nations that have diplomatic or commercial ties with Israel. But he condemned American-backed efforts to broker a broader peace between Israel and the Palestinians as ''unjust, arrogant, contemptuous and, finally, illogical,'' and he called them a ''losing transaction'' for the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>On a matter closer to Iran's borders, he complained that ''the political designers of arrogance'' -- a standard euphemism for the United States and its Western allies -- ''are breathing their poisonous breath to make our neighbors in the Persian Gulf fearful of Islamic Iran, which holds the banner of unity and brotherhood.''</p>
        <p>As Iran has done before, the Ayatollah called on countries bordering the Persian Gulf to band together for self-protection rather than rely on outsiders like the United States.</p>
        <p>So far, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Bahrain, the United Arab Emirates and the other conservative monarchies of the gulf have rejected such appeals, fearing that Iran may still intend to export the kind of religious unrest that led in 1979 to the overthrow of Shah Mohammed Riza Pahlevi, another staunch ally of the United States.</p>
        <p>Today, Crown Prince Abdullah of Saudi Arabia referred obliquely to such concerns by urging delegates to the conference to remain on guard against ''extensive militancy that has shed Islamic blood in the name of Islam.''</p>
        <p>But in his own bid to revive Iran's quest to establish new military ties among the countries of the gulf, Ayatollah Khamenei solemnly declared, ''Islamic Iran poses no threat to any Islamic country.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Renewed Offer to Hold Talks</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, Dec. 9 (Reuters) -- The United States embraced a call today by President Khatami for a dialogue and renewed its offer to hold talks with an ''authorized'' Iranian Government representative.</p>
        <p>The State Department deputy spokesman, James Foley, said, ''We are not seeking to change the nature of the Iranian regime.'' The United States has often called Iran an outlaw regime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foley's comments were the latest in a series of cautious public overtures underscoring a willingness to consider re-engaging with a country the United States has worked to isolate for nearly 20 years.</p>
        <p>''Certainly we would welcome and support the idea of an open dialogue between different cultures and civilizations,'' Mr. Foley said. ''I think President Khatami has been endeavoring to emphasize the commonality of world civilization and of world values. And we hope that those kinds of remarks begin to be reflected also in the foreign policy sphere in the way nations deal with each other on a state-to-state level.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Foley was reacting to comments earlier today by Mr. Khatami,  at an Islamic conference in Teheran.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khatami said that Muslims should take advantage of the positive scientific, technological and social achievements of the West to build an ''Islamic civil society.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
