<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic Vows a Parade of Witnesses, Including Clinton</title>
    <meta content="Y16MIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/16/international/europe/16MILO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1368179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hague (Netherlands)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations War Crimes Tribunal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/The Hague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">The Hague (Netherlands)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">International War Crimes Tribunal</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5D7133FF935A25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic Vows a Parade of Witnesses, Including Clinton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Milosevic Vows a Parade of Witnesses, Including Clinton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER and MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise; Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>THE HAGUE, Feb. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Slobodan Milosevic says he will call present and past world leaders, including former Pres Bill Clinton, to stand during his war crimes trial at Hague; says he will personally cross-examine witnesses, including those who were raped, tortured or had their families killed, purportedly by Serbs; International War Crimes Tribunal must manage defendant who seems likley to represent himself with full-bore focus during trial that may last two years; Milosevic outlines his defense during defiant speech lasting over four hours; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sweeping away his last sliver of indifference to his war crimes trial, Slobodan Milosevic announced today that he would call present and past world leaders, including former President Bill Clinton, to the stand.</p>
        <p>Now engaging actively with a tribunal he once affected to spurn, he said he also planned personally to cross-examine witnesses, including those who were raped, tortured or had their families killed, purportedly by Serbs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slobodan Milosevic announced on Friday that he would call present and past world leaders to the stand as part of his his war crimes trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sweeping away his last sliver of indifference to his war crimes trial, Slobodan Milosevic announced today that he would call present and past world leaders, including former President Bill Clinton, to the stand.</p>
        <p>Now engaging actively with a tribunal he once affected to spurn, he said he also planned personally to cross-examine witnesses, including those who were raped, tortured or had their families killed, purportedly by Serbs.</p>
        <p>Jutting out his chin, the former Yugoslav leader still addressed the chief judge, Richard May, as ''Mister May.'' But he set aside his disdain for the bench in a brief polite exchange in English. This afternoon, Judge May granted Mr. Milosevic -- who had complained all morning about being rushed -- an extension of his opening statement, in its second day today, until ''lunch time'' on Monday.</p>
        <p>''I understand that is up to one  o'clock?'' Mr. Milosevic, who has spoken in Serbian, asked in English. ''O.K. Thank you.'' He then moved on without argument, promising to slow  his flood of words to ease the burden on the interpreters.</p>
        <p>In its fifth year of trials, the International War Crimes Tribunal is now facing a position without precedent: it has to manage a defendant who is not only representing himself without lawyers, but seems likely to do so with full-bore focus during a trial expected to last two years.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Milosevic, speaking for over four hours, continued to outline that defense. He did so by switching among at least three roles: the fighter against what he says is a stacked trial; the humanist and pacifist who spoke in reverence about the dead, even ethnic Albanian civilians; the professor explaining how the Balkans have been battered by history.  His oratory was as harsh as on the first day of his opening statement, on  Thursday: He accused the Clinton administration of ''genocide'' against Serbs and asked NATO leaders, who bombed Yugoslavia for 78 days in 1999, how they confronted their consciences.</p>
        <p>''It constitutes a crime,'' he said, again showing dozens of photographs of civilians torn to pieces and turned to ash by NATO bombs. ''Those who kill children while they sleep can hardly sleep peacefully themselves if they are human at all, if they have any moral sense.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic is himself charged, in essence, with being the man most responsible for more than 200,000 deaths in wars in Croatia, Bosnia-Herzegovina and Kosovo, the southern province of Serbia, during the 1990's. The first head of state to be charged with crimes so grave, he has been indicted for genocide against Bosnian Muslims, as well as crimes against humanity and other offenses.</p>
        <p>Since his arrest in June, Mr. Milosevic has questioned the legality of the court, claiming that he refused to appoint defense lawyers as a way of negating the court's authority.</p>
        <p>But today, after watching him speak for two days, legal experts saw him as deeply immersed in the trial, even if his exposés amounted to a political offensive against NATO and its ''accomplice,'' the tribunal, rather than a legal defense.</p>
        <p>''He has now implicitly recognized the court,'' said Avril McDonald, a lawyer at the Asser Institute for International Law here and a former official of the tribunal. ''He is addressing it. He still calls Judge May 'Mr. May' as a way to avoid his authority.'' But, she said: ''He's following the process and has engaged in it, and he's going to ask the help of the court to subpoena witnesses.''</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Milosevic named some of those witnesses, all of whom were involved with negotiations in the three wars but few of whom may appear. They include: former President Clinton; Madeleine K. Albright, the former American secretary of state; Kofi Annan, the United Nations secretary general; Gerhard Schröder, the German prime minister, and his predecessor, Helmut Kohl; Klaus Kinkel, the former German foreign minister; and Rudolf Scharping, the German defense minister. On Thursday, he said he would call President Jacques Chirac of France.</p>
        <p>He also said he would cross-examine the prosecution's witnesses, who are scheduled to begin testifying in the Kosovo portion of the trial early next week. Some of the first witnesses are expected to describe how Serb forces, who prosecutors say were under Mr. Milosevic's ultimate command, killed their relatives.</p>
        <p>The tenor of the trial will then change. After the opening statements, during which both sides are permitted to contend what they please, the judges will permit little leeway aside from what is relevant to each witness's testimony.</p>
        <p>''It's up to the judges to maintain the dignity of the proceedings, and they will,'' said Jim Landale, the  spokesman for the tribunal.</p>
        <p>Still, there is some degree of uncertainty since the tribunal has never had a defendant act without a lawyer before, and has never had one  with Mr. Milosevic's high profile. ''It will be a very tricky process, both for him and for the judges,'' said a judge who has served at the tribunal. ''It will be a unique trial.''</p>
        <p>In court today, Mr. Milosevic continued the assault on NATO that he began on Thursday, this time accusing President Clinton of ''genocide''  for what he said was deliberately selecting civilians as targets in the bombing of Kosovo and Serbia. Western leaders say the bombing was meant to force Mr. Milosevic's army to end atrocities against the Kosovar Albanians.</p>
        <p>''What no predecessor did before him, Clinton did,'' Mr. Milosevic said.</p>
        <p>''He proclaimed genocide as a state policy. He said there would be no victims on their side. He proclaimed the destruction of an independent and sovereign state -- 776 times weaker, 10,000 kilometers  away from America as a target for a war without casualties.''</p>
        <p>In one of several historical accounts, he warned against the dangers of Albanian nationalism and the Albanian ''mafia'' -- calling them traders in drugs, white slaves and weapons -- with whom he said the West had sided.</p>
        <p>He asked why NATO leaders were not charged with war crimes because they were in charge in Kosovo at a time when tens of thousands of Serbs were forced from their homes by Albanians after Mr. Milosevic surrendered in June 1999.</p>
        <p>He also said that he had issued orders and instituted new laws in 1999 that prohibited war crimes and the formation of paramilitary units.  He said he gave strict orders to arrest and disarm the paramilitary units because they ''usually consisted of looters, not patriots.''</p>
        <p>There were orders against committing war crimes against civilians, he said, ''orders against murder, rape, robbery, grave armed robbery.'' He held up texts, presumably of the orders, saying they would be made available to the court. ''So what more can you expect from a supreme commander or head of state?''</p>
        <p>And again and again, he appeared to address Serbs back at home, telling the judges at one point that ''you are actually holding a trial of the whole country here.''</p>
        <p>''My advantage is that I can look anyone in the eye,'' he said. ''I defended my country honorably and chivalrously. I can say that the Yugoslav Army and police also conducted themselves honorably and chivalrously. They did not stain their name in any way.''</p>
        <p>The seat of chief prosecutor, Carla Del Ponte, remained empty today. She was in the Bosnian town of Banja Luka, demanding that Bosnian Serb authorities arrest Radovan Karadzic, the fugitive wartime leader who has been indicted for genocide.</p>
        <p>''For sure we know that Karadzic is here,'' she said. After meeting with the Bosnian Serb authorities, she said their lack of cooperation had left her ''unsatisfied and frustrated.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
