<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concerns on Safety Push Britain to Reassume Control of Rail Maintenance</title>
    <meta content="Y25RAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/25/business/worldbusiness/25RAIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1529849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Network Rail Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1231F936A15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concerns on Safety Push Britain to Reassume Control of Rail Maintenance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Britain to Reassume Control of Rail Maintenance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Britain's railway authorities announce that maintenance contracts awarded to seven private companies will be taken over by government-backed Network Rail; series of fatal train crashes have raised concern that safety standards have suffered under privatization drive; shares of some of maintenance companies fall by as much as a fifth, reflecting investor calculations that rail maintenance contracts, which are worth $2 billion a year, provided those companies with badly needed revenue to offset slowdown in construction and engineering (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spurred by growing safety concerns, Britain's railway authorities reversed a crucial element of the nation's rail privatization on Friday, announcing that maintenance contracts awarded to seven private companies -- worth $2 billion a year -- would be taken over by the government-backed Network Rail.</p>
        <p>The move was the most significant setback in a mostly successful series of privatizations in the 1980's and 1990's that put businesses from telecommunications to utilities into private hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spurred by growing safety concerns, Britains railway authorities reversed a crucial element of the nations rail privatization on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spurred by growing safety concerns, Britain's railway authorities reversed a crucial element of the nation's rail privatization on Friday, announcing that maintenance contracts awarded to seven private companies -- worth $2 billion a year -- would be taken over by the government-backed Network Rail.</p>
        <p>The move was the most significant setback in a mostly successful series of privatizations in the 1980's and 1990's that put businesses from telecommunications to utilities into private hands.</p>
        <p>Shares of some of the maintenance companies fell by as much as a fifth, reflecting investor calculations that rail maintenance had provided those companies with badly needed revenue to offset a slowdown in construction and engineering.</p>
        <p>The return to government control on maintenance of the 20,000-mile network followed a series of fatal train crashes, which raised concern that safety standards since privatization were being overlooked in the rush for profit.</p>
        <p>Some 18,500 workers from the private maintenance groups will be absorbed by Network Rail.</p>
        <p>Britain's creaky rail network, sold into private hands nine years ago, was initially run by a private company called Railtrack, which went bankrupt last year. The government was forced to transfer control of the rail network, signals and stations to Network Rail. After decades of underinvestment, the poor state of the rail network was blamed for fatal train wrecks at Hatfield and Potters Bar north of London.</p>
        <p>Under the rail privatization of the 1990's, the monolithic British Rail was broken up, with the tracks and stations, rolling stock and regional franchises all going to separate private owners. The system is overseen by the government's Strategic Rail Authority, which said on Friday that the latest move was not a step toward renationalization'' because private contractors would still handle track renewal and other work not related purely to maintenance.</p>
        <p>Some of the companies to lose contracts said that they had been unaware of Network Rail's plans. Ian McAllister, the chairman of Network Rail, said the move was ''the right thing to do'' to increase the quality of maintenance and save around $340 million a year.</p>
        <p>Shares in one of the seven companies, the Peterhouse Group, fell by 25 percent while shares in another, Carillion, dropped almost 16 percent.</p>
        <p>The move could have repercussions beyond the national rail service. Three of the companies that lost rail-maintenance contracts -- Jarvis, Amey and Balfour Beatty -- also have separate 30-year maintenance contracts as part of a program to improve London's subway system, which is known as the Tube.</p>
        <p>Labor leaders representing 9,000 subway workers are already calling for strikes to protest poor maintenance after a series of recent derailments that have disrupted subway services in central and north London. They now seem likely to turn their sights to the maintenance contractors.</p>
        <p>Bob Crow, a labor leader representing subway workers, said that ''any justification for maintaining these crazy contracts has now completely evaporated.''</p>
        <p>''It is now untenable that the same companies now being kicked out of maintenance contracts on the national railway network should be allowed to continue to profit from declining safety standards on the Tube,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
