<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Center Drops the Joffrey</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES MUSIC CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1339F93AA35750C0A967958260" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Center Drops the Joffrey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles Music Center has decided not to extend its contract with the Joffrey Ballet, which has been the center's resident ballet troupe since 1983.</p>
        <p>Sandra Kimberling, president of the Music Center Operating Company, said yesterday that a contract had been offered to the financially troubled Joffrey, which is based in New York City, but that it had not met a March 4 deadline to prove its fiscal soundness or provided a $725,000 guarantee against ticket sales for the winter and spring seasons in 1991-1992 in Los Angeles. A request by the Joffrey for an extension was turned down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Los Angeles Music Center has decided not to extend its contract with the Joffrey Ballet, which has been the center's resident ballet troupe since 1983.</p>
        <p>Sandra Kimberling, president of the Music Center Operating Company, said yesterday that a contract had been offered to the financially troubled Joffrey, which is based in New York City, but that it had not met a March 4 deadline to prove its fiscal soundness or provided a $725,000 guarantee against ticket sales for the winter and spring seasons in 1991-1992 in Los Angeles. A request by the Joffrey for an extension was turned down.</p>
        <p>The loss of the Music Center as a second home may significantly reduce the Joffrey's fund-raising base. The troupe also loses the yearly allocation that the Music Center gives to all its resident companies, and that in the Joffrey's case ranged from $1 million to $2 million.</p>
        <p>For the Joffrey, the announcement came in the midst of a triumphant 35th-anniversary season at the New York State Theater that featured three new works and a revival created with new funds from Absolut Vodka.</p>
        <p>"The Joffrey Ballet is saddened that the Music Center Operating Company has chosen to release the performing time that it had been holding for the company for next year," the company said in a statement yesterday. "The company is widely regarded to be at a new peak of creativity and artistry. At the same time that we are receiving artistic and public acclaim, we continue to strengthen our administrative and financial position."</p>
        <p>The Joffrey added that while it understood the pressure the center was under to book its hall, "we are disappointed that it decided not to grant our request for an extension of its time deadline for providing the guaranties."</p>
        <p>Ms. Kimberling said that the budgets of all resident companies were reviewed annually at the Music Center. "We asked for guarantees because of past problems," she said, citing internal difficulties at the Joffrey that led to the resignation last May of Gerald Arpino, the artistic director and a founder of the company with Robert Joffrey. At the same time, there were disclosures of a $1.4 million accumulated deficit, since cut to $500,000, and a debt of $800,000 in payroll withholding taxes, which the company has paid.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kimberling said the operating company, which manages the center, and the center itself, which raises money and has independent contracts with the resident companies, stopped getting Joffrey financial reports in November.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
