<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shutdown Warning At Pan Am</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED AIR LINES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PAN AMERICAN WORLD AIRWAYS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D71E31F93AA35750C0A967958260" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shutdown Warning At Pan Am</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The operations of Pan American World Airlines could be shut down as early as next week if negotiators from the United States and Britain fail to reach an agreement that would allow Pan Am to transfer its London routes, several advisers to Pan Am said yesterday.</p>
        <p>If an agreement is reached in the negotiations, which continued in Washington yesterday, Pan Am could close on its sale of the routes to United Airlines and receive a payment of $290 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The operations of Pan American World Airlines could be shut down as early as next week if negotiators from the United States and Britain fail to reach an agreement that would allow Pan Am to transfer its London routes, several advisers to Pan Am said yesterday.</p>
        <p>If an agreement is reached in the negotiations, which continued in Washington yesterday, Pan Am could close on its sale of the routes to United Airlines and receive a payment of $290 million.</p>
        <p>The money would enable Pan Am to pay off $100 million it has drawn from a $150 million loan from the Bankers Trust Company. The airline could also make about $40 million in lease payments owed on 100 of the 154 planes in its fleet.  Assets Vulnerable</p>
        <p>If Pan Am is unable to make the payments, Bankers Trust would be able to seize some of Pan Am's assets -- in particular the Pan Am Shuttle, which was used as collateral for the loan.</p>
        <p>The airline's secured creditors -- those whose loans are backed by collateral -- could also begin seizing up to 100 of Pan Am's planes, a step that would severely disrupt passenger service and possibly force a liquidation of the company.</p>
        <p>Judge Cornelius Blackshear of the United States Bankruptcy Court in Manhattan ruled yesterday that the secured creditors would have the right to seize the planes if Pan Am failed to make lease payments. Pan Am had asked the judge to issue an order preventing any seizures.</p>
        <p>Pan Am said it planned to appeal the decision to a higher court. Talks Seen as Crucial</p>
        <p>Several advisers close to Pan Am said yesterday that the carrier's fate would be decided in the talks between negotiators of the Transportation Department and the State Department and their British counterparts.</p>
        <p>"If there is life in the negotiations, there is life in Pan Am," said one aviser, who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>If the talks continue, United could intervene and seek to persuade Bankers Trust to hold off on demanding its payment of $100 million.</p>
        <p>The secured creditors are also expected to delay asking United States marshals to seize aircraft if there is a chance that an agreement on the London route sale can be reached.</p>
        <p>If the talks break down, however, there is general agreement in the airline industry that the carrier -- which pioneered service over the Pacific, helped bring in the jet age and virtually became the official carrier of the United States -- would have to stop service and be liquidated.</p>
        <p>James Giddens, a lawyer representing some of the secured creditors, said he did not expect any of them to move precipitiously to stop the aircraft from flying. He added, "But they could."</p>
        <p>The decision by Judge Blackshear improved the bargaining position of the secured creditors, Mr. Giddens said.</p>
        <p>Generally when a company like Pan Am files for protection under Chapter 11 of the Federal Bankruptcy Code, its assets can be transferred to creditors only if the bankruptcy court approves.</p>
        <p>In the case of airlines, however, a section of the bankruptcy code gives creditors the right to seize aircraft after 60 days of the bankruptcy filing if the airline has defaulted on its lease payments. Differing Interpretations</p>
        <p>The courts have made differing interpretations on what are called sale-leasebacks, agreements under which an airline buys a new airplane or sells an old one to a group of investors. Those investors, in turn, lease the plane back to the airline. Pan Am operates most of its planes under such arrangements.</p>
        <p>In the case of Continental Airlines, which declared bankruptcy last year and faced a similar problem, Federal Bankruptcy Judge Helen Balick held that the creditors did not have the right to seize the planes after 60 days.</p>
        <p>Judge Blackshear held, however, that the statute was clear in giving the creditors the right to seize the aircraft.</p>
        <p>The latest developments put new pressure on the American negotiators who are trying to bridge a large gap with the British officials over the transfer of Pan Am's London routes.  Change Sought in Pact</p>
        <p>The United States is asking Britain to change an agreement governing aviation rights between the two nations so that two powerful American carriers, United and American Airlines, could take over the Heathrow airport landing rights of Pan Am and Trans World Airlines.</p>
        <p>In addition to allowing Pan Am to continue to operate, approval of the transfer would strengthen T.W.A., which is also financially shaky.</p>
        <p>For the British, the transfers would put much greater competitive pressure on British Airways, now the dominant carrier at Heathrow. The airport is more desirable than the other big London airport, Gatwick, since it is closer to London, is connected to the city by subway and has a large number of connecting flights.</p>
        <p>The position of the United States is complicated by the fact that it cannot offer one simple concession to the British, who are asking for such major changes in aviation policy as the right of British airlines to carry passengers in the United States when British planes are flying between American cities.</p>
        <p>They have also asked for through rights, which would enable them, for example, to take on passengers at a stop like Dallas-Fort Worth Airport and fly them to Mexico City.</p>
        <p>Better representation of British carriers on the computer reservation systems of the big domestic airlines is also sought. The move would help to improve the marketing of those airlines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
