<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sixth Child Dies in Philadelphia; 5 Others Are Given Measles Shots</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEASLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VACCINATION AND VACCINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA (PA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FAITH TABERNACLE CONGREGATION (PHILADELPHIA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Measles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Measles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD1031F93AA35750C0A967958260" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sixth Child Dies in Philadelphia; 5 Others Are Given Measles Shots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, March 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sixth child whose family opposes measles vaccinations for religious reasons died here today, and five others were inoculated against the disease undercourt order.</p>
        <p>Both the State Superior and State Supreme Courts refused today to intervene in the court-ordered inoculation of the children. On Monday, Judge Edward R. Summers of the Family Court ordered that the city immunize the five, whose families belong to the Faith Tabernacle Congregation, and on Thursday he specified that the inoculations be done by 4:30 P.M. today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sixth child whose family opposes measles vaccinations for religious reasons died here today, and five others were inoculated against the disease undercourt order.</p>
        <p>Both the State Superior and State Supreme Courts refused today to intervene in the court-ordered inoculation of the children. On Monday, Judge Edward R. Summers of the Family Court ordered that the city immunize the five, whose families belong to the Faith Tabernacle Congregation, and on Thursday he specified that the inoculations be done by 4:30 P.M. today.</p>
        <p>Members of Faith Tabernacle Congregation believe in faith healing and oppose medical treatment.</p>
        <p>John Wiggins, a lawyer for the Philadelphia Department of Health, said this evening that the inoculations had taken place without incident. He said the families were cooperative, but he declined to say where the inoculations had taken place.</p>
        <p>Earlier, after the death of a sixth child whose family belongs to a religious group that opposes medical treatment, the City Solicitor, Charisse R. Lillie, said, "We are very nervous." Firm Feeling on Protection</p>
        <p>"We are certain if we inoculate them their lives will be saved and they will be protected from the disease," she said. Five of the deaths have been children from the Faith Tabernacle Congregation in North Philadelphia. The sixth child's family belonged to the First Century Gospel Church in Northeast Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>There was no official confirmation today that the latest death was caused by measles. Phyllis Propert, a spokeswoman for St. Christopher's Hospital for Children, said the child, James Jones, 19 months old, had died from brain damage. But Ms. Propert said the cause of the damage "is not clear at this time."</p>
        <p>The boy, whose mother, Jean, belongs to Faith Tabernacle Congregation, had contracted measles within the last two weeks and had appeared to be recovering before taking a turn for the worse. He was hospitalized on Wednesday after his father, who is not a member of the church, telephoned the police. The hospital listed the child in very critical condition and put him on life support systems.</p>
        <p>Today's court actions left unanswered the question of whether the city will have the ability to intervene medically in the families' lives in the future. Earlier this week Judge Summers imposed stringent requirements on the churches that believe in faith healing, like having preschool children see a doctor once a month and having schools report children absent from school more than three days. But on Thursday the judge postponed enforcement of that order until a hearing later this month.</p>
        <p>"I'm assuming this kind of opens the door for intervention in their lives," said Ms. Lillie, the City Solicitor. "I'd be surprised if this issue is over with."</p>
        <p>Stefan Presser, legal director for the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, which is helping represent the families, said the group was prepared to appeal further.</p>
        <p>"This drama has been played against a backdrop of a real human tragedy," Mr. Presser said. He suggested that today's death could be having an effect on court action. "Courts are often persuaded to rule because of certain facts," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
