<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Given a Shot at Lefties, Cone Trips Up</title>
    <meta content="17YANK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DE1530F934A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Given a Shot at Lefties, Cone Trips Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Detroit Tigers beat New York Yankees, 3-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees could average about two victories a week the rest of the season and still make the playoffs. Now the guiding force behind most of Manager Joe Torre's decisions will be what's best for the Yankees in October.</p>
        <p>Allowing David Cone to succeed or fail in the eighth inning against Detroit tonight, as Torre did, injects Cone with the knowledge that his manager has confidence in him, and maybe that will benefit the Yankees in the post-season. Tonight, Cone allowed a tie-breaking single to Luis Gonzalez with two outs in the eighth and the Yankees lost, 3-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees could average about two victories a week the rest of the season and still make the playoffs. Now the guiding force behind most of Manager Joe Torre's decisions will be what's best for the Yankees in October.</p>
        <p>Allowing David Cone to succeed or fail in the eighth inning against Detroit tonight, as Torre did, injects Cone with the knowledge that his manager has confidence in him, and maybe that will benefit the Yankees in the post-season. Tonight, Cone allowed a tie-breaking single to Luis Gonzalez with two outs in the eighth and the Yankees lost, 3-1.</p>
        <p>Detroit's Brian Moehler threw eight and one-third innings to become only the second pitcher to beat the Yankees twice this season.</p>
        <p>Maybe Torre should have replaced Cone with the left-hander Mike Stanton as the left-handed-hitting Gonzalez came to bat. Maybe not. A debate team could probably win arguing either side. But it's all about the big picture now with the Yankees, a byproduct of their 67-22 record. Any mental edge derived from Torre's decisions far outweighs a loss that very likely will be meaningless to the American League East standing.</p>
        <p>''That was nice, because it told me that he trusted me,'' said Cone, who lost for the first time since June 19. ''It gives me confidence.''</p>
        <p>Torre said: ''What I like to do with starters is give them a chance to win. But they deserve a chance to lose, too.''</p>
        <p>The near inevitability of a Yankee playoff appearance is why Torre may decide to rest Darryl Strawberry, who has a sore left knee, for the next two weeks. On Sunday, Torre did not use Paul O'Neill to pinch-hit for the rookie Ricky Ledee in the ninth inning of a tie game, primarily because Torre wants Ledee to adapt to pressure situations -- such as those he may face in October.</p>
        <p>Cone is Torre's ace, the soul of his pitching staff. Torre says he believes in Cone ''as much as I believe in anybody,'' adding, ''I trust his heart, basically.''</p>
        <p>After seeing Cone work and struggle and eventually succeed in his comeback from shoulder surgery, Torre wants Cone to feel this trust.</p>
        <p>Cone (13-3) allowed only five hits in the first seven innings; his fastball was sizzling once again, his command excellent. His only mistake had been throwing a high fastball to Raul Casanova in the fifth inning that Casanova blasted into the right-field stands. That tied the score at 1-1, matching a home run to lead off the game by Chuck Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>But with one out in the eighth, Damion Easley, who had struck out in his first three at-bats, worked the count to 3-2. Cone thought about throwing Easley a fastball, but each of his strikeouts had come with a sidearm slider -- the laredo, Cone sometimes calls it. Cone came with the slider over the plate, and Easley lined a double to left, directly at Ledee, and then over his head.</p>
        <p>Stanton was warming up in the bullpen, a left-hander preparing to possibly face the next three hitters -- the left-handed-hitting Bobby Higginson, the switch-hitting Tony Clark and left-handed-hitting Gonzalez. Torre said, however, that Stanton was more of a contingency, in case Cone tired quickly.</p>
        <p>Cone zipped a 3-2 fastball over the inside corner to strike out Higginson, and both he and Joe Girardi thought at that moment that they were going to get out of the inning. There were two outs.</p>
        <p>Clark, 0 for 20 in his career against Cone, went to a 3-2 count, and again Cone thought about trying to throw a fastball inside. Cone tried a slider instead and missed with it, walking Clark.</p>
        <p>Gonzalez walked to the plate, Torre stayed in the dugout. Cone threw a splitter that dived low and away, and Gonzalez managed to pull a ground ball to the right side. An out, Cone thought for an instant. He was wrong. Knoblauch, the second baseman, noted that this ground ball never hit the grass -- it hit the dirt in front of home plate, bounced over the grass that surely would have slowed it and then skipped on the infield dirt and into right field.</p>
        <p>O'Neill, trying desperately to cut down Easley at the plate, threw high and away, and Clark followed Easley across home with Detroit's third run. Gonzalez's hit was the first with runners in scoring position against a Yankee pitcher in 30 innings.</p>
        <p>Afterward, there was no lamenting, no anger. They just got beat, Cone said, by a team that played better. ''It sounds like a cliche,'' he said, ''but it's true in this case.''</p>
        <p>Particularly with Moehler, regarded as a solid but unspectacular pitcher who throws sinkers and sliders. From the on-deck circle, Chad Curtis said, Moehler is the type of pitcher about whom a hitter thinks: ''O.K., as soon as he makes a mistake, I'm going to get him. But he's not making very many mistakes.''</p>
        <p>On only five occasions this year has an opposing starter allowed one run in eight or more innings to the Yankees. Moehler (10-5) has done it twice now. ''It was nerve-wracking,'' he said, ''but lots of fun.''</p>
        <p>He had beaten Cone, a Cy Young Award candidate, and well-deserved bragging rights for a day. But Torre is probably more concerned that Cone win bragging rights against the Angels' Chuck Finley or the Indians' Jaret Wright in the fall.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER's return to his home state of Michigan was not bountiful. He went 0 for 5 on Wednesday, striking out three times, and on Thursday night he hit into a double play and struck out while going 1 for 4.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
