<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yeltsin, in Reversal, Will Attend Rite for Czar and Family</title>
    <meta content="Y17CZA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980725T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romanov Family (Russia)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholas II (Czar) (1868-1918)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DF1530F934A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yeltsin, in Reversal, Will Attend Rite for Czar and Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Russia, July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Boris N Yeltsin reverses himself, saying he will attend elaborate and much-debated interment of Czar Nicholas II, most of his family and four servants in Czar's imposing riverside fortress in St Petersburg; after Yeltsin changes his mind, leaders of upper house of Parliament say they will also send official delegation; lower house, the Duma, is ignoring event, and Duma's Communist leader claims Yeltsin is acting under political pressure from his advisers, charge Yeltsin's spokesman denies; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is difficult to upstage the burial of the final Czar, emperor and autocrat of all the Russias, the man whose remains were hidden for nearly eight decades by the Communists who killed him and seized his empire. But President Boris N. Yeltsin managed to do just that today.</p>
        <p>In trademark fashion, Mr. Yeltsin announced on television that he had decided to attend Friday's elaborate and much-debated interment of Czar Nicholas II, most of his family and four servants in the Czar's imposing riverside fortress here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is difficult to upstage the burial of the final Czar, emperor and autocrat of all the Russias, the man whose remains were hidden for nearly eight decades by the Communists who killed him and seized his empire. But President Boris N. Yeltsin managed to do just that today.</p>
        <p>In trademark fashion, Mr. Yeltsin announced on television that he had decided to attend Friday's elaborate and much-debated interment of Czar Nicholas II, most of his family and four servants in the Czar's imposing riverside fortress here.</p>
        <p>''This truth has been concealed for 80 years,'' Mr. Yeltsin said, referring to the killings. ''And we have to tell this truth tomorrow, and I should take part. This will be the right thing to do from the human point of view.''</p>
        <p>That caused a small sensation. Mr. Yeltsin had said only weeks ago that he would not go to the funeral, apparently because the country's political and religious factions are deeply split over its meaning and propriety. That announcement had, in turn, caused a stir, because it was Mr. Yeltsin who had virtually ordered a state funeral for the Czar in the first place, as an act of national repentance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's spokesman said today that the turnabout had occurred after ''hard thinking'' and a talk with Dmitri Likhachyov, a historian and major figure in Russian cultural affairs. It was not Mr. Yeltsin's first turnabout. As the Communist Party chairman in his hometown of Yekaterinburg, in the Ural Mountains, he ordered the destruction of the building where the Czar's family was held and executed.</p>
        <p>Almost but not quite lost amid the day's pirouettes was Nicholas himself, returning to his ancestral home for the first time since he abdicated in March 1917. The fragmentary remains of the Czar; his wife, Alexandra; three of his four daughters, and four servants were flown today from Yekaterinburg to the St. Petersburg airport, where they were unloaded to the accompaniment of an Army band's dirge and an honor guard's salute.</p>
        <p>Then each small wood coffin -- embellished with a cross, silk tassels and an engraved nameplate -- was loaded into its own teal minivan and escorted through the city to the hexagonal riverside fortress built by Nicholas's ancestor Peter the Great some 350 years ago.</p>
        <p>Aside from an occasional Communist flag, there was neither much protest nor approval along the long route until the motorcade neared the fortress. There thousands watched the procession of vans as the Russian tricolor and the red-and-yellow flag of St. Petersburg flapped under a bright sun and stiff wind at half-staff.</p>
        <p>Then, as bells rang, snare drums kept march time, and a Scottish bagpiper wheezed mournfully -- the Czar was related to Queen Victoria, and was honorary commander of a company of Scottish dragoons -- the coffins were taken into the fortress and carried to a cathedral, where services will be held on Friday. Then, at noon, the remains will be eulogized and lowered into a single crypt in the cathedral, which is already a mausoleum for the Romanov dynasty that ruled Russia from the 1600's until Nicholas's death.</p>
        <p>The execution of the Romanovs was until recently both one of the pivots and enigmas of 20th century history. It was long known that the imperial family and their servants were executed by Bolshevik revolutionaries in 1918. But the details of the deaths and the location of the bodies were carefully hidden secrets until close to the end of Communist rule in the late 80's.</p>
        <p>Leading historians now say most victims were hastily buried in a pit and covered with logs. Two bodies -- those of the Czar's only son and one daughter -- have never been found. Many experts say they believe that those bodies were partly burned and buried nearby.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. Yeltsin ordered the other bodies recovered and authenticated, after their discovery had become public. DNA tests in American and European laboratories concluded that the remains were almost certainly those of the royal family.</p>
        <p>But many Russian leaders have contested or ignored much of that account -- especially the still powerful Communist Party, whose leaders ordered the executions, and the Russian Orthodox Church, which is split over the authenticity of the remains.  The Russian public, ever suspicious of official pronouncements, is almost evenly split over whether the coffins contain royal bones, according to a new poll.</p>
        <p>Four hundred Government officials, diplomats, Romanov descendants and others will witness the service. But until today the guest list included few of the political or religious elite.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Yeltsin changed his mind, the leaders of the upper house of the Parliament, the Federation Council, said they would also send an official delegation. But the lower house, the Duma, is ignoring the event, and church leaders also are staying away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin is prone to schedule and cancel appearances almost as often as he fires and hires Cabinets, a trait -- or a tactic -- that has served to keep him at the center of public attention.</p>
        <p>His spokesman, who said on Monday that rumors of Mr. Yeltsin's attendance at the funeral were ''nonsense,'' said today that the change of heart was ''a courageous, humane and Christian act'' devoid of political meaning. Mr. Yeltsin's political allies and foes immediately began reading import into it anyway.</p>
        <p>Viktor Chernomyrdin, once Mr. Yeltsin's Prime Minister and now a candidate for President, called the funeral ''a mess.'' ''We shouldn't turn it into a show, trying to clear out who will attend and will not attend the ceremony,'' Mr. Chernomyrdin said.</p>
        <p>The Duma's Communist leader, Gennadi A. Zyuganov, said Mr. Yeltsin was clearly acting under political pressure from his advisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's spokesman said that was ''ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Outside the cathedral, a stooped and white-haired Russian woman in formal dress said her father had commanded forces in the so-called White Army that fought a failed counterrevolutionary battle against the Communists in 1918. ''Praise God,'' she said of the funeral. ''It's about time!''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 25, 1998, Saturday  An article on July 17 about President Boris N. Yeltsin's decision to attend the burial of Czar Nicholas II and his family in St. Petersburg misstated the age of the fortress of Peter and Paul, build by Nicholas's ancestor, Peter the Great. It was built some 250 years ago, not 350.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 25, 1998, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on July 17 about President Boris N. Yeltsin's decision to attend the burial of Czar Nicholas II and his family in St. Petersburg misstated the age of the fortress of Peter and Paul, build by Nicholas's ancestor, Peter the Great. It was built some 250 years ago, not 350.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
