<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</title>
    <meta content="17VIDB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Great Expectations (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Four Days in September (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Krippendorf's Tribe (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Zero Effect (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFD61730F934A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW VIDEO RELEASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of films now released on video: Great Expectations starring Gwyneth Paltrow, Four Days in September, Krippendorf's Tribe and Zero Effect; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Great Expectations</p>
        <p>It's Dickens a go-go in Florida as young Finn (Pip in the novel) grows up artistically inclined and hopelessly smitten with the lovely, haughty Estella. Miss Favisham is now Nora Dinsmoor (Anne Bancroft), spruced up and ready to party, and Magwitch, Dickens's escaped convict, is called Lustig (Robert De Niro) and has mob connections. Later, in New York, Finn (played as an adult by Ethan Hawke) electrifies the art world and again encounters Estella (Gwyneth Paltrow, above), who's still haughty but a little nicer. In sum, Alfonso Cuaron's film is saved by its look, which, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''makes up in visual exoticism some of what it loses in character and context.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Great Expectations</p>
        <p>It's Dickens a go-go in Florida as young Finn (Pip in the novel) grows up artistically inclined and hopelessly smitten with the lovely, haughty Estella. Miss Favisham is now Nora Dinsmoor (Anne Bancroft), spruced up and ready to party, and Magwitch, Dickens's escaped convict, is called Lustig (Robert De Niro) and has mob connections. Later, in New York, Finn (played as an adult by Ethan Hawke) electrifies the art world and again encounters Estella (Gwyneth Paltrow, above), who's still haughty but a little nicer. In sum, Alfonso Cuaron's film is saved by its look, which, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''makes up in visual exoticism some of what it loses in character and context.''</p>
        <p>1997. Fox. $104.16. Laser disk, $39.98. 111 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Four Days in September</p>
        <p>To protest government death squads and torture, students kidnap the United States Ambassador to Brazil (Alan Arkin), which happened in 1969. What is achieved is arguable as the dissidents are caught and tortured themselves. In real life, democracy didn't return until 1989, partly because, Bruno Barreto's film suggests, student terrorism only fueled the tyranny. As for his gripping but often clumsy semi-fictional account, it ''presents a disturbingly ambiguous and unromantic portrait of retaliation against oppression'' (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>1997. Miramax. $104.16. Laser disk, $39.99. 105 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Krippendorf's Tribe</p>
        <p>Left in a funk when his wife dies, an eminent anthropologist (Richard Dreyfuss) blows a $100,000 grant on playthings and household expenses. To explain what happened to the money, he invents a lost tribe he says he has discovered called the Shelmikedmu, an amalgam of the names of his children (Shelly, Mickey and Edmund), who are obliged to play tribe members. Complications multiply, but Todd Holland's film ''maintains a focused plot, keeps its characters in character, uses its imagination and disdains dumb, irrelevant jokes'' (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
        <p>1998. Touchstone. $104.16. Laser disk, $39.99. 94 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Zero Effect</p>
        <p>Looking for a new hero, Jake Kasdan's film drums up a brilliant nerd from the Northwest. A wealthy recluse, Daryl Zero (Bill Pullman) makes a poor man's Sherlock Holmes, aided by a disrespectful Watson (Ben Stiller). For a case, there is the blackmail of a timber tycoon (Ryan O'Neal), but that gets sidetracked by a woman (Kim Dickens) who distracts Zero and robs the film of ''some of the wit that kept its early episodes lively'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1998. Warner. $104.16. Laser disk, $34.98. 115 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release at one time or appeared on television.</p>
        <p>IMAGE OF AN ASSASSINATION: A NEW LOOK AT THE ZAPRUDER FILM. The famous home movie of the bullet's impact when President Kennedy was shot has been digitally enlarged on a videotape that includes commentary by photography experts and representatives of the National Archives. 1998. MPI. Videocassette: $19.98, 45 minutes; digital video disk, $24.98.</p>
        <p>TIGHT SPOT. Available on tape for the first time, Phil Karlson's fine little thriller about a gangster's woman stars Ginger Rogers, Edward G. Robinson, Brian Keith and Lorne Greene. 1955. Columbia Tri-Star. $19.95. 97 minutes.</p>
        <p>SEVEN YEARS IN TIBET. No, this is not the Jean-Jacques Annaud adventure starring Brad Pitt, but the British documentary with Heinrich Harrer's original 16-millimeter film, shot in 1939 and 1940, of his trek in the Himalayas and sojourn in Tibet. 1957. Kino. $24.95. 79 minutes. Black and white.</p>
        <p>THE CHARLIE CHAN COLLECTION. By the 1940's, the series based on the novels of Earl Derr Biggers about the Chinese detective (Sidney Toler) with the No. 1 and No. 2 sons had become formulaic. The following -- all made in 1944 -- were fun nevertheless (and made in a hurry): ''Charlie Chan in the Secret Service,'' ''Meeting at Midnight,'' ''The Chinese Cat,'' ''The Jade Mask'' and ''The Scarlet Clue.''  MGM. $12.95 each. Running times are about 65 minutes each.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
