<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Predator Returned to the Wild Discovers It Is Now Prey</title>
    <meta content="22WOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5DA123CF931A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="1446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Predator Returned to the Wild Discovers It Is Now Prey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>ALPINE, Ariz., Dec. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Endangered Mexican grey wolf is having rocky return to forests of Arizona, where 11 were released under special program by wildlife officials in March; five have been shot, either by ranchers or hunters, 2 are missing and presumed dead and remainder recaptured for their safety; biologists, who plan to rework program, will release two more packs in National Forest in March 1999; goal is to have population of 100 Mexican wolves roaming forest by year 2005; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last spring, Bobby Fite peered down the sight of his .22 magnum rifle at what he thought was a coyote stalking two newborn calves near his house here.</p>
        <p>''I threw that scope on her, then I saw that box on her, and I thought, man, that's one of them wolves,'' Mr. Fite, a rancher, said, recalling how he lowered his rifle after he realized that the predator in his pasture was a Mexican gray wolf, or lobo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last spring, Bobby Fite peered down the sight of his .22 magnum rifle at what he thought was a coyote stalking two newborn calves near his house here.</p>
        <p>''I threw that scope on her, then I saw that box on her, and I thought, man, that's one of them wolves,'' Mr. Fite, a rancher, said, recalling how he lowered his rifle after he realized that the predator in his pasture was a Mexican gray wolf, or lobo.</p>
        <p>Newly reintroduced after ranchers exterminated them half a century ago from the high timberlands of eastern Arizona, today's lobos wear  radio collars that allow them to be tracked by biologists.</p>
        <p>But the wolves have had a rocky return to Arizona's forests this year. Of the first batch of 11 released in March, 5 were shot, 2 are missing and presumed dead, and the rest had to be recaptured for their safety while biologists reworked the program.</p>
        <p>Last week, scientists gave it another go, releasing two pair into the wilderness. This time, the hindquarters of each wolf were spray-painted orange. The radio collars were also painted, orange for males, pink for females.</p>
        <p>The paint should not interfere with the wolves' mating habits, because the animals are color-blind. But some environmentalists grumble that, even though the intent is to protect the wolves, marking them this way is the equivalent of painting large, fluorescent targets on their backsides.</p>
        <p>The paint is to help hunters distinguish Mexican wolves, one of the smallest wolf subspecies in North America, from coyotes, the garden-variety predators of the West. In much of the rural West, coyotes can be legally shot year round, no questions asked, no permits needed.</p>
        <p>''Coyotes are varmints,'' said Sam Luce, another rancher near here. ''They are in our chicken houses, killing our chickens, killing our barn cats. A lot of the sportsmen consider them a target. That puts the wolf in a bad situation, because he looks just like a coyote.''</p>
        <p>After the rash of wolf shootings in the fall, wildlife officials angrily called the killings ''sabotage.'' But now they say it appears that errors by hunters may account for most of the shootings.</p>
        <p>Aware that many local ranchers were hostile to the release of the wolves, biologists worked early this year to monitor the animals and remove them from areas with sheep and cows. They also educated ranchers about the penalty for intentionally killing a Mexican wolf, an endangered animal, on public land: a fine of up to $100,000 and a jail term of up to one year.</p>
        <p>The efforts appeared at first to be successful. Until the hunting season began in August, only one wolf was shot and killed -- by a camper.</p>
        <p>''If the ranchers wanted to shoot wolves, they would have shot them in April, May and June, when the wolves were in town, in calving pastures, among sheep, among horses,'' said Diane Boyd-Heger, a wolf biologist for the Arizona Game and Fish Department, who has directed the introduction program. ''The local people had plenty of opportunities to shoot these wolves. I really don't think it was the ranchers.''</p>
        <p>But things took a turn for the worse with the annual fall invasion by hunters of the Apache National Forest, which surrounds this tiny village. Before the season began, wildlife officials had mailed brochures explaining the wolf-recovery program to the 6,000 hunters who had permits to hunt dear, elk, bear and mountain lions in the wolf area.</p>
        <p>But from August through November, four wolves were shot dead over an area the size of Connecticut. According to the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, which is leading the investigation into the killings, at least three guns were used. Rewards totaling $45,000 have been posted for information leading to an arrest and conviction in a wolf killing case.</p>
        <p>''My personal feeling is it is just random,'' Ms. Boyd-Heger said. ''I don't think there is a concerted sabotage attempt. I don't think there is a conspiracy.''</p>
        <p>Undaunted by losing half of the wolves in the first year, biologists plan to release in the National Forest here next March two more packs, totaling nine wolves. The goal is to have a population of 100 Mexican wolves roaming the National Forest by the year 2005.</p>
        <p>Bruce Babbitt, the Secretary of the Interior and a former Governor of Arizona, has stressed his support for the program in two visits this year to this remote mountain town, a five-hour drive from Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Many people here, and in the rest of Arizona, support the return of the wolves. A poll in October of 720 Arizona residents by the Behavior Research Center, a Phoenix company, found that 61 percent of respondents said they had become more supportive in recent years of efforts to protect endangered wildlife.</p>
        <p>But in this economically depressed corner of the state, many people see the wolves as another blow imposed by outsiders to a traditional rural economy already hammered by dramatic reductions in timber harvests from public lands and in the number of cows that ranchers can have graze on public lands.</p>
        <p>''We've got plenty of predators around here already -- mountain lions, coyotes, lots of bears,'' said Dr. Luce, a retired doctor whose cattle grazes on his own land along the Blue River. He said that every fall when his neighbors rounded up their cattle from grazing on National Forest lands, they regularly discovered that they had lost about 10 percent of their calves to predators.</p>
        <p>''This competition just throws these wolves into the cattle,'' said Dr. Luce, who added that he occasionally saw wolves in his pastures this summer and that, in May, a wolf killed his 8-year-old trained cow dog, which he valued at $5,000.</p>
        <p>''A little old calf that can barely get into a trot is a lot easier to catch than a deer or elk that can run full blast,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tim Anderson, a big-game hunting guide, said over lunch at the Bear Wallow Cafe here that he had no problems with a few wolves in the woods. ''But if they get 100 up here, I don't know what will happen,'' Mr. Anderson said, as his prized blue tick hunting hounds barked outside.</p>
        <p>Worried by articles in hunting magazines about wolves killing hunting dogs in Minnesota, he said: ''I have hounds that I have turned down $4,000 for. I guess I'll just keep my fingers crossed.''</p>
        <p>The wolf release program was opposed by the ranching associations of New Mexico and Arizona, the Governors of both states and votes of county commissioners in 11 counties.</p>
        <p>In the past, ranchers were the angriest of the opponents, and some environmentalists charge that they are the ones are behind the killings.</p>
        <p>''The ranchers came out publicly saying, 'We will kill the wolves,' '' said Kieran Suckling, executive director of the Southwest Center for Biological Diversity, an environmental group in Tucson. ''After the killings, ranchers were the only group of people who came out and applauded. Now ranchers are the only group who are suing to stop the program.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting the polarization caused by the wolf release, on Dec. 6 someone fired a shotgun into the offices of a Santa Fe animal rights group. The group had received an anonymous letter threatening ''to kill any wolf reintroduced.''</p>
        <p>Four days later, someone spray-painted in large letters, ''Wolves'' and ''N.M. Needs Wolves'' on the building that houses the New Mexico Cattle Growers' Association. ''It is part of a radical agenda to move us off the land,'' said Caren Cowan, the association's executive secretary.  Noting that her ranching group has filed a legal challenge to the wolf program, Ms. Cowan added: ''Our members are law-abiding citizens. We don't condone anyone breaking the law.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Cattle Growers' Association sent out a press release urging hunters to boycott a Fish and Wildlife Service questionnaire about the wolf killings. Slipping into the kind of harsh language that  has often surrounded the wolf program, the association called the query ''Gestapo tactics by an out-of-control Federal agency embarrassed by the total failure of its all-advised reintroduction program.''</p>
        <p>[Faced with sharp criticism by three of New Mexico's Congressmen, the service retracted the questionnaire on Friday.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
