<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HCIA falls off the growth curve and the reaction is brutal.</title>
    <meta content="02PLAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Market Place" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Market Place"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hcia Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDD163FF931A35753C1A960958260" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HCIA falls off the growth curve and the reaction is brutal.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris (Market Place) column profiles HCIA, Baltimore company that collects and sells data in the health care industry; notes company announcement that it would post earnings for quarter ended Monday of 10 to 15 cents share, compared with expected 29 cents, had brutal impact on its stock, which closed at $32.875, down $27.125 in Nasdaq trading; stock price graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GROWTH is treasured on Wall Street, but the reaction can be brutal when a growth story is called into question.</p>
        <p>So it was with HCIA Inc., a company based in Baltimore that collects and sells data in the health care industry. It has been growing internally at 20 percent or more a year, and adding another 10 percent or so through acquisitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GROWTH is treasured on Wall Street, but the reaction can be brutal when a growth story is called into question.</p>
        <p>So it was with HCIA Inc., a company based in Baltimore that collects and sells data in the health care industry. It has been growing internally at 20 percent or more a year, and adding another 10 percent or so through acquisitions.</p>
        <p>But after the market closed on Monday, HCIA said it would not live up to the expectations it had created. Instead, it would post earnings for the quarter that ended Monday of 10 to 15 cents a share. The expectation had been for 29 cents.</p>
        <p>The reaction yesterday was brutal. The stock, which had closed Monday at $60 a share, fell as low as $30 and ended the day at $32.875, down $27.125 in Nasdaq trading. It was the session's most actively traded stock, with volume at 11.4 million shares, an extraordinary figure considering that the company has only 11.8 million shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>HCIA's explanation was that some big orders had failed to close by the end of the quarter. ''We knew there were some things pending, and we just had to wait to see what the final answers were.'' said Jean Chenoweth, the company's chief financial officer, in an interview.</p>
        <p>In a statement, George D. Pillari, the company's chairman and chief executive, said that the shortfall reflected a management paying a lot of attention to acquisitions and stock offerings and not enough to customer relations. He promised a new emphasis on that area.</p>
        <p>HCIA has been public for fewer than 20 months, and for most of that time has lived the kind of existence that companies dream of. ''We always made our numbers before,'' Ms. Chenoweth said.</p>
        <p>HCIA went public at $14 a share in February 1995, and closed at $19 the first day. After that, the share price kept rising even though the company was regularly selling stock to finance acquisitions. It sold shares in August 1995 at $28.50, in May of this year at $51 and in August at $54.125.</p>
        <p>The explanation of the shortfall seemed to indicate that HCIA, like many another company, had gotten into the habit of posting a lot of revenue at the end of each quarter to live up to expectations it had generated.</p>
        <p>HCIA has not yet been a huge profit generator anyway, in part because of a substantial write-off last year in connection with an acquisition. Another similar write-off is planned for the quarter just ended, as the company takes a loss relating to acquired research and development associated with the August acquisition of LBA Health Care Management Inc. The earnings forecast are before that write-off.</p>
        <p>Such write-offs are in accord with generally accepted accounting principles, but also have the effect of bolstering future earnings, because there is no need to amortize the cost of the research and development against those profits.</p>
        <p>Even ignoring that write-off, however, HCIA had been expected to earn only 97 cents a share this year, and thus was trading at more than 60 times anticipated earnings. With HCIA having also warned that its fourth-quarter earnings were likely to be 15 to 20 cents a share, it is estimating that profits for this year, before the write-off, are likely to be in the range of 77 to 87 cents a share. So even now, it is trading for at least 37 times forecasted earnings.</p>
        <p>Such is the risk for investors seeking growth. If and when that growth fails to appear, the fall can be stark, simply because the anticipation of so much good news is already in the price.</p>
        <p>''We're focused on making sure we don't miss our numbers again,'' Ms. Chenoweth said. ''We hope that things will even out as we move forward and perform and re-establish confidence.''</p>
        <p>Market Place</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
