<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restrictions Put on Right To a Lawyer</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWYERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RIGHT TO COUNSEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE1631F930A35754C0A966958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restrictions Put on Right To a Lawyer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH KOLBERT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, July 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Reversing a decision that had made New York's right to legal counsel the most far-reaching in the nation, the state's highest court ruled today that representation by a lawyer could be restricted in some cases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Reversing a decision that had made New York's right to legal counsel the most far-reaching in the nation, the state's highest court ruled today that representation by a lawyer could be restricted in some cases.</p>
        <p>Reversing a decision that had made New York's right to legal counsel the most far-reaching in the nation, the state's highest court ruled today that representation by a lawyer could be restricted in some cases.</p>
        <p>A deeply divided Court of Appeals ruled that a suspect who has retained a lawyer to represent him on one set of charges may be questioned about other charges without a lawyer present.</p>
        <p>The 4-3 decision overturned a landmark ruling by the court in 1981. In that ruling, the court held that a suspect who had requested a lawyer could not waive the right to counsel even if rearrested on different charges.</p>
        <p>Suspects Free on Bail Affected</p>
        <p>The ruling applied mainly to suspects out on bail. It meant that even a confession freely offered by the suspect in connection with the new charges could be suppressed if the lawyer representing the suspect on the first charges was not present during questioning. It established a broader right to counsel in New York State than that guaranteed by the United States Supreme Court or by any other court in the country.</p>
        <p>Today's ruling was actually a composite decision that combined three separate cases - one in Nassau County and two in Manhattan. The majority and the minority concurred on the results of two of the three cases, differing only on the outcome of the third case. But in a highly critical dissent, written by Judge Judith Kaye, the minority broke with the majority on the fundamental principals in all three cases.</p>
        <p>''Today the court breaks with its proud tradition,'' Judge Kaye wrote.</p>
        <p>The original ruling had longed vexed the police and prosecutors in New York, who contended that it protected repeat offenders.</p>
        <p>Today jubilant prosecutors said that the court's reversal would make it easier to prosecute some of the state's most practiced criminals.</p>
        <p>''We're delighted,'' said Edward Grilli, a spokesman for the Nassau County District Attorney's office, one of the parties to today's decision. The ruling, he said, ''will definitely have an impact on prosecutions.''</p>
        <p>One case prosecutors cite to illustrate what they say is the foolishness of the original ruling is the 1982 murder of a newspaper boy on Long Island. The suspect in that case had recently been arrested on an unrelated burglary charge and was out on bail. Because he had a lawyer in connection with the burglary charge, a written statement that the suspect made admitting to the murder was suppressed by the court.</p>
        <p>On the basis of other evidence, however, the suspect was eventually convicted of the murder.</p>
        <p>Right Must Be Waived</p>
        <p>Today's ruling will not affect the right to counsel of suspects who demand to have a lawyer present; it will only affect those suspects who agree to waive their right to counsel. Defense lawyers said today that they were disappointed by the decision, which they said would add to the disadvantages already suffered by poorly educated suspects.</p>
        <p>''It is clear that the better educated defendant is more likely to assert his right to counsel,'' said Philip L. Weinstein, chief of the appeals unit of the Legal Aid Society. The ruling, he said, ''will alter the results in a fair number of cases.''</p>
        <p>There are no reliable figures on how many prosecutions were stymied by the original ruling, but prosecutors said today that the number ran into the hundreds.</p>
        <p>Figures presented by the Manhattan District Attorney's office, which also was a party to today's decision, showed that more than half of the defendants arraigned in a state court in 1979 had other cases pending at their arrest and would have been covered by the original ruling. Although recent figures are not available, experts said today that they had no reason to believe they had changed significantly.</p>
        <p>'Lessons of Experience' Cited</p>
        <p>It is unusual for the court to abandon a landmark decision, as it did today, and both the majority ruling and the dissent reflected the uneasiness of the judges over the reversal.</p>
        <p>Writing for the majority, Judge Richard D. Simons said, ''Although a court should be slow to overrule its precedents, there is little reason to avoid doing so when persuaded by the 'lessons of experience and the force of better reason.' ''</p>
        <p>Chief Judge Sol Wachtler, the only judge still sitting on the court who participated in the 1981 decision, voted with the majority today. He dissented from the original decision.</p>
        <p>One reason for overruling the original decision, the majority said, was that it favored recidivists over first-time offenders.</p>
        <p>''The first-time arrestee, with no criminal experience, may waive his rights and be questioned without the presence of counsel,'' Judge Simons wrote. ''Why then should the second-time offender be foreclosed from waiving his rights on the matter for which he was detained?''</p>
        <p>Potential Abuses Feared</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers said they were worried that under the new ruling, the police might use the pretext of a second arrest to question a suspect without a lawyer present.</p>
        <p>''It's going to result in more aggressive interrogations,'' Mr. Weinstein said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
