<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detectives Testify in Case of Youth Garroted in Ritual Slaying</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CLIFTON (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MATONAK, CARL (DETECTIVE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARR, JOHN (DETECTIVE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOLIMINE, ROBERT A JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WANGER, JAMES P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE133EF934A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detectives Testify in Case of Youth Garroted in Ritual Slaying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON, N.J., Sept. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends of 17-year-old Robert Solimine Jr. who admitted their part in his slaying named James P. Wanger as the person who actually garroted the victim, police officers testified today.</p>
        <p>In the first full day of testimony in Mr. Wanger's murder trial in State Superior Court, three police officers described their investigation after finding the still-warm body of Mr. Solimine shortly after midnight on Feb. 17, 1992, led to the arrest of Mr. Wanger the next day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Friends of 17-year-old Robert Solimine Jr. who admitted their part in his slaying named James P. Wanger as the person who actually garroted the victim, police officers testified today.</p>
        <p>In the first full day of testimony in Mr. Wanger's murder trial in State Superior Court, three police officers described their investigation after finding the still-warm body of Mr. Solimine shortly after midnight on Feb. 17, 1992, led to the arrest of Mr. Wanger the next day.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wanger's lawyer, Anthony Pope, in cross-examining the officers, kept stressing that no physical evidence was linked to his client. He also tried to show that statements the youths gave to the police were inconsistent and made them unreliable witnesses. Rituals and Symbolism</p>
        <p>Mr. Wanger, 19, is charged with strangling Mr. Solimine on the night of Feb. 16, 1992, in the victim's parked car, using shoelaces tied to an extension cord. The authorities say Mr. Solimine was considered a pest and a "nerd" by five youths who plotted for months to kill him in meetings that mixed Mafia-like rituals with religious symbolism.</p>
        <p>According to the authorities, the victim, who had moved from Clifton to North Haledon, was killed after he, Mr. Wanger and a third youth recited the final line to the "Hail Mary" prayer, the authorities say. Prosecutors say two other youths acted as lookouts in another car while the mastermind of the group, Frank Castaldo, waited at his house for a report.</p>
        <p>Under direct examination by an assistant Passaic County prosecutor, John Snowden, Detective Carl Matonak of the Clifton police explained what happened when the body was found in a Clifton school parking lot.  After determining the victim's identity, the police called a friend of Mr. Solimine's whose name was in a file on the victim dating to 1991, when his mother had reported him missing.</p>
        <p>The girl gave the detective the name of one of three youths who has since pleaded guilty to the crime as well as the name of Mr. Castaldo, the only youth who was legally an adult -- 18 -- at the time of the murder. Tire Tracks Found</p>
        <p>Because tire tracks were left on the muddy area near where Mr. Solimine was found in the driver's seat, with the seat belt still fastened, the police drove past Mr. Castaldo's house and that of the other youth named to see whether their cars were muddy, Detective Matonak said. They found mud on the car of the youth named and brought him in for questioning, along with another youth who was at his house.</p>
        <p>Based on their statements, the police went to arrest Mr. Wanger, Detective Matonak said.</p>
        <p>Under cross-examination, he said neither the murder weapon nor any other key evidence was found in Mr. Wanger's home. The police were searching for Mr. Solimine's car keys, lighter fluid, the gas cap to his car and other evidence, the detective said. Mr. Solimine's car was found with a rag doused with lighter fluid stuffed in the gas tank in an unsuccessful effort to set the car afire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wanger was arrested about 2 P.M. the next day when the police found him lying on the couch at his grandparents' house in Clifton. Search Warrants</p>
        <p>Another Clifton police detective, John Barr, testified that there were two search warrants executed at Mr. Wanger's house because of inconsistent statements given by youths as to what he was wearing. One youth said he was wearing a peacoat, the other said a long trench coat.</p>
        <p>Detectives asked Mr. Wanger's grandmother for a peacoat and Mr. Wanger's sneakers in their first search, Detective Barr said, then returned for the trench coat and another pair of sneakers the second time. They did not find another pair of sneakers, he said under cross-examinatin from Mr. Pope.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Pope asked him why detectives went looking for another pair of sneakers, Detective Barr said that it was because if there was a mistake about the coat, there may have been a mistake about the sneakers. He said Mr. Wanger's sneakers did not have any mud on them.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say the youths involved in the slaying were given a purpose in planning the murder of Mr. Solimine.</p>
        <p>But according to the defense, Mr. Wanger has been scapegoated by the three youths who pleaded guilty because he was deserting the cult-like group to join the Marines. The three youths, whose names are protected by law because they were convicted as juveniles, are expected to testify against Mr. Wanger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
