<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="11DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="922004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DA103CF932A25757C0A961958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Store Sales Lack Luster, Though Discounters Thrive  Retailers reported a mixed bag of results for March. As has been the trend lately, discounters showed big sales gains but department stores and specialty shops were hurt by shifts in customers' tastes.</p>
        <p>The Goldman, Sachs retail composite index, which tracks sales at stores open at least a year, increased 4 percent in March, after a 4.2 percent gain a year earlier. $(Page D6.$)</p>
        <p>Freddie Mac Investigation Sought  Jim Leach, the chairman of the House Banking Committee, called for an investigation into the investments of Freddie Mac, saying it had abused the preferential borrowing terms it enjoys through its ties to the Government. He said it had borrowed $125 million in the bond markets at a low interest rate and then used the money to buy Philip Morris bonds yielding more. $(D2.$)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Store Sales Lack Luster, Though Discounters Thrive  Retailers reported a mixed bag of results for March. As has been the trend lately, discounters showed big sales gains but department stores and specialty shops were hurt by shifts in customers' tastes.</p>
        <p>The Goldman, Sachs retail composite index, which tracks sales at stores open at least a year, increased 4 percent in March, after a 4.2 percent gain a year earlier. $(Page D6.$)</p>
        <p>Freddie Mac Investigation Sought  Jim Leach, the chairman of the House Banking Committee, called for an investigation into the investments of Freddie Mac, saying it had abused the preferential borrowing terms it enjoys through its ties to the Government. He said it had borrowed $125 million in the bond markets at a low interest rate and then used the money to buy Philip Morris bonds yielding more. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>Dollar Stumbles After Big Gains  The dollar fell for the first time in a week, tumbling from a four-and-a-half-year high against the Japanese yen, after Japanese officials suggested that Japan might sell dollars to halt the currency's rally. $(D4.$)</p>
        <p>Executive Pleads Guilty to Fraud  An executive of Bennett Funding, which regulators say was the biggest Ponzi scheme in history, pleaded guilty to securities fraud, conspiracy to obstruct justice and conspiracy to commit bankruptcy fraud. $(D13.$)</p>
        <p>General Electric Profits Rise  General Electric said that its earnings rose 10.5 percent in the first quarter, matching expectations. $(D13.$)</p>
        <p>Morgan Results Beat Forecasts  J. P. Morgan said that its earnings fell 3.4 percent in the first quarter, with the recent decline in stock and bond prices hurting the bank's securities trading business. Nonetheless, the earnings exceeded expectations. $(D3.$)</p>
        <p>Networking Deal for Compaq  Compaq Computer agreed to buy Microcom, a maker of modems and software used to manage remote access to computer networks, for $280 million. $(D6.$)</p>
        <p>US Airways Warns of Possible Cuts  US Airways told union members that if it is unable to reach cost-cutting agreements with its labor leaders, it may start dropping unprofitable routes. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>S.E.C. Sues Drug Researchers  The S.E.C. has sued 13 people in the first insider trading case to be brought against clinical drug researchers. The S.E.C. accused a researcher, his wife and his assistant of warning 10 people that a drug was ineffective in clinical trials. The 10 avoided big losses by selling the shares of the drug's developer and of the primary licensee. $(D13.$)</p>
        <p>Nazi Victims' Claims to Be Studied  Allianz, the German insurer, promised to investigate claims from the families of European Jews whose insurance policies were confiscated by the Nazis in World War II. $(A3.$)</p>
        <p>Wages Up, but Not Inflation  For all the fears of inflation that have been prompted by recent wage increases, there are no signs that the raises are going to translate anytime soon into the kind of pressures that cause American business to lift prices. $(A1.$)</p>
        <p>Treasury Market in Doldrums  Prices of Treasury securities were slightly lower to unchanged, with the 30-year bond yield steady at 7.10 percent. $(D13.$)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
