<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Who Benefit From the Injury List</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91F31F930A35756C0A964958260" item-length="1526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Who Benefit From the Injury List</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Bell played two games and landed on the disabled list. Jim Thome and Reggie Jefferson didn't even get to do that. They ended spring training with injuries worthy of the list. Gary Scott's psyche probably should be on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Andy Stankiewicz, on the other hand, has no problems or complaints. Nor does Rich Amaral. They have benefited from injuries to other players, and they have become two rookies to watch. Gary DiSarcina, Reggie Sanders, Donovan Osborne, Anthony Young and Pat Mahomes have also shown they are worth watching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Bell played two games and landed on the disabled list. Jim Thome and Reggie Jefferson didn't even get to do that. They ended spring training with injuries worthy of the list. Gary Scott's psyche probably should be on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Andy Stankiewicz, on the other hand, has no problems or complaints. Nor does Rich Amaral. They have benefited from injuries to other players, and they have become two rookies to watch. Gary DiSarcina, Reggie Sanders, Donovan Osborne, Anthony Young and Pat Mahomes have also shown they are worth watching.</p>
        <p>Bell, who began the season as the Toronto Blue Jays' right fielder, was the off-season favorite to be the American League rookie of the year, but a Frank Tanana pitch in the second game of the season broke his wrist. Thome and Jefferson were going to be half of the Cleveland Indians' infield, but ligament sprains in Thome's hand and Jefferson's elbow forced a change in plans.</p>
        <p>Scott was the Chicago Cubs' third baseman when the season began. He was their third baseman when last season began, too, as a result of his surprising spring in which he batted .366 and stole the job. But it wasn't his for long. After he struggled with a .165 average in 31 games, the Cubs sent Scott to their Iowa farm team May 18.</p>
        <p>He struggled again this season, and this time the Cubs sent him to Iowa on April 24 after he batted .091 in 13 games. The highlight of his brief tenure occurred April 20 when he hit a grand slam against Kyle Abbott of Philadelphia. He batted 13 times after the home run and didn't get another hit. Opportunity for Stankiewicz</p>
        <p>Stankiewicz, meanwhile, gained a spot with the Yankees when shortstop Mike Gallego opened the season on the disabled list, and he became the second baseman when Pat Kelly sprained a ligament in his thumb diving for a grounder. Stankiewicz, the kind of scrappy guy who becomes a crowd favorite, is hitting .313.</p>
        <p>The Seattle Mariners summoned Amaral from the minor leagues when Omar Vizquel, their shortstop, sprained ligaments in his knee. Amaral had a .313 average to show for his first 13 games.</p>
        <p>DiSarcina is the man responsible for solving the Mets' shortstop problem. He beat out Dick Schofield as the California Angels' shortstop and made Schofield expandable so the Mets could acquire him. DiSarcina had a .318 average, which placed him well ahead of other rookie shortstops: Kim Batiste of Philadelphia .250, Royce Clayton of San Francisco .216 and Freddie Benavides, filling in for the injured Barry Larkin with Cincinnati, .204.</p>
        <p>Sanders has replaced Eric Davis in the Cincinnati Reds' outfield, and his 24 hits (for a .316 average) are the most among rookies in both leagues.</p>
        <p>Osborne, Young and Mahomes have been the most successful rookie pitchers in the early weeks. Osborne overcame a sprained ankle he suffered in his first start for St. Louis and has a 2-0 record with a 1.71 earned run average. Young has a 2-0 record and 3.26 e.r.a. for the Mets while Mahomes has a 2-0 record with a 4.24 e.r.a. for Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Abbott has lost all four of his starts for the Phillies; Dave Burba of San Francisco has a 1-2 record and Dave Fleming of Seattle has a 2-1 mark. Fleming, though, has a 6.53 e.r.a. to Burba's 3.32. Safety Has Trouble Hitting</p>
        <p>Kenny Lofton, the Indians' center fielder, was hitting .209 with 10 stolen bases in 11 attempts. Brian Jordan, a safety with the Atlanta Falcons, played a lot of right field for St. Louis in Felix Jose's absence but has had less success hitting a baseball (.203) than running backs and receivers.</p>
        <p>Todd Hundley, the Mets' sometimes catcher, had a .150 average, and Eddie Taubensee, Houston's primary catcher, was hitting .208. Eric Karros, the Los Angeles Dodgers' sometimes first baseman, was hitting .286. Ruben Amaro Jr. had the most home runs among rookies, three, but he had a .138 batting average.</p>
        <p>Given the slow starts of many of the first-year players, the rookies of the year may still be playing in the minor leagues. Leaving Home Isn't Easy</p>
        <p>When the Houston Astros left home 10 days ago for the first time this season, they had a 9-6 record and were in first place in the National League West.</p>
        <p>In six games on the road, they suffered three shutouts, lost two other games and scored a total of nine runs. Of course, they encountered two of the best pitching staffs in the league, and they should not have been embarrassed when Steve Avery of Atlanta and David Cone and Bret Saberhagen shut them out on a total of nine hits.</p>
        <p>But the Astros, who scored 10 runs and won as soon as they returned home Friday night, do look like a different team when they put on their road uniforms.</p>
        <p>"We've got a two-year track record that's not vey favorable to our club on the road," General Manager Bill Wood said. "We're very well aware of that. One of our goals this year is to have our ball club learn to win on the road and get used to winning on the road. The focus is to get the players to relax and be challenged by being on the road. We want them to understand that the atmosphere isn't that nonconducive to winning."</p>
        <p>The team, Wood noted, has changed over the last few years, and problems experienced by one group of players shouldn't affect another group. But, he added, "It's just something where subsconsciously they think about what's happened the last couple of years. There's already a hill to climb before we get to the ball park."</p>
        <p>The Astros' worst results in recent years occurred in 1990 when the team had a 49-32 record at the Astrodome and a 26-55 mark elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Learning to win in other parks will be especially vital later in the season. Because the Republican convention will be held in the Astrodome, the Astros will play on the road for four weeks, from July 27 through Aug. 23. They will visit 8 of the other 11 league cities.</p>
        <p>"We could look at that as an opportunity and a challenge," Wood said. "We'd like to get it done before that because we'd like to have as good a season as possible. We feel winning and a good attitude are contagious. If we could have a couple trips that are winning trips, it would be great for the ball club." The Under-.200 Club</p>
        <p>Despite the rush of success -- they won a couple of games last week -- the Kansas City Royals have maintained their solid corps of under-.200 hitters. On any given day, the Royals can pack their lineup with players whose batting averages begin with a "1" or a "0."</p>
        <p>Only first baseman Wally Joyner and second baseman Keith Miller have been consistent outcasts, hitting near or over .300. Gregg Jefferies slips back and forth, creeping above .200 to .207 yesterday.</p>
        <p>George Brett (.189), Kevin McReynolds (.173), Brian McRae (.169) and Rico Rossy (.167) emerged from yesterday's game in Boston as members in good standing of the corps. Jim Eisenreich (.211)and Mike Macfarlane (.205) abandoned their under-.200 colleagues Friday night but are not far from rejoining them.</p>
        <p>Curtis Wilkerson (.043), the backup shortstop, and Brent Mayne (.167), a backup catcher, also are part of the under-.200 corps. Another shortstop who would qualify, David Howard (.077), is on the disabled list, and Terry Shumpert (.156), who had been the starting second baseman, has been sent to the minor leagues. Pitching Takes a Back Seat</p>
        <p>The Swift race: Bill Swift won both of his starts last week, giving him a 5-0 record, and he also maintained his unusual position of having a higher batting average than earned run average. In the two games, against Los Angeles last Sunday and Philadelphia yesterday, Swift allowed four earned runs in 14 innings and got two hits in four at-bats. His e.r.a. rose from 1.10 to 1.54 but his batting average soared from .214 to .278.</p>
        <p>Ramon Martinez of Los Angeles was having a Cy Young Award-type season last year through the first four months. His 14-5 record matched the mark of Tom Glavine of Atlanta, who proceeded to win the award.</p>
        <p>Martinez didn't win it because he staggered to a 3-8 record in his last 12 starts. The 24-year-old right-hander continues to stagger. He has emerged from five starts this season with one loss and no-decisions in the other four games, three of them Dodger losses. He's Some Slow Walker</p>
        <p>Don't waste time talking to Bob Tewksbury about walks. The underrated St. Louis pitcher doesn't know what they are. In 28 innings this season, Tewksbury has walked only 1 batter, Larry Walker of Montreal.</p>
        <p>"And I shouldn't have walked him," Tewksbury said. "It was a 3-2 pitch, I took something off it and it drifted out of the zone. If I had thrown it hard, it would have been a strike."</p>
        <p>Tewksbury, who has a 2-0 record and a 1.64 e.r.a., noted that he went to a 3-0 count on Dave Hansen of Los Angeles the other night. "That's probably one of the first 3-0 counts I've had all year," he said. "He fouled off strike 1, then popped up strike 2. I said thank you."</p>
        <p>Last season, Tewksbury averaged one walk every five innings, the year before one every 9.7, or less than one a game.</p>
        <p>"I'm going to walk somebody again," he said. "But it's kind of a neat little streak. Actually, I'd rather have a scoreless streak: one run in 28 innings."  NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
