<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let a Thousand Lipsticks Bloom</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="OUT THERE: GUANGZHOU"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COSMETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AVON PRODUCTS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC173EF930A35756C0A964958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let a Thousand Lipsticks Bloom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS</byline>
      <dateline>GUANGZHOU, China</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few Chinese houses have doorbells, but that has not stopped the emergence here of a growing army of 10,000 women who are called "elegant and fragrant ladies."</p>
        <p>That is what the Chinese call their Avon Ladies, and they are peddling cosmetics with a determination that has made Avon one of the most successful and best-known companies here in southern China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few Chinese houses have doorbells, but that has not stopped the emergence here of a growing army of 10,000 women who are called "elegant and fragrant ladies."</p>
        <p>That is what the Chinese call their Avon Ladies, and they are peddling cosmetics with a determination that has made Avon one of the most successful and best-known companies here in southern China.</p>
        <p>If rampaging Red Guards symbolized the revolutionary spirit of China in the late 1960's and early 1970's, then the equally tenacious "elegant and fragrant ladies" capture the bourgeois spirit of China in the 1990's. Avon opened for business here in September 1990, sold what was to have been six months of inventory in the first four weeks, and has been booming ever since.</p>
        <p>"We came at the right time," said Samantha Kong, sales director of Avon's office in Guangzhou, also known as Canton. "People here aspire to look good, as they do anywhere, but they have no one to teach them how."</p>
        <p>In many ways, Avon is a perfect fit with the local culture. Incomes are rising rapidly, local women are showing increasing interest in makeup, consumers have a strong preference for American products, and there is an enormous pool of entrepreneurs who are eager to earn extra money by selling cosmetics part time.</p>
        <p>"I use myself as a model," said Tian Ruihua, a 25-year-old hotel secretary who began selling for Avon just a month ago. "So when my friends ask how I make myself up, I tell them that I use Avon products."</p>
        <p>In her first month, Ms. Tian sold the equivalent of $278 worth of cosmetics to her friends and earned a 30 percent commission worth more than $83. That sum, which would be an excellent monthly salary in China for a full-time job, represented three hours of work.</p>
        <p>One-third of Guangzhou's Avon ladies earn monthly commissions of more than $275, and the star saleswoman, Zhao Lizhen, earned $6,600 in her best month.</p>
        <p>"When some Avon ladies sell a lot of cosmetics and make a pile of money, then other people notice," said Li Qilan, a 25-year-old whose self-confidence has turned her into a super saleswoman. "Then the others want to sell for Avon, too."</p>
        <p>For now, Avon operates only in Guangdong Province, the southern Chinese region that for the last dozen years has enjoyed some of the highest economic growth rates in the world. Guangzhou is the capital of Guangdong Province.</p>
        <p>The number of Avon ladies is expected to double to 20,000 within a year.</p>
        <p>In China, far more than in the United States, Avon has cachet; indeed, most American products do. Many Chinese manufacturers now try to come up with foreign-sounding brand names and English-lettered packaging to lure customers.</p>
        <p>Avon's image has been bolstered by the company's Chinese name, yafang, meaning elegant and fragrant. Calling the Avon representatives "ladies" (there are no Avon men, although husbands can help unofficially) also helps impart sophistication, because the Chinese word that is used for lady or Miss, xiaojie, was rarely used in China until recent years and still sounds cosmopolitan and exotic.</p>
        <p>Part of Avon's appeal, and of cosmetics generally, is that they tap a widespread yearning among Chinese to shed backward customs and enjoy the sophistication for which Hong Kong is widely envied. One successful pickup line in Guangzhou might be: "Miss, are you from Hong Kong?"</p>
        <p>Cosmetics have reappeared in China only gradually since the early 1980's. Consequently, many women have to learn on their own how to use eye shadow instead of being taught by mothers or elder sisters. This need for tutoring gives Avon ladies, who offer beauty tips as well as mascara, a special advantage over department stores.</p>
        <p>While Avon encourages its saleswomen to go door to door, this almost never seems to happen. Instead, the "elegant and fragrant ladies" typically bring their supplies to the workplace and offer products and advice to fellow workers. Some factories welcome such beauty classes as a kind of cultural program that will make employees more educated and sophisticated.</p>
        <p>"We sell mostly to friends and to people in our 'work units,' " said Chen Jianhong, a 37-year-old government worker who moonlights for Avon. "I once studied a bit about beauty and makeup, so now I show my friends how to look better and also sell them some cosmetics."</p>
        <p>Avon targets only the relatively prosperous consumers who can afford nearly $4 for a lipstick or face cream -- two of the best-selling products. By comparison, a typical monthly income for a factory worker is $40 or so. This makes Avon one of the handful of American companies to have cashed in successfully on the Chinese consumer market.</p>
        <p>Avon is trying to expand sales of baby products to go along with cosmetics. It could be a large market. Most urban Chinese families are not allowed to have more than one child and consequently often fawn over their "little emperors" and buy them almost anything available.</p>
        <p>"I'm going to focus on selling baby products," said Ms. Tian, the hotel secretary. "People will just gobble them up."  OUT THERE: GUANGZHOU</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
