<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bed With The Lions</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE SEXES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARSON, JOHNNY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLEMENTS, MARCELLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LENO, JAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALL, ARSENIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LETTERMAN,
DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, DENNIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASE, CHEVY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TONIGHT SHOW (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED7143EF930A35756C0A964958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bed With The Lions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marcelle Clements</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLEMENTS, MARCELLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE is America's shadow lover. People watch him in bed. He's the last person hundreds of thousands of women think about before they drift to sleep. If they're in bed with someone, they must unconsciously confuse him, or at least compare him, with their companion. If they're alone, he's the king of the night, leading the way into the darkness. They dream about him. The atmosphere of his show has been an aspect of America's sex life for 30 years. Whether you watch him or not, he's helped maintain a psychosexual status quo.</p>
        <p>In fact, he's been a cultural marker for a certain kind of sexuality -- assisted, of course, by the presence of Ed McMahon as an always visible suggestion of lousy gender politics. Johnny Carson with a starlet as a guest</p>
        <p>is</p>
        <p>the American myth, dream, legend, role model in one. Mr. Carson's erotic presence, masculine but gentle, libidinous but gentlemanly (in the worst and best senses of the word), has helped maintain the collective belief that desire and ambition can coexist in an attractive way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE is America's shadow lover. People watch him in bed. He's the last person hundreds of thousands of women think about before they drift to sleep. If they're in bed with someone, they must unconsciously confuse him, or at least compare him, with their companion. If they're alone, he's the king of the night, leading the way into the darkness. They dream about him. The atmosphere of his show has been an aspect of America's sex life for 30 years. Whether you watch him or not, he's helped maintain a psychosexual status quo.</p>
        <p>In fact, he's been a cultural marker for a certain kind of sexuality -- assisted, of course, by the presence of Ed McMahon as an always visible suggestion of lousy gender politics. Johnny Carson with a starlet as a guest</p>
        <p>is</p>
        <p>the American myth, dream, legend, role model in one. Mr. Carson's erotic presence, masculine but gentle, libidinous but gentlemanly (in the worst and best senses of the word), has helped maintain the collective belief that desire and ambition can coexist in an attractive way.</p>
        <p>Well, goodbye to all that.</p>
        <p>Like a good father, Mr. Carson has prepared us for his departure. It's all out in the open: no dysfunctional family behavior here. We've been primed. Jay Leno has been eased in. Mr. Carson's guests are, one by one, paying tribute and saying goodbye. The press is going absolutely mad with endless fervent adieus. Even James Wolcott says he will miss Mr. Carson.</p>
        <p>But none of this, I believe, can really prepare us for the reality of the change: now Late Night will be ruled by a bunch of young lions who exhibit all of the sexual confusion of their generation. What will this mean for the sex life of America?</p>
        <p>The rivals -- Mr. Leno, David Letterman, Arsenio Hall and Dennis Miller -- behave like potential dates while, so far, we continue playing the field. But, to a certain extent, they are interchangeable: they are all flirtatious and yet withdrawn, seductive and yet inhibited. While much has been made in the Carson/Leno changeover of passing the scepter from the 50's generation to the baby boomers, this confusion is not merely generational.</p>
        <p>I T's no accident that late night, a segment in electronic time almost singlemindedly devoted to ambition and sex, has become a battleground for these challengers. Television has been tremendously sexed up of late, with networks competing in more and more ingenious ways -- for example "Studs" and spandex gladiators on Fox -- to show skin and trigger bawdy associations. With the sole exception of "Nightline" (for the 80's throwbacks still attracted to the Henry Kissinger types), each of the Late Night shows is laced with as much sexual suggestion as possible.</p>
        <p>But this transition cannot go on indefinitely. The king must die, but who will be king? Will one dominate? Or will each contender become the ruler of a cultural fief with its own psychosexual sensibility?</p>
        <p>Playing the sexual card doesn't come as easily to Jay Leno as does baby-boomer bonhomie. Moreover, he must deal with the grudge factor. At least some of the audience is angry with him for taking Mr. Carson's place, and many consider him too calculating to be sexy. It could take several years to work through that. Also, he's saddled with that big band, musically exquisite but compatible with an older generation's sexual style. By then, Messrs. Letterman, Hall and Miller, lean and mean, supported by small, funky bands, will have established themselves as respectably countercultural.</p>
        <p>David Letterman, the most truly hip of the lot, is perceived by some as cruel, an attribute that American women are no longer as attracted to en masse. I have a fantasy he might say something sadistic in bed, a prospect that rather mitigates the advantage his good looks and seductive irony would have given him. He probably inspired too much fear to generate the level of concupiscence needed to take him all the way to the top.</p>
        <p>Arsenio Hall, the first African-American on Late Night, seems to be lying low sexually. He certainly has the advantage of being socioculturally refreshing, but he may bypass the electronic erogenous zone of the 30-to-45-year-old consumer group. But he has been seen to get down: I once caught him kissing Diana Ross on the air for an incredibly long time, audience howling all the while, producing perhaps the most authentically lust-filled visual bite of the 90's to date.</p>
        <p>Dennis Miller often makes references to his penis, so that one is both aware and suspicious of his erotic consciousness. He's exceedingly telegenic but may be too jejune to score really big. I recently heard him ruthlessly making fun of French people, a common activity of the American male, which invariably indicates, in my view, major discomfort regarding his own sexuality.</p>
        <p>And now Chevy Chase has signed on with Fox for a talk show starting next season. What Mr. Chase's relationship will be with the viewer and what that will mean for America's sex life are not yet a matter of speculation.</p>
        <p>Of course, the very fact that there's competition signals a change. If you're optimistic, you may find reason to hope, in the Touch-All-Bases 90's, that the Late Night tournament will inject into the national atmosphere a measure of novel phallic vitality tempered with a new and agreeable political correctness. If you're pessimistic, there's plenty of cause to assume that our sexual consciousness will become even more confused and divided than it is now, if such a thing is possible.</p>
        <p>Who knows? All one knows for sure is that, once again, Daddy's gone.</p>
        <p>THE SEXES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
