<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Prices Dip in Slow Day</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONEY SUPPLY (ECONOMIC INDICATOR)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILPIN, KENNETH N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DD113CF935A35757C0A966958260" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Prices Dip in Slow Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILPIN, KENNETH N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Prices of Treasury securities dipped in sluggish trading yesterday. Dealers sold securities after a rumor that swept the credit markets on Wednesday - that a major Japanese institution would disclose serious liquidity problems when trading began in Tokyo - proved to be unfounded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Prices of Treasury securities dipped in sluggish trading yesterday. Dealers sold securities after a rumor that swept the credit markets on Wednesday - that a major Japanese institution would disclose serious liquidity problems when trading began in Tokyo - proved to be unfounded.</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities dipped in sluggish trading yesterday. Dealers sold securities after a rumor that swept the credit markets on Wednesday - that a major Japanese institution would disclose serious liquidity problems when trading began in Tokyo - proved to be unfounded.</p>
        <p>The Japanese rumor had touched off speculative buying that led to a rally in Treasury securities on Wednesday. But the difficulties in Japan never materialized.</p>
        <p>''Nobody went bankrupt Wednesday night,'' one government-securities trader said. ''The rumor that caused the rally just isn't there.''</p>
        <p>Focus on Employment Data</p>
        <p>When the rumor dispelled, traders began to focus on the forthcoming release of March employment data. In advance of the report, which is due this morning from the Labor Department, most Wall Street economists were projecting an increase of 150,000 in nonfarm employment. Dealers said that if the number exceeded 200,000, it would not be well received in the fixed-income markets and could cause the Federal Reserve Board to tighten monetary policy.</p>
        <p>''The employment number is very important,'' another bond trader said. ''With prices where they are, it suggests the market is expecting a good number. If we get a negative surprise, it will probably lead to a sell-off, and could make the Fed push the funds rate up.''</p>
        <p>A number of analysts took issue with that assessment.</p>
        <p>''At this point in time, it is hard to think of a number that in and of itself would dislodge the Fed from its current policy stance,'' said David M. Jones, senior vice president and chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Company, a primary dealer in Government securities. ''The employment numbers were distorted by abnormally warm weather in January and February, and I would think the Fed would at least want to see April data before they contemplate any sort of move. And they won't get those numbers until May.''</p>
        <p>Nonfarm employment rose by 332,000 in January and 372,000 in February.</p>
        <p>Steady Funds Rate</p>
        <p>The overnight Federal funds rate, the money market rate the central bank most directly controls, has remained at 8 1/4 percent since the middle of December.</p>
        <p>Aside from last-minute positioning before the release of the employment figures, dealers said that little other business was transacted yesterday.</p>
        <p>By late in the day, the Treasury's 8 1/2 percent bonds of 2020 were offered at a price of 99 27/32, down 5/32, to yield 8.51 percent. At the end of Wednesday's strong rally, the bellwether issue was offered at a price to yield 8.50 percent.</p>
        <p>Note issues also posted modest price declines. In late trading, the 8 1/2 percent 10-year notes were offered at 99 21/32, down 5/32, to yield 8.55 percent. And the 8 1/2 percent two-year notes were offered at 99 31/32, down 1/32, to yield 8.51 percent.</p>
        <p>Bids at yesterday's auction of one-year Treasury bills produced an average discount rate of 7.72 percent, down from an average rate of 7.76 percent at the last one-year bill auction on March 8.</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for Treasury bills, three-month bill rates were unchanged late yesterday, at an offered rate of 7.73 percent. Six-month bill rates rose by 3 basis points, or hundredths of a point, to a late offered rate of 7.73 percent.</p>
        <p>Fixed-Income Report</p>
        <p>In other developments, a quarterly report released yesterday from Salomon Brothers showed that the sharp rise in interest rates during the last three months did some financial damage to investors in fixed-income securities.</p>
        <p>For the first time in more than two years, all asset classes tracked in the firm's Broad Investment-Grade Bond Index posted negative quarterly returns. The Treasury market turned in the weakest performance of the major sectors tracked by Salomon, returning a negative 1.29 percent for the first quarter.</p>
        <p>New-issue activity in the investment-grade corporate bond market was strong again yesterday, as several deals were priced.</p>
        <p>Among the issues offered was a $500 million sale of 40-year debentures for Hydro-Quebec. The 9 3/8 percent issue, which matures April 15, 2030, was priced at 99.873, to yield 9.837 percent, 68 basis points higher than the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 8 1/2 percent bonds of 2020 at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch Capital Markets acted as lead manager for the underwriting, which is rated AA-3 by Moody's Investors Service and AA-by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation.</p>
        <p>New York Serial Bonds</p>
        <p>Activity in the tax-exempt municipal bond market was highlighted by the negotiated sale of $166 million worth of serial and term bonds for New York's Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority.</p>
        <p>Maturities on the serial bonds are from 1991 to 2005, with yields ranging from 6 percent to 7.25 percent.</p>
        <p>The term bonds include a 7 3/8 percent issue maturing in 2016 that was priced to yield 7.48 percent, and a 6 percent issue maturing in 2020 that was priced to yield 7.34 percent.</p>
        <p>Dillon, Read &amp; Company acted as lead manager for the transaction, which is rated AA by Moody's. An A+ rating from Standard &amp; Poor's is expected.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, the Federal Reserve Board reported yesterday that all three measures of the nation's money supply rose in the week ended March 26. The report had no impact on prices in the credit markets.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of yesterday's auction of one-year Treasury bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>92.194</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.72%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>8.32%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>92.214</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.70%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>8.30%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>92.184</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.73%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>8.33%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>63%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$25,184,520</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$9,766,470</p>
        <p>N.Y. applied for</p>
        <p>$22,040,650</p>
        <p>N.Y. accepted</p>
        <p>$8,621,870</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,110,270</p>
        <p>The one-year bills mature April 11, 1991.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
