<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Playing for Pride, Houston Sparks Knicks</title>
    <meta content="06KNIC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/06/sports/basketball/06KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DA143DF935A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Playing for Pride, Houston Sparks Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knicks Need Help, and Turn to Draft</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks defeat Seattle SuperSonics, 86-83 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few hours before Tuesday's game against the Charlotte Hornets, Mark Jackson Jr. darted over to his father and Allan Houston in the Knicks' locker room. The last believer standing, Jackson Jr. enthusiastically presented a wild scenario that would enable the Knicks to make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Mark Sr., tickled by his son's innocence, laughed heartily. Houston chuckled too before saying, ''Way to keep hope alive, Little Jack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Layden will do his best to make a trade, although the chances of the Knicks pulling off something major remain remote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few hours before Tuesday's game against the Charlotte Hornets, Mark Jackson Jr. darted over to his father and Allan Houston in the Knicks' locker room. The last believer standing, Jackson Jr. enthusiastically presented a wild scenario that would enable the Knicks to make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Mark Sr., tickled by his son's innocence, laughed heartily. Houston chuckled too before saying, ''Way to keep hope alive, Little Jack.''</p>
        <p>The faint hope that sparked the 10-year-old Jackson disappeared after Thursday's loss in Portland, officially whittling the Knicks' list of incentives down to one -- pride.</p>
        <p>''You have to just compete and play hard and try to have fun,'' Houston said before tonight's game against the Seattle SuperSonics. ''You have to find it within yourself to find a purpose for going out and representing what's on your jersey and taking pride in what you're doing.''</p>
        <p>Houston epitomized that sentiment as well as anyone tonight, scoring 14 of his game-high 28 points in the fourth quarter to lead the Knicks to an 86-83 victory over the Sonics at Key Arena. Seattle (43-34) could have clinched a playoff berth with a victory.</p>
        <p>Houston, coming off an 8-point game against Portland, scored 7 of the Knicks' final 11 points, all in the last 2 minutes 24 seconds. His run began with a 3-pointer that put the Knicks ahead to stay at 78-76. Clarence Weatherspoon (10 points, 6 rebounds) added a key 19-foot shot from the right baseline to give the Knicks an 83-80 lead with 46 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Kurt Thomas had 18 points and 14 rebounds. Howard Eisley also played well, scoring 11 points and hitting 2 crucial free throws with 5.4 seconds to play. Latrell Sprewell struggled, scoring just 3 points, shooting 1 of 11.</p>
        <p>Gary Payton led Seattle with 22 points and 13 assists.</p>
        <p>With the playoffs out of sight for the Knicks (29-46), the victory could bring them only so much joy. ''At the end of April, that's when it'll probably hit us that we won't be in the playoffs,'' Houston said. ''We'll just be watching them.''</p>
        <p>Many believe the Knicks will miss the playoffs again next season. Scott Layden, the team's president and general manager, will do his best to make a trade, although the chances that the Knicks will pull off something major remain remote.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' best hope for quick and significant improvement will be the June draft. Armed with a lottery pick for the first time since 1986, they have a chance to land a potential superstar. If they somehow get the first, second or third pick, the Knicks could end up with Yao Ming, the 7-foot-5 Chinese center, or Jason Williams, the outstanding point guard from Duke.</p>
        <p>Either player could make the Knicks a playoff threat next season, but most of the other available players will need some time to make an impact. Knicks players are not expecting to get the help they need out of the draft. Several of them said they would not even watch the May 19 draft lottery, which will determine when the Knicks will select.</p>
        <p>''I've never watched it,'' Houston said, ''and I probably still won't watch the draft lottery -- just because of the principle.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell said the only time he watched it was in 1993 when he was a second-year guard for the Golden State Warriors. Don Nelson, the Warriors' coach at the time, telephoned Sprewell before that draft to ask his opinion on whether the team should select Chris Webber or Shawn Bradley.</p>
        <p>''That was an easy one; I couldn't even believe he asked me that question,'' Sprewell said with a huge laugh. ''Webber was my vote definitely.''</p>
        <p>Golden State selected Webber, securing him in a draft-day trade with Orlando for Anfernee Hardaway and three first-round picks. Webber averaged 17.5 points and 9.1 rebounds in helping the Warriors reach the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Now, with so many players entering the draft after high school or just one year of college, the draft has changed. Very few players will make that type of impact in their rookie season, which is unfortunate for a team that needs the help immediately, like the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''Whoever they select is not going to come in and give us 20 points and 10 rebounds off the bat,'' Marcus Camby said. ''Whoever they draft is going to be young. There aren't really any mature seniors out there.''</p>
        <p>Houston likes Drew Gooden, the versatile 6-10 forward out of Kansas, and Chris Wilcox, the 6-10 forward from Maryland who emerged as a potential lottery pick with his play in the N.C.A.A. tournament. ''Those are two big guys that seem like they would be able to help,'' Houston said. Help the Knicks avoid playing for just pride.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>SCOTT LAYDEN did not attend the McDonald's high school all-American game Thursday at Madison Square Garden. He was at the Portsmouth Invitational Tournament in Virginia, an event that showcases second-tier college seniors.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
