<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asking, Not Demanding, to Be Elks</title>
    <meta content="10ELKS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Hartford Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="921855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Hartford Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hartford (Vt)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elks (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rimer, Sara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6D9123CF933A25757C0A961958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asking, Not Demanding, to Be Elks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA RIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rimer, Sara</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, Vt., April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Five Hartford, Vermont, women file sex discrimination complaint against Benevolent and Protective Order Of Elks for rejecting them as members; are mainstays of lodge's dinners, weddings, picnics and bingo games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is hard to imagine what Hartford Lodge 1541 of the Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks would do without Loretta Lapine, Jane Thibodeau, Ann Burns, Marilyn McMillan and Sandy Tisdale.</p>
        <p>For one thing, who would wash the dishes?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is hard to imagine what Hartford Lodge 1541 of the Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks would do without Loretta Lapine, Jane Thibodeau, Ann Burns, Marilyn McMillan and Sandy Tisdale.</p>
        <p>For one thing, who would wash the dishes?</p>
        <p>Ms. Lapine, a 70-year-old widow, and the other women, are the mainstays of the lodge's dinners, weddings, picnics and bingo games. They help prepare the food, bus the tables and serve drinks, as well as do the dishes -- all without pay.</p>
        <p>''They do 97 percent more work than most of the men do,'' said Jane  Thibodeau's husband, Norman, who is about to finish his term as exalted ruler of the lodge. ''They give up a lot of Saturdays -- all summer, when it's hot, and they could be doing other things.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thibodeau thought his wife, and the other women, deserved to be members of the all-male Hartford lodge. His fellow Elks did not agree, even though the national organization, pressed by costly lawsuits and with its membership falling, began to admit women two years ago.</p>
        <p>The local lodge rejected Mrs. Thibodeau, Ms. Lapine, Ms. Burns, Mrs. McMillan, Ms. Tisdale and two other women who were sponsored by Mr. Thibodeau and several other Elks in a secret vote last year.</p>
        <p>''A real Elk would not blackball a woman,'' said Mr. Thibodeau, who is 43 and has been a member of the fraternal club for 21 years. Membership requires a two-thirds majority of those voting.</p>
        <p>He and his wife and the other women were standing around Mrs. McMillan's spotless kitchen after work this evening, talking over coffee and mint Girl Scout cookies about the ongoing struggle with the Elks.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to quit,'' said Ms. Lapine, who cut logs in the woods with her father, and put in 30 years making heels at a shoe factory before retiring.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Thibodeau, who is an assistant manager at a Shaw's supermarket, said, ''The guys are still living back in the 40's and 50's.''</p>
        <p>The women recently filed a sex discrimination complaint against the lodge with the Vermont Human Rights Commission. The commission is investigating, but is forbidden by law to discuss the matter.</p>
        <p>''We're very equal when we're cooking and cleaning,'' Ms. Burns, a freelance court reporter, said of her  husband, George, who is an Elk.</p>
        <p>''He voted for me,'' Ms. Burns said. ''He told me he voted for me.''</p>
        <p>Like a lot of men in town, Mr. Burns did not want to talk about the controversy.</p>
        <p>While the Elks are waning in influence and numbers in the big cities,  they are still an important institution in rural Vermont. There are 9,400 people in Hartford -- and 1,028 men in Lodge 1541. The Elks have as their headquarters an imposing old Victorian house on Main Street, with an American flag out front.</p>
        <p>When someone's house burns down in Hartford, the club's members -- and the women -- are there to help. They raise money for veterans, the handicapped and the poor. Weddings, banquets and dances are held at the lodge, with its spacious dining room, basement bar with big-screen television, pool tables and shuffleboard. It is the only place for miles that serves alcohol, and mixed drinks are inexpensive, at $1.75 a drink and $1.50 a beer. The $5 all-you-can-eat spaghetti suppers are one of the best bargains around.</p>
        <p>''Aside from all of this male chauvinist stuff that is going on, it's a wonderful organizaition,'' Ms. Burns said.</p>
        <p>The women are welcome -- if they are signed in and with a man who belongs. ''I don't like to have to get on my knees and beg someone to sign me in,'' Ms. Lapine said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thibodeau said he got the idea to invite the women to join last fall, when the grand exalted ruler, Gerald Coates, came from Greensboro, N.C., to a meeting in Springfield, Vt. ''He's the top dog of the Elks,'' Mr. Thibodeau said. ''He presented a challenge to all the exalted rulers to go back and make the change and get women into the clubs.''</p>
        <p>But change is apparently hard for some of the men of Lodge 1541. At 5 P.M. today, its parking lot was filled with pickup trucks and four-wheel-drives with gun racks in the back. Inside, 20 men were seated around the circular bar.</p>
        <p>''This is my club,'' said Wendell Grant, 45, who drives a cement truck. ''It's a men's club. We feel comfortable about it.''</p>
        <p>But Tim Sample, a carpenter, said he would not mind having women as members. ''They'll have to listen to what goes across the bar,'' Mr. Sample said. ''It can get rough.''</p>
        <p>''They're all good ladies,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Down the street, at the post office, the postmaster, Mary Nadeau, rooted for the women. ''You know what really irritates me?'' Mrs. Nadeau  said. ''These women are good enough to go and wash the dishes and prepare the meals, but they're told they're second-class citizens when it comes to membership. I really admire these women for not backing down.''</p>
        <p>At Mrs. McMillan's house, the women made a point of saying they did not consider themselves feminists. Nor do they plan to cut back on their volunteer duties at the Elks. In fact, they had just about finished making the hors d'oeuvres for the officers' installation dinner.</p>
        <p>''At first I thought, 'If I'm only good enough to go to the club and work, why work?' '' said Mrs. Thibodeau, recently named Lady Elk of the Year. ''Then I said, 'No, I'm not going to be that way. I enjoy going there with my husband.' ''</p>
        <p>Hartford Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
