<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Northern Exposure</title>
    <meta content="14FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="73" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/14/magazine/14FOOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1519331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norway</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Norway</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DB173BF937A2575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Northern Exposure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Northern Exposure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Reynolds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reynolds, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Reynolds Food column on Norwegian cooking; recipes; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Norway, land of the , the  and the Rated X, rebellion may have come to the cuisine at last -- though if I'm right, it will be one in which no shots are fired. Ever since the Vikings took over Iceland and Greenland as pre-Australian penal colonies for their incorrigibles in the 10th century, the culinary stereotype has been that all food in Norway has to look and taste white. A typical serving is boiled cod plated next to florets of cauliflower with a cheese sauce juxtaposed with a few boiled potatoes accompanied by the sour-cream porridge that is a national dish. This is followed by aged cheese snowy as a cleric's collar and concluded with fruits smothered in whipped cream -- all served on bleached china, making the meal a circular celebration of Wite-Out. You might need not just sunglasses to get through dinner but also a can of Jolt.</p>
        <p>Like many stereotypes, this one is pretty much true. Comfort food is part of childhood, and no matter how unhealthy or unfashionable, the attachment to it is hard-wired. Indeed, what one friend calls Norwegian soul food remains plentiful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even amid Norway's natural beauty, someone is paying attention to the food.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Norway, land of the , the  and the Rated X, rebellion may have come to the cuisine at last -- though if I'm right, it will be one in which no shots are fired. Ever since the Vikings took over Iceland and Greenland as pre-Australian penal colonies for their incorrigibles in the 10th century, the culinary stereotype has been that all food in Norway has to look and taste white. A typical serving is boiled cod plated next to florets of cauliflower with a cheese sauce juxtaposed with a few boiled potatoes accompanied by the sour-cream porridge that is a national dish. This is followed by aged cheese snowy as a cleric's collar and concluded with fruits smothered in whipped cream -- all served on bleached china, making the meal a circular celebration of Wite-Out. You might need not just sunglasses to get through dinner but also a can of Jolt.</p>
        <p>Like many stereotypes, this one is pretty much true. Comfort food is part of childhood, and no matter how unhealthy or unfashionable, the attachment to it is hard-wired. Indeed, what one friend calls Norwegian soul food remains plentiful.</p>
        <p>Although this observation is 100 percent anecdotal, Norwegian cooking seems to divide roughly along generational lines -- traditionalists cling to fare epitomized by plainly boiled cod (frequently overboiled) and even more plainly boiled potatoes or lapskaus (a soup made from stock, root vegetables, onions and salted meat and usually served with buttered or sugared potato pancakes called lefse). Youthful upstarts, on the other hand, are spearheading a spreading French invasion.</p>
        <p>It's not that Norway is without exotic ingredients. You can find reindeer, moose, fillet of horse, carpaccioed whale, nettles, sea-gull eggs, musk-ox pâté, fried cod tongues and smoked mutton heads with rutabaga all over the place. Reindeer can be delicious provided it's not overcooked -- a slightly sweet, juicy version of beef. Whale has a liverish thread running through it that's not altogether unpleasant, but it's chewy and without considerable doctoring may not be worth the effort -- and that's aside from all the bilious algae PETA will shower you with if they find out.</p>
        <p>And it's not that Norwegian chefs are without invention: salt-baked cod with avocado sauce, halibut with soy jus, grilled roe deer with black salsify, crispy dried ham on salad greens, gooseberry soup, delicious potato-barley-rye flatbread and the ubiquitous sour-cream porridge appear on menus in many parts of the country.</p>
        <p>But finding the essence of an ingredient and enhancing it -- not disguising it with a sauce or spice -- is a chef's true challenge, and pride of invention has yet to trickle down to most kitchens. This is changing, albeit glacially.</p>
        <p>A group of us spent six days at what must be one of the most exquisitely situated resorts on earth and another three at what must be one of the most remote. Located immediately on the Bjornafjord (''Bear's fjord,'' in English), the Solstrand Fjord Hotel near Bergen is so beautiful it almost hurts your eyes. All fjords are salt water because they connect to the sea, and this one, ringed by the Kvinnherad Mountains, with the Folgefonn glacier in the distance and the isle of Tysnesoy not far off, is reminiscent of but surpasses the Lake Tahoe of the 50's -- before all the water traffic. It sparkles even in the mist. (Norway, Land of the Midnight Sun, is also frequently Land of the Midnight Rain. However, taking a leaf from C.S. Lewis, perhaps we needed rain and mist on Days 2 through 5 to appreciate the blindingly beautiful sun of the first and sixth.)</p>
        <p>The kitchen staff doesn't always succeed in exploiting the local fare to the max, but rimming perfectly roasted cod with a strip of smoked pork at one meal gave the fragile flesh of the fish a pleasingly musky gravity not usually associated with cod (at least when it's on the plate). Bedding three plump shrimp on greens and a saffron sauce brought out nuance without masking flavors.</p>
        <p>If the Solstrand is not exactly a bastion of progressive cuisine, that may be at least partly because it must appeal to a large and varied clientele, ranging in age roughly between 6 months and 103. (The hotel capacity is 300.) At the mountain retreat Harahorn, the trio of young chefs includes two Danes, Lars Kopp Christiansen, who is 30, and Jannie Lind, 21. They usually feed fewer than 30 guests, so they can afford to experiment.</p>
        <p>At three meals, we were treated to a perfectly cooked lamb fillet, an unusually intense guinea fowl pâté, turbot braised in red wine (that's right, red), king crab soup gratifyingly a-chunk with the actual meat, medium-rare reindeer with mushrooms and a superlative mocha fragilité, a roll cake of meringue and marzipan. Although a genuine modesty, coupled with a regionally genetic inability to be politically incorrect that rivals Hollywood's, prevented either of the cooks from criticizing traditional Norwegian cooking, it was clear that white food isn't in their repertory.</p>
        <p>Prices in Norway are so ludicrously steep you may fantasize Tokyo and London to be bargains. A slab of salmon at the Grand Hotel in Oslo runs to $40 or more; a hot dog and a Coke, to seven bucks and up. This is largely because you're required to add 24 percent to the total in order to carry out the most ambitious social schemes in Europe. To order an $8 fast-food burger is to make a political statement.</p>
        <p>But Norwegians are not, as one friend suggested, the goody-goodies of Europe, though having dinner with a group of them does sometimes feel like an attack by the newsreaders of NPR. They are justifiably proud of their social and environmental records, and if smugness creeps into the conversation occasionally, who can blame them?</p>
        <p>And by the way, spectacular as the Solstrand is, the five-hour drive from it to Harahorn is Spectacular Squared. You can see more drama than on all of Broadway, the West End and ''America's Most Wanted'' combined: thrilling fjords, ravines, waterfalls, sheer cliffs, trees, flowers, sometimes all at the same time, and once you get up in the mountains, a landscape hybrid of our Wild West and the moon.</p>
        <p>In fact, so continuously beautiful is the Norwegian landscape that after 10 days of it, I turned to a friend and said: ''I'm sick of this. I want to see a slum.'' But there weren't any to be found.</p>
        <p>King Crab Soup  With Saffron  (Adapted from the Harahorn Hotel, Norway)  4 tablespoons butter  2 shallots, finely chopped  1 1/4 cups white wine  6 1/2 cups crab or fish stock  5 carrots, julienned  2 leeks, white and light green parts only, julienned  Salt to taste  3 tablespoons cornstarch  Large pinch saffron  2 cups half-and-half or cream  10 ounces king crab meat, picked over  Pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. In a soup pot, melt 2 tablespoons of the butter over medium heat. Add the shallots and cook until just soft. Add the wine and simmer until all liquid except about  1/2 cup has evaporated. Remove from the heat, strain and discard the shallots. Return the reduced wine to the pot and add the stock. Bring to a boil.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, melt the remaining butter in a large skillet over medium-high heat. Add the carrots and leeks, season with salt and sauté until just tender. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. Stir the cornstarch into 2 tablespoons of water and stir it and the saffron into the boiling soup. Cook for 5 minutes, stirring occasionally. Stir in the carrots and leeks and the half-and-half or cream. Cook until very hot. (If using half-and-half, do not let it boil.) Add the crab meat, season with salt and pepper and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 to 10 servings.</p>
        <p>Reindeer, Venison  or Beef With Mushrooms and Berry Sauce  (Adapted from the Harahorn Hotel, Norway)  For the sauce:  1 3/4 cups beef or veal stock  1 chopped shallot  1 3/4 cups sweetened cranberry juice  Juice of 1 lemon  2 teaspoons sugar  10 whole, peeled shallots  Salt and pepper to taste  2 stalks celery, each cut into 5 pieces  1 tablespoon butter  2 teaspoons cornstarch</p>
        <p>3/4 cup cream</p>
        <p>1/2 cup lingonberries, raspberries or cranberries  For the meat:  4 tablespoons butter  1 1/2 pounds mushrooms, finely chopped  3 shallots, finely chopped  Salt and pepper to taste  4 pounds fillet of reindeer, venison or beef  2 tablespoons vegetable oil.</p>
        <p>1. To make the sauce, combine the stock, shallot and 1 cup of the cranberry juice in a small saucepan. Simmer until reduced to about  1/3 cup. It will be very thick and syrupy. Set aside.</p>
        <p>2. In another small pan, combine the remaining  3/4 cup cranberry juice, lemon juice and sugar and bring to a boil. Add the whole shallots, season with salt and pepper, cover the pan and simmer until the shallots are tender, about 15 minutes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. Sauté the celery in the butter until crisp-tender. Add the celery to the pan with the reduced stock, along with the whole shallots and the juice they cooked in. Set aside.</p>
        <p>4. To make the meat, melt 2 tablespoons of the butter in a large skillet over medium-high heat and add half the mushrooms and half the shallots. Season with salt and pepper and cook, stirring frequently, until all the moisture from the mushrooms has evaporated, about 10 minutes. Transfer to a bowl. Wipe out the skillet, melt the remaining butter and season and cook the remaining mushrooms and shallots.</p>
        <p>5. Preheat the oven to 400 degrees. (If using beef fillet, which is much larger and thicker than reindeer or venison, have your butcher tie it and cut it into at least 2 sections.) Using the handle of a heavy wooden spoon, make a tunnel as wide as possible through each piece of meat. Fill with the mushroom mixture.</p>
        <p>6. Season the meat well with salt and pepper. Heat the vegetable oil in a large ovenproof skillet or roasting pan over high heat. Sear the meat on all sides. Transfer to the oven and roast until medium rare (about 8 minutes for reindeer and venison; longer for the beef fillet). Remove and allow to rest for 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>7. To finish the sauce, dissolve the cornstarch in 1 tablespoon of water and add it and the cream to the saucepan. Simmer for a few minutes, stir in the berries and season with salt and pepper. Thin with more stock if necessary.</p>
        <p>8. Slice the meat and serve it with the sauce.</p>
        <p>Yield: 10 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
