<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Madison Avenue</title>
    <meta content="SOTSTREET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/14/travel/sophisticated/14ST-STREET.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1519294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="ONE STREET AT A TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madison Avenue (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71038F937A2575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Madison Avenue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Madison Avenue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates article on shops along New York's Madison Avenue; photos; map (The Sophisticated Traveler, part 2 of 2-part section) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The important thing about Madison Avenue has always been that it lies between Fifth and Park.</p>
        <p>Fifth Avenue is and has long been the most fashionable address in Manhattan, with all those mansion-size apartments and terraces overlooking Central Park. If it was good enough for Jacqueline Onassis, it's good enough for us. Park Avenue, whose name long ago became synonymous with high-priced elegance, is an almost equally grand boulevard, its medians planted year-round with tulips, daffodils, lighted Christmas trees, depending on the season. Strolling up Madison, you'll see several real estate brokers with photographs of offerings in the neighborhood. The least expensive thing I saw there on a recent walk was a one-bedroom on 84th Street for just under $1 million. Here a $5-million apartment is no big deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A walk along New York's most stylish thoroughfare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The important thing about Madison Avenue has always been that it lies between Fifth and Park.</p>
        <p>Fifth Avenue is and has long been the most fashionable address in Manhattan, with all those mansion-size apartments and terraces overlooking Central Park. If it was good enough for Jacqueline Onassis, it's good enough for us. Park Avenue, whose name long ago became synonymous with high-priced elegance, is an almost equally grand boulevard, its medians planted year-round with tulips, daffodils, lighted Christmas trees, depending on the season. Strolling up Madison, you'll see several real estate brokers with photographs of offerings in the neighborhood. The least expensive thing I saw there on a recent walk was a one-bedroom on 84th Street for just under $1 million. Here a $5-million apartment is no big deal.</p>
        <p>When you see Prada facing Chloé and DKNY across the street from Calvin Klein in the midst of scores of other chic stores, it's easy to forget that Madison is a neighborhood, not just a ridiculously upscale shopping center. The proof is in the number of people you'll see walking their dogs -- well-groomed Maltese, cocker spaniels and bichon frisés. It's the sort of place where you might run into a Chinese crested and a papillon, out shopping with their owners, checking out travel bags.</p>
        <p>Madison is basically just part of the Midtown business district until 61st Street or so. That's where you'll find Barneys, the high-fashion store that turned its back on its downtown roots a few years ago to relocate here. I once bought a $300 Helmut Lang evening purse at Barneys because I thought it was witty, only to realize when I carried it that it really did look like a paper shopping bag, and not an ironic comment on one.</p>
        <p>Boyd's Chemists -- now renamed Boyd's Department Store -- is across the street. This New York institution has added a back room with sexy lingerie and is overwhelmed by tote bags and pashminas, but you can still get a free beauty makeover. Madison may also be the world's hair ornament capital, with combs, clips, headbands, bows, pins and the occasional scrunchy (recently declared déclassé on ''Sex and the City'').</p>
        <p>Sherry-Lehmann, purveyor of fine wines, delivers all over the place and takes orders by e-mail. But once in a while it's good to visit the store, between 61st and 62nd, to see hundreds of bottles of Chateaux Margaux and Latour and Lynch-Bages and far more affordable labels on display.</p>
        <p>Just north of 62nd, on the second floor, is Salon A.K.S., my longtime home away from home, where it's easy to spend $400 for a haircut and highlights. You need this sort of thing if you're going to hold your head high while strolling among all those expensively dressed, well-cared-for residents. Or, if you want a different kind of beauty shop experience, there is Alberto dei Montecchi, where they still have the old-fashioned helmet hair dryers that your mother (or grandmother) sat under in curlers.</p>
        <p>Next door to A.K.S. is Nello, an Italian restaurant where customers exude remarkable well-being at their open-to-the-sidewalk tables. It is, predictably, not inexpensive (a recent lunch for one pasta, sparkling water and a glass of the least expensive wine on the list -- was $64 before tip). La Goulue, the gorgeous French bistro, is a couple of blocks north, with its own sidewalk tables and a menu that offers cheese soufflés, steak frites and tarte Tatin. It is widely believed that you will best enjoy La Goulue if you go with one of its fashionable regulars.</p>
        <p>You'll also find tiny coffee shops along Madison. The best known is Soup Burg, at 73rd, where the cottage cheese and fruit plate comes with three huge cubes of Jell-O and you can get a burger and a Coke for under $8.</p>
        <p>Fashion designers are everywhere: Givenchy, Chanel, Valentino, Missoni, Saint Laurent, Armani, Gaultier, Sonia Rykiel, Emmanuel Ungaro, Issey Miyake, Donna Karan, Michael Kors, Carolina Herrera, Gucci and Gianfranco Ferré. J. M. Weston is displaying very retro two-tone penny loafers for men. At Miu Miu, they're pushing mock crocodile bags and skirts with raw-edge waistbands. And in the middle of it all is the inexplicably affordable BCBG Max Azria, which is showing a lot of browns and pinks for fall. The gray sweater I fell in love with was $118.</p>
        <p>Ralph Lauren pretty much rules the avenue between 71st and 72nd Streets, although the stately late-19th-century St. James Church shares the eastern side with him. The St. James parish itself began in 1810 as a resort-area church when Manhattanites lived downtown but came uptown to their summer houses on the East River. St. James's brownstone building has been renovated several times and a lot of people still aren't happy with the steeple, but that hasn't kept the church from being the site of many notable weddings and funerals -- a Pierpont here, a Churchill there. Lauren's main store, which occupies the 1898 limestone mansion at 72nd, feels a lot like Mr. Lauren's ads. They're showing cashmere and corduroys and soft tweeds for fall. Across the avenue, at 71st, cute toddler mannequins pose in childhood chic garb.</p>
        <p>It doesn't matter a whole lot whether you can afford such high-end merchandise. Madison Avenue is very much about window-shopping. When I last saw Steuben Glass, its window was carpeted with bright green apples to set off one perfect little glass apple on a table. Gaultier's mannequins were sharing the windows with about three dozen naked baby dolls. Frette had achieved a new level of tastefulness by placing white and ivory pillows embroidered with the word ''sale'' in the window. Graff, between 63rd and 64th, is probably the only place I'll ever see a 21.54-carat diamond up close.</p>
        <p>Madison isn't known for any particular architectural style, but the Whitney Museum of American Art stands out, a granite 1966 Marcel Breuer design with the occasional trapezoidal window. Even if you don't have time to go inside, you can have an art experience just enjoying the sculpture terrace outside.</p>
        <p>The Carlyle Hotel is a block north. Its Madison Avenue entrance leads almost directly into the elegant brown velvet dining room, Dumonet, where a two-course dinner, which might be steak au poivre, a fresh morel omelet or veal cheeks, is only $36. The Carlyle's Bemelmans Bar is just across the hall. Far lesser known than the Café Carlyle, where Bobby Short's shows have become a tourist attraction, Bemelmans may be most famous for its murals, done by Ludwig Bemelmans, the creator of the children's-book character Madeline. (They say he did it in exchange for 18 months' rent.) This is the sort of place where I want to wear a hat with a veil and order a Dubonnet.</p>
        <p>As you go into the high 70's and low 80's, a true neighborhood feel reasserts itself. The designer stores are intertwined with the quotidian here. You'll pass the Frank E. Campbell funeral home, where anyone who was anybody (George Gershwin, Judy Garland) passed through. The red brick building across the street is P. S. 6, one of the few public schools in Manhattan that affluent parents will even consider. Going into Fauchon, about three blocks down, is like entering a miniature Hollywood version of Paris. There are ice creams, chocolates, madeleines, éclairs, cakes and half a dozen tiny tables in the back. La Maison du Chocolat sells chocolates and, during the holiday months, marrons glacés ($39 for 10 pieces to $201 for 54); I'm going to start saving for them now. E.A.T., Eli Zabar's casual restaurant, is a semiaffordable place for lunch, as long as you avoid the Beluga caviar dishes. The coconut cake comes highly recommended.</p>
        <p>The best part of Zitomer's, another pharmacy that has declared itself a department store, is Zitomer Spot, the pet products boutique, which reminds us again of the avenue's sidewalk character. There are Burberry coats (of course), pet sunglasses, Yankees caps for dogs and some elegant food and water bowls set in their own little countertops. I was in the market for a small-size life preserver for my West Highland white terrier's next weekend in Martha's Vineyard, but had no luck. Maybe there are a few things you can't find on Madison.</p>
        <p>ONE STREET AT A TIME Anita Gates reviews film, television and theater for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anita Gates reviews film, television and theater for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
