<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Taken With World Cup, But What About Pro Soccer?</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="700280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD CUP '94"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD CUP (SOCCER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAJOR LEAGUE SOCCER</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIFA (WORLD SOCCER ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LONGMAN, JERE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDF163EF93AA25754C0A962958260" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Taken With World Cup, But What About Pro Soccer?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LONGMAN, JERE</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif., July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans showed up in record numbers for the World Cup. The question now is, how many of them will come back to support a new professional soccer league and nourish the sport in general?</p>
        <p>As of today, soccer will largely disappear from television and the sports pages until April, when the proposed Major League Soccer league is scheduled to begin play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans showed up in record numbers for the World Cup. The question now is, how many of them will come back to support a new professional soccer league and nourish the sport in general?</p>
        <p>As of today, soccer will largely disappear from television and the sports pages until April, when the proposed Major League Soccer league is scheduled to begin play.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen whether Americans in large numbers are truly interested in soccer or whether they were drawn to the World Cup because it was a big event, a novelty such as the Olympics, where curiosity is enthusiastic but fleeting.</p>
        <p>FIFA, the sport's world governing body, brought the quadrennial tournament here to create interest in the game, to tap the riches of a vast potential new market and start a first-rate professional league. But it is uncertain whether the intended legacy will be fulfilled.</p>
        <p>"We are confident that the professional league will go through," said Joseph (Sepp) Blatter, secretary general of FIFA. "We now have plenty of reason to trust U.S. organizing capabilities and public interest in the United States."</p>
        <p>Others, however, disagree on the World Cup's lasting impact.</p>
        <p>"For World Cup soccer worldwide, the World Cup gets a grade A; for staging of the World Cup in America, it gets a grade A," said Nye Lavalle, chairman of the Dallas-based Sports Marketing Group, a marketing research company that represents World Cup corporate sponsors. "But for the future of soccer in America, the grade is incomplete. If you want a prediction, it seems like the term paper will be turned in and it will get a failing grade."</p>
        <p>He added: "To say that it will ever be on par with hockey or golf or even wrestling is way off the mark."</p>
        <p>Perhaps, but a day after the World Cup final, organizers were basking in a statistical glow over the accomplishments of the past month. A record attendance of 3,567,415 was achieved for the 52 games played at nine football stadiums, exceeding by more than a million the 2,517,348 spectators who attended the 1990 World Cup in Italy. Average attendance was 68,604.</p>
        <p>The financial surplus should surpass projections of $20 to $25 million, according to Alan Rothenberg, chairman of World Cup USA '94. Gate receipts for Sunday's final, for which 94,194 spectators paid an average ticket price of $460, totaled $43.5 million, Rothenberg said at a news conference today, adding that he thought the figure was a record for a single sporting event.</p>
        <p>"I think the achievements of the last 31 days speak for themselves in terms of putting on the greatest World Cup ever," Rothenberg said.</p>
        <p>Sunday's final, broadcast on ABC, drew an overnight rating of 12.4; if the rating holds, it means that the game was seen in 10 million American households. This rating is minuscule compared with Super Bowl numbers and figure skating at the recent Winter Olympics, but it represents the high-water mark for soccer in this country. Up, Up and Away</p>
        <p>Rothenberg had projected an average rating of 4.5 for the 11 games broadcast by ABC. After 10 games, the average rating was 4.7, buoyed by a 9.3 rating for the United States-Brazil game on the Fourth of July. Once Sunday's final is factored in, the average rating will get another boost.</p>
        <p>ABC would like to stay involved in the sport by bidding for the 1998 World Cup, televising the M.L.S. championship game and arranging made-for-television games between the United States and other world powers such as champion Brazil, said Dennis Swanson, president of ABC Sports. Rothenberg said the Americans have received offers to play against England at Wembley Stadium in London and against Brazil at Rio's 200,000-seat Maracana Stadium.</p>
        <p>"It worked out quite well for us," Swanson said. "I felt we'd pull some double-digit ratings. I didn't know exactly how high the final would be, but it was clear there was an audience for soccer in our country."</p>
        <p>The question is, how big of an audience? Organizers may have burned as many bridges as they built. Spectators lodged numerous complaints about price gouging at hotels and the mishandling of ticket requests. In Chicago, dissatisfaction with seating has led to a class-action lawsuit.</p>
        <p>As of now, 16 million Americans play soccer, but most of them are kids and immigrants. It is a participatory rather than a spectator sport. Rothenberg, who is set to run the new league, is cautious about attendance for the new league, projecting average crowds of 12,000 the first year with a steady increase.</p>
        <p>"Our goal, 10 years from now, is to be in position where we can be considered a sport on the level, in terms of interest, of the big ones: football, baseball, basketball," Rothenberg said. What Will It Take</p>
        <p>For a first-class league to survive in America, the league needs first-class American players. Rothenberg said he expected "virtually all" of the United States players to remain in the country to play in the new league or to return when their foreign-league seasons end. But many American players have said they want to gauge the M.L.S. in terms of competition and salaries before making a commitment. A consensus of players said they feel they must play in Europe to hone their skills if they expect to advance beyond the second round in 1998.</p>
        <p>"It's a crazy idea to think that you can start a league without the best American players," said midfielder Tab Ramos. "If you start a mediocre league, you're going to have problems. People aren't dumb."</p>
        <p>Given the success of the World Cup in the United States, there is already talk of its return, possibly in 2014 after tournaments in France, Asia, Germany, South America, and South Africa. Only France has been awarded the Cup for certain. The rest is up in the air, just like the future of soccer in America.  WORLD CUP '94</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
