<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="13DIAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1183609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EED9123BF930A25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>On a recent visit to New Orleans, I was boarding a tour bus when the guide asked everyone his or her place of origin. There were visitors from Tennessee, Oklahoma, California, France, Italy and Germany, and the guide's reply was always the same: ''How nice! Welcome to New Orleans!'' When he came to me, I answered ''New York.'' ''Welcome to America,'' he replied. Are we really viewed as that different?</p>
        <p>DALIA LIEBERSOHN</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>On a recent visit to New Orleans, I was boarding a tour bus when the guide asked everyone his or her place of origin. There were visitors from Tennessee, Oklahoma, California, France, Italy and Germany, and the guide's reply was always the same: ''How nice! Welcome to New Orleans!'' When he came to me, I answered ''New York.'' ''Welcome to America,'' he replied. Are we really viewed as that different?</p>
        <p>DALIA LIEBERSOHN</p>
        <p>When she returned from Paris recently, Susan Rappaport brought two charming and basic French books for Alexandra Hall, her 5-year-old granddaughter. She explained that Alex might enjoy beginning to learn French now, in preparation for future visits. Alex listened attentively and then placed her hands firmly on her hips. ''Thanks for the books, but I can't learn French,'' she said. ''Listen, I don't even know all the words in New York City yet.''</p>
        <p>A man in a crowded subway car going uptown managed to extricate his large saxophone from its case. He then proceeded to play very loudly and not very well, drowning out even the usual screeching and creaking. ''Blissfully he then stopped,'' said the Rev. Roger John Callan, who was among the passengers, but it was only to announce to his captive audience that, for a small fee, he would play no more. Mr. Callan reported that the nearby passengers contributed to the ransom with enthusiasm. Silence prevailed.</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was driving on the Upper East Side when a pedestrian pointed to my front wheel, indicating something was wrong. I pulled up next to the curb. He bent over, examined the tire and asked me to pull up about a foot and then back up so he could show me what had caused the flat tire.</p>
        <p>Seeing that I was annoyed at the prospect of changing the tire, he offered to give me a hand. By pure good luck, he had a plug and the glue necessary to fix it. He quickly yanked out the sharp screw that had caused the damage, inserted the plug and in two minutes had executed a perfect  repair. I offered him $5 but he said he wanted $15. I gave him $10, but felt he had earned the money.</p>
        <p>On my way home, I pulled into a gas station to check the tire pressure. As the attendant checked the tires, I recounted my story.</p>
        <p>He roared with laughter. ''I told Charlie to cut that stuff out. He'll ruin the neighborhood reputation,'' he said. Of course, what Charlie did when he bent over was to place a screw on the road and ask me to rock the car back and forth until I had given myself a flat tire.</p>
        <p>Apparently Charlie doesn't feel he's ready to give up his repair work. Soon after, he did the same thing to a good friend of mine, but was paid twice since he was able to put two holes in the tire.</p>
        <p>JAMES M. STEWART</p>
        <p>NOTHING IS FOREVER</p>
        <p>Still winter's captive.</p>
        <p>After repeated flurries</p>
        <p>Of deep standing snow</p>
        <p>And howling winds</p>
        <p>That threaten to upend and transport me</p>
        <p>Whereas I would not go.</p>
        <p>I hear a gentle voice</p>
        <p>Saying ''nice day is it not?''</p>
        <p>I feel a tickle at my heart</p>
        <p>That turns into a titter</p>
        <p>And then a laugh that roars</p>
        <p>Until I imagine I have encircled the globe</p>
        <p>And everybody is out dancing</p>
        <p>And clapping their hands with glee</p>
        <p>To welcome a sunny day at last.</p>
        <p>ISIDORE ELFMAN</p>
        <p>Harold R. Rainin and his grandson Robbie were crossing a parking lot to a Manhattan restaurant when it began raining. One of the members of a group leaving the restaurant commented, ''Look, it's rainin'.'' Robbie looked up at his grandfather. ''Pop, does everyone know you?'' he asked. Mr. Rainin didn't affirm or deny, he just fudged. ''Not quite,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Thelma Mielke recently recalled an unusual encounter with a woman visiting from Texas. Ms. Mielke was across from Saks Fifth Avenue, trying to hail a taxi. As she raised her arm, she felt a foreign object in her right hand and without even looking at it, flung it into the street. The next thing she knew, a man was yelling, ''For God's sake, get out of the street'' as he pulled a woman back to the sidewalk. The traffic light changed and the man ran into the road himself and retrieved a woman's wig. It was the foreign object Ms. Mielke had tossed away. She had swept it off the woman's head with the curled finger of her upraised, taxi-hailing arm.</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Going online is perfectly fine</p>
        <p>When you need to search for stuff.</p>
        <p>But have a care, for hackers are there,</p>
        <p>And surfing is sometimes rough.</p>
        <p>Perhaps your fate is discovering too late</p>
        <p>An occasional crash is the norm,</p>
        <p>''Yahoo!'' you say, and maybe ''eBay!''</p>
        <p>It's the dot-com before the storm.</p>
        <p>ROBERT H. NUTT</p>
        <p>Kim Corcoran recently spotted this sign in an East Village delicatessen:</p>
        <p>LOST CHIHUAHUA: REWARD</p>
        <p>Name: Walter (also answers to Don't You Ever Shut Up!). This is a horrible, horrible dog who will make your life a living hell. Bring him back so I can beat him and give you money.</p>
        <p>It's enough to make one wonder, according to Norman I. Reisman. He was among the crowd on the subway platform waiting to push onto the uptown local at Lexington Avenue and 59th Street when the following announcement came over the loudspeaker: ''Please step fully into the train and watch the closing doors. There really is another train right behind this one.''</p>
        <p>Observations for this column may be sent to Metropolitan Diary, Style Department, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Please include your name, address and daytime telephone number (required); upon request, names may be withheld in print. Letters become the property of The Times and cannot be returned. They may be edited, and may be republished in all media.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Observations for this column may be sent to Metropolitan Diary, Style Department, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Please include your name, address and daytime telephone number (required); upon request, names may be withheld in print. Letters become the property of The Times and cannot be returned. They may be edited, and may be republished in all media.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
