<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preparations Before House Painting</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1238F930A25756C0A966958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preparations Before House Painting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR exterior house paint to last as long as its manufacturer says it will, the surface to which the paint is applied must be carefully prepared. This can be the most arduous and time-consuming part of painting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR exterior house paint to last as long as its manufacturer says it will, the surface to which the paint is applied must be carefully prepared. This can be the most arduous and time-consuming part of painting.</p>
        <p>FOR exterior house paint to last as long as its manufacturer says it will, the surface to which the paint is applied must be carefully prepared. This can be the most arduous and time-consuming part of painting.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, it must be done diligently for the final result to be worth the effort and expense. Not all surfaces are prepared the same way. Here are techniques for preparing exterior surfaces found on most houses.</p>
        <p>New, unpainted wood requires primer only. Select the type specified in the instructions for the finish paint you plan to apply.</p>
        <p>To prepare previously painted wood, first determine whether the existing paint contains lead, a serious and common health hazard. Virtually all house paint applied before 1950 contained lead, and the practice continued into the 70's.</p>
        <p>The only way to determine the presence of lead in paint is to have the paint tested. Community services regarding such testing and abatement vary. For advice on how to proceed, ask the health department.</p>
        <p>If previously applied paint does contain lead, have it removed by a professional who specializes in lead abatement. The techniques used should minimize the production of airborne particles and fumes and include the removal of all paint chips and debris from the ground and other surfaces.</p>
        <p>If the paint does not contain lead, remove all loose paint with a scraper or by sanding. A hot-air paint remover - it resembles a hair dryer - is useful for softening thick layers of paint for scraping, but avoid using a torch with an open flame.</p>
        <p>Sand areas of shiny but sound old paint to produce a rough surface that new paint will adhere to more easily. For all paint removal and sanding, wear goggles and a dust mask approved for protection against damaging airborne particles.</p>
        <p>Excessive peeling and blistering are usually caused by moisture condensing inside the walls. This problem must be taken care of before repainting, generally by reducing and venting household moisture and by installing an indoor vapor barrier of plastic sheeting or special paint. Otherwise, the condition will continue.</p>
        <p>After scraping and sanding, or if the paint is in good condition and thus makes removal unnecessary, it is a good idea to wash the surfaces thoroughly. This removes dirt and powdery paint particles that also interfere with the bonding of new paint to old.</p>
        <p>Use household detergent mixed with water according to the manufacturer's instructions, and rinse by spraying with plain water from a garden hose.</p>
        <p>If mildew is present, adding one cup of borax per gallon of water to the detergent mixture should remove it; if stronger treatment is necessary, apply a liquid mildew remover containing bleach. For both treatments, wear goggles and rubber gloves for protection against harsh chemicals.</p>
        <p>Countersink protruding nails with a hammer and nail set and cover the nail heads with waterproof putty. Apply fresh caulking.</p>
        <p>Next, coat stains and areas where paint remains powdery even after washing by brushing with a stain-blocking primer-sealer. Cover other bare spots with ordinary primer suited to the paint you plan to apply.</p>
        <p>If removing loose paint results in baring large areas, or if the new paint will be a very different color from the old, priming the entire surface to be painted is recommended.</p>
        <p>To prepare aluminum siding for painting, remove loose paint by sanding or brushing with a wire brush. Lead in the paint is unlikely.</p>
        <p>Afterward, wash and rinse the siding as described for wood. Just washing and rinsing are often sufficient.</p>
        <p>Vinyl siding can be painted to change its color, provided the new coat is not significantly darker than the original (the sun's heat may warp dark siding). Preparation consists of washing with detergent and rinsing. Sanding or using a wire brush is unnecessary and will scratch the siding.</p>
        <p>To prepare unpainted concrete, brick and stucco surfaces, scrub the surface with a wire brush to remove loose particles. Then rinse by spraying with a garden hose and allow thorough drying.</p>
        <p>The same procedure can be used to remove old, peeling paint from these surfaces. However, unless you are certain the paint contains no lead, have testing and professional removal carried out as described earlier.</p>
        <p>Unpainted or fresh concrete, brick and stucco must be coated with an alkali-resistant primer before finish paint is applied.</p>
        <p>Previously painted surfaces in good condition usually need only wire brushing and rinsing before painting. Surfaces with paint in poor condition, particularly paint that remains powdery even after scrubbing and rinsing, first should be coated with masonry conditioner. This type of sealer is available at paint stores.</p>
        <p>Depending on the type of finish paint to be applied, masonry conditioner can sometimes be mixed with the paint and the two applied as a primer. Afterward, a second coat of paint containing no conditioner is applied.</p>
        <p>Metal downspouts and gutters that may be coated with lead paint should be tested and professionally stripped, if necessary. Provided previously applied paint is free of lead, preparing these surfaces for repainting consists of sanding or scouring away loose paint and applying a coat of rust-resistant primer. Rust spots should be sanded down to bare metal before primer is applied.</p>
        <p>Primer is not necessary for galvanized metal in good condition. But new, unpainted galvanized surfaces should be washed with detergent to remove oils that may be left from the galvanizing process.</p>
        <p>Afterward, rinse with water and allow the surfaces to dry before painting.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
