<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate and White House Near Pact on Child Care, Lawmakers Say</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD CARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DAY CARE CENTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC143EF935A25753C1A966958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate and White House Near Pact on Child Care, Lawmakers Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Senate and the White House are near an agreement on a $13 billion child care bill that would provide matching money to states seeking to set up programs to train professionals and to subsidize state-regulated day care centers, Senate leaders said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Senate and the White House are near an agreement on a $13 billion child care bill that would provide matching money to states seeking to set up programs to train professionals and to subsidize state-regulated day care centers, Senate leaders said today.</p>
        <p>The Senate and the White House are near an agreement on a $13 billion child care bill that would provide matching money to states seeking to set up programs to train professionals and to subsidize state-regulated day care centers, Senate leaders said today.</p>
        <p>After years of efforts, it appears that Congress has finally devised the vehicle to provide Federal money to modernize the nation's child care system.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers involved in negotiations over the weekend said the two sides are close to concluding an agreement under which participating states could either give families vouchers for day care or grant direct subsidies to centers. The legislation is intended for low- and moderate-income families, who have an income of up to about $29,000 for a family of four.</p>
        <p>Intense Negotiations</p>
        <p>The negotiations, which have intensified in recent days, seek to avert a White House veto. Lawmakers and the White House have been deadlocked for months on the issue, with the White House threatening to veto separate Senate and House legislation on grounds that the Congressional measures establish a new and unnecessary Federal child care bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>Once the White House and the Senate reach a compromise, the plan would have to be approved by House and Senate conferees and then passed by the full House and Senate. It is not unusual for the White House to negotiate with one chamber on legislation it wants to see passed but which it finds unacceptable in its current form.</p>
        <p>President Bush has said he prefers a child care program that extends direct tax credits to families and lets them choose what kind of care to provide for their children. By contrast, House and Senate legislation would create 50 state systems to administer child care assistance.</p>
        <p>Supporters of child care legislation were hopeful today that a compromise could be worked out to avert a veto.</p>
        <p>''There's been a lot of give and take, meetings into the wee hours of the morning over the weekend,'' said Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the Massachusetts Democrat who heads the Senate Labor and Human Resources Committee. ''I'm more hopeful than I was a week ago. We still have a ways to go. But there is a general sense that Congress has to address this issue before we leave.''</p>
        <p>'Working Very Hard'</p>
        <p>''They're working very hard on it,'' said Senator Bob Dole of Kansas, the Republican leader.</p>
        <p>By early this evening, Congressional aides said the main issue that remained unresolved was how much Federal money to distribute to the states. Of the $13 billion, to be spent over the next five years, most of the money would go to taxpayers in the form of tax credits. There was intense debate tonight over the size of the annual block grants awarded to states. While Senator Christopher J. Dodd, Democrat of Connecticut, sought a grant program of $1.2 billion a year or more, the White House insisted on grants totaling $830 million.</p>
        <p>One issue that has been resolved is the use of child care centers run by religious groups. Under both Senate and House bills, such day care centers could use vouchers, provided they did not discriminate based on religion. But because of the separation of church and state, local governments could not contract with such centers and provide them with Federal money.</p>
        <p>Year of Negotiations</p>
        <p>Over the past 16 months, the House and Senate have passed four different child care bills, and negotaitions between the two chambers have been in progress for more than a year to work out the differences. While both present bills are similar in the basic provisions, the major difference is that under the House bill, a new day care grant program would be established by an amendment to the existing social services block grant program, while the Senate bill would establish an independent program.</p>
        <p>Both Senator Kennedy and Senator Dodd confirmed that an agreement was near but would not discuss details for fear of scuttling tentative agreements.</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas J. Downey, Democrat from New York and a sponsor of the House legislation, said any agreement would have to include consideration of House provisions that are not in the Senate bill, including a tax credit for low-income workers that permits them to get health insurance for small children.</p>
        <p>White House Is Asked to Join</p>
        <p>Congressional aides said today that until recently the White House had not been involved in the negotiations. But it was asked to join the negotiations by Senator Dodd last week in an apparent effort to produce a bill that would be acceptable to the President.</p>
        <p>''The thinking is that the President does not want to veto a child care bill two weeks before the elections,'' said one Senate aide.</p>
        <p>In addition to providing block grants for states, the legislation is also likely to include incentives for low-income taxpayers. Those include an increase in the earned income tax credit for low-income wage earners and an increase in the dependent care tax credit.</p>
        <p>At the center of agreement, according to Senate aides, is a plan to offer block grants to states to set up their own systems of training child care professionals and setting health and safety standards for any center the received Federal assistance.</p>
        <p>Children under 13 years old would be eligible if their parents meet the income test and are either working or in training.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
