<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion;   In London, 60's Return, but Softer</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19901024T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BERNADINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED81E3EF935A25753C1A966958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion;   In London, 60's Return, but Softer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNADINE MORRIS; Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BERNADINE</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The most talked about fashion show of the moment is, ironically, Pierre Cardin's 40-year retrospective at the Victoria and Albert Museum. The 1960's is a major movement in fashion everywhere today, but especially here. Cardin's space-age designs from the decade when he moved from conventional to futuristic designs provide key source material.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The most talked about fashion show of the moment is, ironically, Pierre Cardin's 40-year retrospective at the Victoria and Albert Museum. The 1960's is a major movement in fashion everywhere today, but especially here. Cardin's space-age designs from the decade when he moved from conventional to futuristic designs provide key source material.</p>
        <p>The most talked about fashion show of the moment is, ironically, Pierre Cardin's 40-year retrospective at the Victoria and Albert Museum. The 1960's is a major movement in fashion everywhere today, but especially here. Cardin's space-age designs from the decade when he moved from conventional to futuristic designs provide key source material. Though the youth revolution in fashion began here with Mary Quant, it was quickly taken up by Cardin and Andre Courreges in Paris.</p>
        <p>In their current incarnation of the 60's spirit, the most successful designers have softened the sharp edges and blunted the aggressive thrust of clothes of that time. If you listen carefully, you can catch an echo of the protest, but many of the clothes shown in the spring collections here last week are simply gentle and relaxed. Only the very short hemlines remain.</p>
        <p>Simple Shapes</p>
        <p>''It's the 60's adapted for the 90's,'' Arabella Pollen tried to explain. A friend of the Princess of Wales, Miss Pollen began designing clothes nine years ago and seems to have hit her stride. Her clothes are young, stylish and friendly. Skirts and shorts both flare gently. Shapes are simple. Pieces of plastic glow in the dark, but they are mainly belt buckles, buttons or jewelry.</p>
        <p>For drama, there are black and white checks for day and short clothes covered with pieces of mirror for evening. The mirrored clothes deserved their ovation. It was a satisfying collection.</p>
        <p>So was Jasper Conran's, which managed to suggest the 60's without recalling the frenzy. His daytime uniform was a tailored blouse cut something like a jacket and tucked into matching pants for the neatness of a jump suit without the inconvenience. Long evening skirts fastened with three buttons at the hips and then stayed open. Best of all were fitted navy or white dresses decorated only with silver hip belts. Colored organdy coats were belted over snug black or white swimsuits.</p>
        <p>''It didn't come easy,'' Mr. Conran said of his spare designs. ''I started playing with the straps on swimsuits and moved to dresses.'' Why did he emphasize simple clothes?  ''Economics,'' he said swiftly. ''If you don't have much money and you want to buy something new, you don't want to put it into sequins.''</p>
        <p>'Flower Power'</p>
        <p>Two icons of the 1960's, Zandra Rhodes and Jean Muir, have been invigorated by the attention to the time when they first developed their style. Miss Rhodes called her collection ''flower power,'' and went to her files to revive her signature prints. Her printed or painted tights with her odd squiggles and personal calligraphy looked right on target with either solid or printed tops.</p>
        <p>Jean Muir seemed marvelously rejuvenated as she presented short, springy clothes in light colors like yellow and salmon pink. Suede shorts were often concealed by long sweaters marked by abstract swirls of color or jackets so supple they seemed airborne. The jackets had no inner construction, not even hems: the edges were simply whipstitched.</p>
        <p>Flower-printed culottes continued the featherweight feeling for evening. Along with her beautifully fitted navy and black jersey dresses, they helped turn her show into a triumph.</p>
        <p>Bruce Oldfield says, ''I lived the 60's.'' He didn't start his own business until 1973, but his formative years in the 60's resulted in a smashing group of black and white cotton-knit clothes that were pure and graphic, providing a nice contrast to his fluffier evening styles.</p>
        <p>The new name to drop was Val Piriot, a 27-year-old woman who was born in Brittany in France but has lived in London for six years. She made her fashion-show debut to the live music of a New Orleans jazz band. Her clothes had so many openings they often looked more like underwear. She likes textured surfaces, wood sequins and makes dresses of the round wood beads taxi drivers use as back rests. More will be heard from her.</p>
        <p>As in the real 60's, not everything on the runways was sweetness and light. Helen Storey, also new to the showings, inscribed ''RAGE'' on her red catsuits. Workers for Freedom wrapped linen bands around bodices and dresses and called the collection ''delicate bondage,'' not realizing that all bondage is dubious.</p>
        <p>Westwood's Long Skirts</p>
        <p>Rifat Ozbek focused on the ethnic part of the 60's scene with a collection called ''Afrodizzia.'' It was presented as a video, with stretch clothes and some African prints worn by dancers. It was more about dancing than clothing.</p>
        <p>Vivienne Westwood kept her reputation intact as British fashion's major iconoclast. Just as everyone seemed to agree that short hemlines were the length of the 90's, she opened her show with narrow suits with very long skirts. They were more like the 50's than the 60's and very well cut.</p>
        <p>She had other outrageous ideas, like showing codpieces over dresses and slashing fabrics within an inch of their life, but it was the lengths that staggered people trying to make sense of the collections.</p>
        <p>Next season, the British fashion industry will assemble all of its collections in a tented village at the Duke of York Headquarters on King's Road to make it easier for viewers, who had to travel all over London this time around. The shows ended tonight with a party at Royal Albert Hall with prizes for many categories, from knitwear to couture. The most prestigious was for designer of the year. The winner was Vivienne Westwood.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 24, 1990, Tuesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A fashion review on Oct. 16 about British designers misidentified one. She is Val Piriou, not Piriot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 24, 1990, Tuesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A fashion review on Oct. 16 about British designers misidentified one. She is Val Piriou, not Piriot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
