<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Their Holiday, but Wage Earners Aren't Happy</title>
    <meta content="02five" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/02/business/02five.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1786956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="FIVE DAYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Labor Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DD1F3EF931A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Their Holiday, but Wage Earners Aren't Happy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Their Holiday, but Wage Earners Aren’t Happy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark A. Stein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stein, Mark A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RETAILERS posted better-than-expected sales this week, but the figures were from July and there is ample evidence that the economy might have taken a turn for the worse since then.</p>
        <p>Corporate news was scarce during the last week before Labor Day, which symbolically draws summer to a close. At least good corporate news was scarce. There were several developments in criminal court.</p>
        <p>GLUM AND GLUMMER -- Consumer confidence plummeted last month amid slowing job growth, the weak housing market and stubbornly high energy costs. In its steepest one-month drop since Hurricane Katrina a year ago, the Conference Board's consumer confidence index fell to 99.6 in August, its lowest level since November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three opinion polls found deep pessimism among American workers, with most saying that their wages were not keeping pace with inflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RETAILERS posted better-than-expected sales this week, but the figures were from July and there is ample evidence that the economy might have taken a turn for the worse since then.</p>
        <p>Corporate news was scarce during the last week before Labor Day, which symbolically draws summer to a close. At least good corporate news was scarce. There were several developments in criminal court.</p>
        <p>GLUM AND GLUMMER -- Consumer confidence plummeted last month amid slowing job growth, the weak housing market and stubbornly high energy costs. In its steepest one-month drop since Hurricane Katrina a year ago, the Conference Board's consumer confidence index fell to 99.6 in August, its lowest level since November.</p>
        <p>At the same time, three opinion polls found deep pessimism among American workers, with most saying that their wages were not keeping pace with inflation, that they had less job security and more on-the-job stress and that they were worse off in many ways than a generation ago.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department issued a report saying that hourly wages are 1.9 percent higher than in 2000, taking inflation into account. Over the last two years, however, wages have failed to keep up with inflation for most workers.</p>
        <p>Using a different measure, the Census Bureau said the median household income rose slightly faster than inflation last year for the first time in six years. But it said the rise occurred because more family members were taking jobs to make ends meet and some people made more from investing. The bureau, part of the Commerce Department, confirmed that wages had fallen.</p>
        <p>Consumer pessimism suggests there will be a significant drop in consumer credit statistics that the Federal Reserve is scheduled to release on Friday.</p>
        <p>PENSION CUT -- DuPont, the giant chemical company, said it would reduce its contribution to workers' pensions by two-thirds after 2007, becoming the first big company to cut its retirement benefit since Congress passed a law its sponsors said would make pensions safer.</p>
        <p>To partly compensate for current employees' smaller pensions, DuPont said it would contribute 3 percent of each employee's pay to a 401(k) plan beginning in 2008 and would match its employees' own retirement savings up to 6 percent of their annual wage.</p>
        <p>Kenneth W. Porter, DuPont's director for global benefits, told The Wall Street Journal that the 401(k) plans would not fully replace the pension benefits, but that workers could come out ahead if their investment returns were exceptional.</p>
        <p>New workers will receive no pension, only help with 401(k) savings. Existing pensioners and employees abroad will not be affected.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUND SCANDAL -- In the first admission of criminal acts in the mutual fund market-timing scandal, Prudential Financial agreed to pay $600 million to settle charges with federal and state regulators that one of its units engaged in more than $2.5 billion worth of inappropriate trades.</p>
        <p>The payment is the second largest levied against a financial institution over the practice, which involves rapid-fire trading of mutual fund shares to capture price inefficiencies. The practice can hurt small shareholders by inflating administrative costs and disrupting investment portfolios.</p>
        <p>Prudential's admission is likely to end the investigation, which began in 2003 and resulted in $4 billion in fines and penalties against some big Wall Street firms, including $675 million from Bank of America in 2004 and $600 million from AllianceBernstein in 2003.</p>
        <p>CRIMINAL SELLING -- Schering-Plough, which makes Dr. Scholl's foot products and Coppertone tanning lotions as well as prescription drugs, pleaded guilty to a criminal charge stemming from a federal inquiry into whether it had advocated using drugs for unapproved uses and had overcharged Medicaid.</p>
        <p>In addition to pleading guilty to a single count of conspiracy, the company agreed to pay $435 million: $255 million in civil penalties and a criminal fine of $180 million.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Schering-Plough agreed to pay $346 million to settle charges that it paid a kickback to a health insurer to protect the market for its allergy drug Claritin.</p>
        <p>The latest agreement is subject to the approval of a federal court in Boston.</p>
        <p>BIG PROBLEMS -- BP, the largest oil and natural gas producer in America, said federal investigators were looking into whether its traders had manipulated part of the crude oil market in 2003 and 2004 and the market for gasoline trading in 2002.</p>
        <p>Federal investigators had already started investigating whether the company's traders manipulated the market for propane. And a judge in Texas has ordered BP's chief executive, Lord Browne, to be available for questioning about an explosion at a BP refinery in Texas. Fifteen employees and contractors died in the blast last year.</p>
        <p>The House Energy and Commerce Committee will question BP executives next week about a large oil spill from the Alaska pipeline that BP operates.</p>
        <p>SALE OF THE CENTURY -- In what would be the most expensive American real estate transaction of modern times, Metropolitan Life said it wanted to sell Stuyvesant Town and Peter Cooper Village, a collection of 110 apartment buildings with 11,000 units spread over 80 acres in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the property, which MetLife built during and after World War II to provide middle-class housing for veterans and their families, could fetch $5 billion, or almost $450,000 for each apartment. They also said the price would probably force a buyer to raise rents significantly as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>Real estate executives said MetLife, which began registering potential bidders last week, hoped to select a winner by November.</p>
        <p>MOST POPULAR -- Following are the most-popular business news articles on nytimes.com from Aug. 26 through Sept. 1:</p>
        <p>1. Real Wages Fail to Match a Rise in Productivity</p>
        <p>2. Whispers of Mergers Set Off Suspicious Trading</p>
        <p>3. A Big Star May Not a Profitable Movie Make</p>
        <p>4. Lockheed Wins Job of Building Next Spaceship</p>
        <p>5. Bargains Are Near; Just Keep Waiting</p>
        <p>Links are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>FIVE DAYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
