<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glavine Struggles in His Return, But the Mets Are Glad He's Back</title>
    <meta content="02mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/02/sports/baseball/02mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1787013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Houston Astros</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DB1F3EF931A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glavine Struggles in His Return, But the Mets Are Glad He's Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Glavine Struggles in His Return, but the Mets Are Glad He’s Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Sept. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Glavine assured his manager, his teammates and everyone else in the Mets organization that he felt completely healthy heading into Friday's start, his first since Aug. 16. His control, he cautioned, was another matter, and he steeled himself for the probability that his pitches would not betray him.</p>
        <p>The Mets were not concerned. They will gladly take an erratic Glavine in September for a fit one in October. Lasting five innings in the Mets' 8-7 victory against the Astros at Minute Maid Park, Glavine struggled with his command late but showed no signs of being bothered by the circulation problem that interrupted his season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Glavine lasted five innings against the Astros and struggled with his command, but showed no signs of being bothered by the circulation problem that interrupted his season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Glavine assured his manager, his teammates and everyone else in the Mets organization that he felt completely healthy heading into Friday's start, his first since Aug. 16. His control, he cautioned, was another matter, and he steeled himself for the probability that his pitches would not betray him.</p>
        <p>The Mets were not concerned. They will gladly take an erratic Glavine in September for a fit one in October. Lasting five innings in the Mets' 8-7 victory against the Astros at Minute Maid Park, Glavine struggled with his command late but showed no signs of being bothered by the circulation problem that interrupted his season.</p>
        <p>''We want to win, but win or lose it's most important we have him back,'' Manager Willie Randolph said of Glavine.</p>
        <p>Glavine left with the score tied, 6-6, and it remained that way until José Valentín's pinch-hit double in the eighth inning scored David Wright with the go-ahead run. Endy Chávez followed with a run-scoring single that proved valuable insurance because Billy Wagner allowed a ninth-inning run while recording his 33rd save.</p>
        <p>Glavine allowed six runs and seven hits, and he threw 93 pitches (52 for strikes). But results did not matter as much as the sight of Glavine on the mound. Statistics are not important to him now, and they will not be for another few starts.</p>
        <p>''Right now my goals are simple, to feel good and to feel good coming out of the game,'' Glavine said. ''Both those things happened tonight.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, when Glavine told the Mets that he felt a cold sensation in his left ring finger, the team feared that he could require surgery that would end his season and jeopardize its chances of advancing in the postseason.</p>
        <p>But after having several tests, Glavine received the best possible news -- an existing condition, which can be treated by baby aspirin and blood-thinning medicine, caused the coldness. He returned to his old, stubborn self, campaigning to avoid being placed on the disabled list for the first time in his 20-year career and imagining when he would return to the rotation.</p>
        <p>He projects a cool confidence, but when he prepared to throw his first pitch, he said, his stomach was churning.</p>
        <p>''I'm normally a little nervous when I pitch, but I was more nervous than normal,'' he said. ''Tonight was a little different.''</p>
        <p>Glavine retired the leadoff hitter, Willy Taveras, on a fly out to center and proceeded to shut down the Astros with trademark efficiency through the first three innings, facing the minimum nine batters. He struck out three batters on his biting changeup, his signature pitch, and with the Mets leading by 3-0, things were going well on all fronts.</p>
        <p>But in the fourth, Glavine went away from pitching inside, and the inning quickly spiraled out of control. The Astros rapped four consecutive one-out hits, closing the gap to 3-1, then Glavine walked Chris Burke to force in a run. With two outs, Humberto Quintero, in his second at-bat this season, ripped a two-run single that gave the Astros their first lead.</p>
        <p>Glavine never got a good grip on his next pitch, and it bounced in front of the plate and scooted toward the backstop, scoring Burke, for only his second wild pitch in three seasons.</p>
        <p>Glavine escaped that inning without further damage, and after Wright hit a bases-loaded double in the top of the fifth inning to give the Mets a 6-5 lead, Glavine was in line to record the victory if he could get through another inning. But Taveras led off with a triple and scored the tying run on a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>The Mets took the lead in the eighth inning after Wright almost did it by himself. After missing a home run by a few feet, he settled for a double off the left-field scoreboard. Then, with one out and the left-handed hitting Valentín up, Wright took the bold step of trying to steal third.</p>
        <p>The pitcher, Russ Springer, has a slow delivery, and he barely looked Wright back to second. Springer delivered an outside fastball, the perfect pitch for his catcher, Quintero, to throw out Wright. Given a clear view, Quintero threw a shade to the second-base side of the bag, and Wright snuck his fingers in beneath the tag. Four pitches later, Valentín banged a double into the right-field corner.</p>
        <p>The Astros began Friday trailing three teams in the wild-card standings and have one month to mount one of their patented charges. If they can slip into the postseason, conventional wisdom dictates that, because of their outstanding pitching staff, the Astros would become instant contenders. No team would enjoy facing Roy Oswalt, Roger Clemens and Andy Pettitte in a five-game series.</p>
        <p>But not many teams would fancy seeing a locked-in Glavine in a playoff series either. He will make about four more starts this month, and then the Mets will see, once and for all, how ready he is.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Pedro Martínez is scheduled to throw 45 pitches in a bullpen session Saturday in Port St. Lucie, Fla., and he will rejoin the team Monday at Shea Stadium. Cliff Floyd (Achilles' tendinitis), who hit two two-run homers for Class A St. Lucie on Friday, is also expected to rejoin the team Saturday.  Orlando Hernández will have to look twice these days when grabbing his suitcase off the luggage carousel. When Anderson Hernández joined the team Thursday, the Mets set a team record by having three players with the same last name, according to the Elias Sports Bureau. Roberto Hernández is the third player.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
