<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Custom-Made Newcasts For Minnesota Viewers</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="737287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATIONS AND NETWORKS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WCCO-TV (MINNEAPOLIS/ST PAUL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEISLER, ANDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D7103BF935A25752C0A963958260" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Custom-Made Newcasts For Minnesota Viewers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY MEISLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MEISLER, ANDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to win the elusive loyalty of channel surfers and compulsive zappers while maintaining its position at the top of the local television news ratings, a broadcast station in Minneapolis-St. Paul is making a most unusual leap into the Interactive Age.</p>
        <p>The biggest surprise is just how low tech and inexpensive this leap is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hoping to win the elusive loyalty of channel surfers and compulsive zappers while maintaining its position at the top of the local television news ratings, a broadcast station in Minneapolis-St. Paul is making a most unusual leap into the Interactive Age.</p>
        <p>The biggest surprise is just how low tech and inexpensive this leap is.</p>
        <p>Futurists and television theorists have been talking for years about "video on demand," and several high-tech experimental systems are already demonstrating the service. But "News of Your Choice," a foray into interactivity by WCCO-TV, the CBS affiliate in Minneapolis-St. Paul, is being introduced without benefit of fiber optic cable, mainframe computers or microprocessor-packed television sets.</p>
        <p>Instead, it depends on the willing cooperation of a low-rated competitor -- and on viewers' old-fashioned remote control devices.</p>
        <p>Starting tonight, viewers of WCCO's 10 P.M. newscast will be able to customize the 35-minute program, bypassing topics and segments that bore them and selecting alternatives.</p>
        <p>WCCO is offering these choices by broadcasting two simultaneous but somewhat different newscasts -- one on its own Channel 4 and one on Channel 23 using air time leased from a local rival, KLGT.</p>
        <p>Near the top of the hour, viewers will be able to watch a segment with world news plus a three-minute weather report on Channel 4, or a segment of the same length on Channel 23 with local news and a 10-second weather forecast.</p>
        <p>Viewers will then be able to choose between a relatively lengthy local feature on Channel 4 and expanded local and national news coverage on Channel 23.</p>
        <p>Sports lovers can select a comprehensive sports report on one channel, while sports haters can switch to a health and life-style segment on another.</p>
        <p>The opening headlines and final wrap-up segments will be identical on both channels. So will most of the commercials. Anchors on both newscasts will promote the coming segments on the other channel.</p>
        <p>Whether this tacit endorsement of channel switching will add to WCCO's ratings or simply confuse viewers is a matter of much interest in the television community.</p>
        <p>"It looks like we've beaten technology to the punch," said John Culliton, vice president and general manager of WCCO, in a telephone interview last week.</p>
        <p>The new program, Mr. Culliton said, addresses a persistent problem: viewers devote a limited time each day to watching news but want the programs they do watch to be tailored to their taste and desires.</p>
        <p>"But by the very nature of the medium you can't satisfy everyone," Mr. Culliton said. "Do people want three minutes of weather? Most say yes; some don't. Some say they want national and international news, yet most gravitate to shows that don't have very much. We have a survey that says 50 percent of the audience wants sports. That means half of the population doesn't."</p>
        <p>The proliferation of remote control devices has worsened the problem. According to Mr. Culliton's figures, about 90 percent of television households use remote control units, and four out of five viewers change channels an average of five times during a newscast.</p>
        <p>A couple of years ago, Mr. Culliton said, he and his news director at the time, John Lansing, came up with the basic concept for "News of Your Choice." The cost of the leased broadcast time, additional news material -- mostly supplied by CBS and CNN or recycled from other WCCO newscasts -- and more news personnel, he said, will be "no more than a couple hundred thousand a year."</p>
        <p>Last year Mr. Culliton signed a contract with KLGT, a three-year-old independent station that mainly broadcasts old movies and reruns and has no news operation. When selling advertising on its 10 P.M. newscast, WCCO is lumping together the combined ratings from channels 4 and 23.</p>
        <p>Linda Rios Brook, president and general manager of KLGT, said the "rent" paid to her station by WCCO would more than compensate for the loss of advertising revenue from the syndicated series "Emergency Call" and "The Red Green Show," which formerly ran at 10 P.M. on Channel 23.</p>
        <p>In addition, KLGT will retain and sell one minute of commercial time during its portion of the newscast.</p>
        <p>WCCO did three test runs of "News of Your Choice" during the summer, and Mr. Culliton said the experiments produced a small but measurable rise in the station's ratings when the audience totals for both channels were combined.</p>
        <p>More important, he said, ratings data showed that a substantial number of viewers were switching from one newscast to the other when prompted. And the most frequent switchers tended to be younger viewers, which are the most desired by advertisers. WCCO, which has been the ratings leader in total households, has been lagging behind its rivals in that age group.</p>
        <p>Eric Braun, a vice president of Frank Magid Associates, a news consulting firm that works for KTSP, the local ABC affiliate, is skeptical. He said: "I wouldn't advise my stations to fracture their audience. Choice is a good promotional phrase. However, there's a funny human trait: the more choices you give folks, the less they're satisfied with any of the choices available."</p>
        <p>Mr. Culliton seems to be paying more attention to projects like Time Warner's experiment with interactive cable television in Orlando, Fla. Later this year, subscribers to the Time Warner system will be able to create their own newscast by piecing together parts of newscasts offered by ABC, NBC and CNN.</p>
        <p>"Ours is a stopgap measure," Mr. Culliton said, referring to his program. "But it's a project that will be historically significant to our industry, whether it works or not."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
