<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Injured Humphrey Run?</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="319985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DENVER BRONCOS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUMPHREY, BOBBY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SUPER BOWL</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC1F3DF936A15752C0A966958260" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Injured Humphrey Run?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Jan. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The cracked sixth and seventh ribs on Bobby Humphrey's left side, the focal point in the Denver Broncos' effort to present a balanced offense in Super Bowl XXIV, have improved enough that Humphrey can rest comfortably.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The cracked sixth and seventh ribs on Bobby Humphrey's left side, the focal point in the Denver Broncos' effort to present a balanced offense in Super Bowl XXIV, have improved enough that Humphrey can rest comfortably.</p>
        <p>The cracked sixth and seventh ribs on Bobby Humphrey's left side, the focal point in the Denver Broncos' effort to present a balanced offense in Super Bowl XXIV, have improved enough that Humphrey can rest comfortably.</p>
        <p>''Sitting up, laying down, that's no problem at all,'' he said this morning. ''But I'm not planning on doing that Sunday.''</p>
        <p>His medical capabilities on Sunday, when the Broncos will meet the San Francisco 49ers, have inspired question after question for the last 10 days. Humphrey's rookie season began with the frustration and uncertainty of the running back's recovery from a broken left foot suffered during his final season at Alabama. 16 Teams Not Interested That injury, which came after a stress fracture in the spring of 1988, created enough doubt for 16 teams to pass up the opportunity to claim Humphrey in the supplemental draft July 7. Humphrey had heard the questions back then, and asked some himself.</p>
        <p>But as his rookie season was coming to an end, Humphrey had not experienced so many people asking him so many times about his condition. ''Never in my life,'' he said. Any limitations imposed by Humphrey's ribs, which were injured early in the second quarter of the American Conference championship game victory over Cleveland on Jan. 14, would determine whether the Broncos will have use of the most significant improvement of their offense this season.</p>
        <p>As the Broncos prepared for practice today, Humphrey's first scheduled contact since he was injured, the rookie seemed to contradict himself when asked about his status.</p>
        <p>To Play or Not to Play</p>
        <p>''I kind of made a decision that I'm going to play,'' he said. ''It just depends how painful it is and how I can deal with it. The way my body is right now, I feel confident that I can play.''</p>
        <p>But when asked about the opinion of the Broncos' coach, Dan Reeves, who said, ''If he's not close to 100 percent, he won't play,'' Humphrey sounded more practical than confident.</p>
        <p>''I agree with that,'' Humphrey said. ''If I can't give my all and play the way I've played all year, I shouldn't be out there.''</p>
        <p>Humphrey, the most valuable offensive player in a vote of the Bronco players, gained 1,151 yards to come within two yards of the second-highest single-season total in club history. His rushing total, eighth best in the league this season, provided the Broncos with the balance that had been lacking in their one-sided Super Bowl losses to the Giants in 1987 and Redskins in 1988. Humphrey said he had been told his injury normally requires at least five weeks to heal. With only 40 percent of that time available, Denver's best-case scenario would seem to include the use of a bandaged and uncertain rookie.</p>
        <p>''In my mind,'' Humphrey said, ''it's like, hey, my ribs hurt. You have to watch out.''</p>
        <p>New Wardrobe</p>
        <p>If he plays Sunday, Humphrey will wear a protective jacket that is more extensive than the padding that left his ribs exposed at the time of the injury. He planned on adjusting to the new jacket in practices this week.</p>
        <p>''When you wear something bulky like that, you can't get a feel for the ball,'' he said. Humphrey said he had not decided if he would be willing to have a shot of painkiller administered. If Humphrey cannot play or is limited, the Broncos would have to rely upon the eight-year veteran Sammy Winder, who gained 351 yards this season but scored two touchdowns after Humphrey was injured against Cleveland.</p>
        <p>''Right now I'm a stunt man,'' Winder said. ''I'm taking all the falls until Sunday.''</p>
        <p>Humphrey's uncertainty was an improvement over what he described as the depression of the supplemental draft. He had conducted a personal test of his left foot on a Birmingham playground during a pickup basketball game last June.</p>
        <p>''I used to do a lot of dunking,'' Humphrey said. ''I went up to dunk the ball and I slammed it through. That gave me a lot of confidence.'' That self-assurance had been threatened by the two foot injuries, which had reduced Humphrey from a contender for the Heisman Trophy to a damaged player of uncertain potential. His time in the 40-yard dash, a fundamental part of the evaluation process, rose from 4.4 to 4.68 seconds.</p>
        <p>''I thought that I've got to prove myself to people,'' Humphrey said. ''Not just teams, fans. People that didn't think I could be successful.''</p>
        <p>Even Reeves Had Doubts</p>
        <p>The questions were serious enough that after the Broncos gave up a first-round draft selection to choose Humphrey in July, Dan Reeves, the Denver coach, began to have doubts. ''I really didn't think that he would last,'' Reeves said. ''Then when we got him, I worried about if we did the right thing.''</p>
        <p>The answers have all been positive. And Humphrey, who chose to leave Alabama without playing for a Crimson Tide team that reached the Sugar Bowl, was able to complete some unfinished business.</p>
        <p>''I've been trying to get to New Orleans for four years, playing in the Sugar Bowl,'' Humphrey said. ''I'd rather play in the Super Bowl in New Orleans than the Sugar Bowl.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
