<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aeroflot Buys First Airliners From West</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="320085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AEROFLOT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AIRBUS INDUSTRIE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD1E3CF936A15752C0A966958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aeroflot Buys First Airliners From West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINER, ERIC</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In its first order for Western aircraft, Aeroflot, the Soviet airline, bought five A310 airliners from Airbus Industrie, the European consortium said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In its first order for Western aircraft, Aeroflot, the Soviet airline, bought five A310 airliners from Airbus Industrie, the European consortium said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In its first order for Western aircraft, Aeroflot, the Soviet airline, bought five A310 airliners from Airbus Industrie, the European consortium said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The purchase, which had been expected for several months, may pave the way for a sale of American jets to the Soviet Union, analysts said. Officials of the Boeing Company and the McDonnell Douglas Corporation are holding talks with Aeroflot.</p>
        <p>Officials at Airbus, which is owned by Britain, Spain, West Germany and France, declined to disclose the value of the order. Industry analysts said the contract was worth about $310 million. Foothold in U.S.S.R.  Some industry experts said that Airbus may have offered Aeroflot concessions to gain a foothold in the Soviet market - potentially one of the world's largest for commercial jets.</p>
        <p>''This could be worth a lot more for Airbus than just the dollars tied up in the deal,'' said Paul Nisbet, an analyst with Prudential-Bache. ''They beat Boeing into the market.''</p>
        <p>Aeroflot bought the Airbus jets partly to attract Western passengers who may be reluctant to fly on the noisier, more cramped Soviet planes, said George Terentiev, Aeroflot's commercial manger in New York.</p>
        <p>In September, Aeroflot began an advertising campaign in the United States, appealing directly to the American business traveler for the first time.</p>
        <p>Aeroflot has yet to decide whether the planes will be powered by engines made by the General Electric Company or Pratt &amp; Whitney. Under current trade restrictions, any significant maintenance to the engines must be performed in the West. The A310 engine's core, which is based on that in military planes, is among the most sensitive technology in a commercial jet.</p>
        <p>Delivery Next Year</p>
        <p>Alexander Aksenov, the Soviet Vice Minister for Civil Aviation, said Aeroflot was holding talks with Western airlines about a maintenance contract for the new aircraft. Tom Ronell, vice president for sales for Airbus North America, said the planes would probably be maintained by Lufthansa, the West German airline.</p>
        <p>Tom Wheeler, a Boeing spokesman, said the company was continuing talks with Aeroflot about the purchase of a 747-400 plane. One problem in striking a deal is the Soviet Union's lack of hard currency, he said.</p>
        <p>Deliveries of the Airbus jets will begin next year. The planes will be used for Aeroflot flights from the Soviet Union to North America, East Asia and Europe. The Airbus planes are wide-bodied, twin-engine jets that carry 195 passengers. In addition to the five aircraft ordered, Aeroflot has taken options on five more. United Technologiesd(Pratt)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
