<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="05FYI.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/05/nyregion/thecity/05FYI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="F.Y.I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planetariums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Williamsburg (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hayden Planetarium</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rock and Roll Ensemble (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DD123CF936A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Birds See Stars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about whether large numbers of birds are flying into Hayden Planetarium's new, transparent glass cube Rose Center, fate of New York Rock and Roll Ensemble and correct spelling of Brooklyn's Williamsburg neighborhood; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No Birds See Stars</p>
        <p>Q. When construction of the Rose Center for Earth and Space began on the site of the old Hayden Planetarium, there were complaints that a great many birds would fly into the transparent glass cube that houses the exhibits. Has this happened?</p>
        <p>A. Thomas Slade, head of the Security and Safety Office at the American Museum of Natural History, said no bird carcasses have been found in the vicinity of the Rose Center since it opened, nor has anything struck  the planetarium's 95-foot-high curtain wall. Because of concern over the West Nile virus, groundskeepers have been especially watchful for bird carcasses, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How many birds have flown into the transparent glass cube that houses the exhibits of the new Hayden planetarium</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No Birds See Stars</p>
        <p>Q. When construction of the Rose Center for Earth and Space began on the site of the old Hayden Planetarium, there were complaints that a great many birds would fly into the transparent glass cube that houses the exhibits. Has this happened?</p>
        <p>A. Thomas Slade, head of the Security and Safety Office at the American Museum of Natural History, said no bird carcasses have been found in the vicinity of the Rose Center since it opened, nor has anything struck  the planetarium's 95-foot-high curtain wall. Because of concern over the West Nile virus, groundskeepers have been especially watchful for bird carcasses, he said.</p>
        <p>Deborah Allen, president of the Linnaean Society of New York, a conservation group, was encouraged, but doubtful. ''You would need someone out there checking at 5 every morning,'' she said. ''I'd be willing to look at the data.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of the project feared that the building, a colorless cube of  glass, would look like open space to the low-flying migratory birds that stop over in Central Park during the fall and spring. Thrushes, warblers and tanagers were among the species considered to be in danger. The building is at Central Park West and West 81st Street. The 87-foot Hayden Sphere, set inside the cube, is illuminated every night at dusk.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Slade, an explanation for the absence of bird accidents might be that the Rose Center is not actually a free-standing cube, but abuts the Museum of Natural History on two sides, shutting off avian access from the south and east. In addition, its glass walls are suspended by two and a half miles of rod rigging, anchored by 1,400 steel spiders and 4,100 bolts, all of which lend a materiality and depth to the otherwise invisible facade.</p>
        <p>Classical Rock</p>
        <p>Q. What became of the New York Rock and Roll Ensemble, the ''classically trained'' rock group that used to perform in city nightclubs wearing white tie and tails?</p>
        <p>A. After recording five moderately successful albums and performing with, among others, the New York Philharmonic and the Boston Pops, the New York Rock and Roll Ensemble disbanded in the early 1970's and faded into obscurity.</p>
        <p>It was organized in 1968 by Martin Fulterman and Michael Kamen, two Juilliard-trained oboists who also played drums and keyboards, respectively. Dorian Rudnytsky, a fellow student, played cello and bass, with two rock guitarists from Toms River, N.J.</p>
        <p>''The thing about the band that was so great,'' Mr. Fulterman said, ''was that in concert we played rock and roll and classical music. We didn't combine them.'' ''We started concerts with this 20-minute piece, just bashing rock and roll. Then, one by one, we started playing our acoustic instruments. I think it was based on Bach's Fifth Brandenburg Concerto.'' Mr. Fulterman records under the name Mark Snow.</p>
        <p>Recording sessions were less satisfying. ''Everybody wanted to do their own thing,'' Mr. Snow recalled. ''There were three or four different singers, but no identifiable sound. It was like five different bands.''</p>
        <p>Since the breakup, he has written theme music for shows like ''The X-Files.'' Mr. Kamen has scored dozens of Hollywood films, received Grammy awards and Oscar nominations, and produced and recorded with Pink Floyd, Eric Clapton and other pop deities. ''We're all still friends,'' Mr. Snow said.</p>
        <p>Burghers at the Bank</p>
        <p>Q. Why do I sometimes see the Brooklyn neighborhood of Williamsburg spelled ''Williamsburgh''?</p>
        <p>A. The town was named for Jonathan Williams, who surveyed it around 1800, and its name was spelled ''Williamsburgh'' until it was absorbed into Brooklyn in 1855 and the final ''h'' was jettisoned. The Williamsburgh Savings Bank, founded four years earlier, chose not to change its spelling, which may account for the lasting confusion.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>F.Y.I. E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
