<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Around the Island, Heaving Seas and Lunch</title>
    <meta content="05SAIL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE WATER WITH: THE SAILBOAT RACERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nadel, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DE173CF936A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="3613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Around the Island, Heaving Seas and Lunch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE NADEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nadel, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 25th Around Long Island Regatta; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RAIN is pretty much guaranteed for this regatta,'' Lori Kilada of Glen Cove said, pulling on foul-weather gear as rain started to blow in from the northeast. It was Thursday, July 26, and Ms. Kilada, 27, was one of seven crew members preparing Reality, a 47-foot Catalina sloop docked at Port Washington Yacht Club, for the 25th Around Long Island Regatta, the Island's premier sailboat race.</p>
        <p>Reality, skippered by Peggy d'Allessandro of Port Washington, was one of 126 boats entered in the 191-mile race, which comes close to circumnavigating the Island, starting on Thursday afternoon off Rockaway Point and ending whenever -- on Saturday for most boats -- at the Glen Cove breakwater in Hempstead Harbor, home of the Sea Cliff Yacht Club, which organizes the event.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RAIN is pretty much guaranteed for this regatta,'' Lori Kilada of Glen Cove said, pulling on foul-weather gear as rain started to blow in from the northeast. It was Thursday, July 26, and Ms. Kilada, 27, was one of seven crew members preparing Reality, a 47-foot Catalina sloop docked at Port Washington Yacht Club, for the 25th Around Long Island Regatta, the Island's premier sailboat race.</p>
        <p>Reality, skippered by Peggy d'Allessandro of Port Washington, was one of 126 boats entered in the 191-mile race, which comes close to circumnavigating the Island, starting on Thursday afternoon off Rockaway Point and ending whenever -- on Saturday for most boats -- at the Glen Cove breakwater in Hempstead Harbor, home of the Sea Cliff Yacht Club, which organizes the event.</p>
        <p>In East Coast sailing circles, the Around Long Island has a reputation as a tricky race in which skill in handling changing winds, seas and tides often trumps raw boat speed. Fred Bauerschmidt, 54, of Mineola, co-chairman of this year's event, described it as ''three races in one'' because of significantly different conditions in the Atlantic Ocean, Block Island Sound and Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>''You can start off with a stiff ocean breeze only to find yourself in the Sound jibing to find a breeze line,'' he said.</p>
        <p>George Christman, 75, of Sea Cliff, who helped to organize the first Around Long Island Regatta in 1977, said: ''This race is a crap shoot. We say it's a 191-mile regatta but that's according to the map. Some people will sail a lot more than 191 miles tacking back and forth in the Sound looking for wind.''</p>
        <p>It can also be a test of stamina, and completing the course is an accomplishment in itself. Rudi Harbauer, 71, of Freeport, the only captain to have completed all 25 A.L.I.R.'s, said this regatta always served up a surprise.</p>
        <p>''In 1989, for example, one boat was dismasted off the coast of Fire Island in a thunderstorm with winds clocked at 96 miles an hour,'' he said. ''Another boat withdrew, citing 'torture' as the reason. The crew of our boat, Bohemia, a 26-foot Lindbergh, went through our whole inventory of sails. Then a few hours later, we were becalmed.''</p>
        <p>To families like the d'Allessandros, the Around Long Island Regatta is the highlight of the season. Ms. Kilada, Peggy d'Allessandro's daughter, has been sailing since she was 9 and has taken part in at least seven A.L.I.R.'s since the age of 11. Her mother has sailed in at least 10 Around Long Island Regattas. This one, however, would be her first as captain; her husband, John, died of a heart attack last October at age 54.</p>
        <p>''This was his favorite race, and I am sailing it for him,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Small-craft warnings were posted and thunderstorms were forecast for later that day, but Captain d'Allessandro was unfazed.</p>
        <p>''Last year, we were just finishing a race when we were hit by lightning,'' she said. ''All our electronics went out, but no one was injured. Lightning doesn't strike twice, they say, so we should be fine as far as that goes.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the first that the d'Allessandros entered Reality in the Around Long Island Regatta, ''we were miserable,'' she recalled. ''There was a lot of rain and no wind. We got home on Sunday after 72 hours. More than half of the 105 boats that entered dropped out.''</p>
        <p>Even that compared favorably with the regatta of six years ago when she and her husband were sailing their previous boat, a 34-foot Hunter. Mrs. d'Allessandro got a concussion when she fell through the companionway in heavy seas, everyone was seasick and her husband decided it would be better to turn back.</p>
        <p>For their $135 entry fee, boats are assigned to appropriate divisions and given a time handicap according to a mathematical formula that enables boats of different lengths, weight and sail area to compete. At the end of the race, the handicap is added or subtracted from the contestant's elapsed time to give the corrected time used to calculate overall standings.</p>
        <p>Any sailboat at least 24 feet in length and with a crew of at least four is eligible to enter. Mrs. d'Allessandro had a crew of six, all veterans of previous races on boats skippered by her husband.</p>
        <p>She seemed excited and a little nervous about her debut as a racing skipper. ''Women do a lot of work on their boats along with their husbands,'' she said, ''but they don't get a chance to be in charge. I got my captain's license in 1993, so I'm fairly experienced. Still, being in charge is something you have to get used to. It's one big responsibility.''</p>
        <p>It also made Mrs. d'Allessandro a sea captain, with centuries of law and stern tradition on her side. When she saw Andrew Prisco, 22, a Roslyn resident and a sailing instructor at the Sea Cliff Yacht Club, tying a knot in a mainsail sheet, she leaned forward to him.</p>
        <p>''Never do that,'' said the captain, and Mr. Prisco quickly untied the knot.</p>
        <p>Four other crewmen -- Dieter Kassl, 54, and David de Blaun, 37, of Manhasset, and Peter Benfield, 22, and Arch Walker, 44, of Port Washington, were attempting to release a mainsail halyard that had gotten stuck in a track running the length of the 63-foot aluminum mast.</p>
        <p>''It's not brain surgery, it's a sail,'' Mr. Walker joked as the other three poked and pulled at the jammed halyard until it released. It was time to motor from Port Washington past Throgs Neck, down the East River, through New York Harbor and out to Rockaway Point for the starting gun that afternoon.</p>
        <p>Around-the-Island races have been held since 1858, but the current series began in 1977, organized by the Sea Cliff Yacht Club and Newsday. Cablevision took over the title sponsorship four years ago. The record time for an A.L.I.R. is the multihull Mirage's 1983 finish in 19 hours, 59 minutes, 23 seconds. But weather conditions and the timing of the tides can cause winning times to vary wildly. Last year's overall winner, Spank Me, finished in 40:10:53.</p>
        <p>''Our biggest mistake was not bringing more ice,'' said Bob Limoggio, 51, last year's winning skipper. Having traded in the old Spank Me, a C&amp;C 44-footer, as partial payment for a 10-year-old, million-dollar 82-foot Grand Prix maxi-yacht, Mr. Limoggio, a contractor from Queens, got his new boat, also christened Spank Me, into the water a week before this year's A.L.I.R. Two days before the start, he and his captain, Jason Goldenberg, 30, of Key West, Fla., were studying the logistics of a maiden race that would entail directing 28 crew members manning eight winch stations, hoisting a mainsail that weighs 1,000 pounds and flying a spinnaker that covers a quarter of an acre.</p>
        <p>Despite his unfamiliarity with the boat, Mr. Limoggio was predicting another victory. That is, assuming Spank Me's 125-foot mast cleared the Brooklyn Bridge on its way to Rockaway Point. ''We'll have just enough clearance to get underneath the East River bridges as long as there's no roadway scaffolding,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>AS she steered past the Statue of Liberty, Captain d'Allessandro was making no predictions about Reality's chances. ''Anything can happen,'' she said. ''That's what's so exciting about this race.''</p>
        <p>Seconds later, as Reality motored past Souwester, a Pierson 10-meter on its way to the starting line, Souwester's boom separated from its mast. ''That's what I mean,'' she said. ''Anything can happen.''</p>
        <p>''The race hasn't started yet, Mom,'' Ms. Kilada said.</p>
        <p>''Theirs has,'' said the captain, nodding toward the Souwester's crew struggling to keep the boom from hitting the deck.</p>
        <p>Mrs. d'Allessandro gave the tankers coming through the Narrows a wide berth. The start was moved from Staten Island to Rockaway Point after the 1991 A.L.I.R., when the wind died, stranding several boats in the middle of the shipping lanes.</p>
        <p>Even without the threat of being run over by a tanker in the Ambrose Channel, adrenaline was running high around bell buoy R2, about a mile and a half off Rockaway Point, around 12:30 p.m. as a chaotic convergence of sailboats of varying sizes tacked back and forth with little room for error.</p>
        <p>Spank Me was sighted bobbing in the swell, having made it under the Brooklyn Bridge by inches. ''We had to take the instruments off the top of the mast to get under the bridge,'' Mr. Limoggio said later. ''When we cleared it, we cheered as if we had already won the race.''</p>
        <p>With the 126 entrants scheduled to start in 13 divisions 20 minutes apart after the first gun at 1 p.m., nerves of steel and full concentration were imperative to avoid collisions.</p>
        <p>With the 1:20 gun for Reality's division less than a minute away, Mrs. d'Allessandro's crew suddenly found themselves on a collision course with a C&amp;C 34 named Starship Enterprise.</p>
        <p>''Uh-oh! You have a boat over here at one o'clock!'' Mr. Prisco called out. ''He's coming up fast!''</p>
        <p>''Bring in the mainsheet,'' Captain d'Allessandro responded. ''Fast. One jibe and we have to go. Now. Jibing. Watch your head!''</p>
        <p>''O.K. Cleat!'' called out Mr. Walker as the screech of a winch releasing at high speed filled the air. Collision averted.</p>
        <p>''Forward!'' the captain called out. ''We're going for the line now!''</p>
        <p>''Forward!'' Mr. Walker echoed.</p>
        <p>''Arch, where's the traveler? Do you see the starting line?'' said the captain.</p>
        <p>''Isn't there a line in the water?'' asked Mr. Kassl, laughing at his own joke.</p>
        <p>''Ten. Nine. Eight,'' said Ms. Kilada as she launched into the final countdown.</p>
        <p>''Should we trim the outhaul?'' asked Mr. Walker. ''Here we go!''</p>
        <p>''Bring up the outhaul,'' said the captain as Reality shot across the starting line.</p>
        <p>''Ooh la la!'' Mr. Walker exulted.</p>
        <p>''Whoo! Good start, everyone!'' the captain called out. ''Now, railmeat! Everyone up there on the high side!''</p>
        <p>With six crew members sitting high on the windward rail to reduce heel and let the sails catch as much wind as possible, Reality sliced through whitecaps on a south-southeast course. Although the prevailing July afternoon wind tends to blow from the southwest, making the first leg of the A.L.I.R. fairly straightforward, there was a nor'easter blowing on start day, bringing winds of 20 to 25 knots and heavy seas.</p>
        <p>Within half an hour, several crew members in the early stages of seasickness had retreated from the deck to the cabin. Experienced sailors say the worst place to be in a storm is down below, where the thick, salty air feels stale and the sound of the boat's pounding is more intense.</p>
        <p>With each wave, the bow made the sound a piano might make when it smashes into a sidewalk after being dropped from a third-story window.</p>
        <p>''You think the boat's going to break apart,'' Mr. Walker said. Exactly.</p>
        <p>Having weathered a few storms, near-misses and accidents in the ocean over the years, I considered myself one of those calm-in-emergency types, but those crashing sounds turned my nausea and anxiety into a physiological cocktail of palpitations, asthmatic wheezing and shivering.</p>
        <p>Up on deck, Captain d'Allessandro held steady at the helm, calling out time-honored signals to her experienced crew.</p>
        <p>''Hard alee!'' she shouted over the screaming wind and pounding waves. ''Coming about!''</p>
        <p>As Reality groaned onto her starboard side, unsecured duffel bags and a couple of seasick sailors flew across the cabin and whacked the far wall. I was one of the projectiles. Whatever I hit was very hard, hard enough to injure my lower back and bruise two ribs. But I was almost too sick to care. Racked by debilitating nausea and dizziness, my body seemed to have melted down, leaving me unable to control my movements or pick myself off the floor. Even sitting up was impossible.</p>
        <p>Vomiting was the easy part. The adage holds that there are two phases to seasickness, the first being fear you're going to die and the second being fear that you won't.</p>
        <p>Those who were better able to fight off nausea looked after those who were too sick to function. ''We never leave anyone who is seasick alone,'' Captain d'Allessandro said. ''It can be serious. People who get really seasick sometimes commit suicide.'' A cheerful thought.</p>
        <p>By 8:30 p.m. on Thursday, the worst of the storm had passed and Reality was making about 7 knots in 18-knot winds off the western end of Fire Island, the last orange fringe of sun fading behind Kismet. All crew members were alive, at least. But the seas were still high and Mr. Walker, who was on watch, conceded that he, too, was struggling with what French mariners call la marea.</p>
        <p>''As a financial adviser, I've been seasick for the past year watching the Nasdaq,'' he quipped in a sportsmanlike effort to make light of his own discomfort. ''I look on this as a test. Can you keep your wits about you when you're seasick?''</p>
        <p>''Beer is good for seasickness,'' said Mr. Kassl, coming up from below for a few minutes. ''I think it's the hops.''</p>
        <p>Some laughed. But even the thought of beer was appalling to those who still were uncomfortable in a rolling swell that continued through the night.</p>
        <p>DAYLIGHT Friday found Reality about a mile off East Hampton. ''We can drop into Stephen Spielberg's for breakfast,'' said the ever-cheerful Mr. Kassl.</p>
        <p>If Thursday night was like ''The Perfect Storm,'' Friday was turning into ''Waiting for Godot,'' with the wind in the role of the mysterious no-show character. By midafternoon, Reality had gone only as far as Amagansett, a distance of less than five miles which, even during peak summer traffic, can be driven in less than an hour.</p>
        <p>''Mom, we're going 1.5 knots,'' said Ms. Kilada around 3 p.m. Friday.</p>
        <p>''What are you doing about it?'' asked Mrs. d'Allessandro.</p>
        <p>''I'm trolling for bluefish and bass,'' Mr. Kassl said.</p>
        <p>The captain assessed scarcity of wind, light but favorable current, and the remaining distance -- 13.4 nautical miles -- to Montauk Point. She chose to tack south.</p>
        <p>''We can pick up some offshore breeze, then make one long tack to the Point,'' she said. ''With luck, we'll arrive before 5:30 p.m. when the tide changes against us.''</p>
        <p>If, as a Chinese proverb goes, a true master sees a thousand choices in any situation, Mrs. d'Allessandro neatly demonstrated her expertise by quickly reading and finessing a number of seemingly minute elements to maximize her limited resources, smiling as her boat speed picked up to 4.5 knots. Reality rounded Montauk at 5:05 p.m.</p>
        <p>As required by the race committee, Captain d'Allessandro called the Sea Cliff Yacht Club when the Montauk Light was off Reality's port beam to report her name, sail number, division and rounding time. The club informed her that hers was the 75th boat to round the Point, and that the total count of participating sailboats was down to 103, 12 having dropped out of the race.</p>
        <p>Mrs. d'Allessandro had just put away her cell phone (in the 21st century, radiotelephones are for farther offshore) when Mr. Kassl threw a blue cap past her shoulder into the water. ''This is for John,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. d'Allessandro smiled and her eyes filled with tears. ''Yes,'' she said. ''That's good. He was always losing his hat.'' Apologizing for not having served dinner the night before, she asked Ms. Kalida to bring the baked chicken and pasta primavera up to the deck from the galley where everyone was served a large helping for dinner. Then Mrs. d'Allessandro and Mr. de Braun discussed the best strategy for heading through the trickiest section of the course, the Plum Gut off Orient Point.</p>
        <p>At full flood, the Plum Gut current can be as strong as five knots, powerful enough to push boats backward in light air. The alternatives are to drop anchor or try the Race, a five-mile detour on the outside of Plum Island. Conversely, when the current and wind cooperate, a boat can rocket through the gut.</p>
        <p>''We're lucky tonight,'' said Captain d'Allessandro. ''We're hitting Plum Gut with three knots against us and eight knots of breeze.''</p>
        <p>Fighting the current but managing a net speed of 2.8 knots, Reality entered Long Island Sound at 10 p.m., navigating toward the middle of the Sound in search of the best breeze. Night watch proved to be cold, damp and strenuous for Ms. Kalida, Mr. Walker, Mr. Benfield, Mr. Prisco and Mr. de Blaun, who split the night into two two-person, four-hour shifts.</p>
        <p>BY 6 a.m. on Saturday, Reality was a little east of Port Jefferson. By 9:30 a.m., it was still a little east of Port Jefferson, the wind having dropped. To the east, a band of mist the color of green tomatoes snuggled up to a bank of low clouds.</p>
        <p>''This is fairly typical for this race,'' said the captain as she cut a section of audiotape from a broken cassette and tied it to the stern to make a telltale to read small puffs of wind. ''We'll sail dead downwind,'' she announced to Mr. Walker and Mr. Prisco, who mounted a spinnaker pole onto the mast to hold the jib out to starboard while the main jibed to port, a set known as wing and wing.</p>
        <p>Heading in the same direction as the pitiful wind, it seemed that hardly anything moved. But the speed gauge showed unmistakable signs of progress. ''We are moving ever so slowly in the right direction,'' Mrs. d'Allessandro said. ''Even though we're only doing between .5 and .9 knots, we're not going backwards.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Prisco blew on the sail as a joke and, in an effort to fill the dead air, Mr. Kassl, an architectural window contractor, launched into his repertoire of raunchy stories, one-liners and non sequiturs.</p>
        <p>''I installed Henry Kissinger's windows,'' he said in connection with nothing in particular. Other crew members reminisced about regattas past.</p>
        <p>''Six years ago, I saw a whale next to the boat off Moriches,'' Mr. Walker remembered. But the sea around him was almost featureless, though from time to time Ms. Kilada or Mr. Denfield would call out, ''Lobster pot at one o'clock!'' or ''Lobster pot at 12 noon!''</p>
        <p>Any sense of competing with other boats had been left behind on Thursday, when the fleet was scattered by the storm. But around 3 p.m., with Reality only 10 miles from the finish line, the Millennium Endeavor, a Beneteau 361 in the same division, sailed into Reality's lonely world and uncharitably edged closer to windward, trying to steal Reality's wind. Captain d'Allessandro deftly eased her boat to starboard, blocking Millennium Endeavor's challenge.</p>
        <p>''I'm the leeward boat. I can push him off so far. Just as long as he can sail,'' she said, passing the wheel to Ms. Kilada so that she could hurry below to jettison the remaining 200 gallons of fresh water, lightening the boat by 1,600 pounds. ''Railmeat!'' she called out one more time. As crew members scrambled to the rail, she announced, ''We're making ground.'' But 20 minutes later, the other boat managed to cover Reality, blocking its wind.</p>
        <p>''I got you!'' the opposing captain shouted on his way past.</p>
        <p>Disappointed but energized by the activity, Reality's crew came back to life as the wind started picking up to eight knots out of the southwest for the final approach to Hempstead Harbor. Reality crossed the finish line at 6:39 p.m., its corrected time of 49 hours, 41 minutes, 13 seconds placing it 12th out of 36 nonspinnaker sailboats competing.</p>
        <p>Millennium Endeavor beat Reality by six seconds in real time, but nearly six minutes in corrected time. Although Spank Me crossed the finish line first at 8:42 p.m. on Friday night in 29 hours, 32 minutes, 36 seconds, its handicap gave it an overall ranking of 13th. First place went to Different Drummer, a Fast 40 with a corrected time of 24:54:17.</p>
        <p>Opening a magnum of sparkling wine, Mrs. d'Allessandro poured bubbly into plastic champagne flutes saved for the occasion. ''Here's to a great crew,'' she said, grinning.</p>
        <p>''Here's to a great captain and great provisions,'' said Mr. Kassl. ''John would be very proud of you.'' He lifted his glass. ''To John. If only he was here.''</p>
        <p>''He was here,'' Mrs. d'Allessandro beamed, touching glasses with everyone before taking a sip. Then she turned on the engine, turned up a Bob Marley CD, and steered her Reality out of Hempstead Harbor, toward home, into the last light of a perfect evening.</p>
        <p>ON THE WATER WITH: THE SAILBOAT RACERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
