<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Mexicans, Worlds Apart, Stir Countrymen's Passion</title>
    <meta content="18FITE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1177370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrera, Marco Antonio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morales, Erik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DF1E31F93BA25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Mexicans, Worlds Apart, Stir Countrymen's Passion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy W</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Feb. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marco Antonio Barrera and Erik Morales, two Mexican 122-pound world boxing champions with disparate backgrounds, will meet in Las Vegas in long anticipated bout, to be broadcast on HBO (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marco Antonio Barrera comes from a privileged background by Mexican standards. His father is a backdrop designer for television, and Barrera dropped out of law school at the University of Mexico in his hometown of Mexico City to concentrate on his boxing career nine years ago. Growing up, Barrera chose boxing over soccer, to the dismay of his parents.</p>
        <p>Erik Morales comes from an impoverished background by most standards, but he was born to a life of boxing. His mother gave birth to him on the first floor of a building that housed a boxing gym in Tijuana, Mexico. Morales is trained by his father, Jose Morales Damian, a former flyweight contender, who wanted his son to attend the university.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marco Antonio Barrera comes from a privileged background by Mexican standards. His father is a backdrop designer for television, and Barrera dropped out of law school at the University of Mexico in his hometown of Mexico City to concentrate on his boxing career nine years ago. Growing up, Barrera chose boxing over soccer, to the dismay of his parents.</p>
        <p>Erik Morales comes from an impoverished background by most standards, but he was born to a life of boxing. His mother gave birth to him on the first floor of a building that housed a boxing gym in Tijuana, Mexico. Morales is trained by his father, Jose Morales Damian, a former flyweight contender, who wanted his son to attend the university.</p>
        <p>Morales and Barrera, two Mexican 122-pound world champions with disparate backgrounds, will meet here on Saturday night at the Mandalay Bay Casino in a long anticipated bout. It will be broadcast on HBO and begins the fourth anniversary of the network's ''Boxing After Dark'' series. Barrera (49-2), the World Boxing Organization junior featherweight champion, kicked off the first ''Boxing After Dark'' program on Feb. 3, 1996 by scoring a 12th-round technical knockout over Kennedy McKinney at the Los Angeles Forum.</p>
        <p>''This fight has stirred interest and passion all across Mexico,'' said Bob Arum, president of Top Rank Inc. and the fight's promoter. ''I look at this fight as the Mexican version of Hagler-Hearns.''</p>
        <p>Morales (35-0), the World Boxing Council superbantamweight champion, said he had been waiting for this bout for a long time.</p>
        <p>''I need the win,'' he said, ''I have to win. This fight is very important for me. It's for honor. It's very personal.''</p>
        <p>Barrera was more pragmatic.</p>
        <p>''I always respect the other fighter, but for me this is just another fight,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Barrera was asked if there were a difference between the boxers from Tijuana and those fromMexico City. ''The fighters in Tijuana are chicken,'' he said. ''They don't like to be hit.''</p>
        <p>Morales said it was a typical response from a boxer who is from the country's capital city.</p>
        <p>''If he is the best how about all of my knockouts?'' asked Morales, who has 28 knockouts. ''I didn't have all those knockouts while backing up.''</p>
        <p>Coley Confident vs. De La Hoya</p>
        <p>Maybe it is because he has been at his Vero Beach, Fla., training camp since Dec. 1, but Derrell Coley is supremely confident about his Feb. 26 bout against Oscar De La Hoya at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''Within the 12 rounds they've given me for this fight, De La Hoya will not see the 12th round,'' Coley said yesterday during a telephone news conference from his training camp. ''Even if he does he won't hear the bell at the end of the 12th.''</p>
        <p>For the last 19 months, Coley has been frustrated because he has been a highly ranked welterweight and he has not been given a title shot by any of the champions. His fight against De La Hoya is not a championship bout, but his manager, Barrett Linde, said that if Coley wins and Trinidad relinquishes the W.B.C. welterweight title that he won against De La Hoya, then Coley would be the W.B.C. welterweight champion.</p>
        <p>Coley said he was not concerned with what De La Hoya planned to do in the fight.</p>
        <p>''My mind is strong enough to do what I want to do when I want to do it,'' Coley said. ''I don't think there will be a problem doing what I want to do with Oscar. I have much faster hands, much faster feet. I'm a much more slick boxer than Oscar.''</p>
        <p>Norris Is Denied a License</p>
        <p>The Nevada State Athletic Commission refused to give Terry Norris, a 32-year-old former junior middleweight world champion, a boxing license earlier this week after watching videotapes of Norris speaking in 1994 and 1995 and listening to the way he speaks now.</p>
        <p>''His speech pattern has deteriorated to the extent that it is obvious there is damage,'' said Marc Ratner, executive director of the Nevada Commission.</p>
        <p>Dr. Margaret Goodman, the commission's neurologist, and Dr. Flip Homansky, the commission's chief medical adviser, reviewed the tapes and Norris's recent medical history and advised against giving Norris a license to box in Nevada. Norris was trying to get on the undercard of the David Reid-Felix Trinidad show here on March 3.</p>
        <p>''His speech pattern was only one element that concerned us,'' Homansky said. ''He had 300 amateur fights and 50 professional fights, many of them wars. He had lost his last three fights and was knocked out in two of them. And when he sparred, he sparred for real, taking a lot of shots to the head. It was a very tough decision. Terry was sitting right next to me for the whole two hours of the hearing.''</p>
        <p>Homansky said they had contacted Greg Sirb, president of the Association of Boxing Commissions, to alert other states that Nevada had denied Norris a boxing license on medical grounds.</p>
        <p>BOXING: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
