<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watch It, Nellie Forbush, They're Rockin' the Boat</title>
    <meta content="18NOTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1177291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wooster Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dafoe, Willem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valk, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">North Atlantic (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDE1131F93BA25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watch It, Nellie Forbush, They're Rockin' the Boat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley Critic's Choice review of Wooster Group production of North Atlantic, starring Willem Dafoe and Kate Valk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yee-haaa! That's the wind they call America, pardners, that's sweepin' down the plains of the Performing Garage in SoHo, where the cultural vivisection society known as the Wooster Group keeps camp. Remember those classic musicals that seemed to mirror the strapping, restless soul of the United States -- Rodgers and Hammerstein shows like ''Oklahoma!'' and ''South Pacific''?</p>
        <p>Well, the Wooster Group has a similar work in its own repertory, a robust song-and-dance spectacle with the contrarian name of ''North Atlantic'' that does indeed bring to mind the keystone works of the American musical theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yee-haaa! That's the wind they call America, pardners, that's sweepin' down the plains of the Performing Garage in SoHo, where the cultural vivisection society known as the Wooster Group keeps camp. Remember those classic musicals that seemed to mirror the strapping, restless soul of the United States -- Rodgers and Hammerstein shows like ''Oklahoma!'' and ''South Pacific''?</p>
        <p>Well, the Wooster Group has a similar work in its own repertory, a robust song-and-dance spectacle with the contrarian name of ''North Atlantic'' that does indeed bring to mind the keystone works of the American musical theater.</p>
        <p>Sort of. I mean, there are all those cowboy songs (think ''Oklahoma!'' and ''Paint Your Wagon'') that are performed aboard an aircraft carrier where enlisted men and women in uniform court and spark and consider the ways of the opposite sex (think ''South Pacific'').</p>
        <p>Of course, it's equally impossible not to think of those heavy-breathing adultery scenes with military backgrounds from films like ''From Here to Eternity.'' And those lively morale-boosting movies of World War II with bubbly, crooning gals in uniform like ''Four Jills in a Jeep.'' And Abbott and Costello movies. And wartime and postwar and cold war espionage movies. And vaudeville routines from nearly a century ago. And Friars Roasts and Lenny Bruce and ''Dr. Strangelove'' and ''The Manchurian Candidate'' and Captain Yossarian and the Iran-contra hearings as seen on television . . .</p>
        <p>It's enough to give a theatergoer vertigo, huh? In watching ''North Atlantic,'' the best policy, as always with the Wooster Group, is to turn off your active mind and just go with the evening's fractured but hypnotic rhythms. Distinct and illuminating patterns emerge soon enough as the troupe keeps feeding its food processor of an entertainment machine with chunks of the American memory. That these chunks are themselves preprocessed, synthetic materials with only faint vestiges of their original flavors is, of course, what the show is about.</p>
        <p>''North Atlantic'' was first performed by the Wooster Group in 1983, and as is the wont of the company, for which everything is an eternal work in progress, it has been toying with the production ever since. The current incarnation, overseen by the group's artistic director, Elizabeth LeCompte, shows a formidable degree of polish.</p>
        <p>And with its portrayal of sexual barbarism and underhanded dealings on an American aircraft carrier, the work has only taken on increased topical weight in the aftermath of the Iran-contra and the Tailhook scandals.</p>
        <p>But satire as delivered by the Wooster Group (if satire is indeed what you call it) is never as much in its content as in its form. The company's highly evolved specialty is the presentation of a world in which images and words -- endlessly repeated, appropriated and scrambled through the mass media and technology -- have been divorced from their original contexts.</p>
        <p>Sturdy cliches and watchwords have lost any substantive meaning, and the people who mouth them onstage appear to be on runaway automatic pilot. Even acts of violence seem to have arrived by conveyor belt, and evil loses its human face. It's a theater of marionettes with some disembodied machine of a god pulling all the strings.</p>
        <p>Unlike many of the troupe's offerings, which are deconstructions of classic works like ''Our Town'' and ''The Three Sisters,'' ''North Atlantic'' isn't playing off one particular prototype. It has a text by James Strahs, with something closer to a story told in real time than the company usually serves up. It also relies less conspicuously on electronic distortions and displacement. There are not, for example, the customary video monitors and television screens echoing, flattening and subverting what occurs onstage.</p>
        <p>Instead, the mechanistic attitude has been thoroughly and chillingly integrated into the very performance styles of the actors. It's a superb ensemble, led here by the movie star and Wooster Group veteran Willem Dafoe, the peerless Kate Valk and another actor more familiar from movies, Steve Buscemi, who alternates in his part, that of a mysterious Air Force colonel with a deadpan manner and a foul mouth, with Scott Shepherd and Pete Simpson.</p>
        <p>They all have the house style down pat, a fluent and natural command of an eerie artificiality. Watch, for example, the way Ms. Valk, playing the lust-inspiring Ensign Word Processor Ann Pusey, seems to be fed by so many mixed impulses when she salutes the fellows that she all but short-circuits. Or the sinister Charlie McCarthy mask that Mr. Dafoe's face relaxes into after a machine-gun discharge of disconnected catch phrases. Or Mr. Buscemi's totally affectless delivery of bad dirty jokes.</p>
        <p>But individuality blurs and dissolves in the world of the Wooster Group, and it's the way the performers (only 10 in number, but it feels like several times that) work together that sustains the work's vision of reality, which is bizarrely both fluid and fragmented. The bleak operations room of a set, brilliantly realized by Jim Clayburgh and Jim Findlay, and Jennifer Tipton's meticulously calibrated lighting are every bit as much characters as those played by the actors.</p>
        <p>And then there are the musical numbers, warped variations on all-American favorites like ''The Streets of Laredo,'' ''Yankee Doodle Dandy'' and ''I Ride an Old Paint,'' in which the ensemble turns into a slightly spastic dance machine. In them, the sexual, romantic and celebratory impulses that usually fuel dancing have been perverted into something creepy and joyless.</p>
        <p>Even more perversely, watching these ritualistic numbers, executed with the precision that comes from thorough understanding and long practice of a particular craft, can be as happy an experience as seeing Agnes de Mille's cowboys soar through the air in ''Oklahoma!''</p>
        <p>Warped at Sea  ''North Atlantic'' continues through Feb. 27 at the Performing Garage, 33 Wooster Street, SoHo; (212) 966-3651. Performances: Tuesdays through Sundays at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $30.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
