<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Agency Orders Power Generators to Justify Prices</title>
    <meta content="Y10FER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/10/national/10FERC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1276721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Energy Regulatory Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dynergy Power Marketing</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke Energy Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reliant Energy Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sacramento</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Energy Regulatory Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Duke Energy Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Reliant Energy Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D8153AF933A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Agency Orders Power Generators to Justify Prices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Energy Regulatory Commission tells 13 power generating companies to justify record-high prices they have charged California utilities for electricity or refund profits that agency says may have been excessive; action, which covers $69 million in electricity sales in January, is agency's first move to directly address widespread accusations that generators have made windfall profits during California's power crisis; wholesalers who made most of sales are Dynergy Power Marketing, Duke Energy Trading and Marketing and Reliant Energy Services (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission told 13 power generating companies today to justify the record-high prices they have charged California utilities for electricity or refund profits that the federal agency said might have been excessive.</p>
        <p>The action, which covers $69 million in electricity sales in January, is the agency's first that directly addresses widespread accusations that generators have made windfall profits during California's power crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission told 13 power generating companies today to justify the record-high prices they have charged California utilities for electricity or refund profits that the federal agency said might have been excessive.</p>
        <p>The action, which covers $69 million in electricity sales in January, is the agency's first that directly addresses widespread accusations that generators have made windfall profits during California's power crisis.</p>
        <p>The order establishes a new and largely hypothetical threshold of $273 a megawatt hour, which the agency estimated was the highest cost any power generator had for producing electricity in the least efficient plant serving California's market. The order covers any sales made above that price during what California calls Stage 3 hours -- when the state declares a power emergency and requires all available generators to produce at peak capacity.</p>
        <p>The 13 generators and marketers cited as selling electricity at prices in excess of $273 a megawatt hour during those specified crisis hours will have 15 days to decide whether to defend their prices or issue credits to utilities. Some generators have argued that high prices in the market reflect short supply and the shaky finances of the state's utilities, not price gouging.</p>
        <p>California regulators praised the order, saying it would help them corral prices. But it was immediately criticized by one commissioner and some experts with the agency who argued that the action effectively cleared the vast majority of high-priced sales that generating companies have recently made in the state.</p>
        <p>Three of the nation's largest wholesalers of electricity, Dynergy Power Marketing, Duke Energy Trading and Marketing and Reliant Energy Services, made most of the sales in question, according to the order by the federal agency. The order was released late today.</p>
        <p>Executives from Duke and Reliant said their companies would submit documents to justify the transactions in question, arguing that the creditworthiness of California utilities and the high price of natural gas -- a key resource for electricity generation -- accounted for a large part of the price spikes.</p>
        <p>''When you see price spikes in a market, those are buyers competing for scarce resources, and the resources were very scarce at that time,'' said Jeremy Dreier, a spokesman for Duke, which was cited in 363 transactions involving nearly $18 million in sales.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, California regulators called on the federal commission, which has the mandate to ensure that electricity prices are ''just and reasonable,'' to order generators to refund $555 million of overcharges in December and January.</p>
        <p>The federal order scrutinized sales made in January alone and excluded some publicly owned electricity companies. But the commission also rejected the standard used by the state and set a much higher threshold for demonstrating that companies abused the market.</p>
        <p>The agency has been under pressure to use its powers to relieve California's electricity crisis, which has cost the state's leading utility companies more than $13 billion and created a political storm in Sacramento as politicians struggled to keep the lights on while keeping electricity bills from rising sharply.</p>
        <p>The agency has rejected California's appeals to set price caps on electricity sales. But in December it vowed to keep closer tabs on prices charged in the state's auction markets, setting up today's potential refund order.</p>
        <p>''Today's refund order demonstrates the commission's commitment to ensure appropriate and reasonable prices in the wholesale electricity market given the supply and demand imbalance in California,'' said Curt L. Hebert, the commission chairman.</p>
        <p>Charles Robinson, general counsel for the California Independent System Operator, which manages the state's electrical grid, said he was pleased that the agency had ''stepped up to the plate.''</p>
        <p>But he said that state regulators were still reviewing the order and might seek a rehearing to try to expand the number of transactions that might be subject to refunds.</p>
        <p>The order was approved 2 to 1 by three sitting commissioners, with Mr. Hebert, a Republican, and Linda K. Breathitt, a Democrat, voting in favor. William L. Massey, a Democrat, opposed the measure and issued a strongly worded dissent, calling the measure ''arbitrary, capricious and an abuse of discretion'' because it sharply restricted the scope of the agency's refund order.</p>
        <p>The agency usually has five commissioners. President Bush has yet to fill two vacant slots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Massey and some other commission officials and outside experts contended that the order let generators off lightly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Massey argued that 81 percent of high-priced transactions in January were effectively excluded from scrutiny by the agency's new order. He said that the order set a precedent -- one he called arbitrarily favorable to generators -- that was likely to apply when the agency examined transactions in other months.</p>
        <p>''There is no logic to this methodology other than limiting the universe of potential refunds,'' Mr. Massey wrote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
