<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE EARTHQUAKE: Trapped; Airborne in Bed: A Building Collapses, Leaving 15 Dead</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTHQUAKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDINGS (STRUCTURES)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DE1630F93BA25752C0A962958260" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE EARTHQUAKE: Trapped; Airborne in Bed: A Building Collapses, Leaving 15 Dead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By ELIZABETH KOLBERT</p>
        <p>Erik Pearson heard a loud explosion and felt a jolt like a bomb. Still on their bed, he and his wife then fell 12 feet through the ceiling of the apartment below.</p>
        <p>"We were airborne," said Mr. Pearson, a 27-year-old nursing student. "I heard the glass break from the glass sliding doors. Our apartment came down and pitched diagonally." The door was jammed shut, the couple said, but they climbed down to safety off their once third-floor, now second-floor, balcony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By ELIZABETH KOLBERT</p>
        <p>Erik Pearson heard a loud explosion and felt a jolt like a bomb. Still on their bed, he and his wife then fell 12 feet through the ceiling of the apartment below.</p>
        <p>"We were airborne," said Mr. Pearson, a 27-year-old nursing student. "I heard the glass break from the glass sliding doors. Our apartment came down and pitched diagonally." The door was jammed shut, the couple said, but they climbed down to safety off their once third-floor, now second-floor, balcony.</p>
        <p>But at least 14 other residents of the tan stucco apartment complex, the Northridge Meadows, did not. They died as building suffered some of the worst damage of the earthquake today and its residents bore the brunt of the casualties.</p>
        <p>The building, half a block from California State University at Northridge, housed many college students. An identical building next to it, the Northridge, buckled but did not collapse.</p>
        <p>The Meadows, a three-story, 164-unit apartment complex near the epicenter of the quake in the San Fernando Valley, looked like a cardboard box that someone had stepped on. In several sections of the building, the first floor no longer existed; it lay crushed beneath the two other floors. Windows had popped out of their frames, balconies dangled at odd angles and entire walls buckled. Famous From Now On</p>
        <p>Until 4:31 A.M. today this sleepy middle-class section of Los Angeles, about 20 miles northwest of downtown, was known only for its tree-lined branch of the California State University. From now, it will be known as the epicenter of a devastating 6.6 earthquake.</p>
        <p>Simply put, city officials said the 14 deaths made this building the site of the largest number of earthquake fatalities in the city's history.</p>
        <p>John William, 36, a survivor who lived on the first floor, managed to slither to safety by following a small path of light to a crack in the building's foundation.</p>
        <p>"I pushed open the crack in the wall; my fiancee and I were pressed together, and we squeezed ourselves free," said Mr. William, who had cuts on both hands and arms. "I felt like we were going to lose circulation at any minute.</p>
        <p>"I was hearing moans and whining and banging from people pinned in the other apartments. I'm not exaggerating: the second floor is now in the dirt. There is not two inches of room in my apartment."</p>
        <p>Residents described a scene of panic in the hours before dawn as people tried to climb from their balconies or pick their way down dark staircases that had been torn apart by the quake. Search for Bodies</p>
        <p>This afternoon, many residents of the complex were still milling around in front of the ruined building, at 9565 Reseda Boulevard, as firefighters, sweaty and exhausted, continued to search the debris. Eight hours after the quake, firefighters held out little hope that anyone still trapped would be found alive, but they said they were inserting electronic listening devices into the rubble that could pick up sounds as soft as human breathing. Earlier, they brought in dogs trained to find survivors in building rubble.</p>
        <p>There was no power in the area, most of the shops were closed and, in an incongruously festive gesture, people up and down the street had taken to eating half-melted ice cream cakes from a nearby Baskin-Robbins.</p>
        <p>The force of the tremor ripped apart homes, businesses, roads and utilities, leaving thousands of people without water, power or shelter.</p>
        <p>Reseda Boulevard, a main thoroughfare, resembled a war zone: broken water mains flooded streets; gas permeated the air, fuel for numerous fires that were controlled by the late afternoon. Traffic lights were knocked out, and accidents occurred throughout the area.</p>
        <p>Many of the community's 20,000 residents camped out in front of their damaged apartment buildings and houses, sleeping on blankets and lawn chairs and clinging to whatever items they were able to salvage in their haste to exit.</p>
        <p>All afternoon, aftershocks, some quite strong, could be felt throughout the neighborhood. With each one, more people moved into the street to stay clear in case more windows shattered.</p>
        <p>Capt. Robert De Feo of the Los Angeles Fire Department said the shearing motion of the quake had twisted the three-story building, causing the floor to collapse into the parking garage below. In what is perhaps the most stunning evidence of the quake's force here, the building now stands two stories high, surrounded by other three-story buildings.</p>
        <p>In addition to the university students who lived here, many Northridge Meadow residents were elderly and had to be coaxed from their apartments after the quake hit. Mike Kubeisy, a 34-year-old photographer who lived on the third floor, said he had broken into several apartments through the windows and forced the elderly residents inside to climb out over the broken glass.</p>
        <p>"They were scared," he said. "I was scared There was water and blood everywhere. I thank God I'm standing here."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearson, who is trained in emergency medical treatment, also helped pull several people from the wreckage. He said he and four groups of five men each spent the morning throwing fire hoses up to the upper floors and climbing up to carry residents down.</p>
        <p>At one point, he said, he heard a woman on the first floor faintly cry for help. She was pinned face down on her bed by a wooden beam. Mr. Pearson went to get help; by the time he got back, three minutes later, she was dead. Screaming for Help</p>
        <p>Syd Dalven, a 35-year-old retiree who lived in Apartment 135 on the first floor, said she had awakened to find herself pinned underneath the walls and ceilings of her apartment. "Everything caved in on my bed, so I started screaming for help," she said. "Luckily, four guys heard me and pulled me out." Sitting on the curb in front of her demolished apartment building, Ms. Dalven rubbed her legs, which had to be treated for minor scrapes and bruises. "This means nothing," she said. "I'm alive."</p>
        <p>Police and fire officials were not releasing the names of those who were killed in the building collapse, pending notification of relatives. Captain De Feo said that in addition to the 14 people who were killed, eight had been taken to hospitals for treatment of injuries, some of them serious.</p>
        <p>The Northridge Meadows was built in 1972, and fire officials said they had no reason to believe that it did not meet building specifications imposed after a large earthquake struck the same area in 1971. They also said they had no idea why this apartment building had collapsed, while others nearby suffered only slight damage.</p>
        <p>Several residents of the complex pointed out that the apartments that had collapsed were built over the parking garage and therefore may not have had as firm a foundation. Signs From Better Times</p>
        <p>This afternoon, the small lawn in front of the complex was strewn with mattresses, furniture and piles of clothing, pulled there as part of the rescue efforts. Little red banners, which had been hung in happier times, fluttered in front of a wooden sign advertising "Luxury Resort Living" complete with "Jacuzzi, pool, putting green, sauna, BBQ, tennis court and billiard room."</p>
        <p>One-bedroom apartments in the complex rented for about $600 a month, residents said.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, the police were not allowing residents back into the complex, and many bemoaned the fact that they had left in their pajamas and now had no clothes to wear.</p>
        <p>Annette Grossman, a retired department store clerk who said she was in her 70's, was standing in front of the building in her nightgown and bathrobe. She said the quake had thrown her out of bed and onto the floor.</p>
        <p>"I threw the pillow over my head and prayed for it to end," she said. It took a half-hour for neighbors to reach her in her second-floor apartment and pull her out through the window.</p>
        <p>"I just feel lucky," she said.</p>
        <p>That also went for her neighbor, a man in his 80's. It was more than four hours after the quake hit when the rescue teams pulled the man from his apartment. He looked up at the bright blue California sky, she said, and "his first remark was, 'Isn't this a beautiful day.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
