<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="30PATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ruffo</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Constance C R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Raf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branquinho, Veronique</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EED9123FF933A05755C0A96E958260" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance C. R. White</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">White, Constance C R</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, Italy</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patterns column on Italian leather company Ruffo hiring Raf Simons and Veronique Branquinho as design consultants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruffo's Newest Talent</p>
        <p>The spate of large companies hiring young talent has speeded up the rate at which designers move from newcomer status to establishment insiders. Ruffo, a second-generation Italian leather company, has hired Raf Simons and Veronique Branquinho as design consultants for the Ruffo Research collection.</p>
        <p>The men's wear, by Mr. Simons, is to be introduced here on Thursday. The women's line, by Ms. Branquinho, will be shown in October, during the spring 1999 presentations, said Joy Yaffe, the head of sales and marketing for Ruffo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ruffo's Newest Talent</p>
        <p>The spate of large companies hiring young talent has speeded up the rate at which designers move from newcomer status to establishment insiders. Ruffo, a second-generation Italian leather company, has hired Raf Simons and Veronique Branquinho as design consultants for the Ruffo Research collection.</p>
        <p>The men's wear, by Mr. Simons, is to be introduced here on Thursday. The women's line, by Ms. Branquinho, will be shown in October, during the spring 1999 presentations, said Joy Yaffe, the head of sales and marketing for Ruffo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons and Ms. Branquinho replace Antonio Berardi, the British designer whose meetings with executives at Versace in the last year attracted considerable attention in the fashion world. Mr. Berardi seemed about to join the Versace team, but that has not happened.</p>
        <p>Even more talked about than Mr. Berardi, Mr. Simons and Ms. Branquinho burst onto the international scene from Belgium, their home base. Linked romantically, they separately represent progressive design voices in the post-minimalist mode, with an emphasis on precise, inventive cut.</p>
        <p>They were designers to watch as they appeared poised for a long climb. But with the Ruffo contract, they have immediately become more of a force, wielding influence on two separate collections and collecting that valuable second paycheck, which can go a long way toward developing and marketing their own lines. The impact that progressive designers can have on classic lines is well documented, but the effect goes both ways, giving the designer immediate establishment status for a signature collection.</p>
        <p>Ruffo has a one-year contract with the designers. Hiring them is part of the company's plan to raise its profile. A line of accessories, Ruffo Origami Express, is being introduced for fall.</p>
        <p>''Our plan is to continue to hire the designer of the moment,'' Ms. Yaffe said. ''We chose Raf because he basically represents the fashion statement of today's man. His work is based on the Bauhaus school and a strong influence from street culture.''</p>
        <p>Ruffo, a classic line, and Ruffo Research, its more avant-garde counterpart, are carried in stores like Barneys New York, Bergdorf Goodman, Louis of Boston, Neiman Marcus and Fred Segal in Los Angeles. Most jackets in the Ruffo line cost between $1,800 and $1,900; Ruffo Research between $2,500 and $2,800.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simons's own collection is scheduled to be presented in Paris on July 3, during the French spring 1999 men's shows.</p>
        <p>Dolce &amp; Gabbana Nights</p>
        <p>Forget the power lunch. Italians in the fashion business consider the power dinner and power party a serious extension of the business day, so the only unusual aspect of the Dolce &amp; Gabbana party held here on Sunday night was that, instead of being just a celebration, it signaled the designers' entry into the club business.</p>
        <p>Stefano Gabbana and Domenico Dolce are co-owners of the new nightclub and restaurant where their post-show party was held. Called Postgarage, it is at 5 Via Castello in Legnano, about a 30- to 40-minute drive from the center of Milan.</p>
        <p>The club is an opportunity to extend Dolce &amp; Gabbana without using the designers' names, Mr. Gabbana said. They began searching for a location two years ago at Mr. Dolce's insistence.</p>
        <p>But though their names are absent, their design insignia sets the club's mood, Mr. Gabbana said. Huge leopard ottomans, red velvet cushions, gold-leafed chairs, gold-colored floors and lamp shades of Venetian glass were designed or chosen by the designers.</p>
        <p>''It's like home, or one big Dolce &amp; Gabbana showroom,'' Mr. Gabbana said. ''I want to open more shops, but this is like another form of communication. Everything is Dolce &amp; Gabbana style but nothing has the label. I don't want to build the club with the label. It should feel like home.''</p>
        <p>Staff members wear black, designed, of course, by Mr. Dolce and Mr. Gabbana. While clubs and restaurants now routinely sell clothing and other club-brand paraphernalia, there are no plans to offer any Dolce &amp; Gabbana merchandise at Postgarage. And there are no plans to turn away patrons not dressed in the same.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
