<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confused Knicks Continue To Struggle</title>
    <meta content="19KNIC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/19/sports/basketball/19KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1344419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Clippers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Clippers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Clippers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DE113BF93AA25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confused Knicks Continue To Struggle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Confused Knicks Lose Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Nov. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Clippers defeat New York Knickerbockers, 99-86 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rude blocked shots and fancy breakaway dunks were bad enough. But when the Los Angeles Clippers' backup point guard began making the Knicks look like the Washington Generals, it really got sad.</p>
        <p>Hoping for a miracle with barely a minute left to play today, Mark Jackson and Shandon Anderson, wide-eyed and in their best defensives stances, tried to trap the 5-foot-5-inch Earl Boykins at midcourt. Handling the ball like a yo-yo, the speedy Boykins twisted and turned, and then burst through the two Knicks like a halfback hitting the hole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defined once again by weak defense, poor outside shooting and messy ballhandling, the Knicks lost to the Los Angeles Clippers on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rude blocked shots and fancy breakaway dunks were bad enough. But when the Los Angeles Clippers' backup point guard began making the Knicks look like the Washington Generals, it really got sad.</p>
        <p>Hoping for a miracle with barely a minute left to play today, Mark Jackson and Shandon Anderson, wide-eyed and in their best defensives stances, tried to trap the 5-foot-5-inch Earl Boykins at midcourt. Handling the ball like a yo-yo, the speedy Boykins twisted and turned, and then burst through the two Knicks like a halfback hitting the hole.</p>
        <p>With the Knicks chasing him as if they were playing tag, Boykins showed off his ballhandling for several seconds before penetrating the lane and passing to an open Quentin Richardson, who sank a 3-pointer from the right corner.</p>
        <p>The basket, the last one for the Clippers in their 99-86 victory at the Staples Center, was a fitting end to the Knicks' latest calamity. Defined once again by weak defense, poor outside shooting and messy ballhandling, the Knicks opened their three-game West Coast trip with an awful performance that dropped their record to 4-7 and their mood even lower.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if guys have the belief that we're going to win,'' said Latrell Sprewell, who scored a game-high 22 points and had four of the Knicks' 18 turnovers. ''I'd just like to see guys get a little bit more upbeat, a little more supportive of each other because that's the only way we're going to break out of tough times like this. The team's spirit is down.</p>
        <p>''But until guys stop feeling sorry for themselves, everybody in general, we have to have a collective spirit that's going to take us through.''</p>
        <p>Already woefully undersized, the Knicks may have to battle through without Kurt Thomas, who sprained his left ankle in the third quarter. Though Thomas (11 points, 11 rebounds) returned to the game minutes after the injury occurred, he said that he will have to wait until Monday morning before determining whether he can play Tuesday at Golden State.</p>
        <p>''Right now, it hurts,'' Thomas said. ''But I don't see it being that bad. I think I'll be O.K.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, the Knicks are far from that. Now 0-6 on the road, the team that just last season held opponents below 100 points in 33 straight games is giving up an average of 99.3 points a game in visiting arenas. The Clippers, who got 20 points apiece from Elton Brand and Richardson in improving to 5-5, shot 47 percent today and scored 30 points in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''We still think just because we have New York on our chest that we're a good defensive team,'' said Allan Houston, who scored 19 points. ''But right now we're not. We used to have resolve. Now, when one or two things go bad, we kind of sink and slouch over instead of staying strong and mentally tough.''</p>
        <p>Coach Jeff Van Gundy said: ''We can't guard. No, not can't. We don't guard. We're very capable. We just don't.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks' problems, however, go way beyond defense. They are also foiled by their offensive ineptitude. They shot 35 percent while managing only 36 first-half points against the Clippers, who entered the contest allowing 101 points a game.</p>
        <p>Michael Olowokandi (three blocks), Brand (two blocks) and Darius Miles rejected several offerings from Clarence Weatherspoon and Othella Harrington.</p>
        <p>Down by 10 at halftime, the Knicks rallied behind Sprewell and Houston to take the lead midway through the third quarter. That is when Thomas sprained his ankle, and Van Gundy replaced him with the former starter Felton Spencer. Spencer was quickly beaten baseline by Brand for a reverse layup that turned into a 3-point play when Spencer fouled him. The basket put the Clippers ahead by 61-58, and they never trailed again.</p>
        <p>The Knicks committed five turnovers in the fourth period.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy, who considered changing his starting lineup after Friday's loss to the Nets, went with his usual starters. But he has scrapped his rotation and has decided to go with whatever seems right at the moment. At times, he played Jackson, Sprewell, Houston and Anderson together.</p>
        <p>''That's called desperation,'' Van Gundy said. ''They can hopefully be a quicker, harder playing, comeback team, but you're not getting away with four guys 6-5 and under for very long obviously.''</p>
        <p>Right now, the Knicks are not getting away with anything.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>In a clear indication that Coach JEFF VAN GUNDY is not in any way being blamed for the Knicks' poor start, the team president, SCOTT LAYDEN, went out of his way to praise Van Gundy before the game. He credited Van Gundy for having the courage to move HOWARD EISLEY into the rotation, for being a great defensive coach, for never making excuses for subpar play and added that management supports any decision he makes. ''The thing is we're very well coached and it's good to know when you struggle that you are well coached, and the team is led by someone who can take you through good times and tough times,'' Layden said.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
