<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taller, Faster Officers on Patrol As Police Dept. Gets 10 Segways</title>
    <meta content="17police" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/17/nyregion/17police.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Segway</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC1031F934A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taller, Faster Officers on Patrol As Police Dept. Gets 10 Segways</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taller, Faster Officers on Patrol as Police Dept. Gets 10 Segways</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A city already patrolled by police horses and bicycles, police speedboats and helicopters, and all manner of cars, vans and armored vehicles bearing the emblem ''NYPD,'' now has a new crime-fighting tool: the rolling lollipop known as the Segway.</p>
        <p>Ten of the two-wheeled Segways are to be deployed today as patrol vehicles on pathways and boardwalks in parks, at beaches and at stadiums, Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said at a news conference yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city now has a new crime-fighting tool in the rolling lollipop known as the Segway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A city already patrolled by police horses and bicycles, police speedboats and helicopters, and all manner of cars, vans and armored vehicles bearing the emblem ''NYPD,'' now has a new crime-fighting tool: the rolling lollipop known as the Segway.</p>
        <p>Ten of the two-wheeled Segways are to be deployed today as patrol vehicles on pathways and boardwalks in parks, at beaches and at stadiums, Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said at a news conference yesterday.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five officers have completed training as Segway drivers, he said, enabling them to maneuver the devices safely for up to eight continuous hours.</p>
        <p>''Their obvious advantages are visibility and mobility,'' Mr. Kelly said. He was referring to the battery-charged agility of a Segway, which can roll up to 12.5 miles per hour, and to the imposing stature the devices tend to give officers, who are eight inches off the ground and ride standing up.</p>
        <p>Even the most petite officers, dressed in police department blue, seem certain to be noticed as they patrol the Coney Island boardwalk.</p>
        <p>Still, the city's use of Segways is modest compared with that of several other police departments, which have been among the largest customers of the devices since they were introduced in 2001.</p>
        <p>Segway Inc., a New Hampshire company that calls its device the Segway Personal Transporter, said it was being used by more than 400 police agencies and security organizations around the world. The Chicago Police Department has 50, for example, and the Italian Railway Police uses 75.</p>
        <p>The 10 Segways in New York, displayed in a row behind a lectern yesterday, are the first to be bought by the department, but not the first to be tested.</p>
        <p>In an ill-fated 2003 experiment, 10 of the devices were provided by Segway and greeted with enthusiasm by officers and curious members of the public, but were recalled by the company after the devices' batteries -- their sole source of power -- were found to be defective.</p>
        <p>In some instances, officers on board the Segways tumbled ingloriously to the ground when the batteries were drained. Mr. Kelly said yesterday that the battery problem had been corrected in the new Segways, which each cost $5,300.</p>
        <p>He said the Segways would be used to patrol Central Park, Prospect Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Coney Island, Orchard Beach, the Bronx Zoo, Yankee Stadium, Shea Stadium and Arthur Ashe Stadium.</p>
        <p>The potential for preventing crime, and arresting lawbreakers, remains to be seen. Mr. Kelly said that the Segways would be driven only on marked pathways or boardwalks, and that officers would be under strict orders not to venture on city streets or sidewalks.</p>
        <p>Such use of Segways by anyone else would be against the law. Despite several recent attempts in Albany to define a Segway as a vehicle that can be legally registered and insured, the rules of the State Department of Motor Vehicles do not even acknowledge the existence of a battery-operated, stand-up scooter capable of carrying one rider. Should it be allowed on the sidewalks? The streets? Legislators disagree.</p>
        <p>Paul J. Browne, the spokesman for the police, said there would be nothing illegal about the use of Segways by the police on sidewalks and streets. But he said the 2003 test showed that the devices were impractical in crowds of pedestrians and in city traffic.</p>
        <p>Carla Vallone, a spokeswoman for Segway Inc., said yesterday that New York is one of five states in which it is illegal for the public to use the devices, despite lobbying in each state to have the laws amended. She said that most states had authorized the use of Segways on sidewalks, and that some had also authorized their use on streets.</p>
        <p>Even in parks and at the beaches, where New York City officers might be expected to give chase on their Segways, Mr. Kelly said there would be few departures from the designated walkways and boardwalks. Indeed, the city chose not to buy more deluxe Segway models, costing about $1,000 more, that are designed for off-road use on hills, in the brush and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Kelly and other police officials said the arrival of the department's first small fleet of Segways had caused a stir among the ranks of beat officers. ''There was no shortage of volunteers'' for the Segway driver training course, Mr. Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Police officials said they expected the Segways to be most effective during the summer, when crowds gather at the parks, beaches and ball fields.</p>
        <p>Whether the fleet will grow remains unclear. ''Let's see how these work,'' Mr. Kelly said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
