<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Caramoor And Tony Bennett</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="768115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARAMOOR MUSIC FESTIVAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, TONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D6153AF932A25755C0A963958260" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Caramoor And Tony Bennett</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1946, a young singer, fresh from a three-year stint in the Army, was spending what he now calls his "scuffling years" trying to establish a career foothold. And 50 years ago a philanthropic couple decided to convert what had hitherto been private recitals at their Katonah estate to public concerts. The singer was Tony Bennett, the recitals at the home of Walter and Lucie Bigelow Rosen expanded into the Caramoor Festival, and on Thursday evening the twain shall meet for the first time, as Bennett performs at the 50th Anniversary Gala Benefit at Caramoor in Katonah in a program also featuring the popular singer-songwriter Mariah Carey and the television personality Regis Philbin as host.</p>
        <p>"It's Caramoor unplugged!" said Howard Herring, Caramoor's executive director. "There's history in the making here, and no question that the gala will be absolutely electrifying." Concertgoers should not be too shocked at the $500 and $1,000 ticket prices: it is a golden anniversary benefit, and guests will be treated to preconcert cocktails and an elegant dinner in the Venetian Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1946, a young singer, fresh from a three-year stint in the Army, was spending what he now calls his "scuffling years" trying to establish a career foothold. And 50 years ago a philanthropic couple decided to convert what had hitherto been private recitals at their Katonah estate to public concerts. The singer was Tony Bennett, the recitals at the home of Walter and Lucie Bigelow Rosen expanded into the Caramoor Festival, and on Thursday evening the twain shall meet for the first time, as Bennett performs at the 50th Anniversary Gala Benefit at Caramoor in Katonah in a program also featuring the popular singer-songwriter Mariah Carey and the television personality Regis Philbin as host.</p>
        <p>"It's Caramoor unplugged!" said Howard Herring, Caramoor's executive director. "There's history in the making here, and no question that the gala will be absolutely electrifying." Concertgoers should not be too shocked at the $500 and $1,000 ticket prices: it is a golden anniversary benefit, and guests will be treated to preconcert cocktails and an elegant dinner in the Venetian Theater.</p>
        <p>As for the regular Caramoor Festival, opening night is June 24. Garrick Ohlsson will play Chopin's E minor Piano Concerto, and Raymond Leppard will conduct the Orchestra of St. Luke's, the festival's resident ensemble, in works by Mendelssohn, Mahler and Beethoven.</p>
        <p>The next afternoon, June 25, Misha Dichter, another pianist who has played at Caramoor through the years, gives the season's first Sunday recital. On June 29, a new Introductions series begins, with the Festival debut of the American Russian Youth Orchestra Chamber Ensemble.</p>
        <p>At the intermission of the concert on June 30, at which the young pianist Awadagin Pratt will play the A major Quartet by Brahms with members of the St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble, I will be the host at the first of five Friday night Caramoor Remembered discussions with Phyllis Curtin, Mitch Miller, Julius Rudel and other artists who helped shape the early Caramoor Festivals. Among later summer highlights: Barbara Cook explores "The Great American Songbook" on July 4; Christopher Plummer heads once more into the breach as Henry V in a July 22 evening of Shakespearean music and drama; Caramoor's artistic adviser, Andre Previn, returns for five July concerts -- as conductor, pianist and composer -- and an August Jazz Fest presents Marcus Roberts, Roy Hargrove and other "dynamic young players who represent the new mainstream in jazz," as Mr. Herring put it.</p>
        <p>Overall, the music is more adventuresome than it has been in past seasons, the all-Vivaldi, Mozart, Bach and Brahms concerts attractively juxtaposed with programs offering such intriguing works as Dvorak's "Bagatelles," violin and piano sonatas by Saint-Saens and John Corigliano, Gnatelli's Concerto for Two Guitars, Schnittke's "Suite in the Old Style" and the world premieres of "Evening Star" and "A Dream Within a Dream" by Deborah Dratell.</p>
        <p>The number to call for tickets to Thursday's benefit (or the gala fund-raiser on July 15, featuring Alicia de Larrocha, the Tokyo String Quartet and Messrs. Previn, Dichter and Ohlsson, among others) is 935-1840. For other reservations or to request a season's brochure listing artists, programs, prices and driving directions, prospective concertgoers should call the Caramoor box office at 232-5035.</p>
        <p>The Westfair Chamber Singers under Judith Hahnssen-Schwab offer a Celebrating Diversity recital dedicated to the 50th anniversary of the United Nations today at 3 P.M. at Memorial United Methodist Church in White Plains. Diverse is indeed a good word to describe the program, which includes choral music from England, Germany, Russia and Hungary, narrative and interpretive dances, American folk songs and a couple of Irving Berlin favorites. In addition, the winners of Westfair's 1995 Youth Artist Awards will be introduced at the concert: Jed Burgess, a 16-year-old violinist from Rye, playing Western pieces, and the Stadel Family Trio of Stamford presenting traditional music of China. For more information, call 686-4345.</p>
        <p>Folk fans have been waiting all year for the return of Clearwater's Hudson River Revival at Westchester Community College in Valhalla. After guiding the revival through its first quarter century, Toshi Seeger has handed over the programming to Margie Rosenkranz, who promises that the 1995 edition next Saturday and Sunday from 10 A.M. to dusk each day will maintain "the musical and ethnic diversity, the focus on the environment, the gathering of the larger community, the accessibility and the inclusiveness" of past years.</p>
        <p>The festival will also offer some innovations: an Iroquois Thanksgiving Ceremony, led by Tom Porter, spiritual leader of the new Mohawk settlement on ancestral lands.</p>
        <p>Among the performers will be Richie Havens, David Amram, Bill Killian, Christine Lavin and the festival's father figure, Pete Seeger, along with the singer-songwriters Susie Burke, Jay Mankita, Steve Schuch and the Duo Magpie.</p>
        <p>For advance credit-card ticket purchases (at a discount over gate prices), call Clearwater at (800) 677-5667.  MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
