<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="768217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDF173FF932A25755C0A963958260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Suzanne MacNeille</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California Hostels</p>
        <p>Q.  In midsummer my 22-year-old German nephew and his friend plan to travel in California for three weeks. How can they get a card that will allow them to stay in California hostels? Is there a listing of hostels in California? -- E. Fusco, Woodcliff Lake, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California Hostels</p>
        <p>Q.  In midsummer my 22-year-old German nephew and his friend plan to travel in California for three weeks. How can they get a card that will allow them to stay in California hostels? Is there a listing of hostels in California? -- E. Fusco, Woodcliff Lake, N.J.</p>
        <p>A.  According to Toby Pyle, spokeswoman for Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels, which represents 5,000 hostels in 77 countries (including 150 in the United States), your nephew and his friend can obtain hostel cards either in the United States or in Germany. The mailing address for the German Youth Hostel Association, which is a member of Hostelling International, is Postfach 1455, Detmold, Germany 32704; telephone (5231) 740139. A 15-month international membership costs 36 marks, ($25.70, figured at a rate of 1.40 marks to the dollar).</p>
        <p>In the United States, a foreign visitor may buy an $18 guest card, good for a year, at any hostel that is a member of Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels. (One-year memberships for United States citizens cost $25 for those 18 to 54; $15 for ages 55 or over, and $10 for those 17 and under).</p>
        <p>While many hostels routinely accept nonmembers as guests during slack times, in the busy summer season, it is, according to Ms. Pyle, sometimes necessary to have membership cards. Furthermore, many hostels will give members discounts. For example, the Hostel at Union Square in San Francisco, which costs $17 a night, and the Santa Monica International Youth Hostel, which costs $19.80, give $3 discounts to members.</p>
        <p>For a brochure listing more than 20 California hostels ranging in price from about $10 to $17 a night, contact Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels, 733 15th Street, N.W., Suite 840, Washington D.C. 20005; (800) 444-6111.  Baltic Weather</p>
        <p>Q.  My wife and I will be taking a Baltic cruise in early August. Ports of call include Stockholm, Tallinn, St. Petersburg, Helsinki and Copenhagen. Can you tell me what the average temperature and level of precipitation is? -- Edward S. Johnson, Suffern, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A.  Weather conditions at all your ports of call will be similar, with average temperatures ranging from the low to mid 50's to the high 60's. In Helsinki, for example, temperatures range from 53 to 68; in St. Petersburg, the average range is 55 to 69. The warmest city on your itinerary is Copenhagen, where temperatures may climb to the 70's.</p>
        <p>You are, however, likely to see some rain. August is one of the wettest months in the region; indeed, St. Petersburg, which averages 3.1 inches of rain in August, and Stockholm, which averages 3 inches, get, on average, the most precipitation during August. This doesn't mean your entire trip will be rainy. You can expect about as much precipitation as one would in New York City in May.  British Literary Tours</p>
        <p>Q.  Do you know of any literary tours of Britain? I'd like to visit places where famous authors have lived and written. My husband likes mysteries like Sherlock Holmes. -- Barbara Frederickson, Great Neck, L.I.</p>
        <p>A.  There are several companies in Britain that offer literary tours, including packages with Sherlock Holmes themes. Among them are the following.</p>
        <p>Sherlock Holmes Country Tours offers a weekend package, called "Sherlock Holmes Breaks", designed to provide fans of the famous detective and his creator, Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, with the opportunity to explore the setting, in Sussex, of some of Holmes's most notable cases. The cost, about $349, calculated at a rate of 63 pence to the dollar, includes accommodations at Dean's Place Hotel in Alfriston, and most meals, but not alcoholic beverages. Participants meet at Lewes station, a one-hour train journey from Victoria Station in London. There are two Sherlock Holmes weekends planned -- one beginning Sept. 15, the other Oct. 6. Information: Sherlock Holmes Country Tours, 2A Cockshut Road, Lewes, East Sussex BNJ 1JH; (01273) 473683, fax (01273) 771146.</p>
        <p>Heritage Touring offers a range of literary tours, each lasting seven days. "On the Trail of British Mysteries" visits places linked to Sherlock Holmes, Agatha Christie, King Arthur, Inspector Morse and John le Carre. The tour, which costs about $1,539, departs July 12 and Oct. 11.</p>
        <p>A seven-day tour in Wales that explores the lives of Dylan Thomas, Tennyson, Lewis Carroll, Richard Llewellyn and others, costs about $1,485 and departs June 13 and Sept. 19.</p>
        <p>Another Heritage Touring package, "Literary Byways of Southern England" visits places connected with Thomas Hardy, Jane Austen, Conan Doyle, Dickens, Chaucer and Henry James. The cost for the seven-day tour is also $1,485; it departs Sept. 8 and Oct. 29. Prices are per person, double occupancy. Information: Heritage Touring, 40 High Street West, Dorchester DT1 1UR; (01305) 266440.</p>
        <p>British Heritage Tours, Richmond Place, 125 Boughton, Chester, CH3 5B1, (01244) 342222, in the United States (800) 964-2819, also offers tours related to well-known writers. A tour from Sept. 5 to 12 of northern England includes visits to Bronte country on the Yorkshire moors; York, the birthplace of Daniel Defoe, and sites in the Lake District connected with Wordsworth, Beatrix Potter and John Ruskin. It costs $1,472.  Long Island Sound Ferries</p>
        <p>Q.  I have heard there is a car ferry between eastern Long Island and New London, Conn. If so, where does one get the ferry and what is its schedule in August? -- Denise Wilson, Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>A.  The ferry service you have heard about is between Orient Point, L.I., and New London. The 1-hour-and-15-minute trip across Long Island Sound will shave nearly four hours off the driving time between the two points.</p>
        <p>The company, Cross Sound Ferry Services, (203) 443-5281 for reservations, (516) 323-2525 for schedules, operates five ferries with capacities ranging from 22 vehicles and 150 passengers to 120 vehicles and 1,000 pasengers. During the summer, the ferries depart from New London and Orient Point every hour on the hour between 7 A.M. and 9 P.M. There is a final departure at 9:45 P.M.</p>
        <p>Prices are $28 one way for a vehicle and driver; $8.50 for adult passengers and $4.25 for children under 12; there is no charge for children under 2. Round-trip fares are $56 for a vehicle and driver; $17 for adults; $8.50 for children. Round-trip fare for the same day is $13.</p>
        <p>While reservations are not required, they are strongly recommended during the peak summer season. A ferry spokesman suggests reserving two to three weeks in advance for weekend travel, and seven days ahead for midweek departures. SUZANNE MacNEILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
