<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Misery Loves Cybercompany but Has Little Sympathy for Market Losers</title>
    <meta content="01CHAT0AB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKET TURMOIL: INVESTORS ON LINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harmon, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D6143FF932A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Misery Loves Cybercompany but Has Little Sympathy for Market Losers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY HARMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harmon, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fearful investors mob cyberspace, checking their stock prices and then commiserating with others on various investment Web sites (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavy Internet traffic slowed many on-line investment sites yesterday as fearful investors mobbed cyberspace, checking their stock prices and then sticking around to commiserate.</p>
        <p>''All the bears are patting themselves on their backs now, saying 'We told you so!' But they don't really care, do they?'' demanded one investor on a Yahoo discussion forum called Follow the Yellow Brick Road. ''I'm back to where I was sometime in the middle of January. I'll go slit my wrists now.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heavy Internet traffic slowed many on-line investment sites yesterday as fearful investors mobbed cyberspace, checking their stock prices and then sticking around to commiserate.</p>
        <p>''All the bears are patting themselves on their backs now, saying 'We told you so!' But they don't really care, do they?'' demanded one investor on a Yahoo discussion forum called Follow the Yellow Brick Road. ''I'm back to where I was sometime in the middle of January. I'll go slit my wrists now.''</p>
        <p>The sense of calm expressed amid market chaos by many of middle America's typical mutual fund investors was nowhere in evidence in Internet forums and chat rooms, where participants tend to be active investors and where emotion is never quite as tempered as it is in other environments.</p>
        <p>On America Online, where chat room convention usually dictates a cheery tone, yesterday afternoon it had turned decidedly somber. Investors kept one another up to date on what analysts were saying on CNBC. (''Shoot the jerks on CNBC,'' one said, ''nothing but bears, one after another.'') A typical exchange went like this:</p>
        <p>ROWNAROWNA: -- Hiya Cohen --- how are you doing?</p>
        <p>CohenInvGr: -- Not good. Bleeding.</p>
        <p>ROWNAROWNA: -- We all are.</p>
        <p>Fozziebare, the screen name of another regular in the America Online investor forums, complained, ''can no longer afford my AOL subscription.''</p>
        <p>David Gardner, co-founder of the Motley Fool, one of the oldest investment sites in cyberspace, said that among the most popular discussion groups on the site yesterday was one titled Living Below Your Means. Another was the Communion of Bears.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gardner said of regulars in the bear forum: ''In the past what characterized that conversation is they had to team up together because they were so marginalized. Now they're just calling for blood.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, sympathy for the market losers did not run deep on several popular message boards yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I have told you people for some time now Dell is going to the dogs!'' a participant known as FantomBoy wrote in a discussion group about Dell Computer. ''Dell lost all its recent gains, and you folks call Dell bullett proof! BAWHAHAHAHAH.''</p>
        <p>Dell's stock, which had held out until yesterday, suffered a 16 percent decline. The rout for technology stocks was particularly hard felt by on-line investors who had remained optimistic amid the market tumult of recent weeks.</p>
        <p>''If this isn't a free fall for for the markets, and Dell, then I don't know what a free fall is,'' wrote Stock Bull, a previously bullish investor. ''Wish I had a parachute on.''</p>
        <p>David Zgodzinski, who writes a column for the SiliconInvestor Web site based on what people are saying in the discussion forums said on-line investors had been harder hit because they typically owned stocks in individual companies, rather than in mutual funds. ''In general, the reaction is shock,'' Mr. Zgodzinski said. ''These people are more enthusiastic and more tuned in, and they're feeling the loss more personally. The man on the street hasn't had the perception of how bad the drop has already been.''</p>
        <p>One participant in a SiliconInvestor forum called the Big Kahuna drew on the immortal words of Dr. McCoy of ''Star Trek'' to convey his feelings: ''They're dead Jim, they're all dead. Japan, Russia and now China and Hong Kong. ANY BUYERS OUT THERE??''</p>
        <p>A relatively new investor on a Yahoo discussion group wrote: ''Gotta love this investment language. I figured I'd need to learn about Fibonacci sequences and 10-K's. Instead, I end up with catching falling knives and dead cat bounces.''</p>
        <p>Still, the cybergloom cleared occasionally yesterday as investors reassured one another that this was a buying opportunity and that they were in it for the long haul. The Motley Fool's ''post of the day'' was an impassioned exhortation from a Dell investor to look on the bright side:</p>
        <p>Subject: Self Fulfilling Prophecy</p>
        <p>Author: rj610w</p>
        <p>With all due respects to those on this board who are so far above me that I can't see the light of the sun coming over their heads, let me sound a note of concern. I am concerned that the bottom doesn't have to fall out from under us less we beat ourselves into believing it's coming and stampede in fear. Once the panic starts, we will have no one to blame but ourselves. I think a lot of our future is in our own hands and how it turns out is up to us. A little more encouragement and a little less scare talk may serve everyone better.''</p>
        <p>THE MARKET TURMOIL: INVESTORS ON LINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
