<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Queens Rivals to Meet Again in Primary for Assembly</title>
    <meta content="01ROCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cummings, Pauline R (Assemblywoman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Evan D (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6D6143FF932A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Queens Rivals to Meet Again in Primary for Assembly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic primary contest for 31st Assembly District in Queens is between Assemblywoman Pauline R Cummings and Rev Evan D Gray, whom she defeated in special election for Assembly seat five months ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Pauline R. Cummings was selected by Queens Democratic Party leaders as their candidate in a special election for an Assembly seat five months ago, she was backed by the party's elected officials in that borough.</p>
        <p>Despite that support, her victory in the race -- to fill the Assembly seat vacated when Gregory W. Meeks was elected to Congress -- was a surprisingly slender one. Only 211 votes separated her from her closest rival in a four-person race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Pauline R. Cummings was selected by Queens Democratic Party leaders as their candidate in a special election for an Assembly seat five months ago, she was backed by the party's elected officials in that borough.</p>
        <p>Despite that support, her victory in the race -- to fill the Assembly seat vacated when Gregory W. Meeks was elected to Congress -- was a surprisingly slender one. Only 211 votes separated her from her closest rival in a four-person race.</p>
        <p>Now, in an eagerly watched contest in the Democratic primary, Ms. Cummings is running against the man who came close to snatching that victory.</p>
        <p>In part, the primary will be a test of the might of the Queens Democratic organization that has officially embraced her. But it is also being watched because it has the potential of illustrating the continued vitality of the black church in the local political process.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cummings's opponent is the Rev. Evan D. Gray, a 29-year-old Baptist minister who is the pastor of a church in Far Rockaway. Mr. Gray showed his electoral strength in the special election not only by drawing nearly as many votes as Ms. Cummings, but also by doing so as a candidate on the Liberal Party line in the overwhelmingly Democratic 31st Assembly District, which includes the neighborhoods of South Ozone Park, Richmond Hill, Springfield Gardens and, across Jamaica Bay, Far Rockaway, which accounts for the bulk of the district's voters.</p>
        <p>Once again, Ms. Cummings, 53, has the support of the Queens Democratic organization and its chairman, Representative Thomas J. Manton,  as well as the City Comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi, and her predecessor in the Assembly, Mr. Meeks.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gray is not without support himself. He is the pastor of the Macedonia Baptist Church, which has a congregation of more than 500, an overwhelming number of whom live within the Assembly district. He has also been endorsed by the Rev. Al Sharpton and one or two union locals. Moreover, Mr. Gray has been the beneficiary of support, all given surreptitiously, from a few Queens politicians who do not want their assistance to become public.</p>
        <p>Although both candidates have had several years of involvement in civic and community organizations in the Far Rockaway section of the 31st Assembly District, they are both new to politics.</p>
        <p>A bookkeeper in the Manhattan garment district for nearly 30 years, Ms. Cummings has also been the chairwoman of the economic development committee of her local community board. Her principal political benefactor is City Councilwoman Juanita E. Watkins, who approached  Ms. Cummings about running for the Assembly seat.</p>
        <p>When asked to discuss the issues she considered most important, Ms. Cummings cited education and economic development. Her goal, she said, is to meet with city and state education officials ''to see how we can best elevate the level of schooling.''</p>
        <p>Her five months in Albany, Ms. Cummings said, have been active ones in which she was a co-sponsor of two bills. ''I spend a lot of my time talking with my constituents,'' she said. ''I listen to their needs, so that when I get back to Albany, I will know what they want me to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray started a civic association in the Arverne section of the Rockaway peninsula and is on the board of a local hospital. Through his church, Mr. Gray has developed a number of programs, some for young people and others for low-income residents.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Cummings speaks of the district's needs in broad brush strokes, Mr. Gray examines them with an eye toward details. Driving through the district in his black Grand Marquis on a recent morning, Mr. Gray pointed to everything, from the need to repair a bulkhead along a section of Jamaica Bay to controlling the mosquito population to installing drainage systems in some streets in the district.</p>
        <p>It is not that Ms. Cummings is ineffective, he suggests, but merely that he would be more diligent.</p>
        <p>''To be honest, I don't have anything negative to say about her,'' Mr. Gray said. ''I just think I'm better for the job because I am a community leader.''</p>
        <p>His major campaign theme has been the need for jobs in a district where the unemployment level is higher than the city's average.</p>
        <p>''I want to sit down with major corporations and entice them to do business in the 31st Assembly District,'' Mr. Gray said. ''We have a lot of vacant land for companies to use for their businesses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray uses as his model the campaigns of the Rev. Floyd H. Flake, whose resignation from Congress last year opened the way for Mr. Meeks's campaign for the Congressional seat. ''We don't have the support of the Democratic organization,'' he said, ''but we'll have the support of the people of the district.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray's predictions have not been widely shared by Queens Democratic politicians, who say that the party's support, coupled with the active involvement of several large unions, will make Ms. Cummings the more formidable candidate.</p>
        <p>''He's popular and he's been active and he's a lifelong resident of the peninsula,'' said Mr. Meeks, who represented the district in the Assembly for five years and is endorsing Ms. Cummings. ''He's not someone to be sneezed at.</p>
        <p>''For that reason,'' he added, ''Pauline must work hard. But she has shown in a short time that she does have the people's concerns at heart. That needs to be rewarded with her re-election. In the meantime, it will be an active campaign in this district.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
