<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THEATER GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="04THEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/04/arts/theater/04THEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1477886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1DB1638F937A35757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="4355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THEATER GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Theater Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend. Approximate running times are in parentheses. * denotes a highly recommended show.  + means discounted tickets were at the Theater Development Fund's TKTS booth for performances last Friday and Saturday nights.  ++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for performances last Saturday night only.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>*+ ''TAKE ME OUT.'' Playing a socially challenged money manager named Mason Marzac, Denis O'Hare shines with the gloom-dispelling wattage that comes when a first-rate actor meets a role he was born to play. When Mason talks about baseball (yes, baseball) in Richard Greenberg's comic drama, directed with verve by Joe Mantello, the show emanates the dewy, delirious passion of a ''Bohème'' for the ESPN set. This story of pride and prejudice in professional sports, seen at the Public Theater last fall, has been advantageously shaved and streamlined for its Broadway incarnation. But in tracing the impact of a godlike baseball player (the perfectly cast Daniel Sunjata) who declares his homosexuality, Mr. Greenberg winds up sacrificing fully developed characters and plotting to Ideas with a capital I. Those notorious shower scenes remain, just so you know. But it's Mr. Greenberg's infatuation with baseball that makes this a show to cheer about (2:45). Kerr, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $66 to $81 (Ben Brantley).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend. Approximate running times are in parentheses. * denotes a highly recommended show.  + means discounted tickets were at the Theater Development Fund's TKTS booth for performances last Friday and Saturday nights.  ++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for performances last Saturday night only.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>*+ ''TAKE ME OUT.'' Playing a socially challenged money manager named Mason Marzac, Denis O'Hare shines with the gloom-dispelling wattage that comes when a first-rate actor meets a role he was born to play. When Mason talks about baseball (yes, baseball) in Richard Greenberg's comic drama, directed with verve by Joe Mantello, the show emanates the dewy, delirious passion of a ''Bohème'' for the ESPN set. This story of pride and prejudice in professional sports, seen at the Public Theater last fall, has been advantageously shaved and streamlined for its Broadway incarnation. But in tracing the impact of a godlike baseball player (the perfectly cast Daniel Sunjata) who declares his homosexuality, Mr. Greenberg winds up sacrificing fully developed characters and plotting to Ideas with a capital I. Those notorious shower scenes remain, just so you know. But it's Mr. Greenberg's infatuation with baseball that makes this a show to cheer about (2:45). Kerr, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $66 to $81 (Ben Brantley).</p>
        <p>+ ''URBAN COWBOY: THE MUSICAL.'' A conclusive demonstration that it's possible to be vulgar and bland at the same time. Based on the 1980 movie and set largely in an oversexed Texas honky-tonk, ''Urban Cowboy'' suggests ''Cabaret'' by way of Branson, Mo. Featuring a rote book by Aaron Latham and Phillip Oesterman and a patchwork of new and recycled country-and-western songs, the show exudes the mechanical air of something dutifully assembled according to a low and specific assessment of audience expectations. The songs are delivered in a shiny, anonymous twang. And as directed by Lonny Price, the young, bottom-twitching ensemble members, attractive in a ''Baywatch'' sort of way, have little in the way of personalities to call their own (2:25). Broadhurst, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. Mondays, Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m. Tickets: $66.25 to $96.26 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* ''AVENUE Q.'' The inspired brainchild of the songwriters Robert Lopez and Jeff Marx, this canny toy chest of a musical takes its stylistic cues from ''Sesame Street,'' from its cheery urban set to its singing puppets of assorted colors and dispositions. And in doing so it becomes the first mainstream musical since ''Rent'' to coo with such seductive directness to theatergoers on the fair side of 40 in their own language, in which irony is less a mind-set than a loosely worn style. Directed by Jason Moore, with a book by Jeff Whitty, the show applies the coaxing, learning-is-fun attitude of children's educational television to the R-rated situations of post-collegiate life in the big city. Featuring a pitch-perfect ensemble of live performers and oversize hand puppets, ''Avenue Q'' is to ''Sesame Street'' what Mel Brooks's ''Producers'' is to vintage Broadway musicals, a connoisseur's tribute to what it only seems to send up (2:00). Vineyard, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 8 p.m. Tickets: $20 to $55 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>*+ ''DIRTY STORY.'' At first glance they're just another crazy, codependent couple, part of a theatrical tradition that stretches from Strindberg to Edward Albee and beyond. He puts her down; she begs for more. He ties her to a ladder; she learns how to humiliate him. But spend some more time with Brutus (David Deblinger) and Wanda (Florencia Lozano), the sadomasochistic lovers in John Patrick Shanley's appallingly entertaining play, and you'll start to realize that the politics shaping their relationship aren't merely sexual. Mr. Shanley, a specialist in the combat zone where love and hate blur (''Psychopathia Sexualis,'' the screenplay for ''Moonstruck''), has expanded his focus from the intimate to the international. And this broadening of perspective has led him to create a bold and -- against the odds -- very funny study of the rocky relationship known as the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. Chris McGarry and Michael Puzzo round out the lively ensemble (2:00). Harold Clurman Theater, 412 West 42nd Street, (212) 279-4200. Tuesdays through Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 7 p.m. Tickets: $45 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* ''THE LAST SUNDAY IN JUNE.'' Gay men gather in an apartment on Christopher Street and discuss the exigencies of gay life; the banter is quick, arch and complete with persistent sexual innuendo, references to opera and the lingering shadow of AIDS. This is the obvious convention at work in Jonathan Tolins's new play. And it might be tiresome if convention itself weren't the object of Mr. Tolins's savvy scrutiny. The subject is the function of the gay community at a time when gay rights is no longer a revolutionary idea. And the questions that underlie the gathering are about things like whether gay men are better off among themselves or living in the wider world and whether defining oneself by one's sexual orientation is healthy and fulfilling. In fact, throughout this timely and very funny play, the self-awareness of the characters is eclipsed only by that of the playwright. Mr. Tolins succeeds smartly at his intention here, which is to express impatience with the staler elements of gay dramatic literature and to push the ''gay play'' forward into its next generation of concerns (1:40). Century Center, 111 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays through Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 4 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $55. (Bruce Weber).</p>
        <p>''POLISH JOKE.'' Heritage may be fate, as David Ives's new comedy seemingly contends. It may be true that you can't escape your roots, no matter who you are. Or maybe that's the joke of the title, that it's only the Poles who, trapped forever by their Polishness, remain ineluctably who they are born. But whichever is meant by Mr. Ives, the argument he makes here is threadbare. The play, with its farcical elements directed with bravado by John Rando, does have its intermittent moments of insight and genuine comedy. And the ensemble is accomplished. But beneath the striven-for ditzy hilarity on the play's surface is a sophomoric, autobiographical earnestness (2:05). Manhattan Theater Club, Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. Tuesdays through Fridays at 7:30; Saturdays at 3 and 7:30 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $45; a limited number of $20 student tickets available at box office up to one hour before the show (Weber).</p>
        <p>*+ ''ZANNA, DON'T!'' Bubble gum rock? Now? Well, why not? Happily oblivious to everything else happening in the world, this chirpy new musical has a pop score that aims to be nothing but catchy and a message that says nothing but that people should love each other. The well-constructed book, candy-flavored melodies and especially deft lyrics are by Tim Acito, and it all feels like the work of a young man who is rather gracefully avenging a tortured adolescence. Set in a high school roiling with hormones, the show wants you to think of ''Grease,'' but with a difference. This is a world in which homosexuality is the norm and heterosexual love is the kind that dare not speak its name. It is gleefully gay in spirit, but Mr. Acito is a cagey enough writer to concoct a plot that invites heterosexuals into the world of the show. And its young, entirely winning ensemble helps give it a matchless appeal as a Saturday night date (1:40). Houseman, 450 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays through Fridays at 8 p.m. Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $65 (Weber).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>*++ ''THE BLACKS: A CLOWN SHOW.'' A cacophonous revival of Jean Genet's strident, maddening riff on race and theater art from 1959 that enhances the reputation for dauntlessness of the four-year-old Classical Theater of Harlem. The play posits a story in which a white woman has been murdered, and a company of black actors is re-enacting the crime before a mock court of other black actors costumed as white aristocrats. Acknowledging the audience, the actors flip in and out of character, confronting racial stereotypes, expressing the fury of black-white relations. There are myriad implications: that faces are masks; that race is an artificial distinction; that the difference between how we look and who we are is played out equally on the stage and in the world. The production, which turns the play into a literal circus, is not always coherent. But its energy and its willingness to set the theatergoer's teeth on edge leave the actors exhausted at the end and the audience battered and unsettled, signs that it has, in no small measure, succeeded (2:00). The East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 206-1515. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $35, with a limited number of $20 student rush tickets available at the box office on the day of the performance (Weber).</p>
        <p>+ ''DUBLIN CAROL.'' Conor McPherson's brooding play, set in an undertaker's office on Christmas Eve, capitalizes on that long, lovely and painful tradition in Irish literature of tales told by drinkers, squinting through the murk of the morning after. And make no mistake, the state of coming off a bender is as much existential as physical in this impeccably acted production, directed by Mr. McPherson. For John, the aging undertaker's assistant played by Jim Norton, a hangover becomes the emblem of the bad faith that has infused an entire lifetime. In bald summary, the play -- in which John is confronted by the daughter (Kerry O'Malley) he abandoned years ago -- sounds bleakly familiar. But leave it to Mr. McPherson to find fresh wellsprings of pain within this musty context, subverting expectations throughout (1:20). Atlantic Theater Company, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200). Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 and 8 p.m. Tickets: $50; a limited number of $10 student rush tickets available at box office until 7:30 p.m. on day of show (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* ''FIFTH OF JULY.'' A beckoning warmth radiates from this revival of Lanford Wilson's gentle comic drama from 1978. With a first-rate, finely tuned ensemble that includes Michael Cerveris Parker Posey, the production glows with that rare feeling of performers who seem to respect and -- get this -- actually like one another as much as they do their own juicy parts. This attitude reflects the benevolent spirit that shapes ''Fifth of July,'' in which a group of burned-out radicals from the 1960's are reunited in an orgy of self-examination. The play may question that decade's gospels of love and transformation, but it does so with the even-handed empathy that is Mr. Wilson's hallmark. Even when it sounds like an especially well-honed sitcom -- and it can -- this ''Fifth of July,'' directed by Jo Bonney, is remarkable for the care and consistency of its acting throughout and its refusal to let one performance overshadow others (2:15). Signature Theater Company at the Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, (212) 244-7529. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $55 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* +''KIMBERLY AKIMBO.'' Marylouise Burke, who has seen six decades come and go, is turning in the freshest, most enchanting portrait of a 16-year-old since Molly Ringwald seduced America in ''Sixteen Candles'' in 1984. And in an unusual instance of just desserts, the ingénue of the year is appearing in what promises to be the comedy of the year, David Lindsay-Abaire's haunting and hilarious new play. In considering the plight of a girl afflicted with a disease that ages her at four and a half times the usual rate, Mr. Lindsay-Abaire has taken on the weighty and weary subject of the stark brevity of life. But there's nothing weary about ''Kimberly Akimbo,'' directed by David Petrarca. The play is at once a shrewd satire, a black comedy and a heartbreaking study of how time wounds everyone (2:20). Manhattan Theater Club, City Center, Stage 1, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212). Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2:30 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $60 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>+ ''MA RAINEY'S BLACK BOTTOM.'' It's the music, of all things, that's so conspicuously missing from this hollow revival of August Wilson's landmark play from 1984 about a blues recording session in jazz-age Chicago. Oh, sure, an assortment of peppery period songs still figure in the show, which stars Charles S. Dutton, in the part he originated 19 years ago, and Whoopi Goldberg as the earthy, imperious singer of the title. What you rarely hear, though, is the enthralling music of words that makes Mr. Wilson one of the few certifiably great dramatists working today. The innate tragic grandeur and gritty, stinging humor of this story of racial exploitation and musicians at loggerheads can be discerned only in fitful flashes. And neither Ms. Goldberg nor Mr. Dutton seems to believe unconditionally in the characters. Despite an amiable ensemble, this ''Ma Rainey,'' directed by Marion McClinton, rarely gets past the level of an orchestra still tentatively tuning up (2:45). Royale, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $51.25 to $81.25; limited number of $21.25 rush tickets available at box office on day of show (Brantley).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
