<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Quartets, One With a Boundary, One With None</title>
    <meta content="04YING$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/04/arts/music/04YING.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1477878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ying Quartet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mendelsohn Quartet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Midgette, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Ying Quartet</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Symphony Space</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDC1638F937A35757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Quartets, One With a Boundary, One With None</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Quartets, One With a Boundary, One With None</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Midgette reviews recitals by Ying Quartet and Mendelsohn Quartet (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>String instruments are often said to sing. The implied comparison of instrument and voice was made tangible at two string quartet recitals last weekend, both featuring a male singer.</p>
        <p>One recital deliberately sought to open up the traditional recital format. Called ''No Boundaries,'' the Ying Quartet's residency at the black-box Thalia in Symphony Space has brought in both dance and text, so it was hardly a stretch when last Friday night's program included both songs and a stint as M.C. by the composer Ned Rorem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The implied comparison of instrument and voice was made tangible at two string quartet recitals last weekend, both featuring a male singer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>String instruments are often said to sing. The implied comparison of instrument and voice was made tangible at two string quartet recitals last weekend, both featuring a male singer.</p>
        <p>One recital deliberately sought to open up the traditional recital format. Called ''No Boundaries,'' the Ying Quartet's residency at the black-box Thalia in Symphony Space has brought in both dance and text, so it was hardly a stretch when last Friday night's program included both songs and a stint as M.C. by the composer Ned Rorem.</p>
        <p>The other recital was more high church: on Saturday the Mendelssohn Quartet concluded its own residency, at the 92nd Street Y, with an all-Beethoven program. Between two late quartets, Opuses 130 and 135, Sanford Sylvan, the baritone, and Diane Walsh, the pianist, performed the song cycle ''An die Ferne Geliebte.''</p>
        <p>Bringing song into a tribute to Mr. Rorem is a natural move since the composer, 79, is a celebrated vocal writer. And song fit neatly into the four Ying siblings' deft program, which described a loose biographical arc: from a large-grained, generous reading of Ravel's string quartet (a nod to Mr. Rorem's French influence) through vocal music from the 1940's (including ''Mourning Scene'' for tenor and quartet) to the New York premiere of Mr. Rorem's fifth quartet, ''United States,'' which the Yings commissioned.</p>
        <p>A set of songs for voice and piano -- six Paul Goodman poems and an encore -- sounded great in spite of the dry, reined-in singing of the tenor, Scott Murphree. They also provided a key to ''United States,'' which, in seven short movements with programmatic titles, comes off not unlike a song cycle itself.</p>
        <p>For all its variety, however, it is a unified piece, moving, a little tongue-in-cheek, from ''A Beginning'' (in questioning, two-note phrases) to ''An Ending'' of long, elegiac arcs, with a range of observations in between. And it's a nice piece: thoughtful, skillful and engaging in the way that often makes people dismiss Mr. Rorem as a light composer. The fact is that he doesn't seek to break boundaries; but he works with quiet mastery within them.</p>
        <p>If the singer on the Rorem program gave a perspective on the vocalism of the music, Mr. Sylvan demonstrated in Saturday's Beethoven program how to make chamber music with the voice. Mr. Sylvan is a rare vocal artist able to use his voice like an instrument, blending word and note into a unified and exact musical expression; and Ms. Walsh's big playing met him phrase for phrase. One wished they would do the whole thing again as soon as they had finished.</p>
        <p>And the Mendelssohn Quartet could be said to sing indeed. Led by the sunny warm tone of Miriam Fried, the first violin, they played with a refinement that sometimes created great effect in poignant understatement. Not that they weren't ready to go out on a limb. The Grosse Fuge, the conclusion of Op. 130, was an all-out, heedless, hair-raising ride, which then pulled up into a conclusion so resoundingly right you could only call it transcendent.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
