<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art in Review</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="857686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, ROBERTA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HIMMEL, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1D81739F937A25755C0A960958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, ROBERTA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Paul Himmel and the Brodovitch Circle' Howard Greenberg Gallery 120 Wooster Street, SoHo Through June 22</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Paul Himmel and the Brodovitch Circle' Howard Greenberg Gallery 120 Wooster Street, SoHo Through June 22</p>
        <p>This mini-retrospective surveys the noncommercial work of Paul Himmel, a prominent fashion photographer in the 1940's and 50's who went on to become a psychotherapist. As with other young photographers who emerged in New York after World War II, Mr. Himmel was inspired by the photographer and designer Alexey Brodovitch. A man of many influential talents, Brodovitch was art director of Harper's Bazaar from 1934 to 1958, founded the legendary Design Laboratory at the New School for Social Research in 1941, and in 1945 published a book of ballet photographs, widely admired for dramatic, motion-filled images that gave  the blur new credibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Himmel's works are given context by a small display that includes images  by many photographers who either worked for Harper's Bazaar or passed through the Design Laboratory, among them, Mr. Himmel himself, Lillian Bassman, Robert Frank, Louis Faurer and Bruce Davidson. A lively selection, it reflects some of  Brodovitch's influence on fashion and street photography alike and includes three images from his book.</p>
        <p>The photographs in Mr. Himmel's show date from 1947 to 1963 and indicate that he had his own talent for capturing the drama of human movement in a way that the eye cannot. In this show, the images of ballet dancers, Kabuki dancers  and especially circus performers remain the most impressive. Trapeze artists and tightrope walkers in action become beautiful blurs. Jugglers and acrobats perform their own kind of sky writing. A rope twirler is surrounded by a fluttering translucent shape that suggests a big jellyfish.</p>
        <p>In a duet from George Balanchine's "Swan Lake," a ballerina moves into her partner's arms on point, followed by a series of crisp after-images that would have done Muybridge or Edgerton proud. In three quintessential New York scenes,  Mr. Himmel photographed Grand Central Terminal at rush hour, taking care to plant a nonmoving "alone in the crowd" friend among the blurry figures.</p>
        <p>In other images, Mr. Himmel experimented with photography's physical possibilities, with often elegant if sometimes vacuous results. He photographed  nude models using scrims and grainy film, giving their hazy silhouettes a Cycladic abbreviation. He also developed black-and-white negatives of models' faces on colored paper, solarizing them with colored light to create dramatic two-toned images. In one, the distorted features of a large female face in green and yellow bring to mind some of Picasso's portraits of Jacqueline Roque, while  the saturated color is reminiscent of Warhol.</p>
        <p>A Cubist effect is achieved by photographing an existing photograph created in this manner through plastic blocks. Many of these images would be accepted as regular fashion photography today, which reflects Mr. Himmel's prescience, but also a slickness and a preoccupation with conventional notions of female beauty that curtails their possibilities as art.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
