<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boeing Chairman Offers 'Exuberance and Dynamism'</title>
    <meta content="16PHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE AEROSPACE MERGER: THE LEADER" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="895983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE AEROSPACE MERGER: THE LEADER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aerospace Industries and Sciences</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcdonnell Douglas Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rockwell International Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Condit, Philip</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DC103EF935A25751C1A960958260" item-length="572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boeing Chairman Offers 'Exuberance and Dynamism'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philip M Condit, president and chief executive of Boeing Co, is known inside and outside company for his exuberance, energy and willingness to make big decisions; Boeing's $13.3 billion acquisition of McDonnell Douglas Corp comes just months after its $3.2 billion purchase of Rockwell International Corp's military and space division (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As he announced the Boeing Company's plan to acquire its longtime rival, the McDonnell Douglas Corporation, Philip M. Condit, Boeing's president and chief executive, departed from his prepared statement yesterday with a word that spoke volumes: ''Wow!''</p>
        <p>The seventh man to lead Boeing in its 80 years, Mr. Condit is known inside and outside the company for his exuberance, energy and a willingness to make big decisions. Acquisitions are rare for Boeing, but since being named chief executive in April, Mr. Condit has made two that will transform the company: the purchase of the Rockwell International Corporation's military and space division for $3.2 billion, announced Aug. 1, and the $13.3 billion deal for McDonnell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As he announced the Boeing Company's plan to acquire its longtime rival, the McDonnell Douglas Corporation, Philip M. Condit, Boeing's president and chief executive, departed from his prepared statement yesterday with a word that spoke volumes: ''Wow!''</p>
        <p>The seventh man to lead Boeing in its 80 years, Mr. Condit is known inside and outside the company for his exuberance, energy and a willingness to make big decisions. Acquisitions are rare for Boeing, but since being named chief executive in April, Mr. Condit has made two that will transform the company: the purchase of the Rockwell International Corporation's military and space division for $3.2 billion, announced Aug. 1, and the $13.3 billion deal for McDonnell.</p>
        <p>''In two bold steps, he's gone from running a cyclical broad-based airplane company to a broad-based and dynamic aerospace company,'' Howard Rubel, an analyst with Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, said of Mr. Condit. ''I think Phil represents a hint of the shape Boeing needs to have, a combination of exuberance and dynamism.''</p>
        <p>Before these deals, space and military work accounted for about 25 percent of Boeing's revenues, Mr. Rubel estimated.</p>
        <p>The McDonnell and Rockwell deals are likely to help Mr. Condit reach his goal of smoothing out Boeing's cycle of booms and busts. With record orders for its commercial aircraft, Boeing is adding more than 1,000 employees a month and is advertising nationwide for more. But in Mr. Condit's 31 years with Boeing, he has also seen severe layoffs that accompanied each downturn in the worldwide airline industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Condit, who is 54, came to the president's office after having been an executive vice president and general manager of the Boeing Commercial Airplane Group's 777 division, where he had primary responsibility for developing the company's newest commercial jet. Mr. Condit is the first chief executive of Boeing to have come up through the ranks on the commercial side rather than the military side of the business.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that his background helps explain Mr. Condit's drive to bring Boeing closer to its customers, to the extent of giving United Airlines and other major carriers early input in the design of the 777. Mr. Condit also played a big role in making Boeing more competitive and cost-conscious, analysts say.</p>
        <p>''He really has been the point man in the whole process of bringing the company into the cruel world of today, where it's cost, cost and efficiency, rather than 'these are airplanes, and airplanes are different,' '' said Wolfgang Demisch, an analyst with BT Securities. ''The old Boeing would never have gone to learn from Toyota, but Phil Condit did.''</p>
        <p>Born and raised near San Francisco, Mr. Condit obtained his pilot's license at 18. He graduated from the University of California at Berkeley with a degree in mechanical engineering in 1963 and two years later earned his master's degree in aeronautical engineering from Princeton University. In 1965, he joined Boeing as an aerodynamics engineer on the supersonic transport project.</p>
        <p>''Through the 757, the 767, the 777, he was always in the thick of it,'' Mr. Rubel said. ''There's a wellspring of talent at Boeing, but from years ago, you could have predicted Phil would be the one to run the show.''</p>
        <p>THE AEROSPACE MERGER: THE LEADER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
