<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Miller Gone, Brooklynites Brawl for Power</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="496994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TABOR, MARY B W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D8153EF93AA15751C1A967958260" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Miller Gone, Brooklynites Brawl for Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY B. W. TABOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TABOR, MARY B W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Mel Miller was stripped of his Assembly seat after being convicted of fraud charges, Brooklyn lost both its decades-long hold on the Speaker's post and a political leader whose brash personality and political acumen had been the threads holding together the borough's disparate Democratic factions.</p>
        <p>Now, with important local issues like reapportionment coming up, Brooklyn is wondering whether those groups will be able to pull together without Mr. Miller at a time when demographic changes are splintering the county's old political alliances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Mel Miller was stripped of his Assembly seat after being convicted of fraud charges, Brooklyn lost both its decades-long hold on the Speaker's post and a political leader whose brash personality and political acumen had been the threads holding together the borough's disparate Democratic factions.</p>
        <p>Now, with important local issues like reapportionment coming up, Brooklyn is wondering whether those groups will be able to pull together without Mr. Miller at a time when demographic changes are splintering the county's old political alliances.</p>
        <p>"Brooklyn is now going through a political reformation," said Edward Griffith, a Democrat from East New York and Brooklyn's senior Assemblyman. "With Mel Miller's descent from the No. 2 position in the state, it necessarily follows that someone must assume a very strong, responsible leadership position in Brooklyn. Right now, there is no force as such." End of a Tradition</p>
        <p>The leadership void has already cost the borough the speakership, a post held by a Brooklynite since 1913 with one brief interruption.</p>
        <p>Though Brooklyn's 19-member Assembly delegation is the largest of the city's five boroughs, it offered no natural successor to Mr. Miller. Future hopefuls for the job, like three-term Assemblyman Anthony J. Genovesi, who represents the 39th Assembly District in Canarsie, did not have enough seniority among their legislative colleagues for the post.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Miller, who had expected to be acquitted of Federal charges that he cheated legal clients out of real-estate profits, had not prepared an heir. That left the door open for the Queens delegation, which ushered in its own Assemblyman, Saul Weprin.</p>
        <p>Now, finding a new leader for Brooklyn with Mr. Miller's political horsepower will take time, legislators and political analysts say.</p>
        <p>Democratic leaders say they believe that Clarence Norman Jr., an Assemblyman from the 43d A.D. in Crown Heights and current Brooklyn Democratic leader, is likely to see his influence grow. But in a recent interview, Mr. Miller said that Mr. Norman has yet to take full advantage of his post as county leader. Political Powers</p>
        <p>Borough President Howard Golden, who was forced to choose between the borough presidency and the party leadership when the City Charter was revised in 1989, is the only boroughwide elected city official and, as a result, may wield some additional power.</p>
        <p>Other prominent Brooklynites, including Charles J. Hynes, the Brooklyn District Attorney, and Elizabeth Holtzman, the City Comptroller, could take on bigger leadership roles, says Edward T. Rogowsky, professor of urban studies at Brooklyn College and co-author of "Changing New York City Politics," (Routledge, Chapman &amp; Hall, 1991). But because neither has been closely tied to the Brooklyn Democratic organization, their ascension may not benefit the party itself.</p>
        <p>For now, Brooklyn's Democrats will have to pull together on their own in order to retain their influence, say members of the Assembly delegation.</p>
        <p>"We no longer have one of our own to look after Brooklyn," Mr. Norman said. "When the speaker is from your home county, you know you are going to get a little extra push. Now we, as a delegation, are going to have to work even closer together."</p>
        <p>Since 1980, Brooklyn, which is home to 2.3 million people, has seen its minority population increase by 30 percent to 1.5 million. Many of the newer arrivals have formed their own political organizations. Splintered Alliances</p>
        <p>Traditional Democratic factions in the borough, once divided among three or four local political groups, have splintered as well, leaving a dozen more vaguely defined forces -- both racial and ideological -- that align and realign themselves intermittently with each other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Genovesi's Thomas Jefferson Democratic Club, for example, has often allied itself with Assemblyman Vito J. Lopez's club in Bushwick and Mr. Miller's club, the Independent Democrats of Flatbush.</p>
        <p>Challengers to those Democrats have included Mr. Golden, who counts Councilman Kenneth K. Fisher and Representatives Edolphus Towns and Stephen J. Solarz as his political friends. Representative Major R. Owens has his own supporters, including Assemblymen Albert Vann and Roger L. Green. Yet another camp includes Councilwoman Mary Pinkett, Councilman Enoch H. Williams and Mr. Griffith, the Assemblyman.</p>
        <p>The next big test of leadership for Brooklyn Democrats will be their ability to influence the redrawing of legislative and Congressional district lines, the control of which now goes to Mr. Weprin.</p>
        <p>That means two of the borough's Democratic congressmen, Mr. Solarz and Charles E. Schumer, who had depended on Mr. Miller to keep their Congressional districts intact, may see their districts merged into one in 1992. Brooklyn's assemblymembers may see their districts reshaped to their disadvantage. Battle for Seat</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, candidates have begun lining up for -- and dropping out of -- the special election to succeed Mr. Miller in the 44th Assembly seat, which includes parts of Flatbush, Midwood, Kensington and Park Slope. The election has been scheduled for Jan. 28 by Gov. Mario M. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller has endorsed Joni Yoswein, a 36-year-old district leader who worked as Mr. Miller's chief aide, making her the immediate favorite in most estimations. Mr. Miller described the endorsement as his political swan song.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, four candidates, including Ms. Yoswein, Alan Fleishman, a project analyst for Ms. Holtzman, Barbara Burger, deputy director of Ms. Holtzman's Citizens Action Center, and Jacob Gold, a co-leader of the 44th district, declared their candidacies for Mr. Miller's seat.</p>
        <p>Three days later, however, Mr. Miller telephoned Ms. Yoswein to say that Mr. Gold would no longer be running.</p>
        <p>"If he tries to run, I'll break his legs," Mr. Miller said jokingly in a telephone interview. "I'm going to crash, but I'm going to wait until she locks it up."</p>
        <p>In a telephone message, Mr. Gold said that he had decided not to run, but did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>That leaves Mr. Fleishman and Ms. Burger, who have said they will oppose Ms. Yoswein in her bid for the Democratic nomination. The winner of the general election will serve out Mr. Miller's term, which ends in December 1992, and face election for a full term in November.</p>
        <p>Whoever succeeds Mr. Miller on his home turf, the wider question of borough leadership remains open. "I think the next wave of leaders to come up from Brooklyn are not going to be Jewish and Italian," said Norman Adler, a Democratic political consultant. "They are going to be African-American and Latino. But in any case, it is going to take some time."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
