<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Right Man Faces a Hard Choice</title>
    <meta content="23RHOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Siena College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D71E39F930A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Right Man Faces a Hard Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>LOUDONVILLE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden, in Sports of The Times column, comments on St John's University's search for new basketball coach; cites Paul Hewitt of Siena College as possible good choice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HAD barely settled into the back seat of his taxi when Bill Race, eyeing his fare through a crooked rearview mirror asked, ''You from St. John's?''</p>
        <p>''No. Why?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HAD barely settled into the back seat of his taxi when Bill Race, eyeing his fare through a crooked rearview mirror asked, ''You from St. John's?''</p>
        <p>''No. Why?''</p>
        <p>Race shrugged his shoulders. ''St. John's wants to hire Paul Hewitt away from Siena,'' he said. ''I thought maybe you were coming up to talk with him.''</p>
        <p>He was half right. I was coming, somewhat unexpectedly and without invitation, not so much to speak with Hewitt, but to see him in this idyllic habitat of Siena College: nice quaint campus, smiles everywhere. Coach, campus community and cab driver were joined in a happy marriage.</p>
        <p>As his taxi rumbled along, Race sang the praises of Hewitt, the first-year coach who lifted Siena's sagging fortunes, following 8-19, 5-22 and 9-13 seasons.</p>
        <p>Hewitt, an assistant at Villanova, was hired and remade the team, got his players running and pressing. They finished 17-12 and reached the Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference title game for the first time ever.</p>
        <p>''This team last year had 'Loss' written on its face,'' Race said. ''This year, like night and day. We lost six games by 1 point.''</p>
        <p>Would he think any less of Hewitt if he took his family and left? Pause. ''No, not really,'' Race said. ''I'd hate to see him go, but you got to do what you got to do.''</p>
        <p>For the last two weeks that's exactly what Hewitt, and to a much greater degree St. John's, has been trying to figure out: what they have to do. Everything has been super-low-key. After the fiasco of Fran Fraschilla's departure, and with the New York news media practically staging parades in support of Fraschilla, St. John's is being circumspect.</p>
        <p>Until now, Hewitt had managed to avoid the city news media. Yesterday afternoon he sat in his office, courteous but firmly staying mum. On Thursday Ed Manetta, the St. John's athletic director, asked and received permission from Siena to speak to Hewitt. The two had a brief conversation and will probably meet sometime next week.</p>
        <p>''No comment,'' Hewitt said when asked about the meeting. ''You'll know something when I know something. Other than that, I really can't comment.'' There was small talk, and then he finally excused himself.</p>
        <p>Hewitt is the man for St. John's.</p>
        <p>St. John's should be Hewitt's new home. But the university may not be perceptive enough to see that, and the coach may be too comfortable to stretch. Life is good here.</p>
        <p>Hewitt and his wife, Dawnette, have two children and are expecting a third in September. They recently moved into new home in a cozy suburb. The fans love him and he loves them. This could be forever.</p>
        <p>Except that Hewitt, who turned 35 earlier this month, has sat on enough benches to know that nothing is forever. Everyone at Sienna, everyone in the community, is beginning to get over the feeling of gratitude. Fans are already talking about how good the Saints should be, not merely next season but for a few more seasons to come. Almost the entire team is coming back -- including Scott Knapp, the conference's freshman of the year, plus two sophomores who made the all-conference team.</p>
        <p>What happens if they don't get any better? A couple of injuries, this mishap or that, and suddenly you are gone. Tim Capstraw, the Wagner coach, was considered the leading candidate for the Siena job before Hewitt got it. Wagner stumbled last year to a mediocre record, and the sense now is that Capstraw's job may be on the line. Hot young coaches cool off.</p>
        <p>So far, there has been too much focus on X's and O's in this job search. The greatest thing that happened to St. John's basketball in the last 10 years took place last weekend, when Felipe Lopez, Tarik Turner and Zendon Hamilton crossed the stage in cap and gown, and received the degree. Some of the greatest players in recent St. John's history ran and jumped but never made that walk across the stage.</p>
        <p>The next group of St. John's stars -- Ron Artest, and two incoming freshmen, Eric Barkley and Antonio Glover -- pose a great challenge.</p>
        <p>Keeping this group in school, in check, for the next three seasons will be an awesome challenge, which, if met, could catapult St. John's back to national prominence. Hewitt, who was an assistant coach at four schools, most recently Villanova, is only a year removed from the recruiting wars, from the mindset of 19-year-olds who have many universities chasing them.</p>
        <p>St. John's faces a mighty test. For once, there are no wrong choices. But there is only one truly right choice. In light of the Fraschilla escapade, St. John's needs a presence like Hewitt's. Whether they'll hire him, whether he comes, is another matter. But they seem made for each other.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
