<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mush! Mush! The Eyes of Texas Are Upon Stars-Wings as Final 4 Begins</title>
    <meta content="23NHLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE STANLEY CUP PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Capitals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Red Wings</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Detroit Red Wings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D71E39F930A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mush! Mush! The Eyes of Texas Are Upon Stars-Wings as Final 4 Begins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preview of final four of Stanley Cup playoff series; Buffalo Sabres face Washington Capitals in East, and Detroit Red Wings face Dallas Stars in West (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mighty television, all-seeing and all-knowing, will be served. The Fox network, hoping to stop the melting of its hockey ratings with late-spring Sunday games of the Stanley Cup playoffs, will resume its coverage this weekend with the conference finals and will continue through mid-June, when the championship will finally be determinded.</p>
        <p>Now that the National Hockey League has delayed the conference finals long enough to ensure at least two Sunday exposures in this round, which matchup would Fox prefer?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mighty television, all-seeing and all-knowing, will be served. The Fox network, hoping to stop the melting of its hockey ratings with late-spring Sunday games of the Stanley Cup playoffs, will resume its coverage this weekend with the conference finals and will continue through mid-June, when the championship will finally be determinded.</p>
        <p>Now that the National Hockey League has delayed the conference finals long enough to ensure at least two Sunday exposures in this round, which matchup would Fox prefer?</p>
        <p>The Eastern final, between Buffalo and Washington, two mediocre teams whose good goaltending has helped them survive while better conference rivals have been upset, or the Western final, between Detroit and Dallas, the defending Stanley Cup champions against the regular-season champions?</p>
        <p>On Sunday and next Sunday, Fox will go west, for the Stars and the Red Wings. The Sabres and Capitals get started Saturday night in Washington on ESPN.</p>
        <p>Does this mean that the real Stanley Cup final is in the Western round? Quite possibly, yes, although the obvious superiority and appeal of the Stars and the Red Wings could work against the eventual Western winner and lead to an upset.</p>
        <p>Should the Capitals or Sabres win a short series, they could sit back to watch and wait while Detroit and Dallas wear each other out in a longer series. In theory, a tired and battered Western winner might let down in the championship round against a rested and overlooked underdog from the east.</p>
        <p>But the games are played on ice, not in theory. In the case of Dallas, that means mushy ice. With the longest season in team sports passing through Reunion Arena in late spring, the playing surface has been poor. It is hard to skate with speed and pass the puck with skill.</p>
        <p>''It's something we have gotten used to,'' said Mike Modano, the star center of the Stars. The puck moves well for the first half of periods, Modano said, and after that, ''You don't know where it's going to go.''</p>
        <p>The puck will move better Saturday night in M.C.I. Center, the new arena in downtown D.C. The problem might be getting it past either goalie. Dominik Hasek of Buffalo and Olaf Kolzig of Washington have been the best players on their respective teams in this tournament.</p>
        <p>Calle Johansson, a Washington defenseman, said of Kolzig, ''You know if you make a mistake, he's still back there with a chance to basically save your bacon.'' Kolzig, who wears a picture of Godzilla on his mask, was expected to serve in a backup role this season. But he won the job after the starter, Bill Ranford, was injured in the first game. A native of South Africa who plays for Germany in international competition, Kolzig grew up in Canada.</p>
        <p>He is less celebrated than Hasek, the Buffalo goalie who helped the Czech Republic to the Olympic gold medal and is once again a candidate for the Hart and Vezina trophies that go to the league's most valuable player and best goalie. In the first two rounds, Kolzig's statistics have been better than Hasek's, although such comparisons are specious because the goalies are facing different teams in different situations in different games.</p>
        <p>Still, the Capitals' Brian Bellows sees a positive message.</p>
        <p>''Our goaltender is playing as good or better than Hasek right now,'' Bellows said.</p>
        <p>A late arrival to Washington, the 33-year-old Bellows was hired off a Berlin team late in the season by George McPhee, the general manager. Also acquired late in the season was the veteran Esa Tikkanen, who often seems to show up on teams that reach at least the third round.</p>
        <p>With other veterans like Adam Oates, Dale Hunter and Joe Juneau, the Capitals would seem to have an advantage in experience over a young Sabres team. That does not bother Aleksei Zhitnik, the Buffalo defenseman who is one of the Sabres' most experienced and skilled players.</p>
        <p>''We were underdogs from the beginning,'' Zhitnik said.</p>
        <p>''Nobody expected us to get in the conference final. Both teams have great goaltenders right now. Both teams play defensive kind of hockey. Both teams got outshot in their last series. But we won, 4-0, and they won, 4-1.''</p>
        <p>In the West, Detroit has played more games than any team in the final four, needing six each to oust Phoenix and St. Louis. With Joe Nieuwendyk of the Stars out for the playoffs with a knee injury, the Wings have an edge at center. If Modano is not matched against Sergei Fedorov, he might face Steve Yzerman. On the wings, Detroit has the better sharpshooters. On defense, the Stars are bigger, and they block more shots. In goal, people still have lingering reservations about Ed Belfour of the Stars and Chris Osgood of the Wings. One of them will lead his team to the final round.</p>
        <p>THE STANLEY CUP PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
