<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Man Is Charged in Voodoo Burn Case</title>
    <meta content="23VOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voodoo</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Haitian-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Irvington (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierre-Pierre, Garry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valme, Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Degraff, Sheila</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Pierrot</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2DB1E39F930A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Man Is Charged in Voodoo Burn Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARRY PIERRE-PIERRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pierre-Pierre, Garry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jean Valme, 36, is second man to be charged in New Jersey with trying to kill Haitian immigrant during voodoo ceremony that left immigrant, Sheila DeGraff, 28, badly burned; last month, New Jersey authorities charged voodoo priest, Pierrot Charles, 41, with attempted murder, aggravated assault and possession of deadly weapon in incident; Irvington police say two men tried to kill DeGraff, but that motive remains unclear; Irvington is city with one of largest populations of Haitians in New Jersey (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A second man has been charged in New Jersey with trying to kill a Haitian immigrant during a voodoo ceremony that left the immigrant, a woman, badly burned, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The man, Jean Valme, 36, was arraigned on Wednesday on charges of attempted murder and conspiracy in Essex County Superior Court in Newark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A second man has been charged in New Jersey with trying to kill a Haitian immigrant during a voodoo ceremony that left the immigrant, a woman, badly burned, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The man, Jean Valme, 36, was arraigned on Wednesday on charges of attempted murder and conspiracy in Essex County Superior Court in Newark.</p>
        <p>Last month, New Jersey authorities also charged a voodoo priest, Pierrot Charles, 41, with attempted murder, aggravated assault and possession of a deadly weapon in the incident, which left the woman, Sheila DeGraff, 28, with second- and third-degree burns on her face, neck and body. Mr. Charles is out on bond.</p>
        <p>Irvington police officials said that the two men tried to kill Ms. DeGraff, but that the motive remained unclear.</p>
        <p>Ms. DeGraff, a registered nurse and a Haitian pop singer, has said that Mr. Valme, with whom she was romantically involved, persuaded her to see a voodoo priest because she was hearing noises in her house in Uniondale, N.Y. She said Mr. Valme told her that the noises were her father's bad spirits and that unless she saw a hougan, as voodoo priests are called, she would die.</p>
        <p>Ms. DeGraff was taken to Irvington, a city with one of the largest  Haitian populations in New Jersey, last October and underwent nine  nights of prayers. But on the last night, she said, Mr. Charles covered her body and head with a white sheet. She said she then heard a whooshing sound and realized she was ablaze.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valme, who was released on bond, could not be reached for comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>But James Weinberg, Mr. Charles's lawyer, has disputed Ms. DeGraff's account and said the burning was an accident. Mr. Weinberg said that Ms. DeGraff, not the priest, had poured Florida Water -- a flammable cologne often used in voodoo ceremonies -- on herself and got too close to a candle.</p>
        <p>Irvington's Police Chief, Steven Palamara, said that the police were seeking one more suspect. Chief Palamara said that they had learned of the events soon after they took place but did not have enough evidence to charge the suspects until recently.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
