<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rock's Excess in Service of Introspection</title>
    <meta content="24ALAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morissette, Alanis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0D81E3DF937A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rock's Excess in Service of Introspection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rock singer Alanis Morissette performs at Hammerstein Ballroom; photo; Ann Powers review (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As an electric keyboard tinkled demurely behind her during her second encore at the Hammerstein Ballroom on Thursday night, Alanis Morissette sang about wailing so hard she would crack. Paying homage to that impulse was only fair, since it made Ms. Morissette a superstar.</p>
        <p>''You Oughta Know,'' the 1995 smash that won her fame, was a wronged lover's howl that unleashed a flood of nasty memories and disheveled emotions. It captured one side of this instantly emblematic performer: the loudmouth who is really an introvert unable to contain herself any longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As an electric keyboard tinkled demurely behind her during her second encore at the Hammerstein Ballroom on Thursday night, Alanis Morissette sang about wailing so hard she would crack. Paying homage to that impulse was only fair, since it made Ms. Morissette a superstar.</p>
        <p>''You Oughta Know,'' the 1995 smash that won her fame, was a wronged lover's howl that unleashed a flood of nasty memories and disheveled emotions. It captured one side of this instantly emblematic performer: the loudmouth who is really an introvert unable to contain herself any longer.</p>
        <p>Like many breakthrough artists, Ms. Morissette connected two cultural strains to create something new. She is not really a gregarious rocker but a pensive singer-songwriter who applies rock's volume and theatricality to material that other artists handle more discreetly. She showed this side on Thursday, strumming so hard on an acoustic guitar that her fingers might have bled and stretching out words like ''potential'' and ''disillusionment'' until her self-interrogations became testaments.</p>
        <p>The songs from her second album, ''Supposed Former Infatuation Junkie'' (Maverick), to be released Nov. 3, were even more ruminative than the several she offered from her multi-platinum ''Jagged Little Pill.'' That album, with its assertions of independence and self-worth, redefined mainstream rock's feminine voice. ''Infatuation Junkie'' is not so tied to gender; Ms. Morissette still writes often about intimate relationships but seems more interested in the subject of spirituality as she reaches toward transcendent wisdom.</p>
        <p>Her attempts, including the current single ''Thank You,'' often rely on another hybrid, connecting the rock ballad to older song forms. Their extremely repetitive lyrics and facile melodic lines make them instantly, almost irritatingly, memorable.</p>
        <p>The sound that bolsters them, created by her highly competent but unassuming band, relies on cyclical riffs that build to depict swirling emotions. Often using the Eastern modalities that reflect her interest in Indian music, they also show signs of Beatles-era psychedelia, techno-trance and, at their most banal, 1980's-style modern rock. The music's carefully designed intensity communicates an obsessiveness that suits Ms. Morissette's role as a public self-analyst.</p>
        <p>These clean structures also serve a function beyond self-expression. ''Hand in My Pocket'' and ''Ironic,'' the hits that sustained Ms. Morissette's career after ''You Oughta Know,'' use repetition not to seem obsessive but to evoke the universal quality common to children's rounds and hymns.</p>
        <p>Many of ''Infatuation Junkie's'' songs are, in fact, secular hymns, using simply beautiful frameworks to express uplifting sentiments. Like ''Everybody Hurts'' by R.E.M. and ''One'' by U2, ''Thank You'' and other Morissette compositions seek to touch listeners with a message and a mood that is holy, if not specifically religious.</p>
        <p>The purity of Ms. Morissette's voice and her trancelike immersion in her music make her an ideal vehicle for these pop psalms. Pacing and flinging her body about, then standing stock still to deliver a ringing chorus, she seemed a bit possessed, as she always has. Now, however, Ms. Morissette apparently believes that the spirit catching her is larger than herself, and her conviction has added a new dimension to her art.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
