<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Request for Visit Denied</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="334967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ESPIONAGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURD, DOUGLAS (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAZOFT, FARZAD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DD1531F936A25750C0A966958260" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Request for Visit Denied</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, March 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Iraq turned down a request by Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd to visit Baghdad this weekend to press Britain's request for clemency for Mr. Bazoft, the Foreign Office said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Iraq turned down a request by Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd to visit Baghdad this weekend to press Britain's request for clemency for Mr. Bazoft, the Foreign Office said today.</p>
        <p>Iraq turned down a request by Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd to visit Baghdad this weekend to press Britain's request for clemency for Mr. Bazoft, the Foreign Office said today.</p>
        <p>As long as ''political and media pressure continued,'' President Saddam Hussein told the Iraqi press agency today, he ''could not decide to intervene'' in the cases of Mr. Bazoft and Daphne Parish, a 52-year-old British nurse accused of helping him. Mrs. Parish was sentenced to 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>British officials said that Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, who said last weekend that she was ''horrified and taken aback'' by the severity of the sentences by an Iraqi revolutionary court, had sent President Hussein a formal appeal for clemency in the two cases.</p>
        <p>An aide to Mrs. Thatcher said that Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar of the United Nations, President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt, King Hussein of Jordan and Yasir Arafat, chairman of the Palestinian Liberation Organization, had all been asked to intervene with the Iraqi leader.</p>
        <p>'Profound Damage' to Ties</p>
        <p>Last weekend William Waldegrave, another Foreign Office minister, said that if the sentences on Mr. Bazoft and Mrs. Parish were carried out, ''inevitably there would be profound damage to bilateral relationships between the two countries.'' Last year, Britain ran a $:350.6 million ($571 million) trade surplus with Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hurd, British officials said, had suggested he could go to Baghdad this weekend for a meeting with President Hussein to discuss the cases, on his way to a meeting of the European Community and the Gulf Cooperation Council in Oman on Saturday.</p>
        <p>''They told us yesterday that this was not the time,'' a Foreign Office spokesman said today.</p>
        <p>Trip to Weapons Plant</p>
        <p>The Observer said that Mr. Bazoft, an Iranian native who holds a British passport, had arrived in Baghdad last September at the invitation of the Iraqi Government, which was familiar with his work from previous visits during the Iran-Iraq war. After he arrived, the newspaper said, he asked permission to investigate published reports that several hundred people had been killed at an Iraqi weapons plant at Al Iskandariya in August.</p>
        <p>He got to the site, the newspaper said, apparently with the help of his acquaintance, Mrs. Parish, and talked openly about the trip after returning to Baghdad. He was arrested Sept. 15, and Mrs. Parish was detained four days later, and much later the Iraqi authorities said they were being investigated for espionage.</p>
        <p>Press restrictions and military secrecy in Iraq are among the tightest in the world.</p>
        <p>At the end of October, after repeated requests by British officials to see Mr. Bazoft had been denied, Iraqi television broadcast a taped interview in which he said he had been on a spying mission for Israel, which had supposedly recruited him in London in 1987 and helped him find the job with The Observer.</p>
        <p>Editor Denies Assertions</p>
        <p>Donald Trelford, the editor of The Observer, has denied all these assertions without qualifications and explained them by saying that they had been made under duress; during the trial, he pointed out, Mr. Bazoft said he was innocent of the charges.</p>
        <p>''No journalist or cameraman can feel safe in Baghdad while Farzad Bazoft is under sentence of death for reporting,'' he wrote in the newspaper's latest issue last Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
