<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report of Plot to Kill Tycoon Leads Yeltsin to Call Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="Y21RUSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berezovsky, Boris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litvinenko, Aleksandr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DC1330F932A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report of Plot to Kill Tycoon Leads Yeltsin to Call Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Nov. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Boris N Yeltsin orders inquiry into spectacular charge that Federal Security Service, spinoff of old KGB, plotted to kill Boris A Berezovsky, one of Russia's most influential tycoons; source of charge, Security Service colonel named Aleksandr Litvinenko, calls news conference to elaborate on accusation and warn that rogue element is running wild within agency; several other agents agree that agency is infested by 'criminal group' using agency for its own private political purposes; Vladimir Putin, new director of agency, denies charge and claims some officers who staged news conference are themselves rogues; there has been upswing in overt anti-Semitism among nationalist and Communist politicians in Russia, and Berezovsky is Jewish (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Boris N. Yeltsin ordered an inquiry today into spectacular charges leveled earlier this week -- so far without evidence -- that Russia's equivalent of the F.B.I. plotted to kill one of the country's most influential tycoons.</p>
        <p>The tycoon is Boris A. Berezovsky, an oil magnate and director of Russia's biggest television network, who was a leading supporter of Mr. Yeltsin during the last presidential campaign in 1996.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Boris N. Yeltsin ordered an inquiry today into spectacular charges leveled earlier this week -- so far without evidence -- that Russia's equivalent of the F.B.I. plotted to kill one of the country's most influential tycoons.</p>
        <p>The tycoon is Boris A. Berezovsky, an oil magnate and director of Russia's biggest television network, who was a leading supporter of Mr. Yeltsin during the last presidential campaign in 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovsky, who is still alive, released a letter last week asserting that the Federal Security Service, a spinoff of the old Soviet K.G.B. that is responsible for domestic law enforcement, plotted last winter to murder him.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday the source of Mr. Berezovsky's information, a Security Service colonel named Aleksandr Litvinenko, called a news conference to elaborate on the accusation and warn that a rogue element was running wild within the agency.</p>
        <p>Moscow has talked of little else since. Today Mr. Yeltsin's spokesman, Dmitri Yakushin, said the President had ordered the Security Service and his chief national security aide to investigate it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin ''is seriously worried by the latest media reports that F.S.B. officials have allegedly committed illegal actions,'' Mr. Yakushin said, using the Russian initials for the service, which is responsible for investigating organized crime, terrorism and foreign intelligence operations.</p>
        <p>At his news conference, Colonel Litvinenko and several other agents -- some thinly disguised in dark glasses -- said the agency was infested by a ''criminal group'' that had been using it ''for its own private political purposes, including settling accounts with unwanted people.''</p>
        <p>Besides the order to murder Mr. Berezovsky, which Colonel Litvinenko contended had been issued by leaders of the agency, other Security Service officers detailed what they said was a plot to kidnap the brother of another prominent Moscow businessman, Umar Dzhabrailov.</p>
        <p>Why the orders were supposedly issued, and why the plots were not carried out, is not clear. The agents took pains to note that all of the plots had unraveled before the service's current director, Vladimir Putin, took command in August.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Putin reacted angrily anyway, saying he had written evidence that some of the officers who had staged the news conference were themselves rogues who had pushed illegal crime fighting methods. Some of them, he said, had actually been Mr. Berezovsky's personal bodyguards at one time.</p>
        <p>''They will be dismissed in strict accordance with the law,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin ridiculed the allegations, arguing that experienced investigators like Colonel Litvinenko would have secured proof of their charges, perhaps through video surveillance, if they had been true.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovsky's Communist Party critics suggested that the once-powerful industrialist, his stature lowered by Russia's economic downfall, was simply seeking to recapture lost limelight. Mr. Berezovsky was one of Mr. Yeltsin's principal backers in the last election, and the President's own drift away from the center of power may have reduced Mr. Berezovsky's influence.</p>
        <p>Still, Muscovites were not dismissing the allegations out of hand. A separate criminal investigation of corruption within the Security Service has already led to several prosecutions, and Mr. Putin has dismantled the service's organized crime unit on the grounds that it was unprofessional.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Berezovsky has some reason for concern. The ORT television network, the nation's largest broadcast company and a locus of much of his influence, was raided by Government officials this week and some of its equipment confiscated for nonpayment of taxes.</p>
        <p>Although the network's arrears are real, so are those of scores of other major corporations, and some people have speculated that the raid was part of the early jockeying to control the media among candidates for the 2000 presidential election.</p>
        <p>The last month has also seen an upswing in overt anti-Semitism among nationalist and Communist politicians. Mr. Berezovsky is of Jewish descent and is a strong supporter of Israel. He has survived one attempt on his life, a 1995 car bombing that killed one man and left his bodyguard seriously wounded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
