<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Depot Warns of 20% Fall in Quarter Profits</title>
    <meta content="Y20HOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/20/business/20HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Depot Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brick, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA143CF933A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Depot Warns of 20% Fall in Quarter Profits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Home Depot says fiscal fourth-quarter profits would fall 20 percent because of slowing national economy; its share price declines $3.25, to $41 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Home Depot Inc. disappointed Wall Street yesterday by warning that its fiscal fourth-quarter profits would fall 20 percent because of a weakening economy.</p>
        <p>Citing a continued decline in lumber prices and slumping demand from consumers unnerved by sagging stock portfolios and surging energy bills, the company said sales in stores open a year or more would be flat for the quarter ending Jan. 28 and would remain under pressure during the first half of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Home Depot Inc. disappointed Wall Street yesterday by warning that its fiscal fourth-quarter profits would fall 20 percent because of a weakening economy.</p>
        <p>Citing a continued decline in lumber prices and slumping demand from consumers unnerved by sagging stock portfolios and surging energy bills, the company said sales in stores open a year or more would be flat for the quarter ending Jan. 28 and would remain under pressure during the first half of the year.</p>
        <p>Several Wall Street analysts said they had expected the announcement, which came a day after the Commerce Department said building permits fell 6.6 percent in December, even though residential construction edged up slightly. But few expected the magnitude of the shortfall.</p>
        <p>Shares of Home Depot, based in Atlanta, fell $3.25, to $41, on the New York Stock Exchange. The stock is well off its 52-week high of $70, reached last April.</p>
        <p>Home Depot expects fourth-quarter profit of 20 cents a share, 3 cents below the predictions of the most pessimistic analysts and 5 cents below its earnings in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>''The tough economy has put tremendous pressure on fourth-quarter sales performance and increased competition for share of the consumers' wallets,'' Robert L. Nardelli, the company's president and chief executive, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Many analysts agreed. ''The consumer has gone into hibernation or vapor lock or whatever terminology you want to use,'' said Steven Roorda, senior equity analyst for American Express Financial Advisors. ''You and I are not going out and remodeling our kitchen or remodeling our bath.''</p>
        <p>The company's reliance on expensive items made it particularly vulnerable to economic factors squeezing retailers, Mr. Roorda contended, though other analysts disagreed. For instance, Gary Balter, a retail industry analyst for Credit Suisse First Boston, argued that 35-  to 55-year-old consumers would continue to make home improvement their first priority when spending disposal income.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most disturbing to analysts was the company's disclosure of flat fourth-quarter same-store sales, a revision from its previous forecast of 4 percent growth.</p>
        <p>Since last February, lumber prices have fallen more than 30 percent. Lumber contributes about 15 percent of the chain's sales, according to analysts, and the price decline is responsible for half of the shortfall in same-store sales, said Robert M. Burton, the company's vice president for investor relations.</p>
        <p>''If you look against the broad range of retail out there,'' a flat report is not so bad, Mr. Burton said, adding that competition is stiffening from less-optional homeowning costs, notably heating.</p>
        <p>''People are looking at their stock portfolios and frankly thinking that a new kitchen is not in the cards,''he said.</p>
        <p>But Donald Trott, specialty retail analyst for Jefferies &amp; Company, said the declines in profit and sales growth distracted from Home Depot's dim overall growth prospects, even if the economy bounces back. He predicts Home Depot will have saturated the United States and Canada by late 2003 with 2,200 to 2,300 of its flagship stores.</p>
        <p>Home Depot also runs about 24 Expo Design Center stores, which offer design services and designer  decorations as well as four Villager's Hardware stores in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nardelli ''is not a retailer,'' Mr. Trott said. ''I don't think he understands the constraints.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nardelli, the former chief executive of GE Power Systems, agreed to join Home Depot in December, just days after General Electric said it had chosen Jeffrey R. Immelt to succeed John F. Welch Jr. as chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Burton, the company spokesman, said Mr. Nardelli would be forced to devise more nimble and conservative corporate strategies, adding, ''Bob is coming into a business that is under a level of economic pressure that it has not faced in many, many years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
