<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Down and Far From Home, Rangers Are Feeling Pain</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="845108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONTREAL CANADIENS NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEETCH, BRIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EED61E39F932A15757C0A960958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Down and Far From Home, Rangers Are Feeling Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brian Leetch was one of the first Rangers to leave the ice after practice today, and one of the last to leave the locker room after receiving attention from the team's medical staff.</p>
        <p>His expression was grim and his mood seemed glum even as he tried to say positive things about his bruised right instep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brian Leetch was one of the first Rangers to leave the ice after practice today, and one of the last to leave the locker room after receiving attention from the team's medical staff.</p>
        <p>His expression was grim and his mood seemed glum even as he tried to say positive things about his bruised right instep.</p>
        <p>It feels better today skating than it did the other day," Leetch said as his team prepared for Game 3 of the Eastern Conference quarterfinals Sunday in the Molson Center. "Actually, I wouldn't say 'better.' We're on less medication, so 'similar' means 'better.' "</p>
        <p>Leetch performed below his usual high standards as the Rangers lost the first two games of their four-of-seven-game Stanley Cup series at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>He has no goals and no assists, and he has been on the ice for five Montreal  goals, including one that began when Leetch turned over the puck during a Ranger power play.</p>
        <p>He hurt the foot last Sunday when struck by a puck in the regular-season finale in Florida.</p>
        <p>"I don't think it's affecting what I want to do out there," he said. Leetch said the Rangers remain confident and unconcerned about having won only once in their last 24 games -- playoffs and regular season combined -- in this city.  Their last regular-season victory here was in 1991. Their last playoff victory was in 1979.</p>
        <p>"You've lost half the battle if you think it's all going to happen again," Leetch said. "We can lose anywhere. We've proved that. Now, we've got to prove we can win anywhere."</p>
        <p>The other crucial injured Ranger, the captain Mark Messier, seemed friskier than he has been all week while recovering from a rib injury. In practice, he skated briskly and showed improved speed on his wrist shots, although he wasn't  slapping the puck.</p>
        <p>"Certainly not in practice," Messier said. He discounted the team's history here by joking that the roster has changed since the finals of 1979. Trying to sound optimistic, Messier said, "There comes a time you've got to look down the  barrel of the gun and pull the trigger," before changing metaphors to clear up misconceptions. "We were the hunted," he said. "Now, we are the hunters."</p>
        <p>He spoke while standing in a corridor next to a small wooden stand that Coach Colin Campbell used as a podium. "I'll stay off the soapbox," Messier said.</p>
        <p>Campbell smiled ruefully when one of the television technicians noted he was  standing with his "back to the wall" when he stepped up.</p>
        <p>Asked about replacing the injured Sergei Nemchinov, out with a cut on his leg, Campbell declined to elaborate.</p>
        <p>Had he spoken with the goal-less Luc Robitaille about the turnover and temper display that led to Montreal's second short-handed goal in Game 2? "Eighteen thousand, two-hundred people were talking to him," the coach said, referring to  the booing Garden fans. "God knows we've had enough talks this year. He has to cut through the pressure."</p>
        <p>Robitaille agreed. "The guys who score goals make a lot of money," said the left wing, who is being paid $19 million on a six-year contract. "They should take pressure."</p>
        <p>Despite the defeats, many Rangers seemed confident they won't be swept. "We knew, going in, it was going to be a long series," Messier said. "That's obviously the way it is turning out."</p>
        <p>Sergio Momesso, who scored twice in Game 2, added: "We don't throw in the towel, that's for sure. There's too much pride. It's bugging us that we're down, 2-0. If we win tomorrow, it changes the whole thing, and the pressure will be on both teams. And they've never had pressure before."</p>
        <p>Across the rink, Montreal's rookie coach, Mario Tremblay, told of using a press clipping to motivate his young players. He said he showed the rookies Saku Koivu and Valery Bure a story quoting Neil Smith, the Rangers president and general manager.</p>
        <p>Smith, according to Tremblay, predicted that the bigger, stronger Rangers would eventually wear down the smaller Canadiens.</p>
        <p>"I don't think Koivu and Bure liked it too much," Tremblay said.</p>
        <p>Koivu concurred.</p>
        <p>"It affected me," he said. "I want to show them we are a small team, but we can beat them."</p>
        <p>-------------------- Avalanche 4, Canucks 0</p>
        <p>VANCOUVER, British Columbia, April 20 (AP) -- Peter Forsberg, Valery Kamensky and Claude Lemieux each scored power-play goals in the first two periods as the  Colorado Avalanche beat the Vancouver Canucks by 4-0 tonight. The Avalanche dominated special teams to take a 2-1 lead in the four-of-seven-game Western Conference playoff series.</p>
        <p>Goaltender Patrick Roy stopped 28 shots for Colorado for his sixth career shutout in the playoffs, making few difficult saves. Many Canucks' fans left in  disgust in the third period.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
