<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Players Heave Air Ball in Boycott</title>
    <meta content="03SAND$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1059212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Turner Sports</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Basketball Players Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1D6103FF930A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Players Heave Air Ball in Boycott</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC and Turner Sports are not quaking at prospect of National Basketball Association players boycotting interview requests during lockout and then during season, whenever it is to begin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NBC and Turner Sports are not quaking at the prospect of National Basketball Association players boycotting interview requests during the lockout and then during the season, whenever it is to begin.</p>
        <p>''It's not a serious threat,'' said Craig Sager, a Turner reporter. ''It came out of uneducated comments. I don't think they'll do it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NBC and Turner Sports are not quaking at the prospect of National Basketball Association players boycotting interview requests during the lockout and then during the season, whenever it is to begin.</p>
        <p>''It's not a serious threat,'' said Craig Sager, a Turner reporter. ''It came out of uneducated comments. I don't think they'll do it.''</p>
        <p>''As long as they plan no comment,'' Bob Costas, NBC's lead play-by-play announcer, said with a barely contained chuckle, ''I have no comment.''</p>
        <p>Sure, we see Michael Jordan barring NBC's Ahmad Rashad from a pajama party where he would exclusively reveal his irksome hangnail to his faithful Boswell, and Karl Malone shunning Sager after scoring 45 points. Just envision Malone telling Sager, ''Forget it, Craig, I don't like your network's contract.''</p>
        <p>How many future Bartlett's quotations will be lost to this venal plot against public discourse? If Bill Wennington doesn't tell NBC's Jim Gray his innermost thoughts as his perspiration drenches the microphone, can we survive?</p>
        <p>Think of this: Charles Barkley turning down a chance to chat -- about anything. Even about deciding not to talk. As soon as he heard the boycott threat, Doc Rivers, the TNT analyst, ascribed it to a small group of agents. ''I just didn't think it would hold water,'' said the former Knick, who has been working out in San Antonio with the Spurs' David Robinson and Tim Duncan. ''Tensions are high, but they won't be once things get settled.''</p>
        <p>Besides, Rivers added, ''As long as Barkley's around, we're safe.''</p>
        <p>Word of a possible boycott came out of a players' meeting in Las Vegas, Nev., last month. The players were incensed that NBC and Turner were paying the N.B.A. in full this season, which is required during a lockout. If NBC and Turner did not agree to such a payment clause, the N.B.A. would have found willing customers elsewhere ''and the players would be talking to CBS and ESPN,'' Rivers said.</p>
        <p>For the perfidy of making guaranteed payments -- bankrolling the lockout and emboldening the league to be resolute, it is alleged -- players talked of denying NBC, TNT and TBS their oratory. In Las Vegas, Patrick Ewing, the union president, said, ''When all is said and done, this lockout will have cost the players a lot of money and NBC's role will not be forgotten.''</p>
        <p>Funny how Ewing never made public his distaste for the same lockout payment clause in past NBC and Turner contracts that helped his salary soar.</p>
        <p>''The players who are informed know most of the money we pay goes to them,'' said Sager, who was at the Las Vegas meeting. ''When I was there, they didn't shun me. Someone kiddingly said to me, 'There's the enemy.' I interviewed 300 players last year. They know I'm there to publicize their achievements.''</p>
        <p>And to provide a forum for future work. On Turner's roster are former players like Rivers and Reggie Theus. On NBC's roster are Isiah Thomas, Bill Walton, Steve Jones and Matt Guokas. After last season, NBC jettisoned John Salley, who had replaced Julius Erving, as a studio show analyst.</p>
        <p>NBC and Turner have each made the first payments on their contracts, which total $2.6 billion over four years. NBC will be repaid for missed games (the network's season does not start until Christmas Day) with rebates on their next three years' fees. Turner, which starts missing games tonight, will get games added to its TBS schedules.</p>
        <p>The damage of a boycott to NBC and Turner would be small. There will be holes in the studio shows where relaxed player interviews, some illuminating, some dull, will have to be filled. But as a whole, being denied the cavalcade of pre-game and post-game player talk is like being barred by your mother from playing your CD of Sebastian Cabot singing ''Blowin' in the Wind.''</p>
        <p>Players not playing during the lockout harms NBC and Turner by forcing them to insert replacement programs that generate reduced advertising revenues.</p>
        <p>But players not talking? Can you say ''empty, misguided threat''?</p>
        <p>'Monday Night' Strike</p>
        <p>''Monday Night Football'' did not suffer much last night from a strike against ABC by the National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians. With fewer cameras, the nonunion production was less elaborate than usual but solid. Something went awry late in the third quarter when commercials ran over several Eagles plays. The strike made ABC shift the pre-game show from the ESPN Zone sports bar in Baltimore to Veterans Stadium, where bad lighting made Al Michaels, Dan Dierdorf and Boomer Esiason look ashen.</p>
        <p>Airwaves</p>
        <p>Channel 11, which carried Sunday's marathon, received a 6.1 local Nielsen rating, down from 7.0 last year. . . . The Giants' loss Sunday produced a 13.5 on Channel 5, beating the 12.2 on Channel 2 for the Jets' victory.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
