<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Soviet Debt Grows, So Do Western Worries</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PROKESCH, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDE1E3DF931A25754C0A967958260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Soviet Debt Grows, So Do Western Worries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN PROKESCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PROKESCH, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Soviet and Western leaders prepare for next week's summit conference, it increasingly appears that they may need to deal quickly with the issue of the Soviet Union's huge debt and shortage of hard currency.</p>
        <p>Soviet officials recently estimated their current foreign debt at $70 billion, up from $60 billion to $65 billion at the end of last year. Some 25 to 30 percent of the total falls due this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Soviet and Western leaders prepare for next week's summit conference, it increasingly appears that they may need to deal quickly with the issue of the Soviet Union's huge debt and shortage of hard currency.</p>
        <p>Soviet officials recently estimated their current foreign debt at $70 billion, up from $60 billion to $65 billion at the end of last year. Some 25 to 30 percent of the total falls due this year.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union is struggling to raise the hard currency to cover these payments and to pay for essential imports like food and drugs. This has forced it to slash other imports, like badly needed capital equipment and replacement parts for the oil industry and other critical industries.</p>
        <p>Western officials say they believe that President Mikhail S. Gorbachev will ask Western leaders for a restructuring of the Soviet debt. The Soviets had $31 billion in loans from commercial banks at the end of 1990, as well as $7.5 billion in other private financing and $21.5 billion from Western governments, according to the Institute of International Finance, a Washington-based research organization financed by banks.  Assessing Economic Reform</p>
        <p>Even if Mr. Gorbachev does not specifically seek the restructuring of loans, Western leaders say they will have to take the debt problem into account as they assess any economic reform program Mr. Gorbachev brings with him to London. While Western leaders have virtually ruled out large-scale financial aid, restructuring debt may be possible.</p>
        <p>Western experts estimate that the Soviets need at least $50 billion in hard currency this year to service their debt and pay for imports. They have $5 billion to $8 billion in hard currency deposits in banks, and are expected to earn $35 billion to $40 billion this year from exports and the sale of gold. Even if they manage to cut imports to limit the outflow of hard currency, and sell $3 billion to $5 billion in gold, the Soviets will probably need at least $14 billion in new financing and possibly much more, according to government officials and financial analysts.</p>
        <p>The Soviet position on foreign currency depends largely on two things: how the country's exports fare and how much grain the Soviets have to import.</p>
        <p>A study by Morgan Stanley estimates that excluding gold sales, the Soviets will need a minimum of $17.9 billion in new hard currency financing this year and $23.9 billion in 1992. That assumes that non-food imports drop by 50 percent this year, that energy and total exports fall by 10 percent and that grain imports increase by 56 percent, to 55.1 million tons.</p>
        <p>"A balance-of-payments crisis could materialize if grain or oil production falls more than now expected," said David C. Roche, a London-based economist at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Soviet officials, in fact, have warned that grain imports might be much higher. And there is a danger that energy production problems may intensify.</p>
        <p>As a result of Draconian measures, Soviet imports bought with hard currency have dropped by 45 to 50 percent so far this year. Western economists expect a drop of 20 to 25 percent for the year as a whole.</p>
        <p>Factory Closings Reported</p>
        <p>The plunge is severely hurting Eastern Europe, a big exporter to the Soviets. But the import curbs have also hurt the Soviet Union, worsening shortages. Scores of factories reportedly have had to close because of a lack of spare parts.</p>
        <p>Whatever the foreign currency shortfall, it is unlikely that the Soviets will be able to turn to private lenders to tide them over. Nervous commercial banks have been increasingly unwilling to lend to the Soviet Union. Keith Savard, an economist at the Institute of International Finance, estimates that the net reduction in bank loans not guaranteed by governments dropped last year by $7 billion or $8 billion, to $31 billion, excluding exchange-rate effects.</p>
        <p>The institute and banks like J. P. Morgan &amp; Company believe such loans could drop an additional $3 billion to $5 billion this year. Much depends on whether Mr. Gorbachev presents an economic reform plan that impresses the West and whether the turbulent conditions in the Soviet Union begin to stabilize so bankers grow confident that loans will be repaid.</p>
        <p>With banks withdrawing as lenders, Western governments have significantly increased financial assistance to the Soviets. The amount the Soviets owe to Western governments increased to $21.5 billion last year from $12 billion in 1989, Mr. Savard said.</p>
        <p>The Germans, Italians and French, which have been the biggest providers of state financing to the Soviets, have reportedly been pushing other Western countries to follow suit.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration appears to be somewhat willing. It recently agreed to grant the Soviet Union $1.5 billion in credits to buy American farm goods. It also supports granting the Soviet Union most-favored-nation status as a trading partner, which would make it easier for the Soviets to obtain more trade credits.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gorbachev is not expected to request more trade financing in London. Soviet officals say credits would only add to the country's debts.</p>
        <p>Complicating the issue of whether the Soviets should seek rescheduling or restructuring of their debt, is the fact that it would probably make it harder for Mr. Gorbachev to attract Western investment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
