<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tri-Star's Chairman Quits In a Sign of Studio Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="660639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRI-STAR PICTURES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SONY PICTURES ENTERTAINMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLUMBIA PICTURES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEDAVOY, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUBER, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANTON, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D61631F93BA35752C0A962958260" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tri-Star's Chairman Quits In a Sign of Studio Turmoil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, Jan. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Medavoy, a one-time talent agent who served as a senior film company executive for more than two decades, resigned today as chairman of Tri-Star Pictures. The resignation came after months of personal tensions between Mr. Medavoy and his boss, Peter Guber, chairman of Sony Pictures Entertainment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medavoy, who is 52, said in a statement that "with a full schedule of pictures for next year and a very strong development slate, it is time for me to take some time out to think about what I would do with my future." Mr. Medavoy had more than a year remaining on a multimillion-dollar contract, and Sony officials declined to discuss the details of any settlement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Medavoy, a one-time talent agent who served as a senior film company executive for more than two decades, resigned today as chairman of Tri-Star Pictures. The resignation came after months of personal tensions between Mr. Medavoy and his boss, Peter Guber, chairman of Sony Pictures Entertainment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medavoy, who is 52, said in a statement that "with a full schedule of pictures for next year and a very strong development slate, it is time for me to take some time out to think about what I would do with my future." Mr. Medavoy had more than a year remaining on a multimillion-dollar contract, and Sony officials declined to discuss the details of any settlement.</p>
        <p>Alan J. Levine, president and chief operating officer of Sony Pictures Entertainment, said Mr. Medavoy's departure was "amicable."</p>
        <p>Since Sony's entry into the movie business in 1989, when it purchased Columbia Pictures for $3.4 billion, the Japanese company has proceeded on a spending spree that included the buyouts of several executives' contracts worth millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medavoy's resignation was a sign of continuing turmoil at Sony's film division, which includes Columbia and Tri-Star. According to the announcement by Sony Pictures Entertainment, Mr. Medavoy will be replaced by Mark Canton, chairman of Columbia Pictures, who was given the title of chairman of the Columbia Tri-Star Motion Picture Companies. Better Year for Tri-Star</p>
        <p>Mr. Canton, 45, joins another executive in the management of Sony Pictures Entertainment, Jonathan Dolgen, president of the Motion Picture Group. The two report to Mr. Levine.</p>
        <p>Although Tri-Star had a troubled record in 1992, the studio picked up last year with successes including "Sleepless in Seattle" and "Cliffhanger." Tri-Star recently released Jonathan Demme's "Philadelphia," the first big studio project about AIDS.</p>
        <p>On the downside, Tri-Star films like "Mr. Jones" and "Wilder Napalm" proved financially dismal. And the comedies "Look Who's Talking Now" and Woody Allen's "Manhattan Murder Mystery" were disappointments.</p>
        <p>But the studio's performance was better than that of its sister company. Last year, Columbia endured the big-budget failure of "Last Action Hero," starring Arnold Schwarzenegger, and the disappointment of a holiday film, "Geronimo: An American Legend."</p>
        <p>Mr. Medavoy, who was born in Shanghai of Russian immigrant parents, grew up in Chile and moved to California in 1956. He worked as an agent at International Famous Agency in the 1970's, with clients including Jane Fonda, Steven Spielberg and Francis Ford Coppola. He joined United Artists in 1974 as senior vice president of production and later helped form Orion Pictures. He became chairman of Tri-Star in 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medavoy, a prominent Democratic Party fund-raiser and friend of President Clinton, declined to comment on his resignation. Although he has more than one year left on his contract with Sony, there have been persistent rumors that he was barely getting along with Mr. Guber.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
