<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>St. Regis to Be Closed for at Least a Year</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="150398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHERATON CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EQUITABLE LIFE ASSURANCE SOCIETY OF THE US</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST REGIS HOTEL (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOLFF, CRAIG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DC1E30F932A35755C0A96E948260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>St. Regis to Be Closed for at Least a Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG WOLFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WOLFF, CRAIG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The marble bannisters leading from the main lobby still have about them a pale shine. The iron plating in the fireplace of the Louis XIV Room still bears the engraving of fleurs-de-lis, untarnished. And Old King Cole still stares down from his throne in a Maxfield Parrish oil. All the understated touches are in place that have given the St.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The marble bannisters leading from the main lobby still have about them a pale shine. The iron plating in the fireplace of the Louis XIV Room still bears the engraving of fleurs-de-lis, untarnished. And Old King Cole still stares down from his throne in a Maxfield Parrish oil. All the understated touches are in place that have given the St.</p>
        <p>The marble bannisters leading from the main lobby still have about them a pale shine. The iron plating in the fireplace of the Louis XIV Room still bears the engraving of fleurs-de-lis, untarnished. And Old King Cole still stares down from his throne in a Maxfield Parrish oil. All the understated touches are in place that have given the St. Regis its status in as one of the grand European-style hotels in New York.</p>
        <p>But the plumbing is bad. The electrical system needs an overhaul. And the discerning eye can see the plaster around the moldings giving way. Sale Is Possible</p>
        <p>Pointing to the difficulties and expense of maintaining an 84-year-old hotel that has been running mainly on 84-year-old pipes and wiring, the Sheraton Corporation and the Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States, co-owners of the St. Regis, announced yesterday that they would shut the hotel at Fifth Avenue and 55th Street on June 30 for at least a year, perhaps two, and that 360 employees would lose their jobs, for what the companies called the ''expectation of a major interior renovation.''</p>
        <p>During that time, said Robert W. Quinn, a spokesman for the Sheraton Corporation, one of the partners might buy out the other or Sheraton and Equitable Life might sell to a third party. He said that there was no guarantee that the renovation would be done before a sale, and that no one had been hired to do the work.</p>
        <p>Asked if there was a possibility that the 22-story hotel would be recast to something other than a hotel, such as an apartment house, Mr. Quinn said, ''There is no reason to think that.</p>
        <p>''The plans are for a renovation,'' he said. ''That's no secret. Whoever buys the hotel will be able to tell that immediately.''</p>
        <p>The renovation, Mr. Quinn said, would cost more than $50 million and involve ripping through the walls in most of the 521 rooms and 84 suites.</p>
        <p>''We're doing this now,'' Mr. Quinn said, ''because costs of fixing had gotten so high and it's not right for guests in a luxury hotel to see workers in their bathroom every other week.''</p>
        <p>Despite the upheaval, the hotel and its staff seemed last night to maintain dignity and grace. An effort will be made to help the waiters, maids, secretaries and front-desk personnel and other workers find jobs at other hotels.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a sentimental woman,'' said Georgetta Prodan, who has worked as a front-desk supervisor for four and half years, ''but I love this place. No hotel in New York has its elegance.''</p>
        <p>Marcel Paray, the captain in the King Cole dining room for the last 25 years, was awash with nostalgia when he talked about the famous guests he had served - from Aristotle Onassis to Richard M. Nixon to Salvador Dali, who lived in the hotel for about 12 years. He said he would retire, but he felt pangs. The young waiters had asked Mr. Paray for his telephone number so they could call him if he heard of available work. Rich History</p>
        <p>Mr. Paray recounted the hotel's folklore: how the Bloody Mary was invented at the old bar in the King Cole room by a French bartender, Fernand L. Petiot, and how John Jacob Astor built the hotel to show his sister, Mary Astor, who had built the original Waldorf Hotel and Astoria Hotel on Wall Street, that he could do better.</p>
        <p>Several guests said they stayed at the St. Regis, paying rates of $175 to $750, because it offered a special kind of privacy.</p>
        <p>Seated amid the classic French decor of the hotel lounge, a guest from Buenos Aires said simply, ''I come here because they treat me like a regular person and it's a regular place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
