<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Get Back to Work</title>
    <meta content="Allen.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/books/review/Allen.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feminist Movement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bennetts, Leslie</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Feminine Mistake: Are We Giving Up Too Much? (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DD133EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Get Back to Work</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Get Back to Work</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EUGENIE ALLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Allen, Eugenie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE FEMININE MISTAKE</p>
        <p>Are We Giving Up Too Much?</p>
        <p>By Leslie Bennetts.</p>
        <p>350 pp. Voice/Hyperion. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An argument against staying home with kids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE FEMININE MISTAKE</p>
        <p>Are We Giving Up Too Much?</p>
        <p>By Leslie Bennetts.</p>
        <p>350 pp. Voice/Hyperion. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Imagine a shy, observant American girl, born in the middle of the last century. For years, her mother comes home from her job as an editor and puts in a second shift cooking, cleaning and supervising homework while Dad dozes in front of the TV. Gradually, the girl realizes that something is very wrong. When she is 13, her mother gives her a newly published book and says, ''Read this,'' and her life begins to change.</p>
        <p>The book was ''The Feminine Mystique.'' The girl was Leslie Bennetts, and 44 years later she is no longer shy. She has built a deeply satisfying career as a print journalist: a longtime contributor to Vanity Fair, she bagged Jen's first post-Brangelina interview; the issue in which it appeared, in September 2005, became the magazine's best seller. Bennetts is also married -- to a mensch who washes the dishes and makes the bed -- and has two happy, talented teenagers. In short, she has managed to have it all. But she has recently become concerned about the next generation of women, too many of whom seem to be ditching their careers to stay home with their children, so she revisits Betty Friedan for inspiration.</p>
        <p>The result is ''The Feminine Mistake,'' an energetic call to mothers to stay in the work force and earn their own way -- or suffer the consequences. She rallies numbers to her cause: Half of all marriages end in divorce, and while a man's standard of living actually rises after divorce, a woman's falls. The average age of widowhood is 55. Women live longer than men, yet typically have far less money for retirement. Even a brief timeout reduces a mom's earning power. As Bennetts asks, ''If your husband divorces you or drops dead, was it really such a great idea to stay home if you can't afford to buy groceries to feed your kids?''</p>
        <p>This ambitious book sets out to replace choice feminism -- the revisionist view that says as long as women are happy with their decisions about balancing work and motherhood, it doesn't matter what those decisions are -- with the ethos that giving up paid work is not just another legitimate option among many but a serious error. By shifting the focus from family values to economics, Bennetts hopes to sidestep the emotion that has dominated the debate and persuade women to change what she perceives as self-destructive behavior. It's a provocative idea (and one that's posited even more starkly in Linda Hirshman's 2006 polemic, ''Get to Work''). It is also -- up to a point -- undeniably correct. Common sense requires every woman who opts out to have a strategy for opting back in, when and if she wants or needs to. (Like Bennetts, I have worked from home as a writer for about 18 years, since my first child was born, but I have taken long time-outs along the way.)</p>
        <p>In her book, Bennetts seeks to counter a wave of media attention that continues to see the ''opt-out'' impulse as admirable or inevitable, and works hard to deflate the myths surrounding the brain drain. She argues, for instance, that many women are not as drawn to raising their children full time as they are dissatisfied with their jobs. And she reminds us that child-care concerns fade as quickly as children grow up, but lost career momentum is gone forever.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, ''The Feminine Mistake'' doesn't do this loaded issue justice. A more thorough argument would first acknowledge that it's possible for a woman to find deep meaning in a life spent mostly caring for her family. Instead, Bennetts portrays the stay-at-home mother as a financial and emotional drain on her husband; a bad example for their children; and a disappointment to her gender, to society and, worst of all, to herself. Forget about carrot versus stick: Bennetts uses a battering ram.</p>
        <p>Despite the author's claim that she has no interest in the Mommy Wars, this book is a battlefield. Women in both camps may find inspiration in her passionate account of the importance of work in her own life. But too often she lapses into know-it-all mode, as if marching into the living rooms of stay-at-home mothers to try to talk sense into them. As in most conflicts, language is a potent weapon. Bennetts and her sources variously refer to the problem that has no good name as ''micromanagers,'' ''lost women,'' ''Ã1/4bermothers,'' ''dependent wives,'' ''schlepper mothers'' and (my favorite) ''unachieving parents.'' Much of the heat is in the kitchen: In Bennetts's book, working mothers never have time to bake, while stay-at-home mothers do little else.</p>
        <p>It doesn't help that the book at times reads like a bloated magazine feature, recycling exhibits that first appeared in The New York Times, The Washington Post and other publications. More troubling -- or perhaps telling -- is that her sample captures a narrow spectrum. Most of the women she interviews live in the Northeast and the Midwest and work (or used to work, or are married to men who work) in the fields of law, media and finance.</p>
        <p>Not everyone can relate to the Manhattan book editor who says she's glad her income buys her the right to tell her husband where she wants to put the pool at their country house. Or the law professor/MacArthur genius award recipient/gourmet cook/mother of one adult son who announces that ''being a mom is a temp job.''</p>
        <p>Bennetts is right to dread an exodus of accomplished women from the work force. But this book is so unwieldy, and so polarizing, that it is unlikely to convince many stay-at-home mothers to return to work -- or to develop that backup plan. Friedan wrote with elegance, authority and empathy for the readers whose lives she hoped to change. Bennetts seems to have little but disdain for the women she is trying to reach. When I finished the book, I didn't feel the need to give it to my daughters, as Tina Brown's back-cover blurb urges. Instead, I dug up an old copy of ''The Feminine Mystique.'' I hear it's really great for teenage girls.</p>
        <p>Eugenie Allen has contributed articles about family life to Time and The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eugenie Allen has contributed articles about family life to Time and The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
