<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Arabic to Hebrew</title>
    <meta content="Ormsby.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/books/review/Ormsby.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Dream of the Poem, The: Hebrew Poetry From Muslim and Christian Spain, 950-1492 (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DC133EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Arabic to Hebrew</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Arabic to Hebrew</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ORMSBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ormsby, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DREAM OF THE POEM</p>
        <p>Hebrew Poetry From Muslim</p>
        <p>and Christian Spain, 950-1492.</p>
        <p>Translated, edited and</p>
        <p>introduced by Peter Cole.</p>
        <p>548 pp. Princeton University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $50; paper, $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Medieval Jewish poets borrowed from classical Arabic forms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DREAM OF THE POEM</p>
        <p>Hebrew Poetry From Muslim</p>
        <p>and Christian Spain, 950-1492.</p>
        <p>Translated, edited and</p>
        <p>introduced by Peter Cole.</p>
        <p>548 pp. Princeton University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $50; paper, $19.95.</p>
        <p>One day in 10th-century Baghdad a visiting foreign student named Dunash Ben Labrat showed his teacher, the revered scholar Sa'adia Gaon, a poem he had composed in a novel style. Sa'adia handed the poem back with the comment ''Nothing like it has ever been seen in Israel.'' This dubious compliment, which all teachers of creative writing might wish to employ, failed to discourage Dunash. He took himself, and his new poetry, back home to Muslim Spain. There, despite the dismay his mediocre verses prompted in other aspiring Hebrew poets, his style caught on. Within a few decades, from these unpromising origins, a brilliant and original body of Hebrew verse began to take shape. Virtually stagnant since late Biblical times, Hebrew poetry and the language itself would be transformed by a succession of poets of genius and their imitators. In Peter Cole's rich new anthology, the extent of their astonishing achievement is fully revealed for the first time in English.</p>
        <p>Dunash's innovation was strikingly simple. He adapted the meters of classical Arabic poetry to Hebrew. This was more radical than it might seem. Arabic is a quantitative language, like ancient Greek; long and short vowels are scrupulously marked, and this imparts a subtly variable music to the lines. Biblical poetry, by contrast, emphasized stress. It took ingenuity, as well as artistry, to force Hebrew into this unaccustomed pattern.</p>
        <p>Only 13 of Dunash's poems survive, along with one by his wife (whose name is lost), and it seems improbable that out of such feeble stuff -- Sa'adia was right to be noncommital -- a poetic renaissance might take flight. But the history of Hebrew poetry in Spain, as Cole makes clear in his witty and erudite notes, thrived on happy accidents. One of its greatest poets, Shmu'el Hanagid, the 11th-century general and sometime vizier to the Muslim ruler of Granada who was also a distinguished Talmudist in his spare time, composed more than 2,000 poems, the manuscript of which lay undiscovered until 1924, when it ''was found by chance in a crate.'' The work of Shelomo Ibn Gabirol, Shmu'el's cranky contemporary (and poetic equal), was snatched from a fireplace in Iraq ''where it was about to become fuel for the week's laundry.'' Many other poets' works were discovered in the Cairo Geniza, that brimming storeroom in the Ben Ezra Synagogue where much of medieval Jewish history lay in tattered bundles until the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>Hebrew poetry in Spain begins with Dunash around 950, but for almost two centuries, Arab poets there had been refining a body of literature unsurpassed for allusiveness and wit. So seductive were its melodies that Jewish poets living under Muslim rule were inspired not simply to imitate it in Hebrew but to rival and, at times, surpass it, taking not only meters from their Arab models but also themes, tropes and entire genres. When Yehuda Halevi wishes to evoke a male friend's charms, he says, ''My heart is pure, but not my eyes.'' The sentiment may be ''Platonic,'' as Cole claims, but there is a delicate, and very Andalusian, uncertainty to the verse; it manages to be at once chaste and erotic. In another poem Yehuda enjoins his soul ''to seek the Lord and His thresholds'' and ''offer your songs like incense.'' Austere poems praising God alternate with sensuous evocations of a lovely girl's -- or boy's -- cheek or curls. As Cole wittily remarks in his introduction, such poets were ''neither crumpet-munching literati in tights nor rhyme-happy rabbis with time on their hands.'' But neither were they Tartuffes in caftans: for them, like their Arab predecessors, the erotic and the spiritual coexisted along a delicate continuum. (From a literary viewpoint, the conflict was less between flesh and spirit than between inherited tropes colliding with passionate impulse.) The Hebrew poets did more than imitate Arabic poetry; they made it distinctly their own and they made it new.</p>
        <p>The difficulties of translating such poetry are probably insurmountable, and not solely because of linguistic differences. The Jewish poets of Granada and CÃ$(3$)rdoba could play on several registers. They used the figures of Arabic poetry but enriched them with Biblical allusion; their poetry glances in opposite directions simultaneously. It yearns for Zion in the accents of Ishmael. Here is Shelomo Ibn Gabirol, addressing God, his ''gazelle'':</p>
        <p>You lie in my palace on couches of gold:</p>
        <p>Lord, when will you ready my bed</p>
        <p>for the one with the beautiful eyes you've</p>
        <p>+foretold?</p>
        <p>The conceits are taken from Arabic but as Cole shows, the poem throbs with Biblical allusions as well, and the effect is subtly polyphonic. No translator could capture this, but Cole comes as close as possible; his versions are masterly.</p>
        <p>In 1492, Ferdinand and Isabella expelled Muslims and Jews from the Iberian Peninsula. That winter, the last Muslim ruler of Granada surrendered the keys to the Alhambra and Ferdinand and Isabella moved in. By the oddest of historical coincidences, Christopher Columbus was present and witnessed the surrender. In the same year that a new world lay open to the West, an old world crumbled, and its vanished grace is now recoverable only in the stanzas of its poets.</p>
        <p>Eric Ormsby is a poet and writer living in London; his new book, ''Ghazali,'' an intellectual biography, will be published in November.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Ormsby is a poet and writer living in London; his new book, ''Ghazali,'' an intellectual biography, will be published in November.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
