<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Crystal Ball Would Have Been Nice</title>
    <meta content="06Hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/realestate/06Hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1845427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weintraub, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weintraub, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDE113EF935A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Crystal Ball Would Have Been Nice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Crystal Ball Would Have Been Nice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Hunt column on search by Julie and Neil Weintraub for 'comfortably large' home in Brooklyn for about $700,000; found five-bedroom detached house for $690,000 in Kensington section; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF they could have predicted the future, Julie and Neil Weintraub would have bought a one-bedroom co-op, not a two-bedroom, for their first home.</p>
        <p>As their family grew, they began hunting for a larger one. But they let several opportunities pass, reluctant to commit to a new place until they sold their old one. That took more than a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If they could have predicted the future, Julie and Neil Weintraub would have bought a one-bedroom co-op, not a two-bedroom, for their first home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF they could have predicted the future, Julie and Neil Weintraub would have bought a one-bedroom co-op, not a two-bedroom, for their first home.</p>
        <p>As their family grew, they began hunting for a larger one. But they let several opportunities pass, reluctant to commit to a new place until they sold their old one. That took more than a year.</p>
        <p>''On some level, I have regretted that we bought that two-bedroom apartment,'' Mr. Weintraub said. They watched as the one-bedroooms in their building flew off the market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weintraub, 36, who grew up in a two-family house in Midwood, Brooklyn, and graduated from Brooklyn College, never strayed far from home. He was living in a studio rental when his mother, who worked for the New York City Department of Education, fixed him up with a colleague's cousin, Julie Tedoff.</p>
        <p>She lived on the Upper West Side, graduated from Macalester College in St. Paul and spent a decade in the Twin Cities. She returned to New York in 1999 for her job in textbook sales, and bought a one-bedroom co-op in Washington Heights for around $100,000. Three years later, in 2002, she sold it for $225,000.</p>
        <p>The two married the same year and bought the two-bedroom co-op on Ocean Parkway in Kensington, Brooklyn, for $140,000. Their apartment, on a high floor, had a view all the way from Coney Island to Lower Manhattan and a relatively high maintenance, around $1,000.</p>
        <p>Their identical twin sons, Ryan and Alexander, were born the next year. More space was imperative -- partly because Ms. Weintraub, 38, sometimes worked from home, and partly in anticipation of another child.</p>
        <p>They hoped to sell their home for around $400,000 and trade up to a three-bedroom co-op. But in their building, and others nearby, three-bedrooms were scarce and coveted, selling for $500,000 to $600,000. By the time they added monthly maintenance they figured they could spend $700,000 or so -- in which case they could buy an entire house of their own.</p>
        <p>They decided to hunt in Kensington and Windsor Terrace, near their friends and the twins' future schoolmates. ''I like the charm and diversity of my neighborhood,'' said Mr. Weintraub, a social worker. ''I prefer a neighborhood where coffee is 85 cents rather than $2.85.''</p>
        <p>The house didn't need to be in great shape, but it had to be comfortably large, with everything in working order.</p>
        <p>The first one they looked at, in Kensington, fit the bill. It had three real bedrooms, a basement and a two-car garage they could convert to a home office. The listing price was $619,000. They were disappointed when it was sold to another family for $590,000, the same amount they had offered. But they were a bit relieved, too, because they were waiting for their co-op to sell.</p>
        <p>A glut of similar two-bedrooms on the market made theirs less desirable, Ms. Weintraub said. Their building had a new sponsor that began selling off the unsold units, which were newly renovated and had lower maintenance costs.</p>
        <p>In Windsor Terrace, they found several one-family homes split awkwardly into two- or three-families. Most needed extensive renovations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weintraub was disturbed by some of the descriptions of apartments, especially when it came to the homes with owners' duplexes, he said. ''When I hear that, I expect to see a three-story house with the third floor being a rental space,'' he said. Instead, the main unit would be the ground floor with a finished basement.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of pressure for owners and real-estate agents to pretend their property is something it's not, and to ask prices in line with that magical thinking,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Their co-op finally went into contract last winter, for $370,000, when most of the sponsor units had been sold. By this time, they were expecting a third son.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, they saw a two-family attached brick house in Kensington. ''It was sweetly decorated and didn't need any work,'' Ms. Weintraub said. The listing price was $779,000.</p>
        <p>Later that day, they saw a house three blocks away, and ''immediately knew this was a different kind of house,'' she said. It wasn't attached and it wasn't narrow. There were five real bedrooms, two floors, a basement and an attic. It was even less -- $759,000.</p>
        <p>The house was also in their preferred school district, No. 15. ''That was for me the last roadblock,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Weintraubs offered $680,000, and bought the house for $690,000. The sellers, a family of Hasidic Jews with seven children, were moving to Borough Park. The house was shown during limited hours, when most of the children were at school, said their agent, Harold Klinger of Delmark Realty in Homecrest.</p>
        <p>''The other parties started haggling over price; this is no good, that is no good,'' Mr. Klinger said. ''The Weintraubs saw and appreciated the house for what it was.''</p>
        <p>At the walk-through, the sellers said they would be leaving mezuzahs, or cases of scriptural scrolls that indicate God's presence, on the doorposts, as required by Jewish law when a Jewish family moves in. ''It was really nice to have some humanity'' in an otherwise dispassionate business transaction, Mr. Weintraub said.</p>
        <p>They moved in March. ''A treehouse!'' the twins exclaimed when they saw the top-floor room, which has a big tree outside. That was supposed to be Ms. Weintraub's home office -- she is now an account manager for Tutor.com -- but it has become the boys' playroom.</p>
        <p>''Three bedrooms would have been enough, but just barely,'' Ms. Weintraub said. ''We are getting more than we needed with this house, rather than compromising.''</p>
        <p>If there was a compromise, it was the condition. But the Weintraubs figure they can fix things over time.</p>
        <p>They're learning fast what it means to own a house. They knew the kitchen water pressure was being weakened by a filter on the tap, commonly used by the city's religious Jews to eliminate microscopic crustaceans. But they couldn't figure out how to remove the filter, so they called a plumber. The filter was off in seconds.</p>
        <p>At night, they were awakened by a steady pounding. It took awhile to realize it was a rattling pipe. ''There is no super to call and no way to gauge the seriousness of the problem,'' Mr. Weintraub said. ''Is it something we have to deal with in a year or tomorrow morning?''</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
