<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Economy Contracts for 3d Straight Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y12YEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wudunn, Sheryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DF1731F931A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Economy Contracts for 3d Straight Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL WuDUNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wudunn, Sheryl</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japanese Government says economy contracted in April-June quarter by annual rate of 3.3 percent, nearly twice as steep a fall as most economists had expected; it marks first time that Japan's economy has contracted for three consecutive quarters since Government began keeping such figures in 1955; economic data released suggest that core of economy slid even more rapidly than it did earlier in year, and there are fears that recession could get even worse; politicians have become deadlocked in bitter battle in Parliament over how to handle nation's jittery financial system (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the starkest sign so far of the depth of Japan's recession, the Government said today that the economy contracted in the April-June quarter by an annual rate of 3.3 percent, nearly twice as steep a fall as most economists had expected.</p>
        <p>This marked the first time that Japan's economy had contracted for three consecutive quarters since the Government began keeping such statistics in 1955. Moreover, the economic data released today suggest that the core of the economy slid even more rapidly than it did earlier in the year, and there are fears that the recession could get even worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the starkest sign so far of the depth of Japan's recession, the Government said today that the economy contracted in the April-June quarter by an annual rate of 3.3 percent, nearly twice as steep a fall as most economists had expected.</p>
        <p>This marked the first time that Japan's economy had contracted for three consecutive quarters since the Government began keeping such statistics in 1955. Moreover, the economic data released today suggest that the core of the economy slid even more rapidly than it did earlier in the year, and there are fears that the recession could get even worse.</p>
        <p>''The Japan economy is probably about to go through its darkest moment,'' said Taichi Sakaiya, Japan's top economic official, at a news conference today after the figures were announced. ''Tough times will continue.''</p>
        <p>That spells trouble for other crisis-hit countries in Asia and elsewhere. As the world's second-largest economy, Japan plays a major role in influencing the trend of growth in the global economy.</p>
        <p>The tough times in the real economy have also coursed through the financial markets, which have been particularly jittery recently because of instability abroad as well as in the wobbly financial system at home.</p>
        <p>The economic figures were announced shortly after the close of the busiest stock trading day of the year, but even without the news of the depth of the recession, stocks in Tokyo spiraled downward in their biggest single-day decline so far this year. The benchmark Nikkei average plunged 5.11 percent from its previous close to end at 13,916.98, down 749.05 points.</p>
        <p>The bond market rallied, sending the yield on the benchmark 10-year Government bond to a record low today of 0.78 percent, just after having set a record on Thursday. Japanese long-term bond yields are already the lowest long-term interest rates of any country in history.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, politicians have become deadlocked in a bitter battle in Parliament over how to handle the nation's jittery financial system. Just today, the main opposition party pulled out of negotiations on the bad-debt crisis, saying that it would not resume talks unless the Government abandoned its plan to use taxpayers' money to bail out the Long-Term Credit Bank, one of the nation's largest and weakest institutions.</p>
        <p>The economic data today showed that domestic demand was weak, with consumer spending falling significantly, along with corporate investment. Deflation is spreading, with prices, profits and pay for workers all dropping. With corporate profits plummeting, companies are being forced to cut back on production, investment spending and hiring, which in turn could lead consumption to fall further.</p>
        <p>''Japan is skirting the edge of a deflationary spiral,'' said Mr. Sakaiya, who heads the Economic Planning Agency.</p>
        <p>Some economists cautioned, however, that even if Japan dipped into a deflationary spiral, it did not mean that Japan was doomed to fall into an even deeper economic abyss.</p>
        <p>''When we talk about a deflationary spiral, the sense is that once it's started, we're finished, sucked into a vortex and there's no way out,'' said Christopher J. R. Calderwood, chief economist at Jardine Fleming Securities (Asia) Ltd. ''If we are there now, I don't think the economy will consume itself over the next two years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sakaiya of the Economic Planning Agency said that he expected economic performance in the third quarter also to be weak and that a recovery may not come for another two years. That is disappointing, given that the Government is now carrying out a giant fiscal stimulus package, worth about $123 billion.</p>
        <p>Tokyo has made a lot of noise about the billions of dollars it says it is spending on bolstering the economy. Yet, a consensus is building among economists that the spending in 1998 will be just barely above spending levels in 1997, when the economy was still growing, and not nearly enough to lift Japan out of a recession.</p>
        <p>''The implication for the market is that the Japanese economy still hasn't bottomed out, fiscal policy is not working and Japan is on the road to fiscal ruin,'' said Andrew Shipley, an economist at Schroders Japan Ltd.</p>
        <p>Although gross domestic product, or G.D.P., did not decline this time as much as it did in the first quarter, when the economy contracted by an annual 5.3 percent, the breakdown by sectors troubles some economists even more.</p>
        <p>Imports fell by about 25 percent on an annual basis, which hurts other Asian countries because Japan traditionally is a major importer of products from the rest of the region. But exports also fell, mainly because Asian countries, in turn, cut their purchases of Japanese products.</p>
        <p>''Even though G.D.P. looks a little better, the mix is very, very bad,'' said Jeffrey D. Young, an economist at Salomon Smith Barney in Tokyo. ''It's bad for Japan. It's bad for everyone else.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
