<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Commuter Hassles for Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="12SUBW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Repair Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Williamsburg Bridge (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Monte</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5D91731F931A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Commuter Hassles for Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONTE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Monte</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City will begin $150-million repair project on Williamsburg Bridge; subway service will be suspended for about five months; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The structural problems that have plagued the Williamsburg Bridge over the years will again inconvenience commuters starting in May, when city transportation officials are to suspend subway service across the bridge for roughly five months for a $150 million repair project.</p>
        <p>Brooklyn-bound service on the J, M and Z lines is to terminate at the Delancey Street station on the Lower East Side, and Manhattan-bound service will stop at Marcy Avenue in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. About 90,000 New Yorkers ride the lines each day, according to the Straphangers Campaign, a rider's advocacy group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The structural problems that have plagued the Williamsburg Bridge over the years will again inconvenience commuters starting in May, when city transportation officials are to suspend subway service across the bridge for roughly five months for a $150 million repair project.</p>
        <p>Brooklyn-bound service on the J, M and Z lines is to terminate at the Delancey Street station on the Lower East Side, and Manhattan-bound service will stop at Marcy Avenue in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. About 90,000 New Yorkers ride the lines each day, according to the Straphangers Campaign, a rider's advocacy group.</p>
        <p>The plan was first reported yesterday in Newsday. Transit officials said they were planning a campaign to notify the public about the service suspension.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make a whole lot of sense to talk about something that's happening eight months from now,'' said Albert O'Leary, a spokesman for New York City Transit. ''We can't tell you what our service plan is. We have a whole organization of people who are working on a service plan and we'll be working on a very agressive public information campaign to let people know how they can still travel around the city.''</p>
        <p>Transportation Department officials said the plan to suspend subway service is part of a $700 million, long-term repair project that started a decade ago, when engineers first expressed concerns about the bridge's structural integrity. The bridge was closed for two months in 1988 and emergency repairs were made.</p>
        <p>Since then, other repairs have been made on the 98-year-old bridge, frustrating both motorists and subway riders. In July 1996, city officials closed the bridge's four Brooklyn-bound traffic lanes for a two-year overhaul, snarling traffic throughout the Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>Repairs to the bridge's south roadway were completed in June, said Connie Crawford, chief engineer in the city's Department of Transportation.</p>
        <p>The bridge was also the site of an accident in June 1995 in which the motorman of a Manhattan-bound J train was killed and 54 passengers were injured when the J train smashed into an M train. That accident, which was not related to the structural condition of the bridge, led to widespread changes in subway speed limits and safety procedures.</p>
        <p>When next year's repairs begin, some riders from Queens may have the option of transferring to the L or E lines, said Andrew Albert, chairman of the New York City Transit Riders Council, a transit advocacy group appointed by the Governor.</p>
        <p>But riders from the Williamsburg, Bedford-Stuyvesant and Bushwick sections of Brooklyn could be severely affected, he warned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Albert called on the city to construct a bypass track for the J, M and Z lines, which he said would cost about $23 million. ''That's not a lot of money when you consider the entire cost of renovating the Williamsburg Bridge,'' he said. ''There are an awful lot of people who are going to be inconvenienced. This is going to add an hour to some people's commutes.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the commuters from Brooklyn, Mr. Albert added, ''Maybe the people inconvenienced are not influential enough for the city to construct the bypass track.''</p>
        <p>''It's difficult to imagine this happening in other places,'' Mr. Albert said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
