<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full Text of Findings Sent to Congress -- Part Six of Thirteen</title>
    <meta content="6STEX.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DD1431F931A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="6675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full Text of Findings Sent to Congress -- Part Six of Thirteen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IX. October-November 1997: United Nations' Job Offer</p>
        <p>Having learned that she would not be able to return to the White House, Ms. Lewinsky sought the President's help in finding a job in New York City. The President offered to place her at the United Nations. After initial enthusiasm, Ms. Lewinsky cooled on the idea of working at the U.N., and she prodded the President to get her a job in the private sector.</p>
        <p>A. October 10: Telephone Conversation</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President telephoned her at approximately 2:00 to 2:30 a.m. on Friday, October 10.(591) They spent much of the hour-and-a-half call arguing. ''[H]e got so mad at me, he must have been purple,'' she later recalled.(592)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IX. October-November 1997: United Nations' Job Offer</p>
        <p>Having learned that she would not be able to return to the White House, Ms. Lewinsky sought the President's help in finding a job in New York City. The President offered to place her at the United Nations. After initial enthusiasm, Ms. Lewinsky cooled on the idea of working at the U.N., and she prodded the President to get her a job in the private sector.</p>
        <p>A. October 10: Telephone Conversation</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President telephoned her at approximately 2:00 to 2:30 a.m. on Friday, October 10.(591) They spent much of the hour-and-a-half call arguing. ''[H]e got so mad at me, he must have been purple,'' she later recalled.(592)</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President said: ''If I had known what kind of person you really were, I wouldn't have gotten involved with you.''(593) He reminded Ms. Lewinsky that she had earlier promised, ''[i]f you just want to stop doing this, I'll . . . be no trouble.''(594) Ms. Lewinsky said she challenged the President: ''[T]ell me . . . when I've caused you trouble.''(595) The President responded, ''I've never worried about you. I've never been worried you would do something to hurt me.''(596)</p>
        <p>When the conversation shifted to her job search, Ms. Lewinsky complained that the President had not done enough to help her. He responded that, on the contrary, he was eager to help.(597) The President said that he regretted Ms. Lewinsky's transfer to the Pentagon and assured her that he would not have permitted it had he foreseen the difficulty in returning her to the White House.(598) Ms. Lewinsky told him that she wanted a job in New York by the end of October, and the President promised to do what he could.(599)</p>
        <p>B. October 11 Meeting</p>
        <p>At approximately 8:30 a.m. on Saturday, October 11, according to Ms. Lewinsky, Ms. Currie called and told her that the President wished to see her.(600) Ms. Lewinsky entered the White House at 9:36 a.m. and departed at 10:54 a.m.(601) The President entered the Oval Office at 9:52 a.m.(602)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky met with the President in the study, and they discussed her job search.(603) Ms. Lewinsky told the President that she wanted to pursue jobs in the private sector, and he told her to prepare a list of New York companies that interested her.(604) Ms. Lewinsky asked the President whether Vernon Jordan, a well-known Washington attorney who she knew was a close friend of the President and had many business contacts, might help her find a job.(605) According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President was receptive to the idea.(606)</p>
        <p>In a recorded conversation, Ms. Lewinsky said that, at the end of the October 11 meeting, she and the President joined Ms. Currie in the Oval Office. The President grabbed Ms. Lewinsky's arm and kissed her on the forehead.(607) He told her: ''I talked to Erskine [Bowles] about . . . trying to get John Hilley to give you . . . a good recommendation for your work here.''(608)</p>
        <p>Later, Ms. Lewinsky and Ms. Tripp discussed their concerns about the President's involvement in Ms. Lewinsky's job search. Specifically, Ms. Lewinsky was nervous about involving the President's Chief of Staff:</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky: Well, see, I don't really think  -- I'm going to tell him that I don't think Erskine should have anything to do with this. I don't think anybody who works there should.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tripp: I don't see how that's -- how that's a problem.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky: Because look at what happened with Webb Hubbell.(609)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky preferred that Vernon Jordan assist her in her job search:</p>
        <p>Ms. Tripp: Well, I don't remember during the Webb Hubbell thing, was Vernon mentioned?</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky: Yeah, but there's a big difference. I think somebody could construe, okay? Somebody could construe or say, ''Well, they gave her a job to shut her up. They made her happy . . . And he [Mr. Bowles] works for the government and shouldn't have done that.'' And with the other one [Mr. Jordan] you can't say that.(610)</p>
        <p>C. October 16-17: The ''Wish List''</p>
        <p>On October 16, Ms. Lewinsky sent the President a packet, which included what she called a ''wish list'' describing the types of jobs that interested her in New York City. (611) The note began: ''My dream had been to work in Communications or Strategic Planning at the White House. I am open to any suggestions that you may have on work that is similar to that or may intrigue me. The most important things to me are that I am engaged and interested in my work, I am not someone's administrative/ executive assistant, and my salary can provide me a comfortable living in NY.'' (612)</p>
        <p>She identified five public relations firms where she would like to work. (613) Ms. Lewinsky concluded by saying of the United Nations:</p>
        <p>''I do not have any interest in working there. As a result of what happened in April '96, I have already spent a year and a half at an agency in which I have no interest. I want a job where I feel challenged, engaged, and interested. I don't think the UN is the right place for me.'' (614)</p>
        <p>In a recorded conversation, Ms. Lewinsky said she wanted the President to take her list seriously and not ask her to settle for a U.N. job. (615) She said she hoped ''that if he starts to pick a bone with me and the U.N., he sure as hell doesn't do it on the phone. . . . I don't want to start getting into a screaming match with him on the phone.'' (616)</p>
        <p>In addition to the ''wish list,'' Ms. Lewinsky said she enclosed in the packet a pair of sunglasses and ''a lot of things in a little envelope,'' including some jokes, a card, and a postcard. (617) She said that she had written on the card: ''Wasn't I right that my hugs are better in person than in cards?'' (618) The postcard featured a ''very erotic'' Egon Schiele painting. (619) Ms. Lewinsky also enclosed a note with her thoughts on education reform. (620)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky testified that she felt that the President owed her a job for several reasons: Her relationship with him was the reason she had been transferred out of the White House; he had promised her a job and so far had done nothing to help her find one; and she had left the White House ''quietly,'' without making an issue of her relationship with the President. (623)</p>
        <p>D. The President Creates Options</p>
        <p>At some point around this time in the fall of 1997, Ms. Currie asked John Podesta, the Deputy Chief of Staff, to help Ms. Lewinsky find a job in New York. (624) Mr. Podesta testified that, during a Presidential trip to Latin America, he approached then-U.N. Ambassador William Richardson while aboard Air Force One and asked the Ambassador to consider a former White House intern for a position at the U.N. (626) At the time, Mr. Podesta could not recall the intern's name. (627) Ambassador Richardson and the President both testified that they never discussed Ms. Lewinsky with each other. (628)</p>
        <p>Ambassador Richardson returned from Latin America on Sunday, October 19. (629) Within a few days, his Executive Assistant, Isabelle Watkins, called Mr. Podesta's secretary and asked whether ''she knew anything about a resume that John was going to send us.'' (630) Mr. Podesta's secretary knew nothing about it and asked Mr. Podesta what to do; he instructed her to call Ms. Currie. (631) At 3:09 p.m. on October 21, Ms. Currie faxed Ms. Lewinsky's resume to the United Nations. (632)</p>
        <p>At 7:01 p.m., a six-minute call was placed to Ms. Lewinsky's apartment from a U.N. telephone number identified in State Department records as ''Ambassador Richardson's line.'' (633) Ms. Lewinsky testified that she spoke to Ambassador Richardson. A woman called, Ms. Lewinsky testified, and said, ''[H]old for Ambassador Richardson.''(634) Then the Ambassador himself came on the line: ''I remember, because I was shocked and I was . . . very nervous.'' (635) The purpose of the call was to schedule a job interview at a Watergate apartment the following week. (636) At odds with Ms. Lewinsky, the Ambassador and Ms. Watkins both testified that Ms. Watkins, not the Ambassador, spoke with Ms. Lewinsky. (637)</p>
        <p>A few days later, according to Ms. Lewinsky, the President called her. She had been upset because no one at the White House had prepared her for the Ambassador's recent call and because she did not want the White House to railroad her into taking the U.N. job. (638) She reiterated that she was eager to pursue other opportunities, especially in the private sector. (639) The President reassured her, promising that a U.N. position was just one of many options. (640)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky spoke to the President again one week later. Ms. Lewinsky testified that she told Ms. Currie to ask the President to call her to assuage her nervousness before the U.N. interview. (641)</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Lewinsky, on October 30, the night before the interview, the President did call. She characterized the conversation as a ''pep talk'': ''[H]e was trying to kind of build my confidence and reassure me.'' (642) The President told her to call Ms. Currie after the interview. (644) In his Jones deposition, the President indicated that he learned of her interview with Ambassador Richardson not from Ms. Lewinsky herself but from Ms. Currie. (645)</p>
        <p>E. The U.N. Interview And Job Offer</p>
        <p>On Friday morning, October 31, Ambassador Richardson and two of his assistants, Mona Sutphen and Rebecca Cooper, interviewed Ms. Lewinsky at the Watergate. (646) According to Ambassador Richardson, he ''listen[ed] while Mona and Rebecca were interviewing her.'' (647) Neither Ambassador Richardson nor any of his staff made inquiries, before or after the interview, about Ms. Lewinsky's prior work performance. (648)</p>
        <p>On Sunday, November 2, Ms. Lewinsky drafted a letter to Ms. Currie asking what to do in the event she received an offer from the U.N. (649) She wrote:</p>
        <p>''I became a bit nervous this weekend when I realized that Amb. Richardson said his staff would be in touch with me this week. As you know, the UN is supposed to be my back-up, but because VJ [Vernon Jordan] has been out of town, this is my only option right now. What should I say to Richardson's people this week when they call?'' (650)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky asked Ms. Currie to speak to the President about her problem: ''If you feel it's appropriate, maybe you could ask 'the big guy' what he wants me to do. Ahhhhh . . . anxiety!!!!!'' (651) Ms. Lewinsky also mentioned the President's promise to involve Vernon Jordan in her job search:</p>
        <p>''I don't think I told you that in my conversation last Thursday night with him that he said that he would ask you to set up a meeting between VJ and myself, once VJ got back. I assume he'll mention this to you at some point -- hopefully sooner rather than later! (652)</p>
        <p>Before Ms. Lewinsky sent this letter, in her recollection, she received an offer from the U.N. (653) Phone records reflect that, at 11:02 a.m. on November 3, a three-minute call was placed to Ms. Lewinsky from the U.N. line identified in State Department records as Ambassador Richardson's. (654) Ms. Lewinsky stated that she believes she spoke to Ambassador Richardson, who extended her a job offer. (655)</p>
        <p>According to his assistant, Ambassador Richardson made the decision to hire Ms. Lewinsky. Ms. Sutphen testified:</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Are you sure;' and he said, 'Yeah,  yeah, I'm sure, why. 'And I said . . . 'Are you sure, though you don't want to talk to anyone else. . . . And he said, 'No, no, I think it's fine; why don't you go ahead and give her an offer?'' (656)</p>
        <p>Ambassador Richardson and Ms. Sutphen both testified that Ms. Sutphen, not the Ambassador, extended the job offer to Ms. Lewinsky. They recalled that the offer was made a week or 10 days after the interview, though Ms. Sutphen, when shown the phone records, testified that the November 3 call to Ms. Lewinsky probably was the job offer. (657)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky testified that she told Ms. Currie about the offer and she probably also told the President directly. (658) Ms. Currie first testified that she had ''probably'' told the President about Ms. Lewinsky's U.N. offer, then testified that she had in fact told him, then testified that she could not remember, though she acknowledged that the President was interested in Ms. Lewinsky's getting a job. (659)</p>
        <p>When the President was asked in the Jones deposition whether he knew that Ms. Lewinsky had received the offer of a job at the U.N., he testified: ''I know that she interviewed for one. I don't know if she was offered one or not.'' (660)</p>
        <p>F. The U.N. Job Offer Declined</p>
        <p>Three weeks after she received an offer, on November 24, Ms. Lewinsky called Ms. Sutphen and asked for more time to consider the offer because she wanted to pursue possibilities in the private sector. (661) Ms. Sutphen told Ambassador Richardson, who, according to Ms. Sutphen, said the delay would be fine. (662) Over a month later, on January 5, 1998, Ms. Lewinsky finally turned down the job. (663)</p>
        <p>X. November 1997: Growing Frustration</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky met with Vernon Jordan, who promised to help her find a job in New York. November proved, however, to be a month of inactivity with respect to both Ms. Lewinsky's job search and her relationship with the President. Mr. Jordan did not meet with Ms. Lewinsky again, nor did he contact anyone in New York City on her behalf. Ms. Lewinsky became increasingly anxious about her inability to see the President. Except for a momentary encounter in mid-November, Ms. Lewinsky did not meet with the President between October 11 and December 5.</p>
        <p>A. Interrogatories Answered</p>
        <p>On November 3, 1997, the President answered Paula Jones's Second Set of Interrogatories. Two of those interrogatories asked the President to list any woman other than his wife with whom he had ''had,'' ''proposed having,'' or ''sought to have'' sexual relations during the time that he was Attorney General of Arkansas, Governor of Arkansas, and President of the United States.(664) President Clinton objected to the scope and relevance of both interrogatories and refused to answer them.(665)</p>
        <p>B. First Vernon Jordan Meeting</p>
        <p>In mid-October, the President had agreed to involve Vernon Jordan in Ms. Lewinsky's job search. (666) In a draft letter to Ms. Currie dated November 2, Ms. Lewinsky wrote that the President had ''said he would ask you to set up a meeting between VJ and myself.'' (667) According to Ms. Lewinsky, on November 3 or November 4, Ms. Currie told her to call Vernon Jordan's secretary to arrange a meeting. (668) Ms. Currie said she had spoken with Mr. Jordan and he was expecting Ms. Lewinsky's call. (669) In Ms. Lewinsky's account, Ms. Currie sought Mr. Jordan's aid at the President's direction. (670) Mr. Jordan likewise testified that, in his understanding, the President was behind Ms. Currie's request. (671)</p>
        <p>Ms. Currie testified at various points that she contacted Mr. Jordan on her own initiative; that the President ''probably'' talked with her about Ms. Lewinsky's New York job hunt; and that she could not recall whether the President was involved. (672) In his Jones deposition, the President was asked whether he did anything to facilitate a meeting between Mr. Jordan and Ms. Lewinsky. He testified:</p>
        <p>''I can tell you what my memory is. My memory is that Vernon said something to me about her coming in, Betty had called and asked if he [Mr. Jordan] would see her [Ms. Lewinsky]. .  .  . I'm sure if he said something to me about it I said something positive about it. I wouldn't have said anything negative about it.(673)''</p>
        <p>When pressed, the President testified that he did not think that he was the ''precipitating force'' in arranging the meeting between Mr. Jordan and Ms. Lewinsky. (674)</p>
        <p>At 8:50 a.m. on November 5, Mr. Jordan spoke with the President by telephone for five minutes. (675) Later that morning, Mr. Jordan and Ms. Lewinsky met in his office for about twenty minutes. (676) She told him that she intended to move to New York, and she named several companies where she hoped to work. (677) She showed him the ''wish list'' that she had sent the President on October 16. (678) Mr. Jordan said that he had spoken with the President about her and that she came ''highly recommended.'' (679) Concerning her job search, Mr. Jordan said: ''We're in business.'' (681)</p>
        <p>In the course of the day, Mr. Jordan placed four calls to Ms. Hernreich (whom he acknowledged calling when he wished to speak to the President (682) and one to Ms. Currie. (683) Mr. Jordan testified that he could not remember the calls, but ''[i]t is entirely possible'' that they concerned Monica Lewinsky. (684)</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan also visited the White House and met with the President at 2:00 p.m. that day. (685) Again, Mr. Jordan testified that he had ''no recollection'' of the substance of his conversation with the President. (686)</p>
        <p>On November 6, the day after meeting with Mr. Jordan, Ms. Lewinsky wrote him a thank-you letter: ''It made me happy to know that our friend has such a wonderful confidant in you.'' (687) Also on November 6, Ms. Lewinsky wrote in an email to a friend that she expected to hear from Mr. Jordan ''later next week.'' (688) The evidence indicates, though, that Mr. Jordan took no steps to help Ms. Lewinsky until early December, after she appeared on the witness list in the Jones case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan initially testified that he had ''no recollection of having met with Ms. Lewinsky on November 5.'' (689) When shown documentary evidence demonstrating that his first meeting with Ms. Lewinsky occurred in early November, he acknowledged that an early November meeting was ''entirely possible.'' (690) Mr. Jordan's failure to remember his November meeting with Ms. Lewinsky may indicate the low priority he attached to it at the time.</p>
        <p>C. November 13: The Zedillo Visit</p>
        <p>On Thursday, November 13, while Ernesto Zedillo, the President of Mexico, was in the White House, Ms. Lewinsky met very briefly with President Clinton in the private study. (691) Ms. Lewinsky's visit, which she described in an email as a ''hysterical escapade,'' was the culmination of days of phone calls and notes to Ms. Currie and the President. (692)</p>
        <p>Over the course of the week that preceded November 13, Ms. Lewinsky made several attempts to arrange a visit with the President. On Monday, November 10, in addition to making frequent calls to Ms. Currie, she sent the President a note asking for a meeting. (693)</p>
        <p>She hoped to see him on Tuesday, November 11 (Veterans Day), but he did not respond. (694) By courier, (695) she sent the President another note:</p>
        <p>''I asked you three weeks ago to please be sensitive to what I am going through right now and to keep in contact with me, and yet I'm still left writing notes in vain. I am not a moron. I know that what is going on in the world takes precedence, but I don't think what I have asked you for is unreasonable.'' (696)</p>
        <p>She added: ''This is so hard for me. I am trying to deal with so much emotionally, and I have nobody to talk to about it. I need you right now not as President, but as a man. PLEASE be my friend.'' (697)</p>
        <p>That evening, November 12, according to Ms. Lewinsky, the President called and invited her to the White House the following day. (698) In an email to a friend, Ms. Lewinsky wrote that she and the President ''talked for almost an hour.'' (699) She added: ''[H]e thought [N]ancy [Hernreich] (one of the meanies) would be out for a few hours on Thursday and I could come see him then.'' (700)</p>
        <p>The following morning, November 13, Ms. Lewinsky tried to arrange a visit with the President. She called repeatedly but suspected that Ms. Currie was not telling the President of her calls. (701) Around noon, Ms. Currie told Ms. Lewinsky that the President had left to play golf. Ms. Lewinsky, in her own words, ''went ballistic.'' (702)</p>
        <p>After the President returned from the Army-Navy Golf Course in the late afternoon, Ms. Lewinsky told Ms. Currie that she was coming to the White House to give him some gifts. (703) Ms. Currie suggested that Ms. Lewinsky wait in Ms. Currie's car in the White House parking lot. Ms. Lewinsky went to the White House only to find that the doors to Ms. Currie's car were locked. Ms. Lewinsky waited in the rain. (704)</p>
        <p>Ms. Currie eventually met her in the parking lot, and, in Ms. Lewinsky's words, they made a ''bee-line'' into the White House, sneaking up the back stairs to avoid other White House employees, particularly Presidential aide Stephen Goodin. (705) Ms. Lewinsky left two small gifts for the President with Ms. Currie, then waited alone for about half an hour in the Oval Office study. (706) In the study, Ms. Lewinsky saw several gifts she had given the President, including Oy Vey! The Things They Say: A Guide to Jewish Wit, Nicholson Baker's novel Vox, and a letter opener decorated with a frog. (707)</p>
        <p>The President finally joined Ms. Lewinsky in the study, where they were alone for only a minute or two. (708) Ms. Lewinsky gave him an antique paperweight in the shape of the White House. (709) She also showed him an email describing the effect of chewing Altoid mints before performing oral sex. Ms. Lewinsky was chewing Altoids at the time, but the President replied that he did not have enough time for oral sex. (710) They kissed, and the President rushed off for a State Dinner with President Zedillo. (711)</p>
        <p>D. November 14-December 4: Inability to See the President</p>
        <p>After this brief November 13 meeting, Ms. Lewinsky did not see the President again until the first week in December. Hoping to arrange a longer rendezvous, she sent the President several notes, as well as a cassette on which she recorded a message. (712)</p>
        <p>Along with her chagrin over not seeing the President, Ms. Lewinsky was frustrated that her job search had apparently stalled. A few days before Thanksgiving, she complained to Ms. Currie that she had not heard from Mr. Jordan. (713) Ms. Currie arranged for her to speak with him ''before Thanksgiving,'' while Ms. Lewinsky was in Los Angeles. Mr. Jordan told her to call him the following week to arrange another meeting. (714)</p>
        <p>In draft letters to the President, which were recovered from her Pentagon computer, Ms. Lewinsky reflected on the change in their relationship: ''[B]oth professionally and personally, .  .  . our personal relationship changing has caused me more pain. Do you realize that?'' (715) She asked for the President's understanding: ''I don't want you to think that I am not grateful for what you are doing for me now -- I'd probably be in a mental institute without it -- but I am consumed with this disappointment, frustration, and anger.'' Ms. Lewinsky rued the brevity of her November 13 visit with the President: ''All you .  .  . ever have to do to pacify me is see me and hold me,'' she wrote. ''Maybe that's asking too much.''(716)</p>
        <p>XI. December 5-18, 1997: The Witness List And Job Search</p>
        <p>On Friday, December 5, Paula Jones's attorneys faxed a list of their potential witnesses --  including Ms. Lewinsky -- to the President's personal attorneys. The following day, President Clinton saw Ms. Lewinsky in an unscheduled visit and then discussed the Jones case with his attorneys and Deputy White House Counsel Bruce Lindsey. A few days later, Ms. Lewinsky met with Mr. Jordan at his office, and he arranged interviews for Ms. Lewinsky at three companies. In the middle of the night on December 17, the President called and informed Ms. Lewinsky that she was on the witness list and that she might have to testify under oath in the Jones case.</p>
        <p>A. December 5: The Witness List</p>
        <p>On Friday December 5, 1997, attorneys for Paula Jones identified Ms. Lewinsky as a potential witness in Ms. Jones's sexual harassment case. (717) At 5:40 p.m., they faxed their witness list to the President's attorney, Robert Bennett. (718) Ms. Lewinsky, however, would not learn of her potential involvement in the Jones case for twelve more days, when the President informed her. (719)</p>
        <p>President Clinton was asked in the grand jury when he learned that Ms. Lewinsky's name was on the witness list. The President responded: ''I believe that I found out late in the afternoon on the sixth.'' (720)</p>
        <p>B. December 5: Christmas Party at the White House</p>
        <p>On Friday, December 5, Ms. Lewinsky returned from Department of Defense travel in Europe. (721) She asked Ms. Currie if the President could see her the next day, but Ms. Currie said he was busy meeting with his lawyers. (722) In the late afternoon, she attended a Christmas party at the White House with a Defense Department colleague. (723) Ms. Lewinsky exchanged a few words with the President in the reception line. (724)</p>
        <p>The Christmas reception encounter heightened Ms. Lewinsky's frustration. On the evening of December 5, she drafted an anguished letter to the President. (725) ''[Y]ou want me out of your life,'' she wrote. ''I guess the signs have been made clear for awhile --  not wanting to see me and rarely calling. I used to think it was you putting up walls.'' (727) She had purchased several gifts for him, and, she wrote, ''I wanted to give them to you in person, but that is obviously not going to happen.'' (728) Ms. Lewinsky reminded the President of his words during their October 10 telephone argument:</p>
        <p>I will never forget what you said that night we fought on the phone -- if you had known what I was really like you would never have gotten involved with me. I'm sure you're not the first person to have felt that way about me. I am sorry that this has been such a bad experience. (729)</p>
        <p>She concluded the letter: ''I knew it would hurt to say goodbye to you; I just never thought it would have to be on paper. Take care.'' (730)</p>
        <p>C. December 6: The Northwest Gate Incident</p>
        <p>1. Initial Visit and Rejection</p>
        <p>On the morning of Saturday, December 6, Ms. Lewinsky went to the White House to deliver the letter and gifts to the President. The gifts included a sterling silver antique cigar holder, a tie, a mug, a ''Hugs and Kisses'' box, and an antique book about Theodore Roosevelt. (731) Ms. Lewinsky planned to leave the parcel with Ms. Currie, who had told Ms. Lewinsky that the President would be busy with his lawyers and unable to see her. (732)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky arrived at the White House at approximately 10:00 a.m. She told the Secret Service uniformed officers at the Northwest Gate that she had gifts to drop off for the President, but that Ms. Currie did not know she was coming. (733) Ms. Lewinsky and the officers made several calls in an attempt to locate Ms. Currie. (734) The officers eventually invited Ms. Lewinsky inside the guard booth. (735) When Ms. Currie learned that Ms. Lewinsky was at the Northwest Gate, she sent word that the President ''already had a guest in the [O]val,'' so the officers should have Ms. Lewinsky wait there for about 40 minutes. (736)</p>
        <p>While Ms. Lewinsky was waiting, one officer mentioned that Eleanor Mondale was in the White House. (737) Ms. Lewinsky correctly surmised that the President was meeting with Ms. Mondale, rather than his lawyers, and she was ''livid.'' (738) She stormed away, called and berated Ms. Currie from a pay phone, and then returned to her Watergate apartment. (740)</p>
        <p>Hands shaking and almost crying, Ms. Currie informed several Secret Service officers that the President was ''irate'' that someone had disclosed to Ms. Lewinsky whom he was meeting with. (741) Ms. Currie told Sergeant Keith Williams, a supervisory uniformed Secret Service Officer, that if he ''didn't find out what was going on, someone could be fired.'' (742) She also told Captain Jeffrey Purdie, the Secret Service watch commander for the uniformed division at the time, that the President was ''so upset he wants somebody fired over this.'' (743)</p>
        <p>2. Ms. Lewinsky Returns to The White House</p>
        <p>From her apartment, Ms. Lewinsky reached the President on the phone.(745) According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President was angry that she had ''made a stink'' and said that ''it was none of my business . . . what he was doing.'' (746)</p>
        <p>Then, to Ms. Lewinsky's surprise, the President invited her to visit him. (747) She testified that ''none of the other times that we had really fought on the phone did it end up resulting in a visit that day.'' (748) WAVES records reflect that Ms. Lewinsky was cleared to enter the White House at 12:52 p.m. and exited at 1:36 p.m. (749)</p>
        <p>During their meeting, Ms. Lewinsky told the President that Mr. Jordan had done nothing to help her find a job. (750) The President responded, ''Oh, I'll talk to him. I'll get on it.'' (751)</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky testified that, overall, she had a ''really nice'' and ''affectionate'' visit with the President. (752) In an email to a friend a few days later, she wrote that, although ''things have been crazy with the creep . . . I did have a wonderful visit with him on Saturday. When he doesn't put his walls up, it is always heavenly.''(753)</p>
        <p>3. ''Whatever Just Happened Didn't Happen''</p>
        <p>Later that day (December 6), the uniformed Secret Service officers at the Northwest Gate were told that no one would be fired -- so long as they remained quiet. According to Sergeant Williams, Ms. Currie said that, if the officers did not ''tell a lot of people what had happened, then nothing would happen.'' (754)</p>
        <p>The President told Captain Jeffrey Purdie, the Secret Service watch commander for the uniformed division at the time, ''I hope you use your discretion.'' (755) Captain Purdie interpreted the President's remark to mean that Captain Purdie ''wasn't going to say anything,'' and he in turn told all of the officers involved not to discuss the incident. (756) One officer recalled that Captain Purdie told him and other officers, ''Whatever just happened didn't happen.'' (757) Captain Purdie told another officer, ''I was just in the Oval Office with the President and he wants somebody's ass out here . . . As far as you're concerned . . . [t]his never happened.'' (758) In response, that officer, who considered the Northwest Gate incident a ''major event,'' ''just shook [his] head'' and ''started making a set of [his] own notes'' in order to document the incident. (759)</p>
        <p>Captain Purdie recommended to his supervisor, Deputy Chief Charles O'Malley, that ''no paperwork be generated'' regarding the Northwest Gate incident because ''Ms. Currie was satisfied with the way things were handled.'' (760) According to Captain Purdie, Deputy Chief O'Malley agreed, and no record of the incident was made. (761) Deputy Chief O'Malley testified that the meeting between the President and Captain Purdie was the only occasion he could recall in fourteen years at the White House where a President directly addressed a job performance issue with a uniformed division supervisor. (762)</p>
        <p>The President was questioned in the grand jury about the incident at the Northwest Gate. He testified that he knew that Ms. Lewinsky had become upset upon learning that Ms. Mondale was in the White House ''to see us that day.'' (763) He testified: ''As I remember, I had some other work to do that morning . . .'' (764) The President said that the disclosure of information that day was ''inappropriate'' and ''a mistake,'' but he could not recall whether he wanted a Secret Service officer fired or gave any such orders. (765) He thought that the officers ''were . . . told not to let it happen again, and I think that's the way it should have been handled.'' (766) When asked if he told Captain Purdie that he hoped that he could count on his discretion, the President stated, ''I don't remember anything I said to him in that regard.'' (767)</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President later indicated to her that he had concerns about the discretion of the Secret Service uniformed officers. On December 28 she asked how Paula Jones's attorneys could have known enough to place her on the witness list. The President replied that the source might be Linda Tripp or ''the uniformed officers.'' (768)</p>
        <p>D. The President Confers With His Lawyers</p>
        <p>Deputy Counsel Bruce Lindsey testified that he met with the President and the President's personal attorney, Robert Bennett, at around 5:00 p.m. on December 6 to discuss the Jones case. (769) According to Mr. Lindsey, it was ''likely'' that he learned about Ms. Lewinsky's appearance on the witness list in that meeting. (770)</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, at around 12:00 p.m. (after Ms. Lewinsky stormed away from the Northwest Gate but before she returned and saw the President), Mr. Lindsey had received a page: ''Call Betty ASAP.'' (771) Mr. Lindsey testified that he did not recall the page, nor did he know, at the time, that Ms. Lewinsky had visited the White House. (772)</p>
        <p>E. Second Jordan Meeting</p>
        <p>The next day (Sunday, December 7), Mr. Jordan visited the White House and met with the President. (774) Mr. Jordan testified that he was ''fairly certain'' that he did not discuss the Jones suit or Ms. Lewinsky. (775)</p>
        <p>On Thursday, December 11, Ms. Lewinsky had her second meeting with Mr. Jordan. (776) Ms. Lewinsky testified that they discussed her job search, and Mr. Jordan told her to send letters to three business contacts that he provided her. Mr. Jordan noted that Ms. Lewinsky was anxious to get a job as quickly as possible, and he took action. (777) In the course of the day, Mr. Jordan placed calls on her behalf to Peter Georgescu, Chairman and Chief Executive Officer at Young &amp; Rubicam; Richard Halperin, Executive Vice President and Special Counsel to the Chairman of MacAndrews &amp; Forbes Holdings, Inc. (majority stockholder of Revlon); and Ursula Fairbairn, Executive Vice-President, Human Resources and Quality, of American Express. (778) Mr. Jordan told Ms. Lewinsky to keep him informed of the progress of her job search. (779)</p>
        <p>At one point in the conversation, according to Ms. Lewinsky, Mr. Jordan said, ''[Y]ou're a friend of the President.'' (780) This prompted Ms. Lewinsky to reveal that she ''didn't really look at him as the President''; rather, she ''reacted to him more as a man and got angry at him like a man and just a regular person.'' (781) When Mr. Jordan asked why Ms. Lewinsky got angry at the President, she replied that she became upset ''when he doesn't call me enough or see me enough.'' (782) Ms. Lewinsky testified that Mr. Jordan advised her to take her frustrations out on him rather than the President. (783) According to Ms. Lewinsky, Mr. Jordan summed up the situation: ''You're in love, that's what your problem is.'' (785)</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan recalled a similar conversation, in which Ms. Lewinsky complained that the President did not see her enough, although he thought it took place during a meeting eight days later. He testified that he felt the need to remind Ms. Lewinsky that the President is the ''leader of the free world'' and has competing obligations. (786)</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan is ''certain'' that he had a conversation with the President about Ms. Lewinsky at some point after this December 11 meeting. (787) He told the President that he would be trying to get Ms. Lewinsky a job in New York. (788) Mr. Jordan testified that the President ''was aware that people were trying to get jobs for her, that Podesta was trying to help her, that Bill Richardson was trying to help her, but that she really wanted to work in the private sector.'' (789)</p>
        <p>F. Early Morning Phone Call</p>
        <p>On December 15, 1997, Paula Jones's lawyers served President Clinton with her second set of document requests by overnight mail. These requests asked the President to ''produce documents that related to communications between the President and Monica Lewisky'' [sic]. (790) This was the first Paula Jones discovery request to refer to Monica Lewinsky by name.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky testified that in the early-morning hours of December 17, at roughly 2:00 or 2:30 a.m., she received a call from the President. (791) The call lasted about half an hour. (792)</p>
        <p>The President gave Ms. Lewinsky two items of news: Ms. Currie's brother had died in a car accident, and Ms. Lewinsky's name had appeared on the witness list in the Jones case. (793) According to Ms. Lewinsky, the President said ''it broke his heart'' to see her name on the witness list. (794) The President told her that she would not necessarily be subpoenaed; if she were, he ''suggested she could sign an affidavit to try to satisfy [Ms. Jones's] inquiry and not be deposed.'' (795)</p>
        <p>The President told Ms. Lewinsky to contact Ms. Currie in the event she were subpoenaed. (796) He also reviewed one of their established cover stories. He told Ms. Lewinsky that she ''should say she visited the [White House] to see Ms. Currie and, on occasion when working at the [White House], she brought him letters when no one else was around.'' (797) The President's advice ''was . . . instantly familiar to [Ms. Lewinsky].'' (798) She testified that the President's use of this ''misleading'' story amounted to a continuation of their pre-existing pattern. (799)</p>
        <p>Later in the conversation, according to Ms. Lewinsky, the President said he would try to get Ms. Currie to come in over the weekend so that Ms. Lewinsky could visit and he could give her several Christmas presents. (800) Ms. Lewinsky replied that, since Ms. Currie's brother had just died, perhaps they should ''let Betty be.'' (801)</p>
        <p>In his grand jury appearance, the President was questioned about the December 17 phone call. He testified that, although he could not rule it out, he did not remember such a call. (802) The President was also asked whether in this conversation, or a conversation before Ms. Lewinsky's name came up in the Jones case, he instructed her to say that she was coming to bring letters. The President answered: ''I might well have said that.'' (803)</p>
        <p>But when asked whether he ever said anything along these lines after Ms. Lewinsky had been identified on the witness list, the President answered: ''I don't recall whether I might have done something like that.'' (804) He speculated that he might have suggested this explanation in the context of a call from a reporter. (805) Nonetheless, he testified, in the context of the Jones case, ''I never asked her to lie.'' (806)</p>
        <p>G. Job Interviews</p>
        <p>On December 18, Ms. Lewinsky had two job interviews in New York City. At MacAndrews &amp; Forbes, she met with Executive Vice President and Special Counsel to the Chairman Richard Halperin, who viewed the interview as ''an accommodation for Vernon Jordan.'' (807) At Burson-Marstellar, she interviewed with Celia Berk, Managing Director of Human Resources. (808) A few days later, on December 23, Ms. Lewinsky interviewed in Washington, D.C., with Thomas Schick, Executive Vice President, Corporate Affairs and Communications, of American Express.( 809)</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
