<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DE153DF935A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-11  YELTSIN APPEARS TO WIN VOTE  Russian voters gave what looked to be firm support for Boris Yeltsin, while demanding new elections for the Congress of People's Deputies. The first official results are not expected until today.  A1  To support Boris Yeltsin, voters have to negate a negative.  A10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-11  YELTSIN APPEARS TO WIN VOTE  Russian voters gave what looked to be firm support for Boris Yeltsin, while demanding new elections for the Congress of People's Deputies. The first official results are not expected until today.  A1  To support Boris Yeltsin, voters have to negate a negative.  A10</p>
        <p>EUROPE HESITATES ON AIR STRIKES  European Community ministers backed away from approving air srtikes against Serbs in Bosnia, despite increasing frustration as the war there enters its second year.  A1  SERBS FACING TOUGHER SANCTIONS  Bosnian Serbs rejected the U.N. plan to put an end to the fighting in Bosnia and Herzegovina, automatically putting into effect tougher sanctions against Yugoslavia.  A8  Srebrenica is "an open jail," a Security Council team said.  A8  A lawyer for the United Nations cast doubt on a war-crimes trial.  A9  JAPAN AVERTS A GHOST TOWN  When Nippon Steel closed a factory in Japan, the nation's corporate tradition insured that a factory town did not also shut down.  A1  ISRAEL CONFRONTS LABOR ETHIC  The shutdown of the West Bank and Gaza Strip, keeping as many as 120,000 Palestinians from their jobs, has forced Israelis to come to grips with their own work habits.  A3  POPE MAKES RARE ALBANIA VISIT  The Pope's visit to Albania prompted a familiar question: Having promoted change in Eastern Europe, how can his church wield the same influence in the Balkans?  A10  CONGRESS-ARMY FACE-OFF IN PERU  Tension is rising in the Peruvian military as the new Congress investigates the Army's role in the killings of nine university students and a professor who were said to be suspected members of Shining Path, the Maoist rebel group.  A11  I.R.A. SAYS IT PLANTED BOMB  The I.R.A. admitted it had planted the deadly bomb that exploded Saturday in London's financial district. Despite extensive damage, officials expect financial markets to operate near normal today.  A2  National A12-15, B8-10  HOMOSEXUALS DEMAND RIGHTS  Hundreds of thousands of gay Americans and their supporters rallied in the capital, celebrating the right to be homosexual and demanding freedom from discrimination.  A1  A MOVEMENT'S TURNING POINT?  News Analysis: The march in Washington is bound to mark a turning point in a movement that until recent years was largely obscured from public view.  A1  Tens of thousands of people from the New York area joined the rally.  B8  HEALTH PLAN TO EXEMPT BUSINESS  Confidential papers from President Clinton's health-care task force show that advisers have tentatively decided to let the nation's biggest companies serve as their own health insurers, bypassing the regional insurance pools that would serve as the plan's core.  A1  OKLAHOMA TORNADO KILLS 7  State troopers sealed off roads around Catoosa, Okla., to prevent looting and National Guardsmen searched for more victims of a tornado that killed at least seven people Saturday night.  A12  JOBS WORRY ADMINISTRATION  Some Administration officials worry that the overhaul of the military and health care industries, which powered the boom of the 1980's, could jeopardize the President's promise to create eight million jobs by the end of 1996.  A15  CLINTON DEFENDS FIRST 100 DAYS  President Clinton defended the accomplishments of his first 100 days in office, saying he had been judged too early and too harshly by his opponents and by the press.  B9  Ross Perot urged people to voice opposition to Clinton policies.  B9  TEXAS CULT'S FINAL DAY  A portrait of the final day inside the Branch Davidian cult's compound and the events leading to the fire that killed 86 people was compiled from interviews with survivors' lawyers and Government officials.  A1  Investigators identified a body retrieved from the compound.  B10  WARNING ON GAMBLING BOOM  Gambling experts warn that the boom in floating casinos on the Missippi and in the Gulf Coast states could prove ruinous for revenue searchers and bettors alike unless the states establish boundaries and common wagering standards.  A12  GROUNDWORK IN BANK FRAUD TRIAL  Prosecutors in the fraud trial of Robert A. Altman have begun laying the groundwork they say will show that Mr. Altman knew that four Arab investors he represented in the takeover of an American bank holding company were illegal front men for the Bank of Commerce and Credit International.  A14  Metro Digest B1  Arts/Entertainment C11-18  The directorial path of Martha Coolidge.  C11  Japanese architect wins Pritzker Prize.  C18  Theater: "Blood Brothers." C11  Music: Cecilia Bartoli's American debut.  C11  Einsturzende Neubaten at Roseland.C11  Dance: In Review.  C13  Books: "The Real Anita Hill," by David Brock.  C18  Television: Benevolent journey to Peru.  C16  Editorials/Op-Ed A16-17  Editorials  For the Middle East, a fresh start.  Officers and gentlemen? Hardly.  New voices for a changed world.  Justice for Yankel Rosenbaum.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: Speak for America.  William Safire: 1st quarter report.  Diana Edensword and Gary Milhollin: Iraq's bomb -- an update.  Business Digest D1  Obituaries B11  Nancy Quinn, the artistic director of Young Playwrights.</p>
        <p>Sports C1-8  Baseball: Padres nip Mets.  C7  Yankees hold off Mariners.  C7  Canseco lifts Rangers.  C7  Tigers continue torrid pace.  C7  Phillies roll on.  C6  Basketball: Knicks defeat Bulls.  C1  Nets lose to Pistons.  C5  Playoff preview.  C5  Columns: Anderson on the N.F.L. draft C3  On Pro Basketball C5  Football: Jets obtain Johnson and draft Jones.  C1, C3  Giants select Strahan, defensive end.  C2  Patriots make Bledsoe top pick in draft.  C2  Hockey: Devils stay alive in playoffs.  C1  Islanders' incredible run in playoff overtime.  C4  Blues eliminate Blackhawks.  C4  Tennis: A tournament throwback.  C2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
