<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D6123CF935A15757C0A965958260" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY  CRIME: ANY IS TOO MUCH</p>
        <p>The frustrated cry against crime that echoed during David N. Dinkins's first summer as Mayor is reverberating again. This time, it is being sounded by Mr. Dinkins's own Police Commissioner. Reported crime may be down, but the public's threshold for pain keeps going up. Which is precisely the point Senator Moynihan was making earlier this month when, in remarks that miffed the Mayor, Mr. Moynihan compared New York with the more stable city he remembered from his youth 50 years ago. Metro Matters. B2. BURNED UP OVER A CIGARETTE BILLBOARD</p>
        <p>To understand how a billboard promoting cigarettes in Shea Stadium has come to be a political thorn for Mayor Dinkins, it is helpful to think of Spider-Man, the comic-book vigilante forever at odds with city leaders. The billboard is a Marlboro advertisement under the huge video screen in left-center field, making, anti-smoking advocates say, a dangerous connection between smoking and athletic prowess. Spider-Man is a childhood hero of Joseph W. Cherner, a once and probably future Wall Street bond trader who as head of a small anti-tobacco group has used his wealth and drive to back Mr. Dinkins into a political corner. B3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY  CRIME: ANY IS TOO MUCH</p>
        <p>The frustrated cry against crime that echoed during David N. Dinkins's first summer as Mayor is reverberating again. This time, it is being sounded by Mr. Dinkins's own Police Commissioner. Reported crime may be down, but the public's threshold for pain keeps going up. Which is precisely the point Senator Moynihan was making earlier this month when, in remarks that miffed the Mayor, Mr. Moynihan compared New York with the more stable city he remembered from his youth 50 years ago. Metro Matters. B2. BURNED UP OVER A CIGARETTE BILLBOARD</p>
        <p>To understand how a billboard promoting cigarettes in Shea Stadium has come to be a political thorn for Mayor Dinkins, it is helpful to think of Spider-Man, the comic-book vigilante forever at odds with city leaders. The billboard is a Marlboro advertisement under the huge video screen in left-center field, making, anti-smoking advocates say, a dangerous connection between smoking and athletic prowess. Spider-Man is a childhood hero of Joseph W. Cherner, a once and probably future Wall Street bond trader who as head of a small anti-tobacco group has used his wealth and drive to back Mr. Dinkins into a political corner. B3.</p>
        <p>NO BILLS AND NO FARE CARDS</p>
        <p>Installing computerized fare boxes in New York City's buses at the same time that computerized turnstiles were being put into subway stations once seemed like a good idea to transit officials. But it is no longer a feasible one. Metrocard, the plastic fare-card system that is expected to replace tokens, is still scheduled to debut in a few subway stations in December and to be operating in 69 stations by the time it is formally introduced next March. But putting automated fare-collection equipment aboard the city's 3,450 buses will not be completed until late 1995, according to a report by the Transit Authority. B3. 'IMPRUDENCE' IN JOBS PROGRAM SUGGESTED</p>
        <p>The City Council Speaker Vallone said that some Council members "may have acted imprudently" in awarding jobs in a city-sponsored youth employment program to the relatives of employees, political allies or friends. Through a spokeswoman, Peg Breen, Mr. Vallone denied that any members had acted improperly. But he said that the appearance of impropriety might demand that more specific guidelines for the selection process be established. B3. REGION  FATAL SINKHOLE PROMPTS FEAR</p>
        <p>Like many other children in North Brunswick, N.J., 8-year-old Nadia Fraser had a restless sleep Saturday night. "I was scared that I was going to fall through the bed," she said, standing within yards of a patch of grassy ground that mysteriously gave way on Saturday and pulled a 7-year-old to his death. "I feel very sorry about the boy." For the children of the North Brunswick Manor Apartments, where the boy, Kwami Sharif, had lived with his parents and twin brother for about a year, it was a surreal day of unfamiliar emotions and fears. B6. PATCHING TOGETHER A WILDLIFE REFUGE</p>
        <p>Piece by piece, salt marsh by salt marsh, environmentalists and the Federal Government are pushing to preserve the last tracts of undeveloped shoreline along Barnegat Bay, the shallow 75-square-mile estuary that is one of the least heralded but most important coastal resources in the northeastern United States. The United States Fish and Wildlife Service, aided by local and national conservation groups, has expanded its Edwin B. Forsythe National Wildlife Refuge northward along the New Jersey coast to acquire open marshland squeezed between condominiums and expensive waterfront homes that have spread along the rim of the bay over the last four decades. B6. CAMPAIGNING FOR COMPTROLLER</p>
        <p>Make no mistake. The competition to fill the unexpired term of the New York State Comptroller Regan will be decided less by issues of substance than by political considerations like electability and ticket balancing. Each of the leading candidates -- Carol Bellamy, H. Carl McCall and Fernando Ferrer -- have said they will be more aggressive than Mr. Regan in using the pension system's clout to influence corporate behavior. B6. Chronicle B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
