<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stamps</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Pastimes Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STAMPS (POSTAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLECTORS AND COLLECTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LINN'S STAMP NEWS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEALEY, BARTH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAZZEI, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, RICHARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WHO'S WHO ON US STAMPS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6113EF933A05755C0A967958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stamps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barth Healey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEALEY, BARTH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who's Who</p>
        <p>Collectors wondering who's who on United States stamps can now find the answers in a useful book by Richard Thomas. Published by Linn's Stamp News, its title is, not surprisingly, "Who's Who on U.S. Stamps."</p>
        <p>Many of the personalities on stamps are obscure: Who, for example, was Philip Mazzei, who appears on a 40-cent airmail stamp issued in 1980? (He was an Italian-born aide to Jefferson, and he was chosen as the subject for a stamp under pressure from the Italian Government.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who's Who</p>
        <p>Collectors wondering who's who on United States stamps can now find the answers in a useful book by Richard Thomas. Published by Linn's Stamp News, its title is, not surprisingly, "Who's Who on U.S. Stamps."</p>
        <p>Many of the personalities on stamps are obscure: Who, for example, was Philip Mazzei, who appears on a 40-cent airmail stamp issued in 1980? (He was an Italian-born aide to Jefferson, and he was chosen as the subject for a stamp under pressure from the Italian Government.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas's book answers the question, and thus could serve as a handy reference work for anyone who might need quick reference to some lesser-known personalities. Each biography is about 300 words and is illustrated with an appropriate stamp.</p>
        <p>There is one annoying lapse: On stamps with more than one portrait, the biographies do not indicate who is on the left and the right.</p>
        <p>Often the stamps themselves are labeled, but reading them often requires a magnifying glass.</p>
        <p>And with some stamps, like the two 31-cent Wilbur and Orville Wright stamps of 1978, the Postal Service did not supply the left-to-right identifications. It would have been generous of Linn's to do so.</p>
        <p>There are 413 biographies here, from Abigail Adams to Babe Didrikson Zaharias, with only one notable omission: No one seems to be able to identify Lieut. Thomas Grosvenor, whose portrait, by John Trumbull, appears on a 6-cent stamp issued in 1968 honoring Trumbull. There is also no attempt to identify everyone in the many group paintings that appeared during the Bicentennial series.</p>
        <p>And it is not true, as Mr. Thomas maintains, that groups like the soldiers on the 1945 Army issue are anonymous. Twenty-seven of those men have been identified from the Associated Press photograph that served as a model for the stamp.</p>
        <p>The book is $14.95 softbound and $30 hardbound, postpaid, from Linn's, Box 29, Sidney, Ohio 45365.  Lives of the Forgers</p>
        <p>Linn's has also published an interesting volume by Varro E. Tyler, "Philatelic Forgers: Their Lives and Works." Again, the short biographies are always illuminating, even though the work would have benefited greatly from more generous illustrations of the forgeries It is worthwhile for warning collectors who may just be getting started in a new area.</p>
        <p>"Philatelic Forgers" is available from Linn's for $14.95 softbound and $30 hardbound, postpaid.  Reviewing 1990</p>
        <p>Linn's has also published its latest yearbook, this one covering United States stamps issued last year.</p>
        <p>The yearbook, by George Amick, is exhaustive, including details on preliminary and rejected designs, printing data and historical footnotes about personalities.</p>
        <p>"Yearbook 1990" is available from Linn's for $18 softbound and $30 hardbound, postpaid.  Soviet Republics</p>
        <p>Decentralization of a sort has come to Soviet philately.</p>
        <p>Beginning next year, four stamps a year will be dedicated to each of the 15 members of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, according to a recent announcement by the central Government's Ministry of Communications. Each republic will select the subjects, and the stamps will bear inscriptions in the language of the republic involved, as well as the Russian Cyrillic notation for U.S.S.R. Post.</p>
        <p>The Baltic republics of Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia, which have been issuing their own stamps for the last year, are to take part in the program, the ministry said, but they did not sign the official protocol.</p>
        <p>Some stamps from the Baltics, though officially recognized only within the three republics, have appeared on mail that has reached foreign destinations without postage-due charges.</p>
        <p>Regional stamps like those planned in the Soviet Union have been issued in Britain since 1958 for Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, and Japan has begun to issue provincial issues with greater enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Soviet stamps are sold in the United States by Unicover World Trade Corporation, 1 Unicover Center, Cheyenne, Wyo. 82008; (800) 443-4225. HONORING GULF SERVICE</p>
        <p>A stamp honoring those who served in the war against Iraq is to be issued Tuesday in Washington.</p>
        <p>The 29-cent stamp has a pale blue background and shows the Southwest Asia service medal hanging from a sand-colored ribbon with red, white, blue, green and black stripes; the five colors appear in the flags of the United States and its Arab allies in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>The medal shows a tank, an armored personnel carrier, a ship, a helicopter and a plane against a background of sand and sea, to reflect the roles of the five military services.</p>
        <p>The stamp is to be issued in booklets of 20 and in panes of 50.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
