<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking Shorter Deal, Olerud Signs With Mets</title>
    <meta content="25METS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olerud, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2D61F3BF936A15752C1A961958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking Shorter Deal, Olerud Signs With Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets re-sign first baseman John Olerud (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The phone rang yesterday afternoon in the Arizona home of Tom Robson, the Mets' hitting coach. The soft, polite voice on the other end belonged to John Olerud.</p>
        <p>''Well, you're stuck with me another two years,'' Olerud told Robson, who, like other members of the Mets' staff and front office, was greatly relieved. Olerud, a free-agent first baseman who hit 22 homers and drove in 102 runs last season, agreed to return for a two-year, $8 million deal -- after surprisingly rejecting a three-year offer from the Mets for $12 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The phone rang yesterday afternoon in the Arizona home of Tom Robson, the Mets' hitting coach. The soft, polite voice on the other end belonged to John Olerud.</p>
        <p>''Well, you're stuck with me another two years,'' Olerud told Robson, who, like other members of the Mets' staff and front office, was greatly relieved. Olerud, a free-agent first baseman who hit 22 homers and drove in 102 runs last season, agreed to return for a two-year, $8 million deal -- after surprisingly rejecting a three-year offer from the Mets for $12 million.</p>
        <p>Finally, something good occurred for the Mets, after a series of mishaps and failed negotiations. Since late September, catcher Todd Hundley had reconstructive elbow surgery that will sideline him into next season; the Mets' bid for Montreal pitcher Pedro Martinez was rebuffed; an overture for Seattle pitcher Randy Johnson fell short, and a potential deal for the Florida slugger Gary Sheffield fell apart, at least temporarily.</p>
        <p>The re-signing of Olerud may not be exactly what the Mets co-owner Fred Wilpon had in mind when he indicated that he expected his team to make a significant move this off season. But wooing Olerud back to New York, and away from an offer from the Mariners, is progress. ''I was anxious,'' said Bobby Valentine, the Mets' manager. ''He's such a good player and had such a good year. Really, I think he wanted to come back with us the whole time.''</p>
        <p>Olerud joined the Mets as damaged goods before last season, following two years of diminished run production. When Toronto dealt him to the Mets, the Blue Jays agreed to pay $5 million of his $6.5 million salary for last year, and Cito Gaston, his former manager, wondered aloud if Olerud possessed the temperament to play in New York.</p>
        <p>But Olerud, encouraged by Robson to return to his previous hitting style and abandon the strategy of trying to pull every pitch, hit .356 the first month of the season, with 11 doubles. Olerud appeared to wear down in midseason, before an increased emphasis in weight training propelled him through the final two months. He drove in 36 runs in his final 160 at-bats, finishing with a .294 average, and after the final game Valentine told Olerud he wanted him back.</p>
        <p>Olerud was intrigued by the idea of signing with Seattle, in the state where he was raised, but the Mariners -- who are believed to have offered Olerud a one-year deal for far less than the salary dangled by the Mets -- could not compete with the Mets' proposal. ''New York was always the club that expressed the most interest in getting me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>By taking a deal for two years, rather than for three, Olerud passed up a guaranteed $4 million to get another chance at free agency following the 1999 season, when he will be 31. ''I wanted to keep it short, and that gives everybody a little more flexibility,'' he said. ''That gives me the chance to go out and have a couple of really strong years.''</p>
        <p>The talks regarding Sheffield are dead, but in the same way movie ghouls die; resurrection is always possible. Executives with other teams believe Florida will be forced to deal with the Mets because of the Marlins' commitment to paring payroll and the apparent lack of interest in Sheffield from other teams.</p>
        <p>The Mets wanted Florida to assume $20 million of Sheffield's $61 million contract and could ask for pitcher Kevin Brown as well. Dave Dombrowski, the Marlins' general manager, told another interested executive last week that Brown and Sheffield were being discussed in the same blockbuster deal.</p>
        <p>Whether it be Brown or Randy Johnson, the Mets are still in the market for a No. 1 starting pitcher, said Steve Phillips, their general manager. He said he has no interest in signing any of the top three free-agent pitchers -- Darryl Kile, Andy Benes or Wilson Alvarez -- because of their contract demands.</p>
        <p>The Mets also are trying to acquire a left-handed middle reliever. Besides Florida's Dennis Cook, they expressed interest in Tony Fossas, the veteran who pitched for St. Louis last year, and Rich Rodriguez, formerly of the San Francisco Giants.</p>
        <p>Talks With Japanese Pitcher</p>
        <p>The Mets are close to signing Jyoei Ushiromatsu, a left-handed pitcher from Japan, according to an independent international scout. Ushiromatsu, who is 6 feet 1 inch and 180 pounds, was not selected by the Japanese professional teams in a draft last week and is considering going to college. The Mets, however, intend to sign and develop the pitcher, who attends Ohmagario Technical High School, in their own system, and have received the needed clearance from Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Mets agreed to terms with Jae-Woong Seo, a Korean pitcher. However, that deal -- worth more than $1 million -- could be in trouble because of visa problems.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
