<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using New Digital Technology, MTV Adds Specialized Channels</title>
    <meta content="25MTV.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Digital and High-Definition Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mtv Networks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Music Television Networks Inc (Mtv)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television Sets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DE1F3BF936A15752C1A961958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using New Digital Technology, MTV Adds Specialized Channels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MTV music network, looking to appeal to ever-changing range of musical tastes, plans to offer selection of well-defined channels next year that specialize in rock, rap, country and other genres to viewers willing to pay extra monthly charge; plan, which uses breakthrough digital technology, is part of new television era in which extra layers of specialized programming will emerge on already crowded cable systems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looking to appeal to an ever-changing range of musical tastes, the MTV music network plans to offer a selection of well-defined channels next year that specialize in rock, rap, country and other genres to viewers willing to pay an extra monthly charge.</p>
        <p>The plan, which uses breakthrough digital technology, is part of a new television era in which extra layers of specialized programming will emerge on already crowded cable systems. This is likely to fragment television viewing in ways that were scarcely imagined a decade ago and could lead to the wide promotion of musical acts that have difficulty getting regular exposure on television now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looking to appeal to an ever-changing range of musical tastes, the MTV music network plans to offer a selection of well-defined channels next year that specialize in rock, rap, country and other genres to viewers willing to pay an extra monthly charge.</p>
        <p>The plan, which uses breakthrough digital technology, is part of a new television era in which extra layers of specialized programming will emerge on already crowded cable systems. This is likely to fragment television viewing in ways that were scarcely imagined a decade ago and could lead to the wide promotion of musical acts that have difficulty getting regular exposure on television now.</p>
        <p>MTV and its sister network, VH1, are expected to announce the plan today.</p>
        <p>''We always knew the audience would like to add more musical choices,'' said Tom Freston, the chairman of MTV Networks. ''We just had to wait for the technology to make it possible.''</p>
        <p>Other cable programmers, like HBO and Showtime, have offered their shows on a number of channels using a system they call multi-plexing. But those services merely reschedule programs that already are on their main services. The new MTV service, called ''The Suite From MTV and VH1,'' will provide totally distinct programming not available on either MTV or VH1.</p>
        <p>The new channels will all have separate titles and will appeal to separate musical tastes. ''MTV Rocks'' will include hard rock and heavy metal music; ''MTV Indie'' will feature music from independent record labels, mostly rap and techno music. ''MTV Ritmo'' will have a Spanish-language flavor, relying on Tejano, Cuban and dance-pop music.</p>
        <p>On the VH1 side, the new ''VH1 Soul'' will specialize in rhythm-and-blues and soul music. ''VH1 Country'' will include country-and-western music artists. And ''VH1 Smooth'' will be devoted to jazz, new age and adult-contemporary music.</p>
        <p>All these channels will be presented without advertising until they reach ''a critical mass'' of viewers, Mr. Freston said. The space for the new channels will be provided using MTV's second channel, called M2, which will remain as the seventh channel on the new ''Suite'' service.</p>
        <p>Digital technology makes it possible for one former analogue channel to be compressed into a large number of digital channels. (Some cable systems will take one analogue channel and compress it into as many as 12 channels for pay-per-view movie services. But the more channels that are squeezed out of one channel, the weaker the visual quality of each digital channel will be.)</p>
        <p>The ''Suite'' service will try to take advantage of the rollout of digital channels now being undertaken by several of the country's biggest cable operators, including Tele-Communications Inc. and Comcast. Cable industry analysts have predicted that about 2.5 million homes would add a digital tier of channels by the middle of next year, with the number growing to 5 million by the end of 1999 and 8 million by 2000.</p>
        <p>A subscriber will have to add a new cable box to receive the digital service. The cost is expected to be about $10 a month above the current charge for cable. Mr. Freston noted that predictions of how many cable subscribers would be willing to pay the additional price vary from a high of 30 percent to a low of 5 percent</p>
        <p>Still, he noted that program costs for MTV would be low because music videos are already being produced in all of these specialized formats. MTV receives the videos free from the record labels. Its only incremental costs for programming the new channels will be whatever individual packaging MTV puts onto each of the new channels and whatever it spends to promote the new channels.</p>
        <p>One of the concerns that many television programmers have expressed about the coming of digital channels has been that new services with similar themes carry the threat of cannibalizing the audience of the parent channel.</p>
        <p>The threat appears especially strong for music channels. The radio industry went through a revolution when stratified tastes in music led to the breakdown of once widely popular stations and the emergence of stations playing well defined genres that appeal to far smaller audiences.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Freston said he was largely unconcerned that MTV could lose hordes of music fans to its new channels.</p>
        <p>''These channels will be loaded up with the types of music not being seriously serviced by MTV or VH1,'' he said. ''Only a sprinkling of this music is available on television now. I think the net-net will be very positive for us.''</p>
        <p>Bill Marchetti, an analyst with Paul Kagan Associates, a company that follows the cable industry, said, ''It's a very logical move for MTV now that the space is opening up for them to do it.''</p>
        <p>He noted that one of MTV's competitors, a music-video channel called the Box, has already moved toward providing digital channels to appeal to different music tastes, though the Box has tried to take a regionalized approach, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
