<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Doctor-Patient Relationships Can Be Dysfunctional</title>
    <meta content="25CASE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jauhar, Sandeep (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DC1530F936A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Doctor-Patient Relationships Can Be Dysfunctional</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDEEP JAUHAR, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jauhar, Sandeep (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Sandeep Jauhar Essay on dysfunctional doctor-patient relationships; some patients described as 'difficult' are seen dependent, entitled, manipulative and self-destructive; some patients have personality traits that kindle aversion, fear, despair and downright malice in doctors; some doctor-patient relationships are dysfunctional simply because of idiosyncracies of doctor and patient: neither is bad, they are just bad together; doctors cannot dismiss their patients, at least not easily; American Medical Assn and courts have set guidelines for when doctor can dismiss patient, and usually only the most egregious misbehavior qualiifies, including threats, violence and noncompliance (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The young woman walked into my office and plopped herself sullenly into a vinyl chair. ''I want a referral to a chiropractor,'' she said. Judging from her face, she was in no mood for small talk.</p>
        <p>She was healthy and angry. Earlier that morning, she had clashed with the doctor answering the phones at the clinic where I work. She had requested the referral, but had gotten upset when he started asking questions about her back pain. When he insisted that she come to the clinic to be examined, she told him he was wasting her time and hung up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The young woman walked into my office and plopped herself sullenly into a vinyl chair. ''I want a referral to a chiropractor,'' she said. Judging from her face, she was in no mood for small talk.</p>
        <p>She was healthy and angry. Earlier that morning, she had clashed with the doctor answering the phones at the clinic where I work. She had requested the referral, but had gotten upset when he started asking questions about her back pain. When he insisted that she come to the clinic to be examined, she told him he was wasting her time and hung up.</p>
        <p>But about an hour later she walked into the clinic where, after an angry exchange of words with the front desk clerk, she was quickly ushered into my room. Her regular doctor was away.</p>
        <p>''How long have you had back pain?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''It started this morning,'' she replied. ''I heard a pop between my shoulders.''</p>
        <p>''Had this occurred before?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, several months ago.''</p>
        <p>She had gone to a chiropractor, which helped. A few more questions and she got impatient. ''How is this important?'' she demanded. ''I just want a referral.''</p>
        <p>''O.K.,'' I replied, but first I had to examine her. I explained that if she had a pinched nerve, a chiropractor might do more harm than good. She reluctantly agreed, but a few minutes later, she changed her mind.</p>
        <p>''You're wasting my time,'' she erupted. ''Call your supervisor.''</p>
        <p>Because I am a resident, a senior physician supervises my work. Now my supervisor that day happened to be a very calm, soft-spoken doctor who had a nice way with his patients.</p>
        <p>I called him to the room, explained what was going on and excused myself. He listened patiently as the woman inveighed against the clinic and the doctors who had mistreated her. His calm manner and attention apparently mollified her because she allowed him to examine her.</p>
        <p>Then, calmly, they discussed her options. She was not interested in Motrin or rest as therapy. She insisted on a chiropractor. About 15 minutes later, he emerged from the room and asked me to please write the referral. I did, and she left, looking satisfied.</p>
        <p>Afterward, in his office, he shrugged his shoulders and weakly smiled. ''She was a difficult patient,'' he said. ''In such cases, you listen and try to do the best you can. Sometimes patients just need to vent.''</p>
        <p>It is hardly surprising, given the broad spectrum of human behavior, that some patients can be labeled difficult. Compared with other appellations in the medical literature -- demanding, hateful -- this one is relatively mild.</p>
        <p>In a 1978 article in The New England Journal of Medicine, Dr. James Groves, then a professor of psychiatry at Harvard Medical School, described certain personality traits that kindle aversion, fear, despair or even downright malice in doctors.</p>
        <p>He described such patients as dependent, entitled, manipulative and self-destructive. Emotional reactions to patients, he wrote, cannot simply be wished away, nor is it good medicine to pretend that they do not exist.</p>
        <p>Freud called such reactions countertransference -- how doctors react to patients, not the other way around -- and said these reactions could be used to explore the unconscious conflicts of doctor and patient.</p>
        <p>Aversive reactions are common in any enterprise involving intimacy: marriage, psychotherapy, the battlefield, and so it is with medicine. The difference is that doctors cannot divorce their patients, at least not easily, and for good reason.</p>
        <p>Entrusted as they are with a fiduciary duty to preserve health, they cannot dismiss patients willy-nilly. But the question demands asking: if patients can choose their own doctors, why can't doctors choose their own patients?</p>
        <p>The American Medical Association and courts have set guidelines for when a doctor can dismiss a patient, and usually only the most egregious misbehavior qualifies, including threats, violence and noncompliance. For example, courts have ruled that kidney specialists do not have to provide dialysis to violent or disruptive patients, even those who need it to remain alive. But in such cases, doctors must ensure that their patients know of other doctors they can see and other basic information.</p>
        <p>If doctors actually do dismiss patients, they risk being charged with abandonment, and if injury can be traced to their breach of duty, they can be sued.</p>
        <p>Abandonment is a charged word. It encapsulates precisely what we dread most in a doctor: lack of availability, empathy, responsibility. It is contrary to the principles of beneficence and compassion that doctors must swear to.</p>
        <p>And yet, sometimes, it makes sense for a patient to get a new doctor. Sometimes a new doctor is just what the doctor ordered.</p>
        <p>Some doctor-patient relationships are dysfunctional simply because of the idiosyncrasies of the doctor and the patient. Neither is bad; they are just bad together. In almost any other sphere, we would accept the dissolution of such a relationship. We accept it in the home and in the courtroom. Why not in the doctors office?</p>
        <p>I recently helped care for a young woman in the hospital who had been troubled for years with abdominal pain and a psychologically abusive boyfriend. She had been in and out of hospitals, undergoing X-rays, ultrasounds, CAT scans and so forth, all of which revealed nothing.</p>
        <p>She was angry and afraid, and frequently came to the emergency room demanding hospitalization and painkillers. Doctors who cared for her in various hospitals had grown weary of her constant complaints and started giving her morphine. Then, she became addicted, and no one cared about her enough to ensure that she got the psychiatric help she sorely needed, including, in retrospect, me. It was easier to abdicate responsibility than to deal with her.</p>
        <p>She was the quintessentially difficult patient. After a while, hers was a room we avoided. Her needs were bottomless, her pain unremitting. In the constant buzz that is ward life for a resident, time seemed better spent on other patients.</p>
        <p>Nothing seemed to be physically wrong with her, at least not anything to explain the severity of her pain. Yet she relentlessly demanded morphine. Try as best we could, it was hard setting limits. A tough approach alienated her. A conciliatory approach simply got her more drugs.</p>
        <p>But one person, her internist, knew how to handle her. Though the internist had been her doctor for only a few months, she had developed an effective style with this patient. She was not afraid to be strict: if the patient yelled, sometimes she yelled back, or she was kind, as the moment required. Though unconventional, she grasped her patient's psychology like no one else, and she truly cared for her. She eventually managed to discharge her without morphine.</p>
        <p>I asked the internist about her approach to difficult patients. She had several in her practice, she said. Like any doctor, I do not seek them out, she said. But, she added, they are not that hard to treat, once you figure out what is bothering them.</p>
        <p>She understands this intuitively, and that is part of the reason she is so effective.  Some doctors know that patients do not always come right out and say what is wrong. Sometimes they hedge or obfuscate, and often the key to treating them is to look a little deeper. But exactly why one doctor can relate to a difficult patient, and another can alienate her, is a mystery.</p>
        <p>Another reminder, perhaps, that medicine is a field of specialties. Some doctors are better at treating certain diseases; some at treating certain patients.</p>
        <p>CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
