<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspired Isles Play Like Champions</title>
    <meta content="16ISLE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOCKEY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="909528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5D6133FF935A25751C0A961958260" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspired Isles Play Like Champions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Feb. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-five years from now, when the Islanders celebrate their second quarter century, how will they remember the players who currently wear their uniform?</p>
        <p>Will Claude Lapointe, Tommy Salo, Todd Bertuzzi and others stand on a blue carpet under a spotlight before cheering, nostalgic fans the way Mike Bossy, Billy Smith and Clark Gillies and others did during the pre-game anniversary celebration tonight?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty-five years from now, when the Islanders celebrate their second quarter century, how will they remember the players who currently wear their uniform?</p>
        <p>Will Claude Lapointe, Tommy Salo, Todd Bertuzzi and others stand on a blue carpet under a spotlight before cheering, nostalgic fans the way Mike Bossy, Billy Smith and Clark Gillies and others did during the pre-game anniversary celebration tonight?</p>
        <p>In the year 2022, will there be more than the four Stanley Cup banners now in the rafters and will they be hanging in a new arena?</p>
        <p>It would be foolish to jump to conclusions, based only on a 1-0 overtime victory over the Florida Panthers, a good show with a thrilling finish that sent the capacity crowd of 16,297 leaping to its feet with lusty cheers.</p>
        <p>Lapointe scored the winner with a backhander from the right-wing circle on an odd-man rush at 2 minutes 46 seconds of the extra session. The puck was only partly stopped by the pads of goalie Mark Fitzpatrick.</p>
        <p>''We said all game long 'Shoot five-hole on Fitzpatrick,' '' Lapointe said. ''It was probably our best game for intensity. And Tommy made some big saves. It was a great win for everybody.''</p>
        <p>Salo stopped all 29 Florida shots for his third shutout of the season.</p>
        <p>''It was a pretty good game for a 0-0 game,'' Salo said, referring to the score after regulation. ''Mark Fitzpatrick came up with big saves. I came up with big saves.''</p>
        <p>Bertuzzi gave a robust effort, dealing out body checks and creating chances by bulling netward. Back from a minor league sojourn, Bertuzzi said of his effort: ''That's my game. It's the way I'm supposed to be playing -- finishing my checks.''</p>
        <p>Coach Rick Bowness said the Islanders want Bertuzzi to ''salvage the season,'' and that this effort promised that.</p>
        <p>''He's working harder,'' Bowness said. ''He's skating harder.''</p>
        <p>The victory was the Islanders' second in succession and third consecutive game without defeat. It left them with 48 points, still within reach of an Eastern Conference playoff berth. In their last 16 games, they are 7-7-2.</p>
        <p>It was the Islanders' first victory over the Panthers this season after two defeats and one tie. The Panthers played without five injured players: Dave Lowry, Brian Skrudland, Mike Hough, Ray Sheppard and Ed Jovanovski.</p>
        <p>Both teams played a rambunctious style, with the Islanders getting the best hits. Each team had at least a dozen good scoring chances.</p>
        <p>''I thought we played well,'' Florida Coach Doug MacLean said. ''Salo was the difference.''</p>
        <p>The pre-game celebration included the former Islanders General Manager Bill Torrey, now the president of the Panthers, and Coach Al Arbour, now an Islander vice president. The screen on the scoreboard showed old, videotaped highlights of longish-haired men, some of them helmetless, skating along clear, white dasher boards while wearing a sweater logo that showed the land mass of Long Island.</p>
        <p>In the flesh, the honored players wore their jerseys and Torrey wore a bow tie. Fireworks exploded over their heads, including the silvery hair of Bossy and the slightly balding dome of Butch Goring.</p>
        <p>Other players honored were Denis Potvin, Ken Morrow, John Tonelli, Bobby Nystrom, Stefan Persson and Dave Langevin. Chico Resch and Bryan Trottier couldn't be there. Resch announces Devils games and Trottier is an assistant coach with the Pittsburgh Penguins.</p>
        <p>When the current Islanders took the ice, they formed a playoff-style handshake line to greet the group that brought the franchise four Stanley Cup championships between 1980 and 1983.</p>
        <p>The ceremony concluded with the legends climbing into the back of pickup trucks for a slow lap around the ice and a wave to the applauding fans. (This being Long Island, it was remarkable that the two vehicles did not try to cut each other off as they headed out the Zamboni exit).</p>
        <p>As they toured, the sound system played ''Glory Days'' by Bruce Springsteen, a New Jersey guy. Then the lights came up, the smoke cleared and the game began as speakers blasted out ''The Boys Are Back in Town.''</p>
        <p>When it was over, the tune again was ''Glory Days.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
