<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soccer Success Forges New Bolivia Optimism</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD CUP (SOCCER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOLIVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDE113DF930A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="1794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soccer Success Forges New Bolivia Optimism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>LA PAZ, Bolivia, Aug. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They come to the games with their faces painted in the national colors -- red, yellow and green -- and dance down the central boulevard, El Prado, to celebrate victories with a new pride and greater social unity than Bolivia has ever known as a country. And all because of a soccer team.</p>
        <p>This land-locked country is the poorest in Latin America, sets the record for military coups in the region and is often mocked by neighbors of fairer complexion for its large Indian population. But Bolivians dare to dream the impossible -- qualifying as one of the 24 teams in next year's World Cup in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They come to the games with their faces painted in the national colors -- red, yellow and green -- and dance down the central boulevard, El Prado, to celebrate victories with a new pride and greater social unity than Bolivia has ever known as a country. And all because of a soccer team.</p>
        <p>This land-locked country is the poorest in Latin America, sets the record for military coups in the region and is often mocked by neighbors of fairer complexion for its large Indian population. But Bolivians dare to dream the impossible -- qualifying as one of the 24 teams in next year's World Cup in the United States.</p>
        <p>In its five-team South American group, Bolivia has beaten everyone -- Venezuela (twice), Ecuador, Uruguay and Brazil. No ties. No losses. It has scored more goals, 20, than any other Latin American team in the qualifying rounds and toyed with Venezuela today in the thin air of this capital city 12,000 feet above sea level, winning by 7-0. With today's victory over Venezuela, Bolivia has won all four of its home games, but must play its three remaining qualifying games away.</p>
        <p>The team and the country suddenly have an international profile. American advertising agencies are already soliciting the Bolivian Soccer Federation about marketing the team in Latin America and the United States. Invitations have come from Miami to play in soccer matches with Mexico and Sweden and from Europe to play against Ireland and Scotland.</p>
        <p>Only twice before in the 63-year history of the World Cup has this Andean country played in the final round, in1930 and 1950, and both appearances were by invitation of the host country (Uruguay in 1930 and Brazil in 1950).</p>
        <p>Bolivians hope that the emergence of the soccer team as a power alongside such familiar World Cup champions as Brazil and Argentina is a precursor to the emergence of the country as an attractive place for foreign investment, with a track record of economic stability and 10 years of uninterrupted democracy.</p>
        <p>"There's a real change in your image when you make the finals of the World Cup," said Marco Antonio Etcheverry, the team's star striker, who is also known as El Diablo (the Devil). "I remember when Colombia qualified for the 1990 games. It was like, 'Wow, the country's reputation soared overnight to another level.' We were in awe of them. That's what we're hoping will happen to us."</p>
        <p>Such bright-eyed faith in the future comes at a time when, politically, the country seems to be leaving behind dictatorships and strongman rule and embracing the initial stages of sharing political power, particularly with its vast indigenous population.</p>
        <p>Last June, in its Presidential elections, a former dictator, Hugo Banzer Suarez, was soundly defeated in the voting, as the public chose a ticket that was known as the "Gringo and the Indian."</p>
        <p>The country overwhelmingly elected Gonzalo Sanchez de Lozada, an American-trained mining executive who speaks Spanish with a thick American accent, and his dark-skinned vice presidential running mate, Victor Hugo Cardenas, a philosopher, educator and an Aymara Indian born on the banks of Lake Titicaca.</p>
        <p>It is the first time in any Latin American country that an indigenous leader has been elected to such a high national office.</p>
        <p>"When I came here, the soccer team reflected the national identity, a very low self-image, a conquered people, down on themselves, such that if things got tough they would just quit," said Xavier Azkargorta, the team's coach and trainer from Barcelona, Spain.</p>
        <p>"The first thing they had to learn was to respect and like themselves, and dignify the image of a soccer player," Azkargorta said. "And I think that is what's happening in the country as well.</p>
        <p>"Bolivia is a country with everything: minerals, natural resources, vast agricultural lands. It only lacks development. There's nothing to be ashamed of. And that's exactly the same with soccer players." Low Inflation, Mineral Riches</p>
        <p>And there are the nascent signs of such change. The country has the lowest inflation rate in all of Latin America, averaging 8 percent a year. American mining companies are beginning to find new deposits of gold and other minerals, and international oil executives say that they have no estimate as to the extent of the energy riches yet undiscovered in the country.</p>
        <p>But these changes come against the backdrop of a history of problems. The Spanish plundered Bolivia's silver and gold, forcing the Indians to work in the mines, where many died. Since independence in 1825, Bolivia has lost territory in wars with all of its neighbors. Years of hyperinflation and backwardness have left the country with the highest poverty rate in the Western Hemisphere, with the exception of Haiti.</p>
        <p>Indeed, its international image among its greatest detractors in Latin America was summed up last month by a former Chilean admiral, Jose Toribio Merino, who described Bolivia as consisting of "metamorphosized llamas who have learned how to speak but not to think."</p>
        <p>But soccer may change some of that. On Sundays during games, local television stations transmit images of fans singing national songs with such lyrics as "Long Live Bolivia Near My Heart," and "Bolivia's My Country, Oh How I Love It."</p>
        <p>"Soccer gives you two things, pride and joy," said Guido Loayza, president of the Bolivian Soccer Federation. "In a country like Bolivia, where so many people are poor, there are very few times when a country as a whole can feel pride and joy. This is one of those times."  Team and El Diablo Front-Page News</p>
        <p>The soccer team and El Diablo, the striker Etcheverry, are front-page news almost every day. Recently, during a headline-grabbing visit by Fidel Castro, a frustrated Sanchez de Lozada, in his typically biting humor said, "apparently Bolivians have forgotten that they have a new president."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the soccer craze has given Bolivia perhaps the biggest moral victory to date in its struggle to legitimize the use of coca leaves. For centuries, Bolivians have chewed coca to allay hunger pangs and cope with the thin air in the Andes. They have also used it as a folk-medicine remedy.</p>
        <p>Here, an herbal tea called mate de coca, made of coca leaves, is served to visitors to help them cope with the effects of the altitude. Pope John Paul II, Queen Sofia of Spain and former Vice President Dan Quayle have all partaken of the brew. It is even served in the American Embassy; however, agents of the United States Drug Enforcement Administration are forbidden to drink it.</p>
        <p>But as raw material for cocaine, the export of coca leaves has been banned by international organizations. And for years, Bolivia has struggled to convince the international community that the fault lies with the consuming nations, since cocaine is produced only when chemicals are added, and that as a leaf, coca is less harmful than coffee. Bolivians describe cocaine, in fact, as a foreign substance.</p>
        <p>Then in early August, FIFA, soccer's international governing body, conducted a surprise anti-doping test here during the Bolivia-Brazil game.</p>
        <p>Two of the players, Bolivia's Miguel Angel Rimba and Brazil's Armelino Donizetti, also known as Zetti, tested positive for cocaine and were suspended after the match. But after a few days of explanation it turned out that both players had consumed small amounts of mate.</p>
        <p>They were reinstated by FIFA, which Bolivians interpreted as the first international recognition that chewing coca or drinking coca tea is not the equivalent of taking cocaine.</p>
        <p>Even with the victory today, Bolivia statistically is not assured of a place in the final round. But a tie in any of its final three games (at Brazil, at Uruguay and at Ecuador) would assure Bolivia of a trip to the United States next June.</p>
        <p>Azkargorta is given much of the credit for the improvement in the team. Previously, soccer players were not held in particularly high regard, and what Azkargorta found when he arrived here to work with the players early this year was low morale and a tendency to give up.</p>
        <p>"They were intermittent soccer players, only for a few days leading up to a match," the coach said. "But you have to be a soccer player all the time and consider that it is a dignity to be one."</p>
        <p>One of the hardest cases was El Diablo himself, who arrived back in Bolivia after playing with Albacete in Spain (his contract was purchased by the Chilean club, Colo Colo) feeling depressed, with family and drinking problems.</p>
        <p>Still, while morale was low when Azkargorta came, the technical skills were high. This was in large part due to the Tahuichi Aguilera Soccer Academy in Santa Cruz, known for training outstanding young players, including El Diablo, who is considered one of Latin America's next superstars. At present, six graduates of the academy are on the national team.</p>
        <p>Only five countries are definitely in the finals so far: Mexico has qualified in the World Cup elimination round for Central America; Russia and Greece both qualified from European Group 5; the United States as the host country, and Germany as the defending champion.</p>
        <p>Colombia and Argentina, along with Peru and Paraguay, are in South American Group A. The winner of that group advances to the finals while the second-place team will have to play Australia in a playoff for a berth in the finals. Bolivia, Brazil, Venezuela, Ecuador and Uruguay comprise Group B. Should Bolivia make it out of Group B (the top two teams will advance to the finals), the players will have to be satisfied with emotional, rather than monetary rewards. While every Argentine player will get a $100,000 bonus if the team qualifies for the final round and every Brazilian player will get $50,000, the Bolivians will get no more than $8,000 apiece. Basque Coach Is a Folk Hero</p>
        <p>But with the World Cup finals still almost a year away, Azkargorta has become a kind of folk hero here, even though he is Spanish and could be seen as an extention of Spain's conquistadors.</p>
        <p>"I'm Basque," he is quick to point out. "We had our own number of bloody and cruel conquistadors, but at the same time we are now an oppressed people ourselves so I can feel for the Bolivians."</p>
        <p>Azkargorta does not let the team focus on future games. "The most dangerous opponent right now is Venezuela," he said. And he stresses that mental approach by the use of three words, "here and now." And he will not discuss with reporters whether the team will beat Brazil, in Recife, Brazil, on Sunday but he says he has no fears of the superpowers of the soccer world.</p>
        <p>"If Brazil qualifies for the finals, they would go as one of the heavy favorites to win and we have already beaten them," he said. "Now you're not going to say to me that we cannot stand on our own against anyone."</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
