<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft Confronts Its Success</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MICROSOFT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORP (IBM)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL TRADE COMMISSION (FTC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHOFF, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D6153CF930A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft Confronts Its Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF,</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In seizing the mantle of computer industry leadership from I.B.M., the Microsoft Corporation is earning the headaches of power as well as the influence.</p>
        <p>The extent of the software publisher's legal problems became clearer on Friday. Shortly after the Federal Trade Commission ended a 38-month investigation into Microsoft's business practices, the Antitrust Division of the Justice Department said that it would pursue its own inquiry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In seizing the mantle of computer industry leadership from I.B.M., the Microsoft Corporation is earning the headaches of power as well as the influence.</p>
        <p>The extent of the software publisher's legal problems became clearer on Friday. Shortly after the Federal Trade Commission ended a 38-month investigation into Microsoft's business practices, the Antitrust Division of the Justice Department said that it would pursue its own inquiry.</p>
        <p>The new investigation is likely to raise complex political issues for the Clinton Administration, which has made support for American high-technology companies part of its main agenda.</p>
        <p>Microsoft, based in Redmond, Wash., was started by William H. Gates and Paul Allen after Mr. Gates dropped out of Harvard University in 1975. It is widely viewed as a model of the kind of company that creates the skilled jobs that the Administration wants to encourage. Specter of I.B.M. Case</p>
        <p>I.B.M. fought a Justice Department investigation from 1969 until 1982, a case that produced more than 760 million documents and ultimately had a debilitating effect on the world's largest computer maker.</p>
        <p>Yet Microsoft, which controls almost 80 percent of the market for personal computer operating systems, and which was investigated by the F.T.C. on accusations that it had locked customers into using its MS-DOS program, had deliberately created incompatibilities for competitors, and had unfairly linked its applications to its operating system, is a very different competitor from I.B.M.</p>
        <p>"I.B.M. was a monolith that was a government in itself," said Susan Braden, a Washington attorney who was part of the Justice Department team that investigated I.B.M. and who later worked at the Federal Trade Commission. "Microsoft is more of an opportunistic culture that is involved in many different parts of the industry."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Microsoft's preoccupation with creating as many new industry alliances as it can, in areas as diverse as interactive cable television, wireless portable computing and office equipment, may limit the damage from any prolonged investigation.</p>
        <p>"Microsoft is waltzing ahead with cable and all the other things where all the action is going to be," said Esther Dyson, publisher of Release 1.0, a computer-industry newsletter.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Microsoft's main software business is going through many of the same changes that the personal computer hardware business has already been through, suggesting that the software publisher might be more willing to strike a quick deal with the Justice Department as it moves ahead to new markets.</p>
        <p>"It's all a market-share game," said Mark Stahlman, president of New Media Associates, a consulting firm. "There's no growth in PC software. As unit prices fall, the competitive game shifts and the question is will Microsoft wind up being handcuffed in a brand new ball game."</p>
        <p>A number of industry executives have suggested that Microsoft may be willing to cut a deal with the Justice Department because any restrictions will presumably come in business areas that are now of less importance to the company. Divided Opinion on F.T.C.</p>
        <p>The F.T.C. dropped its investigation on Friday after its commissioners deadlocked twice on proposed charges assembled by staff attorneys. There are five commissioners; one, Roscoe B. Starek, refrained from both votes because of a possible conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>In February, commission investigators sought to bring a suit against Microsoft in Federal court accusing it of "exclusionary tying practices," creating incompatibilities between its own and its competitors' operating systems, and illegal licensing practices.</p>
        <p>In July, the F.T.C. staff tried to persuade the commissioners to issue an administrative complaint against Microsoft for violations of the Federal Trade Commission Act, as well as for violating Section 3 of the Clayton Antitrust Act, which forbids contracts or selling agreements that exclude use of competitors' products or which tend to create a monopoly. Rivals Offer Their Research</p>
        <p>At a meeting on Aug. 4 with financial analysts, Mr. Gates said Microsoft had not engaged in anticompetitive practices. However, a number of competitors have supplied the F.T.C. with volumes of information in an effort to limit Microsoft's power.</p>
        <p>Novell Inc., the Provo, Utah-based maker of computer office network software, has been the leader in a campaign within the industry against Microsoft. Novell, which has a dominant share in its own market and which publishes a PC operating system that competes with Microsoft's, has hired several law firms, economists and public relations people as part of the effort.</p>
        <p>Operating systems govern a computer's basic functions, and thus a supplier of such a program has tremendous influence both with hardware manufacturers and with companies who write applications like word-processing programs, spreadsheets and data bases.</p>
        <p>A principal issue before the Federal Trade Commission was whether Microsoft had licensed its MS-DOS operating system program to personal computer companies in a way that it made it impossible for competing companies to sell their products.</p>
        <p>One issue has been whether Microsoft forced computer makers to pay royalties for each personal computer they sell, regardless of whether or not a copy of MS-DOS was shipped with the machine.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has repeatedly insisted that its licensing practices do not require companies to make such commitments.</p>
        <p>But an executive at a competitor, who spoke on the condition that he not be further identified, said he frequently found that customers would tell him that they would only get the best royalty rates if they agreed to license a copy of MS-DOS for every personal computer they shipped.</p>
        <p>"If you agreed to pay royalties based on the number of Intel-compatible systems you shipped, as opposed to the number that actually went out with the software, you got a substantial discount from Microsoft," he said. MS-DOS is an operating system designed for Intel-compatible computers. Illegal or Simply Aggressive?</p>
        <p>But whether or not such a pricing strategy is illegal has yet to be decided.</p>
        <p>A separate issue before the F.T.C. was the relationship between Microsoft's two operating system products, Windows and MS-DOS. A number of competitors had charged that Microsoft's applications programmers were able to take unfair advantage of undocumented instructions in MS-DOS -- secret operating-system functions that are not in programmers' manuals. These undocumented capabilities could theoretically be used to give Microsoft's word processors, spreadsheets or data bases a feature advantage.</p>
        <p>Microsoft in theory could also take advantage of the relationship between Windows and MS-DOS, which have both become industry standards. A Message Varies</p>
        <p>The issue was raised in the September issue of Dr. Dobbs' Journal, a programmer's magazine. Andrew Schulman, a technical writer, examined a mysterious message found in the Windows 3.1 source code, the instructions readable only by a programmer. The message, which appeared in one pre-release version of Windows, informed a user running Windows with a non-Microsoft version of the operating system that a nonfatal error had occurred and suggested that the user call Microsoft.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schulman discovered that in the release version of Windows, Microsoft had turned off the feature, but had left the instructions buried in the program. In his article, he raised the possibility that Microsoft could use the instructions to discourage customers from using non-Microsoft operating systems, which would be a violation of antitrust law.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has replied that the code was developed to determine if MS-DOS was being used, in an effort to reduce the support burden on the company. The instructions were not activated in the release version, it says, because the company was concerned about further accusations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
