<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemens Adds 6th Cy Young to Case</title>
    <meta content="16CLEM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/16/sports/16CLEM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cy Young Award</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6D7143BF935A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemens Adds 6th Cy Young to Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clemens Wins His 6th Cy Young</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher Roger Clemens wins Cy Young award in American League; it is sixth time he has won; chart compares Clemens's stats in years he won award; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kacy Clemens, 7, pushed a chair to the kitchen sink last summer and held a baseball under a running faucet. His father, a Yankee pitcher of some note, asked the boy what he was doing, and Kacy explained that he had hit this particular ball for a home run in tee ball and it needed cleaning before being added to the family's trophy case.</p>
        <p>His father's stuff is starting to crowd Kacy Clemens's home run ball. Roger Clemens won his sixth Cy Young award yesterday, dominating the balloting for the American League's best pitcher; no other pitcher has won the award more than four times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roger Clemens won his sixth Cy Young award, dominating the balloting for the A.L.'s best pitcher. No other pitcher has won the award more than four times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kacy Clemens, 7, pushed a chair to the kitchen sink last summer and held a baseball under a running faucet. His father, a Yankee pitcher of some note, asked the boy what he was doing, and Kacy explained that he had hit this particular ball for a home run in tee ball and it needed cleaning before being added to the family's trophy case.</p>
        <p>His father's stuff is starting to crowd Kacy Clemens's home run ball. Roger Clemens won his sixth Cy Young award yesterday, dominating the balloting for the American League's best pitcher; no other pitcher has won the award more than four times.</p>
        <p>''To win the award one time is a thrill,'' Clemens said, ''and to win it a sixth time is incredible.''</p>
        <p>Clemens, who turned 39 in August, is the third-oldest Cy Young award winner. Early Wynn was 39, but seven months older than Clemens, when he won the award with the Chicago White Sox in 1959, and Gaylord Perry was 40 when he won with the San Diego Padres in 1978.</p>
        <p>Clemens is the first Yankees pitcher to win the award since 1978, when Ron Guidry was 25-3. He is the first pitcher to win the award with three teams; he was named the Cy Young winner while with the Boston Red Sox in 1986, 1987 and 1991, and with the Toronto Blue Jays in 1997 and 1998.</p>
        <p>Clemens was the only A.L. pitcher listed on all 28 ballots submitted before the postseason by voting members of the Baseball Writers Association of America. He received 21 first-place votes, 5 second-place votes and 2 third-place votes for a total of 122 points in a 5-3-1 scoring system. Mark Mulder of the Oakland A's received 2 first-place votes and finished second with 60 points. Freddy Garcia of the Seattle Mariners had 4 first-place votes and 55 points over all. The Mariners' Jamie Moyer received the other first-place vote.</p>
        <p>Clemens did not lead the American League in any of the major pitching categories, finishing ninth in earned run average (3.51), third in strikeouts (213) and tied for second in victories (20), behind Mulder (21). What Clemens did more often than anyone, however, was pitch his team to victory. The Yankees won every game he started for four months, a total of 20 consecutive starts. He lost to Seattle on May 20 and did not lose again until Sept. 25, against Tampa Bay. Clemens won 20 of his first 21 decisions, the first pitcher in major league baseball to do so.</p>
        <p>''Once the streak got over 10 games, guys, it became pretty interesting,'' Clemens said.</p>
        <p>''I was talking to Andy and a couple of other pitchers about how you get into a mode where you don't feel like you're going to lose,'' he added, referring to his teammate Andy Pettitte.</p>
        <p>Clemens, who started the All-Star Game for the A.L., lost his final two regular-season decisions to finish at 20-3, and his .870 winning percentage matched David Cone's in 1988 for the fifth-highest winning percentage for any pitcher with 20 or more victories in a season.</p>
        <p>In his final start of the regular season, Clemens strained a hamstring while covering first base. He aggravated the injury the day before the playoffs while jogging in the outfield. Clemens lost his first playoff start, on Oct. 10, and it seemed he would be a major question throughout the postseason, if the Yankees survived. Some teammates, knowing how badly Clemens was hurt, doubted he would be able to start Game 5 of the division series against Oakland.</p>
        <p>But Clemens pitched five innings with his right leg wrapped heavily and with lingering soreness in his shoulder, and the Yankees won. Clemens pitched effectively against Seattle in the A.L. Championship Series and the Yankees won his start, and Clemens dominated the Arizona Diamondbacks in Game 3 of the World Series. He seemed to gain strength with each of his outings.</p>
        <p>Clemens started Game 7 of the World Series. He allowed one run in six and a third innings, giving the Yankees a chance to come back and take a lead, which they did in the eighth inning. But after the Yankees lost in the ninth, he said goodbye to his teammates and slipped out of the clubhouse, stopping with three of his sons in the Arizona clubhouse to congratulate Curt Schilling, Randy Johnson and others. Clemens said that he could still feel the effect of the last month in his body and that he would not begin working out for next season in earnest until next month.</p>
        <p>Clemens set the A.L. record for career strikeouts on opening day last season, surpassing Walter Johnson, and by summer's end he was third on the major league list, with 3,717, behind Nolan Ryan (5,714) and Steve Carlton (4,136). With each passing milestone, Clemens keeps a memento, whether it is the record-setting ball, a uniform, a hat, a glove or spikes.</p>
        <p>His house is already packed with memorabilia. He has jerseys and baseballs signed by Hall of Famers and All-Stars. He has an autograph from Smokey Joe Wood, who pitched for the Boston Red Sox from 1908 to 1915 before an arm injury forced him to move to the outfield. Wood's might be his favorite autograph, Debbi Clemens, his wife, said in an interview in August.</p>
        <p>She has watched him at events when he has stood with players like Henry Aaron and Ted Williams and has seen how much joy he derives from the association.</p>
        <p>''I think he's always appreciated the history of the game, and how important it is,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Clemens has 280 career victories,  and with the increased reliance on specialized relievers, he might be among the last in the foreseeable future to have a shot at 300 victories,  the last significant personal goal in his sights, he said.</p>
        <p>''I'll see how I feel,'' he said. ''I'm just hoping I can get there, injury free. Three hundred would be just about it. It's been a challenge to me.''</p>
        <p>He reiterated yesterday that he was leaning toward requesting a Yankees cap for the Hall of Fame plaque he will eventually receive, but that will come after more milestones, more memorabilia, plaques and trophies, more window dressing for Kacy Clemens's shiny ball.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
