<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Days of War And Wonder</title>
    <meta content="16TVWK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/16/arts/television/16TVWK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shah, Saira</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Unholy War (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Beneath the Veil (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">National Geographic Explorer: Holy War, Inc (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D8173BF935A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Days of War And Wonder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Days of War and Wonder in Afghanistan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James Critic's Notebook review of three television documentaries about Afghanistan: Saira Shah's Beneath the Veil and sequel Unholy War, on CNN, and National Geographic Explorer: Holy War, Inc, on MSNBC; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Saira Shah and her film crew sneaked across the border from Pakistan to Afghanistan last month, they kept the cameras rolling. In haunting black-and-white night vision, they are seen driving along a smugglers' road while Afghan men herd goats the other way, illegally heading to market. The journalists spot a Pakistani border patrol and abandon their truck, traipsing on foot for hours after their guide gets lost, wading across a river in 14-degree weather.</p>
        <p>In the morning, when the film bursts into color, they are in northern Afghanistan, 16,000 feet high (the same altitude as the base camp at Mount Everest). The frigid temperature and the thin air leave Ms. Shah, exhausted, barely able to talk, her speech slurred and her mouth askew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CNN's extraordinary "Unholy Wars" is one of three eye-opening documentaries about Afghanistan, and it's not easy to be eye-opening in the barrage of recent news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Saira Shah and her film crew sneaked across the border from Pakistan to Afghanistan last month, they kept the cameras rolling. In haunting black-and-white night vision, they are seen driving along a smugglers' road while Afghan men herd goats the other way, illegally heading to market. The journalists spot a Pakistani border patrol and abandon their truck, traipsing on foot for hours after their guide gets lost, wading across a river in 14-degree weather.</p>
        <p>In the morning, when the film bursts into color, they are in northern Afghanistan, 16,000 feet high (the same altitude as the base camp at Mount Everest). The frigid temperature and the thin air leave Ms. Shah, exhausted, barely able to talk, her speech slurred and her mouth askew.</p>
        <p>They travel a road that is shelled by the Taliban minutes after they pass. Yet in the midst of all this, the most poignant, revelatory scene is one that Americans would take for granted: in a classroom, little girls hold their books and read. This is the scene Ms. Shah accurately calls ''a miracle,'' and it arrives near the end of ''Unholy War'' with stunning impact. If a school for girls is a miracle, then the cultural distance between America and Afghanistan is unimaginably vast.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary ''Unholy War,'' which has its premiere on CNN tomorrow night, is one of three eye-opening documentaries about Afghanistan this weekend -- and it's not easy to be eye-opening in the barrage of recent news. It is the sequel to ''Beneath the Veil'' (to be repeated tomorrow afternoon). In that tough and deservedly acclaimed film, Ms. Shah, a reporter of Afghan descent raised in London, went to Afghanistan last winter and spring to report on the brutality of life under the Taliban, especially for women.</p>
        <p>''Holy War, Inc.,'' Sunday's installment of ''National Geographic Explorer,'' complements ''Unholy War'' in more than its title: it begins in Pakistan with a classroom of little boys being trained for a jihad. Based on Peter L. Bergen's new book, ''Holy War, Inc.: Inside the Secret World of Osama bin Laden,'' it relies more heavily than Ms. Shah's films on Western experts and reporting. And although it is disappointing and perfunctory next to Mr. Bergen's slim yet thorough book, it has a thoughtful, opinionated quality rare among current documentaries.</p>
        <p>Events have moved so fast this week that television has been filled with unexpected images from Kabul of men shaving their beards, women showing their faces and Taliban corpses in the streets. Even the most recent documentaries might literally be yesterday's news. These three function on a level beyond flat-out information. They do not bridge the gap between Western and Islamic culture but expose it with unforgettable drama.</p>
        <p>''Beneath the Veil'' and ''Unholy War'' create before and after images of Afghanistan in recent months. When ''Beneath the Veil'' was first shown in late August, it was barely noticed. After the terror attacks in September it was replayed often (and helped Ms. Shah land a reported $650,000 book deal with Knopf). Seeing it again in the light of this week's events delivers fresh insights. When Ms. Shah visited Kabul earlier this year, she passed bombed-out buildings and streets full of rubble, the evidence of two decades of war, she explained. The once-thriving city had been decimated even before the Taliban took over in 1996. Her images of Kabul before the American bombing campaign look identical to this week's.</p>
        <p>The names of the cities she visits are more familiar now, but her audacity in reporting remains amazing. In ''Beneath the Veil'' she switches to using a hidden camera after she and her crew are arrested for filming in Kandahar and taken to the Ministry for the Prohibition of Vice and the Promotion of Virtue. The documentary includes horrific film (not originally shot for this program) of women in burqas being executed in Kabul's soccer stadium. And she travels to a village that was the site of a massacre by the Taliban, where she finds three girls, then 9, 12 and 15, who saw their mother shot to death.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shah's search for those girls gives her sequel its dramatic structure. In ''Unholy War'' she sets out to find how the bombing campaign has changed Afghanistan, but she is driven by the need to know if those sad girls whom she left huddled on the ground outside their house have survived. As in the first film, she addresses the camera directly and becomes our guide through dangerous terrain.</p>
        <p>In Pakistan she visits a weapons bazaar and finds that stingers, once available, have been sold out since Sept. 11. In Afghanistan she interviews a Northern Alliance soldier who offers a chilling prediction of this week's issues. Despite his allegiance to the anti-Taliban forces, he says: ''The Northern Alliance's veil will slip off when they capture Kabul. God forbid that the Northern Alliance should ever return to the anarchy and lawlessness which it brought about when the Communist government fell'' before the Taliban took over. (Throughout, people speak in their native languages, their words heard in English voice-overs.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Shah's quest to find the girls is milked a bit. Still it would be unfair to deprive her of the suspense she is determined to build. It is fair to say that she arrives in their village and finds her answer and that after she leaves she comes upon the school for girls.</p>
        <p>Unlike the school she visited in ''Beneath the Veil'' in Taliban-controlled territory, this one is not illegal. But it is heartbreaking and hopeful nonetheless. The students, who sit on the floor in a circle, are so poor they live in tents. A girl who looks about 4 gnaws on one of the bright yellow food packets that have been airdropped by the United States.</p>
        <p>''The girls want to be doctors, engineers,'' their teacher says, though that sounds more like her dream than theirs. Ms. Shah tells the camera that she has decided to help send some girls to this school, but in the end her offer is rebuffed by their father. Even she, who has been immersed in this culture, has misread it.</p>
        <p>The boys' school seen at the start of ''Holy War, Inc.'' is one of thousands like it in Pakistan, and its headmaster does not have a reassuring message. ''Osama is doing this because whatever is happening is not his fault,'' he says. ''And he has every right to take revenge, whatever is in his power.''</p>
        <p>The film has some peculiar lapses. Mr. Bergen, CNN's terrorism analyst, is not the narrator but the primary talking head. And though his book begins with a stunning description of his meeting with Mr. bin Laden in 1997, when Mr. Bergen was the CNN producer for Peter Arnett's interview, no film of that interview is included. (The rights were not available from CNN.) Instead, we see a photograph of Mr. bin Laden in a cave, Mr. Bergen on his left and Mr. Arnett on his right.</p>
        <p>Much of the bin Laden history presented is familiar, but the film raises valuable questions about United States intelligence failures and responds with harsh assessments, taking on a subject too many reporters still consider off-limits. Mr. Bergen points to the case of Ali Mohamed, an Egyptian-American who served in both countries' armies and was an instructor at Fort Bragg in North Carolina. He was also an Al Qaeda sleeper agent, who took a photograph of the American embassy in Nairobi, which helped Mr. bin Laden plan its bombing later. He is a template of the hijackers, Mr. Bergen says.</p>
        <p>And the film notes that the United States government had a great deal of information, badly handled and assessed, about the dangers of refueling a ship in Yemen. The bombing there of the U.S.S. Cole was, the narrator says, ''a plot that the government could have known about.''</p>
        <p>''Holy War, Inc.'' also observes glaring examples of the gap between Islam and the West and of how culture and politics get tangled. During the Persian Gulf war, Mr. bin Laden was furious when American troops entered Saudi Arabia; he saw infidels in the Muslims' holy land. In contrast, the narrator says, ''Most Americans thought their troops were risking their lives in order to help the people of Kuwait.'' (That ignores the fact that plenty of Americans thought it was all about oil, but the point about clashing cultures holds.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bergen, whose reasoned, solid analyses on CNN make it clear that he is no alarmist, concludes the documentary by saying that even if Mr. bin Laden and the top Al Qaeda leaders were to vanish tomorrow, their legacy of terror would remain. ''Too many people have been trained in bin Laden's camps, and he has inspired too many people in the Muslim world with a sort of anti-Western, anti-American sentiment,'' he says. ''We're going to see this conflict go on for a very long time.''</p>
        <p>Cultural Chasm</p>
        <p>The dates and times of the television programs in the Critic's Notebook article:</p>
        <p>''BENEATH THE VEIL,'' CNN, tomorrow at 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>''UNHOLY WAR,'' CNN, tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 11 a.m. and 4, 7 and 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>''NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC EXPLORER: HOLY WAR, INC.,'' MSNBC, Sunday at 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
