<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solid Contemporary Sale Ends 2 Weeks of Auctions</title>
    <meta content="16AUCT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/16/arts/design/16AUCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lichtenstein, Roy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Warhol, Andy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Johns, Jasper</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kelly, Ellsworth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFD8143BF935A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solid Contemporary Sale Ends 2 Weeks of Auctions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High Energy and Prices at Contemporary-Art Sale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Auction of contemporary art is held at Christie's; sale totals $6.9 million with 38 of 49 works being bought; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the quirky world of contemporary art, taste comes in many forms. At Christie's last night, more than four bidders each would have happily taken home a partially used bar of soap inlaid with an artist's pubic hair, or 325 pounds of hard candy  wrapped in blue cellophane, or even a stark hanging light bulb. Lots of people were also willing to pay many thousands of dollars for photographs that exist in multiple editions.</p>
        <p>The auction -- the last in two weeks of evening fine art sales -- ended with a sigh of relief. The international crowd of dealers and collectors who converged on Christie's Rockefeller Center salesroom seemed drained. Yet while there were no fireworks or even million-dollar objects changing hands, restrained but solid bidding produced a respectable outcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>American artists like Roy Lichtenstein, Andy Warhol and Jasper Johns are exactly what collectors want right now. And that's exactly what Sotheby's offered for sale. right now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the quirky world of contemporary art, taste comes in many forms. At Christie's last night, more than four bidders each would have happily taken home a partially used bar of soap inlaid with an artist's pubic hair, or 325 pounds of hard candy  wrapped in blue cellophane, or even a stark hanging light bulb. Lots of people were also willing to pay many thousands of dollars for photographs that exist in multiple editions.</p>
        <p>The auction -- the last in two weeks of evening fine art sales -- ended with a sigh of relief. The international crowd of dealers and collectors who converged on Christie's Rockefeller Center salesroom seemed drained. Yet while there were no fireworks or even million-dollar objects changing hands, restrained but solid bidding produced a respectable outcome.</p>
        <p>The auction totaled $6.9 million, near the middle of its estimate of $6.1 million to $8.3 million. Of the 49 works on offer, 11 failed to sell.</p>
        <p>''Before the sale, people were worried about how it would fare,'' said Christophe van de Weghe, a Chelsea dealer. ''Considering there wasn't a lot of great material, it was fine.''</p>
        <p>Since 1998, when Christie's separated postwar art (works made from 1945 to the late 1960's) from what it defines as contemporary art (works dating from the last 35 years), it has brought young artists out of the galleries and into the auction house. The formula has been a phenomenal success, but last night's offerings -- 18 photographs, 16 paintings, the rest sculpture or installation works -- weren't as strong as those in past sales, and the audience knew it. Still, throughout the last two weeks, good works brought strong prices.</p>
        <p>The Cuban-born artist Felix Gonzalez-Torres's ''Untitled'' (Blue Placebo),'' from 1991, the 325 pounds of hard candies, one of the most expensive work of the evening. Three bidders tried to buy the work, which it ended up selling to a telephone bidder for $666,000, at its low estimate, $600,000. (Final prices include Christie's commission, 17.5 percent of the first $80,000 plus 10 percent any amount above that. Estimates do not reflect commissions.)</p>
        <p>Alex Katz's ''Blue Umbrella No. 2,'' a 1972 portrait of the artist's wife, Ada, standing under an umbrella in the pouring rain, also brought $666,000. Lorinda Ash, a Manhattan dealer bought the painting, which had an estimate of $500,000 to $700,000. After the sale, she said she had bought it for a client.</p>
        <p>The photography market, which had reached a somewhat frenzied pitch in recent seasons, remained  strong. Last night's offerings included a group of works being sold by Hans Grothe, a 70-year-old German real estate developer, who tried without great success to sell a group of works by German artists at Christie's on Tuesday night. Last night, Mr. Grothe offered 15 photographs. all of which brought solid prices. Christie's had given Mr. Grothe a guarantee, an undisclosed minimum price promised to a seller regardless of a sale's outcome, on all the property he was consigning this season, and the photography performed well.</p>
        <p>By far the top seller was Mr. Gursky's ''Paris, Montparnasse'' (1993). Estimated at $300,000 to $400,000, it sold to an unidentified buyer for $600,000, a record for the artist.</p>
        <p>Three photographs by Mr. Struth, taken at different museums, all sold.  The most highly sought-after was ''Kunsthistorisches Museum III,'' No. 9 from an edition of 10 executed in 1989, which sold to the Marion Goodman Gallery for $88,125, above its high estimate of $80,000.</p>
        <p>The market for young British artists was tested last night. Artists like Gary Hume, Sarah Lucas, Chris Ofili and Jenny Saville, whose prices began falling at the June sales in London, brought mixed results. The main seller was Charles Saatchi, the British advertising magnate and collector, who has been a large consignor at auction over the years.</p>
        <p>Last night, Mr. Saatchi was selling two works by Ms. Lucas. ''Receptacle of Lurid Things'' (1991), a wax sculpture of a middle finger, estimated at $30,000 to $40,000, was bought by Eugene Lopez, a Mexican collector, for $30,550. But ''Figleaf in the Ointment,'' by Ms. Lucas, a 1991 plaster cast of the artist's armpits and hair, did not appeal to last night's crowd. Estimated at $25,000 to $35,000, it went unsold at $18,000.</p>
        <p>Three bidders tried to buy Mr. Hume's ''Jealousy and Passion'' (1993), a collage depicting an androgynous figure that was expected to bring $80,000 to $120,000. It sold to a telephone buyer for $88,125. A 1995 painting by Chris Ofili with clumps of the artist's signature elephant dung sold to another telephone bidder for $82,250, just above its low estimate, $80,000.</p>
        <p>''There's still a lot of money floating around,'' said Jack Tilton, a Manhattan dealer, as he was leaving the sale. ''There's just not a lot of top material.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
