<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THEATER GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="16THEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/16/arts/theater/16THEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5DD173BF935A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="4194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THEATER GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Theater Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend. Approximate running times are in parentheses. * denotes a highly recommended show.  + means discounted tickets were available at the Theater Development Fund's TKTS booth for performances last Friday and Saturday nights.  ++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for last Friday night only.  +++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for performances last Saturday night only.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend. Approximate running times are in parentheses. * denotes a highly recommended show.  means discounted tickets were available at the Theater Development Fund's TKTS booth for performances last Friday and Saturday nights.  means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for last Friday night only.  means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for performances last Saturday night only.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy Broadway and Off Broadway shows this weekend. Approximate running times are in parentheses. * denotes a highly recommended show.  + means discounted tickets were available at the Theater Development Fund's TKTS booth for performances last Friday and Saturday nights.  ++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for last Friday night only.  +++ means discounted tickets were available at the TKTS booth for performances last Saturday night only.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>*+ ''DANCE OF DEATH.'' As the infirm army captain living in spiteful and isolated wedlock in Strindberg's poisoned portrait of a marriage, Ian McKellen brings something frightening and majestic to the act of putting one wayward foot before the other. He projects aggressive arrogance that doesn't so much conquer decay as ignore it. Every willed gesture, no matter how sloppy, becomes a death-defying act. And he has been given a co-star of comparable firepower in the throaty siren Helen Mirren as the captain's adversarial helpmate, Alice, who bursts into glorious artificial bloom in the second act. The production as a whole, directed by Sean Mathias, doesn't entirely live up to its leading couple. As the third member of the play's triangle, David Strathairn takes his character's passivity past the vanishing point. And there are chafing discrepancies in tone throughout. Still, watching Mr. McKellen shooting off sparks in the dark mouth of mortality is about as thrilling as theater gets (2:20). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.  Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $50 to $70 (Ben Brantley).</p>
        <p>*+ ''HEDDA GABLER.'' Ibsen's most perplexing heroine has been reincarnated by Kate Burton with a clarity that stings in Nicholas Martin's pistol shot of a production. In a way Ms. Burton does for Hedda, who has traditionally been shrouded in glamorous shadows, what Simon Russell Beale recently did for Hamlet: she has scaled a titanic figure down to accessible human dimensions without ever trivializing her. For once, we are allowed to understand and perhaps identify with the contradictory impulses that jerk Hedda Gabler through life. We may even -- and of course she would loathe this -- feel sorry for this woman, who is positively electric with dissatisfaction. Hedda's rabid, jittery unhappiness and dry wit set the evening's pace: a rhythmic back and forth between self-containment and disintegration. The fine supporting cast includes Michael Emerson as Hedda's obtuse scholar of a husband and Harris Yulin, who is superb as Judge Brack, that most sinister embodiment of the status quo (2:30). Ambassador Theater, 215 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performance Nov. 23 at 2 p.m. Tickets: $30 to $70; $25 student rush tickets available on the day of the performance (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* ''MAMMA MIA!'' It's a widely known truth that when the going gets tough, the tough want cupcakes. Those in need of such solace -- and who isn't now? -- have been rewarded with this giant singing Hostess cupcake of a show. Sure, the ingredients sound icky: a score made up of songs from the disco-era Swedish pop group Abba, a sitcom-ish excuse for a plot that might as well be called ''My Three Dads.'' Yet under the direction of Phyllida Lloyd, this sunny look at generational clashes (on a blissfully bug-free Greek island) becomes the canniest exercise in klutziness to hit Broadway, the theatrical answer to comfort food. With a very happy cast led by three well-seasoned belters -- Louise Pitre, Judy Kaye and Karen Mason -- the show conjures up the way old Top 40 hits insinuate themselves into your mind at critical moments, providing unsolicited sound tracks. Hokey, silly, square and terrific fun (2:20). Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 563-5544. Mondays through Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performance Nov. 23 at 2 p.m. Tickets: $55 to $98.75 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* ''NOISES OFF.'' In this spectacularly funny revival of Michael Frayn's peerless backstage comedy, there are moments when everyone -- onstage and in the audience -- seems to be riding the same runaway roller coaster. Onstage, a group of perfectly likable actors is falling apart. And as for the audience -- well, if someone had thought to replace screams with laughter in the days of primal therapy, this is what it would have sounded like. The reassuring fact remains, however, that the creators of this production are supremely in control. The director Jeremy Sams masterfully orchestrates a fine-tuned ensemble that includes Patti LuPone, Peter Gallagher, Faith Prince, Richard Easton and a dazzling comic bombshell named Katie Finneran. As a team, they go to pieces with balletic exactitude. And for theatergoers in New York, the world capital of control freaks on the verge, this disciplined rendering of chaos starts to feel like an exorcism (2:25). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performance Nov. 23 at 2 p.m.Tickets: $40 to $75 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>* ''URINETOWN.'' This fiercely loopy and self-conscious satire of the social conscience of the musical theater is both exuberantly entertaining and, in the context of recent events, a defiant statement on behalf of American creativity and vibrancy. The story is ridiculous spoofery: the population of a city that has been desiccated by drought revolts against the corrupt alliance of business and government that controls public toilets. And with a rousing score by Mark Hollmann, a ribald and tongue-in-cheek book by Greg Kotis, hilariously referential choreography by John Carrafa, gregarious staging by John Rando and a cast that is, as an ensemble, absolutely in sync in its level of hyperbole, the show couldn't be more ludicrously enjoyable. All that being said, however, it is impossible to ignore the solemnity of current events, from which the show is not entirely a distraction. Beneath its cartoonish surface, it tiptoes thematically along the edge of the grave issues that are now consuming all of us. It presents innocent people victimized by conscienceless evil, debates the appropriateness of murderous vengeance, illustrates the rage of those who suffer in poverty and perceive cruelty in capitalism and in the end lambastes the presumption and wastefulness of people who don't recognize that they are privileged. ''Urinetown'' is equal part visceral entertainment jolt and lingering provocation -- and simply the most gripping and galvanizing theater experience in town (2:10). Henry Miller, 124 West 43rd Street, (212) 239-6200. Mondays, Wednesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 and 7:30 p.m. Added performance Nov. 21 at 2 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performance Nov. 23 at 2 p.m. No performance Nov. 25 at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $35 and $85; a limited number of $25 tickets are at the box office three hours before each performance (Bruce Weber).</p>
        <p>''THE WOMEN.'' Clare Boothe Luce's 1936 play may be remembered by some as a clever toxology report on feminine venom. But its enduring and dubious appeal has more to do with the rowdy spectacle of ladies being anything but ladylike. It's a glorified cat show, made for overripe, overdecorated stars to cut loose in. That is more or less the approach of Scott Elliott's bumpy revival, which features dressed-to-maim (and not always flattering) costumes from Isaac Mizrahi. There are occasional glimmers of something more substantive -- most notably in a superb performance from Cynthia Nixon, who finds layers of class-bred conflict in the play's noble heroine. But overall, the production is overwhelmingly shrill. Jennifer Tilly is miscast as the sexually cunning shopgirl, but Jennifer Coolidge and Kristen Johnston are very funny as two specimens of refined vulgarity, Park Avenue-style (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2 p.m. Added performance Nov. 19 at 8 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performance Nov. 25 at 8 p.m. Tickets: $40 to $70 (Brantley).</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>++ ''THE COMPLETE WORKS OF WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE (ABRIDGED).'' Jeremy Dobrish, the artistic director of the Adobe Theater Company, has taken over the show in its second Off Broadway revival since it appeared in New York in an international arts festival 10 years ago. This revival is proof that ''Shakespeare Abridged'' has a robust life of its own. We still get all the comedies as uncomplicated variations on a simple plot involving endlessly confused identities and sexes. All the history plays are still rolled up into a very fast televised football game. The second act is saved for ''Hamlet'': a half-hour sendup followed by a one-minute version that is performed and spoken backward immediately after (1:40). Century Center for the Arts, 111 East 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. Mondays, Wednesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 4, 7 and 10 p.m.; Sundays at 4 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Added performances Nov. 23 at 4 p.m. and Nov. 28 at 2 p.m.  Tickets: $25 and $55 (D. J. R. Bruckner).</p>
        <p>* ''ELAINE STRITCH AT LIBERTY.'' Ethel Merman, who knew about such things, wrote of the star of this remarkable one-woman show: ''Stritch's glands work overtime.'' And the director, George C. Wolfe, has provided a luxuriously minimal prduction that makes no attempt to compete with such industrious glands. A collage of song and reminscence from the most enduring of musical comedy veterans, assembled by Ms. Stritch and John Lahr, the show is nothing like the concerts in the manner of the aging Marlene Dietrich, mummified in sequined splendor. Ms. Stritch's glamour comes from her timing, her solar energy and a voice that makes gravel seem like Carrara marble. Reanimating several decades of her personally embossed showstoppers, from ''Zip'' to ''The Ladies Who Lunch,'' Ms. Strich turns ''At Liberty'' into a one-woman testimony to the vitality that once made the Broadway musical the liveliest of the American arts (2:20). Joseph Papp Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Tickets: $45; extremely limited (Brantley).</p>
        <p>+++ ''WHERE'S MY MONEY?'' John Patrick Shanley's new play about marriage has a sardonic, wicked tone that sounds personal, the kind that results when a talented writer tears into his own rage and frustration with exorcising zeal. The play takes the form of a series of two-handed scenes in which a perverse daisy chain of connections is established. Celeste, an unhappy young single woman, tells Natalie, a former co-worker, about the sado-masochistic affair she is having with Sidney, a divorce lawyer who clings adhesively to the mutual vitriol he shares with his wife, Marcia Marie. Sidney's junior colleague, Henry, turns out to be married himself, to a woman whose commitment he fears is shaky: Natalie. There is also a ghost, a spectral symbol of the emotional, psychological and circumstantial burdens that are too unwieldy for the characters to manage. That their tangled problems end up being reduced to the title question is a measure of the play's bitter humor (1:25). Manhattan Theater Club Stage 2, City Center, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. Tuesdays through Fridays at 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays at 3 and 7:30 p.m. Added performance Nov. 19 at 7:30 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Tickets: $45 (Weber).</p>
        <p>''WONDER OF THE WORLD.'' David Lindsay-Abaire, the gifted young author of ''Fuddy Meers,'' hasn't lost his playfully wicked eye for the United States as a consumerist version of Alice's Wonderland in which everything swells and shrinks out of proportion. In this exceedingly whimsical tale of the self-seeking odyssey of an exceedingly whimsical young woman (the delectable Sarah Jessica Parker), a giant peanut butter jar becomes a murder weapon and a Barbie doll's head is an object of desire. Yet while the evening features four actresses -- Ms. Parker, Kristine Nielsen, Amy Sedaris and Marylouise Burke -- who are experts in making loopiness seem logical, the play's wackiness mostly feels strained and imposed. In ''Fuddy Meers,'' Mr. Lindsay-Abaire swept you into his characters' surreal road trip; this one provides only the map, however colorfully drawn. The show has been directed with surface-skimming smoothness by Christopher Ashley (2:25). Manhattan Theater Club Stage 1, City Center, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. Tuesdays through Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2:30 and 7 p.m. Added performance Nov. 19 at 8 p.m. No performance Thanksgiving evening. Tickets: $60 (Brantley).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
