<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Not everyone is surprised as a dental-industry deal goes awry.</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="714826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW IMAGE INDUSTRIES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DENTSPLY INTERNATIONAL INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DD113AF93BA1575AC0A962958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Not everyone is surprised as a dental-industry deal goes awry.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE proposed takeover of New Image Industries, a dental supplier, died yesterday. But it looks as though some traders may have been less surprised than others.</p>
        <p>New Image, which had signed a letter of agreement on July 28 to be acquired by Dentsply International, a much larger company, at $16.375 a share, plunged $5, to $8, yesterday after an announcement that Dentsply had backed out of the deal. Dentsply said issues uncovered in due diligence had not been resolved to its satisfaction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE proposed takeover of New Image Industries, a dental supplier, died yesterday. But it looks as though some traders may have been less surprised than others.</p>
        <p>New Image, which had signed a letter of agreement on July 28 to be acquired by Dentsply International, a much larger company, at $16.375 a share, plunged $5, to $8, yesterday after an announcement that Dentsply had backed out of the deal. Dentsply said issues uncovered in due diligence had not been resolved to its satisfaction.</p>
        <p>The deal's demise was perhaps not totally unexpected. New Image stock fell in mid-September, on very heavy volume, as rumors circulated of problems in due diligence.</p>
        <p>A trader, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said brokers told him of an order by one investor to sell 100,000 New Image shares on Sept. 15.</p>
        <p>On that day, on volume of 102,500 shares, New Image fell 25 cents, to $14.625. The next day, on volume of 631,600 shares -- 14 percent of the shares outstanding -- it plunged $2.125, to $12.50. That was the last trading day before a definitive merger agreement was scheduled to be signed.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 19, the two companies announced they had extended the due diligence period, and the stock rallied a bit. But then came yesterday's announcement that the deal was off. It left unanswered the question of just what had gone wrong in the due diligence, and the stock fell to a level lower than it was before the deal was announced.</p>
        <p>In any such case, the question of who sold, and why, becomes an interesting one. Some, no doubt, were responding to rumors. But some may have had better information on what was going on.</p>
        <p>One group of sellers who were little involved were short-sellers; they borrow shares and sell them, in hope of profiting from a decline in price. Under new Nasdaq rules, which went into effect this month, short-sellers cannot sell if the current bid price for the stock is below the previous bid price. On the heavy volume days, there were few such downticks, and one short-seller, speaking on condition of anonymity, said he had tried to sell stock short all day on Sept. 15 and managed to sell exactly 300 shares.</p>
        <p>"This rule," he complained at the time, well before yesterday's announcement, "protected them from people like me, but not from the longs who were selling."</p>
        <p>New Image makes a computer dental imaging system that allows dentists to take pictures of a patient's mouth, then alter them to show just how much better the mouth would look with cosmetic dental surgery. The stock climbed as high as $21 in the summer of 1993, but has suffered this year in part because of a suit contending that the camera used in the system violates another company's patent. New Image has redesigned the camera and says its current product does not violate the patent.</p>
        <p>Roger Leddington, New Image's chief executive, did not return telephone calls. But in a statement yesterday, he said that New Image remained "a strong company" that would not be hurt by Dentsply's decision. The statement did not discuss what the issues identified in due diligence were.</p>
        <p>For some shareholders who paid more, even the company's decision to sell to Dentsply at $16.375 a share had been a big disappointment. Now, with a buyer having gained inside information and deciding to back away, it appears that the company will eventually have to offer a more complete explanation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
