<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Center Field, Soriano Has No Place to Hide</title>
    <meta content="18soriano" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/18/sports/baseball/18soriano.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Soriano, Alfonso</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DE1630F93BA25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Center Field, Soriano Has No Place to Hide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Center Field, Soriano Has No Place to Hide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>SCOTTSDALE, Ariz., March 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alfonso Soriano of the Chicago Cubs crouched so low in center field that his waist was almost even with his knees. He rose from his crouch when a ball soared into a cloudless sky and he sprinted across the grass to make a stylish catch. For those few seconds, Soriano looked and acted like a competent center fielder.</p>
        <p>Of course, this seamless sequence occurred in pregame drills. Soriano knew a coach was hitting a fly ball toward him and he basically knew the area where it would travel. His challenge is to become as comfortable playing this demanding position in games that matter as he looked during a workout that barely mattered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alfonso Soriano is critical to any hopes, authentic or idealistic, that the Chicago Cubs have of ending their 98-year funk without a World Series title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alfonso Soriano of the Chicago Cubs crouched so low in center field that his waist was almost even with his knees. He rose from his crouch when a ball soared into a cloudless sky and he sprinted across the grass to make a stylish catch. For those few seconds, Soriano looked and acted like a competent center fielder.</p>
        <p>Of course, this seamless sequence occurred in pregame drills. Soriano knew a coach was hitting a fly ball toward him and he basically knew the area where it would travel. His challenge is to become as comfortable playing this demanding position in games that matter as he looked during a workout that barely mattered.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I'm going to have problems,'' Soriano said. ''I want to make sure I'm ready for opening day.''</p>
        <p>The Cubs open another season on April 2 with renewed hope that they can finally end a 98-year World Series title drought. Soriano, who signed an eight-year, $136 million free-agent contract, is critical to any hopes, authentic or idealistic, that the Cubs have of ending that exasperating hex.</p>
        <p>While the speedy, sinewy Soriano was signed because he is an offensive force who hit 46 homers and stole 41 bases with the Washington Nationals last season, Manager Lou Piniella added a thorny assignment by asking him to switch from the low pressure of left field to the caldron that is center.</p>
        <p>Remember, this is the same player that initially objected to moving to left from second base for Washington a year ago because he was worried about embarrassing himself. Soriano acquiesced and was not an embarrassment. Still, some baseball officials are skeptical that Soriano can suddenly morph into a valuable center fielder.</p>
        <p>Piniella sees an athletic player whose quickness will help him corral shots driven into the gaps and whose infield experience should help with his footwork. Even though Soriano, 31, may never adapt and may cause the Cubs to unveil a Plan B, Piniella does not consider the move a gamble.</p>
        <p>''What are the risks?'' Piniella said. ''We make a change. Look, the only thing I don't want to do is let it affect his hitting. Outside of that, I think the rest will take good care of itself.''</p>
        <p>When Mike Quade, Chicago's third-base and outfield coach, began to tutor Soriano last month, he started with the basics. Quade tossed balls high in the air, like a father does with an 8-year-old, to gauge how Soriano broke for them and to study Soriano's footwork.</p>
        <p>If a center fielder's footwork is sloppy and he does not take the right angles or have a crisp crossover step, Quade said he was doomed. Quade's first lesson to Soriano stressed how repetition should eventually lead to him gliding along without wondering about his footwork. Quade's next lesson and the one after that will impart the same message.</p>
        <p>While Quade praised Soriano's improvement, he was candid about the degree of difficulty regarding what Soriano is attempting. He mentioned how the premier center fielders are the ones who master the nuances of the position, something that only happens after they have been doing it for years.</p>
        <p>''You look at the great center fielders,'' Quade said. ''Very few of them have decided in their late 20s, after playing second or the infield, that, you know, very few of them have just become great center fielders. It's just to put in perspective what we're asking of him and what should be expected initially as far as his progress goes.''</p>
        <p>Soriano said the most arduous plays are judging the line drives that are punched directly at him and navigating around the warning track and the fence. Quade noted that Soriano, who was subservient in left, has to be aggressive and take control around right fielder Jacque Jones and Matt Murton or Cliff Floyd in left.</p>
        <p>Little by little, Soriano keeps learning. He was appreciative when Mike Cameron of the San Diego Padres, a three-time Gold Glove winner in center, told him to play deeper. Cameron advised Soriano to retreat a few steps because he was better equipped to run in for a ball than to back up on one.</p>
        <p>Regardless of what Soriano does in spring training, his serious tests will come when he deals with the playing conditions at Wrigley Field. The twisting winds there can punish outfielders, and the ivy-covered brick wall is an element Soriano has never experienced.</p>
        <p>''I'm more comfortable,'' Soriano said. ''Last year, I proved I can make some plays.''</p>
        <p>Once the Nationals threatened to put Soriano on the disqualified list last year, he jogged out to left, stayed there and had a productive season. Soriano, who has a strong arm and an unorthodox motion, led the major leagues with 22 assists, in part because runners challenged him. He also made 11 errors, which was the second most in the majors and a high amount for someone at such a benign position. Soriano said he finally thinks like an outfielder.</p>
        <p>''I believe that I have the talent to play outfield,'' Soriano said. ''In the past, I had a problem making the transition. I didn't believe in myself.''</p>
        <p>Robin Yount, who was a Gold Glove shortstop, and Craig Biggio, a four-time Gold Glove award winner as a second baseman, both moved to center field in their careers. Soriano, who is not as sharp defensively as them, is trying to do the same.</p>
        <p>When Piniella was asked if Soriano reminded him of any center fielder, he paused for 15 seconds. Eventually, he concocted an answer.</p>
        <p>''Let's hope,'' Piniella said, ''he reminds me of Mike Cameron by the time the summer is over.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
