<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bernadette Murray and Randy Fertel</title>
    <meta content="18VOWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/18/fashion/weddings/18VOWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murray, Bernadette (Bernadette Fertel)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fertel, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murray, Bernadette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fertel, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reckdahl, Katy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDD1F31F93BA25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bernadette Murray and Randy Fertel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bernadette Murray and Randy Fertel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATY RECKDAHL</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernadette Murray and Randey Fertel wed in New Orleans; photos (M) (Vows Column)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE chatter among the 175 guests gathered under the live oaks of Audubon Park in New Orleans for the wedding of Bernadette Murray and Randy Fertel was upbeat but also circumspect. They gushed about the setting and marveled about the beauty of the bride. And barely a word about the tough times the couple had just been through.</p>
        <p>Less measured were the bride's grade-school-age nephews: ''Don't tell,'' one said in a stage whisper. ''Aunt Bernadette is wearing a wig!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For this couple, whose relationship was cemented during her battles with cancer, the words “in sickness and in health” had special meaning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE chatter among the 175 guests gathered under the live oaks of Audubon Park in New Orleans for the wedding of Bernadette Murray and Randy Fertel was upbeat but also circumspect. They gushed about the setting and marveled about the beauty of the bride. And barely a word about the tough times the couple had just been through.</p>
        <p>Less measured were the bride's grade-school-age nephews: ''Don't tell,'' one said in a stage whisper. ''Aunt Bernadette is wearing a wig!''</p>
        <p>Aunt Bernadette has been wearing a wig since shortly after she began treatment in May 2005 for acute myeloid leukemia, several months after Ms. Murray began dating Mr. Fertel.</p>
        <p>Early on, Ms. Murray tried to let Mr. Fertel off the hook, telling him that she didn't expect him to endure what appeared to be a long illness. Mr. Fertel responded by returning to the hospital with a big diamond ring in a blue Tiffany box.</p>
        <p>''I felt like she needed to know I wasn't going anywhere,'' said Mr. Fertel, who is 56 and works part of the year at the New School in New York, where he is an adjunct instructor, specializing in the literature of the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>He was in New York in late 2004 when the couple became acquainted, through a dating Web site. Ms. Murray, a Manhattanite, saw Mr. Fertel's online portrait, with his tousled hair and a goatee, and expressed her interest. ''He had such an earnest face, so I read on,'' she recalled.</p>
        <p>He in turn scanned her profile and responded, ''I know that you like to cook, what do you cook?''</p>
        <p>She said, apologetically, that unlike many of her fellow New Yorkers, she's a ''rabid carnivore.''</p>
        <p>She need not have apologized. Mr. Fertel, an easygoing, witty, divorced native New Orleanian, is a son of the late Ruth Fertel, who founded the Ruth's Chris Steak House chain there. (His father, Rodney Fertel, ran a quixotic campaign for mayor of New Orleans in 1969 that was notable for its sole focus on the need to obtain a gorilla for the Audubon Zoo there.)</p>
        <p>Their first meeting, at Babbo, the Greenwich Village restaurant, went badly, at least according to Ms. Murray, now 48. ''It was not a great first date,'' she said. ''All his answers were monosyllabic.''</p>
        <p>The evening was salvaged during the long walk they took afterward, and their next date was cemented as Mr. Fertel put her into a cab. ''He asked if he could give me a kiss,'' she said. ''That got him the second date -- he's a good kisser.''</p>
        <p>Subsequent dates in New York went more smoothly, but it was on a visit to New Orleans -- where he is head of the Fertel Foundation, which finances art, education and culinary projects, and also the Ruth U. Fertel Foundation, dedicated to education in Louisiana -- that the never-before-married Ms. Murray truly fell for him. While in town she met Mr. Fertel's longtime circle of friends. ''Creeps don't have good friends,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fertel explained his attraction. ''Here was this incredible, successful executive who was at the top of her game but wasn't cutthroat,'' he said of Ms. Murray, who was an executive vice president at BBDO, the advertising firm in New York, before becoming the associate publisher for marketing and creative services at House &amp; Garden magazine. Mr. Fertel also liked that she was driven but generous.</p>
        <p>Ms. Murray, one of a family of nine children who grew up in Kent, N.Y., nearly vibrates with energy and warmth. She is the one who keeps guests' wineglasses filled, arranges internships for nieces, asks about co-workers' children and takes home-cooked meals to sick relatives.</p>
        <p>After their first few dates, Mr. Fertel said he knew he was serious about her. But he also was in no hurry to commit. Then came Ms. Murray's chest pains, which led to tests and the diagnosis that rapidly altered the timeline of their relationship.</p>
        <p>The cure was less swift. She received a bone-marrow transplant at NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital in September 2005, but during her treatment she became bald, wilted to 88 pounds and couldn't go out in public for nearly a year, while her immune system rebuilt itself.</p>
        <p>At times it was embarrassing to be so needy and fragile in front of someone she had dated only for a short time, Ms. Murray recalled. ''I weighed nothing, my head was swollen, and my hair was coming out in clumps, so we had a barber come shave my head,'' she said. ''I couldn't move, I couldn't lift my head.''</p>
        <p>During that period, she recalled one day when Mr. Fertel visited her with tubes of fancy lotions: ''I looked down and thought, 'There is this man at the end of the bed that I hardly know who is rubbing my feet so that I'll feel better.' ''</p>
        <p>In January last year, as she was recovering, she was diagnosed with breast cancer. ''I thought this was just about too much,'' Mr. Fertel said. ''But I couldn't bring myself to desert her. She needed me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fertel was also concerned about how Ms. Murray would emerge from her illness. ''If she made it through, I didn't know if she would be the person I fell in love with,'' he said. ''It was a crapshoot, but I come from a family of gamblers.''</p>
        <p>Because Ms. Murray was too fragile for chemotherapy, she had a mastectomy followed by breast-reconstruction surgery. By July 2006, her blood work showed no sign of cancer.</p>
        <p>The couple are splitting their time between New York and New Orleans, but they chose to marry in the Crescent City, partly because they felt symmetry with the city's destruction and climb back to life.</p>
        <p>The process began on March 9, when they were joined in a civil ceremony at the Orleans Parish Civil District Court, officiated by Judge Madeleine Landrieu. When Judge Landrieu, reading the service from a three-ring binder, asked whether they would take each other ''in sickness and in health,'' the couple's eyes welled up.</p>
        <p>In keeping with the couple's theme, at their public ceremony on March 10, the jazz musician Kermit Ruffins raised his trumpet to the sunny sky and walked up the aisle playing ''Just a Closer Walk With Thee,'' a traditional New Orleans funeral dirge, for their processional. Though not empowered to marry the couple legally in that city, Ben Fong-Torres, the rock journalist and a Universal Life minister, led a service in which he talked about Ms. Murray's illness and how at one point in their courtship Ms. Murray had swooned when Mr. Fertel played for her an Olu Dara tune that went: ''Your lips, your lips, your lips are juice-saaayyyy'' like a Louisiana plum.</p>
        <p>The bride wore a copper-colored silk dress and carried orange and yellow tulips; the bridegroom wore a dark-blue tuxedo with black lapels and a black silk bow tie. Her little white dog, Bonnie, carried the rings on her collar.</p>
        <p>Afterward Mr. Ruffins and his band struck up an upbeat and joyous funeral tune, and led the guests to a reception at Mr. Fertel's home, an Arts and Crafts home built in 1915, which borders the park.</p>
        <p>As the adult guests sipped wine and ate canapés in the yard, the nephews sneaked into the dinner tent and attempted to rearrange the place cards so that they could sit next to their aunt. A waiter followed discreetly behind them and rearranged the cards so the bridegroom could be, as always, beside his rosy-cheeked bride in her renaissance.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
