<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Talk</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="466324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARRELL, HERMAN D JR (ASSEMBLYMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MICHELS, STANLEY E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE153AF932A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sam Howe Verhovek</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neutral but Leaning</p>
        <p>At the core of the struggle over redistricting of seats for the New York City Council has been minority politicians' demands that they be better represented on the expanded Council, whose primary is on Sept. 12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Neutral but Leaning</p>
        <p>At the core of the struggle over redistricting of seats for the New York City Council has been minority politicians' demands that they be better represented on the expanded Council, whose primary is on Sept. 12.</p>
        <p>But sometimes personal ties can conflict with this theoretical goal. One apparent case involves the loyalties of the Manhattan Democratic leader, Assemblyman Herman D. Farrell Jr., who is black.</p>
        <p>Although he has been in the forefront of calls for greater minority representation on the Council, other Manhattan Democratic leaders now say that Mr. Farrell seems to be favoring a longtime associate, Stanley E. Michels, who is white, over two black hopefuls for one of the seats whose boundaries have been redrawn to favor a black candidate.</p>
        <p>The race is in the new Seventh District, which includes portions of central and west Harlem, along with the western halves of Washington Heights and Inwood. Mr. Michels, a four-term Council incumbent, is battling the Harlem district leader, Peggy M. Shepard, and a lawyer, C. Vernon Mason.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrell, one of the highest-ranking black officials in the state, is publicly neutral in the race. But though he is close to Ms. Shepard, four party officials in northern Manhattan interviewed last week say Mr. Farrell has made it clear he is backing Mr. Michels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrell insisted in an interview that he was not endorsing anyone in the race. But he admitted to a warm feeling for Mr. Michels, who has been his ally in local politics for a quarter-century. "I've always considered Stan a very hard worker for our community," he said. Song's the Same</p>
        <p>A flurry of national attention surrounded last Friday's meeting of the United States Conference of Mayors in Hyannis, Mass., after its head, Mayor Raymond L. Flynn of Boston, predicted that Gov. Mario M. Cuomo would use the occasion to signal an intention to run for President.</p>
        <p>But even before Mr. Cuomo stepped into the hotel to speak, he gave a clear signal that there would be no such signal.</p>
        <p>Anyway, the signal was this: As he stepped out of his car, the Governor was greeted by Harry Belafonte, who was in town for an engagement at the Cape Cod Melody Tent.</p>
        <p>"You know, Harry," said Mr. Cuomo, who appeared bemused by the gaggle of national reporters who quickly surrounded him, "there's really nothing new in this speech. It'll be as familiar to you as your 'Day-O!' is to me." For Love Nor Money</p>
        <p>Has New York State fallen out of love with itself?</p>
        <p>Not really. But like a devoted suitor who cannot afford an engagement ring, it no longer has the money to tell the world how it feels.</p>
        <p>It all gets back to budget problems. The state tourism budget, which reached a high of $15.8 million in 1988, officials said, is now down to $3 million. And since March, the state has not broadcast any of its "I  NY" television commercials, some of which have featured Mr. Cuomo telling viewers, "You never knew love could be like this."</p>
        <p>While the State Department of Economic Development spent about $2 million last year on summer-oriented tourism advertising, there have been no such public displays of affection this year, although the state is hoping to begin a modest campaign in the fall. Running or Jumping</p>
        <p>Speaking of those who may or may not be running for President, add Ralph Nader to the list. The consumer advocate met recently with two of his former staff members who have filed papers with the Federal Election Commission to form a committee to draft Mr. Nader.</p>
        <p>Spearheading the effort is Carl Mayer, a Hofstra University law professor who worked for Mr. Nader's Center for the Study of Responsive Law about 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>"If enough citizens join together and indicate that they want him in the arena, he may relent," Mr. Mayer said. Mr. Mayer and his partner, Matthew Rothschild, publisher of The Progressive magazine, have not decided whether Mr.  Nader should run as a Democrat or as an independent.</p>
        <p>The two organizers are optimistic about talking Mr. Nader into a run. "So far," Mr. Rothschild said, "he hasn't told us to jump in the lake."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
