<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Consumer Groups Warn Tires May Explode</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="466439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLOSIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INSTITUTE FOR INJURY REDUCTION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC CITIZEN (ORGN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIRESTONE TIRE &amp; RUBBER CO</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD113CF932A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Consumer Groups Warn Tires May Explode</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two private safety groups contend that millions of tires used on light trucks may explode if mounted on the wrong-size wheels, and they accuse the tire industry of failing to eliminate a potentially fatal risk.</p>
        <p>Firestone, which was singled out by the groups, says no problems have occurred except when people mounting tires disregard "long-standing and well-known tire industry safety rules."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two private safety groups contend that millions of tires used on light trucks may explode if mounted on the wrong-size wheels, and they accuse the tire industry of failing to eliminate a potentially fatal risk.</p>
        <p>Firestone, which was singled out by the groups, says no problems have occurred except when people mounting tires disregard "long-standing and well-known tire industry safety rules."</p>
        <p>But at a news conference held by the safety groups here on Friday, Benjamin Kelley of the Institute for Injury Reduction, an organization founded by trial lawyers, said more than 250 lawsuits had been filed or were in the process of being filed concerning deaths or injuries from explosions as the tires were being inflated. Deaths and Injuries</p>
        <p>Based on that figure, he estimated that 2,000 to 3,000 people have been hurt or killed in the past 20 years from explosions caused by mounting 16-inch tires on 16 1/2-inch rims.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelley said at the news conference that Firestone, a subsidiary of Bridgestone Tire, and other tire makers have known about the danger for years. But he added that the manufacturers have only recently begun to reinforce their 16-inch tires to prevent the explosions when the tires are mistakenly inflated on 16 1/2-inch wheels.</p>
        <p>Joan Claybrook of Public Citizen, the other consumer group at the news conference, called the situation "a totally unnecessary and devastating tragedy." Public Citizen was founded by Ralph Nader.</p>
        <p>The two groups, in a letter to National Highway Traffic Safety Administration chief Jerry Ralph Curry, said a 16 1/2-inch rim was nearly indistinguishable from a 16-inch rim, even to an auto mechanic, and few tires or rims carry warnings of the potential danger. An explosion, they said, can hurl a 170-pound man 60 feet in the air.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Federal agency said his office had just received the letter and was discussing the issue.</p>
        <p>Firestone, based in Akron, Ohio, said it had made millions of the 16-inch light truck tires and they had "proved to be absolutely safe when fitted on the correct-size wheel rim." Warning Clearly Displayed</p>
        <p>A safety warning is clearly displayed on the sidewall of the tire, Firestone said in a statement, and "every accident of which we are aware that has occurred during the mounting of 16-inch tires on 16 1/2-inch rims has involved the violation of long-standing and well-known tire industry safety rules including the failure to properly match tire and rim sizes."</p>
        <p>The groups called for the tire industry and the Highway Traffic Safety Administration to recall all 16-inch tires lacking strengthened reinforcing beads, ban the use of 16 1/2-inch rims and launch a major campaign to alert pickup truck owners of the mismatch danger.</p>
        <p>Modesta Hernandez, of Beeville, Tex., whose husband suffered severe brain damage in a 1984 explosion and later committed suicide, blamed the tire industry for her suffering. "You're doing something very wrong," she said at Friday's news conference. "You're hurting people."</p>
        <p>In January, a Beeville court ordered Firestone to pay more than $1 million for a "deliberate campaign" to conceal evidence in a suit filed by Mrs. Hernandez, Mr. Kelley said. Firestone agreed to settle the case with a $4.9 million payment to the Hernandez family, he said.</p>
        <p>Firestone and other tire manufacturers knew of a mismatch danger by the early 1970's, shortly after production of the 16 1/2-inch rim began to rise, according to the Institute for Injury Reduction.</p>
        <p>The Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company began equipping its 16-inch tires with stronger beads resistant to explosion in 1980, at a cost of 15 cents a tire, but Firestone and General Tire began using the stronger bead only last year, Mr. Kelley said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
