<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York City: Garbage Ostrich</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="523837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN NAVY YARD (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1339F935A15757C0A964958260" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York City: Garbage Ostrich</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City faces a danger as grim as crime and disease. It could soon find itself strangling on its own garbage. Even as the volume of solid waste swells, the ways to get rid of it decline. The last landfill is nearly full. Recycling efforts are sorely inadequate. Exporting garbage is becoming ever more costly, and vulnerable to cutoff.</p>
        <p>What other option is there? Incineration, the alternative that City Hall reluctantly selected seven years ago because it had no other reasonable choice. By agreeing to build several safe incinerators that convert garbage to energy, the city was finally, painfully climbing upward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City faces a danger as grim as crime and disease. It could soon find itself strangling on its own garbage. Even as the volume of solid waste swells, the ways to get rid of it decline. The last landfill is nearly full. Recycling efforts are sorely inadequate. Exporting garbage is becoming ever more costly, and vulnerable to cutoff.</p>
        <p>What other option is there? Incineration, the alternative that City Hall reluctantly selected seven years ago because it had no other reasonable choice. By agreeing to build several safe incinerators that convert garbage to energy, the city was finally, painfully climbing upward.</p>
        <p>But Mayor David Dinkins, after three years of destructive procrastination, has not only stopped climbing. He is burying the city's head, like a stubborn ostrich, in the garbage.</p>
        <p>Instead of moving ahead with construction of the first new incinerator plant at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Mr. Dinkins once again embraces delay. He has put off initial construction until 1996 at the earliest. If the Mayor does not reverse himself, he risks burdening the city with immense costs, even a health crisis, before the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>Even the Mayor's own administration acknowledges New York has no choice. "This status quo, this waste-management system, cannot continue because the places where this waste was being put were either filling up or going out of existence," reads the Sanitation Department's new plan for managing solid waste.</p>
        <p>The city's last remaining landfill -- Fresh Kills on Staten Island -- will run out of space by the end of the decade even if the volume of garbage dumped there does not increase. But in all likelihood,</p>
        <p>it will</p>
        <p>. Congress is likely to ban the export of garbage or make it prohibitively expensive. Now, all of the city's commercial garbage -- about 40 percent of the total -- goes to out-of-state landfills. A new Federal law inhibiting the export of garbage would mean sending that waste, too, to Fresh Kills, so it would fill up faster.</p>
        <p>Aggressive recycling is essential to reduce the city's volume of garbage. But it's not going well in this city of crowded sidewalks and tall buildings.  New Yorkers now recycle only 6 to 8 percent of their garbage, and even if they could get that to 40 percent by the year 2000 -- the ambitious goal of Sanitation Commissioner Emily Lloyd -- what about the remaining 60 percent? Composting and reducing the waste stream could help, but not enough.</p>
        <p>The Dinkins administration knows and concedes all this. But then where is the leadership? Mr. Dinkins could be explaining that right now nearby cities -- including Newark and Bridgeport -- are safely operating modern incinerators that convert the heat they produce by burning garbage to electricity. He could be teaching that control systems now safely filter gases and that burning at high temperatures limits the production of poisonous pollutants. He could tell New Yorkers that the residual toxic ash can be properly disposed of in lined "ash-fills."</p>
        <p>City Hall says that if it appears likely that Fresh Kills has to close earlier than the year 2000, it will accelerate construction of the Navy Yard plant. It's not that easy. The longer the city waits, the more trouble it could have getting state and Federal environmental permits. Delay now risks greater delay -- and danger -- later, when the city has run out of time and options.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
