<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Chamber To Offer Plans Of SunAmerica</title>
    <meta content="Y26INS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chamber of Commerce of the United States</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sunamerica Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D81330F935A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Chamber To Offer Plans Of SunAmerica</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Chamber of Commerce is making push to increase retirement plans among its members and says it is turning to SunAmerica Inc, one of biggest variable annuity companies, to do the job (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Chamber of Commerce, the largest organization of small businesses, is making a push to increase retirement plans among its members and said yesterday that it was turning to SunAmerica Inc., one of the biggest variable annuity companies, to do the job.</p>
        <p>SunAmerica, a unit of American International Group, beat out 10 other retirement plan companies in bidding for the business, chamber officials said, after Fidelity Investments decided it no longer wanted to offer its retirement plans through the chamber.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Chamber of Commerce, the largest organization of small businesses, is making a push to increase retirement plans among its members and said yesterday that it was turning to SunAmerica Inc., one of the biggest variable annuity companies, to do the job.</p>
        <p>SunAmerica, a unit of American International Group, beat out 10 other retirement plan companies in bidding for the business, chamber officials said, after Fidelity Investments decided it no longer wanted to offer its retirement plans through the chamber.</p>
        <p>The deal gives SunAmerica a link to the group's roughly three million small business members. The costs of the SunAmerica plan to employers and workers will be about the same as with Fidelity, said P. Daniel Demko, who is in charge of group retirement plans at SunAmerica.</p>
        <p>SunAmerica will offer a package of variable annuities, a combination of insurance and funds similar to mutual funds, in its retirement plans while Fidelity's plans were made up of standard mutual funds. Variable annuity plans usually charge more than mutual fund plans, partly because of the insurance feature, and many financial advisers say the extra expense is not justified.</p>
        <p>In any case, Mr. Demko said SunAmerica was willing to cut its costs on the plans sold through the chamber in exchange for a chance at great volume. Sun feels it can succeed -- where Fidelity, a unit of the FMR Corporation, did not -- because of plans to unleash a much more aggressive sales approach through its force of 9,000 representatives, one of the largest in the business.</p>
        <p>Fidelity executives said they sold more retirement plans to small businesses through efforts outside the chamber. Moreover, Fidelity said it was starting an Internet company for setting up and running retirement plans on May 1. Costs for customers over the Internet, Fidelity said, will be lower than through the other channels.</p>
        <p>Robert L. Reynolds, the president of Fidelity Investments Institutional Retirement Group, said Fidelity had worried that small-business owners might have become confused and gone elsewhere as Fidelity's plans were offered to them through the chamber, Fidelity representatives and the Internet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
