<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Real Estate; Cartier Spruces Up to Show Off Its Jewels in Style</title>
    <meta content="26REAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cartier (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DA1330F935A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Real Estate; Cartier Spruces Up to Show Off Its Jewels in Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cartier will temporarily close its landmark store on Fifth Avenue and 52nd Street during renovation that will begin in three months; will move to store at 711 Fifth Avenue, where it will do business until spring of 2001; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When your name is Cartier, you don't worry about stirring with every new breeze in fashion. Still, it is probably about time to freshen up Cartier's landmark store at Fifth Avenue and 52nd Street.</p>
        <p>The last big renovation, after all, occurred in 1917.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When your name is Cartier, you don't worry about stirring with every new breeze in fashion. Still, it is probably about time to freshen up Cartier's landmark store at Fifth Avenue and 52nd Street.</p>
        <p>The last big renovation, after all, occurred in 1917.</p>
        <p>That was when Pierre Cartier obtained the building from Commodore Morton F. Plant, the yachtsman and financier, in exchange for $100 in cash and a $1 million, double-strand, natural pearl necklace for Mae Cadwell Plant.</p>
        <p>In three months, Cartier will temporarily decamp from the six-story Plant mansion and move four blocks north, to the former Coca-Cola store at 711 Fifth Avenue, where it will do business until the spring of 2001.</p>
        <p>While the baubles are away, workers will recreate the long-lost main entrance on 52nd Street and construct a canopy over the new door. They will remove the mezzanine from the Fifth Avenue salesroom and shift the avenue entrance two bays south. They will also expand the size of the display windows, extend the bronze window grilles from the avenue facade around to 52nd Street and install retractable awnings on the first, second and third floors.</p>
        <p>''The whole project is like a Cartier product that you redesign as it was before and make it contemporary at the same time,'' said Alain Viot, president and chief executive of Cartier Inc.</p>
        <p>The point is to heighten Cartier's profile -- ever so tastefully -- at a time when commercial gigantism is steadily engulfing the discreet understatement of Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>''It will certainly raise the visibility of the facade, absolutely,'' said Simon J. Critchell, the chairman of Cartier Inc. and president and chief executive of Vendome North America Inc., the luxury-goods company that includes Cartier, Alfred Dunhill, Baume &amp; Mercier, Montblanc, Sulka and Piaget.</p>
        <p>Cartier's architects are Jean-Michel Wilmotte of Paris and Timothy P. Greer and David Schwartz of Butler Rogers Baskett in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The project was approved unanimously yesterday by the Landmarks Preservation Commission. ''Everything they've done is so right for the building,'' said Jennifer J. Raab, chairwoman of the commission. ''This proposal unifies the facade and continues one of the most successful adaptive reuses of a Fifth Avenue building.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Critchell would not disclose the cost of the remodeling or the recently completed office renovation upstairs and in the adjoining 4 East 52nd Street town house, other than to say that both projects would be worth ''a number of necklaces'' -- double-strand, natural pearl necklaces, that is, at 1917 prices.</p>
        <p>Cartier has not owned its New York headquarters for many years. Instead, it is a long-term tenant of Olympic Tower Associates, controlled by the Alexander S. Onassis Public Benefit Foundation, which was founded by Aristotle Onassis and named for his son. The Olympic Tower group is itself a tenant of the estate of Sol Goldman, which owns the entire Fifth Avenue block-front from 51st to 52nd Street, including the land under Olympic Tower.</p>
        <p>The original owner, Morton Plant, was a yachtsman, financier and benefactor of Connecticut College in New London. His 52nd Street mansion, completed in 1905, was designed by Robert W. Gibson in Italian Renaissance style.</p>
        <p>In 1914, at age 61, the commodore married Mae Cadwell Manwaring.  Although her age was not given at the time of her death in 1956, Cartier legend has it that she was 19 when Mr. Plant fell in love.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Plant apparently admired a necklace of 128 pearls that Pierre Cartier had painstakingly assembled in his workrooms at 712 Fifth Avenue, near 56th Street, now part of the Henri Bendel store.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Cartier needed more space and the Plants wanted to move uptown, away from the encroachments of commerce. So an exchange was effected: the $1 million necklace for the house. (With the advent of cultured pearls, the necklace plunged in value, fetching only $151,000 at auction in 1957.)</p>
        <p>The Plant house was renovated as the Cartier store in 1917 by William Welles Bosworth, architect of 195 Broadway, the former American Telephone &amp; Telegraph headquarters, at Fulton Street.</p>
        <p>About the only interior feature Bosworth left untouched was a coffered ceiling, embellished with swags and rosettes, in what was the second-floor music room and is now Cartier's service center. This ceiling will be preserved.</p>
        <p>Quite literally the centerpiece of the renovation will be the reopening of an arched portal on 52nd Street that has been a window since 1917. It sits under a two-story portico of neo-Classical style, announcing architecturally that it is supposed to be the front door, which it once was.</p>
        <p>This new entrance will usher customers directly into the middle room, known as the Oval Room, which will not be greatly altered. The biggest interior change will be the removal of a mezzanine from what was once the smoking room on Fifth Avenue, resulting in a ''sense of space that is going to be quite extraordinary,'' Mr. Critchell said.</p>
        <p>Though Cartier has 201 stores worldwide, it regards those on Fifth Avenue, New Bond Street in London and the Rue de la Paix in Paris as its ''temples,'' Mr. Critchell said. Attractive as the merchandise may be, he said, a building ''is as much a part of the way the company shows itself to the outside world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
