<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Presents Labor Proposals But Union Says It Is Insulted</title>
    <meta content="26LABO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Teamsters</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D91330F935A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Presents Labor Proposals But Union Says It Is Insulted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Giulaini administration, seeking to push citywide labor negotiations forward, presents its first formal contract proposals to Teamsters Local 237, but union calls proposals 'an insult' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to push citywide labor negotiations forward, the Giuliani administration presented its first formal contract proposals yesterday, but the union local that received the proposals, one that represents school safety officers and Housing Authority workers, called the proposals an insult.</p>
        <p>The city's labor commissioner, James F. Hanley, who has been overseeing the city's labor negotiations, presented a package that called for no across-the-board pay increases, with all raises coming instead in the form of individualized merit pay. The city also called for the workers to pay part of their health insurance premiums; the city now covers 100 percent of those premiums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to push citywide labor negotiations forward, the Giuliani administration presented its first formal contract proposals yesterday, but the union local that received the proposals, one that represents school safety officers and Housing Authority workers, called the proposals an insult.</p>
        <p>The city's labor commissioner, James F. Hanley, who has been overseeing the city's labor negotiations, presented a package that called for no across-the-board pay increases, with all raises coming instead in the form of individualized merit pay. The city also called for the workers to pay part of their health insurance premiums; the city now covers 100 percent of those premiums.</p>
        <p>The city made those proposals in talks yesterday with representatives of Local 237 of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, which represents 18,000 city workers. On March 2, that union local became the first union of municipal workers to present its demands in this year's round of negotiations.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Mancuso, the union's chief negotiator, denounced the city's demands. ''This proposal is an insult,'' he said. ''We are taxpayers and we are not going to be treated like beggars.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mancuso attacked in particular the city's merit pay proposal. ''We will not entertain the idea of merit pay as a condition for a new contract,'' he said. ''Merit pay is retrogression to a political patronage system.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani has repeatedly defended his merit pay proposal, saying the best way to encourage city workers to be more productive is to give raises to those doing the best work.</p>
        <p>In the proposals that the local presented in March, it called for across-the-board wage increases substantially higher than the inflation rate and a cash bonus to compensate workers for the three-year wage freeze that they took as part of their old contract.</p>
        <p>The union local represents school safety officers, police officers at city-owned hospitals and more than a dozen categories of Housing Authority workers, including maintenance workers, superintendents and heating technicians. For some of those workers, their contract expired on Dec. 31, while for others, it expired on March 31. The union's workers earn from $20,000 to more than $40,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Local 237 officials said yesterday that they would hesitate to bargain again with Mr. Hanley, the labor commissioner, unless some of Mr. Giuliani's City Hall aides were on hand.</p>
        <p>While many union officials have praised Mr. Hanley's professionalism, they say they believe that it will be hard to make significant progress in contract negotiations unless Mr. Giuliani sends top aides to join the commissioner at the table.</p>
        <p>In yesterday's talks, the city requested a five-year contract. Local 237 and other municipal unions are seeking a three-year contract.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
