<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feuds Rack Albania, Loosed From Communism</title>
    <meta content="Y14ALB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Albania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Albania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Albania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DB1E3DF937A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="1347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feuds Rack Albania, Loosed From Communism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>OLD TROPOJE, Albania</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blood feuds, which follow precepts laid down in medieval canon, is again part of Albanian society in which it lay superficially submerged during 50 years of Communist rule; since early 1990's revenge killings have spread among clans in village of Old Tropoje; weapons have become valued as much as human life, such that man who kills another and takes his weapon can be avenged with taking of two lives; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beneath the snow-splashed escarpments that protect northern Albania from the outside world and have left life much as it was centuries ago, the Sylaj family have been cooped up on their homestead for months, too afraid to move.</p>
        <p>A blood feud, following precepts laid down in a medieval canon, hangs over the men of the household, including the patriarch, Shaban Sylaj, 99, who welcomes visitors with a two-tooth grin, wisps of ash-colored hair poking out from under his skullcap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beneath the snow-splashed escarpments that protect northern Albania from the outside world and have left life much as it was centuries ago, the Sylaj family have been cooped up on their homestead for months, too afraid to move.</p>
        <p>A blood feud, following precepts laid down in a medieval canon, hangs over the men of the household, including the patriarch, Shaban Sylaj, 99, who welcomes visitors with a two-tooth grin, wisps of ash-colored hair poking out from under his skullcap.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sylaj's son, Chel, 38, shot and killed another Albanian man in January, and now the dead man's family have the right, under the still-flourishing code, to take revenge. Their target is one of the Sylaj men.</p>
        <p>The threat is real. Since the early 1990's, revenge killings have spread among the clans here, where the precepts of Lek Dukagjin, a 15th-century chieftain, prize honor and freedom above honesty, and where vengeance is the ruling passion.</p>
        <p>Weapons -- pistols in the old days, automatic assault rifles now -- are valued as much as human life: a man who kills another man and takes his weapon too can be avenged with the taking of two lives.</p>
        <p>''Who knows how many people have been killed through revenge?''  said Man Mulosmani, 64, a clan leader who is preaching reconciliation rather than retribution. ''Countless, countless. People don't want to report killings to the police because then the accused would be protected by the state in prison instead of being available to kill.''</p>
        <p>This closed corner of Europe was described by British spies who trekked here on mule and foot during World War II as the wildest physical -- and psychological -- terrain on the continent. It is still reached by a precipitous dirt road hacked out of the mountains and a jade-tinted lake that swerves through vertical limestone cliffs and stony land.</p>
        <p>For nearly 50 years, the world's most isolated Communist system superficially submerged the customs that decree an eye for an eye and keep women in the lowliest position. But as Enver Hoxha's Communism evaporated at the beginning of this decade, so did the temporary covering it provided for ingrained ways of living.</p>
        <p>When the Albanian police force and army disintegrated during civil strife last year and the arms depots stashed with assault rifles and mortars sprang open, revenge killings skyrocketed. With households heavily armed and escaped prisoners in possession of armories of weapons, the Tropoje region became off-limits for outsiders, even for Government officials from the capital, Tirana. The fact that the sparsely settled area is the stronghold of the former President, Sali Berisha, adds to the inability of the new Socialist Government to impose order.</p>
        <p>In some places, like the village of Dragobi, the instability of the past and the present are easy to see. The Ismaeli family's house, for example, has narrow slits in the limestone walls. They are ideal for aiming a gun at the outside world while providing protection against anyone who might want to attack, family members explained. In their living room, a hole in the wall covered by a sliding door once served as a hiding place for their grandfather's pistol. Now this is where the women keep their embroidery. Instead of a pistol, the family now keep assault rifles.</p>
        <p>As hard as Mr. Mulosmani, a retired agronomist with a shock of white hair, tries to mediate between feuding families, it is a difficult task. He spent a session cross-legged on the Sylajs' living room floor -- a manner borrowed from the Turks who dominated Albania until 1912 -- discussing ways to avert more bloodshed. He came away with no resolution.</p>
        <p>Intended to regulate medieval life, the Canon of Lek, as it is known, has been perverted by people to suit their own needs, Mr. Mulosmani said. Now, the lawless society floats between the ages-old customs and a state unable to adapt to modernity in the wake of Communism.</p>
        <p>For example, Fatmir Haklaj, 27, recently resigned as police chief of Tropojo to avenge a family murder and is reported by his former colleagues to have killed, or ordered the killing, of eight men so far for the murder of his brother. His brother was sprayed with nine bullets in January.</p>
        <p>The leader of one of the most powerful clans, Mr. Haklaj vowed that he would kill one man for every bullet pumped into his brother's body, his colleagues said. According to Mr. Haklaj's arithmetic, he has one killing to go.</p>
        <p>Last week the opposing Hoxe clan, which is accused of killing Mr. Haklaj's brother, were in mourning after burying a relative who they believe was the latest victim of Mr. Haklaj's revenge. The police have stood by, pleading powerlessness.</p>
        <p>The unchecked violence in the Tropoje district is combined with extreme poverty.</p>
        <p>The Communist-era hospital has been looted so often that robberies have subsided because there is nothing left to steal. International aid agencies are too frightened to come to help.</p>
        <p>Many families make do with one chicken a week made into broth and served with a plank of hard cornbread. There is no industry and only families who have men abroad -- often as illegal immigrants in Greece or Italy -- can make ends meet. Those families sometimes flaunt their flimsy foreign contact with pictures of Western starlets pinned to their walls.</p>
        <p>Such families usually spend the first remittances from abroad on a television set. But those wealthier families remain self-sufficient, living off the land, even down to the limestone rocks that are fashioned into bricks in outdoor kilns.</p>
        <p>The Ismaelis in Dragobi are one such family. Another is the family of Hatixhe Selimi, 42, a teacher in Valbone, a tiny settlement near the border with Kosovo.</p>
        <p>By necessity, Mrs. Selimi is a prudent homemaker. For her 12-year-old daughter, Aurela, and her 7-year-old niece, Viola, she uses milk from her cow, makes feta-style cheese and bakes bread from water and corn in a wood-burning oven. For guests, she serves potatoes and cabbage from her garden. She and her daughter dress in Western castoffs sold at outdoor markets and keep warm in socks hand-knitted from the wool of their sheep.</p>
        <p>When Lek conceived his canon in the mid-15th century, women were held in such low esteem that they were exempt from most feuds and were regarded as chattel to do a man's bidding. Today, women still back out of a door so as not to show disrespect to the men in the room.</p>
        <p>Under the Communists, Mrs. Selimi was allowed to choose her own husband. But such freedom was unusual even then and is getting rarer now. The old rules of arranged marriages are back in vogue, she said.</p>
        <p>Asked how the Canon of Lek affected women now, Mrs. Selimi rolled her eyes, held her breath and looked around her living room, where several male visitors were gathered.</p>
        <p>''Well, I suppose I'll tell you,'' she replied tentatively.</p>
        <p>Last year, she recounted, there was a marriage ceremony in Valbone. As usual, the wedding feast was strung out over several days. Suddenly the festivities stopped.</p>
        <p>The groom had discovered that his bride was not a virgin. He dispatched her back to her parents.</p>
        <p>Later, unable to bear the shame -- the worst kind of affliction in these stubborn highlands -- the young woman slipped away down the mountains to the anonymity of the lowlands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
