<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Get Last Laugh On McGrady</title>
    <meta content="04KNIC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/04/sports/basketball/04KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1532754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McGrady, Tracy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDF1F30F937A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Get Last Laugh On McGrady</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knicks Get Last Laugh on McGrady</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., Nov. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks defeat Orlando Magic, 75-68; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tracy McGrady might as well have laughed in his opponents' face. On Monday morning he said the Knicks were prone to folding, citing Orlando's overtime victory in the season opener.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks laughed last Monday night, holding on for their first victory of the season, 75-68, but it came with a measure of concern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlandos Tracy McGrady said that the Knicks were prone to folding. But the Knicks made McGrady eat his words, taking home their first victory of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tracy McGrady might as well have laughed in his opponents' face. On Monday morning he said the Knicks were prone to folding, citing Orlando's overtime victory in the season opener.</p>
        <p>But the Knicks laughed last Monday night, holding on for their first victory of the season, 75-68, but it came with a measure of concern.</p>
        <p>McGrady's words almost seemed prophetic in the third quarter when the Knicks' best player, Allan Houston, left the game with back spasms. The Knicks' 15-point lead dwindled to 2 points.</p>
        <p>With Houston in the locker room, Othella Harrington rescued the Knicks (1-2) by coming off the bench to score 8 points to begin the fourth quarter and Kurt Thomas made three straight timely blocks.</p>
        <p>Houston said that with treatment he hoped to play Wednesday at home against Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>''It was a great win, even though I wasn't out there, it was fun to watch,'' said Houston, who watched the remainder of the game from the locker room. The attendants left him alone, he said with a sardonic grin, ''so I could watch us not fold.''</p>
        <p>Houston, 32, has been slow to recover from off-season knee surgery and has not shown that he can withstand a grueling N.B.A. schedule. The right knee was not the problem -- although he said it might have made him compensate on a landing after a missed layup with 8 minutes 27 seconds to play in the third quarter. He left the court two minutes later with the Knicks ahead, 50-35. The Magic then went on its 17-4 run.</p>
        <p>''I felt something pull a little bit,'' he said. ''After that it kind of locked up on me.''</p>
        <p>''We felt like we let one slip away in Game 1, and we're definitely not going to let Orlando steal another one from us, especially after Tracy made his little comment,'' said Thomas, who finished with a game-high 11 rebounds and 5 of the Knicks' 10 blocks -- one more than they had in any game last season.</p>
        <p>The Knicks held McGrady to 19 points and 5-of-20 shooting and had the best defensive night in franchise history by holding the Magic to 25 percent shooting, a franchise-low Orlando (1-3) has dropped three straight since beating the Knicks.</p>
        <p>McGrady said in the season opener between the teams, the Knicks seemed vulnerable when they held a 10-point lead with less than four minutes to play, before losing in overtime.</p>
        <p>Houston said he was not surprised by McGrady's comment. ''That's what we did,'' he said. ''We didn't finish the game. We did it tonight.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks did it with defense on a night when Keith Van Horn shot 4 for 20. When Houston left the game, Chaney said he was ''a little concerned'' about the offense.</p>
        <p>Although the Magic came within 4 points with 6:15 to play on McGrady's free throws, Thomas swatted away any threat by blocking three shots in succession.</p>
        <p>Keith Van Horn, who started the game shooting 0 of 6, managed to score 14 points, the most crucial basket a dunk with 2:22 left to boost the lead back to 8 points.</p>
        <p>After McGrady then cut the deficit to 6 points on two free throws, Howard Eisley made a layup and McGrady missed a 3-pointer with 1:19 to play that sealed the Knicks' victory. McGrady did not see what he had just six nights earlier.</p>
        <p>When asked about the season opener and whether the Knicks might crumble, McGrady said Monday morning: ''We definitely have been in that situation with the Knicks before, I've realized that before. When you have a team where you feel like you close in on them during crunch time they're going to fold, and that's how I felt the night that we played the Knicks, that if we can somehow get this thing close, that they're going to fold.''</p>
        <p>McGrady was not remorseful about his comments after the game.</p>
        <p>''I don't regret what I said,'' McGrady said. ''We held them to 75 points. We couldn't make any shots tonight. We missed shots from close up. You could credit their defense and they beat us, I'll give them credit for that. But we beat ourselves tonight.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks' defense, a combination of zones and quick-closing double teams frustrated McGrady as it did throughout most of opening night. He was forced to pass and his teammates kept missing.</p>
        <p>Thomas and Dikembe Mutombo -- who had three blocks -- clogged the paint and stymied the Magic. But Thomas was everywhere making the difference.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>GRANT HILL said he is looking to return in ''January or February,'' from his fourth ankle surgery.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
