<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Court Rules Religious Clubs Can Meet in Public High Schools</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ORGANIZATIONS, SOCIETIES AND CLUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM OF RELIGION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OMAHA (NEB)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAYHEW, BRIDGET MERGENS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, SANDRA DAY (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, JOHN PAUL (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service"></object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EQUAL ACCESS LAW (1984)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nebraska/Omaha</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D81E30F936A35755C0A966958260" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Court Rules Religious Clubs Can Meet in Public High Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Supreme Court today upheld a 1984 Federal law that requires public high schools to allow students' religious and political clubs to meet on the same basis as other extracurricular activities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Supreme Court today upheld a 1984 Federal law that requires public high schools to allow students' religious and political clubs to meet on the same basis as other extracurricular activities.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court today upheld a 1984 Federal law that requires public high schools to allow students' religious and political clubs to meet on the same basis as other extracurricular activities.</p>
        <p>A high school need not permit any student activities not related to the curriculum, Justice Sandra Day O'Connor said in the opinion. But she said that if it does, the school is bound by the Equal Access Act not to discriminate against any student group on the basis of its religious, philosophical or political viewpoint.</p>
        <p>The decision, in a case from a public school district in Omaha, upheld a ruling last year by the United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, in St. Louis. A group of Omaha high school students led by Bridget Mergens Mayhew, then a senior at Westside High School, successfully sued the school district in 1985 after being denied official recognition for a Christian Bible club.</p>
        <p>Undercover Role Upheld</p>
        <p>In another decision today overturning an appellate ruling, the Court ruled that a law-enforcement officer can pose as a prison inmate and elicit a confession from an actual inmate even though the officer gives no Miranda warning about the inmate's constitutional rights. [Page A24.]  The Omaha case was the latest battle over the place of religion in the public schools, and today's decision could affect other cases.</p>
        <p>In Buffalo, a student Bible group won temporary permission from a judge to meet at a high school after school officials barred them. In Renton, Wash., the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit struck down the Equal Access Act on the basis of a 1989 appeal by high school students who wanted to start a Bible study club.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of schools waiting for this decision,'' said Virginia Roach, project director for the National Association of State Boards of Education.</p>
        <p>By a vote of 8-to-1, the Justices today rejected arguments that the Equal Access Act breached the constitutionally required separation between church and state. But the Court's constitutional analysis was splintered. Three separate opinions, none commanding a majority, supported the result. The eight Justices agreed, however, that the Federal law was not an unconstitutional ''establishment of religion'' by the Government.</p>
        <p>The only dissenter was Justice John Paul Stevens, who said the Court had interpreted the Federal law in a way that left too little discretion to local school districts.</p>
        <p>'Students Are Mature Enough'</p>
        <p>In essence, today's decision was an extension of a 1981 Supreme Court ruling, Widmar v. Vincent, in which the Court held that public universities had to permit student religious groups to meet on the same terms afforded other student organizations. That ruling suggested, without deciding, that the analysis might be different for younger, more impressionable students below the college level.</p>
        <p>In her opinion today, Justice O'Connor said: ''We think the logic of Widmar applies with equal force to the Equal Access Act. We think that secondary school students are mature enough and are likely to understand that a school does not endorse or support student speech that it merely permits on a nondiscriminatory basis.''</p>
        <p>She went on, ''There is a crucial difference between government speech endorsing religion, which the establishment clause forbids, and private speech endorsing religion, which the free speech and free exercise clauses protect.'' Those three clauses are in the First Amendment to the Constitution.</p>
        <p>The case, Westside Community Board of Education v. Mergens, No. 88-1597, was one of the more politically charged of the Court's term, now in its final month. The Equal Access Act was a long-sought goal of the religious right after the defeat of earlier efforts to bring prayer back to public school classrooms. The law was strongly supported in Congress by the Reagan Administration and in the Supreme Court by the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>Reaction to the Ruling</p>
        <p>Many friend-of-the-Court briefs were filed. A number of Jewish groups, including the American Jewish Congress, the American Jewish Committee and the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, urged the Court to strike down the law, as did the American Civil Liberties Union and People for the American Way. But a number of Protestant and Catholic groups filed briefs supporting the law.</p>
        <p>Burton S. Levinson, chairman of the Anti-Defamation League, said today that the ruling was ''troubling because it sanctions the use of public school facilities to advance religion in violation of the First Amendment.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mayhew, now 23 years old, told The Associated Press today that the decision sent a clear message to schools that they could not discriminate against religion. ''It's a source of strength to be able to share your faith and share what you believe,'' she said. ''I think it's a very important part of that age because you're a kid and you've got all these things coming at you.''</p>
        <p>Tying Activities to Curriculum</p>
        <p>The Equal Access Act applies to ''any public secondary school which receives Federal financial assistance and which has a limited open forum.'' Virtually all public schools receive some Federal money. Justice O'Connor noted that high schools could remove themselves from the law by refusing Federal money, although she added that ''this may be an unrealistic option.''</p>
        <p>The Act says that a school has a ''limited open forum'' if it permits at least one ''noncurriculum related'' student group to meet on the premises.</p>
        <p>The school district argued that all 30 of the student organizations at the high school, including the chess club and the scuba diving club, were related to the curriculum, and that the school was therefore not an open forum under the law.</p>
        <p>But the Court rejected this argument in a section of Justice O'Connor's opinion that five other Justices joined. She said that Congress meant ''to provide a low threshold for triggering the Act's requirements'' and that a school would be covered unless all student activities were tied directly to the curriculum. For example, she said, participation in a band or orchestra would be directly related to the curriculum if it resulted in academic credit.</p>
        <p>Clarifying School's Position</p>
        <p>In a separate concurring opinion, Justices Thurgood Marshall and William J. Brennan Jr. said that depending on the context, the majority's approach to the open forum question could pose a danger under the Establishment Clause.</p>
        <p>They said that schools that already permit organizations with distinct or controversial viewpoints could more readily absorb a religious club than a school in which only a few student clubs engaged in advocacy. In that situation, the two Justices said, the school ''must fully dissociate itself'' from a religious club to make clear that it was not sponsoring or endorsing the club's goals.</p>
        <p>Justice O'Connor's opinion was joined in full by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and by Justices Byron R. White and Harry A. Blackmun. Justices Anthony M. Kennedy and Antonin Scalia filed a separate concurring opinion in which they said that recognition of religious clubs was constitutional as long as no student was coerced to participate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
