<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Charges 2 in Shuttle Debris Theft, Citing Need to 'Make an Example'</title>
    <meta content="Y06DEB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/06/national/nationalspecial/06DEBR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="LOSS OF THE SHUTTLE: RECOVERY EFFORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Michael P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccool, William C (Cmdr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Husband, Rick D (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Laurel Salton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chawla, Kalpana (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, David M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettleman, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaudet, Bradley Justin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hipp, Merrie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DC173BF935A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Charges 2 in Shuttle Debris Theft, Citing Need to 'Make an Example'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Charges 2 in Shuttle Debris Theft to 'Make an Example'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gettleman, Jeffrey</byline>
      <dateline>NACOGDOCHES, Tex, Feb. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal agents in Texas arrest Bradley Justin Gaudet and Merrie Hipp, accusing them of stealing debris from space shuttle Columbia; photo; authorities continue to seek public cooperation in retrieval effort; map of confirmed reports of debris findings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal agents arrested two people in East Texas today and accused them of stealing debris from the space shuttle Columbia.</p>
        <p>The authorities said that Bradley Justin Gaudet, a 22-year-old college student, removed clumps of thermal coating from a soccer field and that Merrie Hipp, a 43-year-old owner of a fried chicken stand, posed as a NASA official and walked off with a circuit board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NACOGDOCHES, Tex, Feb. 5  Federal agents arrested two people in East Texas today and accused them of stealing debris from the space shuttle Columbia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal agents arrested two people in East Texas today and accused them of stealing debris from the space shuttle Columbia.</p>
        <p>The authorities said that Bradley Justin Gaudet, a 22-year-old college student, removed clumps of thermal coating from a soccer field and that Merrie Hipp, a 43-year-old owner of a fried chicken stand, posed as a NASA official and walked off with a circuit board.</p>
        <p>Since the first hours after the breakup, federal authorities have warned the public not to touch any part of the shuttle that fell off during its plunge through the atmosphere. If convicted, each suspect could face 10 years in prison and a $250,000 fine.</p>
        <p>As the charges were announced, United States attorneys in Texas said there would be a two-day grace period for people to turn in shuttle debris without facing prosecution.</p>
        <p>They asked the public to cooperate.</p>
        <p>''That thing you may be holding in you pocket, on your desk or on your mantel could be the single piece that saves the lives of future astronauts,'' said Michael T. Shelby, United States attorney for the Southern District of Texas. ''This isn't about prosecuting people. It's about trying to gather as much of the debris as we can to figure out what happened.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the laborious search for debris continued as the weather turned foul and sheets of rain, sleet and hail fell from a gray sky.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of police officers on horseback and on foot slogged through muddy forests locating, and retrieving pieces of wreckage.</p>
        <p>Among the top finds today were a harness, a shoe, more strips of clothing and a 700-pound rocket engine that drilled a 12-foot hole in the ground and sprayed dirt 35 feet in the air.</p>
        <p>Also retrieved was an eight-foot section that some speculated came from the shuttle's left wing, with dozens of thermal tiles and heat sensors.</p>
        <p>Mac Powell, an engineer who lives near Nacogdoches, said he had been waiting ''all day and all night'' for the authorities to retrieve the piece, which stuck out of his cow pasture like a javelin.</p>
        <p>''I missed work baby-sitting this thing,'' Mr. Powell said. ''Looked pretty important to me.''</p>
        <p>NASA officials, however, now say they do not believe damage to the left wing was the primary cause of the accident on Saturday that killed all seven astronauts on board.</p>
        <p>The hunt for body parts intensified today with the arrival of two Israeli experts, who, according to Israeli radio, helped recover the remains of Col. Ilan Ramon, the Israeli astronaut.</p>
        <p>''From earth he comes, to earth he comes back,'' said Yisroel Stefansky, one of the Israeli specialists working in Nacogdoches.</p>
        <p>Federal authorities said every piece of the wreckage was precious and that was why they cracked down on the two people accused of stealing government property.</p>
        <p>''We needed to make an example,'' said Matthew D. Orwig, United States attorney for the Eastern District of Texas.</p>
        <p>According to the authorities, Ms. Hipp, who lives in Henderson, Tex., an hour north of Nacogdoches, picked up a piece of a circuit board from the ground near downtown Nacogdoches. When bystanders asked what she was doing, they said, Ms. Hipp told them she was from NASA and drove away. Someone then took a picture of her car, and the police tracked her down through her license plate number.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how the authorities came to arrest the other suspect, Mr. Gaudet, a senior at Stephen F. Austin University in Nacogdoches and a member of the Reserve Officers Training Corps.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaudet's roommate, Derryl Dennis, said Mr. Gaudet and his girlfriend came home on Saturday with some ''white stuff'' a few hours after the shuttle broke up in the skies above Texas.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he was trying to do anything wrong,'' Mr. Dennis said. ''He just seemed all excited about it.''</p>
        <p>LOSS OF THE SHUTTLE: RECOVERY EFFORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
