<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Nets Star Settles Lawsuit With Dead Driver's Siblings</title>
    <meta content="06WILL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/06/nyregion/06WILL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alexandria Township (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hunterdon County (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Iver</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Jayson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christofi, Costas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christofi, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adams, Andrea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Jayson</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEEDA163BF935A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Nets Star Settles Lawsuit With Dead Driver's Siblings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Siblings of Limousine Driver Settle Suit With Ex-Nets Star</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVER PETERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Iver</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former basketball star Jayson Williams settles civil suit brught against him by Anthony Christofi and Andrea Adams, brother and sister of limousine driver Costas Christofi, whom he is accused of fatally shooting; terms of settlement are not disclosed; state appellate court agrees to hear Williams's motion to dismiss charges against him in criminal matter, move that delays Feb 18 start of his trial (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jayson Williams, the former basketball star, has settled a civil lawsuit brought against him by the brother and sister of the limousine driver he is accused of fatally shooting a year ago.</p>
        <p>Neither side would disclose the terms of the settlement, which has been reached even before the criminal case against Mr. Williams is resolved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jayson Williams has settled a civil lawsuit brought against him by the brother and sister of the man he is accused of fatally shooting a year ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jayson Williams, the former basketball star, has settled a civil lawsuit brought against him by the brother and sister of the limousine driver he is accused of fatally shooting a year ago.</p>
        <p>Neither side would disclose the terms of the settlement, which has been reached even before the criminal case against Mr. Williams is resolved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams, 34, a former New Jersey Nets star rebounder, has pleaded not guilty to aggravated manslaughter and obstruction of justice charges in the shooting of the driver, Costas Christofi, 55. He could face nearly 45 years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Williams's lawyers, William R. Martin and Joseph A. Hayden Jr., released copies of two letters, dated Jan. 31, exchanged by Mr. Williams and Mr. Christofi's brother and sister, Anthony Christofi and Andrea Adams. In his 12-line, typewritten letter, Mr. Williams said he prayed every day for forgiveness for the shooting, and begged the two to forgive him.</p>
        <p>''I know that I cannot begin to feel your pain, and I want to say that I am truly sorry for this unfortunate accident,'' Mr. Williams wrote. ''While I know the pain I feel cannot compare to yours, I will live my whole life with the thought that Mr. Gus Christofi is no longer with you.''</p>
        <p>In their three-sentence reply, Mr. Christofi and Ms. Adams spoke of Mr. Williams in the third person, saying, ''We are sure that he did not intend to hurt Gus and that he sincerely regrets what occurred.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Adams and Mr. Christofi filed a civil wrongful death suit in October, claiming that Mr. Williams had defamed their brother by trying to make his death look like a suicide, and demanding compensation to replace the support Mr. Christofi had been providing them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin and Mr. Hayden said that the civil case was settled so Mr. Williams could prepare for next month's appeal.</p>
        <p>Ken Berkowitz, the lawyer for Mr. Christofi and Ms. Adams, did not return a call requesting comment.</p>
        <p>Steven C. Lember, the former acting prosecutor for Hunterdon County, said today that the settlement of the civil suit ''had nothing to do'' with the criminal case.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a state appellate court agreed to hear Mr. Williams's motion that charges against him be dismissed, a move that delays the long-scheduled Feb. 18 start of his trial. The court has scheduled arguments for March 12.</p>
        <p>In his quest for a dismissal, Mr. Williams said the prosecutors had misled the grand jury about the accidental nature of the shooting.</p>
        <p>In their response to his motion, prosecutors said that Mr. Williams had been drunk and was verbally abusive toward the driver, who had driven a group, including several members of the Harlem Globetrotters, to the Williams estate in rural New Jersey last Feb. 14, after a night out that included a basketball game and dinner at a restaurant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams was showing off his prowess with a 12-gauge Browning rifle, the prosecutors charge, when he snapped the barrels shut and fired 12 buckshot pellets into Mr. Christofi's chest. Mr. Williams is also charged with witness tampering -- trying to have his guests portray the death as a possible suicide.</p>
        <p>In his letter to Ms. Adams and Mr. Christofi, Mr. Williams reiterated several times the sincerity of his remorse, reminding them that he had sent a handwritten letter last year and saying that his lawyers had prevented him from writing again.</p>
        <p>''I think they were concerned that the prosecutor and police may try to misinterpret this statement by manipulating it into something different than I intended,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>''It is my hope and prayer that over time you will find it in your heart to forgive me,'' he wrote in conclusion. ''My wife, Tanya, and I pray for your forgiveness every day of our lives. May God bless you and speed the healing process for you and your family.</p>
        <p>''With the utmost sincerity, Jayson Williams.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
