<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uneasy Bond Inside a Promised Land</title>
    <meta content="Y04RAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/04/international/africa/04RAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Shashemene Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rastafarianism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shashemene (Ethiopia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selassie, Haile (1892-1975)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Ethiopia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Selassie, Haile</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DF133CF937A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uneasy Bond Inside a Promised Land</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Uneasy Bond Inside a Promised Land</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>SHASHEMENE, Ethiopia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rastafarianism's true believers remain in Shashemene, Ethiopia, clinging to their beliefs that late Emperor Haile Selassie I is God and Ethiopia is their promised land; they are mostly from Caribbean but also from United States and Britain; their numbers have shrunk to about 500; their many problems with Ethiopians attest to uneasy relationship that often develops between Africans and non-African blacks seeking spiritual home there; mutual alienation is deep, because Rastafarians hold beliefs and engage in practices that are directly against those of most Ethiopians; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Welcome home to Ethiopia,'' read the banner over the Rastafarians' church compound. Several men in long dreadlocks were waving the movement's familiar green-yellow-red flags, an old man in a white robe was reciting biblical verses, another was sucking lustily on a footlong pipe that had transformed his nostrils into two hyperactive chimneys.</p>
        <p>The strong, strong whiff of marijuana hung in the air, making everybody oblivious to the chilly morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alienated from the local population, Ethiopia's Rastafarians see their land and numbers shrinking</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Welcome home to Ethiopia,'' read the banner over the Rastafarians' church compound. Several men in long dreadlocks were waving the movement's familiar green-yellow-red flags, an old man in a white robe was reciting biblical verses, another was sucking lustily on a footlong pipe that had transformed his nostrils into two hyperactive chimneys.</p>
        <p>The strong, strong whiff of marijuana hung in the air, making everybody oblivious to the chilly morning.</p>
        <p>''We've come to our ancient land! Ethiopia!'' sang a woman in a clear Jamaican lilt, her body swaying near a table on which stood framed portraits of the man she and the others considered God: Haile Selassie I, this country's last emperor, who was deposed in a 1974 Marxist coup and assassinated a year later.</p>
        <p>Outside the church gates, past the armed guards, local Ethiopians looked quizzically at the spectacle inside. Later, a Rastafarian parade to the town center drew similar skeptical puzzlement.</p>
        <p>''This is really foolishness and they have to stop,'' said Adane Giday, 26, a parade watcher. ''They are bad for Ethiopia. We have our own culture and we don't want to mix with them. What is their culture? Nothing. We see them as African brothers. But we do not see them as Ethiopians.''</p>
        <p>The Rastafarian movement, founded in Jamaica in the 1930's, would perhaps have faded into obscurity but for two things: the music of Bob Marley, the king of reggae and the most famous Rastafarian, and the land that Emperor Selassie granted its followers half a century ago in Shashemene, about 130 miles south of the capital, Addis Ababa.</p>
        <p>At one point, thousands of Rastafarians, mostly from the Caribbean but also from the United States and Britain, settled here. Nowadays, their land shrunk to 11 acres from 500, the Rastafarians have dwindled to about 500, though the population swelled for the celebration of Emperor Selassie's birthday on July 23.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the world, Rastafarianism may have become more of a lifestyle, one emphasizing hedonism, freedom and good music. But the true believers remain in Shashemene, clinging to their beliefs that the emperor is God and Ethiopia their promised land. They stay despite their many problems with Ethiopians, a fact that attests to the uneasy relationship that often develops between Africans and non-African blacks seeking a spiritual home here.</p>
        <p>The mutual alienation is deep, because the Rastafarians hold beliefs and engage in practices that are directly against those of most Ethiopians. So while the banner at their church proclaimed, ''Welcome home to Ethiopia,'' the Rastafarians forbade Ethiopians from coming inside; when one Ethiopian man was seen videotaping the ceremony, through the barbed wire, Rastafarians grabbed his tape.</p>
        <p>''The people here are very ignorant of who we are,'' said George Isles, 40, a Rastafarian who was born in the Caribbean and lived in London before arriving here in 1992.</p>
        <p>Like most Rastafarians, Mr. Isles, a carpenter, saw himself as Ethiopian and was angry that the locals did not. ''They call me faranji,'' he said, using Ethiopians' term for foreigners. ''The people don't treat us well. We give them work, but they still rob us. I have to have a guard at my house. If I don't, they would come and steal from me.''</p>
        <p>B. J. Moody, 65, a Rastafarian elder who has lived here since 1980, tried to soften Mr. Isles's words.</p>
        <p>''All of us are experiencing some sort of cruelty, some unbrotherly actions by our Ethiopians brothers,'' said Mr. Moody, a tiny man with the gentlest of voices. ''But we are determined to bring them to a higher state of consciousness.''</p>
        <p>This state of consciousness emerged when Marcus Garvey, a Jamaican who led the Back to Africa movement in the early 20th century, predicted -- in 1927 -- that a black king would rise and return members of the black diaspora to Africa.</p>
        <p>In 1930, when an Ethiopian prince named Ras Tafari was crowned emperor, the descendants of African slaves in Jamaica took that as confirmation that the day of deliverance had arrived. They called themselves Rastafarians and worshiped the emperor, who took the name Haile Selassie I, as God.</p>
        <p>The Rastafarians regarded Ethiopia as their ancestral home and called themselves Ethiopians, rejecting Jamaica and the West as Babylon. One reason that Ethiopia represented Zion to them was its status as an African country relatively untouched by colonialism.</p>
        <p>Emperor Selassie -- who was credited with modernizing Ethiopia -- was, like most Ethiopians, a member of Ethiopia's Orthodox Christian Church and did not consider himself divine. He was said to be embarrassed by the worship. But in the 1950's, partly in recognition of the support blacks outside Ethiopia had given Ethiopians in their fight against Fascist Italy, the emperor gave 500 acres of his own land here to black people living in the West.</p>
        <p>To hear Rastafarians tell it, the immigration here began only after Emperor Selassie's momentous visit to Jamaica in 1966. Back then, Mr. Moody was a grocer in Kingston.</p>
        <p>''Jamaica had been experiencing a drought for two years,'' Mr. Moody said, telling a story famous among Rastafarians. ''But upon His Majesty's arrival in Jamaica, no sooner had the Ethiopian Airlines carrier been focused on that part of the world, than there was a thunderbolt and rain. And just as soon did the rain subside and the sun appear -- the airplane landed and taxied on the airport -- most miraculously.''</p>
        <p>At their peak, the Rastafarians are said to have numbered 2,500. The Marxists who overthrew Emperor Selassie tried to blot out all imperial symbols but allowed the Rastafarians to stay -- although the community lost most of its land.</p>
        <p>Life became easier after the end of Marxist rule in 1991, the Rastafarians here said. But Caribbean immigrants must get resident and working visas like other foreigners.</p>
        <p>Many Ethiopians find the worship of their former emperor as a deity a little odd.</p>
        <p>Negussi Assfaw, 24, had come down from Addis Ababa for the week's celebrations. An Ethiopian, he wore a Rastafarian T-shirt and said he liked Rastafarians because of their clothes and music.</p>
        <p>''They say he's the God of all black men,'' Mr. Assfaw said, speaking of the emperor. ''Haile Selassie was a very, very powerful man, a king. But he's a man, like me, like you.''</p>
        <p>To many Ethiopians in Shashemene, the Rastafarians are guests who have overstayed their welcome. Kasib Burka, 28, a businessman, said the first Rastafarians were motivated by idealism and often helped the Ethiopians here, handing out free medicine. Today, he said, they cared only about enriching themselves, and he pointed out that several hundred Rastafarians did not even live here, but simply owned and exploited the land, visiting twice or three times a year and selling medicine.</p>
        <p>The 109th birthday of Emperor Selassie went unobserved by most Ethiopians. ''There is no salvation for this generation of Ethiopians because they have rejected His Majesty,'' Mr. Isles said.</p>
        <p>More Rastafarians will eventually come to Shashemene -- Mr. Isles was sure of it -- and they will help save the very people who had been supposed to save them.</p>
        <p>''Those Rastafarians,'' he said,  ''are just getting what they can out of Babylon before coming home here.''</p>
        <p>Shashemene Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
