<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Near Zurich, Art and Industry</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="632682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SWITZERLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WINTERTHUR (SWITZERLAND)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WINTERTHUR (MUSEUM)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFMANN, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DU PONT FAMILY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIDERMANN, JAMES ANTOIONE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DE173BF936A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Near Zurich, Art and Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL HOFMANN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOFMANN, PAUL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAY "Winterthur," and many Americans will think of the du Pont mansion in Delaware with its recently enlarged museum of Americana. Wall Street types instead may perceive a reference to Winterthur Insurance, a financial giant.</p>
        <p>The du Pont estate and the insurance company both derive their names from a thriving industrial city -- today also a trove of fine art -- just 12 miles northeast of Zurich. James Antoine Bidermann, who married into the du Pont clan and in 1839 built himself the chateau-like residence in Delaware's Brandywine Valley, called it after his native town in Switzerland. And the concern that covers risks in many parts of the world has its headquarters in the Swiss Winterthur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAY "Winterthur," and many Americans will think of the du Pont mansion in Delaware with its recently enlarged museum of Americana. Wall Street types instead may perceive a reference to Winterthur Insurance, a financial giant.</p>
        <p>The du Pont estate and the insurance company both derive their names from a thriving industrial city -- today also a trove of fine art -- just 12 miles northeast of Zurich. James Antoine Bidermann, who married into the du Pont clan and in 1839 built himself the chateau-like residence in Delaware's Brandywine Valley, called it after his native town in Switzerland. And the concern that covers risks in many parts of the world has its headquarters in the Swiss Winterthur.</p>
        <p>Visitors to Zurich shouldn't be deterred from making a quick trip of a few hours to Winterthur by its role as Switzerland's most industrialized city.</p>
        <p>It recommends itself not only by its celebrated art collections but also by pretty neighborhoods nestling in a rolling countryside, by plenty of greenery and by stately public buildings. Although so close to Switzerland's biggest city, Winterthur isn't a satellite of Zurich. It has over the centuries managed to retain an urban and cultural identity of its own.</p>
        <p>Actually there are three Winterthurs. A quaint, ancient core is surrounded by museums, a theater, other imposing edifices, gardens and villas that speak of considerable wealth and civic pride. All this is nourished by a vast manufacturing area. It is so varied that the city has signposted a special itinerary for visitors who are interested in industrial archeology, history and architecture.</p>
        <p>No fewer than seven railroad lines converge on Winterthur. Before the quadruple tracks from Zurich reach its monumental rail station, the traveler sees to the left the sprawling Sulzer plant, which builds locomotives and other machinery. Nearby are diverse engineering enterprises, textile mills and state-of-the-art print shops.</p>
        <p>International art connoisseurs head straight for the Oskar Reinhart Collection in Romerholz, a mansion on the city's northern outskirts, to see its Daumiers, its Impressionists and its other treasures. Romerholz translates as Romans' Forest. There are also a Roman Street and a Roman Gate elsewhere in the city. Winterthur traces itself back to a fortress that the Romans erected in A.D. 294; they called it Vitudurum, incorporating a Celtic word for "water" -- the nearby Toss River, a tributary of the Rhine.</p>
        <p>Just before World War I a member of the factory-owning Sulzer family commissioned the renowned architect Maurice Turrettini of Geneva to build him a villa on the Romerholz slope. The collector Oskar Reinhart (1885-1965) bought the property in 1924, had annexes built, and filled the residence with works of art, which he assembled over many years.</p>
        <p>Reinhart was the youngest son of the chief of a big Winterthur merchant company who himself was a patron of artists. After a few years' service in the family business with its global involvements, Oskar Reinhart, backed by his father, made it his full-time job to acquire paintings and drawings from the 15th to the 19th centuries, focusing on French Impressionist, 19th-century Romantic and Renaissance works. He traveled widely and kept in touch with many artists and dealers.</p>
        <p>In 1958 the younger Reinhart, who never married, donated the Romerholz property with its furniture, library and all pictures and sculptures to the Swiss Confederation. Under the terms of his agreement with the Government in Bern none of the works of art may be sold or allowed to leave the mansion on temporary loan. To see any of the 179 objects of the Oskar Reinhart Collection you have to go to Winterthur.</p>
        <p>The Romerholz villa, in a garden, is a U-shaped two-story building in late Art Nouveau style with dormer windows on top. A gallery and a few other ground-floor rooms were added by Reinhart to provide additional exhibition space.</p>
        <p>From the lobby the visitor reaches the so-called Renaissance Room containing Venetian, German and Flemish works. Portraits by Tintoretto, Lucas Cranach the Elder and Hans Holbein the Younger hang side by side with the drawing of a grieving woman by Mathias Grunewald, a study for his powerful Isenheim altarpiece (now at Colmar in the French Alsace).</p>
        <p>A PASSAGE where Reinhart kept indoor plants leads to a chamber in which 19 drawings and paintings by the French 19th-century satirist Honore Daumier are on display. Among them are famous representations of lawyers and physicians in the self-important exercise of their professions, and of dazed third-class travelers in early railroad cars.</p>
        <p>The large, rectangular main gallery, with a crystal chandelier, and some side rooms contain a wealth of works ranging from El Greco's chilling portrait of the Cardinal-Inquisitor Don Fernando Nino de Guevara (circa 1600) to pencil sketches by Picasso (1919). Most of the paintings shown are by French artists: Watteau, David, Ingres, Delacroix, Courbet, Corot and the great names of the Impressionist and Post-Impressionist movements -- Manet, Monet, Degas, Renoir, Pissarro, Toulouse-Lautrec and Cezanne.</p>
        <p>One of the six Goyas in the collection is an unfinished portrait, the last picture painted by the 82-year-old Spanish master before his death in Bordeaux in 1828. Other outstanding items are landscapes by Constable (a Hampstead Heath) and Alfred Sisley; a luminous "Garden of the Hospital at Arles" by van Gogh, and bronzes by Rodin.</p>
        <p>Some of the exhibits are so impressive that one may want to go back to them for prolonged contemplation, maybe after having a cup of tea or coffee. The pleasant snack bar with small, round, beige-covered tables looks out on the mansion's garden and on the city of Winterthur below.</p>
        <p>The Romerholz villa holds only a portion of the art that Reinhart had amassed. To see the rest, the visitor would normally return to the city center. There, at 6 Stadthausstrasse, is the Oskar Reinhart Foundation, a dignified 150-year-old former high school that houses more than 600 paintings and sculptures that the civic-minded collector donated to the City of Winterthur.</p>
        <p>The building is now closed for renovation, and until its reopening, on Feb. 28, 1995, a collection of more than 100 of its works is on tour. The exhibition is now in Berlin, and will be shown at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art from Oct. 3 through Jan. 2, and at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York from Feb. 10 through April 24 before moving on to the National Gallery in London and to Geneva.</p>
        <p>The Oskar Reinhart Foundation collection is a grand parade of Swiss, German and Austrian art of the 18th to the 20th centuries. Landscapes, portraits and genre pictures by Moritz von Schwind, who was Schubert's close friend, Ferdinand Georg Waldmuller and other masters of the Romantic school and Biedermeier era are remarkable.</p>
        <p>Near the Oskar Reinhart Foundation, on Museumsstrasse, is the Fine Arts Museum, a neo-classical structure not unlike the columned Stadthaus, or Municipal Building, diagonally across an intersection. This civic museum is devoted mainly to Swiss, German and Austrian art of the 18th to the 20th centuries, but one of its prizes is van Gogh's "Summer Evening at Arles." It too owns a few Hodlers (including a portrait of the poet Rainer Maria Rilke), and works by Giovanni Giacometti (father of Alberto and Diego), Paul Klee and Oskar Kokoschka.</p>
        <p>With so much art to view, the visitor may hardly find the time for a stroll around the inner city. It's worthwhile, though. The proud public buildings and well-tended gardens on the sites of long-razed fortifications encircle a picturesque Old Town, which is closed to motor traffic. The central Marktgasse (Market Street) is bordered by old houses with gaudy facades and some with bow windows -- look at Nos. 15, 22, 30 and 40, which still look more or less as they did when they were built. The Town Hall, at No. 20, is from the late 18th century, in the sober lines of the classical revival movement, with a popular cafe on the street floor. An outdoor fruit and vegetable market on Tuesday and Friday and a flea market held on the second and last Saturday of the month always attract crowds to the heart of the city.</p>
        <p>The twin-tower Parish Church of St. Laurent, which is Reformed Protestant, goes back to the 12th century, has an early-Gothic choir and a late-Gothic beamed nave, and was partially rebuilt in the Baroque fashion during the 17th century.</p>
        <p>The industrial areas are on the outskirts. Some executives arriving at Zurich's international airport at Kloten immediately turn east to Winterthur, only a 10-minute car ride distant, to hold their business talks before returning to Zurich, with its fine hotels and night life. There is plenty of commuting between the two neighboring cities every day.</p>
        <p>I have nevertheless heard Zurichers say they had never been to Winterthur in the same tone as some Manhattanites will tell you they have never set foot in Brooklyn. Yet it was a smart move when Zurich bought what has become the rich industrial town of Winterthur from the House of Hapsburg for 10,000 guilders 525 years ago. VISITOR'S GUIDE TO THE TOWN Getting There</p>
        <p>Trains for Winterthur depart from Zurich's main railroad terminal (Hauptbahnhof) about every 20 minutes. Frequent trains run to Winterthur also from Zurich's Kloten Airport. The Zurich-Winterthur rail trip takes 20 to 26 minutes, depending on the type of train.</p>
        <p>The round-trip fare is $12.40 in second class, $19.85 in first, calculated at a rate of 1.45 Swiss francs to $1. Art Collections</p>
        <p>Oskar Reinhart Collection am Romerholz, 95 Haldenstrasse; telephone 213-41-21. Take No. 10 bus from the Winterthur railroad station to the Haldengut stop, or No. 3 bus to the Spital stop, and walk uphill about a third of a mile. The Romerholz mansion can be reached on foot in 30 to 40 minutes, turning north (left) on stepping out of the railroad station, walking the length of Theaterstrasse, turning left on Lindstrasse and, after the railroad overpass, looking for Romerholz markings. The collection is accessible 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Tuesday to Sunday.</p>
        <p>Admission: $2.05, children and students, 70 cents.</p>
        <p>Fine Arts Museum (Kunstmuseum), 52 Museumstrasse; 267-51-62. No. 3 bus to the Stadthaus stop, or a walk of less than 10 minutes on Stadthausstrasse and Lindstrasse. Open Tuesday from 10 A.M. to 8 P.M., Wednesday to Sunday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>Admission is free except during special exhibitions. Hotels</p>
        <p>Garten Hotel, 4 Stadthausstrasse; 212-19-19, fax 213-68-70, in a park close to the city center, is comfortable and quiet, with Belle Epoque decor downstairs and modernly equipped rooms. Its French-oriented restaurant La Jardiniere has a terrace. A double with bath and breakfast costs $152.</p>
        <p>Romertor, 6 Guggenbuhlstrasse, off Romerstrasse; 242-69-21, fax 242 24-89, in the city's northeast, has a popular restaurant, a snack bar and bowling alleys. Doubles with bath and breakfast, $96. Restaurants</p>
        <p>The cuisine of Winterthur is like Zurich's, with an accent on minced and creamed veal (Geschnetzeltes), and roast potatoes (Rosti), fresh water fish, bratwurst and innards. Rathaus, 20 Marktgasse, 213-47-25, is a restaurant and cafe in the old Town Hall. A full lunch for two with local beer or wine will be around $60. Closed Sunday. Arcade, 20 Stadthausstrasse, 212-49-34, is near the museums. Coffee is $2, cake $3.25, snacks $4.15 to $10.35. Pizzeria Santa Lucia, 12 Bahnhofplatz, 213-54-44, opposite the railroad station, offers pizzas from $8.15 to $10.90. Information</p>
        <p>Winterthur Tourist Office, 12 Bahnhofplatz, CH-8401 Winterthur, 212-00-72, fax 212-24-35. For calls from outside Switzerland the country and city codes are 41-52; for long-distance calls within Switzerland, Winterthur's city code is 052.</p>
        <p>PAUL HOFMANN is the author of "Switzerland, the Smart Traveler's Guide to Zurich, Basel and Geneva," to be published soon by Holt &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">PAUL HOFMANN is the author of "Switzerland, the Smart Traveler's Guide to Zurich, Basel and Geneva," to be published soon by Holt &amp; Company.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
