<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reclaiming Homes, Iraqis Find Peril Still at Door</title>
    <meta content="23return" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/23/world/middleeast/23return.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DC1530F930A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reclaiming Homes, Iraqis Find Peril Still at Door</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reclaiming Homes, Iraqis Find Peril</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, March 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraqis who fled their Baghdad neighborhoods because of soaring sectarian violence are returning, only to find that threat of violence remains very real; Prime Min Nuri Kamal al-Maliki has made resettlement of displaced people primary goal of latest Baghdad security plan; he vows to use force to uproot squatters who have seized abandoned houses and even offered financial incentives to displaced families who want to return; government claims 2,000 families have returned to Baghdad, but figure is suspect and does not account for those who have returned only to leave again; rumors have circulated that some people who returned have been killed by resurgent militants; nearly all displaced families have decided to remain where they are until conditions improve, crammed into relatives' homes, rental apartments and shelters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Hazim Said and his family returned to their house in southwestern Baghdad on March 1, two months after fleeing a murder and intimidation campaign by Sunni Arab insurgents, Mr. Said's wife and two sons collapsed to the floor in tears of joy and kissed the walls.</p>
        <p>It mattered little that insurgents had looted the house of computers and other electronics and used it as a hide-out, or that most of the neighbors had taken flight and not returned, leaving their block empty and forlorn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As families begin to return to the Baghdad neighborhoods they fled, the threat of sectarian violence remains very real.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Hazim Said and his family returned to their house in southwestern Baghdad on March 1, two months after fleeing a murder and intimidation campaign by Sunni Arab insurgents, Mr. Said's wife and two sons collapsed to the floor in tears of joy and kissed the walls.</p>
        <p>It mattered little that insurgents had looted the house of computers and other electronics and used it as a hide-out, or that most of the neighbors had taken flight and not returned, leaving their block empty and forlorn.</p>
        <p>They had their home back. ''The only thing I have is this house,'' explained Mr. Said, a 35-year-old Shiite minibus driver from Baghdad's Amil neighborhood, which for months has been a battleground between sectarian militias. ''Without this house, I have nothing. That's the only way I can express it to you.''</p>
        <p>Under the protective cover of the latest Baghdad security plan, begun Feb. 13 and dependent on the infusion of American troops into the capital, a small number of families who had fled their neighborhoods because of soaring sectarian violence are hesitantly returning and trying to reclaim their lives. Many are finding, however, that the threat of violence that drove them away in the first place remains very real.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki has made the resettlement of displaced people a primary goal of the new security plan. He has vowed to use force to uproot squatters who have seized abandoned houses and has even offered a financial incentive to displaced families who want to return: a payment of about $200, a hefty sum in this impoverished economy, to help cover moving costs and the replacement of lost, stolen or damaged belongings.</p>
        <p>It is an ambitious program, one that seeks to reverse the tide of sectarian cleansing that has driven a wedge between Sunni Arabs and Shiites, cleaved entire neighborhoods and torn families from their moorings.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi government said last week that about 2,000 families had returned to their homes in Baghdad since the security plan was put in place, many in neighborhoods that had experienced some of the worst sectarian cleansing.</p>
        <p>Though hundreds of thousands of Baghdad residents remain displaced, officials say the steady flow of people returning is an indication that the security plan could eventually work.</p>
        <p>''We can't expect this to happen overnight,'' Brig. Gen. Qasim al-Moussawi, Mr. Maliki's spokesman for the plan, said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>But the government's figure of 2,000 is open to question. There has been no rigorous and systematic resettlement survey, so the number is based largely on anecdotal evidence from Iraqi security forces posted at checkpoints. The figure does not appear to account for the families who have returned home only to leave again. But it also seems to omit families who have slipped under the government's radar to avoid unwanted attention, particularly from sectarian death squads.</p>
        <p>What is certain, however, is that nearly all displaced families have decided to remain where they are until conditions improve, crammed into relatives' homes, rental apartments and shelters. In the Shiite neighborhood of Baladiyat, four extended families have sought refuge in an abandoned Sunni mosque. Of the 10 people in one of those families, that of 50-year-old Karima Abid, only one has a job. ''I am in a miserable situation,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Rumors have circulated for weeks that some people who returned have been killed by resurgent militants, so few people seem willing to take the chance. Indeed, the return has been so fraught and perilous that all the displaced persons who spoke with The New York Times did so on the condition that they be interviewed only by telephone or away from their neighborhoods. Nearly all refused to allow their full names to be printed.</p>
        <p>They told of a deep pull that is often less about real security improvements and more about an aching desire to be home. For every hopeful tale there are several more of woe. Last November, Umm Maher, a 67-year-old Sunni widow, fled Amil when Shiite militiamen began to burn down Sunni homes. For three and a half months she, her daughter and two teenage granddaughters moved from relative's house to relative's house.</p>
        <p>Last month, she started hearing from friends that the neighborhood had calmed down under the new security plan. She also saw news broadcasts of military officials trotting out statistics that appeared to reflect the early successes of the program. She was tired and wanted to go home.</p>
        <p>''I had the feeling that everything was going to get stable,'' she said in a telephone interview. (Umm Maher is an honorific; she did not want her full name published out of concern for her safety.) On March 5, she drove to her house and found it in good shape. The block was eerily quiet, and most houses remained empty. But she was comforted by the sight of Iraqi soldiers and police officers posted at checkpoints in the area and American soldiers on patrol.</p>
        <p>She tidied the house in preparation for her family's homecoming, and two days later she returned with her son and a car full of their belongings; her daughter and granddaughters were planning to arrive later. As they pulled up to the house, they saw a chilling message scrawled in red paint on the front wall: ''Residents of this house, your blood is wanted. Leave.''</p>
        <p>''When I saw the handwriting on the wall, I became very scared and started to shake,'' she recalled. She decided to move back in with a niece in the Jihad neighborhood, where she remains with her family.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what to do now,'' she said, desperation in her voice. ''I'm just crying and beating myself because I don't have any plans.''</p>
        <p>Abu Hassan, a 35-year-old Sunni taxi driver, returned to his house in Amil earlier this month. He planned to move his extended family back from a rental apartment but he, too, found a message painted on his wall: ''This house belongs to terrorists and as soon as they return, we will kill them.'' As he was taking pictures of the graffito with his cellphone camera, he said, he came under fire from a sniper and fled.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Abu Hassan's brother stopped by the house with his fiancée to check on the property, and a sniper opened fire on them, too, killing the fiancée. She was 19. The shooting happened within view of a checkpoint operated by Iraqi security forces, according to Abu Hassan, who provided only his nickname for publication.</p>
        <p>Abu Ali, a neighbor of Abu Hassan, whose family is one of only three Sunni families that have remained on that block, said residents had lost faith in the ability of the Iraqi security forces, which they see as incompetent and biased in favor of Shiites, and trust only the American forces.</p>
        <p>''I feel so lonely in this place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the chaos of conflict, the number of displaced people in Iraq is incalculable, and estimates by Iraqi and international officials vary.</p>
        <p>According to the Ministry of Displacement and Migration, about 470,000 displaced people have officially registered with the government since the fall of Saddam Hussein, though that figure is almost certainly an undercount. Meanwhile, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees estimates that nearly 500,000 of Iraq's 26 million people were displaced within Iraq in 2006 alone.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Maliki and his military commanders are eager to show gains in this war, officials on the front lines of the displacement crisis are privately urging caution to families thinking about returning home.</p>
        <p>Tufan Abdul Wahab al-Harbi, 38, director of the migration ministry's Baghdad bureau, said he refused to advise displaced people whether they should return home. ''We could be the reason behind the killing of a family,'' said Mr. Harbi, who has been living and working in Baghdad since he and his family were displaced from their home in Baquba, north of the capital, six months ago. ''It's not a normal situation.''</p>
        <p>Some humanitarian officials have suggested that it might be a better strategy for the government to help displaced people build new lives where they are now, rather than trying to send them home.</p>
        <p>Yet, for many of the displaced, the tug of home will not be so easily reconciled.</p>
        <p>''These families live in hell,'' Mr. Harbi said during an interview in his small office in eastern Baghdad. ''Each moment they experience is a tragedy for them. So as soon as it's safe, they will go back.''</p>
        <p>Those who have returned to their homes and stayed say that while they feel safer than they did before they left, the difference is small and, they fear, fleeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Said, the minibus driver, said he realized that in this war, death came easily, and that his decision to return to Amil had as much to do with force of will as with better security. His family is among only a few who have returned to his block, and he senses enemies lurking in the shadows. As far as he knows, the insurgents who beheaded two of his neighbors and kidnapped and killed others remain at large.</p>
        <p>He has stopped driving his bus. Instead, he is supporting his family on an army pension, sleeping by day and, by night, standing guard on his rooftop with a Kalashnikov.</p>
        <p>''I always think I'm going to be a victim,'' Mr. Said said during an interview at a relative's workplace on the other side of Baghdad; for security reasons he did not want a foreign journalist to visit him at home. He spoke softly and with little emotion, though his dark eyes, which were subtly scanning his surroundings, betrayed a deep intensity and suspicion.</p>
        <p>''Even now,'' he continued, ''I expect I'll be killed by them.''</p>
        <p>But he vowed not to move his family again.</p>
        <p>''When we returned home,'' he said, ''my wife was crying and saying, 'We better die here than leave this home.' '' And if the insurgents come again with their weapons and threats?</p>
        <p>''I will fight.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
