<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Culture Of Intoxication' And a Victim</title>
    <meta content="23anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/23/sports/football/23anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD1530F930A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Culture Of Intoxication' And a Victim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Culture of Intoxication’ and a Victim</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFFSIDE PARK, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nine-year-old Antonia Verni was home from school, her dark eyes sparkling, her voice bubbling like that of any other third-grader.</p>
        <p>''I love school,'' she said Wednesday afternoon in her turreted home on a quiet street in this northern New Jersey town. ''When we had a snow day, I cried. I don't want school to be canceled. I'm the top of the class in math, the top of the class in the times tables.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In October 1999, 9-year-old Antonia Verni was paralyzed in an accident involving a football fan who drank 14 beers at Giants Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nine-year-old Antonia Verni was home from school, her dark eyes sparkling, her voice bubbling like that of any other third-grader.</p>
        <p>''I love school,'' she said Wednesday afternoon in her turreted home on a quiet street in this northern New Jersey town. ''When we had a snow day, I cried. I don't want school to be canceled. I'm the top of the class in math, the top of the class in the times tables.''</p>
        <p>But Antonia is not like any other third-grader.</p>
        <p>As happy and as talkative as she was, her head rested on a pillow in her wheelchair, her arms and legs limp in her pink pajamas. Antonia is a quadriplegic. Her body was hooked up to a ventilator and to a computer flashing her heart rate and oxygen flow. Suddenly her mother, Fazila Baksh-Verni, and her day nurse, Nadine Ferrigno, noticed her wince slightly.</p>
        <p>''She's relaxing her muscles now to break her spasm,'' her mother said. ''Her spirit keeps you going. In her mind, she's just as normal as any other child. She feels she can do everything. She works her computer in school with voice recognition. She sings. She wants to be on 'American Idol.' She never complains. And she has no memory of the accident. She never asked about it.''</p>
        <p>As Nadine comforted Antonia, Fazila, who is with her through the night, sighed.</p>
        <p>''You have to be her hand, her foot,'' Fazila said softly. ''You have to be her everything.''</p>
        <p>Antonia's everything changed in that accident when she was 2 years, 4 months and 3 days old.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 24, 1999, Daniel Lanzaro, a carpenter from Cresskill, N.J., who had attended a game at Giants Stadium, veered across a double-yellow line while driving his pickup truck and slammed head-on into a rented Toyota Corolla driven by Antonia's father, Ron Verni, in Hasbrouck Heights, N.J. The Vernis were returning from a Halloween pumpkin-picking trip to eastern Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Antonia sustained a broken neck and was paralyzed. She spent nearly a year in a hospital and in rehabilitation. Her mother fell into a coma, then needed a metal rod inserted in her right leg and reconstructive facial surgery. Her father was not injured.</p>
        <p>Lanzaro's blood-alcohol level, according to the police report, was 0.266, more than three times the legal limit, 0.08. The father of two children, Lanzaro acknowledged that he had been drinking beer before entering the stadium, during the Giants' 31-3 victory against the New Orleans Saints that day and later at a nearby strip club before the accident. He pleaded guilty to vehicular assault and is serving a five-year prison sentence.</p>
        <p>The Vernis sued Aramark, the company that operates concessions at Giants Stadium as well as at more than 350 sports sites on three continents. When a jury awarded the Vernis $105 million in damages on Jan. 19, 2005, Aramark appealed. Last Aug. 3, a three-judge state appeals court panel ordered a new trial. The panel said that the evidence presented by the Vernis's lawyers to prove a ''culture of intoxication'' at Giants Stadium should not have been admitted.</p>
        <p>The new trial is scheduled to begin July 23 in Superior Court in Hackensack, N.J. A spokeswoman for Aramark, Kristine Grow, said in a telephone interview from company headquarters in Philadelphia, ''Our hearts and our thoughts continue to be with Antonia Verni and her family.''But if you -- yes, you who are reading this -- ever saw a drunken fan served alcohol at Giants Stadium during a Giants or a Jets game, you may be Antonia's everything. Perhaps you already noticed the advertisement that her lawyer, David A. Mazie, of Roseland, N.J., placed in the sports section of The Record of Hackensack last Sunday and plans to place in other New York-area newspapers:</p>
        <p>''Giants/Jets Fans. Have you seen drunk fans served alcohol at the stadium? If, so, we need your help in a lawsuit in which a two-year-old girl was paralyzed by a drunk driver after he left the stadium.''</p>
        <p>For the new trial, Antonia's lawyers are seeking witnesses, especially current or former Aramark employees, who will testify to having seen Aramark vendors selling alcohol to visibly intoxicated customers at Giants Stadium during Giants or Jets games. By order of the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority, alcohol sales there must end three minutes into the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Antonia's medical expenses are being met by insurance and financial settlements, including $200,000 in insurance money from Lanzaro, but Mazie estimated that her lifetime care would cost $75 million. And every day she remains in her wheelchair, with tubes in her body, in what was once the Vernis's family room but is now really a hospital room. In another room, her 5-year-old brother, Jibrael, watched cartoons while she stared at an ''American Idol'' recording on a flat-screen television.</p>
        <p>''Could you sing in front of all those people?'' Fazila asked.</p>
        <p>Antonia said with a laugh, ''If I get the stage fright out of me.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
