<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cosby Embraces Dignity, Then Laughter</title>
    <meta content="28COSB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mifflin, Lawrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cosby, Ennis William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cosby, Camille</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Autumn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Shawn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4DD113AF93BA15752C0A961958260" item-length="1351" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cosby Embraces Dignity, Then Laughter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRIE MIFFLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mifflin, Lawrie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Cosby, in interview with CBS newsman Dan Rather, speaks of his family's anguish at murder of his son, Ennis, and says that he and his wife want to be able to grieve with dignity; also admits to having brief affair 20-some years ago with Shawn Thompson, whose daughter, Autumn Jackson, claimed last week that Cosby was her father; tells Rather that he is sure that he is not the father of Jackson, who was indicted on extortion charges last week after she demanded $24 million for not taking her story to tabloid newspapers; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a two-and-a-half hour interview with Dan Rather, his first since the killing of his son, Ennis, Bill Cosby spoke of his family's anguish and said that he and his wife wanted to be able to grieve with dignity.</p>
        <p>The interview took place on Sunday, the day after Mr. Cosby returned to New York City from his family's home in western Massachusetts, and one day before he was to resume taping of his CBS sitcom ''Cosby.'' Parts of the interview were broadcast on Sunday night and yesterday morning; the network's highest-rated news program, ''60 Minutes,'' will carry a longer segment on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a two-and-a-half hour interview with Dan Rather, his first since the killing of his son, Ennis, Bill Cosby spoke of his family's anguish and said that he and his wife wanted to be able to grieve with dignity.</p>
        <p>The interview took place on Sunday, the day after Mr. Cosby returned to New York City from his family's home in western Massachusetts, and one day before he was to resume taping of his CBS sitcom ''Cosby.'' Parts of the interview were broadcast on Sunday night and yesterday morning; the network's highest-rated news program, ''60 Minutes,'' will carry a longer segment on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby described his son's burial last week, in an herb garden on the property. He said 10 or 11 friends and family members joined hands and carried the coffin down a snowy hill, ''and I set the coffin down over the hole, and I said, we now want to give praise to God for allowing us to know him -- not for giving him to us, but just letting us know him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rather said Mr. Cosby talked repeatedly of his desire to see his family's tragedy, and his son's memory, treated with dignity.</p>
        <p>''He must have used that word two dozen times or more,'' Mr. Rather said. ''This man is hurting. He is really hurting. But he is determined to get past it, and it would be impossible to overstate his determination that he and his family be able to grieve with dignity, in keeping with his son's memory.''</p>
        <p>The interview between CBS's leading entertainer and its leading newsman took place in Mr. Cosby's office at Kaufman Astoria Studios in Queens. In it, Mr. Cosby also admitted to having had a brief affair 20-some years ago with a woman whose daughter claimed last week that Mr. Cosby was her father.</p>
        <p>He told Mr. Rather that he was sure he was not the father of the woman, Autumn Jackson, who was indicted on extortion charges last week after she demanded $24 million for not taking her story to tabloid newspapers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby also spoke about his wife's grief, his acquaintance with the friend of Ennis Cosby who may have seen the shooting on Jan. 16, his confidence in the Los Angeles Police Department and his reasons for returning to work on ''Cosby,'' his Monday night sitcom, which began last fall.</p>
        <p>The interview was initiated by Mr. Cosby, who called CBS News, which contacted Mr. Rather at Madison Square Garden, where he was watching the Knicks play the Miami Heat. Later that afternoon Mr. Rather and a camerawoman went to Queens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby was also watching the Knicks game, on television, in his office with only a few technicians.</p>
        <p>''He said it was Super Bowl Sunday, and he remembered watching Super Bowls with his son,'' Mr. Rather said yesterday. ''He said he wanted to talk, and then he said: 'Bring your camera and your microphone. I have some things I want to tell people.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby has declined to talk to any other reporters about the death of his son, who was 27. People at the network said CBS executives had discussed the possibility of an interview with Mr. Rather, but not even tentative plans had been made.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby typically acts on his own, however, and on Sunday, he gave Mr. Rather a hint of why he had suddenly reached out. He told Mr. Rather that he had driven back to New York from Massachusetts on Saturday night, and once in the city had been spotted in his car by several people. In the past, when passers-by recognized him, he would make a face or give them a thumbs-up sign, and they would laugh, Mr. Rather said, but this time they turned away ''with very sad faces.''</p>
        <p>''He said to himself, 'This can't go on,' '' Mr. Rather quoted Mr. Cosby as telling him. ''He knows this is a hurt that will never go away, but insofar as humanly possible, he wants people to move back to the time where they saw him as someone who brings laughter into their lives.</p>
        <p>''This is his passion, his life's work. He told me, 'I'm a comedian, I'm a performer, I'm an entertainer.' He said that's the way people know him, and the way he knows people, and he wanted to return to that relationship.''</p>
        <p>In a portion of the interview broadcast on Sunday night, Mr. Cosby said his wife was disturbed that their son's killer was still at large. He said: ''Mrs. Cosby wants this man. I mean she verbalizes she wants him. She wants him now. She refuses to accept that this 'thing' is still out there. She doesn't accept the fact that nobody comes forward to help with the truth.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, television crews, photographers and reporters began filling the sidewalks outside the Astoria studio at dawn, hoping to glimpse Mr. Cosby. But he had spent the night inside the studio, which has comfortable living quarters. He met with the cast and crew at 8 A.M. and gave a short talk, told some jokes and said it was time to make people laugh again.</p>
        <p>A rerun episode of ''Cosby'' was seen last night. The series had been scheduled to show reruns for the last two weeks of January.</p>
        <p>The cast and crew will be able to get back on schedule this week, because they had been on the verge of taping a new episode on the day Mr. Cosby learned of his son's death. That episode was taped yesterday, without the usual studio audience.</p>
        <p>The next new episode will be rehearsed for the rest of this week and will be taped on Friday, this time with an audience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rather said that he had known Mr. Cosby for about 20 years, although they were ''not close personal friends.'' He said Mr. Cosby told him to ask anything he wanted: ''He made a point of drilling into me with his eyes, really locking my eyes, and saying, 'Anything.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby ''was very candid and said he took full responsibility for what happened'' between him and Ms. Jackson's mother, Mr. Rather said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby did not discuss the reaction of his wife, Camille to the affair, nor did he say when she had learned of it. ''We talked about Camille,'' Mr. Rather said, ''but not in that context.''</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Cosby had made only one request for the interview Sunday, that he be filmed sitting in front of a portrait of Ennis wearing his cap and gown on the day he got his master's degree from Columbia University in 1995.</p>
        <p>Ennis Cosby had overcome a severe learning disability to earn bachelor's and master's degrees and was working toward a doctorate in special education, hoping to start a school for children with similar learning problems.</p>
        <p>''The more I hear and read about Ennis Cosby,'' Mr. Rather added, ''the more I understand what has been lost, not only by the Cosby family but by all of us. This was a young man who had already made a difference, and would have made more difference had he lived.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cosby also talked about a pine tree the family had planted at the grave, Mr. Rather said. They decided to put lights on it on Ennis's birthday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rather said: ''As the family talked, some of the others said 'We want lights on it on our birthdays, too, and on special occasions.' And Bill Cosby told me, with a smile, with a laugh even, that he bets it'll be lighted a good part of the year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
