<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Says D'Amato Profited As Brokerage Broke Rules</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SECURITIES AND COMMODITIES VIOLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITEWATER CASE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STRATTON OAKMONT (BROKERAGE FIRM)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SECURITIES AND EXCHANGECOMMISSION (SEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, IAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'AMATO, ALFONSE M (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM ALFONSE MD'AMATO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DF1639F934A35755C0A960958260" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Says D'Amato Profited As Brokerage Broke Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, IAN;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Long Island brokerage house violated its own rules -- and did so for questionable motives -- when it earned Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato a profit of $37,125 in one day of stock market trading in 1993, according to a report prepared for the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>The report, completed in 1994 but not released until this week, drew no conclusions about whether the Senator himself violated any laws or broke any Senate rules. And S.E.C. officials said yesterday that there was no indication that Mr. D'Amato used his position on the Senate Banking Committee to help the firm, Stratton Oakmont, which has been repeatedly investigated and fined by securities regulators since 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Long Island brokerage house violated its own rules -- and did so for questionable motives -- when it earned Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato a profit of $37,125 in one day of stock market trading in 1993, according to a report prepared for the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>The report, completed in 1994 but not released until this week, drew no conclusions about whether the Senator himself violated any laws or broke any Senate rules. And S.E.C. officials said yesterday that there was no indication that Mr. D'Amato used his position on the Senate Banking Committee to help the firm, Stratton Oakmont, which has been repeatedly investigated and fined by securities regulators since 1989.</p>
        <p>But Democrats in New York and Washington slammed Mr. D'Amato, who leads the  Senate Whitewater hearings, for his blistering criticism of Hillary Rodham Clinton's windfall profits a decade ago when the report shows that he himself benefited handsomely from his connections.</p>
        <p>The York City Public Advocate, Mark J. Green, who has announced his intention to run against the Republican Senator in 1998, called the report "just another rock in the avalanche of an unethical career."</p>
        <p>"It is unseemly if not unethical for a ranking member of the Banking Committee to seek and obtain preferential treatment from a stock firm under his  jurisdiction," Mr. Green said. The Senate Banking Committee, on which Mr. D'Amato was the ranking Republican at the time of the trade, directly oversees the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>The issue of Mr. D'Amato's large profit, from an initial public stock offering with a California computer company called Computer Marketplace Inc., was first disclosed nearly two years ago. The Senator said yesterday that the Federal report contained nothing new.</p>
        <p>"It's old news, it really is," Mr. D'Amato said in a telephone interview from Washington. "It's pretty obvious to me that some people are just trying to embarrass me."</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato said he received no special treatment from the firm, never spoke  with any of its principals about his investments and invested in the firm only because one of its brokers, David Beall, is the son-in-law of a close family friend and political donor.</p>
        <p>The report documents two differing accounts of how Mr. D'Amato became involved with Stratton Oakmont, and the Senator hotly denied one of them. According to the version he denied, related in the report by Daniel Porush, now  Stratton's president, Mr. D'Amato spoke with the firm's chairman at the time, Jordan Belfort, at a fund-raising event in New York City in February 1992.</p>
        <p>"Can you make me some money?" Mr. D'Amato asked Mr. Belfort, according to Mr. Porush's account.</p>
        <p>Mr. Belfort replied that the S.E.C. was investigating Stratton Oakmont. "Are  you sure you want to do this?" he said, referring to the agency. "They are looking at me. It would look bad."</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato replied, according to Mr. Porush's account, "Since when is it illegal to make money in the stock market?"</p>
        <p>The report said Mr. Porush's account did not explain why more than a year elapsed between that conversation and the investment in June 1993. Mr. D'Amato said that proved the conversation was fiction.</p>
        <p>"I never spoke to anyone other than David," he said.</p>
        <p>On June 22, 1993, Mr. D'Amato invested $18,000 to buy 4,500 shares in Computer Marketplace at $4 a share, in an initial public offering in which the allocation of shares was controlled by Stratton. The Senator sold his shares later that day for $12.25 a share, for a $37,125 profit.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by an outside consultant, Carl H. Loewenson Jr., a New York lawyer, said this trade was "atypical" for Stratton Oakson and violated internal rules in several ways. Mr. D'Amato's net worth of $70,000, excluding his home, was far less than company policy of $500,000 for such investments.</p>
        <p>The report also said Mr. D'Amato was allocated many more shares of Computer Marketplace than "other customers with accounts of comparable size and history at Stratton.</p>
        <p>"Stratton's bending of its own rules to service a United States Senator who,  through his status as senior minority member of the Senate Banking Committee wielded influence over the S.E.C., raises suspicions about Stratton's motives,"  the report said.</p>
        <p>Stratton has been in trouble since 1989 and over the years has settled numerous regulatory complaints. In 1994, the firm agreed to pay $2.5 million to  settle allegations of fraud. Two founders, including Mr. Belfort, were barred from the securities business. Stratton also agreed to hire an independent consultant to evaluate and monitor its practices, though it remains under scrutiny for its sales practices. It is a part of that consultant's report that  was released on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The report was made in August 1994, but Stratton Oakwood officials fought its release to the public. On Wednesday, United States District Judge Joyce Hens Green unsealed eight pages of the report in response to a suit filed by The Wall Street Journal, which carried a story about it Thursday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
