<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;A proposed deal by Warnaco raises fair questions of conflict.</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AUTHENTIC FITNESS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WARNACO GROUP INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDF1639F934A35755C0A960958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;A proposed deal by Warnaco raises fair questions of conflict.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S been six years since the Warnaco Group, needing to raise cash to pay down debt from its 1986 leveraged buyout, sold a division to its management. Yesterday, Warnaco offered to buy back that division, now called the Authentic Fitness Corporation, for a vastly higher price.</p>
        <p>The ties between the two companies are far more than historical. The companies share the same chairman and chief executive, Linda J. Wachner. And the Authentic Fitness board committee that will review the offer is run by a former  Warnaco official who resigned from that company's board only yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S been six years since the Warnaco Group, needing to raise cash to pay down debt from its 1986 leveraged buyout, sold a division to its management. Yesterday, Warnaco offered to buy back that division, now called the Authentic Fitness Corporation, for a vastly higher price.</p>
        <p>The ties between the two companies are far more than historical. The companies share the same chairman and chief executive, Linda J. Wachner. And the Authentic Fitness board committee that will review the offer is run by a former  Warnaco official who resigned from that company's board only yesterday.</p>
        <p>The offer is for a share exchange that values Authentic Fitness shares at $21.39, based on Warnaco's closing stock price of $29.50, down $1.75 in New York Stock Exchange trading yesterday. Authentic Fitness shares rose $3.375, to $21.50.</p>
        <p>The result is a boon for those who bought Authentic Fitness when it went public in 1992, at a price of $7, adjusted for a subsequent split. It is a bigger boon for Ms. Wachner and other Authentic Fitness executives, who paid $1.28 a share when they bought the company from Warnaco.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Ms. Wachner spoke of the opportunities involved in combining the two companies, which are both in the apparel business. She said Warnaco could profit from getting manufacturing business from Authentic Fitness, whose Speedo Authentic Fitness stores have been growing rapidly. Warnaco's products include Calvin Klein underwear and Warner's and Olga women's intimate apparel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner said she had suggested the idea of a merger to the Warnaco board, then stayed out of the process. Two members of the Warnaco board without ties to Authentic Fitness were appointed to a committee, decided to proceed and determined the price, she said.</p>
        <p>"There are no conflicts," she said when asked about apparent conflicts of interest. "This is not a process that I am running." She said the key players were CS First Boston, which is advising the Warnaco board, and Salomon Brothers, which is advising the Authentic Fitness committee.</p>
        <p>The Authentic Fitness committee is led by Robert D. Walters, who resigned yesterday from the Warnaco board, on which he had served since 1988. He had worked as the company's chief financial officer in the late 1980's. "Rather than have any appearance of a split in my loyalties, I felt it was necessary to resign from the Warnaco board," he said. He added that he did not think his ownership of 80,000 shares and options on Warnaco shares constituted a conflict. He owns 32,000 shares and options on Authentic Fitness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walters said that he thought it would take 10 days to two weeks for Salomon to study the offer and for the Authentic Fitness committee to decide whether it was a good idea. "We don't know which direction this will go, or whether we will recommend it," he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner declined to discuss the prospects of either company she runs, and would not quantify the synergies she sees in merging the operations. She said that analysts estimate profits of $1.50 a share for Warnaco this year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner is a major holder of shares and options to buy shares of both companies, with a 13 percent stake in Warnaco and a 12 percent stake in Authentic Fitness, where her holdings include 1.78 million shares and 1.05 million options.</p>
        <p>Warnaco went public in 1991 at a price of $10 a share, adjusted for a subsequent split. Months before that, Ms. Wachner was allowed to buy 2.6 million shares at $2.33 a share.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner said it should be noted that the value of both Authentic Fitness  and Warnaco shares "have more than tripled since they went public." She's right. Shareholders have done well in both companies. Indeed, a case could be made that either company is getting the worset of the deal. The offer is for less than Authentic Fitness shares traded for a few weeks ago. But it values Authentic Fitness at a higher multiple of profits, based on 1996 forecasts, than it values Warnaco.</p>
        <p>But that is the problem. When executives have two masters, anything they do involving both of them is sure to arouse questions. This may be a fair deal for  both companies, but it is not one in which the instigator of the deal, Ms. Wachner, can be said to have no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
