<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Governor's Empire Is Now in Ruins</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SYMINGTON, FIFE (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR FIFE SYMINGTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DF1639F934A35755C0A960958260" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Governor's Empire Is Now in Ruins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR FIFE SYMINGTON;</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When J. Fife Symington 3d first ran for governor in 1990, he promised Arizonans that if elected, he would run the state just like he ran his own ostensibly thriving Phoenix real estate empire.</p>
        <p>He was elected, and then, four years later, was re-elected, his constituents  apparently satisfied with his ability to mix politics with business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When J. Fife Symington 3d first ran for governor in 1990, he promised Arizonans that if elected, he would run the state just like he ran his own ostensibly thriving Phoenix real estate empire.</p>
        <p>He was elected, and then, four years later, was re-elected, his constituents  apparently satisfied with his ability to mix politics with business.</p>
        <p>But today, in his sixth year in office, Mr. Symington, a conservative Republican, is bankrupt, bouncing along the bottom in the polls, charged with political arrogance and let-'em-eat-cake insensitivity, and under scrutiny by Federal investigators for possible financial wrongdoing and misuse of office.</p>
        <p>Bankruptcy documents just made public raise puzzling questions about how the  Governor financed some of his upscale store-and-office projects. A renegotiated  promissory note set conditions for repayment that were as politically brassy as  they were financially offbeat.</p>
        <p>In the note, Jerome Hirsch, a Phoenix lender and former Symington-project partner, agreed that he would accept as little as $100,000 from the Governor in  final payment of a $4.2-million loan -- if, on the loan's due date, Dec. 1, 2001, Mr. Symington were still in deep financial difficulty and also "is then President of the United States of America."</p>
        <p>The Governor, who is 50, has maintained he is "absolutely innocent" of any financial wrongdoing in any of his business dealings. And insofar as the promissory note is concerned, he maintains that its unusual terms constitute nothing more than a bit of fun.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, his critics, especially Democrats, see the note as a classic example of Symington self-importance.</p>
        <p>"He doesn't view himself as regular folks," said Sam Coppersmith, a former Congressman who is chairman of the Democratic Party of Arizona, "so this is the  kind of thing you get from him. He runs the state, and his life, with the same mentality he ran his real estate developments -- don't worry until the due date  falls, if then."</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, though Mr. Symington comes from a long line of wealthy industrial blue bloods with an admirable history of service in elected and appointed office, and though as Governor he has succeeded in cutting taxes, spending and bureaucracy, there has never been any serious talk of him running for President, let alone making it to the White House by the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>Other than to proclaim himself innocent of any wrongdoing and to cast himself as one of the victims of the great 1980's real estate bust, Mr. Symington has refused public comment on how he precipitously went from being $12 million in the black to being $25 million in the red, unable to make payments on a dozen troubled commercial developments in Phoenix.</p>
        <p>"What he has to say, he'll say in bankruptcy court proceedings," said Doug Cole, his press aide. "He's done nothing illegal, and the record will show that  in the end. This is all just a political vendetta by the Governor's enemies."</p>
        <p>The newly released documents from the bankruptcy proceedings held thus far include the transcript of a sometimes illuminating Symington deposition.</p>
        <p>Asked to explain the odd payment terms of the $4.2-million loan, Mr. Symington calls it "very creative note-making" and says it represents the "style" of the creditor, Mr. Hirsch.</p>
        <p>"Really?" shoots back an incredulous Michael Manning, a lawyer for four union pension funds that lent Mr. Symington and some developer partners $10 million and are now struggling to recover their money.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning then suggests that Mr. Symington obtained loans by giving potential lenders a rosy financial picture of real estate developments, some of which, in fact, were financially failing. He contends the Governor vastly inflated the worth of the properties he held and grossly overstated the number of their rental occupants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning accuses Mr. Symington of understating and concealing his true debt problems -- not just to protect his financial flank but also his political  flank, lest voters might see him as a devious and inept manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Symington counters that he gave lenders a true picture of his finances. Further, he says, he was always ready and willing to provide more documentation  if creditors asked for it, which, he adds, they never did, even when they knew full well that real estate deals all over the Southwest were going sour.</p>
        <p>As for his estimates of his assets, the Governor argues that they were based  on what projects would be worth in the long run, not on current worth.</p>
        <p>In an effort to show that Mr. Symington misled not only creditors but also voters, Mr. Manning produced a document written by a lawyer representing a Symington creditor. The lawyer had just discussed Mr. Symington's financial problems with the Governor's own lawyer and concluded in a note summing up the meeting and the problems: "Very sensitive as political publicity."</p>
        <p>Mr. Manning then asked the Governor, according to the deposition, whether he  had ever broached with the creditor the political problems that might ensue should there be public disclosure that the Symington real estate empire was in deep financial trouble.</p>
        <p>"I don't remember having a discussion like that," Mr. Symington replies, "and it wouldn't have made any difference in any event, politically."</p>
        <p>In fact, since word got out, the Governor's political empire has also begun to crumble, taking a particularly sharp dive last fall when he declared bankruptcy -- just a few weeks after returning from a European vacation.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Governor's approval ratings in the polls were 65 percent favorable. But now they have flip-flopped and stand at 65 percent unfavorable.</p>
        <p>Polls show that about half of Arizona voters believe that the Governor should resign.</p>
        <p>Bruce Merrill, an Arizona State University professor who closely follows state politics, said that people in the state "don't care so much about his actual bankruptcy as the way he's handled it -- the perceived arrogance and brassiness." For many, Mr. Merrill said, "it's become a question of character."</p>
        <p>Federal investigators refuse to discuss their work regarding the Governor's finances.</p>
        <p>There is no law against a politician's misleading voters about his or her business acuity, if indeed that is what Mr. Symington did. But under Federal law it is illegal for anyone, public official or private citizen, to make a false or misleading statement about a financial deal that involves money passing through  a Federally insured financial institution.</p>
        <p>Most of the institutions that Mr. Symington has dealt with over the years would seem to be Federally insured.</p>
        <p>Further, should Federal investigators conclude that Mr. Symington broke some  state or Federal law in carrying out an official duty as governor, they might invoke the Federal law that prohibits abuse of a public office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
