<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Over the Rail With Flaubert</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="553436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, RICHARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLAUBERT, GUSTAVE (1821-1880)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC123CF933A0575BC0A964958260" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Over the Rail With Flaubert</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD GOODMAN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I BUMPED into Gustave Flaubert recently in my travels. As always, it was a pleasure. While I didn't actually talk to M. Flaubert, the meeting, through his writings, was as intimate as if he were standing beside me. Flaubert was surely one of the most delightful travelers who ever lived, and wrote some of the most delightful descriptions about his travels. Whereas in "Madame Bovary" he is wondrously controlled, in his letters and journals written abroad and in his short travel pieces, he is free, sly, bawdy, vivid and friendly. It's clear he likes to travel, and he is never dull.</p>
        <p>The last time I came upon the great man was in rather unfortunate circumstances. It was at sea, and we were both hanging over the rails. Not a pretty sight -- unless, of course, Flaubert writes about it. Yes, he can give even seasickness a kind of beauty. I was glad to run into him, because I didn't think it was possible to write about being seasick and get anywhere near to capturing how you really feel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I BUMPED into Gustave Flaubert recently in my travels. As always, it was a pleasure. While I didn't actually talk to M. Flaubert, the meeting, through his writings, was as intimate as if he were standing beside me. Flaubert was surely one of the most delightful travelers who ever lived, and wrote some of the most delightful descriptions about his travels. Whereas in "Madame Bovary" he is wondrously controlled, in his letters and journals written abroad and in his short travel pieces, he is free, sly, bawdy, vivid and friendly. It's clear he likes to travel, and he is never dull.</p>
        <p>The last time I came upon the great man was in rather unfortunate circumstances. It was at sea, and we were both hanging over the rails. Not a pretty sight -- unless, of course, Flaubert writes about it. Yes, he can give even seasickness a kind of beauty. I was glad to run into him, because I didn't think it was possible to write about being seasick and get anywhere near to capturing how you really feel.</p>
        <p>I was living in the south of France, writing a book about fishermen, and I was planning a trip to Corsica. I went to the library in Toulon to do some research and found that in 1840, when he was 19, Flaubert had taken a short trip there with a friend of his father's, an eminent surgeon named Jules Cloquet. It was Flaubert's first real journey. He kept a journal of the trip, which wasn't published until after his death in 1880. Dorothy Carrington, in her classic book on Corsica, "Granite Island," says the piece has "a magical quality." I still remember many parts of it, how he traveled across the island on a donkey, tramping through the maquis and meeting bandits on the run. (As far as I know, the journal has never been translated into English. Alas.)</p>
        <p>But our encounter occurred before Flaubert landed at Ajaccio. It was shortly after his boat left Toulon and made its way past the Iles d'Hyeres. That's when he got seasick. I had recently had an awful time on one of the fishing boats off Sanary-sur-Mer during an all-night search for swordfish. I had never been so sick before, including all the summers I spent on fishing boats off the Virginia coast when I was a boy. How bad I felt was unique, or so I thought at the time, and it wasn't my stomach that got the worst of me, but my brain.</p>
        <p>As the boat became a floating pendulum, swaying to great heights and great depths, I first became nauseated, then sick, and then I began to hallucinate. My mind went through an eerie catechism as I desperately tried to hold on. At one point, I created and starred in a fantastical exchange. Entirely in French, it was between myself and a traffic judge over an accident, replete with technical terms and jargon, none of which I actually knew. The hours crawled miserably by, and when we finally returned to port, I continued to feel bad for hours.</p>
        <p>I was somewhat frustrated afterward about how to put this nightmare into words, until I ran into M. Flaubert on his boat off Toulon. I found out he had already done it:</p>
        <p>"When we left Toulon, the sea was fair and promised to be kind to weak stomachs -- so much so that I found myself embarking with the security of a man certain to digest his lunch. In fact, just until the end of the harbor, the 'treacherous element' was being very well behaved, and the light pitching of our boat moved us to a charming sort of languor."</p>
        <p>Yes, it was like that for me, too! It had been a serene, lovely day when we set out, not 10 miles from Toulon.</p>
        <p>"I felt the sun's soft rays, and I abandoned myself to the rocking of the water-nymph while watching behind us the wake that widened and then was lost under the great blue surface."</p>
        <p>Yes, the Mediterranean can be incredibly beautiful, but . . .</p>
        <p>"Off the Iles d'Hyeres, we hadn't taken up a breeze, but nevertheless broad waves broke vigorously against the sides of the boat making its body creak -- mine, too. A big black line showed along the horizon, and the waves, as we advanced, took on a more somber tint. . . . I was lying on my back, in the most horizontal position possible, looking at the sky, and I thought as hard as I could so that the creations of the mind might quell the crisis of the flesh."</p>
        <p>Yes, here it comes, sneaking up on you like a cat, and what can you do about it? Nothing!</p>
        <p>"My back was being shaken by the engine's regular piston strokes, lengthwise by the pitching of the waves, from side to side by the rolling. . . . I saw only the top of the mast, and my eye, fixed and stupid, followed below it all the rocking movements, without being able to stop. Rain followed, and I had to get up to go inside and lie down in the cabin where I was to stay for 16 hours, like spit on the floor."</p>
        <p>Besides Dr. Cloquet, his cabin mates include an engineer, a young Corsican doctor, a tax collector and three priests. Night arrives, and the table is set for dinner. Only Dr. Cloquet and the three priests are able to eat. Flaubert writes that, in fact, the priests eat "like laymen." I remember through my delirium watching the fishermen wolf down huge sandwiches and swig cheap wine.</p>
        <p>How?</p>
        <p>Full of self-pity, "already humiliated by my position," Flaubert declines to dine.</p>
        <p>The meal over at last, he dozes off -- only to be awakened at midnight by the priests' snoring and, worse, the noise of the wooden mast creaking, while the lamp, to the ship's rolling, throws its light up and down and around the cabin. Flaubert is resigned to his suffering.</p>
        <p>But then his troubles really begin. Off Corsica, the weather becomes truly bad, and Flaubert gets monstrously seasick.</p>
        <p>He</p>
        <p>starts to hallucinate: He imagines the cabins as coffins stacked one upon the other, and this has the immediate effect of making him feel in hell. Then he does what I tried, and failed, to do. He imagines he's on land. And in a lovely leap of the imagination he "doubles" himself: "I imagined myself sitting on the grass . . . smoking in the shade, thinking of the</p>
        <p>other me</p>
        <p>who was lying in bed on the boat and vomiting into a steel bowl." He transports himself back to his home in Rouen, recreating the most exact details, even to how the floor stones were bleached in certain places. Oh, what desperate lengths! Oh, what futility!</p>
        <p>A huge wave rudely brings him back from his temporary escape, and he stares into a very real steel bowl "three-quarters full." The chairs and tables turn over. One of Flaubert's cabin mates, a priest, becomes tangled in some curtains while the tax collector tumbles onto Dr. Cloquet "in the most immoral position possible." Flaubert forces himself to laugh at this, because he thinks it might divert his attention from his misery. The physical exertion of laughing, however, makes him vomit again.</p>
        <p>And, finally, in one of the most charming pictures I have ever read of the creator of "Madame Bovary," in a desperate attempt to take in a bit of liquid, he squeezes some drops from a lemon onto his lower lip and -- remember that he is lying down -- he amuses himself, even in his agony, by blowing them up, and onto, his mustache.</p>
        <p>Mercifully, the boat at last arrives in Ajaccio. It's not over, though, as anyone who has been really seasick knows. "Several hours after getting off the ship," Flaubert writes, "the earth continued to move, and I watched the furniture rise, and then fall."</p>
        <p>What luck that I should meet M. Flaubert 150 years later in that library in Toulon. And that I could find someone as poetic and funny as this 19-year-old magician to commiserate with.</p>
        <p>I ran into him a few months later in Bizerte, Tunisia, down at the old port. It appears we might have stayed in the same dumpy hotel. But that's another tale.</p>
        <p>RICHARD GOODMAN is the author of "French Dirt: The Story of a Garden in the South of France" (Algonquin).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">RICHARD GOODMAN is the author of "French Dirt: The Story of a Garden in the South of France" (Algonquin).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
