<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Free Agents May Find Many Closed Wallets</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="553215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE AGENTS (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D91E38F933A0575BC0A964958260" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Free Agents May Find Many Closed Wallets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets' decision to trade David Cone rather than give him millions of dollars as a free agent did not come as a surprise to at least one general manager. Even while Al Harazin, the Mets' general manager, was saying a couple of weeks ago that he would not trade Cone, his counterpart on another team, during a discussion of the coming free-agent market, remarked, "The Mets may have more constraint because they're so awful this year."</p>
        <p>Perhaps that general manager had greater insight into Harazin's thinking than Harazin himself. Whatever, by trading their best pitcher to the Toronto Blue Jays, the Mets have begun what can be considered the Cone constraint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets' decision to trade David Cone rather than give him millions of dollars as a free agent did not come as a surprise to at least one general manager. Even while Al Harazin, the Mets' general manager, was saying a couple of weeks ago that he would not trade Cone, his counterpart on another team, during a discussion of the coming free-agent market, remarked, "The Mets may have more constraint because they're so awful this year."</p>
        <p>Perhaps that general manager had greater insight into Harazin's thinking than Harazin himself. Whatever, by trading their best pitcher to the Toronto Blue Jays, the Mets have begun what can be considered the Cone constraint.</p>
        <p>Except the Cone constraint could have ramifications well beyond the Mets, who want to reduce the $44.5 million payroll they have labored under this season. It certainly adds intrigue to what is expected to be the key question of the off season:</p>
        <p>With the coming free-agent class potentially the most glamorous ever, are clubs prepared to spend the type of money to which top-flight free agents have become accustomed, or will some players suffer economic shock, discovering that the money they expected isn't there? Plenty of Big Names</p>
        <p>Cone, Doug Drabek, Greg Maddux, John Smiley, Greg Swindell are the most attractive starting pitchers heading for free agency. The hitting part of the potential market includes Barry Bonds, Kirby Puckett, Mark McGwire, Ruben Sierra, Joe Carter and Paul Molitor.</p>
        <p>As the salaries soar to superstratospheric levels, more teams drop out of the competition for the superstar types. With so many of those players available, then, will they find enough teams willing to spend the kind of money they seek? After all, how many Kirby Pucketts can one team sign?</p>
        <p>"When there have been impact and premium players available, they have always been well-rewarded," Fred Claire, the Los Angeles Dodgers' general manager, said. "I don't know of any exception to that. Of course, we've never had as many potential impact players as far as I can recall."</p>
        <p>Bobby Bonilla, who was the most attractive free agent available last winter even though his credentials fell short of some in this year's group, signed with the Mets for $29 million over five years, a record annual average income until the Chicago Cubs gave Ryne Sandberg $28.4 million for a four-year extension that prevented him from joining this year's free agents. Danny Tartabull signed with the Yankees for $25.5 million for five years. Here Comes Reality</p>
        <p>Sandy Alderson, the Oakland Athletics' general manager, said he thought it was possible that some free agents might fall short of their quest for riches.</p>
        <p>"I think that came close to reality last winter," Alderson said. "Danny Tartabull came very close not to being shut out but to being surprised by what was available until the Yankees bailed him out. This year, with the sheer number of free agents who will be available in the winter, given an additional year of fiscal evolution -- that is, expenses have risen to a level much closer to or beyond our revenues -- you're going to see some of that."</p>
        <p>The San Diego Padres are one of those teams that does not plan to participate in the expensive sweepstakes. Bonds, who lives near San Diego, has expressed a desire to play there, but he would have to take maybe 50 cents on the dollar to interest the Padres.</p>
        <p>"The number of teams that can afford them is diminishing," Joe McIlvaine, the Padres' general manager, said of the big-name free agents. "For a team like the Padres, it would be extremely difficult, almost impossible, to sign a player of that magnitude for the bucks they're talking about. We'd almost have to strip our team to pay for them."</p>
        <p>Player agents are aware of the possibly shrinking market, but they remain confident that the top layer of free agents will go through the procedure economically unscathed. They aren't so certain about the players just below the top.</p>
        <p>"I do have a feeling it will be tough for a lot of guys," said Chuck Berrty, Sierra's agent. "I think that will happen to a degree. There will be some who can get jobs at any level, but at what point does that number stop? Are there three, six, nine spots available? Somewhere down the ladder guys are going to be surprised."</p>
        <p>Wade Boggs, whose string of successive .300 seasons is about to end at 10, is expected to be one of those who have a surprise awaiting them. One agent, not his, who always has a good read on the market, referred to Boggs as a player who "has become the quintessential mediocre third baseman." The tarnished Boston star, the agent said, "is going to find no one giving him $4 million a year and losing a draft choice."</p>
        <p>Scott Boras, who represents Maddux and Benito Santiago, said he believed that some players having off years will adopt a different strategy.</p>
        <p>"Players may decide to use salary arbitration," he said, "and go at it another year where there is less talent available, where there is a better market. I think that plan B will be utilized by a number of players if there is a question of the market. That could be a very viable alternative. If a club doesn't offer arbitration, he can sign wth someone for one year and be a free agent next year."</p>
        <p>Tom Reich, an agent with years of free-agent experience, noted that the top pitchers won't have anything to fear. "The economic market is totally different for pitchers and everyday players," he said.</p>
        <p>That's one of the reasons the Mets decided to trade Cone. Once the Cubs confirmed Reich's view by offering Maddux a five-year contract (for $27.5 million), Harazin concluded that someone might indeed offer Cone five years, but that it wasn't going to be the Mets. Harazin is not alone in his thinking about placing constraints on that type of offer.</p>
        <p>"I was shocked when I read about the Maddux negotiations," the A's Alderson said. "My immediate reaction was the only thing dumber than making the offer was rejecting it." The Skydome Is the Limit</p>
        <p>The David Cone trade carried with it another significant development.</p>
        <p>In 1982, when the Yankees traded Tommy John to the California Angels on Aug. 31, the transfer of his salary on that day, when rosters are used to compile average team salaries, catapulted the Angels' average past the Yankees' figure, $423,403 to $411,988. That made the Angels No. 1 after the Yankees had held that spot the first four years the Players Association computed average team salaries.</p>
        <p>Cone's move from New York to Toronto virtually assures the Blue Jays the No. 1 spot in this year's salary standing. Although Cone earned $3,362,637 of his salary with the Mets and will earn only $887,363 with the Blue Jays, the entire $4.25 million salary will be included in the Toronto total. That's the way labor and management salary practices work.</p>
        <p>The roster changes created by the trade left the Blue Jays with an average salary of $1,517,272, the Mets $1,367,635. An Ace, Without the Bandages</p>
        <p>If Mike Harkey's body ever lets him, he could become one of the best pitchers in the major leagues. The Chicago Cubs wait patiently, if with frustration.</p>
        <p>After shoulder and knee injuries deprived him of a chance of pitching in the majors in 1989, Harkey had an outstanding rookie season in 1990, compiling a 12-6 record. An early-season shoulder injury led to surgery May 2 last season and limited him to four starts. The shoulder wasn't right this year, either, and he began the season on the 60-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>But he finally was able to pitch again after the All-Star Game break, and he reeled off four victories without a loss and a 1.93 earned run average in his first six starts. It was no coincidence that the Cubs' resurgence occurred once Harkey joined the starting rotation.</p>
        <p>The 25-year-old right-hander began a Cubs' four-game winning streak with his first victory, extended a winning streak to four games with his second, ended a four-game skid with his third and started a five-game winning streak with his fourth.</p>
        <p>Harkey was scheduled to try to extend the Cub's streak to six last Tuesday, but he aggravated a groin pull he suffered in his previous start and couldn't pitch. The Cubs lost the game. They're grateful that this time they won't lose Harkey for long.</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
