<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Vacant Post: Ending a Tradition</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="553471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUNTY EXECUTIVES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D8143FF933A0575BC0A964958260" item-length="1704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Vacant Post: Ending a Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES FERON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FERON, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Westchester Board of Legislators is about to take a step long urged by its Democratic minority and recommended by a Charter Revision Commission: filling vacancies that occur on the Board and in the post of County Executive through special elections, rather than through appointments.</p>
        <p>Since the Board supplanted the County Board of Supervisors in 1970, it has been controlled by Republicans. Whenever a vacancy has occurred, a Republican has been named to fill it. County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke was originally appointed to the office in 1983.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Westchester Board of Legislators is about to take a step long urged by its Democratic minority and recommended by a Charter Revision Commission: filling vacancies that occur on the Board and in the post of County Executive through special elections, rather than through appointments.</p>
        <p>Since the Board supplanted the County Board of Supervisors in 1970, it has been controlled by Republicans. Whenever a vacancy has occurred, a Republican has been named to fill it. County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke was originally appointed to the office in 1983.</p>
        <p>Those appointees eventually had to face the voters at the next general election -- legislators are elected for two years and the County Executive for four -- but months of incumbency represented a huge advantage at the polls. Going to Referendum</p>
        <p>Opponents of the appointive process have argued that it disenfranchised voters. "Under the present procedure, you have people who do not live in the district choosing who will represent the district," said Legislator Audrey G. Hochberg, a Scarsdale Democrat, "and that is wrong."</p>
        <p>Even if the Board votes to approve the move, which is expected, the proposal must go before the voters in a referendum, and that cannot take place before November next year, because it must be approved by the Legislature 90 days before a general election.</p>
        <p>But the process has begun. On Aug. 21 the Board's Committee on Legislation, headed by Joseph M. Delfino, Republican of White Plains, voted to recommend that the full Board ask County Attorney Marilyn J. Slaatten to draw up the necessary legislation to present the issue to the voters.</p>
        <p>Stephen P. Tenore, a New Rochelle Republican and the Board chairman, asked Ms. Slaatten to "start drafting the laws we would need so we can move on them as quickly as possible." He said he was eager to "lock in the Board's approval while it had the present makeup."</p>
        <p>He was referring to two possible vacancies that could occur later this year, when Ms. Hochberg and Sandra R. Galef, a Democrat of Ossining, campaign for State Assembly seats. Both are in favor of special elections and sought unsuccessfully for years to end the use of appointments to fill vacancies. Ms. Galef said that while Mr. Tenore should be commended for acting to change a method that previous Republican chairmen had long embraced, the proposal could have been placed before county voters in a referendum this November. "We had it on our agenda last December," she said, referring to the Democratic list of recommended legislation.</p>
        <p>"What is even more puzzling is that Steve Tenore mentioned it as one of his own priorities when he became chairman in January," Mrs. Galef said. "But speaking in favor of it is one thing, while getting it on the floor is another. He delayed long enough to miss the 90-day referendum deadline for this year's election."</p>
        <p>Why the push for change now? Mr. Tenore and other legislators speak of it as a "good government" recommendation and cite its endorsement by the Charter revision experts and others who have studied government processes. But there may also be a more pragmatic political incentive.</p>
        <p>The Republicans stood to gain from the appointment process as long as they controlled the Board, but that luxury may not last much longer. The present lineup is the closest in the Board's history, with eight Republicans, eight Democrats and one Conservative, Suzanne R. Swanson, who joined the Republicans in selecting a chairman and organizing committees.</p>
        <p>Changing the appointment process to one featuring special elections might be impossible to achieve under a Democratic majority, especially after the party spent two decades in the political wilderness.</p>
        <p>The Democratic proposal, issued on Dec. 31, said that when a new County Executive must be found, and the special election to fill the office falls in an even-numbered year (the terms of County Executives begin and end in odd-numbered years), "that special election should be for a three-year term." 'Rise Above Politics'</p>
        <p>"At the end of the three-year term," the Democratic proposal continued, "the next election for the office, which would fall in an odd numbered year, should be for a full four-year term." This, the Democrats noted, "would eliminate the destabilizing sequence of a one-year term, followed possibly by a two-year term, followed finally by a four-year term."</p>
        <p>Chapters of the League of Women Voters in New Castle and Somers urged the Board "to rise above the politics of the present situation," presumably a reference to the Board's selection of Republicans to replace Ms. Galef and Ms. Hochberg if they win their Assembly races, by changing the law in the manner recommended by the County Charter Revision Commission in 1988.</p>
        <p>That proposal called for a special election to be held within 60 days after a vacancy occurred unless a general election was scheduled within 90 days.</p>
        <p>The change in filling vacancies, which also requires a public hearing before being considered by the 17-member Board, "was precipitated by all the talk last year of the County Executive leaving," Mr. Tenore said, referring to Mr. O'Rourke, who was recommended for a seat on the Federal District Court in Manhattan by Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, the New York Republican-Conservative. Bush Nomination Last November</p>
        <p>President Bush formally nominated Mr. O'Rourke last November, prompting speculation about his possible successor, who would be chosen by the County Board.</p>
        <p>Under the proposed legislation, a special election would be held to fill the vacancy until the next general election, with the new incumbent facing the voters a second time to fill an unexpired term. The County Executive's four-year term expires in 1993. Mr. O'Rourke's judicial nomination expires on Dec. 31 if the United States Senate does not act by then.</p>
        <p>The 59-year-old Mr. O'Rourke has become accustomed to running for County Executive, doing it twice in two years after he first took office in 1982, when he was selected by the Board to replace Alfred B. DelBello, who resigned after winning election as Lieutenant Governor.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Rourke, who began serving as County Executive in January 1983, won election in November that year to the two-year balance of Mr. DelBello's term. In 1985 Mr. O'Rourke won election to a full four-year term as County Executive and won re-election in 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Rourke's initial selection by the Board raised some eyebrows, because the Board was barred by law from selecting one of its own members for the County Executive post. To get around this obstacle, Mr. O'Rourke resigned as a legislator and thus was technically eligible to be picked by his fellow Republicans to the county's highest post. A Question of Ethics</p>
        <p>This angered many Democrats, who saw it as unethical if not illegal, and prompted a Croton-on-Hudson Democrat, Richard Barbuto, to write letters to local newspapers complaining of what he called "blatant abuse" of the law and noting that this "farce" was intended to assist a "public official who has been reported for years as wanting to be a judge."</p>
        <p>Last April Mr. Barbuto, a lawyer who has been a candidate for office 10 times since 1979 (winning once, in 1986, as a village trustee), sent an affidavit describing the circumstances of the O'Rourke selection process to the United States Senate Judiciary Committee, which is weighing the qualifications of the nominees to the Federal bench.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barbuto questioned Mr. O'Rourke's "ethically questionable behavior" and his "blatant disregard for the law."</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Rourke has not denied the circumstances of his selection. His official biography states that he "resigned from the Board of Legislators in order to accept nomination to the office of Westchester County Executive by his fellow legislators in January 1983." Weighing Cost of Special Election</p>
        <p>Legislator Daniel P. Thomas of Yonkers, a Republican and member of the Legislation Committee, said he supported asking the County Attorney to prepare the necessary legislation to change the appointment process and said he had "no problem calling for a special election to fill these vacancies."</p>
        <p>"But it depends on when the vacancy occurs," he said. "If it's going to be a full year until the next general election, then I would totally support a special election. If it's within a couple of months, however, you'd have to weigh it against the cost of having a special election."</p>
        <p>Mr. Delfino, who has pressed for action on the special election, said he would like the Board to consider other changes in how it operates, like changing its term of office from two years to four; instituting term limitations of, say, no more than 12 years of service, and eliminating the $60 fees it awards legislators for each committee meeting they attend, raising salaries instead.</p>
        <p>The principle argument for the four-year legislative term is that it would reduce the cost of campaigning, which averages $30,000 for many incumbents. Those who favor the two-year term say that it forces legislators, "who represent an invisible layer of government," as Ms. Galef put it, to interact with voters at least every two years. Division on Term Limitations</p>
        <p>There also seemed to be divided opinion about term limitations, with proponents noting that some legislators have served for two decades and should be replaced, while opponents argue that the veterans represent experience on a Board that has a substantial number of one- and two-term members.</p>
        <p>The $60-a-meeting fee is intended to insure that legislators attend the committee sessions, where most of the work of the Board is done. The basic legislative salary is $27,950, but committee heads earn additional sums of $6,000 to $9,000. The chairman of the Board receives an additional $30,000, the vice chairman $12,000, the majority and minority leaders $9,000 each and the majority and minority whips, $3,000 each.</p>
        <p>In Rockland County, where county legislators receive no fees for attending committee meetings, "it doesn't work," Ms. Galef said. "They have trouble making quorums." On the other hand, some Westchester legislators are assigned to four committees, making the $60 fees a major source of income.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
