<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TVWeekend; Back to the Prairies With Tall Sarah</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="588235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLOSE, GLENN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALKEN, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HALLMARK HALL OF FAME (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SKYLARK (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB1730F936A35751C0A965958260" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TVWeekend; Back to the Prairies With Tall Sarah</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Original plans didn't include a sequel, but CBS's "Sarah, Plain and Tall" proved so popular, ending up the highest-rated television movie of the 1990-91 season, that a continuation of the Kansas prairie story could hardly be avoided. So on Sunday at 9 P.M., the Witting family returns in still another "Hallmark Hall of Fame" presentation. This one is called "Skylark." Once again Sarah, the mail-order bride from Maine, and her husband, Jacob, are played by Glenn Close and Christopher Walken; their children, Anna and Caleb, by Lexi Randall and Christopher Bell.</p>
        <p>The time has jumped two years to 1912. Out of hesitant beginnings, a family has taken shape. The dour, tortured Jacob is no longer obsessed with the death of his first wife. His children have come fully to accept Sarah as their new mother. She is very much in love with all of them. But now the land itself turns against the family as a severe drought threatens crops and livestock. Electric storms trigger dangerous fires across the prairie. Neighbors begin moving away. After the Witting barn is destroyed in a fire, Jacob persuades a reluctant Sarah to go to Maine with the children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Original plans didn't include a sequel, but CBS's "Sarah, Plain and Tall" proved so popular, ending up the highest-rated television movie of the 1990-91 season, that a continuation of the Kansas prairie story could hardly be avoided. So on Sunday at 9 P.M., the Witting family returns in still another "Hallmark Hall of Fame" presentation. This one is called "Skylark." Once again Sarah, the mail-order bride from Maine, and her husband, Jacob, are played by Glenn Close and Christopher Walken; their children, Anna and Caleb, by Lexi Randall and Christopher Bell.</p>
        <p>The time has jumped two years to 1912. Out of hesitant beginnings, a family has taken shape. The dour, tortured Jacob is no longer obsessed with the death of his first wife. His children have come fully to accept Sarah as their new mother. She is very much in love with all of them. But now the land itself turns against the family as a severe drought threatens crops and livestock. Electric storms trigger dangerous fires across the prairie. Neighbors begin moving away. After the Witting barn is destroyed in a fire, Jacob persuades a reluctant Sarah to go to Maine with the children.</p>
        <p>The script for "Skylark," written by Patricia MacLachlan, author of the book "Sarah, Plain and Tall," clearly favors character over incident. The lean plot is not nearly as important as the relationships explored. At its core, "Skylark" is a love story tracing the ties, ever more binding, between Sarah and Jacob.</p>
        <p>The sense of family, encompassing not only parents and children but also immediate relatives in a dazzlingly green and somewhat eccentric New England, expands further to a sense of community when, in simpler and less cluttered times, neighborliness was a necessity as well as a virtue. It is not difficult to figure out why these stories might appeal to today's audiences.</p>
        <p>"Skylark," directed by Joseph Sargent, is brimming with fine performances. Ms. Close once again seems to have spurned makeup, getting down to a freckled, somewhat weathered self that is as natural and attractive as her overall performance. Her birthday scene, in which Caruso can be heard singing "Martha" on a new-fangled Victrola, is irresistible. Mr. Walken, a touch too gloomy in "Sarah," here gets an opportunity to bring more colors to the portrait, and makes the most of it. Ms. Randall and Mr. Bell are the kinds of winning youngsters who make canards about child actors sound silly. And the rest of the cast is splendid, not least Tresa Hughes, Lois Smith and Elizabeth Wilson as three Maine sisters, one more irrepressibly doting and dotty than the other.</p>
        <p>In short, if you loved "Sarah," catch "Skylark."  'Great Television Moments' 'What We Watched'</p>
        <p>ABC, tomorrow at 8 P.M. (Channel 7 in New York)</p>
        <p>If there has to be another clips history of television, it doesn't hurt to have it produced by the Museum of Television and Radio in Manhattan, which at least approaches the medium with seriousness and sophistication. This two-hour dip into the archives is introduced by Candice Bergen, who talks briefly about television's "amazing ability to bring us together," not least for the birth of a couple of babies, Lucy Ricardo's and Murphy Brown's.</p>
        <p>The rest of the program is divided into thematic segments, with various personalites as the hosts: Marlo Thomas for comedies, James Woods for dramas, Barbara Walters for news events, and so forth. Ranging from "All in the Family" and "Roots" to Edward R. Murrow and the Challenger explosion, the bombardment of images is rather stunning, even staggering.</p>
        <p>Neat touch after the final credits: a poker-faced Alfred Hitchcock intoning, "Those of us who work in television have a technical term for this part of the program: The End." Skylark  CBS, Sunday at 9 P.M. (Channel 2 in New York) Producted and directed by Joseph Sargent; written by Patricia MacLachlan; director of photography, Michael Fash; editor, Mike Brown; costumes by Van Broughton Ramsey and Jim Echerd; production designer, Ed Wittstein; a production of Self Productions and Trillium Productions for the Hallmark Hall of Fame; Glenn Close and William Self, executive producers. Sarah . . . Glenn Close Jacob . . . Christopher Walken Anna . . . Lexi Randall Caleb . . . Christopher Bell Maggie . . . Margaret Sophie Stein Matthew . . . Jon De Vries Chub . . . Lee Richardson Mattie . . . Tresa Hughes Harriet . . . Elizabeth Wilson Lou . . . Lois Smith</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
