<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY NEWS</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="812322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD1139F933A05752C1A963958260" item-length="1322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY NEWS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAF BANCORP IN DEAL TO BUY N. S. BANCORP MAF Bancorp Inc. said late yesterday that it had agreed to buy N. S. Bancorp Inc. in a stock and cash transaction valued at $277.2 million. The acquisition will give MAF Bancorp 20 branches in Chicago and its western suburbs, with about $3 billion in assets. MAF Bancorp, based in Clarendon Hills, Ill., is the parent company of Mid America Federal Savings Bank. N. S. Bancorp, based in Chicago, is the parent company of Northwestern Savings Bank. Under the agreement, each common share of N. S. Bancorp will be exchanged for 0.8466 common share of MAF Bancorp, plus $20.34 in cash. Based on yesterday's closing price of $26 a share  for MAF Bancorp, the deal values N. S. Bancorp shares at $42.35 each, $6.10 above their closing price of $36.25. Both companies trade on the Nasdaq stock market.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones)</p>
        <p>FLAGSTAR AGREES TO SELL ITS STADIUM FOODS UNIT The Flagstar Companies has agreed to sell its Volume Services unit for an undisclosed sum and has ended talks to sell its Quincy's Family Steakhouse restaurants. The nation's No. 4 restaurant company said late on Tuesday that it  would sell Volume Services, which sells food and merchandise at sports stadiums, to an investor group formed by the unit's management and Blackstone Capital Partners II. Volume Services has revenue of $200 million a year. Flagstar, based in Spartanburg, S.C., also said it had ended talks to sell its Quincy's restaurants to a management-led group. Flagstar is 47 percent owned by the investment firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company in New York.</p>
        <p>(Bloomberg Business News)</p>
        <p>RHONE-POULENC TO SELL STAKE IN A PRODUCER OF SODA ASH Rhone-Poulenc S.A. agreed yesterday to sell its 51 percent stake in the soda ash producer Rhone-Poulenc of Wyoming to Oriental Chemical Industry for $150 million. The rest of the company is owned by the Union Pacific Resources Company, a unit of the Union Pacific Corporation. The transaction does not include Rhone-Poulenc's sodium bicarbonate business. Rhone-Poulenc of Wyoming produces more than two million tons of soda ash annually from natural deposits in Green River, Wyo. It has about 500 employees. Soda ash, or sodium carbonate,  is a raw material used primarily in making glass. It is also is used in the chemical industry and in making detergents. Oriental Chemical Industry is a Korean chemical company.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones)</p>
        <p>CONVERSE TO CUT MORE JOBS AND ELIMINATE PRODUCT LINES Converse Inc., the maker of athletic shoes, announced a reorganization yesterday that would cut jobs, eliminate some product lines and save $25 million a year, starting in 1996. The company, based in North Reading, Mass., said it would stop making its outdoor, running, walking, tennis and football shoes, and would concentrate on its basketball, cross-training, children's and "athleisure" products. Converse, which announced the elimination of 496 jobs in October, said that another 98 jobs would be lost, leaving a work force of 2,504. The company also said it expected to take a pretax charge of $2.5 million in the fourth quarter to cover the cost of the reorganization. The company's shares fell 25 cents yesterday, to $4.25, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ALLEGHENY TO BUY REMAINING INTEREST IN GENERATING UNIT Allegheny Power System Inc. of New York agreed yesterday to buy the Duquesne Light Company's half-interest in a coal-fired generating unit near Morgantown, W.Va., for about $170 million. Allegheny Power said that its AYP Capital division planned to sell the 276 megawatts of generation capacity as an independent marketer. Duquesne Light, a unit of DQE Inc. in Pittsburgh, said it  planned to use the money to help offset the reduced value of its investment in nuclear power plants. The Monongahela Power Company and the Potomac Edison Company, both units of Allegheny Power, already own the other half of the No. 1  unit at the Fort Martin Power Station. Allegheny Power subsidiaries jointly own  the No. 2 unit at Fort Martin.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones)</p>
        <p>INVESTMENT GROUPS TO BUY UNITS FROM TROUBLED INSURER Penncorp Financial Group Inc. and a related investment group said yesterday that they would buy two units of the ICH Corporation, a troubled insurance company in Dallas, for $260 million. In an auction supervised by the Bankruptcy Court, Penncorp and Knightsbridge Capital Fund I L.P. said they would pay $210 million  in cash, $40 million in convertible debt securities and $10 million in stock for the Southwestern Life Insurance Company and Union Bankers Insurance Company. Once the deal is completed, Penncorp will own 55 percent, Knightsbridge will own 27 percent and ICH will retain 18 percent, assuming the conversion of the securities. ICH began Chapter 11 proceedings last month.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones) BURNHAM PACIFIC PROPERTIES CUTS ITS DIVIDEND 30% Burnham Pacific Properties Inc. slashed its dividend by more than 30 percent yesterday and said it would sell part of its office portfolio in an effort to focus on retail properties. Burnham Pacific, a real estate investment trust in San Diego, said the sale of office properties would reduce its fourth-quarter earnings by about $22 million. The company said that it would record additional  expenses of $2.8 million. The company also said it had agreed to sell Beverly Garland's Holiday Inn Hotel for an undisclosed sum. The company, which had more  than 17 million shares outstanding on Sept. 30, said it would use proceeds from  the sale to buy back up to one million shares. Burnham Pacific will pay a quarterly dividend of 25 cents a share, down from 36 cents.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones)</p>
        <p>COURT BLOCKS LOMAS FINANCIAL FROM SELLING ASSETS The Lomas Financial Corporation was denied court permission yesterday to sell substantially all of its remaining assets to First Nationwide Bank for $150 million. Still, Peter Walsh, a Federal Bankruptcy Court judge in Wilmington, Del., called his decision conditional and ordered the creditor committee to vote on the sale. Creditors are entitled to take the risk of shopping the company if  they believe they can get a higher offer, he said. The judge said creditors had  not been provided enough information about the proposed sale to First Nationwide to make an informed judgment. First Nationwide Bank of San Francisco, is a subsidiary of MacAndrews &amp; Forbes Group Inc., which is controlled by the investor Ronald O. Perelman.</p>
        <p>(Bloomberg Business News)</p>
        <p>INTEL ANNOUNCES PLANS FOR A CHIP FACTORY IN SHANGHAI The Intel Corporation said yesterday that it would build a semiconductor assembly and test plant in Shanghai. The computer chip maker, based in Santa Clara, Calif., said construction was scheduled to begin soon and should be completed by the end of 1997. It did not disclose how much the plant would cost. The plant will be the company's third in Asia and will employ about 900 people.  Intel also said it had signed an agreement with Shanghai officials to "preferentially recommend Intel Pentium processors" in future projects.</p>
        <p>(Dow Jones)</p>
        <p>COASTAL CORP., Houston, said it planned to divest most of its generic wholesale  gasoline business in the upper Midwest to concentrate its activities near its core refineries, terminals and pipelines.</p>
        <p>CASE CORP., Racine, Wis., which makes construction equipment, agreed to purchase Concord Inc. of Fargo, N.D., a privately held maker of air drills used in planting grain, for an undisclosed sum.</p>
        <p>SURGICAL CARE AFFILIATES INC., Nashville, a health care concern, agreed to buy Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corp.'s stake in Alaska Surgery Center. Terms were not disclosed.</p>
        <p>TII INDUSTRIES, Copiague, L.I., a telecommunication components manufacturer, said it would supply fiber optic network products for a Northern Telecom Ltd. project in Mexico.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
