<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief Seeks Charges in Police Beating</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRUTALITY AND HARASSMENT CHARGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSAULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GATES, DARYL F (POLICE CHIEF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, RODNEY GLEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDA123CF93BA35750C0A967958260" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief Seeks Charges in Police Beating</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chief of Police of Los Angeles said today that he would seek felony criminal charges against three officers seen beating a prone suspect, apparently not resisting arrest, in an amateur videotape that has stirred national revulsion.</p>
        <p>Calling the incident an aberration in a "well-disciplined department," Police Chief Daryl F. Gates said all 15 officers present at the beating late Sunday night would also face departmental charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chief of Police of Los Angeles said today that he would seek felony criminal charges against three officers seen beating a prone suspect, apparently not resisting arrest, in an amateur videotape that has stirred national revulsion.</p>
        <p>Calling the incident an aberration in a "well-disciplined department," Police Chief Daryl F. Gates said all 15 officers present at the beating late Sunday night would also face departmental charges.</p>
        <p>He singled out the supervising sergeant at the scene who stood by while the officers rained from 53 to 56 nightstick blows on the subdued suspect and kicked him at least seven times, what Chief Gates conceded at a news conference was "excessive force" in a making an arrest.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates said he did not seek criminal charges against the sergeant because he had not participated in the beating, apart from applying a shock from a stun gun, which he said was an accepted departmental procedure.  Defending the Department</p>
        <p>In his announcement, Chief Gates stoutly defended his department against charges that his officers regularly brutalized blacks and other minority members and defiantly rejected suggestions that he should resign.</p>
        <p>"We do not and have never allowed our officers to use excessive force," he said, adding that two officers had been killed in the last four months and five shot. "Suddenly the tables are turned by one incident, and, unfortunately, we are painting 8,300 additional officers with this broad brush."</p>
        <p>Today's action seemed unlikely to quiet the crescendo of calls for Chief Gates's resignation from political leaders who have charged he has failed to correct a pattern of police abuse.</p>
        <p>"I have absolutely no thoughts of resigning," Chief Gates said.</p>
        <p>His critics have included Mayor Tom Bradley, who met with his Police Commission, a five-member body that oversees the department but which has no authority to dismiss Chief Gates.</p>
        <p>At news conference at City Hall this evening, Mayor Bradley, a former police officer, demanded a "speedy bringing to justice of the guilty," adding "This city will not tolerate that kind of conduct by its police officers."</p>
        <p>He said the Police Commission would take a "comprehensive look" at the department's training and supervisory practices and at whether there were any patterns of racial discrimination in their behavior. He praised Mr. Gates for his action today, declining to renew his past criticism of the Chief.  Possible Assault Charges</p>
        <p>Chief Gates said that he would ask the District Attorney of Los Angeles County to bring criminal charges, probably including assault with a deadly weapon, against the three officers who could be identified in the videotape as administering the blows to Rodney Glen King, the 25-year-old suspect, after a chase on the Foothill Freeway in the northern part of the city.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates said the names of the three officers would not be released until the District Attorney had filed charges.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates was particularly critical of the sergeant because an explicit duty after a violent arrest is to prevent excited officers from inflicting unnecessary injury. He added that all other officers who did not intercede would be charged internally with neglect of duty.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for District Attorney Ira Reiner said today that prosecutors were investigating the incident and that charges could be brought against more officers than just the three cited by Chief Gates.</p>
        <p>The chief maintained race was not a factor in the beating. "We can turn up absolutely nothing except that the officers were white and the suspect black," he said.</p>
        <p>With that much, at least, Mr. King apparently agreed. "We are not seeking to make a racial issue out of this," said one of his lawyers, Robert Rentzer. "This is simply a violation of one human being's human rights. It is a matter of human dignity, not a matter of racial dignity at this time."</p>
        <p>He said Mr. King, an unemployed construction worker from Altadena who is on parole from a robbery conviction, was preparing to file a civil rights suit against the Police Department and had signed a criminal complaint against the men who beat him, at the request of the Police Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rentzer said Mr. King would undergo tests to determine the extent of his injuries, including examinations of his eyes, a fractured ankle, possible internal injuries, a possible broken nose, dizziness and memory loss. He added that Mr. King's wife, Carol, would file a separate civil suit.</p>
        <p>In defense of his officers, Chief Gates asserted that it was Mr. King who "created" the incident by speeding and evading arrest, adding that they suspected he was under the influence of alcohol or PCP, an illicit drug. The police report stated that Mr. King was driving at 115 miles an hour. Mr. Rentzer said tests were being conducted on the Hyundai sedan to determine whether it could have reached such a speed.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates said he believed that Mr. King behaved in a threatening way at the beginning of the tape but that once he was on the ground and restrained further blows were "inappropriate."</p>
        <p>Leaders of minority groups said the incident would have gone unnoticed had it not been videotaped by a man outside whose apartment the beating took place. The photographer, George Holliday, who lives in the San Fernando Valley, turned the tape over to a local independent television station, KTLA-TV, in Los Angeles, which gave it to the Cable News Network.</p>
        <p>Chief Gates praised Mr. Holliday today as a citizen who "decided to get involved" and publicly assured him that his wife's fears of retribution by police officers were unfounded. He also thanked KTLA and Mayor Bradley.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
