<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD8153CF93BA35750C0A967958260" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the War A8-11</p>
        <p>The U.S. does not expect initiatives to rise immediately from President Bush's call for Israel to give up occupied Arab lands in return for peace, but hopes to secure modest good-will gestures, officials said. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Most of Israel agrees that there has never been a more opportune time for Israel to make peace with its Arab neighbors. But Israel has no compromises to offer Syria, Jordan or the Palestinians. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the War A8-11</p>
        <p>The U.S. does not expect initiatives to rise immediately from President Bush's call for Israel to give up occupied Arab lands in return for peace, but hopes to secure modest good-will gestures, officials said. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Most of Israel agrees that there has never been a more opportune time for Israel to make peace with its Arab neighbors. But Israel has no compromises to offer Syria, Jordan or the Palestinians. A1</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Kuwaitis were released from Iraqi custody and crossed into Kuwait. Thousands of others arrived at the border to be told that they could not cross because they were not Kuwaiti citizens. A1</p>
        <p>Crown Prince says martial law in Kuwait could be extended A9</p>
        <p>Iraq acknowledged it faced a revolt but claimed victory in the war, saying President Bush's pronouncements on the Middle East showed that Baghdad had forced the U.S. to focus on the Arab-Israeli dispute. A8</p>
        <p>Most of the journalists who vanished while traveling toward Basra to cover civil unrest will be freed by Iraq along with Kuwaiti civilians who had been abducted by the Iraqis, officials of the Red Cross said. A9</p>
        <p>B-52 pilots and crews tell of high- altitude strikes on Iraq A9</p>
        <p>Families prepared for troops' return. "The people coming home tomorrow are going to get the hero's welcome that was denied those who came back from Vietnam," a soldier at Langley Air Force Base said. A10</p>
        <p>Troops will receive more than just a ticker tape parade A10</p>
        <p>House approves $15 billion for war and warns allies to pay too A11  International A2-7</p>
        <p>Albania's rulers imposed martial law in the country's largest port and barred public assembly in three other cities, including Tirana. A youth was reportedly killed as crowds stormed foreign embassies.  A2</p>
        <p>Moscow accused its domestic critics of fomenting civil disorder and foreigners of plotting against the referendum March 17 on protecting national unity from dismemberment by sovereignty-minded republics. A3 Witness in Mandela trial says he had to take part in killing A3</p>
        <p>India's leader accuses Ghandi of pushing country to brink A7</p>
        <p>The Thai military has eased fears by naming an interim Government of respected and experienced civilians, diplomats and businessmen. But Western diplomats say the junta's intentions are not entirely clear. A5</p>
        <p>Psychiko Journal: Learning about the Greeks in Greece A4  National A12-20</p>
        <p>White House Memo: President Bush is riding a wave, and while Republicans are dreaming up campaign commercials for 1992, Democrats are desperately trying to forget their early skepticism about the war. A1</p>
        <p>Americans are far less ebullient about the economy and other domestic concerns than about the war, a new poll has found. President Bush is still extraordinarily popular, but there are signs of vulnerability. A14</p>
        <p>Retail sales remain down in February as wariness persists D1</p>
        <p>Congress moves closer to approving $30 billion for S.&amp; L.'s D1</p>
        <p>Nineteen cities eligible for U.S. grants to fight infant mortality have been identified by Federal officials. But the cities will have to compete for the money, and only 10 of them will ultimately win grants. A12</p>
        <p>A new method of billing phone calls developed by long-distance companies calculates the length of a call to the second or the nearest six seconds. The method is only for businesses, not residential customers. A1</p>
        <p>A settlement in the Exxon case was blocked by a Federal judge. Alaskan Indian tribes sought the order, saying they had been locked out of negotiations to settle civil litigation from the Exxon Valdez oil spill. A12</p>
        <p>The Chief of Police of Los Angeles said he would seek felony charges against three officers seen beating a suspect in an amateur videotape. He called the incident an aberration in a "well-disciplined department." A12</p>
        <p>The National Institutes of Health needs to improve management of its AIDS research program to deal with a budget problem as the epidemic continues to spread, a two-year study recommeded. A20</p>
        <p>Senate panel approves Martinez as anti-drug director A16</p>
        <p>The cost of nursing home rules fuel a revolt in California A20</p>
        <p>Judge again orders Philadelphia to immunize youths A17  Regional B1-4</p>
        <p>The State Financial Control Board issued new warnings about New York City's handling of its long-term fiscal problems, saying Mayor Dinkins's $29 billion plan "actually disguises" the city's budget gap. A1</p>
        <p>Members of the City Council attacked Speaker Peter Vallone, accusing him of cronyism, demagogy and even dullness. The attacks were a response to his awarding of influential committee chairmanships. B1</p>
        <p>Archdiocese is expected to close some parochial schools B2</p>
        <p>Study blames dilapidation in schools on frugal city spending B3</p>
        <p>The latest teen-age fad is the beeper. Once a sign of doctors and drug dealers, beepers are popping up everywhere. While some adults disagree, teen-agers say they have practical uses in a crime-ridden city. A1</p>
        <p>The Daily News's unions must cut more than 800 jobs, said Robert Maxwell, the British publisher who wants to buy the paper. But the tone of the opening day of negotiations was reportedly encouraging. B1</p>
        <p>St. Patrick's Day parade refuses to allow homosexual group B3</p>
        <p>Park Aveune lawyer is indicted as a $3.5 million swindler B3</p>
        <p>A woman's odyssey through Housing Court (and she won) B3</p>
        <p>An emaciated 7-month-old baby is found dead in the Bronx B3</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. postponed service cuts on the Long Island Rail Road, just days before they were to take effect and one week after it was revealed that the authority had a $93 million surplus fund. B1</p>
        <p>Private clubs in Brooklyn Heights -- like the Rembrandt Club, Mrs. Field's Literary Society and the Ihpetonga Club -- continue to keep alive the traditions of the more genteel days of the Victorian era. B1</p>
        <p>Two groups begin campaign against Weicker's tax plan B2</p>
        <p>Lawmakers approve change to Florio's school-aid plan B2  Business Digest D1  Weekend</p>
        <p>Etiquette for gallerygoers C1</p>
        <p>Satire for a boring era C1</p>
        <p>The New York Flower Show C5</p>
        <p>Theater: "Road to Nirvana" C1</p>
        <p>On Stage, and Off C2</p>
        <p>Film: At the Movies C8</p>
        <p>Dance: Trisha Brown anniversaryC5</p>
        <p>Art: Selections from the 80's C26</p>
        <p>Outdoor sculpture C30</p>
        <p>Auctions C22</p>
        <p>Restaurants C20</p>
        <p>Word and Image: "An Awfully Big Adventure" C27  Law Page B5</p>
        <p>Depositions can be ordeal as well as a protection  Obituaries A22</p>
        <p>Gaylord A. Freeman Jr., led Chicago's First National Bank</p>
        <p>Katinka Loeser, writer Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Howe impressive A27</p>
        <p>Basketball: Villanova rallies past B.C.  A23</p>
        <p>Death of coach's wife overshadows game A23</p>
        <p>Column: Vecsey on odd ball parks A23</p>
        <p>Hockey: Rangers lose to Nordiques A23  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>EditorialsA28</p>
        <p>Fine, 100 days. But for what?</p>
        <p>Level with labor, and the city</p>
        <p>Hard passage in India</p>
        <p>Summary injustice</p>
        <p>Letters A28</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: The poet judge A29</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: Break the boycott A29</p>
        <p>Raymond Learsy: How to get oil to $10 a barrel A29</p>
        <p>Richard J. Margolis: Cost per life -- $22,000 A29</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
