<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Romp Smartly On; Will Nothing Stop the Bull?</title>
    <meta content="05STOX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="OUTLOOK '98: MARKETS &amp; INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's Stock Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB1730F936A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Romp Smartly On; Will Nothing Stop the Bull?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of American stock market in 1990's has been amazing, particularly in last three years, when investors in Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index saw their money more than double; much of outstanding performance came from demographics, as baby boom generation began investing for retirement; also important was that corporate earnings rose, with consistency and magnitude not seen in nearly half century; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 1990's, the performance of the American stock market has been nothing short of amazing, particularly in the last three years. Over that stretch, investors in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index have seen their money more than double. That had never happened before in so short a period.</p>
        <p>Much of that performance has come from demographics, as the baby boom reaches the age when it seems wise to invest for retirement and surveys an investment scene characterized by interest rates far lower than when the boomers were young and borrowing to buy homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 1990's, the performance of the American stock market has been nothing short of amazing, particularly in the last three years. Over that stretch, investors in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index have seen their money more than double. That had never happened before in so short a period.</p>
        <p>Much of that performance has come from demographics, as the baby boom reaches the age when it seems wise to invest for retirement and surveys an investment scene characterized by interest rates far lower than when the boomers were young and borrowing to buy homes.</p>
        <p>But the stock market's outstanding performance reflects more than demographic levitation. It has had an important fundamental support: Corporate earnings have also risen, with a consistency and a magnitude not seen in nearly half a century.</p>
        <p>To be sure, stock prices have also risen rapidly, leading some to question whether investors are overpaying when they buy stocks. And companies do not necessarily have to have earnings to be stock-market stars. The best performer of last year, excluding stocks that began the year at less than $5, showed a gain of more than 500 percent. It was an Internet company that has yet to show an annual profit. And its name aptly summed up the attitude among stock market investors: Yahoo. (Ranking second was another money-losing Internet company with an appropriate name for this market: Mindspring Enterprises.)</p>
        <p>Still, for most companies profits do count. And the very persistence of rising profits has helped to convince investors that it does not matter if you pay a bit much for a stock based on current conditions: better days and higher profits that are coming will more than offset that.</p>
        <p>For 1998, the biggest question mark on the bullish horizon may be whether confidence in earnings growth will still prove to be justified. While most Wall Street analysts think profits for companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 will rise for a seventh consecutive year -- which would also be a first -- there are some who see clouds on the horizon.</p>
        <p>It is a horizon that has remained remarkably clear for most of the 1990's. Corporate profits fell in 1991, reflecting the aftermath of a brief recession in 1990 and a slew of restructuring charges. But they rose in 1992 and every year thereafter. Standard &amp; Poor's estimates that profits on the S.&amp; P. 500 in 1997 were up 163 percent from the 1992 level.</p>
        <p>The only better performance over a six-year stretch came in the years 1945 through 1950, amid a postwar boom. Then profits more than doubled, but that was off a very low base that had been held down by wartime wage and price controls.</p>
        <p>The rise during this decade has come from a variety of forces that may be running out of steam. The widespread corporate reorganizations of the early 1990's cost jobs but made companies more efficient. That helped them to get a rising share of profits from exports. The threat of overseas competition helped to keep wage costs down, and the health care revolution stemmed the rise in employee benefit costs. One result was that corporate profits came to take an ever bigger slice of the revenue pie while workers got much less.</p>
        <p>Now, that may be changing. Wage-cost pressures seem to be rising, though the data are ambiguous. And while the pressure of low-cost imports, particularly from Asia, seems likely to keep price inflation in check, the tight labor market in this country could push wages up.</p>
        <p>As a result, companies might end up with higher costs from wages without an ability to pass on the costs to customers. That would mean lower earnings.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, interest rates are expected to remain low, providing little competition for investments. The yield on 30-year Treasury bonds fell below 6 percent late in 1997 and is likely to remain there.</p>
        <p>In 1997, the S.&amp; P. 500 rose 31 percent, for a total profit for holders of the stocks in the index of 33.4 percent, including reinvested dividends. That brought the three-year performance for the index, which dates back to 1928, to a stunning 125 percent, including reinvested dividends. The previous best performance for the index over a three-year stretch came in 1933-35, when the market was bouncing off Depression lows. In that period, investors made a 95 percent profit.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the S.&amp; P. 500 figure overstates how most investors did. The S.&amp; P. 500 outperformed most other indexes by a sizable margin last year in part because a lot of foreign money came into the United States market, fueled by worries about the crisis in Asia, and gravitated toward the internationally known companies that dominate the index. Still it was remarkable.</p>
        <p>To some, the current period is most reminiscent of the mid-1950's. Then, as now, inflation and interest rates were low. (Lower, in fact, than they have been during this three-year run.) And from 1954 through 1956, the S.&amp; P. 500 had a total return of 88 percent, assuming annual reinvestment of dividends. Until now, that had been the best postwar return for such a stretch.</p>
        <p>It is a comforting analogy. For while stock prices fell in 1957, as the country endured a brief recession, the slide was not a deep one. And in 1958 stock prices shot up again, with the total return on the S.&amp; P. 500 more than 40 percent.</p>
        <p>There are several similarities. During the 1950's run, as during the current one, a President was re-elected by a large majority. But the opposition party held on to control of both the House and the Senate as the President proved to have very short coattails. (Memo to Bill Clinton and Al Gore: At the mid-term election in 1958, the fact that the stock market was soaring did President Dwight D. Eisenhower's party little good as the opposition Democrats scored a landslide victory in Congressional elections. And two years later, Vice President Richard M. Nixon lost the Presidential election.)</p>
        <p>But before investors settle down for another comfortable period, they should note that there is one way in which the market does not resemble the 1950's. That is in volatility. The 1950's market was remarkably placid. Last year's gyrations reached a peak on Oct. 27, when the market plunged amid worldwide panic over the Asian turmoil. But there was plenty of volatility even before that. For the year, 32 percent of the trading days saw the S.&amp; P. 500 end the day up or down at least 1 percent from the previous day. That is an average of about three days every two weeks. That is more than double the volatility of 1996 and three times that of 1995.</p>
        <p>Another means of measuring volatility, known formally as the standard deviation of daily moves, shows just how widely spread out daily moves are. By that measure, 1997 was the fourth most volatile year of the last half century, trailing only 1987, 1982 and 1974. All those years saw violent reversals of the market trend. The fact that there was no such clear reversal this year could indicate that one is about to come.</p>
        <p>Or, the higher volatility could be reflecting changes in the way markets operate. In the current world of derivative securities and huge bets placed by institutions, higher volatility may endure until the market adjusts to new trading strategies.</p>
        <p>The day last fall when American stock markets were forced to close early because a wave of selling had sent prices plunging seems largely forgotten now. Unlike the 1987 market crash, that plunge, on Oct. 27, is barely reflected in mutual fund cash flow data. When professional investors got scared, individual investors saw an opportunity and stabilized the market.</p>
        <p>Such commitment by individuals, reflecting both demographics and a widespread conviction that stocks are now and always will be the best long-term investment, is the strongest thing the stock market has going for it in 1998. If that behavior persists, even widespread earnings disappointments might not be enough to slay the great bull of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK '98: MARKETS &amp; INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
