<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Species, Old Struggle</title>
    <meta content="29KAUF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DF123AF93AA15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Species, Old Struggle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on evolution of online businesses; venture capitalists and public markets alike are becoming skeptical of promises of fabulous future earnings and are tightening capital flow to e-retailers (Special Section, E-Commerce); drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A CENTURY from now, Internet archaeologists may look back at the last several years and liken them to an electronic Precambrian era: a time when new life exploded in spectacular abundance. But as in that prehistoric era, not all the creatures emerging from the fecund swamps are equally adapted for survival; there are crocodiles and then there are dodo birds.</p>
        <p>When the Net was still new and all potential (about six months ago), it seemed that practically everyone who had a half-baked idea or worse was starting a dot-com enterprise, raising a truckload of cash, going public and becoming a millionaire. So many prospered so easily because investors, both public and private, were willing to buy into companies with enormous losses on promises of great future returns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A CENTURY from now, Internet archaeologists may look back at the last several years and liken them to an electronic Precambrian era: a time when new life exploded in spectacular abundance. But as in that prehistoric era, not all the creatures emerging from the fecund swamps are equally adapted for survival; there are crocodiles and then there are dodo birds.</p>
        <p>When the Net was still new and all potential (about six months ago), it seemed that practically everyone who had a half-baked idea or worse was starting a dot-com enterprise, raising a truckload of cash, going public and becoming a millionaire. So many prospered so easily because investors, both public and private, were willing to buy into companies with enormous losses on promises of great future returns.</p>
        <p>This could not go on forever, and, in fact, since the new year it has been clear that the venture capitalists and the public markets alike are becoming skeptical of promises of fabulous future earnings and are starting to tighten the capital flow to e-retailers. There is still money flowing, but it is often going to ventures that facilitate commerce among businesses, a rather more stable proposition.</p>
        <p>The pull of real-world gravity has been widely felt. From service providers like Juno to community sites like iVillage, e-businesses have seen their stock prices sink from celestial levels. But the punishment has been particularly brutal to retailers that do business solely on the Internet. Not only do those merchants have to contend with an increasingly crowded field, but they also have to battle clicks-and-mortar retailers like Wal-mart.com and Macys.com, which were slow to enter the Internet game but are now wielding their well-established brand names like clubbed tails.</p>
        <p>In this tougher environment, the evolutionary winnowing should begin pretty quickly. Companies that cannot show a plausible way to stanch the outflow of cash are going to be very vulnerable very soon. ''Come April, we are going to be watching first-quarter results very closely,'' said Steve Westly, a vice president for business development at the profitable online auction site eBay, his voice purring with the contentment of a predator about to be well fed. ''We think after the news of the disappointing results gets out, there will be a lot of bargains out there,'' he said, for bigger companies looking to expand by acquiring smaller ones.</p>
        <p>Now that the gold-rush mentality has started to fade, and it is apparent that not every company with a dot-com in its name will strike the mother lode, serious players -- venture capitalists, stock analysts, company executives -- are beginning to evaluate survivability in a more systematic manner. Of the organisms that have crawled out of the primordial electronic muck, a rough consensus has emerged as to which types are eventually going to be profitable. Of course, evolution on the World Wide Web is happening so fast that generalizations get out of date quickly, and even dodo birds get lucky sometimes.</p>
        <p>Today, people who shop on the Web are used to getting bargains. Drugstore sites will sell, say, a large package of disposable diapers, a tube of toothpaste, vitamins and athlete's-foot powder, all for $3.50 (only a small exaggeration). Electronics sites will sell DVD players for $169.95 each, less than their cost, and then ship them free overnight. ''It's too good to be true,'' you say to yourself. And you're right!</p>
        <p>The first victims of tighter investment capital will be Web sites that have been selling goods at a loss or giving them away while they were, in effect, buying customers. Not long ago, building market share at any cost was the mantra of the Web, but the gratuitous cash-bleeding model is increasingly being viewed, to quote that famous, now out-of-business, New York retail innovator, Crazy Eddie, as ''Insaaannne!''</p>
        <p>The goal of most sites that lose money on products -- the most prominent example of which is Buy.com -- is to draw a huge customer base and sell those eyeballs (and data on their buying habits) to advertisers. Here is the problem with that model: most shoppers do care about price, but they have other concerns, like credit-card security, familiarity and reliability -- priorities that retailers overlook in their chase for advertising dollars rather than sales dollars.</p>
        <p>So far, it turns out that the number of people willing to give away their souls for bargain-priced goods is smaller than was anticipated -- and certainly smaller than the threshold for enticing advertisers. At the beginning of last year, Free-PC -- whose plan was to give away computers to customers willing to accept two permanent strips of company-controlled advertising space on either side of the computer screen -- was bragging that it would be bigger than Microsoft. But in November, Free-PC agreed to be acquired by another computer manufacturer in a tacit admission that its business plan had failed. ''We believed that to get the business model to work we needed at least one million users,'' the founder, Bill Gross, said at the time. ''At 10,000 a quarter, we couldn't get to one million fast enough.''</p>
        <p>There is another drawback to the below-cost model. It turns out that consumers who care only about price are gone the moment they smell a better deal. ''Price-loyalty people are the most fickle,'' said Ken Orton, the chief strategist at Cognitiative, an e-business consulting firm in San Francisco. ''They are antibrand loyal. They can't tell you where they bought their last toy or CD.''</p>
        <p>The upshot of such disloyalty is that a Web site that plans to make money on the size of its customer base has to spend money on advertising to achieve a big enough audience. ''They are in the business of media arbitrage,'' Mr. Orton said.</p>
        <p>Bred for the Web</p>
        <p>The best business to have on the Web, logically, is a business that cannot exist in the real world because such a venture faces none of the very real, very fierce competition being perpetuated by the clicks-and-mortar retailers.</p>
        <p>''The concepts that have the best chance of surviving,'' said Henry Blodgett, an Internet analyst with Merrill Lynch, ''are those whose content and services are not portered from traditional media and retailing, but are purely Internet or interactive services.''</p>
        <p>Companies that fit best into this slot are those that let consumers negotiate their own price, and the best of these are auctions. EBay, of course, has popularized the online auction model and is still the biggest operator of such a site. It used the Web's technology to bring together an audience that had previously been hopelessly fragmented by geography. Suddenly, a collector of 1940's soda bottles did not need to peruse every flea market on the Eastern Seaboard to find the perfect World War II Coke bottle; he just needed to search online.</p>
        <p>The beauty of being a middleman, from the site operator's point of view, is low overhead: no inventory, no shipping and primarily word-of-mouth advertising, in return for a cut of each transaction. Compare that with Amazon.com, which lost $720 million in 1999, largely by investing in marketing and very expensive infrastructure, like automated warehouses. Most online retailers, if they want to service their customers well, will have to do the same thing. But not eBay, which made $11 million in 1999. That is why its model is being duplicated widely. Now Yahoo does auctions. Amazon does auctions. Ubid does auctions. And so will anyone else with half a brain. Allowing customers to sell to one another is a path to easy money.</p>
        <p>The real question now is whether there is another alternative-pricing model that makes as much sense.</p>
        <p>Paul Allen, a co-founder of Microsoft, has put money into finding out. He is an investor in the two leading examples of such models: Priceline.com and Mercata.</p>
        <p>Priceline is the best-known actor in the reverse-auction business, where the consumer names a price and sellers bid to meet it. To keep customers happy, the company used to make up the difference (within reason) between what buyers bid and sellers will accept. That translated into a $1 billion loss last year (ouch!) and a stock price that has gyrated between $160 and the $50's.</p>
        <p>Mercata's plan is to allow consumers who want to buy the same item to group together and negotiate a price from a seller: the idea is that the bigger the sale, the lower the price. Despite television ads comparing this power-buying concept to having sex, Mercata has not aroused enough naturally existing passions to bargain as much as eBay and other auctions do. But sometimes it takes a while for kinkier practices to catch on.</p>
        <p>Danger in the Niches</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, entrepreneurs rushed to set up stores that they inevitably promised would be the Amazon.com of fill-in-the-blank: pet stuff, watches, beauty products, baby gear, furniture, pig entrails (O.K., that's made up), wine, ad infinitum. Some of these stores are focusing on a startlingly narrow array of merchandise. FogDog.com sells sportswear, but Chipshot.com just sells golf clothes and equipment.</p>
        <p>Word on the street is that the next big set of goners is a majority of the niche retailers. That is because there are too many in each category and many are in businesses where profit margins are too thin to make sense. ''As we approach the third or fourth inning,'' said James W. Breyer, a managing partner of Accel Partners, the Palo Alto, Calif., venture capital firm, e-businesses without high gross-profit margins will not succeed. ''One has to be highly suspect of the pets portals that are about to go public,'' he said. ''I would run for the hills.''</p>
        <p>Age Matters</p>
        <p>But it is not just the niche retailers who look vulnerable. It is all the new Internet retailers that have no connection to or history in the physical world. The big lesson from the most recent Christmas shopping season is that a long-established brand name is an unmatchable asset. To make their names known, dozens of dot-coms spent millions of dollars each to advertise on programs like ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Monday Night Football.'' The outcome? The start-ups' cost per customer was stratospheric, while Old World retailers new to the medium walked away with the majority of customers.</p>
        <p>The 50 most-visited Web sites during Christmas read like a who's who of land retailing. JCPenney.com, Barnesandnoble.com, Gap.com, Wal-Mart.com and VictoriasSecret.com were among the clicks-and-mortar merchants who made the grade. With few exceptions, the dot-coms that thrived were already fixtures -- including eBay, Amazon and CDnow.</p>
        <p>No wonder that in Silicon Valley, the hottest Web sites for investing are hybrids of the new and old. Bluelight.com, for example, is a joint venture of Kmart, Yahoo and venture capitalists. The independent company, which will sell Kmart merchandise and more, will make use of the chain's vast buying power and giant customer base to lower its costs.</p>
        <p>Passing along those savings to shoppers may be critical to sales volume. Steve Jurvetson, a managing partner of Draper, Fisher Jurvetson, a venture capital firm, envisions a future where consumers will shop through an electronic wallet service -- a place where you keep credit-card information that follows you as you browse the shelves at Amazon.com and Wal-Mart.com. Such a service would allow one-click shopping anywhere on the Web, eliminating the time-consuming step of filling out forms on the first visit to each e-store. But such a service could also be used to do comparison shopping by offering the same product from a competing merchant at a lower price.</p>
        <p>For obvious reasons, retailers would not want to cooperate with such a service. But if  consumer demand forced them to comply, only merchants selling brands they completely control would be safe from price-cutting wars. If, for example, a customer wants Nike sneakers, and Nike sneakers can only be purchased at FogDog.com, no amount of competitive comparison would have an effect.</p>
        <p>Such an e-tailing plan is at least five years off, Mr. Jurvetson said. And one never knows what fierce creature might spring from the fertile Web-based loam and change the rules all over again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
