<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gephardt Courts the Technology Industry</title>
    <meta content="29GEPH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gephardt, Richard A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Richard A Gephardt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DF173CF93AA15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gephardt Courts the Technology Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Richard S Gephardt, House Democratic leader, courts high-technology community by embracing pieces of its legislative wish list, but he glosses over the issue of establishing permanent, normal trade relations with China, the issue that industry executives and lobbyists care most about this year and that Republicans are trying to wield against Democrats; says Democrats are working to draw up an alternative China bill that a majority of party in House could support without alienating Republicans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the political loyalties of the high-technology community still up for grabs, Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House Democratic leader, intensified his courtship of the industry today by embracing pieces of its legislative wish list.</p>
        <p>But, in his first major policy address on high-technology issues, Mr. Gephardt, of Missouri, glossed over the issue that industry executives and lobbyists care most about this year and that could most hurt Democrats: establishing permanent, normal trade relations with China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the political loyalties of the high-technology community still up for grabs, Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House Democratic leader, intensified his courtship of the industry today by embracing pieces of its legislative wish list.</p>
        <p>But, in his first major policy address on high-technology issues, Mr. Gephardt, of Missouri, glossed over the issue that industry executives and lobbyists care most about this year and that could most hurt Democrats: establishing permanent, normal trade relations with China.</p>
        <p>A number of Democrats oppose granting China normal trade relations, despite President Clinton's strong backing, because of labor union opposition to the agreement and the country's poor human rights record. Mr. Gephardt and other Democratic leaders have said they would vote against a China bill that did not address concerns over the environment, workers' rights and human rights.</p>
        <p>''The most important vote of this decade is going to be China because it clearly translates into investment, new markets, jobs,'' said Dave McCurdy, a former House Democrat who is the president of the Electronic Industries Alliance, a major high-technology trade group. ''The vote on China is going to be a dividing line. For those who support China, the business community has an obligation to recognize that vote and support the people who vote for it.''</p>
        <p>House Republican leaders, all of whom support the China deal, are already trying to gin-up support among high-technology industry executives by labeling Democrats as foes of free trade.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid he still doesn't get it,'' Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the House majority leader, said about Mr. Gephardt. ''In his speech today, he was silent on trade.''</p>
        <p>''We'll all be watching to see just how tech-friendly this new Dick Gephardt is,'' Mr. Armey said, adding that Mr. Gephardt voted with the industry only 50 percent of the time last year, according to figures compiled by the Information Technology Industry Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt said Democrats were working to draw up an alternative China bill that a majority of the party in the House could support without alienating Republicans. And he pointed out, after his speech, that the China vote was problematic for both parties, since several Republicans also oppose the agreement. .</p>
        <p>''If both parties are split, it has interacting political consequences in both parties,'' Mr. Gephardt said. ''So you've got to stop worrying about the politics and just try to figure out the issue and do what you think is right.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gephardt tiptoed around trade in his speech today, he put forward an ambitious agenda on a roster of other issues that high-technology companies hold dear. And he portrayed himself, not as a traditional, old-style Democrat, a label many apply to Mr. Gephardt, but as a lawmaker who understood the universal principles of the technology revolution and could apply them if he were to become the next speaker of the House.</p>
        <p>In this vein, Mr. Gephardt underscored his own decision to co-sponsor a bill to expand the number of work visas for immigrants with high-technology skills, legislation the labor unions oppose and Mr. Gephardt voted against last time around.</p>
        <p>''It is sheer hubris to claim that one party or the other in America is the technology party,'' he told the group of assembled Northern Virginia high-technology representatives. ''The government is not the leader -- nor should it be. But the government, by pursuing wise, prudent politics has the ability to help keep this technology revolution on track.''</p>
        <p>In his speech, the Democratic leader endorsed several initiatives, many of them originally pushed by Republicans. He called for a three-year sales tax moratorium on the Internet, until a final solution could be agreed upon. The Internet industry would like to see no taxes on electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt also endorsed the elimination of certain taxes, including the telecommunications excise tax and taxes on Internet access and transmission. And he called for a permanent tax credit on high-technology research and development.</p>
        <p>For months now, Mr. Gephardt, prodded by a group of technology friendly moderate Democrats who call themselves New Democrats, has been working to solidify his relationship with high-technology executives and embrace many of the issues important to them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt has said he would not lobby House Democrats to vote against the China bill, which he has done on other trade bills. His No. 2, Representative David E. Bonior of Michigan, has taken on that task.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is China,'' Representative James P. Moran, Democrat of Virginia, said, ''and I think Dick is taking the Democratic caucus in that direction.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
