<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southern Water of Britain Gets a $2.35 Billion Offer</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED KINGDOM</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN WATER PLC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCOTTISH POWER PLC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN ELECTRICITY PLC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4DF1E39F93AA15756C0A960958260" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southern Water of Britain Gets a $2.35 Billion Offer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, May 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another company in Britain's rapidly consolidating utility industry is in play.</p>
        <p>Scottish Power P.L.C. said today that it had offered L1.56 billion, or $2.35  billion, to buy Southern Water P.L.C., while a second electricity company, Southern Electricity P.L.C., said it was holding talks with Southern Water aimed at reaching a takeover accord.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another company in Britain's rapidly consolidating utility industry is in play.</p>
        <p>Scottish Power P.L.C. said today that it had offered L1.56 billion, or $2.35  billion, to buy Southern Water P.L.C., while a second electricity company, Southern Electricity P.L.C., said it was holding talks with Southern Water aimed at reaching a takeover accord.</p>
        <p>An acquisition of Southern Water would be the 10th takeover of a British utility in the last 18 months. Eight of Britain's 12 power distribution companies have been acquired or have received takeover offers.</p>
        <p>If Scottish Power's bid succeeds, the company will have interests in the four major utility sectors: electricity, water, natural gas and telecommunications. Less than a year ago, Scottish Power bought Manweb P.L.C., a regional electricity distributor in northwestern England.</p>
        <p>The consolidation in the electricity and water sectors has been brought about by deregulation. By 1998, 23 million electricity customers and 19 million natural gas consumers in England and Wales will be able to choose their suppliers.</p>
        <p>"We are heading toward fewer, larger more highly geared public utility companies," said David Campbell, an analyst at Greig Middleton &amp; Company. "Scottish Power has staked its claim to be at the forefront." Gearing refers to  a company's debt load relative to equity.</p>
        <p>Scottish Power's offer of cash and stock values each Southern Water share at  L9.75, or $14.75, based on Friday's closing stock prices. (The London Stock Exchange was closed Monday for a holiday.)</p>
        <p>In trading today, Southern Water rose L2.60, or 38 percent, to L9.41. Shares  of other water companies also rose sharply.</p>
        <p>Scottish Power shares fell 17 pence, or 5.1 percent, to L3.19. Southern Electric declined 26 pence, to L7.26.</p>
        <p>"The price is pretty generous, frankly," Nigel Hawkins, an analyst at Yamaichi International, said of Scottish Power's offer.</p>
        <p>Scottish Power said it was "actively seeking a recommendation" from Southern  Water's board that shareholders accept the takeover offer. Southern Water said it was advising its shareholders to take no action.</p>
        <p>Amid the industry consolidation, there have been only two mergers of water and electricity companies thus far: North West Water P.L.C. acquired Norweb P.L.C., and Welsh Water P.L.C. bought South Wales Electricity P.L.C.</p>
        <p>Both water companies said they could achieve large cost savings by providing  several services to the same customers and that they would also benefit from economies of scale.</p>
        <p>Charles Berry, director of strategy at Scottish Power, said: "What we see looking forward to 1998 is that the most successful companies must provide the full range of services."</p>
        <p>However, Marshall Whiting, an analyst at SGST Securities, questioned the ease with which Scottish Power would be able to woo customers away from current suppliers.</p>
        <p>Southern Water has 1.8 million customers in southern England. The electricity in the region is provided by Southern Electricity and Seeboard P.L.C., a subsidiary of the Central and South West Corporation of Dallas.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
