<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revisiting the Issue of Crime, Dole Offers List of Remedies</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GUN CONTROL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIREARMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEPHANOPOULOS, GEORGE ROBERT DOLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDF1E39F93AA15756C0A960958260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revisiting the Issue of Crime, Dole Offers List of Remedies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q;</byline>
      <dateline>AURORA, Colo., May 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labeling the current era "the age of violence" without guilt or remorse, Bob  Dole returned today to the subject of crime, portraying himself as tougher than  President Clinton and calling for a constitutional amendment to protect victims' rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Labeling the current era "the age of violence" without guilt or remorse, Bob  Dole returned today to the subject of crime, portraying himself as tougher than  President Clinton and calling for a constitutional amendment to protect victims' rights.</p>
        <p>Speaking in a downpour to about 50 people outside the municipal justice center of this suburb of Denver, Mr. Dole, the presumptive Republican Presidential nominee, said, "It is a shameful national disgrace that nightfall has become synonymous with fear for so many of America's women."</p>
        <p>He offered proposals that he said would make all Americans safer: end parole for violent offenders, build more prisons, periodically test all prisoners for drug use and have anyone charged with a sexual assault tested for the AIDS virus.</p>
        <p>Declaring that the Federal laws against child pornography were too lenient, he proposed minimum sentences: 10 years for a first offense, 15 years for the second offense and life in prison for the third. His proposals are so tough, he  said, that "child pornography will end in a Dole Administration."</p>
        <p>In this, his third speech on the criminal justice system in two months, Mr. Dole was at his most specific about his own proposals. His campaign aides believe that crime is part of a package of issues that can help define Mr. Dole  as tough and conservative while portraying Mr. Clinton as weak and liberal.</p>
        <p>George Stephanopoulos, an adviser to Mr. Clinton, said Mr. Dole was talking tough on crime but in fact had done little to prevent it by voting against the bill to require a waiting period before a handgun can be bought and by opposing  the ban on the sale and manufacture of 19 types of assault weapons.</p>
        <p>In a speech warning of random murderers, drive-by shooters, serial killers and mail bombers, Mr. Dole also roped in an unlikely suspect: one of President Clinton's political advisers, Dick Morris.</p>
        <p>"One of the President's top political advisers is also helping an accused rapist beat the rap," Mr. Dole said, without mentioning Mr. Morris by name. "The same P.R. consultant who has been helping Bill Clinton pose as a crime fighter has been moonlighting for an accused rapist in Connecticut, advising the rapist's legal team on techniques for selecting an easy-going jury."</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris was hired last year to conduct a poll for the legal team defending Alex Kelly, who is accused of raping two teen-age girls in 1986 and then, while  out on bail awaiting trial, fleeing the country for eight years.</p>
        <p>In a statement released recently by the Clinton campaign, Mr. Morris said, "My role was that of a disinterested researcher with expertise in measuring public opinion." The purpose of the poll, he said, was to determine the effect of pretrial publicity on the client's ability to get a fair trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, returning to the theme of an earlier speech criticizing Mr. Clinton for appointing liberal judges, said today: "The truth is that if Bill Clinton had done more to fight crime, if he'd appointed people serious about fighting crime, he wouldn't need a high-priced P.R. man to help him with the issue."</p>
        <p>At that moment, someone finally arrived with an umbrella to hold over the already wet Mr. Dole, who was about a third of the way into his speech. "Oh, it  stopped raining," he noted, then continued:</p>
        <p>"The single most important thing a President can do to fight crime is put crime fighters in our courtrooms -- both on the bench and at the prosecutor's desk. And when I am President, that is exactly what I will do."</p>
        <p>He also took Mr. Clinton's rapid response team to task for plying reporters with what he said was misinformation. In an anti-crime speech given in Omaha earlier this month, Mr. Dole accused Mr. Clinton of putting only "a fraction" of his proposed 100,000 police officers on the streets. The White House said 43,000 police officers would be "on the street and funded" the next week, but a few days later, Attorney General Janet Reno said the number was 17,000.</p>
        <p>"That's the way it goes with this Administration," Mr. Dole said. "This is another reason I'm running for President. Every country ought to have one, and I'm going to be your President."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephanopoulos said today that 43,000 police had been financed, 17,000 were on the street, and that all 100,000 were financed in the budget that Mr. Clinton recently signed, "despite Dole's opposition" to the anti-crime bill that provided the police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole has repeatedly portrayed himself as a friend of victims and Mr. Clinton as a friend to criminals, and he tried to further that image today by proposing a constitutional amendment that would give victims "some basic rights."</p>
        <p>Those, he said, should include "the right to appear and stay informed of proceedings involving their victimizers."</p>
        <p>Noting that 20 states already had state constitutional amendments protecting  victims' rights, he added, "Let's extend those rights to every crime victim in America."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Dole Chooses Nixon Aide</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, May 28 (AP) -- Intensifying his search for a running mate, Mr. Dole has asked Robert Ellsworth, a former diplomat in the Nixon Administration and a longtime friend from Kansas, to oversee the initial selection process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellsworth, a former House member, is "someone I know and trust" who "won't talk to the media," Mr. Dole told reporters during a campaign stop today  in Colorado.</p>
        <p>Dole aides said the search for a Vice-Presidential nominee remained wide open. Mr. Dole is known to want a broad search.</p>
        <p>"What I asked Ellsworth to do," Mr. Dole said today, "is just sort of put the process together, get different records on everybody. I told them also, that when the time came, I wanted to look outside of politics. Let's take a look at the country."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
