<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spring in His Step, Rodriguez Forgets Winter Squalls</title>
    <meta content="21yanks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/21/sports/baseball/21yanks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1741366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED9113EF932A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spring in His Step, Rodriguez Forgets Winter Squalls</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spring in His Step, Rodriguez Forgets Winter Squalls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Feb. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees infielder Alex Rodriguez reports to spring training; hpoto (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The real drama behind Alex Rodriguez's ponderous decision on the World Baseball Classic played out at his home in December.</p>
        <p>In one corner, representing her native United States, was Rodriguez's wife, Cynthia. In the other, representing her native Dominican Republic, was Lourdes Navarro, his mother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The real drama behind Alex Rodriguez's decision on the World Baseball Classic played out at his home between his mother and his wife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The real drama behind Alex Rodriguez's ponderous decision on the World Baseball Classic played out at his home in December.</p>
        <p>In one corner, representing her native United States, was Rodriguez's wife, Cynthia. In the other, representing her native Dominican Republic, was Lourdes Navarro, his mother.</p>
        <p>As the husband and son in the middle of the tussle, Rodriguez, the Yankees' third baseman, ducked for cover.</p>
        <p>''I kept going to the bathroom,'' he said Monday after arriving at Legends Field. ''You never want to get your mother and your wife going back and forth. I think my wife probably won that. And all of us that are married know that was probably a good choice.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez was buoyant Monday, bouncing around the clubhouse before 9 a.m. with hugs and backslaps and smiles. He will stay with the Yankees until March 2, when he will report to Arizona to train with the United States team, which also includes his teammates Derek Jeter and Johnny Damon.</p>
        <p>It took Rodriguez months to arrive at his decision. He was born in the United States but was eligible to play for the Dominican Republic because his parents were born there.</p>
        <p>Last July, Rodriguez pledged his loyalty to the Dominican team. In December, he announced he would not play at all. A month later, he decided to play for the United States.</p>
        <p>In the weeks between his withdrawal and his reversal, Rodriguez said he grew agitated at reports that he would change his mind, believing those stories were coming from the commissioner's office or the players union as a way of pressuring him into playing.</p>
        <p>''All that garbage in between was Major League Baseball, and I blame them for that,'' Rodriguez said. ''I don't know who was leaking what, but I spoke once, I disappeared and I spoke again. So all those things back and forth, I would think that was ridiculous, too.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez's indecision sparked criticism from Chicago White Sox Manager Ozzie Guillen, who called him a hypocrite in last week's issue of Sports Illustrated. Rodriguez said he would speak with Guillen if he called, but he said it was not necessary because Guillen retracted his comments. ''The apology has already been accepted,'' Rodriguez said.</p>
        <p>As he pondered his decision this winter, Rodriguez spent two hours on a conference call with Commissioner Bud Selig and Gene Orza, the chief operating officer of the union. They stressed to Rodriguez how much they wanted him to play. They left it to him to choose which country.</p>
        <p>''We felt it was very important to have Alex play,'' said Pat Courtney, a spokesman for Selig. ''We think that way about All-Star players, and Alex is one of the best. Everybody wanted him to play, and we're glad he's playing.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez said he recognized what baseball had given him, and joked that he chose the United States because of how much he paid in taxes. His main concern with playing, he said, was how it would disrupt his preparation for the season.</p>
        <p>''I'm a crazy man when it comes to my routines,'' Rodriguez said. ''I'm a little panicky about the situation.''</p>
        <p>Some players have declined to participate, including Yankees left fielder Hideki Matsui, who worked out Monday at the minor league complex. With only a few days of training, he said, he doubted he would have been ready to play for Japan, which will feature Ichiro Suzuki of the Seattle Mariners. He also said he wanted to concentrate on playing for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Asked if his popularity in Japan has waned, Matsui, through an interpreter, said: ''It's very possible. But it can't be helped. If my popularity goes down, it goes down. It's beyond my control.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez said his own image was starting to turn. Fans have been more supportive than they were after the 2004 postseason collapse against Boston, even though he went 2 for 15 in last fall's first-round playoff loss to the Angels. That performance overshadowed a regular season that earned him his second Most Valuable Player award.</p>
        <p>''It was very miserable,'' Rodriguez said. ''When you play as miserable as I did in the most important five games of the year, it kind of fuels you going into the year. It fuels you tremendously. I do feel my career will not be complete without a championship.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez is learning to brush off his critics. At this time last year, he was fending off ridicule from some Red Sox players, who objected to what they thought was his bragging about workouts. ''I didn't do anything this year,'' Rodriguez said, laughing. ''I just went to the beach every day.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, who caused a controversy last October and November after playing in poker clubs, also made sure to joke about it. Referring to the Yankees, he said: ''To use a poker term, we're all in. This is the most urgent we've been. It's going to be exciting.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams worked out at Legends Field for the first time this spring. With Johnny Damon replacing him in center field, Williams will play this spring in left and in right field. He has not played defense at any position except center since Aug. 6, 1992, when he played right in a game against Boston. ''I'll rely on my athletic ability to make the transition,'' Williams said. ''It will be a challenge. It won't be easy, but I don't think it will be impossible, either.'' The Yankees gave a tryout to Mike Porzio, a left-hander who pitched for Colorado and the White Sox from 1999 to 2003.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
