<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2nd Russian Paper Shut in Cartoon Furor</title>
    <meta content="21russia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/21/international/europe/21russia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1741355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartoons and Cartoonists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1D9113EF932A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2nd Russian Paper Shut in Cartoon Furor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2nd Russian Paper Shut in Cartoon Furor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The owner of a small Russian weekly that printed a composite of the Danish cartoons depicting the Prophet Muhammad said Monday that he would close the newspaper. His was the second newspaper to close in Russia in the wake of international protests over the cartoons.</p>
        <p>The newspaper, Our Region, based in Vologda, north of Moscow, which printed its illustration last Wednesday, was the first in Russia to publish, at least in part, the Danish cartoons. The publication prompted criticism from public officials, an apology from the local governor and a criminal investigation into the paper's activity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Also, the death toll in violence in Nigeria reached 24 and Pope Benedict XVI urged respect for religious symbols.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The owner of a small Russian weekly that printed a composite of the Danish cartoons depicting the Prophet Muhammad said Monday that he would close the newspaper. His was the second newspaper to close in Russia in the wake of international protests over the cartoons.</p>
        <p>The newspaper, Our Region, based in Vologda, north of Moscow, which printed its illustration last Wednesday, was the first in Russia to publish, at least in part, the Danish cartoons. The publication prompted criticism from public officials, an apology from the local governor and a criminal investigation into the paper's activity.</p>
        <p>The owner, Mikhail M. Smirnov, said he decided on his own to close the newspaper on Friday, even as the prosecutor general's office announced it would bring criminal charges against the paper's editor, Anna V. Smirnova.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smirnova, who is also the owner's wife, faces charges of inciting religious animosity, a crime punishable by a maximum sentence of two to four years in prison.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smirnov's decision followed one by Volgograd, in central Russia, to close its official newspaper after it printed a different illustration that included Muhammad, along with Moses, Jesus and Buddha. The cases reflected the sensitivity by Russian officials to any Islamic backlash and served as a measure of the limits of expression in a country where the media often endure government pressure, if not outright censorship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smirnov, in a telephone interview, apologized for the decision to print a version of the Danish cartoons. He added that the article with the illustration, which included commentary by religious and human rights leaders, was not intended to provoke anti-Islamic sentiments.</p>
        <p>''My concern was about the people who worked at the newspaper, so that in the future neither the newspaper nor these people could be accused of fanning up inter-religious conflict,'' he said of his decision to shut the paper down.</p>
        <p>The newspaper, part of a larger media company called Severinform, has a staff of three and a circulation of roughly 4,000.</p>
        <p>He called the criminal investigation ''absolutely disproportional.''</p>
        <p>Aleksei K. Simonov, the president of the Glasnost Defense Foundation in Moscow, said the two cases would lead to still more self-censorship. He said the law on inciting religious or ethnic hatred was so broadly interpreted that any discussion of religion risked investigation.</p>
        <p>''You start to think what might happen,'' he said. ''Think of Chekhov. His works are full of funny stories about priests.''</p>
        <p>Death Toll in Nigeria Reaches 24</p>
        <p>LAGOS, Nigeria, Feb. 20 (Agence France-Presse) -- The death toll in weekend violence in Nigeria over the publication of cartoons depicting the Prophet Muhammad has risen to 24, the Red Cross said Monday, with 230 people wounded.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one people died in Maiduguri, in the north, and three in Katsina, said the Red Cross officer in charge of disaster management, Adronicus Adeyemo.</p>
        <p>Protesters in Maiduguri turned on the Christian minority, burning churches and shops, and troops and police officers were deployed to restore order.</p>
        <p>Most of the victims in Maiduguri are believed to be Christians because they were attacked in churches, the Red Cross official said. A Roman Catholic priest was among those killed. Authorities in the region have imposed a curfew.</p>
        <p>Nigeria's 130 million people are divided roughly equally between Muslims and Christians of a variety of sects and denominations. Northern Nigeria is overwhelmingly Muslim, but major cities have significant Christian minorities.</p>
        <p>Pope Urges Respect for Symbols  (By The New York Times)</p>
        <p>VATICAN CITY, Feb. 20 -- Pope Benedict XVI said Monday that it was ''vital and urgent'' that religion and religious symbols be respected, in clear comments on the controversy over cartoons of the Prophet Muhammad that have ignited riots around the Muslim world.</p>
        <p>The pope said, ''Intolerance and violence can never be justified as a response to any offense, because it is a response that is incompatible with the sacred principles of religion.''</p>
        <p>The pope made his comments in a speech as the new Moroccan ambassador to the Holy See presented his credentials.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
