<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elusive Victories in Iraq; Hussein's Defiance of Demands by U.N. Leaves Allies Wondering How to Prevail</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICAL WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SECURITY COUNCIL (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1139F936A15754C0A964958260" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elusive Victories in Iraq; Hussein's Defiance of Demands by U.N. Leaves Allies Wondering How to Prevail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the flight from Baghdad today of a number of United Nations inspectors, President Saddam Hussein of Iraq has demonstrated to his people that he refused to blink when George Bush and the United Nations sought to face him down in the parking lot outside Iraq's Agriculture Ministry.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi leader's victory may be short lived, but the definition of any new and impending allied "victory" over Mr. Hussein has also become elusive 18 months after the end of the Persian Gulf war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the flight from Baghdad today of a number of United Nations inspectors, President Saddam Hussein of Iraq has demonstrated to his people that he refused to blink when George Bush and the United Nations sought to face him down in the parking lot outside Iraq's Agriculture Ministry.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi leader's victory may be short lived, but the definition of any new and impending allied "victory" over Mr. Hussein has also become elusive 18 months after the end of the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>President Bush, gathering his senior advisers at Camp David this weekend, may seek to humble the Iraqi dictator with a military strike in the days ahead and, of course, there is still time for Mr. Hussein to back down, with the "very positive" response that the Iraqi delegate to the United Nations spoke of today.</p>
        <p>But whatever happens next, Mr. Hussein seems to have surprised the United States and its allies by presenting them with the most brazenly confrontational strategy he has fielded since the war. The fact that it comes a month after a failed coup attempt in Baghdad may reflect the desperation of Mr. Hussein's position, but it also may reflect his strength, his determination to survive, and all that might imply for President Bush's political fortunes this year.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi leader's belligerence this summer across a broad front, from threatening demonstrations against the United Nations' presence in Iraq to Iraqi Air Force strikes on Shiite Muslims in Southern Iraq, has sent President Bush scrambling to come up with a response that is militarily effective and politically safe.</p>
        <p>Armed with an endorsement for any United Nations-sponsored action in Iraq from the Democratic Presidential candidate, Bill Clinton, Mr. Bush's actions may seem to have been politically inoculated. But as President Jimmy Carter learned from his failed 1980 effort to free American hostages in Iran, political unity in a foreign policy crisis is transitory and leads eventually to harsher judgments about who won and who lost.</p>
        <p>Just as his prewar policy of support for President Hussein is being dissected by Democratic investigators in Congress, Mr. Bush's actions in the current crisis will be scrubbed with even greater intensity in a political season where there is virtually no margin for error by Mr. Bush. Another failure can only add to the image of albatross that Iraq policy has earned in this Administration.</p>
        <p>Already, there are questions.</p>
        <p>If the Administration understood that Mr. Hussein was taking a bolder and more confrontational course, why did it agree to send a United Nations inspection team to seize a sensitive archive of the Iraqi ballistic missile program without having a plan to deal with a standoff that could have been predicted?</p>
        <p>And, why was there little or no planning during the 17 days the inspectors camped in the parking lot of the ministry, facing increasingly threatening demonstrations?</p>
        <p>The Administration seemed unprepared to galvanize the United Nations into a quick consensus on how to react, even though there had been a series of previous and similar confrontations.  Military Moves Foreshowed</p>
        <p>Most frustrating for Mr. Bush, as the standoff developed this week, none of the military options he had been ordering up since last winter seemed adequate to the task of backing Mr. Hussein down. In the end, the critical archive of documents, if it existed as suspected in the Agriculture Ministry, has likely been removed.</p>
        <p>During the week, many officials working on Iraq policy were complaining that they had no attractive options and were getting little guidance from the top. That appears to have changed on Thursday, when Mr. Bush summoned Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Gen. Colin L. Powell, Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, to the White House for an unscheduled meeting on Iraq options, after which Administration officials said they were discussing a plan to issue an ultimatum to Baghdad.</p>
        <p>But an ultimatum demanding access to the Agriculture Ministry was quickly overtaken by the greater demand to confront Mr. Hussein's new attacks against Shiites and the broader agenda of refusal to comply with the terms of the United Nations cease-fire resolution.</p>
        <p>Therefore the breadth of any ultimatum that emerges from this weekend's councils will foreshadow the type of military action contemplated and will dictate the timing of any deadline, which must be linked to the time required to prepare for an attack.</p>
        <p>General Powell is known for insisting on having a clear military objective and bringing to battle the force necessary to win decisively and handle all contingencies. Mr. Bush has not publicly articulated his definition of victory beyond stating a firm determination that the terms of the United Nations cease-fire and other resolutions on Iraq must be obeyed.</p>
        <p>To many, the simplicity of the task was ordering up cruise missiles and bombers against an array of designated targets, but military planners were having to deal with the unknowns of Mr. Hussein's air-defense network, his Scud missile reserves, which once again could be loosed against Israel and Saudi Arabia, raising the question of Israel's neutrality in any new attack, and any hidden chemical-weapons stockpiles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will also have to contend with the prospect of American casualties in any raids against Iraq as well as the prospect of prisoners of war being paraded once again onto Iraqi television. Mr. Hussein most certainly is betting that those anxieties will play to his advantage in the war of nerves with Washington.</p>
        <p>In September, in a private breakfast with Mr. Bush during the first parking-lot confrontation involving United Nations inspectors, General Powell told the President that Mr. Hussein would continue to try to "frustrate" American policy toward Iraq and that Washington should develop a strategy to "frustrate" Mr. Hussein's attempt to hold on to power, according to a Pentagon official.</p>
        <p>After months of secret contingency planning, including a C.I.A. campaign to incite and, perhaps support, a successful military coup in Iraq, Mr. Hussein has proved more adept at setting the agenda and picking the venue for confrontation, though he is far from secure.</p>
        <p>If the bombs begin falling across Iraq in coming days, Mr. Bush will certainly contend that he and America's allies have reaffirmed an important principle about the role of the United Nations and the sanctity of international law.</p>
        <p>That may be victory enough, but it may also invite a sustained and as yet undefined siege of Iraq if Mr. Hussein emerges from the rubble, defiant and spoiling to continue his duel with Washington and its coalition during Mr. Bush's most difficult season.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
