<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Huskey And Gilkey Are a Hit For Mets</title>
    <meta content="10METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="928799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5DD1239F933A25756C0A961958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Huskey And Gilkey Are a Hit For Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat St Louis Cardinals, 10-3, St Louis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Butch Huskey needed to get away from third base to start hitting. Maybe what Bernard Gilkey needs is a weekend in his former home, Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Gilkey, his average under .200, had three hits and three runs batted in, and Huskey broke a late-inning tie with a solo homer, as the Mets beat the St. Louis Cardinals, 10-3, tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Butch Huskey needed to get away from third base to start hitting. Maybe what Bernard Gilkey needs is a weekend in his former home, Busch Stadium.</p>
        <p>Gilkey, his average under .200, had three hits and three runs batted in, and Huskey broke a late-inning tie with a solo homer, as the Mets beat the St. Louis Cardinals, 10-3, tonight.</p>
        <p>For the fourth time in a week, the Mets (17-18) are within a game of .500, a mark they have not achieved this late in a season since June 3, 1994. Mark Clark pitched six innings and picked up his fourth victory, but Gilkey provided a good deal of support with a single, double and triple.</p>
        <p>Huskey, playing right field tonight, led off the seventh inning with the score tied, 3-3. With the count at one ball and one strike, he mashed a fastball into the Mets' bullpen beyond the right-center-field wall. Huskey started this season slowly, but has heated up since he began playing positions other than third base. He has hit .178 with 1 homer in 45 at-bats while playing third, but .317 with 4 homers in 41 at-bats.</p>
        <p>The Mets added two runs in the eighth and four in the ninth. Shortstop Rey Ordonez curtailed a St. Louis threat in the eighth by making a spectacular leaping catch as he chased a blooper in center field.</p>
        <p>Gilkey, slumping most of the first five weeks of the season, left the Mets for four days at the end of April for the funeral of his grandfather in Mississippi. In the moments alone, Gilkey thought back to what Johnny B. Gilkey always told him: just relax and hit the heck out of the ball.</p>
        <p>''That's basically what I'm trying to do,'' Gilkey said before tonight's game. ''I'm just trying to relax and see the ball and hit it. I'm trying not to complicate things.''</p>
        <p>Tom Robson, the Mets' hitting coach, explained how Gilkey was looking for the right feel to his swing, keeping his hands close to his body and driving the ball toward the right side of the field. As if to demonstrate Robson's point, Gilkey -- hitting .183 with 14 r.b.i. going into tonight's game -- smashed a triple to right field in his first at-bat.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals jumped ahead in the bottom of the first, when Dmitri Young powered an opposite-field homer off Clark. In the second, Royce Clayton's fly ball scored John Mabry.</p>
        <p>The Mets rebounded in the fourth with a quick spurt of offense. Edgardo Alfonzo doubled, St. Louis starter Todd Stottlemyre hit John Olerud with a pitch and Todd Hundley pulled a double into the right-field corner to score Alfonzo. Then Gilkey punched a single into short center, both runners raced home and the Mets led, 3-2.</p>
        <p>When Carlos Baerga singled sending Gilkey to third with nobody out, the Mets had a chance to blow the game open. But Huskey struck out, Ordonez lined out and Clark whiffed.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals tied the score in the fifth, when Clayton came home on Delino DeShields's single. The Mets got a break in the bottom of the sixth: Gary Gaetti rocked a long drive that bounced off the top edge of the wall in left-center, just missing a home run. Gaetti was stranded at second.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Pitcher JASON ISRINGHAUSEN, recovering from what doctors believe is tuberculosis, is at home in Brighton, Ill., less than an hour from St. Louis. Isringhausen told teammates he might visit them this weekend. GEORGENE ISRINGHAUSEN, his mother, said her son ''has been doing much better in the last day or two.'' She paused, and added cheerfully, ''You can tell he's getting better, when he gets a little mouthy. . . . PETE HARNISCH has regained about 7-8 pounds of the 20 or so he lost as he battled depression, and the pitcher is targeting June 15 as his return date to the Mets.</p>
        <p>BILL PULSIPHER's control failed him again in an outing for Class A St. Lucie against Fort Myers tonight. In five and one-third innings, he gave up six hits, two runs (one earned), walked six and struck out one. In addition, he hit a batter and threw four wild pitches. . . . ANDY TOMBERLIN, the reserve outfielder placed on the Mets' disabled list in April, underwent surgery Friday. Dr. RICHARD FRASER, after removing the herniated portion of a disk in Tomberlin's neck, estimated his recovery time at 8 to 12 weeks. . . . The Mets will play an exhibition against Class AAA Norfolk on Monday. Manager BOBBY VALENTINE intends to use the utilityman STEVE BIESER as a catcher, infielder MATT FRANCO in left field and catcher TODD HUNDLEY at first base. YORKIS PEREZ, the left-hander coming back from shoulder trouble, may pitch.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
