<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kidnappings Stir Political Dispute in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="16iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/16/world/middleeast/16iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Maliki, Nuri Kamal al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D6173EF935A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kidnappings Stir Political Dispute in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kidnappings Stir Political Dispute in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE; Qais Mizher contributed reporting from Baghdad, and James Glanz from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Nov. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Nuri Kamal al-Maliki's effort to project image of authority during crisis is undermined by dispute that erupts between Iraqi officials over fate of dozens of captives abducted from government building; spokesman for minister of higher education claims nearly 100 of 150 captives are still being held, while government's chief spokesman contends that only 39 people were kidnapped and all but 2 have been released; mass kidnapping, conducted inside government building during office hours, underscores profound weaknesses of Iraq's security forces and puts further strain on Maliki's relationships with Americans and his Sunni Arab critics;; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute erupted Wednesday between Iraqi officials over the fate of dozens of captives abducted from a government building, undermining an effort by Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki to project an image of authority during the crisis.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Abed Dhiab al-Ajeeli, the minister of higher education, said nearly 100 of about 150 captives were still being held a day after the kidnapping, at the ministry's compound. But the government's chief spokesman, Ali Dabbagh, contended that only 39 people had been kidnapped and that all but 2 had been released. Both men angrily dismissed the other's comments as false.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dispute erupted among senior Iraqi officials over the number and fate of the hostages abducted Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dispute erupted Wednesday between Iraqi officials over the fate of dozens of captives abducted from a government building, undermining an effort by Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki to project an image of authority during the crisis.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Abed Dhiab al-Ajeeli, the minister of higher education, said nearly 100 of about 150 captives were still being held a day after the kidnapping, at the ministry's compound. But the government's chief spokesman, Ali Dabbagh, contended that only 39 people had been kidnapped and that all but 2 had been released. Both men angrily dismissed the other's comments as false.</p>
        <p>Late Wednesday, Mr. Dhiab, one of the few Sunni Arabs in Mr. Maliki's Shiite-dominated cabinet, announced that he was stepping down from his post until all the captives had been rescued. In a written statement, apparently directed at the Maliki administration, he said that any effort to make the kidnapping ''a political issue'' would be ''unacceptable behavior.''</p>
        <p>The disagreements emerged as Mr. Maliki and his aides sought to convey a sense of governmental cohesion and resolve in response to the abductions. Mr. Dabbagh attributed the releases to an aggressive series of overnight raids and persistent pressure on the kidnappers by Iraqi security forces. Mr. Maliki told an audience at the University of Baghdad that he would bring the kidnappers to justice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki has been accused by American officials and some Iraqi leaders of failing to act decisively to curb surging violence, eliminate rampant corruption and improve public services. In particular, he has been criticized for his inability, or unwillingness, to dismantle Shiite militias linked to the governing Shiite parties yet responsible for staging sectarian attacks in cooperation with Iraqi security forces or with access to government uniforms and vehicles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliki and other Shiite leaders have tried to deflect attention away from the militias, insisting that the greatest threat to public security still remains the insurgency, led by Sunni Arabs, which is responsible for the vast majority of casualties inflicted on American and Iraqi government forces. At the same time, the prime minister has pressed American officials to give him more authority over the country's security.</p>
        <p>But the mass kidnapping on Tuesday, conducted inside a government building during office hours, underscored the profound weaknesses of Iraq's security forces and put further strain on Mr. Maliki's relationships with the Americans and his Sunni Arab critics.</p>
        <p>The kidnapping, by gunmen wearing Iraqi police commando uniforms and driving more than 20 vehicles with Interior Ministry markings, was similar in style to several other mass abductions this year. The captives, who included Shiites, Sunni Arabs, Kurds and Christians, were driven to a predominantly Shiite area of eastern Baghdad, officials said, probably passing through numerous police checkpoints unimpeded.</p>
        <p>Hours after the abduction, the Interior Ministry, which oversees the nation's police forces, arrested several police commanders in charge of the area where the ministry site is. And late Tuesday, Mr. Maliki, in an appearance on state-run television, said he had ordered an intensive search for the kidnapping victims.</p>
        <p>But the identity of the kidnappers remained unclear on Wednesday, as did their motive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dabbagh said the kidnapping had been conducted by a ''gang of criminals that belongs to a certain militia,'' and was intended to foment sectarian tensions, but he did not identify the militia. He said he could not explain why the kidnappers had attacked the Ministry of Higher Education. The attackers were ''trying to break the stability between the Shiites and Sunnis,'' he said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The ministry has long been viewed as a Sunni Arab bastion. During Saddam Hussein's rule, it was known mockingly among non-Sunnis as ''the Ministry of Al Ani and Al Rawi,'' after two towns in the overwhelmingly Sunni Arab province of Anbar, said Dr. Abdullah Kendoush, a longtime physicist in the Ministry of Science and Technology who recently left Iraq to take a temporary post at the University of Florida in Gainesville.</p>
        <p>In the argument over numbers, Basil al-Khateeb, the spokesman for the Ministry of Higher Education, said late Wednesday that ''about 150 people'' had been kidnapped and 52 of them had been released. He said the ministry had arrived at its tallies by debriefing witnesses and victims who were freed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dabbagh said that in all, 16 ministry employees, 18 guards and five visitors had been kidnapped from the building and that 37 had been released by late Wednesday under pressure from Iraqi security forces conducting operations in eastern Baghdad. He described Mr. Khateeb's comments by saying, ''That is not an official statement of the government.''</p>
        <p>The American military command put the number of kidnapping victims at about 55.</p>
        <p>Balal Hassan, a Sunni Arab who said his brother Walid worked for the ministry and was one of those kidnapped, said he and his relatives had been desperately trying to find out information about the kidnappings but had received no help from government officials. ''So far they have done nothing,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''Hopefully they will do something significant.''</p>
        <p>The United States military on Wednesday announced the deaths of six Americans. Three marines and one soldier were killed on Tuesday during combat operations in Anbar Province, the military said, and two soldiers were killed by a bomb in northwestern Baghdad.</p>
        <p>[On Thursday morning, Reuters reported, gunmen opened fire on a bakery in eastern Baghdad, killing nine people and wounding two, the police said.]</p>
        <p>A car bomb exploded on Wednesday at a gas station near the Interior Ministry, killing eight people and wounding 32, according to a ministry official. A suicide bomber joined a crowd of mourners at a funeral in Dora, in southern Baghdad, and detonated his explosives, killing three people and wounding 12.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
