<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fair Share for City Schools</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="119594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA133BF935A25751C0A96E948260" item-length="370" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fair Share for City Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: More than a third of New York State's public-school children live in New York City. Yet the city receives less than a third of state aid to local schools. Fairness and necessity cry out for the gap to be closed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: More than a third of New York State's public-school children live in New York City. Yet the city receives less than a third of state aid to local schools. Fairness and necessity cry out for the gap to be closed.</p>
        <p>More than a third of New York State's public-school children live in New York City. Yet the city receives less than a third of state aid to local schools. Fairness and necessity cry out for the gap to be closed.</p>
        <p>Though local school districts are directly responsible for education, the state pays nearly half the bill. State funds are distributed on the basis of complicated formulas that are supposed to take into account each district's relative wealth and needs. In practice, however, the legislators first determine the city's share of state aid, then adjust the formulas accordingly. In a typical formula-rigging scheme last year, New York City schoolchildren were considered to be worth 94 cents, while all other state students were worth one dollar.</p>
        <p>As a result, the city receives only 32.6 percent of state school aid, even though it must educate 36.2 percent of the students. The projected budget gap will total at least $266 million this year - enough to pay for nine new staff positions in each of the city's 974 schools. The shortchanging seems particularly egregious since the city can make a good case for more than an equitable numerical share of state funds. City schools are responsible for 80 percent of all state students with limited proficiency in English, 63 percent of the economically disadvantaged, 61 percent of those reading below minimum standards and 54 percent of the handicapped.</p>
        <p>Resistance to giving New York City its fair share typically comes from upstate Republicans in the State Senate. The upstaters are particularly protective of their school funds these days because school enrollment is declining in many upstate districts, while it has stabilized in New York City and even increases in some neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Shortchanging the city's schools, however, is a shortsighted response. The problems generated by inadequate schools come back to haunt welfare, health and criminal justice agencies that are supported by taxpayers statewide. In any case, the issue creates a special obligation for Republican senators from the city, like Roy Goodman and John Marchi, to show leadership in securing a fair share for city education. The city's million schoolchildren deserve no less.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
