<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Rejects Bush Bid to Ease Delivery of Food To Poor Nations</title>
    <meta content="23aid" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1704272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D81730F930A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Rejects Bush Bid to Ease Delivery of Food To Poor Nations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Bush administration proposal that sought to get food to starving people more rapidly and efficiently was rejected by Senate leaders yesterday, but the Canadian government announced that it was increasing the use of the same technique.</p>
        <p>Up to half of Canada's food aid budget may now be used to buy food in developing countries near a hunger crisis, with the rest bought from Canadian producers. Before, only 10 percent could be bought abroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Bush administration proposal that sought to get food to starving people more rapidly and efficiently was rejected by Senate leaders yesterday, but the Canadian government announced that it was increasing the use of the same technique.</p>
        <p>Up to half of Canada's food aid budget may now be used to buy food in developing countries near a hunger crisis, with the rest bought from Canadian producers. Before, only 10 percent could be bought abroad.</p>
        <p>Canada's minister of international cooperation, Aileen Carroll, said in an interview that the new policy would permit Canada to spend more than $100 million in aid ''to get more food to more people more quickly.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, under the food aid program run by the United States Agency for International Development, with a budget of more than $1 billion, all food must be bought in United States markets and most must be shipped on United States-flagged vessels. Shipping costs consume 40 percent to 50 percent of the food aid budget, and delivering the food typically takes four months.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration asked that the aid agency be allowed to spend up to a quarter of its food aid budget in or near the poor countries afflicted by hunger crises. The Senate leadership declined to include such a provision in the agricultural appropriations bill passed yesterday. The House did the same in June.</p>
        <p>Keith Williams, a spokesman for Senator Saxby Chambliss, Republican of Georgia and chairman of the Agriculture Committee, said yesterday that there were concerns that food aid bought abroad might not be delivered as reliably as aid bought in the United States, and that such purchases might drive up food prices and worsen scarcity in drought-stricken areas.</p>
        <p>The American proposal appears all but dead, but Senator Mike DeWine, Republican of Ohio and a member of the Appropriations Committee, said through his spokesman that he would try to revive a scaled-down version when the bill goes to a House-Senate conference committee.</p>
        <p>He sought unsuccessfully yesterday to persuade Republican leaders of the Senate Appropriations and Agriculture Committees to allow 10 percent of the food aid budget to be spent in poor countries.</p>
        <p>''There will be a time lag in how quickly we can get food in to help, and in that lag there are children dying,'' his spokesman, Jeff Sadosky, said.</p>
        <p>In the looming hunger crisis in southern Africa, Canada already buys corn in the region. The World Food Program estimates that more than 10 million people will need food in Malawi, Mozambique and Zambia, among other nations. At the same time, South Africa has had a bumper corn crop.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
