<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Resurgent Red Storm Has a Tough Task Ahead</title>
    <meta content="12EAST$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/12/sports/ncaabasketball/12EAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1471805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES: BIG EAST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St John's University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Big East Conference</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3D6153EF931A25750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Resurgent Red Storm Has a Tough Task Ahead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">St. John's Faces a Big Task in the Big East</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big East Notebook discusses St John's University, which prepares for Big East tournament and chance of potentially facing four good basketball teams in pursuit of NCAA tournament bid; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All that stands between St. John's and a trip to the N.C.A.A. tournament is a four-game sweep through the Big East tournament.</p>
        <p>As daunting a task as that may be -- against No. 17 Notre Dame, a Boston College team that won six of its last seven games, a potential game against No. 5 Pittsburgh and another behemoth in the championship game -- St. John's will begin Big East Conference tournament play today at noon at Madison Square Garden with a dose of optimism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>All that stands between St. John's and a trip to the N.C.A.A. tournament is an unprecedented four-game sweep of the Big East tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All that stands between St. John's and a trip to the N.C.A.A. tournament is a four-game sweep through the Big East tournament.</p>
        <p>As daunting a task as that may be -- against No. 17 Notre Dame, a Boston College team that won six of its last seven games, a potential game against No. 5 Pittsburgh and another behemoth in the championship game -- St. John's will begin Big East Conference tournament play today at noon at Madison Square Garden with a dose of optimism.</p>
        <p>It may be all the Red Storm players have, but they believe it can carry them to the conference championship and the automatic bid in the N.C.A.A. tournament that goes with it. Otherwise, the Red Storm (15-12, 7-9) appears destined to have to accept a bid to the National Invitation Tournament.</p>
        <p>The Red Storm's sudden resurgence and its quest, as improbable as it may seem, to pull out an N.C.A.A. bid will be among the more important story lines when the four-day tournament begins today. Seton Hall is another team whose N.C.A.A. tournament hopes may hinge on how it performs in the tournament. With 16 regular-season victories, the Pirates will probably need to win at least a game to avoid the N.I.T. They will play Miami in the second game of tonight's doubleheader.</p>
        <p>''Confidence is important all the time, but you have to earn it and you have to deserve it,'' Red Storm Coach Mike Jarvis said. ''The guys really believe that they can win this tournament. It's not just talk. Whether or not we can remains to be seen. We could be out after one day, but that won't be because we didn't believe we can win it.''</p>
        <p>It was only 10 days ago that St. John's had no assurance of qualifying for any postseason tournament, even the Big East's. The Red Storm was 12-12, had lost six of seven games and was playing host to No. 6 Duke. In what was no doubt its biggest victory of the season, St. John's defeated the Blue Devils, 72-71, in a game that revived what had been a dismal season from an underachieving team.</p>
        <p>The Red Storm showed no signs of a letdown, trouncing Rutgers, 75-59, four nights later, and completed the regular season with a 76-73 victory at Miami last Saturday.</p>
        <p>''Better late than never,'' Jarvis said.</p>
        <p>The lingering question is how could this team have struggled as it did for so long, then abruptly turn around a season with a victory over a team as strong as Duke. Jarvis is not sure he has the answers, but believes that he had finally found a lineup that clicked and that has made a difference. The junior Grady Reynolds was added to the starting rotation for the Duke game and has made a difference in a frontcourt that has blossomed into a strong rebounding unit.</p>
        <p>''We're playing a front line of Grady Reynolds, Anthony Glover and Kyle Cuffe, and that's probably been the biggest difference,'' Jarvis said. ''They are doing a tremendous job on the offensive boards. They make it possible for us to get 25 offensive rebounds or so a game.''</p>
        <p>Another factor has been the recent play of Marcus Hatten, who is averaging 33.3 points a game during the three-game winning streak. He made the winning play against Duke when his last-second steal led to a trip to the foul line at the end of regulation, where he hit a free throw that won the game. Against Rutgers he scored a career-high 44 points. Against Miami, he had 27 points while hitting 11 of 23 shots from the floor.</p>
        <p>''I hope I can continue to ride the cloud I've been on,'' Hatten said. ''I feel like I'm in a zone and I've been taking advantage of all situations.'' Should St. John's defeat Notre Dame, it will play Boston College, which has a first-round bye. Next up could be Pitt, which needs to defeat West Virginia or Providence to advance to the semifinals. St. John's needs four victories to win the Big East tournament, a feat that has never been done.</p>
        <p>B.C.'s Bell Is Honored</p>
        <p>Troy Bell, who set a Big East record for scoring average, was selected the conference player of the year yesterday, the fifth player to win the honor more than once.</p>
        <p>A 6-foot-1 senior guard at Boston College and the co-player of the year with Notre Dame's Troy Murphy in 2001, Bell is one of 10 players selected to the conference's first team three times.</p>
        <p>Seton Hall's Louis Orr was chosen the Big East coach of the year. (AP)</p>
        <p>COLLEGES: BIG EAST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
