<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Jarvis, A Number With Magic</title>
    <meta content="08VECS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/08/sports/ncaabasketball/08VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1374049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Notre Dame</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jarvis, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Notre Dame (Ind)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Jarvis, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EED71030F93BA35750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Jarvis, A Number With Magic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Jarvis, a Number With Magic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses St John's University's winning 20 games during regular season and loss to Notre Dame University by 20 points in Big East tournament; coach Mike Jarvis hopes that 20 wins will be enough for invitation to NCAA tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY. The number makes such a powerful statement, like the grizzled face of Andrew Jackson on the $20 bill or the passage of no longer being a teenager. Pitchers who win 20 games in one season are celebrated in baseball, but pitchers who win 19 know they somehow fell short.</p>
        <p>Mike Jarvis, the St. John's coach, knows the value of any version of 20. He reached that number of victories Wednesday night during the Big East tournament but stalled last night after formidable Notre Dame wore down the Red Storm, 83-63.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Jarvis is hoping his team's 20 victories will be the magic number of wins that will get St. John's into the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY. The number makes such a powerful statement, like the grizzled face of Andrew Jackson on the $20 bill or the passage of no longer being a teenager. Pitchers who win 20 games in one season are celebrated in baseball, but pitchers who win 19 know they somehow fell short.</p>
        <p>Mike Jarvis, the St. John's coach, knows the value of any version of 20. He reached that number of victories Wednesday night during the Big East tournament but stalled last night after formidable Notre Dame wore down the Red Storm, 83-63.</p>
        <p>Even at that, Jarvis knows the importance of 20 victories. He is still hoping it will be enough to get his team selected for the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament when the committee picks its final 65 on Sunday. He knows that 20 is just a whole lot better than 19.</p>
        <p>''No matter whether you have 20 wins or 14 wins, it always hurts when you are on the down side,'' Jarvis said afterward.</p>
        <p>He thought his team did not play with ''the energy, the fire, that we have to have,'' which may have explained why he did not insist he belonged in the national tournament.</p>
        <p>''We're going to play next week,'' he said without referring to the afterthought National Invitation Tournament, known as Plan B. ''What I think doesn't make a difference. What we have done, what we have accomplished, is in front of the committee. They will make the decision. I know what we've done.''</p>
        <p>What they have done is win 20. And Jarvis is on record as respecting 20. He recalls being impressed with the portrait of President Jackson being flashed on a rental-car bus not too long ago.</p>
        <p>''Let me tell you something,'' Jarvis said. ''Twenty. It's like I once was in a Hertz bus with Roger Clemens. I sat about two seats from him. I could feel 20's all over the place.''</p>
        <p>''When he got out of the Hertz, he gave the guy a $20 bill,'' Jarvis recalled, clearly impressed. ''It feels good to see a twenty.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, it is a nicer image of Clemens tipping a driver $20 than throwing a jagged bat near Mike Piazza, but Clemens probably was not pumped sky-high at the moment. (I have crunched the numbers and concluded that considerably lower tips to rental-van drivers are appropriate for those of us who do not earn Clemens-level salaries.)</p>
        <p>Anyway, warming to his subject, Jarvis recalled how huge 20 victories seemed when he coached a player named Patrick Ewing at Rindge &amp; Latin High in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>''I thought when I went to college, you know, maybe it wouldn't be such a big deal, but I can remember every 20-win season.''</p>
        <p>For the record, Jarvis won 20 games five of seven times in high school, three of five at Boston University, three of eight at George Washington and now three of four times at St. John's. Last year was his first losing season.</p>
        <p>Winning 20 this season is a credit to Jarvis and his scattershot St. John's team. The Storm did not look like a team that could make much of a dent in even the first or second round of the national tournament, but don't expect Jarvis to say that.</p>
        <p>With basketball coaches in early March, there is always a commercial. Dean Smith used to waggle his fingers and explain why North Carolina wasn't as good as it seemed, but certainly deserved a favorable seeding in the tournament nonetheless. Coach K of Duke is a master at it, and he hardly needs to rationalize anything. But it starts getting dicey at the 20-victory level. So Jarvis put out the message:</p>
        <p>''At some point in time when it's over we will then realize what a really good year we've had,'' Jarvis said the other night.</p>
        <p>At the very least St. John's has reached the magic level of Andrew Jackson being wielded by Roger Clemens.</p>
        <p>Twenty is better than 19. Just ask Craig Esherick, the coach of Georgetown, which lost to Miami, 84-76, in overtime, and is now stuck with a 19-11 record.</p>
        <p>''As I told the team after the game, 'We have now put our destiny in somebody else's hands,' '' Esherick said. ''We got three days to wait: Friday, Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>''And I told the guys that are coming back next year, 'You need to remember this feeling. This is a helpless feeling. We have no idea what's going to happen. We have no idea if we're in or out.' ''</p>
        <p>Esherick still has one victory fewer than Jarvis. Twenty is just so much better than 19. But last night Jarvis sounded as if he dearly needed that 21st victory that did not happen.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
