<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial By Fire</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="665367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAW, DAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KILLIAN, TODD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DE1439F933A05752C0A962958260" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial By Fire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN SHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHAW, DAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHOOSING the site for a fashion show is a lot like looking for a house or an apartment: location means everything. Maybe Todd Killian, a fledgling men's-wear designer, should have used a broker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian's first runway show was scheduled to begin at 2:30 last Monday afternoon at Gilda, a new Italian restaurant on East 49th Street, which donated the space in hope of getting some exposure. The 30-year-old Mr. Killian, who has been in business for three years and has sold his oversize cotton and linen shirts to Barneys, Bloomingdale's and Bergdorf's, thought the restaurant would be convenient for buyers and journalists who would be attending two must-see shows: John Bartlett's on West 40th Street at 1:30 P.M., and Calvin Klein's on West 39th Street at 4 P.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHOOSING the site for a fashion show is a lot like looking for a house or an apartment: location means everything. Maybe Todd Killian, a fledgling men's-wear designer, should have used a broker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian's first runway show was scheduled to begin at 2:30 last Monday afternoon at Gilda, a new Italian restaurant on East 49th Street, which donated the space in hope of getting some exposure. The 30-year-old Mr. Killian, who has been in business for three years and has sold his oversize cotton and linen shirts to Barneys, Bloomingdale's and Bergdorf's, thought the restaurant would be convenient for buyers and journalists who would be attending two must-see shows: John Bartlett's on West 40th Street at 1:30 P.M., and Calvin Klein's on West 39th Street at 4 P.M.</p>
        <p>The plan might have worked if the restaurant hadn't decided to try to serve lunch that day, too. If fact, the last table wasn't cleared until 2:20. By 2:45, when chairs had finally been placed in a serpentine configuration around the awkwardly shaped restaurant, some of the 250 guests who had been waiting outside decided to bolt.</p>
        <p>"Nonnie Moore just left!" said Norma Quinto, Mr. Killian's publicist, referring to the influential fashion director of GQ magazine. "I feel like crying."</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian, who was upstairs overseeing the volunteers Ms. Quinto had rounded up to help dress his 13 models, decided it was too late to panic. Having worked until 5 A.M. two nights in a row, the designer, still boyishly cheerful, was subsisting on adrenaline.</p>
        <p>"It wasn't our lack of organization," he said right after the show, which finally began at 3 P.M. "It's what happens to small designers, that's all."</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian, who has sales of about $100,000 a year, had begged and bartered for three months to put together a major presentation, adhering to a rigorous schedule to produce the samples for his fall collection. "Follow or Die!" he had printed in bold letters on the large calendar in his office.</p>
        <p>The show was part of his campaign to establish his label. "Even if you've sold to the most prestigious stores in the world, there are so many other stores that you need to let know about you," Mr. Killian said. "Once they know about you, they'll come see you. Otherwise, it's phone call after phone call, hang-up after hang-up."</p>
        <p>By holding a show during New York's men's-wear week -- three days when there are about a dozen shows by big shots like Donna Karan and by young companies like Boing -- he could be sure that his collection would be seen by out-of-town buyers and reporters. And it also meant that his clothes would be photographed and reviewed by DNR, the industry's daily trade paper.</p>
        <p>In its report, DNR made no reference to the haphazard presentation. Ms. Quinto had been overly optimistic about how many chairs could be squeezed into the restaurant; the space left for the models was so narrow that they had to navigate an obstacle course of combat boots and loafers. Mr. Killian's "understated look," DNR said, "would be perfect for a man with an artistic yet cerebral bent, such as an architect."</p>
        <p>But not everyone overlooked the mayhem. Tom Mendenhall, the men's-wear buyer for the Charivari stores in Manhattan, said, "The clothes were perfectly nice, but the presentation didn't help."</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian spent $6,000 on his show, mostly for the clothes. Even that "was more than I had," he said. (If he had paid professionals to do the work of his volunteers, the show would have cost two or three times $6,000.) Working out of a cramped SoHo office with a gas furnace in the window, he and his intern, Masahiro Uemaru, a recent Fashion Institute of Technology graduate, cut and sewed cigarette trousers and gabardine jackets, while Ms. Quinto, his only paid staff member, put together a guest list of 1,000 editors, stylists, retailers and photographers.</p>
        <p>The invitations, printed on glossy cards, were designed gratis by Jin O'Reilly Advertising, a small agency co-owned by Mr. Killian's girlfriend, Mika Jin; the agency also designed the program, which Mr. Killian didn't finish writing until 5 A.M. the day of the show, after he completed mixing the accompanying music. Du Pont, whose Micromattique fiber was mentioned on the invitations, paid for their printing and picked up the tab for posters given guests and for videotaping the show for future promotion.</p>
        <p>Friends, relatives, strangers who were friends of friends, and students at F.I.T. were enlisted to help in the final week. Volunteers who handled the R.S.V.P.'s from people who had never heard of Mr. Killian were instructed to tell callers that his subtly detailed clothes were similar to those of the respected Japanese designers Yohji Yamamoto and Rei Kawakubo of Comme des Garcons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian's best friend since the fourth grade in Fleetwood, Pa., Fred Fry, now an engineering student at Penn State, came to New York for the weekend to be an all-purpose gofer. On Monday morning, Mr. Fry loaded his pickup truck with racks hung with Mr. Killian's clothes for the trip from SoHo to midtown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian had hoped to get models to work for nothing, too. "The agencies wouldn't go along with that," he said. "We paid them $100 or gave them one of my shirts."</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian's fiscal conservatism is understandable. "I hear all these nightmare stories at the fabric mills about designers not paying and going out of business," he said. "I'm taking my steps slowly and lightly."</p>
        <p>He wasn't that cautious when he graduated from high school in Fleetwood. "I joined the Army because I didn't know what else to do and knew I could save money for college," he said. "And I counted every single day until I got out."</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, it was in the Army that he first became interested in being a designer. "I bought a secondhand sewing machine at a pawn shop near the base so I could make a tuxedo to take a girlfriend to her prom," he recalled. "I also did alterations for other guys to make extra money. I made camouflage curtains for the captain's office."</p>
        <p>When he wasn't sewing, Mr. Killian was training for combat. "I was in a hot platoon in Panama for a month," he said. "Our bags were packed, and we were ready to be shipped out to Honduras in five minutes."</p>
        <p>But preparing for his first fashion show was more frightening. "Basic training wasn't this tough," Mr. Killian said after two models and the hair stylist canceled the morning of the show. "I overcame a lot of dark periods to get to this point."</p>
        <p>Mr. Killian said he had no regrets, although it is still too early to know whether the show will pay off in orders. "I understand the process now," he said. "I'll be more organized next time." His satisfaction, he said, came from seeing his designs being worn.</p>
        <p>"Right before the show, when all 13 models were lined up waiting to go out, I really liked the way the clothes looked," he said. "That was worth everything."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
