<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hopkins Earns a Bout With De La Hoya</title>
    <meta content="06FITE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/06/sports/othersports/06FITE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1587481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Boxing Federation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hopkins, Bernard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Allen, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDA1131F935A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hopkins Earns a Bout With De La Hoya</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hopkins Earns a Bout With De La Hoya</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KATZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Katz, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Hopkins wins unanimous 12-round decision over Robert Allen to defend middleweight title (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oscar De La Hoya's fans started booing Bernard Hopkins three months early as the boxers set up a Sept. 18 fight that could shatter money-making records for a nonheavyweight bout.</p>
        <p>Hopkins looked vulnerable here Saturday night, but he still gained a lopsided 12-round decision against Robert Allen at the MGM Grand Garden. It was Hopkins's 18th successful middleweight title defense, a record, and his third victory against Allen, who then predicted De La Hoya would beat Hopkins (44-2) in their matchup in September.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernard Hopkins looked vulnerable at MGM Grand Garden Saturday night, but he still gained a lopsided 12-round decision against Robert Allen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oscar De La Hoya's fans started booing Bernard Hopkins three months early as the boxers set up a Sept. 18 fight that could shatter money-making records for a nonheavyweight bout.</p>
        <p>Hopkins looked vulnerable here Saturday night, but he still gained a lopsided 12-round decision against Robert Allen at the MGM Grand Garden. It was Hopkins's 18th successful middleweight title defense, a record, and his third victory against Allen, who then predicted De La Hoya would beat Hopkins (44-2) in their matchup in September.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya, who began his pro career as a 130-pound junior lightweight and was fighting for the first time as a 160-pound middleweight, beat Felix Sturm of Germany by unanimous decision, and by narrow 115-113 margins, for the World Boxing Organization title, his sixth title in a different weight class.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya, now 37-3 since winning an Olympic gold medal in 1992, did not look as if he would be a hard-punching middleweight, but then, he was not exactly a killer at welterweight and at junior middleweight. Sturm took De La Hoya's best shots well, and vice versa. Sturm entered with only eight knockouts and a 20-0 record against middling European middleweights. De La Hoya controlled the fight, although he tired somewhat in the middle rounds.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya and Hopkins were favored, and there did not seem much risk of their big fight not happening. The crowd seemed already in September. Hopkins said the booing by the crowd of about 13,000 motivated him. He said he was a little out of character and more nervous than usual.</p>
        <p>''I've never been in this situation before, with $10 million waiting for me,'' he said. ''I was cautious because freak accidents can happen and I was in with a big puncher.''</p>
        <p>Hopkins, 39, is guaranteed $10 million for his showdown with De La Hoya, but he will make perhaps 50 percent more from his share of the revenues; De La Hoya could make up to $30 million.</p>
        <p>Hopkins said the turmoil of the last days, when he threatened not to fight because Joe Cortez was assigned to referee, were past him. He said he had no problems with Cortez.</p>
        <p>''He refereed a great fight and he could do any of my fights,'' Hopkins said.</p>
        <p>Cortez deducted a point from Allen, a tough left-hander, for a low blow in the fifth round. When Allen tried to touch gloves, Hopkins threw a right hand at him. Cortez was also able to count to the mandatory eight for the bout's only knockdown.</p>
        <p>A looping right hand, thrown as Allen was trying a right hook in the seventh round, sent the challenger sprawling on his stomach. He rolled over on his back, but jumped up and absorbed two minutes of heavy punishment the rest of the round and the rest of the defeat, which lowered his record to 36-5. Hopkins, who had a no contest with Allen -- the champion was injured falling out of the ring from a push -- before knocking him out in the rematch, is now 44-2-1.</p>
        <p>PUNCH LINES</p>
        <p>JOSE LUIS CASTILLO of Mexico pounded out a unanimous 12-round decision over JUAN LAZCANO of Sacramento to regain the World Boxing Council lightweight title he lost two years ago to FLOYD MAYWEATHER JR., who vacated it earlier this year. Castillo (50-6-1) did not knock down Lazcano (33-3-1).</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
