<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Big Gains, Angolan Rebel Offensive Is Halted</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="636401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANGOLA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAVIMBI, JONAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7123CF937A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Big Gains, Angolan Rebel Offensive Is Halted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>GANDA, Angola, Sept. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of euphoric advances in which his guerrillas extended their reach over more than two-thirds of Angola's territory, the rebel movement of Jonas Savimbi appears to have been fought to a standstill, and in some places turned back, by a rebounding Government army.</p>
        <p>Here on the embattled central plateau that is Mr. Savimbi's political base and the war's greatest symbolic prize, the Government has expelled the insurgents from several towns conquered during their great surge, and is slowly amassing troops and weapons for a promised major offensive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of euphoric advances in which his guerrillas extended their reach over more than two-thirds of Angola's territory, the rebel movement of Jonas Savimbi appears to have been fought to a standstill, and in some places turned back, by a rebounding Government army.</p>
        <p>Here on the embattled central plateau that is Mr. Savimbi's political base and the war's greatest symbolic prize, the Government has expelled the insurgents from several towns conquered during their great surge, and is slowly amassing troops and weapons for a promised major offensive.</p>
        <p>But while the tide may have turned again in Angola's relentless civil war, neither a decisive military outcome nor a diplomatic settlement appears to be within reach. Long Standoff Seen</p>
        <p>Officials and diplomats in Luanda, the capital, say the country seems doomed to months or years more of a lethal standoff that has already created some of the most wretched pockets of misery in Africa and demolished what little remained of the Angolan economy.</p>
        <p>The prevailing view of diplomats and military analysts is that the Government has not yet mustered the strength to throw a knockout punch. Mr. Savimbi, in turn, is considered largely immune to diplomatic pressures, such as the United Nations Security Council's threat on Sept. 15 to declare an oil and arms embargo unless the rebels stop fighting and show signs of accepting their defeat in elections a year ago.</p>
        <p>"We're looking at a protracted stalemate," said a Western military expert in Luanda. "The most realistic hope is that the Government can eventually push Savimbi back to where the country has a degree of normalcy, but with a guerrilla threat continuing indefinitely."</p>
        <p>By most accounts, the last year of war has been the most punishing in 30 years of fighting -- first against Portuguese colonialists, then, after independence in 1975, between rival Angolan factions, armed and abetted by the superpowers. The patrons of Mr. Savimbi's National Union for the Total Independence of Angola, known by its Portuguese acronymn, Unita, were the United States and South Africa</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Savimbi spurned the election outcome and led his guerrillas back into the bush, an estimated 50,000 people have been killed, and 2 million more of the country's 12 million people have fled the fighting to crowded city slums and refugee camps.</p>
        <p>The rebels' swift advances isolated many cities and towns that were not disturbed in the earlier bush war, disrupting food supplies and raising fears of famine. Government Massing Troops</p>
        <p>The Government has been massing forces on two fronts: one just north of Luanda, where the main targets are the rebel-held oil town of Soyo and two northern provincial capitals, the other at a Cuban-built air base in Catumbela, on the Atlantic coast. From that base the army directs its advance toward Huambo, Angola's second-largest city and Mr. Savimbi's headquarters.</p>
        <p>"Huambo has no military value," conceded Gen. Armando da Cruz Neto, the commander of the central front, in an interview. "But it has great psychological value for Savimbi."</p>
        <p>In the field, the only noticeable impact of diplomatic maneuvering is to set off periodic struggles for position, in the event a cease-fire takes hold.</p>
        <p>Just outside Ganda, a highland agricultural town that is as close as reporters are allowed to the front line, rebels attacked from behind the eucalyptus trees early Thursday morning.</p>
        <p>Col. Jose Manuel de Sousa, the 30-year-old commander whose troops had recaptured Ganda from the rebels just a month ago, said the attackers were routed with heavy losses. But the fact that they could muster such an attack behind Government lines reflects the see-saw nature of the battle.</p>
        <p>Despite his party's reputation for corruption, President Jose Eduardo dos Santos, a colorless petroleum engineer, won the elections last year by running as the peacemaker against the bellicose, charismatic Mr. Savimbi.</p>
        <p>The demobilization and elections were sparsely monitored by international observers, and it soon became obvious that while the Government's battle-weary army had virtually collapsed, Mr. Savimbi had kept plenty of firepower in reserve.</p>
        <p>Denouncing the election as a fraud, he ordered his 30,000 guerrillas back into the bush, and salvaged the heavy weapons he had secretly cached. This time he has tended to portray his war less as an anti-Communist crusade and more as a defense of his minority Ovimbundu people, although the Ovimbundus are sharply divided in this war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Savimbi's forces gobbled up territory far beyond what the rebels had held during the earlier war. He is still estimated to have loose control of about 65 percent of Angola's land area, including 4 of 18 provincial capitals and roughly a third of the population.</p>
        <p>He conquered the important diamond fields of Lunda Norte province, menaced the outskirts of Luanda with hit-and-run attacks and in March, after an eight-week battle in which thousands died, he took Huambo.</p>
        <p>"If Unita was going to win the war militarily, their chance was between October and April," said a Western military expert. "They didn't do it."</p>
        <p>Slowly the Government has built a new army from inexperienced teen-age conscripts, and distributed assault rifles to thousands of urban civilians.</p>
        <p>Western officials believe the Government has already mortgaged its oil income for the next three years to raise money for weapons. Besieged Provincial Capital</p>
        <p>The fiercest fighting of the renewed war now centers on the provincial capital of Cuito, northeast of Huambo, where 2,000 Government troops have held out since January.</p>
        <p>Government radio broadcasts from the besieged city tell of dogs devouring unburied corpses in the streets.</p>
        <p>The United States, after supporting Mr. Savimbi for years, recognized the dos Santos Government in May, but some Angolan officials are bitter that this has not brought military help.</p>
        <p>"In my opinion the United States does not want to abandon the monster it created," asserted Reis Esteves, the Vice Governor of Benguela province.</p>
        <p>"We didn't create Savimbi," retorted an American official, when asked about American responsibility for the situation. "We may have rented him for a couple of years, but I don't believe we owned him." Washington, the official added, has no popular mandate for any deeper involvement in Angola.</p>
        <p>It is generally believed Mr. Savimbi uses money from his captured diamonds to buy black market weapons, bringing them in through neighboring Zaire and Namibia.</p>
        <p>A United Nations embargo, diplomats in Angola say, might raise the price of his weapons, but would not cut off his access to arms merchants.</p>
        <p>As for diplomacy, neither Mr. Savimbi nor the Government has shifted position since the last peace talks ended in failure in May.</p>
        <p>Margaret Anstee, then the United Nations special envoy to Angola, now retired, has said the talks might have succeeded if the United Nations had been willing to invest in a small, symbolic presence of peacekeeping troops.</p>
        <p>But other participants in the talks said Mr. Savimbi would not agree to withdraw from territories he captured after the election.</p>
        <p>The Government, in turn, flatly rejects any settlement that allows Mr. Savimbi to keep his gains.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
