<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Snoozing Rangers Startled</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PENGUINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONDY, FILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE113FF937A35756C0A964958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Snoozing Rangers Startled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FILIP BONDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONDY, FILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers skated onto the ice last night at Madison Square Garden still looking for Claude Lemieux, or Scott Stevens, or some Devil-ish player they could really and truly hate.</p>
        <p>Instead, they got the Pittsburgh Penguins, a polished, professional team with a doctorate in the counter-attack. The Penguins fashioned a workmanlike 4-2 victory in Game 1 of the Patrick Division final series, and the Rangers were still trying to figure out how to get excited about an opponent who doesn't wear a chip on its shoulder pads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers skated onto the ice last night at Madison Square Garden still looking for Claude Lemieux, or Scott Stevens, or some Devil-ish player they could really and truly hate.</p>
        <p>Instead, they got the Pittsburgh Penguins, a polished, professional team with a doctorate in the counter-attack. The Penguins fashioned a workmanlike 4-2 victory in Game 1 of the Patrick Division final series, and the Rangers were still trying to figure out how to get excited about an opponent who doesn't wear a chip on its shoulder pads.</p>
        <p>"We sat back, and it seemed like they sat back," Tie Domi said. "And the next thing you know, we lost."</p>
        <p>The defending Stanley Cup champions could not have plotted this flat series opener any better. The Rangers swarmed Pittsburgh goaltender Tom Barrasso for the first 15 minutes, getting nowhere. The Penguins scored three goals in just over eight minutes over the first and second periods, opening up the ice briefly with a series of counter-thrusts. Then they went into an un-Penguin-like shell, holding to a four-man-back formation that frustrated the Rangers and made them dump and chase the puck as the game trickled to a dull finish.</p>
        <p>"I've never seen them play four men back before," Kris King said. "It's an effective way to play in the playoffs. We're going to have to find a way to solve it."</p>
        <p>Coming off their emotional, seven-game victory against the Devils, the Rangers appeared to be unenthusiastic participants. But the Penguins, seven-game winners over Washington, could have used the same excuse. They didn't.</p>
        <p>"We're playing the top team in the league, so we realize that we're fighting for our lives from Day One," Pittsburgh defenseman Gord Roberts said. "We have to be sharp at all times."</p>
        <p>There were several discouraging signs for the Rangers. Mark Messier was practically invisible all night, hardly his trademark big-game presence. John Vanbiesbrouck stopped Mario Lemieux on two breakaways but then allowed a couple of soft goals that might have made the difference.</p>
        <p>"The intensity just didn't seem to be there for us," Coach Roger Neilson said. "The game all of a sudden doesn't seem to be quite as important as the last series. We just better win the next game. I think the guys will realize that quickly."</p>
        <p>The game spiraled out of control quickly last night. Vanbiesbrouck was caught off balance scrambling back into his net after making a save off Bryan Trottier on a 2-on-1 break. Vanbiesbrouck, screened by Penguin left wing Phil Bourque, was unable to set himself on a slap shot by Troy Loney that beat him low at 13 minutes 56 seconds.</p>
        <p>The Penguins scored again less than two minutes later on a quick dash by Larry Murphy down the right side. Murphy's chance came after Mike Gartner hit the crossbar with a shot at the other end, and the puck bounced out to near the blue line.</p>
        <p>With James Patrick serving two minutes for holding early in the second period, Kevin Stevens's shot from low on the right side bounced off the left glove of defenseman Jeff Beukeboom and through the pads of Vanbiesbrouck at 2:00 for a 3-0 lead.</p>
        <p>The Rangers charged back briefly, on a goal by King and a power-play score by Tony Amonte. But Ron Francis clinched the game for Pittsburgh on an awkward shovel backhand low to the stick side that should not have beaten Vanbiesbrouck. It did, at 12:08 of the third period.</p>
        <p>"Our plan was to really take it to them," Domi said. "But that Lemieux is something to watch on the ice. Everything revolves around him."</p>
        <p>Wrong Lemieux. Wrong sentiment. Wrong time of the year for a flat game. SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The game was not a sellout, drawing 17,744 fans. The late start, 8:30 P.M. on a Sunday, might have been a factor. . . . Since ROGER NEILSON said that both his goaltenders would be starting in this series, it figures that MIKE RICHTERwill get a start in Game 2. Neither Richter nor JOHN VANBIESBROUCK has been particularly sharp in their last few appearances.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
