<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Riots Raise Concerns About Insurance Redlining</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMEOWNERS INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REDLINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERR, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DC1E3DF937A35756C0A964958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Riots Raise Concerns About Insurance Redlining</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER KERR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KERR, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As damage estimates rise to hundreds of millions of dollars, consumer advocates and some insurance regulators say they fear the Los Angeles riots could aggravate a problem that has plagued America's inner cities for more than 25 years: the abandonment of the poor by insurance companies.</p>
        <p>After race riots in six American cities between 1965 and 1967, a Presidential commission found that the redlining of businesses and homes in poor neighborhoods by private insurers grew by an "intolerable degree." Officials later reported the sudden cancellation of property policies in New York, Philadelphia, St. Louis and other cities that experienced riots after the assassination of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. in April 1968.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As damage estimates rise to hundreds of millions of dollars, consumer advocates and some insurance regulators say they fear the Los Angeles riots could aggravate a problem that has plagued America's inner cities for more than 25 years: the abandonment of the poor by insurance companies.</p>
        <p>After race riots in six American cities between 1965 and 1967, a Presidential commission found that the redlining of businesses and homes in poor neighborhoods by private insurers grew by an "intolerable degree." Officials later reported the sudden cancellation of property policies in New York, Philadelphia, St. Louis and other cities that experienced riots after the assassination of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. in April 1968.</p>
        <p>Redlining, the systematic refusal of insurance companies to sell policies in poor neighborhoods, is illegal, but officials say it is extremely hard to monitor or prosecute. Essential to Business</p>
        <p>The industry generally denies that it engages in redlining, and companies with many customers in Los Angeles say they will respond efficiently and unemotionally to civil disturbances.</p>
        <p>A lack of property insurance can strangle a neighborhood's economy. Banks usually refuse to give mortgages on uninsured property, and small businesses find it next to impossible to lease equipment or order goods on consignment if they are unprotected against fire, theft or civil disturbances.</p>
        <p>"I'm afraid these disturbances could increase insurers' reluctance to do business in poor neighborhoods across the country," said Robert Hunter, a former Federal Insurance Administrator who was responsible for inner-city insurance programs during the Carter Administration. "I think we have seen a bit of improvement on redlining in recent years, and these new events could prove a setback."</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for major insurance companies say such worries are both speculative and unfair.  States Offer Plans</p>
        <p>They point out that in contrast to the situation in the 1960's, 28 states now sponsor Fair Access to Insurance Requirements, or FAIR plans, that provide at least minimum property insurance to businesses and homeowners in high-risk urban areas.</p>
        <p>"I just don't think you are going to see a withdrawal of business from the inner city," said Richard G. Donegan, the regional underwriting manager for Allstate Insurance in Los Angeles and the chairman of the governing committee of California's FAIR plan. Customers in riot-torn areas, he said, should see modest increases at most in their premiums.</p>
        <p>Although Mayor Tom Bradley of Los Angeles this weekend estimated that property damage may exceed $500 million, Patty Lombard, a spokeswoman for the Insurance Information Institute, an industry trade group, said it would take weeks for companies to assess the damage and the companies' obligations. California officials said last week that they believed that many of the burned or looted businesses had no insurance. Urban Policies Cancelled</p>
        <p>In January 1968, a Presidential commission headed by Gov. Richard J. Hughes of New Jersey surveyed 3,000 homeowners and businesses in six large cities in the wake of the riots of the mid-196o's. The commission found that 40 percent of businesses and 30 percent of homeowners in poor areas found it unusually difficult to get or keep insurance, and that 14.4 percent of the uninsured businesses had lost their polices after the riots.</p>
        <p>Later that year, officials in New York City, Philadelphia, St. Louis, and Detroit said they had found evidence of companies canceling policies after the April riots. Repeated government studies since then have concluded that redlining of poor neighborhoods by insurers continues.</p>
        <p>Last year, more than a dozen insurance agents and customers in minority communities testified in a hearing held by the California Insurance Commissioner, John Garamendi, that insurers redlined poor neighborhoods in California by charging exorbitant rates, keeping sales forces out of the areas and, in some cases, refusing to sell policies to people who do not speak English.</p>
        <p>Steven Miller, California's deputy insurance commissioner in charge of rate regulation, predicted that the riots "will be used by insurers to justify continued discriminatory practices and possibly the withdrawal of business from some areas."</p>
        <p>"It is something we will have to monitor closely," he added.</p>
        <p>As a result of the Hughes Commission report of 1968, most industrial states, including New York, New Jersey, Connecticut and California have enacted FAIR plans. The policies, which are sometimes expensive and limited in coverage, are sold to people who live in high-risk areas and cannot get private coverage.</p>
        <p>To discourage companies from redlining, the Federal Government originally provided riot reinsurance to companies that sold FAIR policies. Under the plan, the Government would reimburse the companies for most of their losses from riots, whether or not they involved FAIR customers. The program was ended during the second Reagan Administration.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
