<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abbie Hoffman and Hey, His Turbulent Times</title>
    <meta content="03HAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampton, Wilborn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sloman, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Abbie (1936-89)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Steal This Dream (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D8133FF930A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abbie Hoffman and Hey, His Turbulent Times</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILBORN HAMPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hampton, Wilborn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wilborn Hampton reviews book Steal This Dream: Abbie Hoffman and the Counterculture Revolution in America by Larry Sloman; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STEAL THIS DREAM  Abbie Hoffman and the Countercultural Revolution in America  By Larry Sloman  Illustrated. 437 pages. Doubleday. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STEAL THIS DREAM  Abbie Hoffman and the Countercultural Revolution in America  By Larry Sloman  Illustrated. 437 pages. Doubleday. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Of all the young rebels, with or without causes, who marched, chanted, tripped and protested their way through the 1960's and 70's, no one was more of an enigma than Abbott Hoffman, a nice Jewish boy from Worcester, Mass., who finagled his way to the front lines of every battle fought during those turbulent years -- from the civil rights campaign to the drug and sex revolution to the antiwar movement.</p>
        <p>In ''Steal This Dream,'' Larry Sloman attempts to piece together a rough mosaic of Abbie Hoffman through the reminiscences of a battalion of friends and foes alike -- classifications that often became blurred over the years. In his exhaustive research, Mr. Sloman interviewed more than 200 people who knew Hoffman and has attempted to turn their recollections into an oral history. In fact, ''Steal This Dream'' reads more like a sound-bite history, since few of the voices speak much more than a sentence or a paragraph at a time. But as Hoffman virtually invented the sound bite, it somehow seems suitable.</p>
        <p>In the beginning this staccato approach leaves the reader feeling as if he has wandered into a reunion of hippies who are all trying to talk at the same time. But as one grows used to it, the style becomes apt for portraying a generation that thrived on confusion and contradiction.</p>
        <p>Who was Abbie Hoffman and what made him run? As Mr. Sloman demonstrates, if you ask 210 people you get at least 210 different answers. Jerry Rubin: ''If you were going to a demonstration . . . Abbie would be the one bringing the ice cream.'' Norman Mailer: ''Abbie was a serious man.'' Sal Gianetta (a friend): ''He was cuckoo.'' His mother: ''He was brilliant, just brilliant.''</p>
        <p>The book follows Hoffman's life in chronological order, starting with his family and classmates from high school, Brandeis, Berkeley; it trails him from his first demonstration (against the execution of Caryl Chessman) at San Quentin and his first riot (in San Francisco) back to Worcester and on to New York, where it was all happening, baby.</p>
        <p>The opening skirmishes were being fought in what would become known as the countercultural revolution (read sex, drugs and rock-and-roll), and the rebel headquarters were in the East Village in Manhattan. Hoffman and his comrades formed the Youth International Party (call them Yippies) to oppose the Vietnam War. The problem was how to get the word out to rally the nation's youth. Hoffman figured that television could deliver the message free, straight into the living rooms of America.</p>
        <p>Nobody knew how to get on television better than Hoffman. As he explained to a friend: ''See, like at 7:26, after they've done all the heavy stuff, they gotta have a sign-off piece, something cute and weird and wacky and whimsical. So I know we can't get on at 7:03. That's Johnson's time. But we could get on at 7:26.''</p>
        <p>Among the weird and wacky and whimsical stunts Hoffman helped stage were throwing dollar bills onto the floor of the New York Stock Exchange and watching the brokers scramble for them, the protest march in Washington at which chanting hippies tried to ''levitate'' the Pentagon and a ''Yip-in'' happening in Grand Central Terminal in New York that turned into a melee. But they were all dress rehearsals for what was originally billed as a Festival of Life, a mass protest against the Vietnam War, to be held in Chicago during the Democratic National Convention in 1968.</p>
        <p>The best part of ''Steal This Dream'' is the section dealing with the Chicago riots and the subsequent trial of the protest organizers, who came to be known as the Chicago Seven (or Chicago Eight, depending on whether you included Bobby Seale on the same scorecard). It is a gripping account of one of the most bizarre episodes in the country's political history, told by those who were on the barricades. The pandemonium in the streets of Chicago was matched only by the confusion among the protest's organizers.</p>
        <p>Hoffman and Rubin, for example, had a falling out and stopped speaking to each other. Stew Albert, one of the organizers and a friend of both, said, ''It was over the pig.''</p>
        <p>One of the stunts the Yippies pulled that week was to run a pig (Pigasus) for President. Hoffman went out and got a pig and took it to downtown Chicago. When the crowd started singing ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' to the pig, the police started making arrests. Mr. Albert recalled: ''When we were in jail a cop came and said, 'I have bad news for you boys, the pig squealed.' That was the best cop joke I ever heard.''</p>
        <p>If the Democratic Convention ended in chaos, it was nothing compared with the trial that was to come. Hoffman wanted to turn the trial into theater, showing via television coverage the bankruptcy of the American judicial system. Other defendants disagreed, and they argued over strategy. William Kunstler recalled: ''When they were charged with conspiracy, Abbie said, 'Conspiracy? We can't even agree on lunch.' ''</p>
        <p>After the trial, the movement slowly began to disintegrate. By the time the 1972 conventions in Miami rolled around, there was a weak effort to repeat the demonstrations of four years earlier. But the Yippies had become mainstream. The remnants of the Chicago Seven all had press passes in Miami. Allen Ginsberg was still om-ing, but this time from the convention floor.</p>
        <p>Rubin had thrown in the towel earlier. As he recalled telling an ex-Yippie who urged him to carry on the revolution from underground: ''I'd rather do yoga than go underground. You want to go underground? Hey, have a good time.''</p>
        <p>The last third of the book follows Hoffman through his feeble attempts at being a family man, his arrest for drug dealing and his own years on the run from the law to his later campaigns for environmental issues and his suicide at 52 in 1989.</p>
        <p>If there is a complaint about the book, it is that Mr. Sloman assumes that readers will readily recall events and names that didn't even grab that many headlines 30 years ago. Yet in focusing his kaleidoscope on Abbie Hoffman, the one unreconstructed radical among the lot, Mr. Sloman succeeds in turning ''Steal This Dream '' into a surprisingly rich and detailed panorama of a movement that helped stop a war, bring down a President and, for better or worse, change the social fabric of the nation.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
