<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Barely a Whimper, Yanks Fail to Win 100th</title>
    <meta content="03YANK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DD113FF930A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Barely a Whimper, Yanks Fail to Win 100th</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Athletics defeat New York Yankees, 2-0 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees talked casually about winning their 100th game of the regular season because they have long expected to do it and because they have almost a month to get the one victory necessary to reach the lofty total. Like every other milestone this relaxed team has conquered, the Yankees treated the pursuit in a businesslike fashion. There is no need to get too excited, they stressed.</p>
        <p>Actually, there was no reason for the Yankees to get too excited last night as a pitcher named Gil Heredia made them look like impostors in guiding the Oakland Athletics to a 2-0 victory last night at Yankee Stadium. So the 100th victory celebration, which was not going to be a celebration for the Yankees anyway, will have to wait until at least Friday night, when they play the White Sox in Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees talked casually about winning their 100th game of the regular season because they have long expected to do it and because they have almost a month to get the one victory necessary to reach the lofty total. Like every other milestone this relaxed team has conquered, the Yankees treated the pursuit in a businesslike fashion. There is no need to get too excited, they stressed.</p>
        <p>Actually, there was no reason for the Yankees to get too excited last night as a pitcher named Gil Heredia made them look like impostors in guiding the Oakland Athletics to a 2-0 victory last night at Yankee Stadium. So the 100th victory celebration, which was not going to be a celebration for the Yankees anyway, will have to wait until at least Friday night, when they play the White Sox in Chicago.</p>
        <p>It was a long night of anticipating for the Yankees and their fans because the start of the game was delayed 2 hours 14 minutes by rain. After it finally started, the A's scored what seemed like a harmless run off David Cone (18-5) in the first inning and surprisingly held tight to the lead behind Heredia.</p>
        <p>Despite the loss, if they win on Friday, the Yankees will still reach 100 victories in the fifth fewest games in history and will do it faster, in terms of the calendar date, than any other team.</p>
        <p>''Once we get to 100, we will go ahead and try and do something else,'' Paul O'Neill said. ''It's not like our goal was to win 100 games by Sept. 2. Our goal is to win the division and eventually win the World Series. One hundred is just a number along the way.''</p>
        <p>After last night, the Yankees are still at 99-38. Cone pitched a marvelous game in stifling the A's on one run and four hits, while striking out 10 in seven innings, but he failed to win his major league-best 19th game for the third time as Heredia baffled the Yankees in his second start since Sept. 28, 1996. The 32-year-old right-hander did not allow a run and gave up five hits and no walks in seven and two-thirds innings.</p>
        <p>''In the back of my mind, it's a little frustrating,'' Cone said. ''I've had great run support all year, so I guess I was due for one of these. It's tough to complain when you're sitting on 18 wins and you've had great run support.''</p>
        <p>It did not seem like a positive sign for Heredia when he dispatched one of the bat boys to the Yankee clubhouse to ask the players to autograph a baseball for him. But Heredia was not awed and he did not surrender a hit in four at-bats with runners in scoring position.</p>
        <p>The opportunities against Heredia, who spent most of the last two years in the minors, were scant. Bernie Williams doubled off the right-center-field fence with two outs in the fourth, but Tino Martinez grounded back to Heredia. Scott Brosius lined a one-out double in the eighth but never budged. Derek Jeter poked a two-out single in the sixth, but Heredia picked him off first.</p>
        <p>''You can't say it's our deficiency,'' Yankee Manager Joe Toree said. ''You have to say it's their efficiency.''</p>
        <p>Of Heredia, he said: ''He kept the ball down and mixed up his pitches. He did a good job.''</p>
        <p>Once the game started at 9:49 P.M., with most of the soggy fans still waiting for the Yankees to pursue their 100th, Cone delighted them by striking out Jason McDonald. But Ryan Christenson made sure that Cone would not chase perfection, as David Wells did the night before, by singling. Jason Giambi hit a ball that bounced off the grass and shot past Martinez at first base to advance Christenson to third, and Matt Stairs's tapper to second was hit too slow to turn a double play, so the A's had a 1-0 lead. Christenson homered off Mike Stanton in the eighth for Oakland's other run.</p>
        <p>If the Yanks were concerned about Cone, who had allowed 10 earned runs in his last two starts, there was no need to be worried. He retired 20 of the last 24 batters he opposed, registering nine strikeouts.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees could not score, so their 100th victory was delayed.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>After DAVID WELLS said he did not care about possibly winning the Cy Young award, he admitted that it might happen and said, ''It would probably be the most amazing accomplishment that has ever happened in my baseball career.'' Wells boosted his chances with six and two-thirds perfect innings in a 7-0 victory over the A's on Tuesday to improve to 17-2 with a 3.22 earned run average and five shutouts. If Wells had become the first pitcher in history to toss two perfect games, he said: ''I would call and say I need a week off. I'm going to the Bahamas or something.'' . . . Since CHILI DAVIS has pain in his rib cage while batting from the left side and the Yanks are not going to push DARRYL STRAWBERRY to get into shape to play the outfield, Manager Joe Torre said he might platoon them at designated hitter in the post-season. . . . JEFF NELSON pitched one scoreless inning and DARREN HOLMES allowed one earned run in an inning for Class A Tampa last night. Both relievers, who are rehabilitating from bulging disks in their backs, will rejoin the Yankees tomorrow.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
