<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Belmont, 100 Years Old, Struggles to Keep Up</title>
    <meta content="05LIJO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/05/nyregion/05lijour.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1677781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFD71638F936A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Belmont, 100 Years Old, Struggles to Keep Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Belmont, 100 Years Old, Struggles to Keep Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <dateline>ELMONT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RICHARD MIGLIORE, a seasoned jockey at 41, has been riding horses at Belmont Park ever since his tryout on Belmont Stakes Day in 1978.</p>
        <p>''As a kid my interest in racing was definitely hooked on a lot of champions that ran here,'' said Mr. Migliore, recalling how he watched the magic runs to the Triple Crown by Seattle Slew in 1977 and Affirmed in 1978, capped by victories in the Belmont Stakes. ''I cut my teeth on the best racing you probably could have at the biggest and best racetrack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aside from Belmont Stakes Day, attendance is down at the racetrack on the Queens-Nassau border, hurt by off-track parlors and online and phone betting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RICHARD MIGLIORE, a seasoned jockey at 41, has been riding horses at Belmont Park ever since his tryout on Belmont Stakes Day in 1978.</p>
        <p>''As a kid my interest in racing was definitely hooked on a lot of champions that ran here,'' said Mr. Migliore, recalling how he watched the magic runs to the Triple Crown by Seattle Slew in 1977 and Affirmed in 1978, capped by victories in the Belmont Stakes. ''I cut my teeth on the best racing you probably could have at the biggest and best racetrack.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Migliore is one of only 43 jockeys to win at least 4,000 races, but in his book, no place can beat Belmont, the racetrack on the Queens-Nassau border that turned 100 when it opened for the season on May 4. One sweeping trip around the oval at Belmont's main track is a mile and a half, longer and therefore more difficult than any other track in North America.</p>
        <p>''It's just sheer size and enormity and something about the presence of history here,'' Mr. Migliore said. ''You can feel the ghosts of racing past congregating in this great venue here at Belmont.''</p>
        <p>That feeling is never stronger than on Belmont Stakes Day, the biggest attraction of the 60-day spring and summer meet. Last year, a record 120,139 spectators watched Smarty Jones, the Kentucky Derby and Preakness winner, fall just short of becoming the 12th Triple Crown champion.</p>
        <p>The crowd is expected to swell again June 11 for the 137th running of the Belmont Stakes, the oldest of the races in the Triple Crown. Giacomo, this year's Kentucky Derby winner, and Afleet Alex, who took the Preakness, are both expected to run in the Belmont.</p>
        <p>But aside from opening day and Belmont Stakes Day, crowds exceeding 5,000 are no longer common. Live telecasts of Belmont races at off-track betting parlors and the proliferation of phone and computer betting accounts are some of the reasons that attendance has fallen since Secretariat's 31-length romp into legend in the 1973 Belmont Stakes, said Francis LaBelle Jr., a spokesman for the track. Add to that easy access to casinos in Atlantic City and Connecticut, and you have a real problem.</p>
        <p>Bettors who do venture to the grandstand at Belmont are just as likely to watch and wager on races being simulcast on large-screen televisions from Churchill Downs in Louisville, Ky.; Pimlico in Baltimore; Monmouth Park in Oceanport, N.J.; and other major tracks around the country as they are to lean over the rails to cheer their horses.</p>
        <p>Charles Hayward, the president and chief executive of the New York Racing Association, the nonprofit corporation licensed by the state to conduct racing at Aqueduct, Belmont and Saratoga, first visited Belmont on its 75th anniversary. In 1980, he said, probably 95 percent of betting across the country was done at the track.</p>
        <p>''Today roughly 10 percent of the wagering is done in the live track environment and 90 percent is done in the non-live or off-track environment,'' he said. ''What that does is put the burden on the live track to create a broader entertainment experience for the fans.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayward said that although the beauty of Belmont's sprawling 430-acre park was a draw -- with landscaped ponds in the infield and a family picnic area known as the Backyard -- some bettors like to actually see the horses they are gambling on.</p>
        <p>Like other tracks, Belmont schedules races about every 30 minutes, and a race every half-hour is something that isn't going to be that exciting except for a hard-core fan, Mr. Hayward said.</p>
        <p>Attendance in the 1960's was about two million a year. Last year, it was 670,417, down from 703,544 in 2003. Betting at the track itself totaled $152 million last year, versus $164 million in 2003, and a precipitous drop from $351 million in 1984.</p>
        <p>The upward surge has been in simulcast betting: for example, of the $111,025,435 bet on Belmont Stakes Day last year, only $14,461,402 was bet at the track. The track receives a smaller cut of off-track bets (4 to 8 percent is split between the track and the horsemen) than it does with on-track wagers (9 percent).</p>
        <p>''If we could upgrade our facilities, create a more dynamic simulcasting environment, if we had a couple of sports bars we could build and develop, this could become a place people could watch ballgames as well as bet on the horses,'' Mr. Hayward said.</p>
        <p>While there are no plans to turn Belmont into an entertainment center, the State Legislature has approved big changes for Aqueduct. By the fall of 2006, Mr. Hayward envisions that 4,500 video lottery terminals, the gambling machines known as video slots, will turn that track into a Las Vegas-style betting parlor with restaurants and performances.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a first-class racino,'' Mr. Hayward said, using the term for a combination casino and racetrack. Belmont was not included in the state legislation allowing the video slots at tracks, but he said he thought it might be eventually.</p>
        <p>''Although there won't be a big crossover from the slots customers, the slots revenue will enhance the racing program,'' Mr. Hayward said.</p>
        <p>Standing in the winner's circle after Rodeo Spirit won the first race on opening day, Richard DeStasio, a trainer, said that Belmont was a great place to race but that the lack of fans was troublesome.</p>
        <p>''You go to Saratoga, and you see the fans there, and then you come here -- it is somewhat sad,'' said Mr. DeStasio, who lives in West Hempstead and keeps 12 horses here.</p>
        <p>Saratoga pulled in an average of 29,147 fans a day last year, and Belmont's average daily attendance was 5,981, not including Belmont Stakes Day. The figure was skewed by weekend crowds, but on most days Belmont's attendance is 4,000 or 5,000, said Mr. LaBelle, the track spokesman.</p>
        <p>In the grandstand, John Gibbons, 42, a lawyer from Garden City, had just placed a bet. He said he had been going to Belmont since childhood and visits 15 times a year. ''You come a lot of days now, and it's half-empty,'' he said. ''It is a little depressing. It's no longer the sport of kings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibbons said he bet only at the track. ''Once you have a phone account, it goes from having fun to being serious,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Andy Serling, a 42-year-old options trader from Manhattan, is a serious horseplayer. On opening day he sat at an umbrella table outside the clubhouse, jumping up to check a television monitor when a race began.</p>
        <p>''Purses will hopefully get much better when they get the slots going,'' said Mr. Serling, who says that he picks horses at the track once or twice a week. ''The crowds have thinned because people play from home. The handle has gone up. It's unfortunate because it was much more fun when there were more people were around.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Serling said the proliferation of off-track betting parlors created a false impression that racetracks were ''a bunch of older men sitting inside a room somewhere.''</p>
        <p>''While Aqueduct is more of a city track, Belmont is a beautiful place and a great way to spend an afternoon,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Inside the cavernous grandstand, groups of men gathered in front of simulcast screens, Daily Racing Forms clutched in their hands.</p>
        <p>Jerry Curtin, 38, of Farmingville, kept his eyes on races from Churchill Downs and Pimlico. Mr. Curtin, who works for the Suffolk County medical examiner's office and has been going to Belmont for 20 years, said he bet on simulcast races between the live races at Belmont.</p>
        <p>And simulcasts, he said, represent the future.</p>
        <p>''It's boring every half-hour,'' Mr. Curtin said. ''Now they have action every 10 minutes. It's a nice fill-in.''</p>
        <p>The prospect of video slots was even more enticing. ''It beats driving to Atlantic City,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Horse racing in New York has troubles beyond dwindling crowds. Earlier this year, a thoroughbred trainer and a harness driver were accused of doping horses at Aqueduct. The racing association's operations are under court-appointed monitor until July because of federal fraud charges in a scandal involving mutuel clerks. And the association's state franchise to run the three tracks is up for renewal in July 2006, and other strong bidders are likely.</p>
        <p>Yet Belmont teems with memories that are larger than life.</p>
        <p>In the barn area, Allen Jerkens, a Hall of Fame trainer from Bellerose Terrace, was watching a rambunctious chestnut named Great Lady K kick her way around a fenced-in playpen.</p>
        <p>''I have a lot of great memories here,'' said Mr. Jerkens, 76, who is often called the Chief and the Giant Killer for upsetting some of the great horses of all time. His horse Prove Out defeated Secretariat at Belmont in 1973 and his Beau Purple beat Kelso in the Man o' War Stakes in 1962.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jerkens started at Belmont as a 16-year-old exercise boy and rode the steeplechase course in 1946.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't any good at it,'' said Mr. Jerkens, who has 34 horses in the barn here.</p>
        <p>The steeplechase course is long gone, as well as a 6 1/2-furlong straight course. But Belmont is still a great place to be a horse. The mile-and-a-half outer dirt oval rings two turf courses. Horses can also stretch their legs on a separate mile-long training track and a quarter-mile pony track.</p>
        <p>Beyond the track is a village with dormitories that can house up to 865 grooms and hot-walkers, and there is even a day care center. The 62 barns with stalls for 2,200 horses, once privately owned by people with names like Vanderbilt and Phipps, are now assigned by the racing association.</p>
        <p>Some vestiges of the crowds of more glorious times have been reclaimed on Sundays with family-oriented days that include petting zoos, miniature golf, magicians and face painting. Breakfasts at Belmont, held on Saturday and Sunday mornings, include a guided tour of the barns and trackside commentary by Mary Ryan, the first woman licensed as a jockey, in Maryland in 1968.</p>
        <p>Looking for a permanent home for thoroughbred racing, in 1902 the Westchester Racing Association bought the land for $500 an acre. Local residents, who were led to believe it was going to be a cemetery or housing project, did not protest.</p>
        <p>On opening day in 1905, 40,000 people showed up, many in their horseless carriages, causing the Island's first traffic jam.</p>
        <p>But Belmont Park has always been about more than horses. The Wright brothers were on hand in October 1910 when Belmont was the site for an international aviation tournament, including a race around the Statue of Liberty. In 1918, Belmont served as the New York terminus for the first American airmail service; the first airmail flight, to Washington, left from the infield. Flights to Boston and Chicago were added before the terminal was shifted to Roosevelt Field.</p>
        <p>Mr. Migliore, the jockey, said that even with smaller crowds, riding a horse at Belmont was incomparable.</p>
        <p>''It's like when you are a kid, and your dad brought you out to Yankee Stadium,'' he said. ''Belmont still holds that for me as I ride a horse through the tunnel from the paddock and up the ramp and then it opens that beautiful expanse of green and racetrack.''</p>
        <p>Richard Teuten, 42, an electronics technician from West Babylon, gathers with about 30 friends and family members at least once every two weeks for a picnic and some wagering in Belmont's verdant Backyard, using the computerized betting machines and watching the action on television monitors.</p>
        <p>''I like to think I'm a handicapper,'' he said. At that point, just before the seventh race on opening day, he was down about $100 but was still hopeful.</p>
        <p>Mr. Teuten said he had a phone-betting account but still preferred placing his bets in person.</p>
        <p>''The thrill is here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
