<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Love Thy Busybody</title>
    <meta content="05AGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/05/fashion/sundaystyles/05age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1677836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E7D61738F936A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Love Thy Busybody</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Love Thy Busybody</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For city folk, a country house brings all kinds of unwanted distractions. In the small Catskills village where I recently bought a second home, there are bears and neighbors. Last weekend I saw more than my share of the latter.</p>
        <p>One in particular. She lingers across the street at her picket fence, which is hung with American flags, a ''God Bless America'' wreath, pinwheels and plastic flowers. Not the kind of thing you'd find in the Hamptons or a shelter magazine. And not the kind of thing I want to look at every time I go for a walk in the cool mountain air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a world where neighborliness has been replaced by iron gates and surveillance cameras, the term "nosy neighbor" isn't so pejorative anymore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For city folk, a country house brings all kinds of unwanted distractions. In the small Catskills village where I recently bought a second home, there are bears and neighbors. Last weekend I saw more than my share of the latter.</p>
        <p>One in particular. She lingers across the street at her picket fence, which is hung with American flags, a ''God Bless America'' wreath, pinwheels and plastic flowers. Not the kind of thing you'd find in the Hamptons or a shelter magazine. And not the kind of thing I want to look at every time I go for a walk in the cool mountain air.</p>
        <p>But hey, it's a free country. In theory.</p>
        <p>''This is to put up on your house,'' Mrs. Neighbor, let's call her, 76 and a widow, said when she came over with an extra flag. ''It's the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>Probably so. But as she walked away in her floral housedress to continue holding court, I couldn't help wondering, Must she be quite so present? Sure, the city is always more anonymous than the country, but I'm sorry, my weekends are supposed to be about communing with nature, not others.</p>
        <p>Well, every town, small, large, real or fictional, has its busybodies. ''Desperate Housewives'' featured several last season. And Gladys Kravitz, the prying neighbor from ''Bewitched,'' will appear in the movie version soon.</p>
        <p>But guess what? In a world where neighborliness has been replaced by iron gates, surveillance cameras and bloodless Internet interactions, the terms ''busybody'' and ''nosy neighbor'' aren't so pejorative anymore.</p>
        <p>Crime specialists say that with working couples now more inclined to hire help than to mow their own lawns, the more buttinsky your neighbors, the better. Local news editors even rely on them for close-hand observations. And when you are selling a house, real estate agents say, nosy neighbors, often very social, may have good buyer contacts.</p>
        <p>So whether we know it or not, and though we like to think we're aloof, independent and only interested in talking to people who interest us for superficial reasons like how they dress or what they do for a living, we need these well-meaning nosy neighbors, disturbing our peace and making us participate in life.</p>
        <p>Mine, when she knew we needed help, came over with the names of an excellent contractor and a reliable gardener. She kept her eye on a package that sat on the front porch while the house was empty. She even watered my azaleas when they got parched.</p>
        <p>Sure, I have to listen to her stories when I would rather be listening to the birds and musing over my lilacs. But to see her walk out her gate in her gaudy, holiday-themed outfits -- to attend parties for the town's not-so-privileged schoolchildren, whom she has lavished with attention for years as a cafeteria aide -- is to see another kind of force of nature: a well-meaning woman with no agenda but to keep things amusing.</p>
        <p>''Everybody in this town knows who I am,'' she told me, ''that's for sure.''</p>
        <p>Last Monday, Memorial Day, she appeared at my door in red, white and blue, with little stars cascading off her ears, to announce that the tiny village parade was about to begin. She would be marching, as she does every year, with the children who had won the annual patriotic essay contest she started at the elementary school 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>I found myself calling out to her as she marched past, pleased to know her, just as I was at the memorial service later, where she stood with the town leaders, listening as each of her little essay contest winners, gaudily bedecked and terribly proud, read to the crowd.</p>
        <p>''These kids are just so wonderful,'' she said. ''It's very rewarding.''</p>
        <p>Her next effort will be organizing for Flag Day. And then the Fourth of July, Columbus Day, Halloween and who knows what else.</p>
        <p>''You're becoming part of the community now,'' she told me after the parade.</p>
        <p>I guess so. And to thank her for being such a welcoming neighbor, I gave her a cap embroidered with a fiber-optic flag that lights up like a fireworks display.</p>
        <p>''Oh my,'' she cooed as she tried it out. ''I can't wait to show this to the children.''</p>
        <p>And everyone else she meets, no doubt.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF DISSONANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
