<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinner-Party Roulette: Who's in the Next Chair?</title>
    <meta content="28feed" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/28/dining/28feed.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="FEED ME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Research in Motion Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beard, James (1903-85)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3D91730F93BA15755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinner-Party Roulette: Who's in the Next Chair?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dinner-Party Roulette: Who's in the Next Chair?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Witchel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex Witchel article on attending a charity event at which she was seated next to 'Hollywood Big Shot' who was totally absorbed in his BlackBerry; gives James Beard recipe for pasta; photo; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU know the moment, walking around the table at a wedding or a charity event, looking for your name card. Joy means you're tucked between two people you like. Misery means wailing to the person you came with, ''Who's that?'' at the stranger's name next to yours.</p>
        <p>I remember a friend once racing over after discovering she was seated next to a newspaper publisher. ''I don't know anything about business,'' she fretted. ''What should I say?'' Half joking, my husband advised, ''Ask about the price of newsprint.'' Three hours later we saw her again, eyes glazed, but grateful. ''One question, and he talked all night,'' she marveled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At charity events and weddings, what's worse than the food? Sitting next to the Blackberry-addled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU know the moment, walking around the table at a wedding or a charity event, looking for your name card. Joy means you're tucked between two people you like. Misery means wailing to the person you came with, ''Who's that?'' at the stranger's name next to yours.</p>
        <p>I remember a friend once racing over after discovering she was seated next to a newspaper publisher. ''I don't know anything about business,'' she fretted. ''What should I say?'' Half joking, my husband advised, ''Ask about the price of newsprint.'' Three hours later we saw her again, eyes glazed, but grateful. ''One question, and he talked all night,'' she marveled.</p>
        <p>I hardly considered her plight a blessing, until I found myself at one of these affairs recently, seated next to a Hollywood Big Shot. He seemed sociable enough at the outset, when people introduced themselves before sitting down.</p>
        <p>Though the temptation at these events is to skip that part and hide behind the centerpiece, it does pay to learn the cast of characters. With large tables, you can't possibly speak to everyone, so you don't want to do something stupid and end up, say, snubbing your boss's new girlfriend. Conversely, a greeting like, ''I'm John Smith, and I'm running for comptroller of North Dakota,'' is exactly the kind of hello and goodbye to look out for.</p>
        <p>At this recent dinner, I met all assembled, including Mrs. Hollywood Big Shot, who seemed perfectly pleasant. Then I sat down and talked with the man to my left, who was downright delightful. All was well until the entrees were served, the accepted moment to switch conversational partners, no matter how much fun you're having. The Big Shot, hereafter known as B.S., did not notice the entree. Nor did he need to be torn away from speaking to the very young, very pretty woman to his right. Nor was he casting pining glances across the table at his perfectly pleasant wife. B.S. was completely absorbed in his BlackBerry.</p>
        <p>I turned to Delightful on my left and motioned toward B.S. ''What's up with that?'' I asked, knowing the two were friends. He laughed. ''He does it all the time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He does? Unacceptable. Because like everything else in life, these events have rules. You almost never go because you really want to; you go because you really have to. Weddings, all family extravaganzas, are emotionally fraught by definition. Charity dinners, however worthy, are about stroking egos, hence the endless speeches. An hour in, you silently swear that next year you'll write a check and stay home.</p>
        <p>But that's next year. If you showed up this year, that means the outside world must fend for itself while you turn off all electronic devices and devote yourself full time to playing chair hockey with the waiter tilting the overloaded serving platter directly toward the back of your neck.</p>
        <p>I noticed that B.S.'s perfectly pleasant wife, blissfully ensconced in a conversation of her own, was completely ignoring him. So I forced myself to make an effort. Peering sideways at his BlackBerry, I found B.S. studying his schedule for the following day. Boldface names galore.</p>
        <p>''Busy day, eh?'' I said, leaning toward him.</p>
        <p>''Uh-huh,'' he answered, never lifting his head. If that counts as a word, it was the only one he uttered all night. To my left, Delightful pushed his plate away and laughed.</p>
        <p>The plate got my attention. Lasagna. Delightful doesn't eat meat. I looked at my lamb chops, raw on one side, desiccated on the other. I don't eat that kind of meat, either. He moved his plate over and we each took a nibble. Yuck. It doesn't help these events that the food is so consistently vile.</p>
        <p>Maybe hunger was at the root of B.S.'s problem. He hadn't taken a bite all night, starved, in that ersatz warrior mode so prized among Hollywood executives, that glorifies asceticism and scorns indulgence. A square of sashimi? Hercules in the boardroom. A plate of pasta? Thumbelina at best.</p>
        <p>But B.S. never succumbed to enemy forces. Not one forkful passed his clenched lips. I noticed that the very young, very pretty woman to his right had just gotten up and left him there. It was too much to hope that she might come back with a pizza.</p>
        <p>I started daydreaming about dinner. Baked ziti? Not after this lasagna. What then? Something cozy, something filling. James Beard's Pleasant Pasta? Yes, that really is its name. And while I wouldn't serve it to my cardiologist, for this group, it would be the perfect choice. Thumbelina, dance!</p>
        <p>James Beard's Pleasant Pasta  Adapted from ''The Fannie Farmer Cookbook,'' revised by Marion Cunningham (Alfred A. Knopf, 1996)  Time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>Salt  1 pound spaghetti  110-ounce package frozen peas  4 tablespoons butter</p>
        <p>1/2 pound thinly sliced prosciutto di Parma, rolled up and cut in  1/4-inch-wide strips</p>
        <p>2/3 cup heavy cream  Freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>1/2 to  3/4 cup grated Parmesan cheese; more as needed.</p>
        <p>1.  Bring a large pot of lightly salted water to a boil. Add pasta, and cook until just tender. While pasta cooks combine peas and 1 cup water in a small saucepan. Bring to a boil, and stir until peas are thoroughly heated. Drain and set aside.  2.  Drain pasta, return to pot and toss with butter. Add peas, prosciutto and cream. Toss to mix well and to separate prosciutto strips. Season with salt and pepper to taste. Add Parmesan to taste, and toss again. Serve piping hot, passing more Parmesan separately at the table.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FEED ME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
