<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Mr. Chow, Same Formula</title>
    <meta content="28rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/28/dining/reviews/28rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mr Chow Tribeca (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Chow, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4D91730F93BA15755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Mr. Chow, Same Formula</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Mr. Chow, Same Formula</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Bruni reviews Mr Chow Tribeca; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S easy to see the bad in things and harder to see the good. Take Mr. Chow Tribeca. There are sane, prudent, well-intentioned people who will tell you why you should avoid this new outpost of a nutty empire, and they'll be indisputably correct. But with a slight adjustment of perspective, a certain generosity of spirit and a bit of willed enthusiasm, many reasons for embracing it can be found.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 1: You can participate in a strand of social history and mull over the eccentric genius of Michael Chow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. Chow TriBeCa stays true to its predecessor's formula: a mixture of familiar and less familiar Chinese food in a slick setting with formally attired servers and an aura of clubby exclusivity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S easy to see the bad in things and harder to see the good. Take Mr. Chow Tribeca. There are sane, prudent, well-intentioned people who will tell you why you should avoid this new outpost of a nutty empire, and they'll be indisputably correct. But with a slight adjustment of perspective, a certain generosity of spirit and a bit of willed enthusiasm, many reasons for embracing it can be found.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 1: You can participate in a strand of social history and mull over the eccentric genius of Michael Chow.</p>
        <p>Almost four decades ago Mr. Chow, who fled Mao Zedong's China for England, had an inspiration. Why not take Chinese food, at that point still somewhat exotic in the West, and swathe it in exaggerated elegance? Tether it to exorbitant prices? Make it fabulous, simply by declaring it to be?</p>
        <p>First came a Mr. Chow in London, then a Mr. Chow in Los Angeles, and then, in 1979, a Mr. Chow in New York, on East 57th Street. Like its forebears it proved that you didn't need great cooking to attract boldface names; you just needed other boldface names. And Mr. Chow, the Amy Sacco of an earlier era, got them in the door, mining contacts in the overlapping worlds of art, fashion and all-purpose elitism. Regulars included Andy Warhol, who, Mr. Chow has said, didn't so much eat his food as play with it. An understandable decision.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chow Tribeca stays true to the template. There are white tablecloths; waiters in white or black jackets and bow ties; a gleaming black bar in front; gleaming white lighting fixtures hanging from the ceiling. The restaurant looks and feels like a slick parody of a suave Italian restaurant, like an oxymoronic experiment in haute kitsch.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 2: Once you've visited Mr. Chow Tribeca, you will appreciate your favorite neighborhood Chinese takeout place like never before.</p>
        <p>The menu at Mr. Chow, which supposedly fuses various Chinese regional traditions, advertises many familiar dishes: scallion pancakes, shark's fin soup, pot stickers, crispy beef, beef with oyster sauce, sweet-and-sour pork. What's unfamiliar is how much they cost.</p>
        <p>For that pork, you pay $29. For crab meat soup, $13. Were there discernible crab in it, you'd understand. But there wasn't, so my companions and I didn't.</p>
        <p>There are also less ubiquitous dishes, along with dishes that -- as servers announce with inexplicable fanfare -- are making their Mr. Chow debuts. One is ''fiery buffalo,'' which wasn't fiery or, for that matter, particularly hot. Was it buffalo? The cubes of bland flesh could have come from any number of beasts or birds. And for $31.50, there weren't many cubes. If I'm going to get a main course this mediocre, I'd at least like more of it.</p>
        <p>Most of the food was precisely that -- mediocre, not bad -- and some of it was quite good. Peking duck had dazzlingly crisp skin and an appealing measure of fat. Sliced pork with chili peppers had an appealing measure of heat. Fried rice was never oily or clumpy.</p>
        <p>But almost none of the dishes improved significantly on cheaper analogues around town, and a few were unforgivable. Asked to steer us toward the best lamb dish, a server chose a minimally spiced shank. If I learned that it had been plucked from a freezer after the better part of a decade and then nuked in a microwave for the better part of a day, I'd be shocked. It didn't taste nearly that tender or flavorful.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 3: You will encounter a kind of service so aggressive at certain times and incoherent at others that it becomes a divine comedy.</p>
        <p>At the start of each meal, servers push expensive Champagne. (''For a toast! How about a toast? Don't you want to make a toast?'') They do it even if you have a full martini in front of you. Even if you have already said no.</p>
        <p>During two visits servers pitched desserts in the middle of a meal, not realizing that our table was empty because we were between appetizers and entrees. And they weren't daunted by not having much to pitch: some ice cream, some fruit, maybe two tarts, unless they run out of one. Of course they ran out of one -- at about 9 p.m. on a night that wasn't busy.</p>
        <p>On a slightly busier night, it took repeated pleas and 25 minutes to get a check. Once we were done with spending, our servers were done with us.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 4: You can get excited about spotting a celebrity, though you may not actually lay eyes on one.</p>
        <p>You know that the possibility exists, because Mr. Chow is the kind of restaurant whose opening is noted in Us magazine, not Saveur.</p>
        <p>But celebrities are like the best animals at the zoo: theoretically present in the designated exhibit but always obscured by a bush or boulder just when you're looking. I arrived at Mr. Chow late one Friday night to be told by a waiting companion that I had just missed Tobey Maguire. Had my companion seen him? Well, he said, sort of, but.</p>
        <p>Reason No. 5: You may indeed lay eyes on Mr. Chow. On a Sunday night I watched him bop from table to table, peering through those owlish glasses. Like Sir Elton and Dame Edna, he gets a lot of iconic mileage out of eyewear.</p>
        <p>His is made for him by Cutler &amp; Gross in London. His prescription adjusts problems with near and far sight. I learned this because I called his Los Angeles offices for information about the restaurant and he insisted on getting on the phone. We had to talk about something. Food seemed beside the point.</p>
        <p>But vision, well, that made sense. Mr. Chow, now 67, foresaw that salt-and-pepper prawns and squid in XO sauce could be vessels for an aura of clubby exclusivity. You just had to season them with enough amusing mannerisms. And regard them with the right kind of attitude.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chow Tribeca  SATISFACTORY  121 Hudson Street (North Moore Street), TriBeCa; (212) 965-9500.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A room with lacquered black and white surfaces and waiters in black and white jackets is the sleek stage set for less impressive food.  SOUND LEVEL -- Moderately painful when crowded.  RECOMMENDED DISHES  -- Water dumplings; pot stickers; crispy beef; sliced pork with chili; Beijing duck; gamblers duck.  WINE LIST  -- International, overpriced and not especially interesting.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $5.50 to $25. Entrees, $26 to $36. Desserts, $10.  HOURS  -- Dinner 6 to 11:30 p.m. seven days a week. Lunch to be added in coming months.  RESERVATIONS -- For prime times, call about two weeks in advance.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Separate entrance on North Moore Street and separate restroom.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:  (None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics:  nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
