<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Horror Movie Adds Shudders to a Shooter</title>
    <meta content="15GAME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/15/technology/15GAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1277933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Electronic Arts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD1F3AF936A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Horror Movie Adds Shudders to a Shooter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles Herold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herold Charles reviews Clive Barker's Undying, new video game published by Electronic Arts; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLIVE BARKER'S UNDYING  (Published by Electronic Arts and developed by EALA; $39.95; for Windows 95, 98 and Me; for ages 17 and older.)</p>
        <p>HOW could I have saved my father from a slow, painful death?'' Ambrose Covenant muses in his journal. ''I could have hit him harder.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLIVE BARKER'S UNDYING  (Published by Electronic Arts and developed by EALA; $39.95; for Windows 95, 98 and Me; for ages 17 and older.)</p>
        <p>HOW could I have saved my father from a slow, painful death?'' Ambrose Covenant muses in his journal. ''I could have hit him harder.''</p>
        <p>The Covenants are not a nice family. The antagonists of Clive Barker's Undying from Electronic Arts are a group of siblings, most of them dead, who cause a remarkable amount of trouble. Fighting against this evil brood is Patrick Galloway, who has traveled back to his Irish homeland to help his friend Jeremiah Covenant eradicate the family curse.</p>
        <p>Undying begins not with a bang but with a shudder. On the grounds of the Covenant estate, a large, creepy mansion, Patrick has a vision of himself hanging from a lamp. Approaching Jeremiah's door, he is accosted by malevolent spirits. The game is wildly cinematic, and when you see a pack of demons running over a hilltop, catch sight of a ghost in the mirror or walk through a hall of billowing curtains, it is as if you are not watching a horror movie but actually living in one.</p>
        <p>Integrating a story into a game can be a tricky procedure, and after a few months of work on Undying, an expert was called in: Clive Barker, a horror novelist. He spent a year discussing characterization and plot with the designers while the game was being built.</p>
        <p>Games are still struggling to hit that perfect balance between story and action. Too much action and the story is lost; too much story and there is not enough play. The latter happened in Blair Witch Volume II: The Legend of Coffin Rock, which had a wonderful narrative device.  The lead character retraced a path he had taken a few days earlier, and the game moved back and forth between two time periods, each with its own story and events. Blair Witch had an interesting plot and incredible atmosphere, but a shortage of actual game play. That was probably for the best because the game play that was there was rather mediocre.</p>
        <p>Undying manages to combine enough story for a movie with enough action for a game. As atmospheric as Blair Witch, it has far superior action, excellent design and entertaining weapons (including spells that will let Patrick fire lightning bolts or turn vanquished foes into zombies) to keep you engrossed.</p>
        <p>Playing Undying is like reading a book you just can't put down. Bleary-eyed, you stay up through the night, pulled from one event to the next. Partly told through journal entries and letters from Jeremiah's four siblings, Undying reveals more and more of the sinister Covenant curse as Patrick explores the estate and neighboring locations, battling innumerable demons as he tracks down Jeremiah's demonic relatives.</p>
        <p>A good game tells its story on two levels, combining the characteristic narrative of a film with an underlying kinetic narrative that is a collaboration between game and player.  In a film we watch the hero beat up the bad guys and save the hostages, but in a game the player chooses the weapons and decides when to fight and when to run.</p>
        <p>Undying does a good job with that kinetic narrative but overlays far more story than most games, giving it its ''living in a movie'' feel. A movie requires an orderly sequence of events, and to achieve that, Undying puts the player in a virtual straitjacket. The Covenant Estate has many rooms, but Patrick can open only a few doors at any particular time in the game. Doors that opened earlier will later be jammed shut, while other doors will suddenly swing open easily. Ghostly laughter the first few times Patrick tries to open a stuck door implies that spirits are forcing him toward a particular goal, but it is hard to understand why the ghosts would be so kind as to guide Patrick toward the things he needs destroy them.</p>
        <p>While preventing the player from wandering around aimlessly for hours is a worthy goal, the stuck doors seem like a cheap trick. A map and a compass might have made for a more elegant solution.</p>
        <p>As Undying progresses, it becomes less of an interactive movie and more of a standard first-person shooter. While there are plenty of remarkable moments -- candles gutter and go out; a rainstorm suddenly clears as you reach an old house -- the story begins to fall apart.</p>
        <p>Some things are poorly explained, like Patrick's relationship to Bethany Covenant's diabolic colleague  Keisinger or the nature and origin of the supernatural land Oneiros. With an unconvincing and anticlimactic ending, Undying has little emotional resonance. You generally don't expect emotional resonance from a game, and Undying should be lauded for creating such high expectations, even if it doesn't fulfill them.</p>
        <p>A game's interactive quality is so central that it can carry the player along past plot imperfections that would sink a film. Undying would probably make a decent movie, but as a game it gives you more. Because no matter how good the story, no matter how scary the monsters, no movie lets you get up and hack a demon's head off with a scythe.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
