<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seoul Journal; Ex-Enemy of the State Sees His Chance to Lead It</title>
    <meta content="Y24KOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D9133BF937A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seoul Journal; Ex-Enemy of the State Sees His Chance to Lead It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kim Dae Jung, long time opposition leader who has survived number of assassination plots by South Korean aides, is leading in polls for Dec's presidential vote; would be first opposition leader elected to post; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was on the grounds of the sprawling presidential mansion here that Government officials hatched successive plans for eliminating their enemy, first by killing him in a car accident, then by drowning him in the ocean, and finally by having him executed by hanging.</p>
        <p>But the presidential staff in those days was more persistent than efficient, and none of these plans worked. And so the next occupant of the presidential mansion may be that onetime enemy, Kim Dae Jung.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was on the grounds of the sprawling presidential mansion here that Government officials hatched successive plans for eliminating their enemy, first by killing him in a car accident, then by drowning him in the ocean, and finally by having him executed by hanging.</p>
        <p>But the presidential staff in those days was more persistent than efficient, and none of these plans worked. And so the next occupant of the presidential mansion may be that onetime enemy, Kim Dae Jung.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim, who would presumably bring a new staff of aides to the mansion, has been an opposition leader in South Korea so long that it is difficult to conceive of him as President. He is still lame from the first attempt to assassinate him, when a truck crashed into his car and killed his driver, but if the polls are right then Mr. Kim may soon be able to limp up the great central stairs of the presidential mansion and claim it as his own.</p>
        <p>A somber man with a thickening middle but a full head of jet black hair, a fiery orator one moment and a patient statesman the next, Mr. Kim is consistently leading in all the opinion polls for the presidential election in December. To everyone's surprise -- except his own -- he is widely regarded as enjoying by far his best chance ever of leading the country.</p>
        <p>A victory by Mr. Kim would be a landmark for Korea and East Asia as a whole, marking the first time in Korean history that an opposition leader had been elected President. South Korea has had reasonably free elections in recent years, but the same pattern has emerged here as in Japan and Taiwan: one party dominates the Government and is nagged by an opposition that is free to speak but usually unable to win the top post.</p>
        <p>''In the 50 years since we became an independent country, we've never had a peaceful transition of the Government, in which an opposition party became a ruling party,'' Mr. Kim reflected in a long conversation in his office in the National Assembly. ''For that reason, the Government became corrupted and static, and reform cannot be implemented.''</p>
        <p>It is a sign of South Korea's increasing maturity as a democracy that Mr. Kim could almost certainly take office if elected. In the 1987 campaign, army officers warned that they might be forced to stage a coup or even kill him if he were chosen President. But now, by all accounts, the army would -- if a bit grudgingly -- accept him as the country's leader.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the secretive Agency for National Security Planning would have to make adjustments if Mr. Kim is elected, such as spying for him instead of on him. Mr. Kim, who believes his phones are still wiretapped along with those of many other Koreans -- a charge that almost everybody finds credible -- says he would like to restructure the intelligence agency to curb its domestic spying. But even the agency could probably accept Mr. Kim as President.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that the people at the agency are too afraid of him,'' a prominent Korean official said with a grin. ''They think they can handle anybody.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kim is now the front-runner, some experts still regard his election as unlikely. At the last minute, voters may rally around the ruling party candidate if they think that Mr. Kim would otherwise be elected. A large number of Koreans worry that Mr. Kim is soft on Communism, or else is a demagogue, or else is simply an old man whose time has passed.</p>
        <p>''In American age, I'm 71,'' Mr. Kim mused with a twinkle in his eye (Korean ages often include a year awarded at birth and another at the beginning of each year, instead of waiting for a birthday). ''But for 6 years I was in prison and for 10 years I was held under house arrest and exile, so those 16 years should be deducted. Then I'm only 55.''</p>
        <p>One indication of the suspicions in Korean politics is that the governing party suggests that Mr. Kim is lying about his birth date and that he is actually a couple of years older. Indeed, at times Mr. Kim has used a birth date that would suggest that he is now 73.</p>
        <p>Another of Mr. Kim's fundamental challenges is that, as his critics see it, he has been reduced to being a regional candidate from his native Cholla area, which is in the southwestern part of the country and is stigmatized as poor, uncouth and unruly. Many respectable Korean families today would be appalled if their daughter were to try to marry a man from Cholla, and they sometimes feel the same way about voting for a candidate from Cholla.</p>
        <p>In the last presidential race, in 1992, Mr. Kim received 90 percent of the vote from the Cholla provinces and just 27 percent in the rest of the country -- many of those coming from people who had migrated from Cholla. The bedrock of support from Cholla and from devoted loyalists around the country means that Mr. Kim is likely to receive about a third of the overall vote nationwide, and that could be a plurality if the rest of the vote is split among the three or four other major candidates.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people think that this time there is a strong possibility that Kim Dae Jung will win the presidential race,'' said Kang Tae Hoon, a professor of political science at Dankook University in Seoul.</p>
        <p>[The ruling party's crisis worsened -- and Mr. Kim's chances of winning the presidency improved -- when a popular politician, Rhee In Je, announced he would leave the ruling party and run for President on his own. Polls show that if the election were held now Mr. Rhee would come in second, after Mr. Kim, and that the ruling party candidate, Lee Hoi Chang, would come in third.]</p>
        <p>Partly because of his search for middle-class votes, Mr. Kim has moderated his political and economic views in recent years. As head of the main opposition party, the National Congress for New Politics, he is still a bit more sympathetic to labor and to a Government role in rescuing failed enterprises than the leaders of the New Korea Party are, but the differences in policy between him and the other candidates are much less than they were in past years.</p>
        <p>Ra Jong Il, a political scientist at Kyung Hee University, noted that even as it has moved to democracy in recent years, South Korea has found it difficult to differentiate state power from politics. The tendency is still for the incumbent to use the police, courts, tax authorities and other powers of the state to tilt the playing field against his opponents.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ra argues that Mr. Kim's election would end that tendency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
