<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Word, Dictionary's Title Stands</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DICTIONARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOGOTYPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRADEMARKS AND TRADE NAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MERRIAM-WEBSTER INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RANDOM HOUSE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, RONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D9153BF937A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Word, Dictionary's Title Stands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, RONALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal appeals court has apparently had the last word in a war over words in the United States Court House in Manhattan in ruling that a jacket design on a dictionary published by Random House was not an unlawful copy of a similar red cover on a dictionary published by Merriam-Webster.</p>
        <p>A jury verdict two years ago awarded Merriam-Webster $2 million in damages on the ground that Random House's jacket "diluted" the value of Merriam-Webster's trademarked combination of the words "Webster's" and "Collegiate" in its title and that it both intentionally infringed and diluted Merriam-Webster's distinctive red-and-white cover with its singular bull's eye logo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal appeals court has apparently had the last word in a war over words in the United States Court House in Manhattan in ruling that a jacket design on a dictionary published by Random House was not an unlawful copy of a similar red cover on a dictionary published by Merriam-Webster.</p>
        <p>A jury verdict two years ago awarded Merriam-Webster $2 million in damages on the ground that Random House's jacket "diluted" the value of Merriam-Webster's trademarked combination of the words "Webster's" and "Collegiate" in its title and that it both intentionally infringed and diluted Merriam-Webster's distinctive red-and-white cover with its singular bull's eye logo.</p>
        <p>But in overturning the jury's verdict and in dismissing Merriam-Webster's complaint, the Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit ruled last week that Merriam-Webster suffered no dilution of either its trademarked combination of words or its distinctive red-and-white cover.</p>
        <p>In an unanimous verdict written by Judge John M. Walker and supported by Judges Thomas J. Meskill and George C. Pratt, the court said, "No confusion or likelihood of confusion exists between the respective jackets." Matter of Marketing</p>
        <p>Merriam-Webster, the largest publisher of dictionaries, sued Random House in 1990 when Random House inserted the word "Webster's" and retitled its dictionary Webster's College Dictionary.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Rosenthal, a Random House lawyer, argued that anyone publishing a dictionary without the name "Webster's" in its title was fighting a losing marketing battle.</p>
        <p>The competing use of Noah Webster's last name alone was not at issue because the 19th-century lexicographer has become a household name for any kind of dictionary and its not held under copyright or trademark.</p>
        <p>But Merriam-Webster argued that Random House's use of the word "Webster's" with "College" violated its trademarked use of the combination of the two words in its dictionary at issue in the case, Webster's Ninth New Collegiate Dictionary. It contended that book stores and buyers would confuse its dictionary with the one published by Random House.</p>
        <p>But the court disagreed. It said, "It is virtually inconceivable that a bookseller would call Random House believing it was Merriam-Webster." It also said, "There was no testimony by any consumer, retail or wholesale, who intended to buy a Merriam-Webster dictionary but mistakenly bought a Random House dictionary because of confusion between the two product's trade dresses."</p>
        <p>Ellis Levine, general counsel at Random House, said, "We're extremely gratified because the ruling completely vindicates our position."</p>
        <p>In a statement, Thomas Stanley, Merriam-Webster's publisher, said that he was disappointed by the ruling and that he would "consider to seek its review."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
