<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers Foes Keep Watching Skies</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARVIN, AL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D7153BF937A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers Foes Keep Watching Skies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL HARVIN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARVIN, AL</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rutgers Coach Doug Graber has an imposing name for his tailback combination of Bruce Presley and Terrell Willis, the back-to-back Big East rookies of the year the last two seasons. Graber dubbed the two running backs Thunder and Lightning, and with both of them returning after combining for 2,002 yards last season, the coach had hoped they would have opponents seeking shelter this season.</p>
        <p>The 5-foot-10-inch, 215-pound Presley, a junior, is designated Thunder because of his straight-ahead, run-over-people style. The 6-0, 200-pound Willis, a sophomore, is called Lightning because of his speed and moves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rutgers Coach Doug Graber has an imposing name for his tailback combination of Bruce Presley and Terrell Willis, the back-to-back Big East rookies of the year the last two seasons. Graber dubbed the two running backs Thunder and Lightning, and with both of them returning after combining for 2,002 yards last season, the coach had hoped they would have opponents seeking shelter this season.</p>
        <p>The 5-foot-10-inch, 215-pound Presley, a junior, is designated Thunder because of his straight-ahead, run-over-people style. The 6-0, 200-pound Willis, a sophomore, is called Lightning because of his speed and moves.</p>
        <p>The two basically ran out of the same tailback position last season as Willis led the Big East in rushing with 1,261 yards on 195 carries.</p>
        <p>This year, they are co-starters at tailback, but they haven't struck with the same force as last year. Graber is counting on that to change Saturday, when the 2-0 Scarlet Knights visit Syracuse for a crucial conference matchup.  Blue Skies, So Far</p>
        <p>Presley and Willis have combined for only 222 yards on 56 carries, and haven't been a major factor in Rutgers' two victories, a 28-6 decision over Kent and a 17-12 triumph over a struggling West Virginia team last Saturday.</p>
        <p>Is everybody keying on Presley and Willis this year?</p>
        <p>"Obviously, they are, but they're not playing nine-man fronts all the time," Graber said. "We can't continue to win unless we control the ball on the offensive side and on the defensive side."</p>
        <p>Syracuse, 1-1 after a 30-29 loss to Oklahoma in the opener and a 34-19 victory at Cincinnati this past weekend, has not lost a game to Rutgers in their past seven meetings. Coach Paul Pasqualoni, in his fourth season at the helm for the Orange, is 3-0 against Graber, who is starting his fifth year in charge at Rutgers. But Pasqualoni is still wary of the two explosive running backs.</p>
        <p>"I think it's just a matter of time," Pasqualoni said. "Sooner or later, those guys are going to break loose. They scare me to death." New-Look Defense</p>
        <p>What probably scares Pasqualoni more about Rutgers is the team's improved defense. John Gutenkunst, Rutgers' new defensive coordinator imported from the University of Minnesota, has switched Rutgers to a 4-3 alignment.</p>
        <p>"We've never played against John Gutenkunst," Pasqualoni said. "It's very hard to figure out what they will be playing against us. I don't know whether they'll do some of the things that Coach Graber has done through the years.</p>
        <p>"I don't know what they'll do against our option and how they're going to handle all of that. It's another scary situation for us to try to get ready for."</p>
        <p>Underlining Pasqualoni's concern is that last week the defensive player of the week in the Big East was the Knights' Alcides Catanho, a 6-4, 220-pound outside linebacker. A Big Game</p>
        <p>Catanho, a senior from Elizabeth, N.J., made a career-high 10 tackles against West Virginia, including 5 by himself. He also broke up three passes and had one interception.</p>
        <p>It was Catanho's third-quarter interception and return for a touchdown that put Rutgers up, 14-6, and came just six seconds after the Scarlet Knights had scored their first touchdown of the game.</p>
        <p>"It's not so much the defense is making us win or lose, but this year we just have a fast defense and we have a big defensive line and they are doing well," Catanho said.</p>
        <p>It helped put the Knights, who were 4-7 over all and 1-6 in the Big East last year, in sole possession of first place with a 1-0 league mark.</p>
        <p>"I think right now the defense is definitely ahead of the offense," Graber said. "I just think the 4-3 is a whole lot simpler for the kids to pick up than the 3-4."  FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
