<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discovering Eloquence Amid Silent Gestures</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEAFNESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PHILIBERT, NICOLAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">IN THE LAND OF THE DEAF (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4D8153BF937A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discovering Eloquence Amid Silent Gestures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Florent, a little boy who seems about 6 years old, romps on the lawn with his mother. He playfully grabs the film maker's microphone and mugs at the camera. While his mother tries to teach the deaf child to speak, the stubborn Florent says, "I look so I can hear."</p>
        <p>Nicolas Philibert, the director of the French documentary "Land of the Deaf," has said, "My idea was to make a film that would plunge the viewer into the world of the deaf, a film whose mother tongue would be sign language." Mr. Philibert is not arrogant; he does not try to recreate the experience of being deaf. Instead, he follows vivid characters like Florent and through them carries viewers into a different but completely understandable culture, a world with its own rich language. Film is the perfect medium for capturing this beautifully lyrical, visual language of gestures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Florent, a little boy who seems about 6 years old, romps on the lawn with his mother. He playfully grabs the film maker's microphone and mugs at the camera. While his mother tries to teach the deaf child to speak, the stubborn Florent says, "I look so I can hear."</p>
        <p>Nicolas Philibert, the director of the French documentary "Land of the Deaf," has said, "My idea was to make a film that would plunge the viewer into the world of the deaf, a film whose mother tongue would be sign language." Mr. Philibert is not arrogant; he does not try to recreate the experience of being deaf. Instead, he follows vivid characters like Florent and through them carries viewers into a different but completely understandable culture, a world with its own rich language. Film is the perfect medium for capturing this beautifully lyrical, visual language of gestures.</p>
        <p>"Land of the Deaf," which opens today at Film Forum 1, includes English subtitles for spoken French and for the sign language that carries much of the dialogue. But the subtitles never distract from the eloquence of people speaking with their hands. Moviegoers who associate sign language with Patty Duke as Helen Keller laboriously spelling out the letters W-A-T-E-R in "The Miracle Worker" will be stunned by the grace of sign language, which uses a sophisticated pattern of symbols, not letters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Philibert gives much attention to Florent and his classmates as they are being taught to speak. It is a slow process that tries the limited patience of the children. Yet it is a vast improvement over the old days.</p>
        <p>Jean-Claude Poulain, a middle-aged deaf man who teaches sign language to adults, recalls that as a child his hands were tied behind him so he would learn to speak. Now education is bilingual, he says, with children taught both French and sign language. As Mr. Poulain teaches his class or discusses deaf culture for the camera, his expressive face and the broad, smooth movements of his hands convey a sense of how people who sign have individual accents and patterns of speech. He is obviously eloquent, a voluble storyteller with his hands. He also explains that sign language varies from one country to another, signing the words for man and woman in French, English and a few other languages. Despite their differences, he explains, within days a French visitor to China can be "chattering away" in a new language.</p>
        <p>The film depicts the deaf as a community of people with a huge network of support for one another, yet Mr. Philibert doesn't overlook the obstacles deaf people face in a hearing world. The film follows a young deaf couple from their wedding day through the first year or so of marriage. Their wedding is joyful, as they sign their vows. Later, when they try to rent an apartment with the help of a deaf friend who speaks for them, it becomes nearly impossible for the agent to communicate that heat and water are not included in the rent. Through such precise details, "Land of the Deaf" becomes a warm, engrossing, eye-opening experience.</p>
        <p>IN THE LAND OF THE DEAF  Written and directed by Nicolas Philibert; director of photography, Frederic Labourasse; film editor, Guy Lecorne; produced by Serge Lalou; released by International Film Circuit. In French sign-language and French with English subtitles. Running time: 99 minutes. This film is not rated. WITH: Florent (boy on poster), Jean-Claude Poulain (sign language teacher)  FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
