<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Council Members Dive In, With a Caucus to Change Some Rules</title>
    <meta content="03COUN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/03/nyregion/03COUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1356286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perkins, Bill (Councilman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Angel (Councilman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Gifford (Councilman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">City Hall</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reed, Philip</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DD1030F930A35752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Council Members Dive In, With a Caucus to Change Some Rules</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Council Members Dive In, With a Caucus to Change Some Rules</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic caucus of New York City Council is meeting to consider plans offered by group of freshmen to ensure that authority over both legislative process and perks of office are shared more evenly; jockeying for speaker's position intensifies, with three incumbents leading pack: Angel Rodriguez, Gifford Miller and Bill Perkins; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as the swirl surrounding the selection of the City Council speaker has begun to move through the corridors of City Hall, a large group of Council members has been plotting to change some rules in an effort to wrest authority from that office.</p>
        <p>Responding to the call of Philip Reed, an incumbent councilman and himself a candidate for the second most powerful political position in the city, the Democratic caucus of the Council -- practically the entire body -- is meeting today to consider plans offered by a group of freshmen operating under the name of the Fresh Democracy Council.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as the swirl surrounding the selection of the City Council speaker has begun to move through the corridors of City Hall, a large group of Council members has been plotting to change some rules in an effort to wrest authority from that office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as the swirl surrounding the selection of the City Council speaker has begun to move through the corridors of City Hall, a large group of Council members has been plotting to change some rules in an effort to wrest authority from that office.</p>
        <p>Responding to the call of Philip Reed, an incumbent councilman and himself a candidate for the second most powerful political position in the city, the Democratic caucus of the Council -- practically the entire body -- is meeting today to consider plans offered by a group of freshmen operating under the name of the Fresh Democracy Council.</p>
        <p>On the agenda for today's meeting is a plan for the Council to vote on the proposed rules next Wednesday, as a pre-emptive strike before voting to choose a speaker. While many of the members are new to the Council, they are not strangers to the powers that were closely held and rigidly controlled by the former speaker, Peter F. Vallone, and they want to make sure that authority over both the legislative process and the perks of office are shared more evenly.</p>
        <p>''We want to empower individual Council members and empower the committee chairs,'' said Charles Barron, a founder of the freshmen's group, which boasts more than a dozen members. Adding that his group wanted to abandon the ''reward and punishment system'' of the last Council, he said, ''We think that would strengthen the position of the Council in dealing with the mayor.''</p>
        <p>The choice of a new speaker could be critical, depending on the relationship that develops between the mayor's office and the Council. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani was so powerful a mayor that the speaker's role was overshadowed in nearly everything from budget matters to major civic improvements.</p>
        <p>Today's caucus meeting, one of the few in recent memory, is playing out against the backdrop of the contest for speaker. And jockeying for that job reached a much higher pitch yesterday, with the leading contenders holding impromptu press conferences in the City Hall rotunda and expressing confidence about their chances. For the time being, consultants and Council members said, the battle is mainly among incumbent Council members, with Angel Rodriguez, Gifford Miller and Bill Perkins leading the pack. And Mr. Reed said that his candidacy was still very much in play.</p>
        <p>Despite the fact that this contest has been unusually open, with debates and forums along the way, many of the traditional political forces, like Democratic county leaders and labor unions, have been maneuvering behind the scenes, trying to wield their influence. As Douglas Muzzio, a political science professor at Baruch College, put it, ''There's still smoke in those back rooms.'' Just yesterday, several Council members said, Thomas Manton, the head of the Democratic Party in Queens, and Roberto Ramirez, Mr. Manton's counterpart in the Bronx, were planning to meet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramirez would say only that he had been in touch with many people, including Mr. Manton and others, over the last several weeks. Saying that his role was to try to forge a consensus, he added that that consensus had not yet been reached. ''I do not have a candidate,'' he said. ''I have a process.''</p>
        <p>Outside officials and community leaders seemed to be lining up behind different candidates. The Rev. Al Sharpton said he wanted to speak with Mr. Ramirez before announcing his choice, in an effort to keep together the coalition that formed in support of Fernando Ferrer's failed candidacy for mayor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed, however, said that Mr. Ferrer had been making phone calls on his behalf. And other leaders of that coalition, like Representative Charles B. Rangel, are supporting Mr. Perkins, of Harlem. The Bloomberg administration has been largely silent. Bill Cunningham, the director of communications and one of the mayor's key campaign strategists, said that the administration had not yet lobbied for any particular candidate. ''We don't have a role in that yet,'' he said yesterday, adding that ''we reserve the right to offer our opinion.''</p>
        <p>Many of the new Council members pushing for changes are hoping to choose a speaker who will share power with them, and are relying on some of the public statements made by the candidates to help them decide.</p>
        <p>Bill de Blasio, a newcomer from Park Slope, Brooklyn, said that while many of the candidates running for speaker had broadly supported the reforms, ''each has expressed some hesitation'' over the particulars. Once elected, Mr. de Blasio said, a speaker might naturally want to take more troublesome aspects of the reforms out of consideration.</p>
        <p>Among the items up for consideration are ensuring that the operating budgets of Council members' offices are equivalent, that committee heads have the authority to choose their own senior staff members, that the speaker provide a detailed accounting of Council expenditures, and that bills considered favorably by committees come to the full Council for a vote within a month and a half of their proposal.</p>
        <p>The changes are designed to keep the speaker from being able to bottle up bills and show favoritism to certain Council members -- charges that have dogged Mr. Vallone in the past. But some public policy experts and officials argue that power would then be too diffuse, because the 51 members could be going off in different directions.</p>
        <p>''I am very concerned that in the attempt to democratize, they weaken the institution, especially vis-à-vis the mayor,'' Mr. Muzzio said. He then used a saying attributed to George Washington: ''An army of asses led by a lion is vastly superior to an army of lions led by an ass.''</p>
        <p>The Council itself is far from unanimous on the changes. ''This is something we need to think through carefully,'' Mr. Reed said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Miller said that he was in support of some changes, but that he wanted to push a separate package to make the Council more efficient.</p>
        <p>James Oddo, an incumbent from Staten Island who will serve as minority leader to the Council's Republicans -- four in all -- in particular questioned changing the process by which bills go to the floor for a vote. ''I say this as a minority member of the Council, but this delegation believes that a strong speaker means a strong City Council,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
