<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style; The Grassi is Greener</title>
    <meta content="30design" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="61" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/30/magazine/30design.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1758038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palazzo Grassi (Venice, Italy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinault, Francois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ando, Tadao</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pinault, Francois</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6D8123FF933A05757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style; The Grassi is Greener</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Grassi is Greener</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Muschamp</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inaugural show of Francois Pinault's contemporary art collection opens at Palazzo Grassi in Venice, whose interiors have been remodeled by Tadao Ando; Pinault, who was thwarted in his plans for museum in Paris, also plans to present exhibition at Venice's Punta della Dogana; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For days, perfume flacons rattled all over Paris. Seamstresses dropped stitches. Up in the sky, Air France flight attendants abandoned their duty-free carts and strapped themselves in for a bumpy ride. These were just a few of the rumored afterquakes following last year's shock deluxe: François Pinault, the richest art collector in France, had abandoned his plans to build a museum on an island in the Seine. Instead, Pinault would install his collection of modern and contemporary masterpieces at the Palazzo Grassi in Venice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the richest collector in france was thwarted by his countrymen, he took his world-class modern art and had it installed in the Palazzo Grassi in Venice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For days, perfume flacons rattled all over Paris. Seamstresses dropped stitches. Up in the sky, Air France flight attendants abandoned their duty-free carts and strapped themselves in for a bumpy ride. These were just a few of the rumored afterquakes following last year's shock deluxe: François Pinault, the richest art collector in France, had abandoned his plans to build a museum on an island in the Seine. Instead, Pinault would install his collection of modern and contemporary masterpieces at the Palazzo Grassi in Venice.</p>
        <p>The Paris project had been in the works for five years. Tadao Ando had prepared a design. The site had been cleared for construction. Then the French government, under assault at the time for the lavish lives supposedly enjoyed by a few prominent officials, got cold feet about proceeding with a project that required public support. Pinault gave the government a deadline to make up its mind. The date passed. Within hours, it seemed, the billionaire had reached an agreement with Paolo Costa, then the mayor of Venice, to move the entire project to the great city on the lagoon. For the prestige of Paris, a city whose embrace of contemporary art had been somewhat halfhearted until the 1990's, the cancellation of the Pinault project delivered a major black eye.</p>
        <p>A second shock: Barely one year has passed between Pinault's decision and the imminent opening, on April 30, of his inaugural show at the Palazzo Grassi. This accelerated timetable is unheard of in Venice, where it ordinarily takes an eternity to arrive at decisions of even minor civic consequence.</p>
        <p>In this astonishingly short span of time, the interior of the palace has been sensitively remodeled, again to a design by Tadao Ando. Alison Gingeras, a brilliant young curator on the staff of the Guggenheim Museum in New York, has put together a breathtaking array of works from Pinault's collection, a selection that ranges chronologically from Mark Rothko to Jeff Koons. The result is likely to upstage the Peggy Guggenheim Collection, a museum that has long dominated the field of modern art in Venice. And the focused vision on view may even jolt some of the trustees at the Museum of Modern Art in New York out of the complacency that has enervated their own institution in recent years.</p>
        <p>Shock No. 3: the Palazzo Grassi is only one part of the program Pinault has envisioned for Venice. With the sponsorship of the present mayor, the distinguished philosopher Massimo Caccari, Pinault will also be presenting exhibitions at the Punta della Dogana, the site of the venerable customhouse of Venice. Located at the mouth of the Grand Canal, the Dogana is crowned by the world's most hypnotic weather vane: a bronze figure of Fortune revolving atop a gilded globe. Other museum directors have dreamed for years of leasing this historic property. What has Pinault got that they don't?</p>
        <p>Artémis, Pinault's investment firm, occupies a large town house on Place François I on the Right Bank of Paris, not far from Avenue Montaigne. The entrance, from a courtyard, is out of proportion to the building's facade. A flight of dark gray stone steps leads up to a glass door of exaggerated height and into a lobby on the second floor. On arrival, a visitor is likely to feel like Alice. Where, oh, where is that potion that will make me feel tall enough to reach the doorknob?</p>
        <p>Maybe Gucci makes a spray version. Or Yves Saint Laurent. Or Bottega Veneta, Alexander McQueen, Balenciaga, Roger &amp; Gallet or any one of the other confidence-building labels owned by the Gucci Group, one of Pinault's many commercial enterprises. Fnac, the department-store chain, is another profitable asset, but it is the luxury brands, combined with a reticent personality, that have conferred on Pinault a mystique enjoyed by few European businessmen.</p>
        <p>Yet this image is an apt one for Venice. It brings to mind the fusion of secrecy, determination and opulence for which the Venetian Republic was celebrated in the years when it dominated trade in Europe and the eastern Mediterranean. Silks, precious stones and cast metals, fragrant spices and unguents, carpets, lacework and mirrors manufactured by methods that were a state secret -- Venice presided over an empire of the senses, a global territory governed as much by the powers of seduction and stimulation as by the insistent Venetian Navy. Ships transporting these luxuries all passed through the Dogana, enriching the city's sumptuous image throughout the centuries when Fortune's winds blew in its favor.</p>
        <p>French restraint, rather than Venetian opulence, rules the interior design of Pinault's Paris office. Though not designed by Ando, the spaces are in harmony with his cool precision. Paintings and sculptures add color to the monochrome enclosures of white walls and gray floors. The art is impeccably installed, yet the effect of calm can nonetheless evoke disquiet for one who grew up with the Romantic notion that art should keep its distance from decoration. If it weren't for the lack of moldings, we could be back in in a Classical age, before paintings detached themselves from walls.</p>
        <p>When the door to Pinault's office opens, a visitor's eye first lights upon a painting by Lucio Fontana. It is an uncommon Fontana: the canvas is white; the single slash in the fabric is vertical. In this strictly regulated environment, where not even a reporter's questions are left to chance, it would be ungracious to dismiss the thought that this prominently placed work is a de facto self-portrait of its owner. It is the picture of an elusive I, a shadowy number 1. An éminence blanche, more absence than presence, the figure in the portrait is nonetheless determined to make his mark. The veiled aggression may even leave scars.</p>
        <p>An art collection is inevitably a self-portrait. It offers insight into areas of subjectivity that a collector might have trouble expressing in other ways. It becomes clear, in the course of a conversation with Pinault, that I would learn more about him by staring at the pictures on the walls than by listening to the words that come out of his mouth. In the hall outside his office, my eye was caught by what looked like a display of butterflies under glass. On closer inspection, the colorful species turned out to be made out of pencil shavings, so I wasn't far wrong. The idea was still metamorphosis, or what Arthur Danto calls the transformation of the commonplace: an ordinary operation has transformed paper-thin slices of wood and colored lead into creatures with rainbow wings.</p>
        <p>That's progress, a word Pinault uses to signify development, or evolution. An artist, a collection, a business -- all should progress naturally. A native of Brittany, Pinault began his collection 30 years ago with paintings by Paul Sérusier and other Post-Impressionist artists of that region. The full extent of his progress since then is not publicly known. A French curator approached about working for the Paris museum project met with Pinault every month for a year before learning about the works it might display. The Palazzo Grassi presentation is the first time his collection will be shown.</p>
        <p>Pinault affirms with a quick smile that only a very determined person could cause a project in Venice to be realized with such speed: ''You have to be, in business. I am not getting any younger, and we wasted five years in Paris.'' In the short time allotted for our interview, I find it difficult to draw him out on his philosophy of collecting. This is frustrating: a friend of mine who has spent time with Pinault says that he loves talking to young artists. But why should he allow a reporter to edit his thoughts when his artists will say it all for him?</p>
        <p>Architecture is autobiography, also. A client's choice of designer portrays a particular balance betweena desire to communicate and an instinct to hide. At the Palazzo Grassi, Ando has accomplished the exceptional feat of turning receptivity into visual action. Like those of the Fontana, Ando's interiors are recessive but not neutral. In the newly remodeled galleries, the white plaster walls glow with reflected light, as if delighted to be paying attention to others.</p>
        <p>As a fan of Gae Aulenti, I confess to being dismayed when I heard that her previous remodeling of the Palazzo Grassi was going to be substantially dismantled. So I must also confess to feeling disloyal in finding Ando's design a substantial improvement. The interiors have been simplified. Aulenti's signature squared-off quatrefoils and tent-shaped white lighting fixtures are gone. Doorways in the upstairs galleries have been aligned to create classical enfilades. Colors in the enclosed central courtyard have been retained, along with the palace's ornately carved wood ornament, but the atrium is now suffused with light filtered by a large vellum panel suspended beneath the skylights.</p>
        <p>I once spent an hour wandering with Ando around the gardens of Versailles. We were there to attend a ceremony at which he was presented with the Pritzker Architecture Prize. The choice of location seemed to me hilarious, and I couldn't resist asking Ando how he felt about it. He replied that he was pleased to be honored in a country that had worked its way so far beyond the values embodied by the palace.</p>
        <p>At the Palazzo Grassi, Ando has had the opportunity to make a similar statement in visual terms. The last great palace to be built on the Grand Canal, the Palazzo Grassi is a product of Venetian decadence. Carnivals and gambling had replaced shipping and conquest. Ando's minimalist interior conveys the modern transcendence of the inner life. As such, it is an ideal partner for much of the art displayed in the inaugural show. Individual galleries are devoted to work by Rothko, Twombly and Judd. It is a conservative showing: Koons and Hirst, also represented, are by now old masters of the new. Its strength lies in its vision of continuity between postwar and contemporary art.</p>
        <p>Subsequent exhibitions at the Palazzo Grassi will not be limited to works from Pinault's collection. As in previous years, when it was under the patronage of Fiat, the museum will present historical surveys and shows devoted to the work of single artists. The Dogana, which will also be remodeled by Ando, will be reserved for works owned by Pinault. Future plans also include the restoration of a small theater at the rear of the Palazzo Grassi. It will be used for movie and video programs and as an auditorium for conferences. A program for scholarly publications is also taking shape.</p>
        <p>Nationalist sentiments notwithstanding, Pinault's Venetian venture should be seen as part of the continuing process of Europe's self-definition. Geography and history are critical factors here. While Italy is a southern country, the position of Venice on the northern Adriatic Coast places it close to the center of Western Europe. That's partly why the city was able to dominate European trade for so many centuries.</p>
        <p>For much of that time, moreover, Venice regarded itself as a city of the East, the heir to Byzantine glory. Constantinople and Alexandria were major influences on its architecture. The eastern Mediterranean was integral to its identity. These traditions, which once seemed to be exotic relics from the distant past, have assumed new importance at a time when Europe has begun to imagine itself as the ''west coast'' of Eurasia, a single continent united in its pursuit of self-sufficiency for an emerging post-American age. Luxury trade and cultural tourism have become integral parts of this cosmopolitan reconfiguration. Contemporary art is one of the lenses that bring it into focus.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
