<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Genghis Newt</title>
    <meta content="09DOWD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Liberties" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="921597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Liberties"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFDE143CF93AA35757C0A961958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Genghis Newt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column contends that Newt Gingrich's forceful performances on his Asia trip and since he returned home seem to have put end to efforts to remove him as House Speaker (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surely it was the first time this sentence had been spoken by a Congressional aide.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me, I have to go retrieve his Mongolian hat,'' Christina Martin, Newt Gingrich's press secretary, told reporters as the Speaker finished talking to conservative supporters on Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surely it was the first time this sentence had been spoken by a Congressional aide.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me, I have to go retrieve his Mongolian hat,'' Christina Martin, Newt Gingrich's press secretary, told reporters as the Speaker finished talking to conservative supporters on Monday night.</p>
        <p>The burgundy velvet and gold crown-shaped hat sat on the podium at the Ritz Carlton Hotel, glowing serenely, the latest wacky Newt prop. (Remember the beach volleyball Olympian he dragged out at the San Diego Convention?)</p>
        <p>Here was the man who frightened Bill Clinton and Al Gore so much they had to auction off the White House to thugs and hucksters and foreigners to beat him back, and what was the Speaker yammering about as his job hung in the balance?</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich's speech to Gopac -- the political action committee he once ran and allegedly enriched by pillaging and plundering donations to charities -- was designed to show him roaring back from cuffing the Chinese to quell the mutiny at home.</p>
        <p>But he wanted the audience to know that in Mongolia, he has never been called ''roadkill.'' There, in the shimmering desert, he is ''Genghis'' Newt, hailed as everything he dreams of being: Definer of Civilization, Teacher of the Rules of Civilization, Arouser of Those Who Fan Civilization. Not since ''Gunga'' Dan Rather skulked around Afghanistan in a burnoose has an American poohbah identified so closely with nomads.</p>
        <p>With his hat perched on the podium, he read part of a Washington Post story about how a G.O.P.-style revolutionary movement helped end Communist rule in Mongolia: ''On a stool in his portable felt and canvas yurt, Yadamsuren, a 70-year-old nomadic sheepherder, offered a visitor chunks of sheep fat and shots of fermented mare's milk to ward off the unspeakable cold. . . . he spoke glowingly of the work of House Speaker Newt Gingrich and the Republican Party. 'I read the Contract With the Voters closely,' he said.''</p>
        <p>The Speaker of the Yurt beamed: ''Isn't it exciting to know that not only in America but in Mongolia ideas are working?''</p>
        <p>His aides passed out a paper that read: ''Why Republicans Should Be Confident -- A Message from Speaker Newt Gingrich. When even The Washington Post reports that House Republicans have helped liberate the people of Mongolia, we are winning. Read the attached articles (and note that the Mongolian Contract had 350,000 copies printed in the widest distribution in Mongolian history, including by camel and horse).''</p>
        <p>Afterward, critics tittered. ''In two years,'' said Bill Kristol, editor of The Weekly Standard, ''we've come from the Contract with America to the Contract with Mongolia.''</p>
        <p>'' 'Our ideas are taking hold in Mongolia' -- it sounded like a 'Saturday Night Live' routine,'' said Arianna Huffington.</p>
        <p>The Speaker's forceful performances on his Asia trip and since he returned home seem to have stopped construction of the guillotine on the Potomac. In his Gopac speech he pledged support for tax cuts and compared the Clinton Administration's campaign-finance scandal to the corruption of Rome after it defeated Carthage.</p>
        <p>The conservative ''bad boys,'' as the Newt rebels call themselves, are hoping that the Speaker has snapped out of his bouts of solipsism and neediness.</p>
        <p>''We want him to get back in the saddle and lead,'' said Matt Salmon, a Congressman from Arizona. ''His ego was badly bruised. But he's got to come to grips that he'll never be popular with the liberal elite. If you blink, you're toast.''</p>
        <p>They are taking Newt one day at a time. They like the tough Newt, but they fear that other Newt grinning behind his shoulder, the weird, volatile one wearing the Mongolian crown and obsessing about his press reviews. ''He'll always be the assistant history professor at the fourth-rate college who desperately wants the approval of the liberal elite,'' says one conservative.</p>
        <p>This is backward. It's the approval of the conservative elite that Mr. Gingrich needs. Now that Gingrichism has caught on in the Gobi Desert, the Speaker might take a shot at the sheepherders of Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Liberties</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
