<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Acts to Bar Repeat of Helicopter Loss</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="699194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HELICOPTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY AIRCRAFT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY AIRCRAFT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERRY, WILLIAM J (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Helicopters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1D9133FF937A25754C0A962958260" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Acts to Bar Repeat of Helicopter Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Offering new details on the chain of human errors that caused American pilots to shoot down two United States helicopters in Iraq, Defense Secretary William J. Perry said today that he has ordered changes in the training of flight crews to prevent a repeat of one of the military's worst self-inflicted losses.</p>
        <p>The changes include more training for Awacs surveillance plane crews, shorter combat tours and a review of flight procedures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Offering new details on the chain of human errors that caused American pilots to shoot down two United States helicopters in Iraq, Defense Secretary William J. Perry said today that he has ordered changes in the training of flight crews to prevent a repeat of one of the military's worst self-inflicted losses.</p>
        <p>The changes include more training for Awacs surveillance plane crews, shorter combat tours and a review of flight procedures.</p>
        <p>Outlining for the first time the underlying causes of the accident, Mr. Perry and his advisers confirmed earlier reports that the pilots of the two American F-15's had misidentified the American Blackhawk helicopters as Iraqi, and that crews on an Awacs plane had failed to tell the fighter pilots that the helicopters were friendly.</p>
        <p>But the officials also described a catastrophic "breakdown of command guidance and supervision" that shed new light on the errors in April that killed all 26 people aboard the two helicopters. What Went Wrong</p>
        <p>Among the contributing factors they cited were these:</p>
        <p>*One of the F-15 pilots who mistook the United States Blackhawk helicopters for Iraqi Hinds has a droopy eyelid that could have impaired his vision.</p>
        <p>*The crew commander of the Awacs radar plane had flown only one mission in three months and was not qualified under Air Force regulations to fly that day.</p>
        <p>*The F-15 pilots were briefed on Iraqi antiaircraft missiles and even on the situation in Rwanda that day, but were not told that American helicopters would be in their patrol area.</p>
        <p>*Commanders failed to adequately train fighter pilots to distinguish between hostile and friendly helicopters, to the extent that the F-15 pilots did not know that Blackhawks were painted a dark green-black camouflage and Iraqi Hinds were painted a light tan desert camouflage.</p>
        <p>"This is a tragedy that never should have happened," Mr. Perry told reporters at a Pentagon news conference. "There were flaws in the procedures for coordinating joint operations, there were lapses of human judgment, and there were errors in the performance of the air units."</p>
        <p>A senior Pentagon official said later that the Defense Department was "actively exploring compensation possibilities" for the families of the 15 Americans killed. American law exempts the Government from liability in the deaths of service members. The families would ordinarily be eligible for death benefits available to any service member killed on duty, but not to any special compensation.</p>
        <p>Officers from Britain, France and Turkey and Kurdish representatives were also on board the helicopters, which were en route to a meeting with Kurdish officials in northern Iraq, and the United States is considering compensation for their families, the Pentagon official said. The Next Legal Step</p>
        <p>But some American family members, who were briefed at their homes earlier today by military representatives, said they might file suit against the military. "They say this was human error, but I say it was extreme negligence," said the relative of one of the Americans killed, who insisted on anonymity. "These guys were all asleep on the watch."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perry is to forward the 3,000-page investigation to three senior military commanders who will use it as a "starting point" to determine what disciplinary action should be taken. Pentagon officials have said the report could lead to criminal indictments or courts martial.</p>
        <p>Maj. Gen. James Andrus of the Air Force, who headed the 31-member investigative team, said multiple human errors were made during the incident, which occurred in clear weather in a mountainous region in northern Iraq.</p>
        <p>"There were multiple causes of the shootdown, any one of which, if it had not existed, might have prevented the accident," General Andrus said. Kurdish Liaison Team</p>
        <p>The helicopters were ferrying the leadership of a Western military field operation that has handled liaison with the Kurds since the end of the Persian Gulf war. The United States and some allies are engaged in a combined relief and military operation to assist the Kurdish minority in Iraq and to keep the forces of President Saddam Hussein at bay.</p>
        <p>Allied fighter jets based at Incirlik, Turkey, fly round-the-clock missions to enforce a "no-flight zone" over northern Iraq. The Army helicopters, however, fly out of a separate base at Diyarbakir, Turkey, and as the investigation disclosed, the two air units at the time of the accident operated almost independently, with little coordination.</p>
        <p>The Awacs radar plane, a modified Boeing 707 filled with controllers who monitor radar scopes that peer out over a 300-mile radius, is responsible for tracking all aircraft. The report concluded that controllers were aware of the Blackhawks but failed to tell the F-15's, and failed to "understand the Blackhawks were an integral part of the operations."</p>
        <p>The F-15's and the Blackhawks are equipped with electronic devices designed to identify aircraft as friend or foe. But the aircraft were inexplicably on different frequencies. When the F-15's electronically interrogated the helicopters, they did not receive a "friendly" response.</p>
        <p>Failing to identify the helicopters electronically, the F-15 pilot flying in the lead position flew to within 1,000 feet of the Blackhawks, which he misidentified as Hinds. The pilot asked his wingman, a senior squadron commander, to confirm his visual identification, and the wingman gave what the lead pilot understood to be a confirmation. The wingman had actually not confirmed the identification, but allowed the lead pilot to attack.</p>
        <p>As a result of the inquiry, Mr. Perry and Gen. John M. Shalikashvili, the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said today that they had ordered measures to prevent a similar accident.</p>
        <p>The Air Force will revamp its training program for all Awacs crew members and have crews recertified by Sept. 30. The Air Force was directed to train additional Awacs crew members to ease extended combat tours. Awacs crew members now average about 170 days on combat tours, 50 days more than the Defense Department standards. Review of Procedures</p>
        <p>Senior commanders will review American flight operations and procedures, particularly those involving helicopters and fighter jets, and operations involving more than one branch of the military.</p>
        <p>The Air Force will review the adequacy of the F-15's visual and electronic identification training and certification procedures. The military will speed the development of new electronic identification devices. And the Joint Chiefs of Staff and senior field commanders will meet in Washington later this month to review the corrective measures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
