<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1738F937A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
      <dateline>NAPA, Calif., July 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It seems only fitting, on Independence Day that we forgo what used to be known as the Old World and set out a few of our own good wines for consideration. Traditionally, this is an occasion to talk about ''picnic wines'' and such. The fact is that even in summer we sit down fully clothed at a table for most meals, and if wine is drunk it is not going to differ markedly from what we drink in winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It seems only fitting, on Independence Day that we forgo what used to be known as the Old World and set out a few of our own good wines for consideration. Traditionally, this is an occasion to talk about ''picnic wines'' and such. The fact is that even in summer we sit down fully clothed at a table for most meals, and if wine is drunk it is not going to differ markedly from what we drink in winter.</p>
        <p>It seems only fitting, on Independence Day that we forgo what used to be known as the Old World and set out a few of our own good wines for consideration. Traditionally, this is an occasion to talk about ''picnic wines'' and such. The fact is that even in summer we sit down fully clothed at a table for most meals, and if wine is drunk it is not going to differ markedly from what we drink in winter.</p>
        <p>So what follows is a group of wines for all seasons, all from the Napa Valley in California, all cabernet sauvignons, mostly expensive, and all worthy of consideration.</p>
        <p>With so much attention lavished on new grape varieties, one might gather that cabernet sauvignon is in eclipse. Far from it. Cabernet is still America's most important red grape, even when wines made from it are not called cabernet anymore. Wines like Dominus and Opus One continue to be made largely from cabernet; the proprietary names permit the winemakers, if they choose, to use less cabernet than the 75 percent that California requires for a wine to be called cabernet.</p>
        <p>There are still plenty of 1985 and 1986 cabernets on the market, and good wines were made in both years. This is the 50th anniversary of the first Beaulieu Vineyards George de Latour Private Reserve cabernet. This event will be marked with considerable hoopla in the fall, but even then it won't be possible to drink the anniversary wine. The 1985 is a wise substitute. As always with Beaulieu, the wine is 100 percent cabernet, and the 1985 continues to uphold the Private Reserve's reputation as one of this country's finest wines. And at about $30 it is most reasonable when compared with some other top-of-the-line cabernets.</p>
        <p>For anyone not conversant with the Beaulieu style, the winery's second label, Beaulieu Rutherford, is a perfect introduction for about $12.</p>
        <p>A friend turned up at a dinner in California last week with a now-rare 1980 cabernet from Freemark Abbey Winery. The wine was delightful, and as it disappeared he remarked that Freemark, one of the new breed of California premium wineries, tends to get lost in the high-powered promotion for some other labels.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, but smaller wineries like Freemark, Caymus, Raymond and perhaps a dozen others who have been making good wine for 25 years or more, have loyal followings. There are enthusiasts who buy these wines every year, just as they might buy favorite Bordeaux.</p>
        <p>Newcomers to wine can join the club. Membership is about $22, the cost of a bottle of the 1985 Freemark Abbey Bosche, its best cabernet. The 1986 is about $25. Freemark cabernets from the late 60's are in beautiful condition; there is no reason why the '85 and '86 shouldn't fare as well.</p>
        <p>James Laube, in his valuable book, ''California's Great Cabernets'' (Wine Spectator Press, $29.95), notes that the 1952 Special Selection cabernet from the Louis M. Martini winery was one of that producer's finest wines and that it's still delicious. He estimates the current price for a bottle of the 1952 at about $450 and notes that it was first sold for $2.50.</p>
        <p>The Martinis have often appeared slightly out of phase with the rest of Napa Valley, making lighter wines when fashion dictated rich, fleshy wines. What has been consistent about the Martini wines is their ability to age. The 1984 Monte Rosso, from a vineyard the Martinis own in the Sonoma Valley, is the favorite Martini wine at the moment, but the 1985, which is more readily available, is probably going to surprise everyone after it has spent 10 years in the bottle. It sells now for about $24.</p>
        <p>The Stag's Leap district, on the eastern side of the Napa Valley, rivals Rutherford, the home of Beaulieu Vineyards and the Bosche Vineyard used by Freemark Abbey, for the distinction of being the Napa Valley's premium wine appellation. Beginning with the great wines of the Stag's Leap Wine Cellars, the district consistently turns out superb wines. Some of the best come from Shafer Vineyards, which has been producing good cabernets since the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>Cabernet fans who prefer what the French call ''vins de garde'' - wines to keep - should look for Shafer's 1984 Hillside Select (about $30), an intense, complex wine that should improve for years. For more current drinking, try the 1985 or 1986 Shafer Vineyards Estate. Both have rich berry flavors along with the backbone that comes from tannin, characteristic of the Stag's Leap district wines. They cost about $18.</p>
        <p>Philip Togni has been making wines under his own label only since 1983, but he has been involved in California wines for some 30 years. More of Mr. Togni at a later date; for now, let it be noted that his cabernets, from his vineyard on Spring Mountain, are spare, elegant, very much in the Bordeaux style, and scarce. The 1986 sells for about $24.</p>
        <p>Another fine Spring Mountain wine is actually made by Ridge Vineyards in Santa Clara County. It is Ridge's York Creek cabernet, about $18, made from Fritz Maytag's York Creek Vineyard on Spring Mountain.</p>
        <p>These are all, admittedly, rather pricey wines; they represent what is happening to California wine prices. Many other wines cost $30 to $40 and a few have brazenly edged up above $50. In spite of their prices, top Napa Valley cabernets are in demand, and this at a time when the overall wine market is in decline.</p>
        <p>Does it cost a great deal to make these wines? Yes. Would their prices drop if demand for them slacked off? What do you think?</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
        <p>Chardonnay 1987, Pine Ridge Knollside Cuvee, Napa Valley; about $17. Some day, the United States may produce its own version of a Batard- Montrachet, but it probably will not come from any of the West Coast white wine regions we know today. California soils and temperatures, with a few exceptions, produce heavy, alcoholic and mostly boring chardonnays that are praised for being ''rich and buttery.'' One of the more pleasant exceptions is this offering from a winery in the Stags Leap district known mostly for its fine cabernets. The Knollside Cuvee has been described as Burgundian and indeed it is leaner and fresher - perhaps livelier is the word - than some of its competitors. It is a medium-bodied wine that can be paired happily with a variety of fish dishes, especially shellfish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
