<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>By Rail Among the Peaks of Peru</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="182299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOENFELD, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D61E39F936A1575AC0A96E948260" item-length="2308" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>By Rail Among the Peaks of Peru</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE SCHOENFELD; BRUCE SCHOENFELD is a writer who lives in New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHOENFELD, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE train had stopped at the Continental Divide and we were hurrying toward the doors when I noticed the elderly woman beside me gasping for air. Some travelers before her must have felt similar problems, for the porters carry an ample supply of oxygen. ''But I didn't want to take the time,'' she said later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE train had stopped at the Continental Divide and we were hurrying toward the doors when I noticed the elderly woman beside me gasping for air. Some travelers before her must have felt similar problems, for the porters carry an ample supply of oxygen. ''But I didn't want to take the time,'' she said later.</p>
        <p>THE train had stopped at the Continental Divide and we were hurrying toward the doors when I noticed the elderly woman beside me gasping for air. Some travelers before her must have felt similar problems, for the porters carry an ample supply of oxygen. ''But I didn't want to take the time,'' she said later. Instead, she stood perfectly still for a moment, took a measured breath, and gamely marched down the aisle to get a closer look.</p>
        <p>This was La Raya, a spot 14,000 feet above sea level in south-central Peru that has a peculiarly attractive bleakness about it. Altitude aside, the elderly woman could well have been gasping at the scenery. The train was sitting in the midst of a stark mesa that rose dramatically into clusters of rock, framed by a set of snow-capped peaks. There was scattered scrub in the foreground, but no other vegetation in sight. There were no animals and no people. The look was lunar and the weather 30 degrees colder than the soft autumn morning we had left in Cuzco some hours before.</p>
        <p>The railroad route from Cuzco to Puno roughly follows the main Inca highway that united the capital of the Peruvian empire with the southern provinces for centuries. The only difference is, the train makes what had been a monthlong trip - the Incas, astoundingly advanced in other ways, never did perfect the wheel - in about half a day.</p>
        <p>Such dispatch makes for a varied panorama. The train lurches from the lushness of the Vilcanota River Valley up hills with sparse greenery to what seems like the top of the world, then back down the other side for a science-fiction landscape of desolate crags and valleys. For a buffet-class ticket of about $8, not including meals, it is one of the travel bargains of the world.</p>
        <p>ON a warm Saturday morning the line outside the Avenida Sol train station is moving quickly, and soon the teen-ager serving as guard is waving in five people at a time with his machine gun. Once through, the second-class passengers sprint to their ticket windows, while the first- and buffet-class prospectives walk more leisurely toward theirs, which don't open for 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>The first hour of the ride features sloping valleys of golf-course green. At 9:15, our tea cups and breakfast utensils arrive. A breakfast of toast, jam, coffee and tea is skimpy, but a logistical success. We manage to drink and munch despite the disquieting jolts that hit the train at irregular intervals. Breakfast later turns out to be relatively expensive: nearly $4 according to the official exchange rate (or $2.50 using the going rate on the ubiquitous black market).</p>
        <p>Shortly after 10, the train stops at Urcos, 30 miles from Cuzco. Outside, a man in full native costume is selling huge hunks of assorted meat on the bone and ears of boiled corn. Tables are covered with pitchers of milk and red juice. A young boy comes to the window. Later, others will try to sell us handmade native crafts and clothing. This one offers toilet paper.</p>
        <p>Our route follows the path of the Vilcanota River. Several name changes and some 4,000 miles upstream, the same waterway empties into the Atlantic as the Amazon. Just several hours from its source at La Raya, the Vilcanota glides through miles of marshy valley. Rolling around one particularly attractive bend near the Kilometer 174 sign, we see rows of terraced corn fields up the slope of a mountain with the river flowing placidly beneath. We count five different shades of green among the vegetation.</p>
        <p>The train has been stopping at tiny valley towns about every 15 minutes, and at noon we pull into Tinta, the scene of the last Inca rebellion. In the 1770's, Condorcanqui, a direct descendent of the legendary Inca Tupac Amaru, led a revolt against the Spaniards over the same issue that was threatening British rule in the American colonies 3,000 miles to the north: tax burdens. Condorcanqui called himself Tupac Amaru II and took his army all the way to Cuzco, which he held under siege in 1781. Ultimately defeated, he is nontheless revered as a hero today.</p>
        <p>Today, Tinta looks much the way it must have in the 18th century. Most of the town is visible from the train station: dwellings with mud walls and barrel-tile roofs, oblong-shaped plazas and white cobblestones. Donkeys and sheep wander in the streets. The mud-spattered dome of a church, the only two-story building in sight, rises above the rest of the town.</p>
        <p>As we pull out of Tinta, we see farmers using scythes in the fields. The relatively modern Cuzco, with its taxicabs and Continental breakfasts, seems centuries away. We cross the Vilcanota and arrive at San Pedro, where children hop on the train between the cars and soon are parading through the aisles selling alpaca wall hangings. An elderly man with a cane pleads to be let on the train for free. He can hardly walk and wants a ride to Sicuani, just up the road. After much conversation, he is allowed to ride in the enclosed area between the buffet-class cars if he squats by the door and bothers no one.</p>
        <p>Sicuani is the first place buffet-class passengers are allowed off the train. Unfortunately, it is the dustiest, least enticing town we've seen. The train appears to have stopped in the midst of a market, for there are stalls and carts selling various kinds of food and confections, but nobody risks a sample. Anyway, lunch is just a half-hour away. Masses of people congregate by the side of the train, most attempting to sell trinkets. Most of us buy something, then, coughing fron the dust, retreat back on the train. After 15 minutes, we depart.</p>
        <p>We soon have orange, white and red tableclothes in front of us, and the porter is going car to car selling Peruvian wine at $8 a bottle. It is rumored to be chalky, so we decline. Besides, alcohol is said to be bad for altitude sickness, and this is no time to be taking chances. Our appetizer comes, half a hard-boiled egg, potatoes, ham, tomato and olive covered with Russian dressing. And in the time it takes to eat the tasty main course of lightly battered fried fish, potatoes and rice, we climb into the mountains. Lunch costs no more than breakfast and is far more substantial. There are rock walls on either side of the train now, and we can see the sky only by pressing our noses against the windows. We stop at Aguas Calientes and see steam rising from the natural hot spring out one side and cattle grazing on a hillside out the other. As we climb higher, rain begins and is soon pelting the windows, which we have closed. We get oranges for dessert. Now, there are alpacas grazing outside. The rain stops. Suddenly, there is sunlight - and shortness of breath. We are approaching La Raya. We remain at the top for only about a minute and a half. It is quite cold. Most of us have slight headaches, dizziness or nausea - and why not? We are nearly three miles up. A couple behind us has coca leaves and is chewing them slowly to relieve altitude sickness; coca tea is available and it helps, but taking aspirin helps more.</p>
        <p>After a quick picture-taking session outside, we depart. There are no stops for a long time, and for a long time nobody talks. Every so often we see sheep, and less often a woman or child standing in a hardscrabble field. In the glare of mid-afternoon, we arrive at Santa Rosa. It is a sunny town of mud huts with thatched roofs. We wander out of the train and into the village, where children are selling food, candy and old coins. Several of the coins date to the 1920's, when the unit of currency was the sol. Priced at about 10 cents they seem a prudent investment, in good luck if nothing more.</p>
        <p>Soon we are moving again, headed for Ayaviri. Once it was a thriving Inca town, and it has an air of faded glory. The dwellings have clay walls, although the tin roofs are a relatively recent addition, and the main street beside the tracks is named after Tupac Amaru. There are animals grazing in the plaza and much hubbub. The women of Ayaviri are renowned for wearing unusual hats, and we would like to see them, but the doors of the buffet cars don't open. ''They can't,'' says the porter. ''Too many thieves here.''</p>
        <p>We notice that there are boys hanging on to the side of the train, peering at us through the windows. They wave and ask us with shouts and gesticulations for ballpoint pens, and we give them one.</p>
        <p>Light is failing now. We are treated to a spectacular view out the right side of the train of the sun dipping behind a mountain, illuminating the low-lying clouds from behind. Soon it is too dark to read, and the temperature has dropped. The polo shirts of midday have been covered by alpaca sweaters bought in the markets of Cuzco, and now by windbreakers.</p>
        <p>For nearly an hour we ride through darkness. There are no electric lights outside, only knots of people huddled around fires each time we pass one of the packed earth platforms. Peru, in many ways the most opulent of South American countries, is also one of its poorest. Though the cathedrals of Lima are inlaid with gold, and the shopping district called Miraflores reminds one of Beverly Hills, two miles up in the brown, barren Andes, life has changed little in a thousand years. In Juliaca we sit in the dark while the train is uncoupled and the Arequipa-bound car is sent on its way.</p>
        <p>Ninety minutes later, we see the lights of Puno. There is supposed to be a scenic view of Lake Titicaca out the left side, but it is too dark to see anything except a row of lights, presumably along the shore. At the Puno station cab drivers are shouting out fares and destinations in English and Spanish. We step off the train bundled against the cold.</p>
        <p>Our travels have taken us half a day, through worlds and time. John Hemming, in ''The Conquest of the Incas,'' wrote of the approach to Lake Titicaca and the altiplano this way: ''After the vertiginous slopes and claustrophobic valley of the Andes, a traveller is relieved to see level ground and something approaching a horizon.'' But in the chill of a Puno night, hard by the shore of the lake and the Bolivian frontier, it wasn't the horizon that comforted me. After a journey to the top of a continent, through bleak landscapes that the modern world has been powerless to alter, I was relieved to see the sturdy doors and spacious lobby of a clean hotel.  TIPS FOR TOURISTS TAKING TRAINS  Buffet Class</p>
        <p>Buffet class, which is recommended, offers comfortable, if worn, cars and an enjoyable mixture of European tour groups, local families and Spanish-speaking travelers from elsewhere on the continent. The second-class and, to a lesser extent, first-class cars were dominated by various animals below, beside, above and around the seats.</p>
        <p>The buffet cars fill up quickly, so tickets should be bought in advance if possible (only from 9 to 11 A.M. and only on the previous morning). For day-of-departure purchases, lines around the block can be expected by 6:15 A.M., and Cuzco's Avenida Sol station opens at 7:10.  Lodgings</p>
        <p>Cuzco has a variety of lodgings: The Hotel Libertador (Calle San Agustin 400; telephone 23-19-61 or 23-26-01; $70 for two people) has ornate, high-ceilinged rooms that tend to be dark and drafty. The Royal Inka (Plaza Rejocijo 299; 23-10-67 or 23-30-37; $50 for two) is a midrange hotel with a good reputation. At the low end, the Hostal Colonial Palace (Saphi Street) costs only $7 a night.</p>
        <p>In Puno, choices are limited. The Hotel Sillustani (less than $20) has clean rooms. The government-run Hotel Isla Esteves, on an island in Lake Titicaca, costs about $40 but can be cold at night.</p>
        <p>Beware of hostals and cheap hotels in general; many are dirty and have no hot water.  Restaurants</p>
        <p>Cuzco has a nice selection of international and Continental restaurants, including the modestly priced and inventive Trattoria Adriano, probably Peru's best Italian food outside Lima. But it's possible, and more fun, to eat well for less than $5 daily by sticking to the local cafes on the side streets off the Plaza de Armas. Breakfast at El Ayllu cafe, next door to the cathedral on the Plaza de Armas, offers the company of an international clientele and classical music.</p>
        <p>In Puno, several good restaurants are at the intersection of Moquega and Libertad. The Internacional has a varied menu that includes Italian and Chinese food, but it's better to stick to the Peruvian dishes. The Restaurant Sillustani, no relation to the hotel of the same name, is a good bargain. - B. S.  A WORD OF CAUTION</p>
        <p>While Americans are flocking to Peru in record numbers (60,000 in 1987, up from 24,000 in 1986), and visiting such popular sites as Cuzco and Machu Picchu, tourists should be alert both to common thievery and politically motivated terrorism.</p>
        <p>The State Department currently issues a travel advisory to Peru that warns of activity by Peru's two main terrorist groups, the Maoist Shining Path Group and the Marxist M.R.T.A., ''Since these terrorists use bombs as their principal weapon, there is a real threat of injury to bystanders,'' the advisory says. The Peruvian Government has designated certain areas of San Martin, Huanuco, Pasco, Ayacucho, Huanacavelica and Apurimac as emergency zones because of severe terrorism, the advisory says.</p>
        <p>But more prevalent than terrorist acts are common incidents of theft and robbery. For example, there were 62 passports reported stolen to the United States Embassy in Lima between October 1987 and March 1988.</p>
        <p>''The thing Americans traveling in Peru have to look out for are pickpockets - especially in areas like Puno and Julicaca,'' said Elsa Maria Elejalde, the sales manager for Explorandes, one of Peru's largest tour operators based in Lima. ''We never get tired of telling tourists to have four eyes rather than two.''</p>
        <p>No State Department travel advisory currently exists for Argentina or Paraguay. - HOLLY A. ORNSTEIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
