<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Japan, Some Shun Lifetime Jobs to Chase Dreams</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="EARNING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TANIKAWA, MIKI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DB1030F936A15755C0A963958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Japan, Some Shun Lifetime Jobs to Chase Dreams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKI TANIKAWA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TANIKAWA, MIKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHIGENORI SASAKI had just about everything. A job at a bank, good pay, prestige and opportunities for promotion. But he did something that once would have shocked many Japanese.</p>
        <p>He quit and took a job elsewhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHIGENORI SASAKI had just about everything. A job at a bank, good pay, prestige and opportunities for promotion. But he did something that once would have shocked many Japanese.</p>
        <p>He quit and took a job elsewhere.</p>
        <p>"Ever since I was a college student, I wanted to do something related to U.S.-Japan relations," Mr. Sasaki said. So he found a job at Sony, in the international relations department. "Sony," he said, "made my dream come true."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sasaki, 31, is among the growing ranks of Japanese workers in this land of lifelong employment who have followed their dreams out the office door. While American workers, both the laid-off and the survivors, grapple with cutbacks, one in three Japanese workers willingly walks away from his job within the first 10 years of his career, according to the Japanese Institute of Labor, a private research organization. And many more are thinking about it. More than half of salaried Japanese workers say they would switch jobs or start their own business if a favorable opportunity arose, according to a survey by the Recruit Research Corporation.</p>
        <p>"People's attitude toward changing jobs has markedly changed," said Torao Tanaka, editor in chief of B-ing, Japan's biggest recruitment magazine. "In the past, we always had difficulty asking people who had changed jobs to appear for interviews, even if their new job was going well. They would feel so sorry or embarrassed for the company they left behind."</p>
        <p>But two recent economic developments have made Japanese workers, particularly younger people, increasingly mobile. As Japan's economy boomed in the mid-1980's, many expanding companies aggressively sought experienced workers as well as entry-level college seniors. Then, when the "bubble" economy burst in the early 1990's, the same corporations were forced to cast off many employees, through buyouts and dismissals. These trends -- midcareer hirings and midcareer dismissals -- had the same result: a weakened national attachment to one job for life.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, foreign influences further attenuate the old way. For many years, Akitaka Asaga, 38, was one of Toyota's "most dedicated employees," he said. But when he went to business school in the United States, his outlook changed. "School taught me that I really have to retrain myself as a specialist and otherwise I won't be able to survive in this world," he said. Toyota and other Japanese companies, however, shape people as generalists, not specialists.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Asaga works in his chosen field -- corporate finance -- at a Ford office near Tokyo. "I had never thought that there was such a good company like Ford," he said. "My hours are considerably shorter, and I get to set the pace of my work."</p>
        <p>But job-switching has its downside, too -- and it goes beyond the predictable risk that the new job won't pan out.</p>
        <p>"Those who make lateral entries often face discrimination in promotion and other kinds of frustration," said Tatsuya Kubo, 37, a former Toyota employee who now works for a large securities company. Many Japanese companies, particularly large ones, "tend to favor those who rise through the corporate ranks," he said. Japanese words like Junketsu-shugi (the principle of "pure blood") and Haenuki (true born) prove the point. According to Mr. Tanaka of B-ing magazine, the advantage stems from the valuable familiarity with company culture and a wide network of allies that longtime workers can acquire.</p>
        <p>A fickle reputation is another peril for Japanese job-changers. "Recruiters of a company would frown upon anyone who changed jobs too frequently, said Naomiki Amano, a counselor at an employment agency run by the Government. "They would question your personality."</p>
        <p>Of course, lifelong employment is hardly dead; it serves the companies and workers' needs in many ways. But mobility is on the upswing. Mika Ishida, 32, who had three different jobs before joining Sony five years ago, said her company had been very open to job-seekers with previous experience. And the numbers show it. About 40 percent of Sony's managers have worked elsewhere.</p>
        <p>And while that number is unusually high, it may not be long before other companies equal it, adopting the attitude of Akio Morita, Sony's retired chief executive. Mr. Morita "used to say in his address to the new recruits that they should all have a dream," Ms. Ishida said, "and if they find that it cannot be realized at Sony, they should consider leaving for a different job. Because after all, we have only one life to live."  EARNING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
