<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Internettled</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNET (COMPUTER NETWORK)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D8133DF936A15755C0A963958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Internettled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY CULTURE DEVELOPS ITS own vocabulary. Computer users in 1980, looking for a word to describe the transfer of data from a large computer to a smaller one, came up with download; that's still what it means, though the large computer is now called a host system. A nice verb, and the transmission in the opposite direction is called, with admirable consistency, upload. (This is on the analogy of the judicial metaphor: to hand up an indictment -- to the bench -- and to hand down a verdict.)</p>
        <p>A new vocabulary soon develops barnacles. Certain words from other cultures are adopted with such frequency that they become cliches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY CULTURE DEVELOPS ITS own vocabulary. Computer users in 1980, looking for a word to describe the transfer of data from a large computer to a smaller one, came up with download; that's still what it means, though the large computer is now called a host system. A nice verb, and the transmission in the opposite direction is called, with admirable consistency, upload. (This is on the analogy of the judicial metaphor: to hand up an indictment -- to the bench -- and to hand down a verdict.)</p>
        <p>A new vocabulary soon develops barnacles. Certain words from other cultures are adopted with such frequency that they become cliches.</p>
        <p>"To think faster and work faster the physical link between you and the machine must be seamless," a Microsoft ad reads, racing past the comma that belongs after the second faster. (They may have spell checks and grammar checks, but not punctuation checks.)</p>
        <p>An ad for "Johnny Mnemonic," a CD-ROM game based on the short story by William Gibson, promises "a multi-million dollar, seamless, non-stop movie that you play." (Drop the hyphens from both non-stop and multi-million; make it "multimillion-dollar.")</p>
        <p>Seamlessness is next to godliness on the Internet. What does seamless mean?</p>
        <p>Originally, it meant "without the stitches showing." The 15th-century word got a boost from the phrase seamless stockings, which filled a too-brief period between silk stockings -- with seams that seemed always to need straightening -- and panty hose. Its opposite, seamy, coined in 1604, meant "showing the rough side of the seam."</p>
        <p>By metaphoric extension, the adjective seamy came to mean "squalid, sordid," as befits the underside of life, while seamless has come to mean "perfectly smooth, without awkward transitions," as every network became a seamless web.</p>
        <p>In my book, seamy is still a lively adjective, but seamless could use a rest.</p>
        <p>Let me not knock Internettese, however; in some cases, word choice is apt and careful. In addresses, the last part, called the domain, is separated from the middle part, called the site, by what most old-timers would call a period. But a period is a punctuation mark that ends a sentence; this mark does not perform that function. Internet users call it a dot, and rightly so (from the Old English dott, "head of a boil," influenced by the Old German tutta, "nipple"). It's not a period; it's a dot, saving two syllables in leaving a message on voice mail.</p>
        <p>A vocabulary also develops conventions. Just as management consultants have incorporated not to worry in their lingo, Internet users -- called browsers, lurkers and cruisers, and perhaps some of them will send in other suggestions for a name -- like to say Film at 11.</p>
        <p>To explain this term, I turn to the Electronic Frontier Foundation's Guide to the Internet, though I am loath to quote directly because what I have downloaded carries such stringent warnings about copyright. These guys are very stern about that. But let's take a chance: "Film at 11. One reaction to an overwrought argument: 'Imminent death of the Net predicted. Film at 11.' "</p>
        <p>I like that. Many times we hear "overwrought arguments" by doom-saying friends, and it is useful to have a lighthearted put-down available. Film at 11 is the close of a promo for a news show, hurriedly interjected by a television announcer between commercials. Its use as a signal by Netties tells a lot in a little phrase.</p>
        <p>Now this: The on-line (soon to be online) vocabulary suffers from initialese. R.T.M. -- "read the manual" -- is unimaginative, even when infixed with an initial for an obscenity. Same with F.A.Q., "frequently asked questions." IMHO -- "in my humble opinion" -- is at least an acronym (pronounceable as a word) but is smarmy.</p>
        <p>We can close this item with a smiley, a happy neologism for "a way to express gladness on a keyboard." A colon, a hyphen and a right parenthesis, observed by tilting your head to the left, will cheer your day. :-) Go Reconfigure</p>
        <p>When a word disappears from the Presidential vocabulary, does it mean a policy change?</p>
        <p>In a speech at the Air Force Academy, Bill Clinton spoke of using United States troops in helping United Nations troops in both a withdrawal and a reconfiguration. After critics in Congress and the press focused on the second word, the President dropped it from his radio address a few days later.</p>
        <p>A reporter noted the absence of the word and asked the White House press secretary, Michael McCurry, what that meant: "Is there a backing away from the commitment to consider using ground forces in a reconfiguration?"</p>
        <p>The answer was a masterpiece of obfuscation. "The result of deliberations with the Europeans in the days follow ing the President's speech," Mr. McCurry said, "indicated that reconfiguration -- the requirement for United States assistance in the event of reconfiguration -- could be limited to cases of emergency extractions and, as a last resort, because there was expertise and resources available from the European powers that could help accomplish that in a more orderly fashion if that was the scenario we were looking at."</p>
        <p>A withdrawal, or "emergency extraction," is one military maneuver, sometimes euphemized as a "retrograde movement"; a reconfiguration is entirely different. In the first case, troops leave; in the second, they stay. Further linguistic confusion arose when the Defense Secretary, William Perry, defined extraction as being "to points of safety in Bosnia" -- which is not extraction but reconfiguration.</p>
        <p>The Latin configurare means "to form from," rooted further in figura, "a figure." The noun configuration means "shape; the arrangement of parts." The verb configure, Merriam-Webster's Tenth Collegiate says, means "to set up for operation esp. in a particular way." (Lexies save a lot of space by dropping the ecially from especially.)</p>
        <p>Before uploading my political column, I bawl at the art department, "What's my configuration?" The answer will be "short and squat" or "tall and skinny," depending on the page's makeup that day. A reconfiguration means "remodeling, restructuring," a kind of perestroika; when applied to columns of troops, it means "assembling in a more defensible position."</p>
        <p>After the negative reaction to the President's first statement, the United States commitment was limited to helping defend a withdrawal, not a reconfiguration. But the only way to tell that the policy had changed was to note the disappearance of the word.  ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
