<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boulez and Stein Stage 'Pelleas' With Modern Nuances in Wales</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WELSH NATIONAL OPERA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROCKWELL, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEIN, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOULEZ, PIERRE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PELLEAS ET MELISANDE (OPERA)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF103EF937A15751C0A964958260" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boulez and Stein Stage 'Pelleas' With Modern Nuances in Wales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROCKWELL, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>CARDIFF, Wales, Feb. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it approaches its 50th birthday in 1996, the Welsh National Opera is recognized as one of the finest operatic ensembles in Europe. It is a particularly striking example of the enrichment of regional culture that has been a feature of operatic life in Western Europe in recent decades.</p>
        <p>But the triumphant new production of Debussy's "Pelleas et Melisande" represents something larger than even this proud company usually boasts: a remarkable international collaboration, a significant aftershock from Daniel Barenboim's departure from the Bastille Opera in 1989 and, not least, a sign that "Pelleas" may mean more now than it did earlier in the century. The first night, on Friday, attracted 80 critics from all over the United Kingdom and the Continent, with twice that number scheduled for subsequent performances, and counted as the most prestigious, intensely awaited event of the British operatic season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it approaches its 50th birthday in 1996, the Welsh National Opera is recognized as one of the finest operatic ensembles in Europe. It is a particularly striking example of the enrichment of regional culture that has been a feature of operatic life in Western Europe in recent decades.</p>
        <p>But the triumphant new production of Debussy's "Pelleas et Melisande" represents something larger than even this proud company usually boasts: a remarkable international collaboration, a significant aftershock from Daniel Barenboim's departure from the Bastille Opera in 1989 and, not least, a sign that "Pelleas" may mean more now than it did earlier in the century. The first night, on Friday, attracted 80 critics from all over the United Kingdom and the Continent, with twice that number scheduled for subsequent performances, and counted as the most prestigious, intensely awaited event of the British operatic season.</p>
        <p>This "Pelleas" is first of all the result of a partnership between two leading European men of music and theater: Pierre Boulez, the French composer and conductor, and Peter Stein, the German theater director. Mr. Stein, who had previously directed Verdi's "Otello" and "Falstaff" in Cardiff -- "Falstaff" was seen on tour at the Brooklyn Academy of Music -- this time reunited with two members of his team at his Schaubuhne theater in Berlin during the 1970's, the set designer Karl-Ernst Herrmann (now a director himself, as in the Brussels Mozart "Finta Giardiniera," also seen in Brooklyn) and the costume designer Moidele Bickel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stein said he and Mr. Boulez had been talking about working together ever since Mr. Stein saw Mr. Boulez's collaboration with the French director Patrice Chereau in Wagner's "Ring" at the 1976 Bayreuth Festival. Then Mr. Boulez, who says he likes "theater directors who work with singers to become real actors," saw a video of Mr. Stein's Cardiff "Otello," found connections between that work and "Pelleas," and began the task of persuading Mr. Stein to undertake Debussy's sole opera.</p>
        <p>"I'm no opera freak: I didn't know the work at all," Mr. Stein said Thursday night. "But we both saw that like 'Otello,' 'Pelleas' is a triangle story with jealousy, hair pulling, etc. When I looked at Maeterlinck's play, and then went through the score with Pierre, I was drawn to the realistic, dramatic elements."</p>
        <p>This emphasis on realism and strength corresponds with the revisionist view that Mr. Boulez has propounded since before his 1969 London production at Covent Garden: oddly, the two times he has done the work have both been in Britain. Although he is now the foremost exponent of French musical tradition, meaning its epitomization of clarity, order and reason, he is a stern polemicist against the prettification and sentimentality that are also very much associated with French musical theater, and with "Pelleas" especially.</p>
        <p>Thus the most controversial aspect of this new Cardiff "Pelleas" was the deliberate starkness of Mr. Herrmann's sets, partly inspired by black-and-white drawings of Seurat, with most scenes filled with inky darkness and ominous panels and walls that opened up, grudgingly, to admit glaring light. This was an abstract, angry "Pelleas," one perhaps over-intent on emphasizing the score's links to modernity. In his notes to his 1969 London recording, Mr. Boulez wrote of "Pelleas" as "a theater of fear and cruelty," and here he reaffirmed that view. Life After Paris</p>
        <p>This production is one of several planned for Mr. Barenboim's inaugural season at the Bastille Opera. When Mr. Barenboim was abruptly dismissed -- "I just happen to remember the exact date, Jan. 13, 1989," Mr. Boulez said -- "everything collapsed, and we left also, as solidarity. Then Brian McMaster" -- who then ran the Welsh National Opera, and has since moved on to the Edinburgh Festival -- "asked if I could work here, and I went and heard the orchestra and realized they could give us the time we needed for rehearsal. I had convinced Peter Stein to do 'Pelleas,' and I didn't want to leave him in the void after the Bastille failure."</p>
        <p>This "Pelleas" is hardly the only Bastille fallout. In addition to Mr. Barenboim's three Mozart-da Ponte operas in Chicago early this month (which Mr. Chereau was to direct in Paris), there will be a Barenboim-Chereau "Wozzeck" of Berg this June at the Chatelet Theater in Paris, a Barenboim-Chereau "Don Giovanni" in Salzburg in 1994 and a Boulez-Stein "Moses und Aron" of Schoenberg in Amsterdam in 1995. In addition, this Cardiff "Pelleas," after a tour of Wales and western England, will travel to the Chatelet in April. The four performances there, long since sold out, will be regarded by everyone as a deliberate challenge to the Pierre Berge regime at the Bastille Opera.</p>
        <p>"Pelleas" had to be recast for Cardiff, using all British singers except for the American Kenneth Cox as the aged Arkel (the singing was in French). Everyone was first-rate, both musically and theatrically, with acting that looked fantastically detailed, yet never stiff or over-calculated. That very much included Donald Maxwell (Mr. Stein's Iago and Falstaff) as the jealous Golaud and Samuel Burkey as the boy Yniold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stein and Mr. Boulez -- who attended nearly all of each other's musical and dramatic rehearsals over the eight-week rehearsal period -- found especially apt exponents of the title roles: young, beautiful singers who could act and who seemed to personify these passionate yet ethereal beings. The Essentials of Melisande</p>
        <p>Mr. Boulez firmly believes a tenor, not a baritone or a hybrid, should sing Pelleas, and Neill Archer, costumed as a mid-19th-century Romantic poet, caught the spirit of the music and text superbly. Even better was Alison Hagley's Melisande, whom this production intended all along as a blend of fragile poetry and overt sexuality. "I've always thought you had to be born for Melisande," said the American Matthew A. Epstein, who has succeeded Mr. McMaster at the Welsh National. "And that you had to be blonde. Alison, who's an essentially blonde creature, was Melisande from the very first rehearsal."</p>
        <p>In the pit -- actually, half of the entire orchestra section in the 1,100-seat New Theater -- Mr. Boulez was even more persuasive than in his recording, abetted by refined playing from the company's orchestra. The music making was as translucent as one could imagine, yet impassioned and spontaneous, as well. "I've had 22 years' more experience," he said with a smile. "I am more free now with tempo and rubato. I still have to be strict at the beginning of rehearsals, because otherwise you don't have freedom, just carelessness. But if you define the structure, then you can</p>
        <p>move</p>
        <p>."</p>
        <p>There seems to be a worldwide "Pelleas" revival. Claudio Abbado has done it in several major theaters and his new recording has just been released in Europe. Michael Gielen and Ruth Berghaus teamed up for a production last season in Berlin, and Simon Rattle and Peter Sellars will do it in Amsterdam next year, and perhaps elsewhere after that. Peter Brook is preparing his own, "Carmen"-style compaction, to be seen in October in Paris. And while there are no present plans for the Stein-Boulez version to travel beyond Paris, the BBC will probably videotape it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boulez and Mr. Epstein seemed ready to dismiss other productions of "Pelleas" as mere coincidence. Mr. Stein wasn't so sure.</p>
        <p>"This opera anticipated the nervousness of the 20th century," he said. "Its mixture of realism and metaphor and symbolism is very contemporary; eclecticism today is our daily bread. There is also a strange fin-de-siecle sense of helplessness about these characters. Perhaps there is a similarity to our own fin-de-siecle."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
