<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vietnam Stance Says a Lot About Candidates</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC1630F937A15751C0A964958260" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vietnam Stance Says a Lot About Candidates</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I must take issue with the views of Prof. Michael Delli Carpini quoted in "When 'the War' Means Vietnam, Politics Gets Muddy" (The Week in Review, Feb. 9): "We as a country have not really come to grips with how we feel about people who did not support the war," and "when something brings it up, we don't really have a set of rules or even a language to evaluate it."</p>
        <p>The concept of personal honor provides me with rules and language for evaluating responses to the Vietnam War. Those I consider honorable:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I must take issue with the views of Prof. Michael Delli Carpini quoted in "When 'the War' Means Vietnam, Politics Gets Muddy" (The Week in Review, Feb. 9): "We as a country have not really come to grips with how we feel about people who did not support the war," and "when something brings it up, we don't really have a set of rules or even a language to evaluate it."</p>
        <p>The concept of personal honor provides me with rules and language for evaluating responses to the Vietnam War. Those I consider honorable:</p>
        <p>Conscientious objectors, who endured hardship rather than violate their code of nonviolence; those who, grieving for a society they felt had lost its values, withdrew and went elsewhere; those who, realizing that others would go in their places if they did not, served in the military even if they had deep reservations about the war; those who supported the war and served because they felt it was their duty; others, men and women, who devoted much of their lives to presenting rational and moral arguments against the war, and yet others who felt an authentic call into the ministry or religious life and who have faithfully served in that way.</p>
        <p>All of these were operating from strong moral principles, doing what they felt was right, whatever the sacrifices and risks to themselves. They do not all need to agree with one another to be honorable people.</p>
        <p>The position of others is more problematic. Many young men found themselves unable to make a decision. They may have felt uneasy knowing that while their college deferments protected them, others were being drafted. Others took their chances on being drafted -- that if they were called up, they would somehow avoid injury or death. Others took chances on not being drafted, refusing to think the issue through.</p>
        <p>Those who may never have had training in moral decision making are difficult to evaluate. Some of them might now wish they had done better grappling with the issues when they were younger. If they are now politicians, we might wish to ask them what mistakes they made and what they learned.</p>
        <p>But there is another group of men to consider, and it is their behavior and rationalizations that destroy the social fabric. They felt, and feel, that they have a right to consider only their own short-term preferences (which may or may not be their best interests). They do not speak the language of personal honor, but rather of being comfortable, of having the right to eliminate what makes them uncomfortable or what threatens them.</p>
        <p>They speak only the language of manipulation, management, damage control. During the Vietnam War, some men felt it was their right, apart from moral principles, the social contract or the risks that others might take on their behalf to excuse themselves from risk or duty to serve or to protest, and to manipulate the system for their immediate needs and wishes, with no consideration of long-term effects, personal or social.</p>
        <p>It is this last group whom we should emphatically reject as national leaders. These people, unmotivated by any sense of personal honor, are crazy-makers in our social life. Since in their thoughts and actions they appeal to no coherent moral world view, their personalities are incoherent too, and their actions unpredictable, however good a front they may have constructed to conceal their real selves. They erode any social group's morale and values, and they disrupt the search for acceptable goals.</p>
        <p>As Christopher Lasch writes in "The Culture of Narcissism":</p>
        <p>"When politicians and administrators have no other aim than to sell their leadership to the public, they deprive themselves of intelligible standards by which to define the goals of specific policies or to evaluate success or failure."</p>
        <p>That is why we need to know if candidates are faithful to their spouses or misled their draft boards or ever put themselves on the line for their moral convictions. We need to know if they</p>
        <p>have</p>
        <p>moral convictions, and whether or not they are prepared to stand by them. We need, finally, to know if the candidates themselves have any real idea of what they are doing. ANNE TROWBRIDGE Brant Lake, N.Y., Feb. 10, 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
