<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convulsive Shakes and Coconuts Tossed Into the Air</title>
    <meta content="05FEST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/05/arts/dance/05fest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1616563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fall for Dance Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sidi Goma (Dance Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">City Center</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Big Dance Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fagan, Garth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7D81E38F936A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convulsive Shakes and Coconuts Tossed Into the Air</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Convulsive Shakes and Coconuts Tossed Into the Air</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews closing program of Fall for Dance Festival featuring performance by Indian troupe Sidi Goma; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed only fitting that the final work on the concluding program of the Fall for Dance Festival at City Center was a dance of ecstasy. With its low ticket prices and high-powered dancing, the six-performance series consistently sent cheering audiences into states of choreographic ecstasy.</p>
        <p>But the ecstasies were spiritual in ''Kari Damal'' (''Standing Devotional Dance''), the program's finale on Sunday night. This surprising production came from by Sidi Goma, a troupe of Indian dancers and musicians of East African origin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunday's final performances by Sidi Goma, Garth Fagan, Big Dance Theater and Paradigm sent cheering audiences into states of choreographic ecstasy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed only fitting that the final work on the concluding program of the Fall for Dance Festival at City Center was a dance of ecstasy. With its low ticket prices and high-powered dancing, the six-performance series consistently sent cheering audiences into states of choreographic ecstasy.</p>
        <p>But the ecstasies were spiritual in ''Kari Damal'' (''Standing Devotional Dance''), the program's finale on Sunday night. This surprising production came from by Sidi Goma, a troupe of Indian dancers and musicians of East African origin.</p>
        <p>Although their dances reflect Sufi mystical religious traditions, anyone expecting a serene choreographic meditation would have been amazed by ''Kari Damal,'' in which Sabbir Kamar Sidi led the dancing and Iqbal Kamar Sidi was the musical leader. The instrumental music was sharply percussive, the singing was loud and throaty and the dancing was wild. Convulsive phrases of shakes and hops developed with ever-increasing abandon until a man tossed a coconut into the air and let it crack open on the floor, and then let other tossed coconuts crack open on his head.</p>
        <p>Garth Fagan, a contemporary American choreographer fond of ingeniously splintered movement phrases, was represented by ''Dancecollageforromie,'' performed by his Garth Fagan Dance. The piece, to selections by Shostakovich, Villa-Lobos and Jelly Roll Morton, honored Romare Bearden, an artist noted for his collages. Paloma Herrera and José Manuel Carreño, of American Ballet Theater, contributed the evening's balletic excitement, the unabashedly exhibitionistic ''Diana and Acteon'' pas de deux. Both ballet as an art and Ballet Theater's own repertory can offer far more substantial fare than this collection of trick steps. Yet Ms. Herrera deservedly won wild applause by tossing off the tricks with aplomb.</p>
        <p>There were also two quietly mysterious pieces. Big Dance Theater, directed by Annie-B Parson and Paul Lazar, offered Ms. Parson's ''City of Brides,'' in which five women in glittering gowns danced their way through enigmatic rituals.</p>
        <p>In ''One,'' created by Johannes Wieland for Paradigm, which Gus Solomons Jr. directs, Mr. Solomons seemed to be confronting aspects of his life, as personified by Keith Sabado and Mr. Wieland, and ultimately mortality itself.</p>
        <p>As a whole, Fall for Dance has proved to be the brightest idea to light up the New York dance scene in a long time. No doubt about it, this first festival was a great success. Can there be a second? And more?</p>
        <p>Fall for Dance Festival  City Center</p>
        <p>DANCE FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
