<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shortage of Doctors in Poor Areas Is Seen as Barrier to Health Plans</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="642674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH MAINTENANCE ORGANIZATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7133FF93BA25753C1A965958260" item-length="1871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shortage of Doctors in Poor Areas Is Seen as Barrier to Health Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two weeks ago, Earn J. Lloyd of the Bronx staggered into the emergency room at Montefiore Medical Center nearly comatose, nearly blind and barely able to walk. Doctors discovered he had severe diabetes, which kept him in the hospital for the next 10 days. But Mr. Lloyd's more serious medical problem was the lack of a decent general doctor, which for him and hundreds of thousands of others in New York's poorer neighborhoods, turns treatable outpatient diseases like diabetes into life-threatening conditions.</p>
        <p>In vast stretches of inner city New York -- from Harlem to Crown Heights to Morris Heights, where Mr. Lloyd lives -- there are only a handful of doctors and virtually none who offer patients a reasonable standard of primary care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two weeks ago, Earn J. Lloyd of the Bronx staggered into the emergency room at Montefiore Medical Center nearly comatose, nearly blind and barely able to walk. Doctors discovered he had severe diabetes, which kept him in the hospital for the next 10 days. But Mr. Lloyd's more serious medical problem was the lack of a decent general doctor, which for him and hundreds of thousands of others in New York's poorer neighborhoods, turns treatable outpatient diseases like diabetes into life-threatening conditions.</p>
        <p>In vast stretches of inner city New York -- from Harlem to Crown Heights to Morris Heights, where Mr. Lloyd lives -- there are only a handful of doctors and virtually none who offer patients a reasonable standard of primary care.</p>
        <p>This severe deficit of doctors in poor urban neighborhoods will make President Clinton's health care plan, or any alternative, difficult to carry out in the areas that most need the help. The President proposes to guarantee coverage for all, and plans to enroll the poorest in health-maintenance organizations. But unless there is a dramatic improvement in the quantity and quality of inner city doctors, policy experts say, many patients will still head to the emergency room for their care.</p>
        <p>"I don't care what kind of health care card you're carrying, it won't help you if the doctors and facilities aren't there," said Ronda Kotelchuck, executive director of the New York State Primary Care Development Corporation, a new organization to finance the building of clinics in underserved areas.</p>
        <p>The number of doctors willing and eager to practice in the poorest neighborhoods, always inadequate, has dwindled to practically none in recent years because of low Medicaid reimbursement rates, the threat of violence and the shifting focus of medical education away from general doctoring and toward specialty training. As a result, people in these areas go without personal doctors or are forced to rely on practitioners who are doctors in name only, providing little in the way of useful care.</p>
        <p>A 1990 survey by the Community Service Society of New York found only 28 properly qualified doctors to serve a population of 1.7 million in nine low-income neighborhoods in Harlem, north central Brooklyn and the South Bronx. "The snapshot was bleak and there was a concentration of older physicians who were nearing retirement, so we have every expectation that the situation has gotten worse," said David R. Jones, the society's president. The society is a nonprofit organization that is concerned with issues like the health and housing of the city's neediest.</p>
        <p>Still there are some signs of hope. The expectation of increased Federal and state payments for taking care of the poor has prompted a spurt of clinic building in areas where there were formerly none.</p>
        <p>And New York City recently opened two Communicare Clinics, community-based primary care centers, and five more are under contruction. But health-policy experts expect the supply to lag far behind the demand.</p>
        <p>As a result, people like Mr. Lloyd will be using emergency rooms because the few doctors in their neighborhoods are unable to provide the most basic medical care: an X-ray, a blood test or even an evaluation of a bad sore throat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lloyd said he dutifully kept his monthly appointments at a grimy storefront clinic in Morris Heights -- even though the doctor there never spent more than eight or nine minutes with him and never examined him before refilling prescriptions for pain and high blood pressure medicines.  Bleak Pictures of Care</p>
        <p>And when he fell desperately ill on a Saturday, he had no other choice but to use an emergency room: The clinic is closed on nights and weekends and his doctor is not affiliated with any hospital. "I heard the doctor there was O.K.," Mr. Lloyd said. "He took my Medicaid card. So I went there."</p>
        <p>Estimates of the shortage of general doctors in the city range from 500 to 1,400, with most of the deficit in poorer neighborhoods. A recent study by the Health Systems Agency of New York City found that there were 0.6 primary care doctors per 1,000 people in Morris Heights, while the Upper East Side of Manhattan had 6.4 per 1,000.</p>
        <p>The survey by the Community Service Society presents a discouraging picture. The society sent workers to knock on the doors of all the doctors' offices in parts of Harlem, Brooklyn and the South Bronx.</p>
        <p>Of the 701 general doctors they found, only 28 -- or 3.9 percent -- met minimum Federal standards for decent primary care. Many did not accept Medicaid, were open less than 20 hours a week, did not provide after-hour coverage in case of emergencies, and did not have admitting privileges at a hospital.</p>
        <p>For patients like Mr. Lloyd, the lack of reasonable primary care means that coughs are neglected until they become pneumonia and chronic conditions like asthma, diabetes and hypertension -- which are generally controlled under the supervision of an attentive doctor -- go untreated until patients are so sick that they need an ambulance.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the Health Systems Agency of New York City tabulated the rates of hospitalization in different neighborhoods for conditions that should be manageable or entirely preventable with good primary care and pinpointed 10 neighborhoods whose admission rates were more than 100 percent above the citywide average. In Morris Heights the number of admissions for bronchitis and asthma was 156 percent above the city average. In Bushwick, the number of hospitalizations related to kidney failure and dialysis were 740 percent above the average.</p>
        <p>With the promise of new financial incentives, public and private agencies are opening community-based primary care programs that will begin to combat these numbers.</p>
        <p>Both state and proposed Federal measures have initiated a huge influx of poor patients into health-maintenance organizations, where they are generally required to have a fixed primary care doctor; a 1991 New York State law requires that half of all Medicaid patients receive their health care through these organizations by 1996.</p>
        <p>So hospitals, which have for years taken care of these patients in their clinics and emergency rooms are opening primary clinics in low-income communities, at least in part, to protect their Medicaid revenues.</p>
        <p>"The health needs of these communities have been there for a long time, God knows," said Ms. Kotelchuck of the Primary Care Development Corporation of New York City. "But the state getting Medicaid patients into managed care and the President's initiative has put them front and center."</p>
        <p>The Primary Care Development Corporation plans to give out $250 million in tax-exempt bonds for the construction of clinics in underserved areas. There are already state grants to help pay off medical school loans for doctors who chose to practice there. And President Clinton has proposed a 20 percent bonus payment for doctors working in so-called "health professional shortage areas."  Fee Based on Income</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Montefiore Medical Center, which has operated a few primary care clinics for more than a decade, opened the University Family Practice, a sparkling new clinic in a row of bodegas and drab brown buildings at 188th Street and University Avenue in the southern end of University Heights in the Bronx. The clinic accepts Medicaid and charges a sliding fee based on income for those who are uninsured.</p>
        <p>Inside, Reginald B. James Jr., director of marketing and member services for the Bronx Health Plan, an H.M.O. that serves only Medicaid patients, was offering to send the mostly empty clinic "as many patients as they can take."</p>
        <p>And Mr. Lloyd was there, too, the day after his discharge from Montefiore, to met his new doctor, Dr. Daisy Otero.</p>
        <p>Dr. Otero meets all the criteria for a good primary care doctor, and then some. A graduate of Harvard Medical School and the Albert Einstein Primary Care Program, she could have chosen to practice on Park Avenue or in Scarsdale, but instead chose to come here. She and four other doctors hope to provide the first good primary care options for the people in this neighborhood.  Always Wanted to Serve</p>
        <p>Dr. Otero, whose family is Puerto Rican, who grew up on Manhattan's Lower East Side, said she has wanted to be a doctor in an underserved area ever since she was a child, when her mother would take her to the clinics at Bellevue Hospital Center, passing Beth Israel, which was a private hospital.</p>
        <p>"I have always wanted to take care of patients, to be their doctor," she said. "I grew up in a neighborhood very much like this one, so I know how health care functions in these areas."</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, she said there was little help during medical school for the path she has chosen and many competing temptations, from ophthalmologists selling her an easier life to gastroenterologists trying to dissuade her from doing general patient care.</p>
        <p>In an effort to produce more primary care doctors, the City University of New York runs the Sophie Davis Biomedical Program, which combines an undergraduate degree with the first two years of medical school and gives medical students encouragement and opportunities to learn about and practice in in poorer neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>More recently, virtually all medical schools, including Harvard's have greatly expanded their primary care teaching programs, awarding credit for time spent in clinics or in private doctors' offices. And some of the other roadblocks that have kept doctors out of the inner cities have fallen or are showing signs of weakening.</p>
        <p>A low Medicaid reimbursement rate, as low as $13 a visit, has made it virtually impossible for doctors to enter solo practice and low salaries in clinics have made these jobs unappealing as well -- particularly to graduates emerging from medical schools with debts of more than $50,000. Salaries have risen sharply, Dr. Otero said. Where she might have earned $60,000 two years ago, the jobs she considered upon finishing her residency this year averaged around $90,000.</p>
        <p>But getting doctors into communities is only the first step, health-policy experts say. Next, the doctors must teach patients who have become experts in how to work the emergency room, how to participate in more mainstream care.</p>
        <p>"People have the illusion that if you create all these nice little centers and plop them down in Bed-Stuy or Harlem all the patients would line up rather than go to the Emergency Room," said Dr. Stanford Roman, who runs the Sophie Davis Biomedical Science Program at the City University of New York. "That's dreaming. One thing about the E.R. is that you don't have to plan."</p>
        <p>He said that patients would have to be taught how to fill prescriptions, keep appointments and call a doctor when they are sick.</p>
        <p>A number of hospital clinics that cater to Medicaid patients require all patients to arrive at a certain time, generally 9 A.M. or 1 P.M., and they are then seen first come, first served.  Dr. Otero said: "When I tell patients they can reach me after hours and that if they need to be in the hospital I will admit them and take care of them, they are shocked. They look at me like, 'What? You're going to see me there?' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
