<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Gossip, There's Often a Relationship</title>
    <meta content="10post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/10/nyregion/10post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1753558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Post</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Campbell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Jared Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkle, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">von Richthofen, Sessa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allan, Col</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Post</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DA1E30F933A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Gossip, There's Often a Relationship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Behind Gossip, There's Often a Relationship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON; William K. Rashbaum contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blurry line between gossip and public relations is illustrated by New York Post's Page Six, where Richard Johnson has been been editor for two decades; Johnson's protege Jared Paul Stern is accused of $220,000 shakedown of billionaire Ronald W Burkle; Johnson himself has flown first class and stayed in luxury hotels paid for by companies he covers; he has also had business dealings with them, as has his new wife, Sessa von Richthofen; Post's editor-in-chief Col Allan does believe conflicts have affected Johnson's coverage of subjects; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jared Paul Stern has been in New York newspapers for 12 years, most of them working for Richard Johnson, the editor of the Page Six gossip column at The New York Post. While Mr. Johnson has never been accused of anything like trying to shake down a billionaire for $220,000 -- as Mr. Stern is now -- the journalistic example that he set for his protégé is one in which writers and the people they write about intersect more than just in print.</p>
        <p>In two decades of running the page, Mr. Johnson has built personal and quasi-business relationships with those he has written about; some of them have become sources of gossip for the column. In recordings made by the billionaire, Ronald W. Burkle, Mr. Stern uses some of Mr. Johnson's relationships as examples of what he called ''the right approach, because it's a pretty complicated business.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The journalistic example set by the editor of the The New York Post's Page Six gossip column is one in which writers and the people they write about intersect personally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jared Paul Stern has been in New York newspapers for 12 years, most of them working for Richard Johnson, the editor of the Page Six gossip column at The New York Post. While Mr. Johnson has never been accused of anything like trying to shake down a billionaire for $220,000 -- as Mr. Stern is now -- the journalistic example that he set for his protégé is one in which writers and the people they write about intersect more than just in print.</p>
        <p>In two decades of running the page, Mr. Johnson has built personal and quasi-business relationships with those he has written about; some of them have become sources of gossip for the column. In recordings made by the billionaire, Ronald W. Burkle, Mr. Stern uses some of Mr. Johnson's relationships as examples of what he called ''the right approach, because it's a pretty complicated business.''</p>
        <p>There is nothing illegal -- or even particularly rare -- about the relationships that Mr. Stern brings up; the muddying of the line between gossip and public relations, subject and comrade, is a longtime tradition in various corners of the industry. It is a well-known element of the glossy magazine business and was even a kind of expectation for a society columnist in the days of ''Sweet Smell of Success.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, as the story again dominated the front page of the Post's chief rival, The Daily News, Mr. Stern got a new lawyer, Joseph Tacopina, who replaced Edward Hayes. In a statement, Mr. Tacopina said, ''Mr. Stern has been the victim of a fallacious smear campaign, and expects to be fully exonerated and reinstated in his position.''</p>
        <p>The accusations aimed at Mr. Stern have put Page Six, Mr. Johnson and gossip journalism under scrutiny, turning the spotlight onto a world far removed from what most newspaper reporters and editors are accustomed to.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson has been flown first class and put up free of charge in luxury hotels by companies, all while covering events for the column; he is also a regular columnist for a magazine whose publisher shows up repeatedly in Page Six and whose publishing company is often mentioned. Mr. Johnson's son has been hired by at least one figure whose name has appeared in the column, and his former wife runs a public relations firm with clients who have also appeared on the page.</p>
        <p>His new wife, Sessa von Richthofen, was hired as an administrative assistant to Christine Taylor, who has shown up quite a bit this year in Page Six as a spokeswoman explaining and clarifying the actions of her boss, Ronald O. Perelman, the chairman of Revlon, who is divorcing the actress Ellen Barkin. Ms. von Richthofen, whom Mr. Johnson married on Saturday, left the position about a month ago, according to Ms. Taylor. Mr. Johnson could not be reached for comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Even though he has some relationships with the people he's covering, Col Allan does not believe it affected his coverage of them in Page Six,'' said Howard Rubenstein, a spokesman for The Post. Mr. Allan is the Post's editor in chief. ''Some of them received some pretty harsh treatment.''</p>
        <p>On the recordings, while telling Mr. Burkle how the gossip business works, Mr. Stern referred to Harvey Weinstein's relationship with the column.</p>
        <p>According to an associate of Mr. Weinstein, a co-founder of Miramax Films, Miramax approached Mr. Johnson to talk about making an American version of ''Jet Set,'' a French movie about socialites, though no deal was ever made. Paula Froelich, one of the two staff gossip reporters who work for Mr. Johnson, had a book published by Miramax Books when Mr. Weinstein was running the company. Mr. Rubenstein said that Miramax had won rights to the book at auction and that Ms. Froelich does not write any items on Mr. Weinstein.</p>
        <p>Nello Balan, the proprietor of Nello, a restaurant often mentioned in the generally fawning Sightings feature in Page Six -- though recently Mr. Balan has been treated with anything but gentleness after he was charged with abusing his girlfriend -- hired Mr. Johnson's son Damon to teach him the restaurant business. The job only lasted a week, Mr. Balan said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rubenstein said there was no deal made, that Page Six would not change its coverage of a notable person just because that person employed Mr. Johnson's son.</p>
        <p>Nadine Johnson, who was married to Mr. Johnson for a decade, runs a public relations firm that represents such Page Six standbys as the celebrity hotelier André Balazs; IMG, which represents models like Gisele Bundchen and Heidi Klum; and, until about 7 years ago, Katie Ford, chief executive of Ford Models.</p>
        <p>''My relationship with Richard gave me easy access to him,'' Ms. Johnson said, ''but by no means did that access ever guarantee positive coverage of my clients.''</p>
        <p>In addition to Page Six, Mr. Johnson writes a column for Gotham, a free magazine and the flagship publication for Niche Media, a company owned by Jason Binn.</p>
        <p>In the past two years, Mr. Binn -- who is also a source for gossip, according to a reporter who has worked for Page Six -- has been mentioned in the column 16 times, and all of the items have been harmless to congratulatory. Mr. Binn was traveling and unavailable for comment yesterday, but a spokeswoman said there was nothing untoward in the relationship.</p>
        <p>''Niche Media puts on over 250 celebrity-driven events a year and publishes over 50 magazines,'' said Sarah Greenberg, a publicist for Niche Media. ''They are in the press every week. I would like to think that I could get my client in The New York Post at least eight items a year.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern's statements on the recordings suggest he believed that forming a relationship with journalists is smart business for a public figure.</p>
        <p>He echoed this in an interview on Saturday night, saying, ''That, to me, indicates that you are maybe going to be a little bit smarter about being a player in the game, and not just a guy who picks up the paper and sees what's written about him.''</p>
        <p>There is a big difference between muddying journalistic lines and asking for cash in return for favorable coverage -- or no coverage at all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burkle, a supermarket magnate and Democratic fund-raiser whose name was mentioned in Page Six four times in the past year, claims that Mr. Stern offered to influence coverage of him in the column in exchange for $220,000.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Mr. Stern said that he was asking Mr. Burkle for an investment in his clothing line, Skull &amp; Bones.</p>
        <p>''Look, you know,'' Mr. Stern said in the interview, ''everybody does it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
