<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year Dwindles Down and So Do Temperatures</title>
    <meta content="31COLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Monte</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DE103FF932A05751C1A96E958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year Dwindles Down and So Do Temperatures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONTE WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Monte</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Temperatures drop sharply in New York area on last day of year; dozens of minor accidents reported in suburbs because of ice (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gone are the jogging shorts and lightweight jackets. New Yorkers swathed in winter gear scurried through the streets yesterday as temperatures sank into the teens by evening after a high of 39 at 4 A.M. And even those readings were deceptive, since a fierce wind made it feel well below zero, a biting contrast to the relative warmth of the beginning of the week.</p>
        <p>Few people felt the effects of the chill as much as those whose work kept them outside. Afroz Mahumud, 29, a newsstand operator from Bangladesh, stood inside a kiosk on 110th Street and Broadway. It offered little protection from the cold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gone are the jogging shorts and lightweight jackets. New Yorkers swathed in winter gear scurried through the streets yesterday as temperatures sank into the teens by evening after a high of 39 at 4 A.M. And even those readings were deceptive, since a fierce wind made it feel well below zero, a biting contrast to the relative warmth of the beginning of the week.</p>
        <p>Few people felt the effects of the chill as much as those whose work kept them outside. Afroz Mahumud, 29, a newsstand operator from Bangladesh, stood inside a kiosk on 110th Street and Broadway. It offered little protection from the cold.</p>
        <p>''We have no choice,'' he said, adding that he was wearing extra layers of thermal underwear. ''The wind hits me on all sides.''</p>
        <p>If forecasters are right, Mr. Mahumud and others in the region should prepare for more of the same.</p>
        <p>On New Year's Eve and New Year's Day, temperatures are expected to remain in the 20's in New York, but may slip into the upper teens in the northern and western suburbs. There is some good news: The wind is expected to diminish.</p>
        <p>''But it will be cold as people watch the ball drop in Times Square,'' said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>For Times Square revelers, that continues a recent trend. Stephen Fybish, a weather historian, said 1997 and 1996 was the first time in 130 years in the city that two consecutive New Year's Eves had temperatures of 17 degrees or colder at midnight.</p>
        <p>The weekend is likely to bring rain and snow. Of course, some points north of the city have already been hit with snow. The Dutchess County towns of Rhinebeck and Red Hook were blanketed with 6 inches yesterday, though Fishkill, at the southern end of the county, barely got an inch.</p>
        <p>The police said there were dozens of minor accidents between Tuesday evening and yesterday afternoon. ''Just within one hour this morning there were like seven accidents, one right after the other,'' said DeWitt Sagendorph, the emergency response coordinator for Dutchess County. Things were even worse on Tuesday night. ''Every few minutes you'd get a call for an auto accident,'' he said. ''When I was driving home there were cars all over the place that had slid off the road into ditches or people's yards.''</p>
        <p>In New York City, Michael J. Ryan, 33, a doorman at an apartment building at Riverside Drive and 113th Street, has a job that requires him to leave the warmth of the building intermittently. ''We have to break out the sweaters and face facts,'' he said. ''It is winter. We've been spoiled with all the 50-degree weather this winter.''</p>
        <p>The freezing temperatures are more than a nuisance for people who have no refuge from the cold. Carmen Jiminez, who lives in the Hunts Point section of the Bronx, said her building had been without heat for two days. Ms. Jiminez, who is 62 and says she suffers from asthma, arthritis and osteoporosis, has three electric space heaters and has turned her oven up to 500 degrees.</p>
        <p>''My Con Ed bill is sky high, but my income isn't,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Of course, those most vulnerable to the cold are the homeless. Susan Wiviott, a spokeswoman for the Department of Homeless Services, said there were ''sufficient shelter beds for anyone who would need them.'' There are eight drop-in shelters, where homeless people can get meals, clean clothes and sometimes medical attention, she added. There are no beds at the drop-in centers, but homeless people are referred to beds at churches, synagogues or city-run shelters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
