<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not the Biggest Man on Campus, but Surely the Biggest Foot</title>
    <meta content="20dinosaur" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/20/nyregion/20dinosaur.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1696023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn College</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Museum of Natural History</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D9103EF933A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not the Biggest Man on Campus, but Surely the Biggest Foot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Not the Biggest Man on Campus, but Surely the Biggest Foot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a good way to hide dinosaur tracks: Wait tens of millions of years while the footsteps fossilize under a shallow sea that will later become Texas, dig up the tracks just before World War II, put plaster around the sides, paint the whole thing a whimsical muddy red, take it to Brooklyn and bolt it to a classroom wall with an unadorned case.</p>
        <p>By accident, this method worked until just this summer for Roland T. Bird, a Harley-riding excavator who called himself a dinosaur hunter. When Brooklyn College started renovating its lecture halls in May, scientists began packing what they had assumed was a case containing a plaster cast of dinosaur tracks, a teaching tool held in such regard that it was often obscured by a projector screen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists discovered a rock embedded with dinosaur tracks more than 100 million years old during a renovation of Brooklyn College.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a good way to hide dinosaur tracks: Wait tens of millions of years while the footsteps fossilize under a shallow sea that will later become Texas, dig up the tracks just before World War II, put plaster around the sides, paint the whole thing a whimsical muddy red, take it to Brooklyn and bolt it to a classroom wall with an unadorned case.</p>
        <p>By accident, this method worked until just this summer for Roland T. Bird, a Harley-riding excavator who called himself a dinosaur hunter. When Brooklyn College started renovating its lecture halls in May, scientists began packing what they had assumed was a case containing a plaster cast of dinosaur tracks, a teaching tool held in such regard that it was often obscured by a projector screen.</p>
        <p>Removing the case, they found that the block on the wall of Room 3123, so phony-looking it could be mistaken for something carbon-frozen in ''The Empire Strikes Back,'' was a real rock embedded with tracks more than 100 million years old, worth hundreds of thousands of dollars and holding immense archaeological value.</p>
        <p>''It was there all the time,'' said Wayne G. Powell, the chairman of the geology department, who was among the scientists removing the block from the wall. ''It really never occurred to us that it could possibly be real.''</p>
        <p>Up three flights of stairs, behind a wooden door marked Geology Lecture Room, with the words Please Lock the Door underneath, the rock is found. It stands 55 inches high and 32 inches across.</p>
        <p>A worker was laying a coat of epoxy on the floor yesterday, and the room smelled like the makings of a headache. The college has enlisted the American Museum of Natural History for help in removing the rock to clean it and put it back on display, but there are other considerations. Classes start in two weeks.</p>
        <p>Considering what it has already been through, though, the rock can be called a survivor. No marker described its provenance, and those who knew what it was had died or moved on over the years. It also was able to hide in plain sight for decades largely because of changes in curatorial sensibilities The scientists who installed it in the 1940's would never have thought to tell anyone it was real; that would be like telling people your hair is real.</p>
        <p>Their latter-day counterparts would never imagine treating a rare fossil so cavalierly as to, for starters, paint it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell, who describes his specialty as ''not dinosaurs,'' removed the rock's case at the close of the spring semester with a paleontology professor, John Chamberlain, and a student, Matt Garb. Because real dinosaur tracks are hard to come by, colleges and museums routinely display replicas, and the rock looked like one, partly because plaster was visible on its side.</p>
        <p>Behind the case, though, written in pencil on the wall, they found the name R.T. Bird and the date, presumably of its installation, of May 16, 1942. Mr. Garb recognized the name, and the men got a copy of Mr. Bird's memoir, ''Bones for Barnum Brown: Adventures of a Dinosaur Hunter.''</p>
        <p>In the book, Mr. Bird, who dropped out of junior high school and worked as a cowboy before barnstorming the country on his motorcycle showing archaeological finds for the American Museum of Natural History, described discoveries in the limestone around the Paluxy River near Glen Rose, Tex. The trackways there, now famous as the site where some creationists claim human footprints were laid contemporaneously with dinosaur tracks, have been preserved as Dinosaur Valley State Park, so fossils can no longer be removed.</p>
        <p>But back in the late 1930's and early 1940's, Mr. Bird was making up his own rules. In his memoir, he described the way he and Erich Schlaikjer, an assistant professor of geology from Brooklyn College, distributed the blocks of tracks. He wrote: ''Erich came up with a proposal. 'And I'd like one of the smaller ones for Brooklyn College.'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schlaikjer got his wish, bolted to the wall of the lecture hall and painted the same reddish-brown color bones that usually appear in history museums.</p>
        <p>''They probably wanted tracks to match the bones,'' Mr. Powell said.</p>
        <p>Kathleen Kovach, a facilities worker at the college, said, ''That's more decorating than curating.''</p>
        <p>There are two tracks in the rock, a shallow one a couple of feet across and a deeper, narrower one the shape of a crescent. Based on the kinds of tracks common to the Paluxy River bed, the scientists at Brooklyn College said the big one was probably made by a Pleurocoelus, a 20-ton herbivore that has been named the Texas state dinosaur. The smaller one may have come from an Acrocanthosaurus, a sharp-toothed monster Pleurocoeluses sought to avoid meeting in dark cretaceous alleys.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bird would have his own ideas about the tracks' origins, and would know why they had painted the rock, bolted it to the wall and lined it with plaster. But he died a long time ago, and left only scattered hints of the way he had lived.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
