<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Withdrawal of Financing Renews Questions About Candidate's Spouse</title>
    <meta content="06WILB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccaughey Ross, Betsy (Lt Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Wilbur L Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DA143EF935A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Withdrawal of Financing Renews Questions About Candidate's Spouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lieut Gov Betsy McCaughey Ross's announcement that her husband, Wilbur L Ross Jr, is withdrawing $2.25 million he had donated to her campaign for Gov raises question of just how wealthy Wilbur Ross is; speculation; until last week, Wilbur Ross was providing most of money for his wife's campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lieut. Gov. Betsy McCaughey Ross's announcement that her husband, Wilbur L. Ross Jr., was withdrawing $2.25 million he had donated to her campaign for governor has raised a question that prominent Democrats have been asking all year: just how wealthy is Mr. Ross?</p>
        <p>No one outside Mr. Ross's immediate circle has a precise idea, because so far he has escaped an almost obligatory ritual in modern American politics: the annual release of tax returns by candidates and their spouses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lieut. Gov. Betsy McCaughey Ross's announcement that her husband, Wilbur L. Ross Jr., was withdrawing $2.25 million he had donated to her campaign for governor has raised a question that prominent Democrats have been asking all year: just how wealthy is Mr. Ross?</p>
        <p>No one outside Mr. Ross's immediate circle has a precise idea, because so far he has escaped an almost obligatory ritual in modern American politics: the annual release of tax returns by candidates and their spouses.</p>
        <p>In recent years, politicians like Geraldine A. Ferraro and Christine Todd Whitman have been pressured into revealing not only their own tax information, but that of their wealthy husbands. If anything, the question of a spouse's finances may be of greater import in Ms. McCaughey Ross's case because -- until last week -- Mr. Ross was providing most of the money for her campaign, and helping to run it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross has revealed nothing about his finances, and he and Ms. McCaughey Ross have faced little pressure to do so. The Lieutenant Governor, who is competing in the Sept. 15 Democratic primary, made her own tax returns available for reporters to review in April, but she and her husband file separately.</p>
        <p>The other three Democrats in the race have made public their joint filings with their spouses, as has Gov. George E. Pataki, the Republican who was once Ms. McCaughey Ross's mentor.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the Lieutenant Governor declined to discuss her husband's finances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross, who is traveling on business in Asia, has not returned calls to his office in recent days. He is senior managing director of Rothschild Inc., the investment bank, and owns a controlling interest in News Communications, which owns 23 weekly newspapers in New York as well as The Hill, a weekly that covers Congress. He is also a director of Syms, the clothing store; Mego Financial Corporation, a developer of time-share vacation properties, and KTI, a waste management company.</p>
        <p>All year, prominent Democrats have questioned whether Mr. Ross is truly wealthy enough to bankroll a credible statewide race. Among those voicing doubt were campaign aides to Ms. McCaughey Ross's chief rival, Peter F. Vallone, the New York City Council Speaker. The other Democratic candidates are Charles J. Hynes, the Brooklyn District Attorney, and James L. Larocca, a former state transportation commissioner.</p>
        <p>But the other candidates have not made an issue of Mr. Ross's refusal to release his tax returns. Officials in the rival camps said they were reluctant to draw attention to Ms. McCaughey Ross, who they said has always received a disproportionate share of the news coverage of the campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larocca, whose effort has been hampered by a lack of money, also contended that the Lieutenant Governor, as the only woman in the race, might have leveled an accusation of sexism against anyone who demanded to see her husband's tax returns. ''She has played the victim throughout her brief public career, and is very good at it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCaughey Ross announced on Thursday that the campaign had returned to Mr. Ross $2.25 million, leaving the campaign virtually without funds. Earlier in the year, she and her aides said Mr. Ross would spend $10 million or more, conferring instant credibility on a candidate who had been a Democrat for just a few months.</p>
        <p>Some wealthy Democratic fund-raisers who know Mr. Ross, including some who are also in investment banking, have said all year that he could ill afford to part with even $5 million, estimating his net worth at $10 million to $20 million. The recent downturn in the stock market and a financial dispute between Mr. Ross and his former wife, reportedly over the terms of their divorce, have raised more questions about the extent of his wealth.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Ross has not made his tax returns public, statements filed by the Lieutenant Governor with the State Ethics Commission give glimpses into his finances.</p>
        <p>The disclosure forms list 37 entities, many of them ventures of Rothschild, in which he holds an ownership interest, and 26 sources of income, including the sale of stock in such major companies as Texaco and Coca-Cola.</p>
        <p>But while the filing lists broad categories of value for each of those holdings and sources of income -- the lowest is under $5,000, and the highest is above $250,000 -- the ethics committee, as a matter of policy, does not make that part of the report available for public review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
