<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Do Thomas Jefferson and Tom Jones Have in Common?</title>
    <meta content="06INDEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981004T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON LINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wales</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graves, Paul (Lawyer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Wales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DA113FF935A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Do Thomas Jefferson and Tom Jones Have in Common?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Graves, lawyer for an on-line information service for lawyers, sets up 'Gwefan Cymraeg Efrog Newydd,' or New York Welsh Home Page, in English and Welsh (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Graves didn't become interested in Wales because of his mother, who is of Italian heritage, or even because of Wales, where he spent part of his junior year abroad. The culture, the language and the taverns, where robust song would break out after a few pints of Brain's Brewery or Felinfoel's, captivated him immediately.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul Graves didn't become interested in Wales because of his mother, who is of Italian heritage, or even because of Wales, where he spent part of his junior year abroad. The culture, the language and the taverns, where robust song would break out after a few pints of Brain's Brewery or Felinfoel's, captivated him immediately.</p>
        <p>''Even if I weren't Welsh, I'd still go to Wales,'' Mr. Graves said.</p>
        <p>To celebrate everything Welsh, Mr. Graves, 31, a lawyer for an on-line information service for lawyers, established ''Gwefan Cymraeg Efrog Newydd,'' or the New York Welsh Home Page, in English and Welsh. Mr. Graves learned Welsh and coined Gwefan, or place with webs, as a close-enough coinage for Web site.</p>
        <p>In Colonial times, the Welsh were a force in American life: Thomas Jefferson and 11 other signers of the Declaration of Independence were of Welse hertiage. But if prominent Welsh-Americans don't spring quickly to mind, it is perhaps because there have been so few at all. In New York, there are perhaps 6,000 people of some Welsh heritage and only 4 million in the United States. Wales was relatively prosperous until its coal industry began to die in earnest in the mid-20th century, so Welsh emigration to America was minimal.</p>
        <p>Wale's linguistic impact has been slim, too. When England conquered Wales in the 13th century, it tried to ban the Welsh language; later immigration into Wales further reduced the number of Welsh speakers in Wales.</p>
        <p>Also, the difficult rhythms of the language, sounding like both Yiddish and Sylvester the Cat in mid- ''suffering succotash,'' vex even the most studious devotees. For example, ''Cynghanedd,'' a meter in Welse poetry, is pronounced ''kung-HAHN-eth,'' with the final syllable pronounced like the ''th'' in ''the'' but rich in saliva.</p>
        <p>Despite the barriers, Welsh has managed to contribute such everyday words as ''penguin,'' (from pen gwyn, or white head) and ''flannel'' (from gwlanen, or wool).</p>
        <p>Famous Welsh include Dylan Thomas, the poet; Richard Burton, the actor; and Tom Jones, the singer. And, in a show of Welsh versatility, Anthony Hopkins and Catherine Zeta Jones play two of the three lead Spanish characters in this summer's hit film, ''The Mask of Zorro.''</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU SEE ''Hysbys,'' or the events calendar, alerts fans of Wales to a New York concert on Oct. 11 with Bryn Terfel, the Welsh bass-baritone. ''Sefydliadau,'' or the organizations page, reports that the small Welsh Congregational Church of New York will hold a Welsh/English bilingual service on the second Sunday of every month from September through June at 3 P.M. at Rutgers Church, West 73d Street near Broadway, in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the country, the national ''cymanfa ganu,'' or festival of hymns, will be held later this year in Columbus, Ohio, with performers from Wales. For those interested in news about Wales, there is ''Y Drych,'' or ''The Mirror,'' founded in 1851, based in St. Paul and the oldest Welsh publication in North America, as well as The North American Welsh Newspaper in Basking Rige, N.J.</p>
        <p>LINKS More than 30, including Lol, a Welsh satire magazine (http://members.tripod.com/-lolwyr/).</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU GET Saving Wales, Internet-style.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK WELSH HOME PAGE  (GWEFAN CYMRAEG EFROG NEWYDD)  http://www.mindspring.com/-pcgraves/croesco.htm</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON LINE  Correction:  October 4, 1998, Sunday  The New York on Line column on Sept. 6, about The New York Welsh Home Page, misstated the name of a Welsh-language publication based in Basking Ridge, N.J. It is Ninnau (translated as We or Us), not The North American Welsh Newspaper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 4, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>The New York on Line column on Sept. 6, about The New York Welsh Home Page, misstated the name of a Welsh-language publication based in Basking Ridge, N.J. It is Ninnau (translated as We or Us), not The North American Welsh Newspaper.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
