<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dealing With Bullies Before They Can Erupt</title>
    <meta content="06SAFE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aggression</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aggression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DF103FF935A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dealing With Bullies Before They Can Erupt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island schools have programs that teach administrators and teachers how to handle bullies in schools before they get out of control; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CINDY PIERCE LEE had planned to handle requests last year for 250 in-school programs dealing with conflict resolution, bullying, anger management and sexual harassment. But a rash of school shootings across the nation changed all that.</p>
        <p>''I had almost more requests than I could fill,'' said Ms. Lee, associate director of Scope, the Suffolk County Organization for the Promotion of Education. ''I had to add more speakers, and we did programs until the day schools closed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CINDY PIERCE LEE had planned to handle requests last year for 250 in-school programs dealing with conflict resolution, bullying, anger management and sexual harassment. But a rash of school shootings across the nation changed all that.</p>
        <p>''I had almost more requests than I could fill,'' said Ms. Lee, associate director of Scope, the Suffolk County Organization for the Promotion of Education. ''I had to add more speakers, and we did programs until the day schools closed.''</p>
        <p>In all, a record 360 programs were conducted and Ms. Lee said that number is expected to surpass 400 this year.</p>
        <p>''Schools want to be proactive in a preventative way,'' she explained. ''Instead of putting bars on the windows, they want to give kids the tools to handle their anger and the bullies in their lives. When you read of the kids who did the shootings, many of them had a reputation for being bullies or were picked on by bullies and wanted to get even.''</p>
        <p>Being alert for bullies is among 20 warning signs teachers and administrators in the Syosset School District were cautioned about last year. The alert was prompted by a spate of school shootings from coast to coast in which 7 students were arrested and charged with killing 14 classmates and teachers and wounding 31.</p>
        <p>''If anyone hears a student saying he is unhappy or going to hurt someone in any way, we take it seriously,'' said Carole G. Hankin, superintendent of Syosset schools. ''Maybe a few years ago a comment like that would have been ignored. Nobody ignores it now.''</p>
        <p>Karen F. Osterman, an associate professor at the Hofstra University School of Education in Hempstead, said that too often, ''test scores and accountability distract teachers from dealing with kids' emotional issues. Every one of the kids in the shootings had experienced some type of rejection, primarily in terms of their social relationships. Teachers need to watch for that and realize that it's their responsibility to help kids develop a sense of community among themselves.''</p>
        <p>Barry E. McNamara, an associate professor of education at Dowling College in Oakdale, said that 85 percent of students are not involved in bullying and that such behavior must not be tolerated.</p>
        <p>''If you can get the silent majority to support the victims, the bullies will stop,'' he said. ''But too often mothers will tell their kids, 'If he is not bothering you, stay out of it,' or 'Mind your own business.' Get them to get a group of friends together to say something, or at the very least tell the teacher.''</p>
        <p>The executive director of Scope, John J. Fagan Jr., said the importance of dealing with bullying and teasing would be stressed at a conference his organization is to hold Oct. 1 at the Sheraton Smithtown Hotel.</p>
        <p>''From all the research we've seen, we feel the victims are more likely to go out and get a gun to take revenge, and we want to prevent that,'' he said. ''There are kids who go to school and their lives are made miserable because of it.''</p>
        <p>The New York State School Boards Association will hold its own daylong conference on school safety Sept. 24 in Albany in response to last year's shootings, according to its deputy executive director, Daniel Kinley. ''What we're trying to say to districts is that they need to take steps to prevent violence from happening and have a policy for managing a crisis if it happens,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One of the speakers will be James Harris, superintendent of Buffalo's public schools, who established a 40-member task force of teachers, administrators, parents, police and business leaders last year following a shooting in one of the system's 80 schools. ''A husband followed his wife into the school after a domestic argument and shot and killed her in the main office'' while their child watched, he said.</p>
        <p>The task force put together a plan that seeks to reduce violence and make ''our schools islands of safety,'' said Mr. Harris.</p>
        <p>It includes an anger-management program for teachers; a code of conduct for students, with a list of consequences for inappropriate behavior; the installation of surveillance cameras at every school entrance, and time-out rooms in each school.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee of Scope said she frequently visits schools in Suffolk and has found a visible tightening of security. ''Now there is not just a sign asking visitors to check in at the main office, there is a person sitting at the front door asking who you are and where you are going,'' said Ms. Lee. ''They give you a badge to wear and you have to sign in so there is control over who is in the building.''</p>
        <p>In addition, she said, the back doors to the schools are now locked.</p>
        <p>''Schools are not just worried about shootings,'' said Ms. Lee. ''Last year a stranger entered the back door of an elementary school on Long Island and tried to grab a child's arm. She was with a friend who screamed and she got away.''</p>
        <p>Noting that some Connetquot schools have installed buzzers on their doors, Ms. Lee said, ''We don't want to turn schools into jails with video cameras and fences, but buzzing people in is better than metal detectors.''</p>
        <p>A metal detector was installed last February in Hempstead High School after a yearlong discussion by the school board, according to the superintendent of the Hempstead School District, Nathaniel Clay. ''The board and I decided to have a safe and secure student environment,'' said Dr. Clay, who said there was growing concern about students bringing guns and knives into the school.</p>
        <p>Since its installation, students have been stopped trying to enter the 1,500-student building with two guns, three knives and two box cutters. ''It has been effective,'' Dr. Clay said.</p>
        <p>But George Besculides, president of the Nassau County Council of School Superintendents and superintendent of the Wantagh School District, said metal detectors are not necessary in all districts.</p>
        <p>''We have not encountered guns and knives and our personnel are in tune with our student body,'' said Dr. Besculides of his district. ''There is also an adult presence in the hallway at all times and if there were an intruder, someone would encounter him quickly.''</p>
        <p>But Marc Bernstein, superintendent of the Bellmore-Merrick Central High School District, said he was concerned that such vigilance might not work in the case of a severely troubled youngster.</p>
        <p>He noted that in May school authorities in Oregon seized the gun a 14-year-old boy carried into school. The child was arrested and released into his parents' custody. The next day, however, he returned to the school and shot and killed two students and wounded 24 others, after first killing his parents.</p>
        <p>''My feeling is that any student who brings a gun to school should have an immediate psychiatric evaluation and not be released back into the community until the results are shared with a judge,'' said Dr. Bernstein. ''No matter how good school security may be, there is no way for us to physically prevent a student from re-entering the school once he or she has been suspended.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
