<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shared Starting Position for Jets Player</title>
    <meta content="06JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Dwayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DE103FF935A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shared Starting Position for Jets Player</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Dwayne Gordon, New York Jets' linebacker; Gordon is White Plains native now living in LaGrangeville, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the role of every professional football player is to be a starter when the season opens, then Dwayne Gordon will be halfway there this afternoon when the New York Jets begin the National Football League season in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Halfway because Gordon, a White Plains native now living in LaGrangeville, N.Y., will be at middle linebacker -- the most important position in Coach Bill Parcells's defense -- on all likely passing downs. The veteran, Pepper Johnson, a holdover from Parcells's Super Bowl days with the Giants, will be on the field for running plays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the role of every professional football player is to be a starter when the season opens, then Dwayne Gordon will be halfway there this afternoon when the New York Jets begin the National Football League season in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Halfway because Gordon, a White Plains native now living in LaGrangeville, N.Y., will be at middle linebacker -- the most important position in Coach Bill Parcells's defense -- on all likely passing downs. The veteran, Pepper Johnson, a holdover from Parcells's Super Bowl days with the Giants, will be on the field for running plays.</p>
        <p>''We have a two-headed middle linebacker'' is the way Parcells put it. And one of those heads belongs to Gordon, 28, an intelligent, mobile athlete entering his sixth year in professional football.</p>
        <p>A season-ending injury in training camp to the middle linebacking incumbent Marvin Jones led to Gordon's shared starting role, but, he said, it has not affected his approach to the season.</p>
        <p>''As a professional I just have to be prepared either way, if I'm a reserve or a starter,'' Gordon said just before making three tackles in a part-time role in the Jets' final preseason game nine days ago. ''My approach toward playing time has always been the same, whether I was starting or not -- because the bottom line is, If somebody does get injured, I have to be able to step in and perform.''</p>
        <p>Which is what happened last year when Jones was injured in mid-season. Gordon started the final 8 games and produced some big efforts, including an 11-tackle performance against the Indianapolis Colts.</p>
        <p>And, while saying the right things about approach, he, of course, relishes starting. ''Your attitude changes when you've had something and don't want to lose it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in his first starting opportunity this season, the opening preseason game against Philadelphia, Gordon had a game-high six tackles, five unassisted, while playing only the first half.</p>
        <p>Not particularly big for his position at 6 feet 1 and 240 pounds, Gordon is quick enough and a quick-enough learner to play either an inside or outside linebacking position and excel on the special teams that Parcells so prizes.</p>
        <p>Al Groh, the Jets' linebacker coach, has praised Gordon's coachability. But early in his career, Gordon conceded that he was not big on watching game films, or his own weight.</p>
        <p>''I just didn't figure it out in terms of being a professional,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Gordon, whose father, Robert, is a lifetime educator and now a Manhattanville College professor and whose mother, Sharon, is a bank loan officer, had it figured out by the time he joined the Jets for the 1997 season. So much so that he can tell a story on himself concerning Parcells, a believer in tough, not tender, love.</p>
        <p>''After my first scrimmage with the Jets in 1997,'' Gordon said, ''Parcells said to me: 'Why didn't you play like that in San Diego? Was it because you were fat and out of shape?' ''</p>
        <p>Actually, Gordon had had a knee injury in San Diego. He did not say a word. No excuses.</p>
        <p>Parcells demands smart linebackers.</p>
        <p>CHUCK SLATER</p>
        <p>Parcells Gives Irvington Man a Role</p>
        <p>THE fortunes of the two sixth-round draft choices from Westchester County trying to earn spots on New York's two pro football teams did not follow the script.</p>
        <p>Todd Pollock of Rye, the tight end from Boston College whose long-snapping talents seemingly had won him a place on the Giants' roster, was injured on the second day of training camp. Nagging injuries kept him from working out most of the time, and he was a reluctant cut two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Eric Ogbogu of Irvington, less than 50-50 to make the team when camp opened, impressed Jets Coach Bill Parcells with his work ethic, strength and straight-ahead sack ability from his defensive tackle position. He cemented his spot with sacks of the quarterback in both of the last two exhibition games and was still standing when the final roster cuts were made last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Pollock received an injury settlement from the Giants and will probably be invited to try out for the team again next spring. While he will not be on the field at Giants Stadium today, another Westchester resident will. Tre Johnson of Peekskill, a standout offensive tackle, will start for the Washington Redskins, the Giants' opponent. Johnson missed the first three exhibition games with an injured right shoulder but played in the fourth and will play today.</p>
        <p>CHUCK SLATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
