<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gently Surreal Story of Human Need</title>
    <meta content="22TALK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/movies/22TALK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Almodovar, Pedro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Talk to Her (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Almodovar, Pedro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DE1539F931A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gently Surreal Story of Human Need</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Gently Surreal Story of Human Need</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts of Elvis Mitchell review of movie Talk to Her, directed by Pedro Almodovar; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Talk to Her'' was shown as part of this year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Elvis Mitchell's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 12; the full text is available online at nytimes.com/movies. The film, in Spanish with English subtitles, opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Like all great doomed affairs, ''Talk to Her'' is full of lovely, sweet suffering. And when it's over, the realization of how much the movie means to you really sinks in; you can't get it out of your heart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like all great doomed affairs, Pedro Almodóvar's tragic comedy is full of lovely, sweet suffering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Talk to Her'' was shown as part of this year's New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Elvis Mitchell's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Oct. 12; the full text is available online at nytimes.com/movies. The film, in Spanish with English subtitles, opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Like all great doomed affairs, ''Talk to Her'' is full of lovely, sweet suffering. And when it's over, the realization of how much the movie means to you really sinks in; you can't get it out of your heart.</p>
        <p>Pedro Almodóvar has created a tragic comedy about need, its liberating and shackling powers. Movies haven't been so rapturous about characters plummeting to an awful end at least since the last Almodóvar film, ''All About My Mother'' (1999). But he doesn't mine the comic strip soap opera mystique so extravagantly here; everything falls into place with an almost surreal delicacy.</p>
        <p>The dense and deeply touching ''Talk to Her'' makes one think he has been listening to a lot of songs by the Smiths, those former post-punk potentates, particularly the band's classic, ''Girlfriend in a Coma.''</p>
        <p>Benigno (Javier Cámara) is a nurse who sits patiently at the side of his unconscious girlfriend, Alicia (Leonor Watling), attending to her needs.</p>
        <p>What he does is talk to her, moving slowly, gently; his honeyed voice is a part of his physicality, going along with his meticulous, deliberate movement. He's a delicate, strangely assured stuffed animal of a man. And as in the compelling peculiarity of the Smiths -- a sensibility that links the director and the band -- the film takes fascinatingly soigné turns.</p>
        <p>Initially the picture is about sympathy; Marco (Darío Grandinetti), taken by Benigno's lead, ministers to his own girlfriend, Lydia (Rosario Flores), who is also in a coma. Both women were intensely physical: Alicia was a dancer, and Lydia, a bullfighter, was gored.</p>
        <p>With his placid face and caramel speaking tones, Benigno is the very center of the film, literally and spiritually. In terms of visual schemes, Mr. Almodóvar uses a dark, sweet richness and camera movements as deliberate and generous as Benigno. And we learn very slowly what depths of benign malice this apparently bland, kind man -- and this superb filmmaker at the grown-up peak of his powers -- is capable of. It is revealed that Benigno is an obsessive with no real ties to Alicia; she has become his after falling into unconsciousness, and the depth of his devotion becomes both a love story and a horror story. By the end of his story we're left as stunned and loyal as Marco.</p>
        <p>By the end Mr. Almodóvar flips the script and demands not just sympathy but also empathy for someone you wouldn't think deserved it. It's a movie about being trapped in various kinds of prisons, spiritual, physical and finally literal. (''All About My Mother'' and his 1997 ''Live Flesh'' were also about being imprisoned.) And we see that ''Talk to Her'' is not about sympathy but about loyalty, and the picture with its crafty twists of fate earns our loyalty as well.</p>
        <p>It's the most mature work this director has ever brought to the screen. His fearlessness used to lend itself to bizarre, wild plot turns that suggested he was out to tickle himself, a practical joker who loved giving his own pictures a hot foot.</p>
        <p>The jabbering neuroses of his chattering characters grew out of Mr. Almodóvar himself; there was something lovable about his compulsive desire to entertain. Now the movies have the freakish, elegant calm of early Tennessee Williams, and the dramatic information is slipped into the movie with devastating panache: a love tap delivered with the force of a speeding car.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almodóvar's purview started out as a lewd, slapstick version of the heightened melodrama of the 50's director Douglas Sirk: as if ''Magnificent Obsession'' had starred a sexual Lucille Ball.</p>
        <p>But the director has moved past candy-colored Fassbinder with a sense of humor.</p>
        <p>His plot turns are no longer as sharp and cruel, which was fun. Mr. Almodóvar couldn't be more unhurried and assured about what he's doing; ''Talk to Her'' is evidence of his own evolving sensibility.</p>
        <p>His movies have not lost their ability to startle, but the wayward ingenuity no longer gives vent to wild, delirious shocks. His metabolism has slowed; he doesn't cram in the lively excess for its own sake.</p>
        <p>Yet the slippery mischievous streak remains, and ''Talk to Her'' shows how reliable he has become at marrying suspense, comedy and tragedy. He has become more capable than ever of not only shifting tones but also balancing several tones at once, answering questions and simultaneously deepening the mystery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Almodóvar's appreciation of flesh -- no other director photographs skin so lovingly -- itself becomes a plot point. Benigno generously strokes Alicia, and the director evokes and subtly parodies movies like ''Love Story.'' Skin, and sex, are the heart of the trouble, and there's a grandly ludicrous scene about how deeply unavoidable sex is and the troubles it can raise. ''Talk to Her'' is totally in love with passion, and with love as we are -- more than may be good for it.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
