<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amish Find Gentler Road Along Busy Highway</title>
    <meta content="Y22AMIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/national/22AMIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Goshen Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amish</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Elkhart County (Ind)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Goshen (Ind)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, John W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amish</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5D61539F931A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amish Find Gentler Road Along Busy Highway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amish Find Gentler Road Along Busy Highway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, John W</byline>
      <dateline>GOSHEN, Ind., Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elkhart County, Indiana, lays out gravel access road for nonmotorized vehicles, to make travel safer for Amish horse-and-buggy traffic; photo (Goshen Journal) (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The black horse drawing the black buggy clopped into the parking lot at Wal-Mart, the usual unnerving journey across Highway 33 for Retha Bontrager and her two children safely ended.</p>
        <p>Out on the highway, the traffic has been known to be unyielding to the horse-drawn buggies making left turns into the Wal-Mart parking lot here in Amish country -- and frightening for their passengers. Some drivers are careful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elkhart County officials laid a gravel access road to make travel safer for the Amish, who travel in horse-drawn buggies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The black horse drawing the black buggy clopped into the parking lot at Wal-Mart, the usual unnerving journey across Highway 33 for Retha Bontrager and her two children safely ended.</p>
        <p>Out on the highway, the traffic has been known to be unyielding to the horse-drawn buggies making left turns into the Wal-Mart parking lot here in Amish country -- and frightening for their passengers. Some drivers are careful.</p>
        <p>''And some are not,'' Mrs. Bontrager said, moments after parking at a horse-and-buggy barn on the parking lot this afternoon. ''Some will cut you off. Some people take dangerous turns.''</p>
        <p>Hoping to make travel safer for the Amish in this town of 29,000, Elkhart County officials here laid a gravel access road for nonmotorized vehicles that offers an alternative to crossing a busy highway in an 18th-century mode of transportation. This afternoon, on a cold and rainy day, Elkhart County officials dedicated the new 2,400-foot-long road to the Wal-Mart lot, which they say should provide safer passage.</p>
        <p>Perry Yoder, 57, who is also Amish, came to the dedication and gave Sheriff Tom Snider an inaugural ride in his horse-drawn buggy.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes traffic gets up to you, especially when you've got to sit in the center of the road while you're waiting to make a left turn,'' Mr. Yoder said.</p>
        <p>''It's not just for our safety but also for the motor vehicles because we're a threat to them,'' he added.</p>
        <p>While county officials said the road was the first of its kind here, Mr. Yoder said similar alternative roads had been laid in other Amish communities.</p>
        <p>Sheriff Snider said that over the years there had been ''near misses of crashes,'' though no fatalities in recent memory.</p>
        <p>Joyce Bontrager, who is not related to Mrs. Bontrager, a spokeswoman for the local Safe Kids Coalition, said the idea for the road came about several years ago when the coalition began working with the Amish on home and farm safety issues.</p>
        <p>''At one of the schools, where the sheriff and I were presiding over a presentation, one of the gentlemen said, 'If you're really concerned about safety, how about getting the buggies off of U.S. 33 south, or at least making it so they don't have to make left-hand turns,' '' Joyce Bontrager recalled.</p>
        <p>She contacted the Elkhart County Commissioners about coming up with a solution. The idea of the access road was eventually hatched.</p>
        <p>Officials said that the road cost about $30,000, with $23,000 donated by the Amish and the rest coming from businesses and the county.</p>
        <p>For many here, building the new road was a lesson in community.</p>
        <p>''This does not serve just one population in our community,'' Joyce Bontrager said. ''It will serve anyone that rides bikes to get them off that dangerous highway.''</p>
        <p>''This does not take away the responsibility of the state to expand the road like it should be with buggy lanes,'' she said. ''But it gives us something in the meantime.''</p>
        <p>The new road is accessible from County Road 38 and makes crossing Highway 33 unnecessary. It snakes to Wal-Mart because once drivers arrive there they can easily cross through the lot to another shopping area.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, after taking the sheriff on his christening ride, Mr. Yoder made his way to Wal-Mart over the road less traveled.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to do some shopping and relax a little bit,'' Mr. Yoder said, standing behind his shopping cart under the warm glow of lights inside the store.</p>
        <p>Goshen Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
