<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Totes Isotoner, readying its first campaign in four years, hopes it rains cats and dogs.</title>
    <meta content="Y22ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/business/media/22ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Umbrellas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Totes Isotoner</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Totes Isotoner</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DB1539F931A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Totes Isotoner, readying its first campaign in four years, hopes it rains cats and dogs.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Totes Isotoner Hopes It Rains Cats and Dogs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sherri Day</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Totes Isotoner will begin braodcasting two television ads to promote its new line of umbrellas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DOES it really matter who makes your umbrella? Totes Isotoner, with its first advertising campaign in four years, is trying to convince a skeptical nation that it does.</p>
        <p>The company will begin broadcasting two television ads on Monday to promote its new line of umbrellas. One spot features 'brella, which at less than six inches long is the smallest umbrella Totes has ever made, while another promotes the Titanium model, which is supposed to withstand blustery winds and heavy rains. Both commercials are aimed at holiday shoppers who are in search of highly functional, if perhaps impersonal, gifts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does it really matter who makes your umbrella? Totes Isotoner, with its first ad campaign in four years, is trying to convince a skeptical nation that it does.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DOES it really matter who makes your umbrella? Totes Isotoner, with its first advertising campaign in four years, is trying to convince a skeptical nation that it does.</p>
        <p>The company will begin broadcasting two television ads on Monday to promote its new line of umbrellas. One spot features 'brella, which at less than six inches long is the smallest umbrella Totes has ever made, while another promotes the Titanium model, which is supposed to withstand blustery winds and heavy rains. Both commercials are aimed at holiday shoppers who are in search of highly functional, if perhaps impersonal, gifts.</p>
        <p>Spending $1.5 million to advertise a product viewed mainly as a commodity might not seem particularly cost effective. But since the company slowed national advertising for Totes after it bought Isotoner from the Sara Lee Corporation in 1997, its umbrella sales have dropped faster than the overall umbrella category.</p>
        <p>Totes Isotoner, which is privately held, declined to give specific sales figures for its umbrella business. But company officials said that for much of the last five years, sales have been relatively flat. And in 2001 sales decreased by about 20 percent because of a lack of advertising, mild winters and droughtlike conditions throughout much of the country, the company said. Sales throughout the umbrella industry, which includes high-end Burberry umbrellas that retail for about $90 and $4 generic brands, have declined 14 percent since 1997, according to NPDFashionworld, and 4 percent from 2000 to 2001.</p>
        <p>Totes executives are betting that the new campaign -- which was created by the WonderGroup, an independent agency based in Cincinnati -- coupled with what could be a cold, wet winter, will reinvigorate consumer interest in the brand.</p>
        <p>''Our strategy for the fourth quarter revolves around trying to present an item that is very giftable,'' said Michael Katz, the vice president for marketing at Totes Isotoner. ''The umbrella is a very good impersonal gift at a reasonable price point. We're trying to take it out of the commodity function into something that's a little bit more special.''</p>
        <p>Totes umbrellas cost about $20, and the company said that nearly 75 percent of its umbrella sales are gift purchases. Most of those sales are in department stores, where Totes maintains 90 percent of the umbrella market.</p>
        <p>But in the last few years, consumers have increasingly shunned department stores in favor of cheaper umbrellas from Hong Kong and China that are sold in drugstores, discount stores like Wal-Mart and Target, and on the street, analysts said.</p>
        <p>With the new campaign, Totes is trying to lure back those former customers while building brand recognition with others. ''They're trying to become the generic version of a Kleenex or Frigidaire,'' said Marshal Cohen, co-president of NPDFashionworld. ''They want to have that association, and television offers the fastest and most powerful method of getting into the consumer's mindset. It's worth the investment to try to recapture consumer awareness of Totes.''</p>
        <p>The television ads are scheduled to be broadcast from Nov. 25 to Dec. 19 on the broadcast networks and on cable channels like the Discovery Channel and the Learning Channel.</p>
        <p>In one commercial, called ''Lil' Boy,'' the advertising agency made the company's first umbrella spot that does not include rain.</p>
        <p>During the 30-second spot, a child approaches a department store clerk and asks for help with selecting a gift for his mother who likes the color red. As soft elevator music plays in the background, the clerk pauses for a moment and surveys a boutique filled with purses and boxed gifts. She finally picks up a red 'brella and a small clutch purse from a nearby table.</p>
        <p>The clerk described the umbrella as so little that the boy's mother could put it inside of the purse and ''carry it with her every day and think of you.''</p>
        <p>In ''Cats and Dogs,'' Totes takes a more comical approach to selling its Titanium umbrella. Three men are standing at a bus stop when it begins to rain lightly. One man raises his Titanium umbrella while the other two cover their heads with a briefcase and a newspaper. As the rain falls more heavily, the raindrops are replaced by cats and dogs. One of the men without an umbrella is felled by a Saint Bernard, but the man with the Titanium umbrella remains dry and unharmed even as a cat bounces off his umbrella. A narrator describes the product as the ''perfect gift for when it's raining really hard.''</p>
        <p>In a separate print campaign, Totes has taken out ads in magazines like People, Vogue and Better Homes and Gardens. Large illuminated signs for Totes umbrellas are also being placed in 30 regional malls along the Eastern Seaboard. The company has placed ads in malls in Philadelphia, Washington, Boston, Atlanta, New Jersey and suburban New York City. They are also trying to persuade retailers to create eye-catching displays for 'brella and Titanium and to put them on gift tables.</p>
        <p>So far, the strategy appears to be working. Sales to retailers have doubled this season, Totes executives said. Now, the company is counting on customers to buy the brand in stores.</p>
        <p>''If we can have a very good retail presentation where retailers stack it up and consumers see it, that's half the battle,'' Mr. Katz said. ''Rain doesn't hurt either.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
