<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ordering Hunt for Bomb Plotters, Sharon Resists More Drastic Steps</title>
    <meta content="22ISRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/international/middleeast/22ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bethlehem (West Bank)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Netanyahu, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Bomb Plots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hamas</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Islamic Jihad</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Netanyahu, Benjamin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2D61539F931A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ordering Hunt for Bomb Plotters, Sharon Resists More Drastic Steps</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ordering Hunt for Bomb Plotters, Sharon Resists More Drastic Steps</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ariel Sharon orders Israeli forces back into Bethlehem to hunt down terrorists responsible for Jerusalem bus bombing that killed 11 people, including four children, and wounded dozens more; resists, for now, pressure from right to take more drastic action even as Israelis reel from images of grieving parents and shredded teddy bear carried from wreckage of bus that was carrying many children to school; 23-year-old suicide bomber came from Bethlehem; Sharon aims to forestall escalation as US prepares for possible military action against Iraq; Israeli officials hope US victory there would force its enemies in region to sever ties with terrorists; criticism from Benjamin Netanyahu has also not done Sharon much damage within Likud party so far, and restrained response places Sharon closer to political center, while underscoring cooperative ties with Pres Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ariel Sharon ordered Israeli forces today to return to Bethlehem to hunt down those responsible for a suicide bombing on a Jerusalem bus this morning that killed 11 people, including at least four children, and wounded dozens, Israeli officials said.</p>
        <p>For the moment Mr. Sharon resisted pressure from his political right for more drastic military action, although Israelis reeled from images of grieving parents and scattered school books, and a shredded teddy bear carried from the wreckage by an emergency worker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ariel Sharon ordered Israeli forces to return to Bethlehem to hunt down those responsible for a suicide bombing on a Jerusalem bus that killed 11 people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ariel Sharon ordered Israeli forces today to return to Bethlehem to hunt down those responsible for a suicide bombing on a Jerusalem bus this morning that killed 11 people, including at least four children, and wounded dozens, Israeli officials said.</p>
        <p>For the moment Mr. Sharon resisted pressure from his political right for more drastic military action, although Israelis reeled from images of grieving parents and scattered school books, and a shredded teddy bear carried from the wreckage by an emergency worker.</p>
        <p>The bombing and the Israeli and Palestinian responses to it provided a painful glimpse into the turmoil in the politics on both sides more than two years into the current conflict.</p>
        <p>In the foreground was the crippled bus, not far from the boundary with Bethlehem, the 23-year-old bomber's hometown; in the background were the sweeping ambitions of the Bush administration to reshape the Middle East with a possible war on Iraq.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials said Mr. Sharon, who met into the night with his security advisers, had been governed in his response by the American military intentions. ''We are not going to allow any kind of escalation,'' said Raanan Gissin, Mr. Sharon's spokesman. He accused Palestinian terrorists of stepping up their own attacks in hopes of provoking such a response and opening a second front ahead of an Iraq war.</p>
        <p>Through a spokesman, the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat condemned the bombing as terrorism. Hamas and Islamic Jihad, two militant Islamic groups, issued dueling claims of responsibility for the attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon calculates that it is in Israel's interest to do what it can to avoid hindering the American effort to gain international support for a possible assault on Iraq. Israeli officials hope that an American victory will ultimately force Israel's adversaries in the region to sever links to terrorism and Palestinian militants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon also has more immediate concerns. In a week he faces a primary contest to retain the leadership of the Likud Party against Benjamin Netanyahu. Mr. Netanyahu, the former prime minister who recently became foreign minister, has shifted his emphasis from criticizing Mr. Sharon for failing to stop Israel's economic slide to criticizing him for failing to safeguard its security.</p>
        <p>Recalling his own tenure as prime minister in the 1990's, Mr. Netanyahu has been declaring in advertisements: ''Four suicide bombings in three years.'' In a deft twist of the knife, the advertisements are appearing on the sides of buses.</p>
        <p>Dozens of suicide bombers have struck since Mr. Sharon was elected in February 2001 on a platform of peace and security.</p>
        <p>But so far, Mr. Netanyahu's attacks from the right have not done much damage to Mr. Sharon within Likud. They appear to have placed him closer to the center of Israeli politics, the position that has helped sustain his popularity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon's response to today's bombing, if it remains restrained, may have the same effect, while also underscoring the cooperative relationship he has built with President Bush.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the bombing could not have been more precisely timed or targeted to undermine Israel's left-of-center alternative to Mr. Sharon. Just two days ago, the Labor Party elected as its new leader Amram Mitzna, who will compete in general elections on Jan. 28 as Labor's candidate for prime minister against the winner of the Likud primary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitzna is a former general who advocates immediate negotiations with the Palestinians, without conditions, and a unilateral Israeli withdrawal of soldiers and settlers from the Gaza Strip. Among other conditions before negotiations resume, Mr. Sharon insists that Mr. Arafat be replaced as Palestinian leader and that Palestinians halt all violence.</p>
        <p>At issue is a fundamental difference of belief over the source of the conflict. Where Mr. Sharon sees a relentless, generations-old campaign of Arab terror to destroy the Jewish state, Mr. Mitzna sees some Israeli culpability, stemming from Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip after the Arab-Israeli war of 1967.</p>
        <p>The wreckage of the No. 20 bus is a problem for the latter theory of the conflict and a possible blow to the idea that an Israeli withdrawal to pre-1967 borders might end the violence. The bombing took place on land that was Israel's before the 1967 war, and its victims included schoolchildren rather than only settlers and soldiers.</p>
        <p>In fact, a debate is under way among Palestinians over whether it is legitimate to attack Israelis outside what is known in shorthand as '67 land.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat today harshly criticized violence against Israeli civilians within the 1967 borders.</p>
        <p>''Resisting Israeli occupation and settlements doesn't mean targeting the lives of the Israeli civilians who have no relation at all with occupation and settlement activity,'' he said through his spokesman. ''They are normal people who are living their daily lives, and targeting them is a condemned act ethically and politically.''</p>
        <p>The effect of such bombings, he said, is to make even ''legitimate resistance'' look like ''blind terrorism.''</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Arafat has recognized Israel's right to exist, at least within its pre-1967 borders, Hamas and Islamic Jihad have not. In practice, these groups make no distinction among Israelis and have repeatedly shown a determination to kill them without regard to age, occupation or geography.</p>
        <p>At the urging of the European Union and Egypt, Mr. Arafat's Fatah faction has been negotiating with Hamas to suspend suicide bombings in pre-1967 Israel, at least during the Israeli election campaign, when such attacks are likely to aid the right wing.</p>
        <p>But in a commentary on a Hamas Web site today, Dr. Abdel Aziz Rantisi, a political leader of Hamas, rejected that distinction as well. ''I'm shocked at what I hear people keep saying, that the Likud is violent and the Labor is peaceful,'' he wrote. They are both violent, he said.</p>
        <p>In hopes of halting the violence on both sides, the so-called Quartet -- the United States, the United Nations, the European Union and Russia -- is pressing the antagonists to adopt a ''road map'' toward peace and a Palestinian state in 2005.</p>
        <p>Terje Roed-Larsen, the United Nations special envoy here, said Palestinians had diverse views about the violence. He argued that only the prospect of political progress could strengthen those in favor of peace, saying that so far ''scores of cease-fire declarations'' had yielded only more violence.</p>
        <p>''Unless there is a political underpinning, they cannot take hold,'' he said, ''and this is precisely what the work on the Quartet road map takes into account.''</p>
        <p>The road map is evolving. The Quartet recently added some requirements on both sides, including some that would be hard for Mr. Sharon: Israel would have to express a commitment to an ''independent, viable, sovereign'' Palestinian state and halt settlement expansion that would interfere with making Palestinian territory contiguous.</p>
        <p>But that schedule means that if Mr. Sharon wins the Likud primary, he will be faced with the road map at least a month before elections.</p>
        <p>''Israel would not want to be put in a position where it would have to make specific decisions with regard to that before the situation with Iraq is cleared up,'' said Zalman Shoval, a Likud politician and Sharon adviser.</p>
        <p>Depending on its final shape and timetable, the road map could force Mr. Sharon to make the decision he has so far evaded: choosing among his rightist political base, his averred willingness to make ''painful concessions'' for peace and his relationship with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>It could also force Mr. Arafat to make an often-avoided choice between merely condemning killing like today's and trying to stop it.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Israeli Troops Move Into Bethlehem</p>
        <p>JERUSALEM, Friday, Nov. 22 (AP) -- Israeli troops began retaliation early today, moving into Bethlehem and surrounding the Church of the Nativity, which marks the traditional birthplace of Jesus. An Israeli military spokesman, Doron Spielman, said the object was to prevent gunmen from seeking refuge in the church.</p>
        <p>The army planned a ''pinpoint operation,'' which would include entering Bethlehem, Mr. Gissin said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
