<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Cerebral Choreographer's Seventh-Inning Stretch</title>
    <meta content="21LIFE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE CREATIVE LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommason, Helgi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DC153DF932A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Cerebral Choreographer's Seventh-Inning Stretch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Dunning</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Helgi Tommason, artistic director and chief choreographer of San Francisco Ballet; his troupe is appearing at City Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Helgi Tomasson became the artistic director of the San Francisco Ballet almost accidentally. A leading dancer with the New York City Ballet, Mr. Tomasson sensed that by the mid-1980's it would be time to retire from the stage. An offer to direct the Royal Danish Ballet didn't pan out, so when Mr. Tomasson got a call from the San Francisco company, he signed on.</p>
        <p>That was 13 years ago. And now Mr. Tomasson, who is also the company's chief choreographer, nonetheless is feeling the need to stretch artistically.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Helgi Tomasson became the artistic director of the San Francisco Ballet almost accidentally. A leading dancer with the New York City Ballet, Mr. Tomasson sensed that by the mid-1980's it would be time to retire from the stage. An offer to direct the Royal Danish Ballet didn't pan out, so when Mr. Tomasson got a call from the San Francisco company, he signed on.</p>
        <p>That was 13 years ago. And now Mr. Tomasson, who is also the company's chief choreographer, nonetheless is feeling the need to stretch artistically.</p>
        <p>The troupe opened last night at City Center with a gala designed to introduce the many new dancers of the multinational San Francisco company, at 65 the oldest continuously operating American ballet troupe. Its ambitious weeklong program is aimed at reacquainting New Yorkers with the company's distinctively sleek, ebullient style.</p>
        <p>''It has been almost three years since we've been to New York,'' Mr. Tomasson said recently. ''I wanted to give audiences an opportunity to get to know the dancers better. I think we have some excellent dancers, so why not start that way?''</p>
        <p>To make that happen, an astonishingly varied roster of work will be performed, a kind of quick trip  through 20th-century ballet, with choreography by George Balanchine and Jerome Robbins and dance by later innovators like William Forsythe.</p>
        <p>And there are two cherished oddities from the middle period of contemporary ballet, Harald Lander's ''Etudes'' and a rarely seen dramatic piece by Flemming Flindt, ''The Lesson.''</p>
        <p>But the season's most interesting aspect may be Mr. Tomasson. Known best for his orderly, cerebral approach to classicism in music and dance, he is breaking loose, in his quiet way with two recent pieces that belie his tidy discipline.</p>
        <p>Is this Mr. Tomasson's equivalent of a seventh-inning stretch? ''Yes,'' he said, with the pent-up fervor of a late convert to the pleasures of iconoclasm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tomasson's two-part ''Crisscross,'' set to scores that bridge two centuries, might almost be a statement of commitment to classicism.  The piece opens with a dance performed to a reworking of Scarlatti harpsichord concerti by the 18th-century composer Charles Avison. The ballet's second section is set to Schoenberg's Concerto for String Quartet and Orchestra, a response to music by Handel. Both music and dance shift from classicism to neo-classicism to the Baroque and back.</p>
        <p>''Avison and Scarlatti belonged to the same time and worked in the classical style,'' Mr. Tomasson said. ''Schoenberg was of a totally different time and style from Handel. But the root is in classical music. I took the same approach.''</p>
        <p>The scores gave Mr. Tomasson a new feeling of freedom, he said. ''The only way I can describe it is the freedom to let myself not rely absolutely on classical technique in movement that has very much changed my way of thinking and what I want to do.'' 'Crisscross,'' he said, aims for a visual evocation of what Avison and Schoenberg did to the original music.</p>
        <p>''Silver Ladders,'' named after its score by the contemporary composer Joan Tower, is even more of a departure for Mr. Tomasson. Like ''Crisscross,'' ''Silver Ladders'' began as a response to music.</p>
        <p>Listening to the score, Mr. Tomasson said he found himself drawn by the music's powerful opening chords into a maze of sound that had the quality of a landscape; indeed, a place whose strangeness led him to think of Stonehenge and why people might have journeyed there so many centuries ago. The new ballet is Mr. Tomasson's attempt to retrace his steps, this time with dancers and audiences, on his own journey through Ms. Tower's urgent, mysterious music.</p>
        <p>In a time when dance seems to be slowly edging away from abstraction and back to dramatic narrative, Mr. Tomasson has created a ritual, he said, drawn from his speculations on what might have occurred at Stonehenge. The gathering of dancers takes place in an enclosure, where people sit as well as dance, that was designed by Martin Pakledinaz.  ''Martin was not quite sure what I was doing when I described it over the phone,'' Mr. Tomasson said. ''But when he saw the finished ballet he said he'd have to create a place, just as I did.''</p>
        <p>''The music is very difficult because although it is rhythmical, it doesn't keep an even beat,'' Mr. Tomasson continued. ''How would the dancers count? I had to make them hear the music the way I did, even though I hadn't known where it would lead me. Obviously, my training is in classical technique, and that will come through. But I'm taking more liberties now.''</p>
        <p>THE CREATIVE LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
