<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Moves On Rushdie Exposing Iranian Rifts</title>
    <meta content="Y21IRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rushdie, Salman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khatami, Mohammad (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Satanic Verses, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2D8153DF932A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Moves On Rushdie Exposing Iranian Rifts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, Oct. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iran's Sept move dissociating itself from death threats to British author Salman Rushdie continues to expose fissures among Iran's rival centers of power; protests by conservatives underscore powerful constraints still facing Pres Mohammad Khatami's relatively moderate Government as he seeks to reshape Iran's image (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A month after Iran's Government dissociated itself from death threats to the British author Salman Rushdie, the decision is still exposing fissures among Iran's rival centers of power.</p>
        <p>A majority in Iran's conservative-dominated Parliament has signed a letter insisting that a religious decree calling for Mr. Rushdie's death  for blasphemy against Islam is still valid. They also declared that Muslims had a duty to carry out the decree.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A month after Iran's Government dissociated itself from death threats to the British author Salman Rushdie, the decision is still exposing fissures among Iran's rival centers of power.</p>
        <p>A majority in Iran's conservative-dominated Parliament has signed a letter insisting that a religious decree calling for Mr. Rushdie's death  for blasphemy against Islam is still valid. They also declared that Muslims had a duty to carry out the decree.</p>
        <p>Although Iran's Foreign Minister, Kamal Kharazzi, said on Sept. 24 that his country would not aid or reward anyone who killed Mr. Rushdie, two hard-line Iranian groups have since publicly vowed to carry out the 1989 decree, and they have offered new bounties on the author's life.</p>
        <p>And last Friday, in the latest of several anti-Government demonstrations, at least 75 members of the hard-line Ansar e-Hezbollah gathered in Teheran to issue new threats against Mr. Rushdie, unveiling a three-story mural dedicated to the memory of a man they said tried to kill the author nine years ago.</p>
        <p>''We don't obey the Foreign Minister,'' chanted a member of the group, which has long been linked to violence and is believed to have the backing of high-level clerics in the Government. ''Remember our faces,  Salman Rushdie. We will kill you.''</p>
        <p>According to journalists who were present, Iranian security forces made no effort to break up the demonstration, and neither has the Government made any evident effort to silence the organizations now offering bounties of more than $3 million payable on Mr. Rushdie's death.</p>
        <p>Diplomats and political experts say the protests by conservatives have underscored the powerful constraints still facing the Government of President Mohammad Khatami, a relative moderate, as he seeks to reshape his country's image with a gentler face.</p>
        <p>''All of this must be seen as part of the broader challenge to Mr. Khatami,'' a Western diplomat said in a telephone interview. ''There are a lot of people determined to oppose him everywhere he turns, and the Rushdie case is one in which some conservatives are trying to portray his stance as a betrayal.''</p>
        <p>Many powerful figures in Iran -- including those who dominate Parliament, the judiciary, and the office of the current supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei -- have interpreted the landslide victory won by Mr. Khatami in the country's May 1997 presidential elections as a threat to their long hold on power. And some conservatives see the Government's new stance on the Rushdie case as deviating from the Islamic republic's strict religious principles.</p>
        <p>''We call on the Government to apologize for this mistake,'' a group of war veterans said last week in announcing that it would collect $333,000 to be paid to anyone who assassinated Mr. Rushdie.</p>
        <p>Despite the renewed threats, the British Government, which restored full diplomatic relations with Iran after Mr. Kharazzi's announcement, has said it has no reason to believe that Iran has changed its position. And on Monday, a group of international committees that had campaigned on behalf of Mr. Rushdie announced in Norway that they had agreed to disband in recognition of a deal that they said had reduced the risk to the author's life.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Rushdie, who last month pronounced himself a free man for the first time in nearly a decade, met on Friday with the British Foreign Secretary, Robin Cook, to review the latest developments.</p>
        <p>The religious decree, or fatwa, against Mr. Rushdie was issued by  Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, who was the country's supreme leader but who died several months later. Islamic scholars have said no one else has the right to lift the ruling, which accused Mr. Rushdie of having defamed Islam with his novel ''The Satanic Verses.''</p>
        <p>Since that time, Iran's policy has been that it did not officially sanction the death decree. But Mr. Kharazzi's more gentle restatement of that position, made during talks in New York with British officials, reflected the temperate tone that Mr. Khatami has brought to Iranian politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kharazzi pledged that Iran would not encourage or assist anybody in threatening Mr. Rushdie's life. He also dissociated the Government from the bounty that a powerful religious charity, the 15th Khordad Foundation, has put the author's head. But since his announcement, that foundation has announced that it would add $300,000 to a bounty that already stood at $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>And the newspaper Kayhan reported on Sunday that another bounty had been offered by the 2,000 residents of Kiyapay village in northern Iran. A village official quoted by the paper said the residents had opened a bank account to gather donations and had pledged to provide farmland, fruit gardens, ''a house, and 10 carpets as a reward for carrying out the execution sentence against the author of the blasphemous book.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
