<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equities Give Up Big Gains; Dow Up and Nasdaq Down</title>
    <meta content="Y21STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DF123DF932A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equities Give Up Big Gains; Dow Up and Nasdaq Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones industrial average is up 39.40 points, to close at 8,505.85; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gains 1.54 points, to 1,063.93; Nasdaq composite index falls 9.54 points, to 1,639.19; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock prices went on a wild ride yesterday, soaring for most of the session only to retreat in the last hour or so of trading and end up narrowly mixed. The Dow Jones industrial average gained ground for the fifth consecutive session, the first time since June it has rallied for that many days in succession.</p>
        <p>The blue-chip index, which at one point in the morning was up 186 points, closed at 8,505.85, up 39.40 points, or slightly under one-half of a percent. It was the first time the Dow closed above 8,500 since Aug. 26. For the year, the index is up 7.56 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock prices went on a wild ride yesterday, soaring for most of the session only to retreat in the last hour or so of trading and end up narrowly mixed. The Dow Jones industrial average gained ground for the fifth consecutive session, the first time since June it has rallied for that many days in succession.</p>
        <p>The blue-chip index, which at one point in the morning was up 186 points, closed at 8,505.85, up 39.40 points, or slightly under one-half of a percent. It was the first time the Dow closed above 8,500 since Aug. 26. For the year, the index is up 7.56 percent.</p>
        <p>The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index eked out a gain of 1.54 points, or a little more than one-tenth of a percent, to 1,063.93. But the Nasdaq composite index fell 9.54 points, or six-tenths of a percent, to 1,639.19.</p>
        <p>Traders said business did not seem especially brisk yesterday, but volume on the New York Stock Exchange was heavy, at 947 million shares. Advancing stocks significantly outnumbered those declining.</p>
        <p>Money continued to flow out of the bond market. The price of the benchmark 30-year Treasury bond fell by more than a point, and the yield rose to 5.07 percent from 4.97 percent. Short-term interest rates rose.</p>
        <p>While some stock traders apparently had second thoughts late in the session about the wisdom of holding highly liquid, well-known stocks, issues of smaller companies were popular all day. Traders said they were encouraged by the continued improvement in small-capitalization companies, which have been battered this year. The Russell 2000 index, made up of small-company stocks, rose 5.86 points, or 1.66 percent, to 358.31. ''There is enormous opportunity in small caps if we have stability here,'' said Michael Clark, head of United States stock trading at Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Stocks got a big boost early in the day from several big banks, including Chase Manhattan and Wells Fargo, which reported third-quarter earnings that were better than expected. Chase, the nation's second-biggest bank, rose 1 13/16, to 53 1/16 after it said it earned 82 cents a share in the period, 5 cents better than the consensus of Wall Street analysts.</p>
        <p>Wells Fargo, which is merging with Norwest, rose 11 1/16, to 378 9/16, after it said earnings rose 20 percent, which also exceeded expectations.</p>
        <p>The results encouraged investors to believe that the worst is over for battered financial services companies and helped lift stocks of money-center banks and brokerage firms.</p>
        <p>Citigroup rose 2 9/16, to 45 5/16. J. P. Morgan gained 2 1/2, to 95 3/8. Fueled by reports it might be acquired by Deutsche Bank A.G., Europe's biggest bank, Bankers Trust gained 4 3/16, to 58 15/16. And Merrill Lynch jumped 2 7/16, to 54 13/16.</p>
        <p>''At this point, just over one-third of the companies that make up the S.&amp; P. have reported third-quarter earnings, and the good news is they have come in as expected, even though the bar was lowered,'' said Bob Gasser, head of block trading at J. P. Morgan. ''But the bigger test will come after we are through this earnings season and people start looking out in the future, trying to determine when they will trough.''</p>
        <p>I.B.M. gave investors reason to start thinking about the future. The computer giant reported yesterday that third-quarter earnings rose 10 percent, a figure that also exceeded expectations. But I.B.M. gave analysts a cautious reading of its prospects, saying that continued problems in Asia and Latin America and decreased spending by corporations on high-technology equipment could crimp profit in the fourth quarter and into 1999.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. shares ended the day down 1 1/2, at 137 7/8. Early in the session, the stock traded as high as 142 7/16.  THE MARKETS: STOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
