<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Priest Guilty in Sex Abuse Of 11-Year-Old Altar Boy</title>
    <meta content="12PRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/12/nyregion/12PRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1447924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banko, John M (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1DA123AF931A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Priest Guilty in Sex Abuse Of 11-Year-Old Altar Boy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Priest Guilty in Sex Abuse of 11-Year-Old Altar Boy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey priest Rev John M Banko is found guilty of sexually assaulting 11-year-old altar boy twice nearly 10 years ago; faces up to 35-year prison sentence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 56-year-old Roman Catholic priest in New Jersey was found guilty yesterday of sexually assaulting an 11-year-old altar boy on two occasions after Sunday Mass nearly a decade ago.</p>
        <p>A jury of nine women and three men deliberated only a few hours between Tuesday afternoon and late yesterday morning before returning its verdict in the first sex-abuse trial of a priest in New Jersey since the scandal erupted this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 56-year-old Roman Catholic priest in New Jersey was found guilty yesterday of sexually assaulting an 11-year-old altar boy on two occasions after Sunday Mass nearly a decade ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 56-year-old Roman Catholic priest in New Jersey was found guilty yesterday of sexually assaulting an 11-year-old altar boy on two occasions after Sunday Mass nearly a decade ago.</p>
        <p>A jury of nine women and three men deliberated only a few hours between Tuesday afternoon and late yesterday morning before returning its verdict in the first sex-abuse trial of a priest in New Jersey since the scandal erupted this year.</p>
        <p>After the priest, the Rev. John M. Banko, was convicted, the trial prosecutor, Dawn M. Solari, of the Hunterdon County prosecutor's office, appealed to victims of other priests to come forward and help the authorities bring charges in their cases. ''I hope they can see that the system worked in this case,'' Ms. Solari said.</p>
        <p>At least one other priest in New Jersey, the Rev. Michael Fugee, 42, of Wyckoff, has been charged with molesting a young male parishioner. His trial is expected to begin in the spring in Hackensack.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the Diocese of Metuchen, in which Father Banko had served as parish pastor and priest, called his actions abhorrent and vowed to help the authorities prosecute any other abuse cases against priests.</p>
        <p>''Our hearts go out to the victims who testified in this matter and to their families, who surely have endured years of pain and anguish,'' the statement said. ''To each of them we apologize.''</p>
        <p>Father Banko's victim, who is now 20 years old, buried his head in his hands when the verdict was announced in New Jersey Superior Court in Flemington. Moments later, according to The Associated Press, his mother said: ''We've waited a long time for this. I'm just glad it's over. My son can get back to, maybe, a normal life.''</p>
        <p>Father Banko, who has been a priest in New Jersey since 1972, showed little emotion. The presiding judge, Ann R. Bartlett, revoked his $25,000 bail and ordered him held in the Hunterdon County jail. He faces a prison term of up to 35 years when he is sentenced Feb. 7. The judge ordered that he undergo psychiatric evaluation at the state's center for sexual predators in Avenel before he is sentenced.</p>
        <p>The jury convicted Father Banko of all three charges against him: aggravated sexual assault, sexual assault and endangering the welfare of a child. The authorities said the assaults occurred on two consecutive Sundays between September 1993 and September 1994 in a small changing room near the main altar at St. Edward the Confessor Church in Milford, N.J. On both occasions, Father Banko, the church pastor at the time, had just finished saying Mass, and he and the youth, who had served as his altar boy, were changing clothes. Both times, the authorities said, the priest performed fellatio on the youth and then forced the boy to touch the priest's genital area.</p>
        <p>After testifying about the acts when the trial opened last Wednesday, the young man said Father Banko warned him that his parents would be harmed if he told anyone of the incidents. The boy kept the secret until he told a friend in November 1999, Ms. Solari, the prosecutor said. The friend notified the authorities, and the investigation started in December 1999. The Diocese of Metuchen suspended Father Banko from ministerial duties in April 2000, meaning he could no longer publicly say Mass, said a diocesan spokeswoman, Joanne Ward.</p>
        <p>Before he was jailed yesterday, Father Banko had been living with his 94-year-old mother in Trenton, his lawyer, Lewis White 3rd said. Mr. White said he planned to apply for reinstatement of the $25,000 bail. As for an appeal, Mr. White said he would refer the priest to the state public defender's office because he is unemployed and unable to afford a private lawyer. Ms. Ward, the diocesan spokeswoman, said the church had provided no funds for Father Banko's defense.</p>
        <p>In addition to the former altar boy, three men, now in their 30's, testified against the priest to show that he had engaged in a pattern of seduction. One said the priest once grabbed his buttocks, another said Father Banko had once masturbated in front of him, and the third said the priest had performed fellatio on him several times while he was still a seminarian in the early 1970's. No charges were filed in their cases because the statute of limitations had expired.</p>
        <p>Father Banko testified in his own defense and denied their accounts, as well as the former altar boy's. But during Ms. Solari's cross-examination he acknowledged that he had once told detectives he had had sexual relations with both men and women who, he believed, were all older than 18. He said he had interpreted his vow of celibacy to mean he could never marry but could engage in sexual relations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
