<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising;On-line services are venturing into unexplored territory as they try to establish their brand names.</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="809304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICA ONLINE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TBWA CHIAT/DAY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DF1239F935A25752C1A963958260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising;On-line services are venturing into unexplored territory as they try to establish their brand names.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Ramirez</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE branding a steer, a branding campaign in advertising seeks to separate the advertised product or service from the herd. But are America Online's new television commercials outstanding or simply egregious?</p>
        <p>Consider this ad: As the spooky and majestic theme music from the film "2001: A Space Odyssey" grows louder in the background, a monkey's paw is seen pushing  a computer mouse. The paw double-clicks on icons and the computer screen sputters and shifts. Does this mean the killer ape from "2001" has traded in his bone for a killer application?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE branding a steer, a branding campaign in advertising seeks to separate the advertised product or service from the herd. But are America Online's new television commercials outstanding or simply egregious?</p>
        <p>Consider this ad: As the spooky and majestic theme music from the film "2001: A Space Odyssey" grows louder in the background, a monkey's paw is seen pushing  a computer mouse. The paw double-clicks on icons and the computer screen sputters and shifts. Does this mean the killer ape from "2001" has traded in his bone for a killer application?</p>
        <p>The camera then pulls back to reveal a different kind of primate, a nerd in  a short-sleeved shirt brandishing an enormous, hairy glove. Then he smiles goofily and says, "Boy, that would have been even easier without the monkey glove!"</p>
        <p>However the viewer reacts to the campaign, developed by TBWA Chiat/Day of New York, it is the most eye-catching effort in the still-nascent business of marketing computer on-line services. America Online of Vienna, Va., and its rivals, Compuserve of Columbus, Ohio, and Prodigy of White Plains, provide a combination citizens' band radio, public library and sewing bee, conducted round-the-clock on sophisticated computer networks.</p>
        <p>In the increasingly competitive marketplace for such services, one of the last concerns of these companies has been advertising. Subscribers walked in off the street, signing on faster than companies' computer networks could handle the load. A busy telephone signal often greeted new subscribers trying to use these services.</p>
        <p>Now, however, growth has slowed for Prodigy, owned by Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, and Compuserve, a unit of H&amp; R Block Inc., while America Online's explosive expansion continues. Today, Prodigy's subscribers number 1.4 million,  up about 8 percent from November 1994, while Compuserve's numbers are up 53 percent, to 2.2 million, according to Jupiter Communications, a consulting firm. By contrast, America Online has tripled to 4 million from 1.35 million a year ago.</p>
        <p>"We've never done a branding campaign before," said Theodore J. Leonsis, president of America Online Services Inc. "We wanted something that would be in-your-face and get us noticed, so we turned to Chiat/ Day because they walked  the walk and talked the talk of cyberspace. We wanted to show diversity and humanity and fun."</p>
        <p>The campaign developed by TBWA Chiat/Day, famed for such campaigns as the Energizer battery bunny, is an often puzzling potpourri of 22 television commercials, each lasting 15 seconds. In one ad, a human caricature of a gap-toothed hillbilly is telling his daughter that he is in a computer "chat room" talking to a "fella" in distant Washington who is "pro-Nafta," as the North American Free Trade Agreement is known. Then, off screen, the sound of a shotgun, blowing away the computer screen, is heard.</p>
        <p>In a third spot, the camera pans across a huge office full of cubicles, where a white-shirted office worker is staring intently at his computer screen. "Your  boss will think you're working," says an off-screen announcer. But the office worker says, "Thanks to America Online, I'm really just goofing off."</p>
        <p>America Online's rivals have taken different approaches. Prodigy's agency, Cliff Freeman &amp; Partners in New York, developed an ad campaign around computer bulletin boards that cleverly demonstrates the often-baffling cornucopia of information on computer networks.</p>
        <p>A fisherman wanders through a desert, a stock exchange and an opera, when all of a sudden a street bus named "Fly Fishing" comes into view. It's filled with happy fishermen and symbolizes Prodigy's "interest group" bulletin boards.</p>
        <p>Compuserve's agency, Martin/ Williams of Minneapolis, seeks to emphasize Compuserve's long-standing strength -- hundreds of data services that are more professional and business-oriented than those of Prodigy and America Online. The agency declined to discuss the television campaign, which it calls "Deeper Answers."</p>
        <p>TBWA Chiat/Day also refused to return repeated phone calls seeking comment on the advertising campaign it developed. Neither it nor America Online would detail the spending on the campaign.</p>
        <p>David Hoffman, who heads the Hoffman Group, a Woodside, Calif., consulting firm whose clients include AT&amp;T and Motorola, said on-line services and their advertising are in unexplored territory.</p>
        <p>"By the nature of computer on-line services, it is elitist advertising placed in mass-market media like television," Mr. Hoffman said. Only 32 percent of American homes have computers, only 21 percent also have modems, and of these only 15 percent use on-line services. Therefore, Mr. Hoffman said, America Online is trying to appeal to only 6 percent of the potential national audience  when it advertises on such shows as NBC's "Seinfeld."</p>
        <p>Especially with spots like "the monkey glove," America Online is in danger of alienating this audience, which might be difficult to motivate. "You have to know the joke to get the joke," Mr. Hoffman said.</p>
        <p>Gene De Rose, president of Jupiter Communications, the New York consulting firm, disagrees. He said America Online, Prodigy and Compuserve were not competing against each other but against the Internet, which has a much more irreverent, free-form style. All three on-line companies have to struggle to avoid looking like the Reader's Digest, compared with Wired magazine.</p>
        <p>"AOL's being irreverent about themselves," Mr. De Rose said, "without necessarily talking down to their actual or potential audience."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
