<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Infertile, a High-Tech Treadmill</title>
    <meta content="14HOPE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971216T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fertility Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Artificial Insemination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Center for Health Statistics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Infertility</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Artificial Insemination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fertility Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fertility Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DD163FF937A25751C1A961958260" item-length="2076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Infertile, a High-Tech Treadmill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Infertile couples find it hard to say no to reproductive technology, even though high-tech path to parenthood yields failure far more often than success; National Center for Health Statistics says that in 1995, United States had 60.2 million women of reproductive age, 10 percent of whom were infertile; of these, 600,000 had tried assisted reproductive technology; less than 25 percent were successful; but new strides in science of making babies encourage infertile couples to press on, hoping that next expensive procedure will be one that will finally work; some patients are going heavily into debt to pay for treatment; only 12 states require insurance companies to cover treatments, which often can drag on for years; experts are studying vicious cycle of depression, noting that infertility causes depression, and depression can also contribute to infertility; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a frigid Sunday morning in February 1995, Nancy Alisberg and Michael Albano took a stroll on a windswept beach. They had fled their Brooklyn apartment for the Hamptons, holing up in a quaint bed-and-breakfast for the weekend. But this was no ordinary getaway.</p>
        <p>It was, rather, a funeral of sorts. After three unsuccessful attempts at conceiving a test-tube baby, the Brooklyn couple had come to the seashore to bury their dream of having a biological child.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a frigid Sunday morning in February 1995, Nancy Alisberg and Michael Albano took a stroll on a windswept beach. They had fled their Brooklyn apartment for the Hamptons, holing up in a quaint bed-and-breakfast for the weekend. But this was no ordinary getaway.</p>
        <p>It was, rather, a funeral of sorts. After three unsuccessful attempts at conceiving a test-tube baby, the Brooklyn couple had come to the seashore to bury their dream of having a biological child.</p>
        <p>Bundled up in their heavy winter coats, they settled in near a log to protect themselves from the wind. There, Ms. Alisberg and Mr. Albano, both lawyers, both in their early 40's, pulled lists from their pockets on which each had written characteristics of the other that they would miss in not having a baby from their own eggs and sperm. They read the lists aloud and then, because it was too windy to burn them, as they had planned, they buried them in the sand.</p>
        <p>The ceremony, Ms. Alisberg said recently, ''was to say goodbye and then to try to work on the moving on.'' But moving on was easier said than done.</p>
        <p>The couple began investigating adoption as soon as they returned home, and they are now the parents of a 2-year-old girl from Korea. But at the same time they plunged back into the seductive, emotionally wrenching world of reproductive medicine, signing up for egg donation, in which Ms. Alisberg might become pregnant using another woman's eggs.</p>
        <p>''The technology,'' Mr. Albano said, ''has given us so many options that it is hard to say no.''</p>
        <p>For infertile couples, saying no to reproductive technology has become a vexing problem. Every month, it seems, there is another stride in the science of making babies. And while public attention inevitably focuses on the latest accomplishment -- the McCaughey septuplets, the California woman who gave birth at 63 and other recent feats -- the reality is that the high-tech path to parenthood yields failure far more often than success, about three out of four times.</p>
        <p>Thousands of couples are riding the infertility merry-go-round, many unable to get off for fear that the next expensive procedure is the one that will finally work.</p>
        <p>''My patients are always saying to me, 'How can I stop?' '' said Dr. Alice Domar, who directs the behavioral medicine program for infertility at the Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston. ''I've got this 42-year-old woman in my group who is just about at the end. She says they are ready to move on, and then she hears about this cytoplasm stuff,'' in which doctors mingle the core genetic blueprint of one egg with the surrounding fluid, or cytoplasm, from another.</p>
        <p>''Where,'' Dr. Domar asked, ''do you get to the point where you say, 'I can't do this anymore?' ''</p>
        <p>Going Against Odds, Sure They'll Win</p>
        <p>The question carries as much angst for infertility specialists as it does for their patients. ''This is the hardest part of my job,'' said Dr. Jamie A. Grifo, director of the division of reproductive endocrinology at New York University Medical Center. ''I have patients whom I tell, point blank, 'You should stop,' and they say to me, 'Well, I want to give it one more try.' I say: 'Here, look at the data. Your chance is one percent.' And they say, 'Well, I'm going to be that one, Doc.' ''</p>
        <p>The National Center for Health Statistics says that in 1995, the most recent year for available figures, the United States had 60.2 million women of reproductive age, and that about about 10 percent -- or 6.1 million of them -- were infertile. Of these, about 600,000 had at some point tried assisted reproductive technology, participating in what Pamela Madsen, who runs a New York support group for infertile women, calls ''the ovarian Olympics.''</p>
        <p>New terms are entering the popular lexicon, from ''assisted hatching,'' in which researches slit open the shells of embryos, to a veritable alphabet soup of techniques. There is IVF, for in vitro fertilization, in which sperm and egg are combined in a laboratory dish and then implanted into the uterus as embryos. There is GIFT, for gamete intrafallopian transfer, in which eggs and sperm are inserted into the fallopian tubes in the hope they will unite into embryos. There is ZIFT, for zygote intrafallopian transfer, in which fertilized embryos are transferred to the tubes. There is ICSI, for intracytoplasmic sperm injection, in which male infertility is treated by sifting through a man's sperm and injecting a single strong one into a woman's egg. And of course, there is egg donation.</p>
        <p>The procedures take place over the course of a month and are therefore called cycles. The American Society for Reproductive Medicine estimates that in 1994, the most recent year for which figures are available, infertility clinics attempted 42,509 cycles of high-tech conception, resulting in 9,573 births, some multiple, for an overall success rate of 22.5 percent. A couple's chances of success depend on a variety of factors, including the woman's age and the quality of her eggs, as well as her husband's sperm count.</p>
        <p>For in vitro fertilization, the most common technique, the success rate was 20.7 percent. Egg donation has a much higher success rate -- 46.8 percent -- but it means that a woman must give up a genetic connection to her child. Some, like Mr. Albano, have a difficult time with that. ''It didn't sit well with me that I wouldn't have a pairing of my genetic material with hers,'' he said. ''But Nancy was very much desirous of wanting to experience pregnancy and birth.''</p>
        <p>Emotional Appeals At Vulnerable Time</p>
        <p>Critics have suggested that there is an element of subtle coercion in all this state-of-the-art medicine, with infertility clinics making emotional appeals to couples at a particularly vulnerable point in their lives. Moreover, they fear that couples in their baby-making fervor are not thinking through the moral implications of having children whose genetic roots are different from their own.</p>
        <p>''This is not just a science problem; it's a marketing problem,'' said Barbara Katz Rothman, professor of sociology at City University of New York. ''Once you are buying these services, there is a never-ending next service.''</p>
        <p>The treatments are expensive. In vitro fertilization costs, on average, $7,800 per cycle. And some patients are going heavily in debt to pay for them, taking second and even third mortgages on their homes. While doctors who treat fertility consider it  a disease, only 12 states require insurance companies to cover the treatments, which often can drag on for years.</p>
        <p>''We pay $550 a month for our own insurance,'' said Heather Higgins, 28, of Billerica, Mass., a small town near the New Hampshire border. She and her husband, Eric, who drives a canteen truck, have spent more than six years trying to have a baby. ''I would have the cheapo accident insurance if it weren't for the infertility. With $8,000 a cycle, I could never do it.''</p>
        <p>Woman Loses Count Of Failures at 21</p>
        <p>By her own estimation, Mrs. Higgins has attempted in vitro fertilization more than 20 times. ''I lost count at 21,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her physician, Dr. Vito Cardone of the Fertility Center of New England in Reading, Mass., says the multiple attempts are necessary because Mrs. Higgins is a ''poor producer,'' meaning the fertility drugs he gives her prompt her body to create only one or two eggs at a time, and sometimes none at all. He is pressing her to try egg donation, but Mrs. Higgins is not ready.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to exhaust all efforts,'' she said, ''emotionally, physically and financially, until I can't.''</p>
        <p>She works part time as a medical assistant, but her days are governed by the rhythm of her in vitro fertilization cycles: 16 days of fertility drugs, which her husband injects into her buttocks (he practiced on an orange); vaginal ultrasound probes to check egg developement; egg retrieval, in which doctors remove her eggs, mix them with sperm in a laboratory dish to create embryos that will be inserted into her uterus when they are no bigger than eight cells, and then 10 days of anxious waiting to find out if she is pregnant. She spends much of her time at the computer, chatting electronically with infertile friends in far-flung places.</p>
        <p>''I probably sign on five or six times a day,'' she said. ''Some of the messages are very sad.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, experts have long suspected that infertility causes depression, and while there is little research on the topic, they are just beginning to learn that depression can also contribute to infertility.</p>
        <p>Dr. Domar, the counselor, said infertile women were twice as likely to be depressed as those who are fertile. In 1993, she published research that found women with infertility had the same levels of depression as those with cancer, heart disease or the virus that causes AIDS.</p>
        <p>But she said the last time anyone examined the link between treatment failure and depression was 1984, when a study showed that 64 percent of women who had undergone an unsuccessful in vitro fertilization cycle demonstrated symptoms of clinical depression. The results did not surprise her.</p>
        <p>''Unsuccessful treatment is going to cause depression,'' she said. ''That's just common sense. The problem is that women who have the resources or insurance bounce right back and do more cycles.''</p>
        <p>Devastating Discovery Led to the Hamptons</p>
        <p>Indeed, Nancy Alisberg and Michael Albano said they would have continued their attempts at in vitro fertilization had it not been for genetic screening that showed Ms. Alisberg's eggs contained chromosomal anomalies, meaning the infant would be born with birth defects.</p>
        <p>The discovery, which prompted their trip to the Hamptons, came after three emotionally grueling years of trying to conceive, including an unsuccessful effort to correct Mr. Albano's low sperm count by removing an enlarged vein in his scrotum; two artificial inseminations, and three in vitro fertilizations, including one that resulted in a ''biochemical pregnancy,'' in which a blood test suggested that Ms. Alisberg was pregnant. But the embryo failed to implant.</p>
        <p>The discovery of the genetic defects left the couple with a difficult decision: Would they move on to egg donation, which might enable Ms. Alisberg to fulfill her desire to carry a baby? Or would they choose adoption, which would virtually guarantee a child? Cost was an issue; while their health insurance covered in vitro fertilization, it did not cover egg donation. If they spent $15,000 for donated eggs, the couple reasoned, they might lose the money they had saved for adoption. While adoption agencies discourage it, they decided to push ahead on both fronts.</p>
        <p>Jumping back on the infertility merry-go-round was no picnic. To test the likelihood that she would get pregnant with a donated egg, Ms. Alisberg had to go through a ''mock cycle'' in which she took fertility drugs, underwent blood tests, ultrasound scans and biopsies, all the while knowing that no embryos would be transferred into her uterus.</p>
        <p>''Everybody I know who has gone through IVF and then started doing donor egg has a real visceral reaction to being back in that waiting room,'' Ms. Alisberg said. ''You don't want to feel those things again.''</p>
        <p>On Dec. 27, 1995, Sophie Sang Ah Albano-Alisberg arrived from Korea, 4 months old, long and lean, with fuzzy black hair and beautiful clear skin. Her new parents met her at La Guardia Airport, after two months of gazing at her picture. ''I recognized her immediately,'' Mr. Albano said.</p>
        <p>Not quite two weeks later, he and his wife received a call from their infertility clinic, which had matched them with an egg donor. They spent a few days considering the offer, but finally rejected it. ''It was not fair to Sophie,'' Ms. Alisberg said. ''She had just arrived.''</p>
        <p>But she and her husband cannot bring themselves to eliminate the possibility of egg donation entirely. Today, two years later, their names remain on the donor candidate list.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 16, 1997, Tuesday  A front-page article on Sunday about infertility misstated the problem of Nancy Alisberg and her husband, Michael Albano. Ms. Alisberg's eggs had chromosomal anomalies that prevented them from implanting as embryos in her womb, not anomalies that would have caused birth defects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 16, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Sunday about infertility misstated the problem of Nancy Alisberg and her husband, Michael Albano. Ms. Alisberg's eggs had chromosomal anomalies that prevented them from implanting as embryos in her womb, not anomalies that would have caused birth defects.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
