<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American, Asian and a Warm Welcome</title>
    <meta content="14DIN.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merry Pedlar (Floral Park, LI, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDC123CF937A25751C1A961958260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American, Asian and a Warm Welcome</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews The Merry Pedlar, restaurant in Floral Park, LI (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER Duffy's Tavern on the radio? The Merry Pedlar in Floral Park is the same kind of homey, neighborhood spot. Instead of a bartender telling all comers, ''Duffy ain't here,'' there was a beaming priest sitting at a table near the entrance who volunteered, ''This is a wonderful restaurant with great food.'' Who could argue with a heavenly endorsement like that?</p>
        <p>On a second visit, we were welcomed with a round of applause. No, it was not the priest and his parishioners. Rather, two multitalented musicians had just finished playing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER Duffy's Tavern on the radio? The Merry Pedlar in Floral Park is the same kind of homey, neighborhood spot. Instead of a bartender telling all comers, ''Duffy ain't here,'' there was a beaming priest sitting at a table near the entrance who volunteered, ''This is a wonderful restaurant with great food.'' Who could argue with a heavenly endorsement like that?</p>
        <p>On a second visit, we were welcomed with a round of applause. No, it was not the priest and his parishioners. Rather, two multitalented musicians had just finished playing.</p>
        <p>Even though the hand was not for us, the greeting by the smiling hostess was a warm one. At the Merry Pedlar everyone feels at home. Family groups in jeans and baseball caps are as comfortable as the couples dressed for an evening out who occasionally get up and dance to a song or two. Valet parking, live music, an inviting antipasto table and a waiter sporting a tuxedo are weekend additions that do not alter the casual spirit of this hospitable restaurant.</p>
        <p>The pleasing decor combines a garden motif with antique touches:  plants, bentwood and wicker chairs with floral cushions, striking etched-glass windows, botanical prints, an old wood bar, period light fixtures and dark wood wainscotting.</p>
        <p>Service is a bit wobbly. One evening our very sweet waitress was knowledgeable and seemed competent, but the meal took forever. The problem may have been in the kitchen. We were ordering a la carte selections while most diners were trying the very economical (and possibly faster) three-course dinner at $19.97. On another evening, service was more speedy, but it always took at least two requests to get a beverage refilled.</p>
        <p>Longtime residents of Floral Park may remember a restaurant at this location called the Merry Pedlar a decade or two ago. The original owner is back, the name is the same but the food is a new story. The chef is Bill McCann, who is French trained, was sous chef at the Rainbow Room and most recently cooked at 13 Barrow Street and the Screening Room in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The food is 1990's American with a few pastas and a smattering of Asian offerings (a trio of stir frys and an orange lacquer duck).</p>
        <p>Among the standout starters are a wild mushroom salad ( a toss of greens, a ragout of mushrooms and a warm thyme vinaigrette) and a plate of seafood-vegetable fritters. The crisp, greaseless morsels, combining corn, peppers, salmon and shrimp, surround a chunky tomato-pineapple relish.</p>
        <p>In that same major league was the soup of the day, a pureed vegetable brew that was full of flavor. Another treat was the help-yourself antipasto table ($6.95) that sparkled with roasted peppers, grilled vegetables, olives, cheese, meats, asparagus, a bowl of mesclun and dressings.</p>
        <p>Also earning kudos were the rich onion soup, the goat cheese-topped caponata, the mixed green (mostly romaine) salad in a pleasing lemon vinaigrette and the rustic salad chock full of blue cheese, apples, croutons and nuts. The less than classic Caesar, though, had a bland, creamy dressing.</p>
        <p>Among the entree choices on the $19.97 dinner is a superb penne with a meat sauce made with chunks of fork-tender sirloin, red wine and vegetables. Another good pick on that menu is the chicken stir fry, overflowing with crisp vegetables and Asian flavors.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the East, the orange lacquer duck is a beauty: a roasted leg with crisp skin, rare slices of tender grilled breast and a seductive pecan-currant rice. In sharp contrast, though, was a lackluster breast of chicken in a very faint Dijon mustard sauce.</p>
        <p>The only fish we sampled, Southwestern grilled tuna, was overcooked. Still, its salsa topper and bed of warm greens nearly saved it.</p>
        <p>Meats fared better. The T-bone veal chop, escorted by artichoke hearts, tomatoes and a marsala sauce, was a hit, as were a special steak in a mushroom-wine sauce and the menu's baron of lamb. The last included juicy chops and a slow roasted meld of shredded leg of lamb.</p>
        <p>Desserts are great. When did you last see a do-it-yourself hot fudge sundae on a restaurant menu? It was a bell ringer but so, too, were the satiny creme brulee, the flaky warm apple tart, the impressive peanut butter brownie torte garnished with peanut brittle, the three-layer chocolate mousse cake and the rich hazelnut cappuccino sundae.</p>
        <p>The six wines on the restaurant's temporary list offer solid dependable choices at prices of $16 to $28. Two French 1995 selections, a rich, ripe Louis Jadot Beaujolais Villages ($23) and a crisp, dry Joseph Drouhin Macon Villages ($23), are recommended.</p>
        <p>The Merry Pedlar  339 Jericho Turnpike, Floral Park.  488-8780.</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>Atmosphere Warm, friendly American bistro.</p>
        <p>Service Hit and miss</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes All desserts, veal chop, baron of lamb, steak in mushroom sauce, orange lacquer duck, chicken stir fry, penne with meat sauce, wild mushroom salad, rustic salad, mixed green salad, vegetable soup, French onion soup, seafood-vegetable fritters, caponata terrine, antipasto table.</p>
        <p>Price range Appetizers $3.95 to $6.95; entrees $10.95 to $19.95. Three-course meal $19.97.</p>
        <p>Credit cards All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours 5 to 10 P.M. Wednesday and Thursday, till 11 P.M. Friday and Saturday, 3 to 9 P.M. Sunday. Sunday brunch 11:30 A.M. to 3 P.M.</p>
        <p>Reservations Needed on weekends.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility One step at entrance.</p>
        <p>The Ratings Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
