<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Negotiations Collapse in the Bottom of the Ninth Inning</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="731365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALARY CAPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLECTIVE BARGAINING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DB1738F936A25751C1A962958260" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Negotiations Collapse in the Bottom of the Ninth Inning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>RYE BROOK, N.Y., Dec. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wisp of hope that flickered at the baseball bargaining table early this morning blew out this afternoon in the ill wind that sent the players home and the owners to Chicago for a decision on impasse and implementation of a salary cap on Thursday.</p>
        <p>When negotiators for players and owners left the bargaining table a few minutes after 2 o'clock this morning, thoughts of progress danced in their weary heads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The wisp of hope that flickered at the baseball bargaining table early this morning blew out this afternoon in the ill wind that sent the players home and the owners to Chicago for a decision on impasse and implementation of a salary cap on Thursday.</p>
        <p>When negotiators for players and owners left the bargaining table a few minutes after 2 o'clock this morning, thoughts of progress danced in their weary heads.</p>
        <p>"There has been some real movement," one union official said after the lengthy late-night session. "There seems to be a sincere effort to make some progress."</p>
        <p>Said Jerry McMorris, the owner of the Colorado Rockies: "Last night I had some hopes that perhaps we were on the way to making a deal. But what I was led to believe about the type of proposal that might be forthcoming wasn't."</p>
        <p>The owners' negotiating committee expected a new proposal from the players' bargaining team based on a new flexibility the owners showed on their tax plan. Union officials, who went to today's meeting with suggestions and movement on matters relating to but not centered on the tax problem, were prepared to discuss the issue but had not had time to prepare a proposal on the fifth day of arduous talks at the Arrowwood conference center.</p>
        <p>"We made some suggestions," Donald Fehr, the players' labor leader, said. "The response we got was it's not good enough and they are very sad and they're going to Chicago. I think it's very sad they're going."</p>
        <p>The 28 club owners had been expected to have an easy decision at their meeting, voting to declare an impasse in negotiations and implement the proposal that would make major league baseball the third of the four major professional sports to have a salary cap.</p>
        <p>But the developments of the previous 24 hours could make them take a harder look at the possible implications of impasse and implementation.</p>
        <p>Asked if he would recommend that step, John Harrington of the Boston Red Sox, chairman of the negotiating committee, said, "We will be making a recommendation along that line, but I can't tell you specifically until we get to the meeting."</p>
        <p>Adoption of the impasse/implementation strategy requires a three-fourths vote, or 21 of the 28 clubs. It would seem to be a stretch to find eight clubs that would oppose the move. Peter Angelos of the Baltimore Orioles is the only owner who has been quoted as saying he would vote no.</p>
        <p>If there are other clubs prepared to join him, the most likely candidates would be the Mets, Yankees, Blue Jays and Dodgers. One owner speculated that the Red Sox, Rangers and Cardinals could be possibilities, but there has been no other indication of that likelihood.</p>
        <p>The owners are free to declare an impasse, a legal step in labor negotiations that allows employers to impose new working conditions unilaterally, but the union can challenge the action before the National Labor Relations Board.</p>
        <p>In this instance, the union will accuse the owners of bad-faith bargaining, and if the owners act Thursday, the union could argue that the two sides were in the middle of making potential progress with a new look at the payroll tax each side has proposed.</p>
        <p>That's why the owners could decide to vote to declare an impasse but on a delayed basis, giving their negotiators a couple of extra days to talk to the union about the issue.</p>
        <p>What appeared to be a breakthrough in the stalled talks in the 125-day-old strike occurred at about 1 A.M. today. The players indicated they could reach compromise on several issues, including the elements of the revenue-sharing plan the owners adopted last January and the elimination of salary arbitration for earlier free agency.</p>
        <p>The owners, for the first time, indicated they might have some flexibility on the way they would tax payrolls. Instead of having an escalating tax cumulate from year to year and be levied against a club's entire payroll, they suggested they would consider dropping the cumulative aspect and have the escalating tax levied only on the part of the payroll that exceeded a designated threshold. The players had proposed a flat tax on a club's entire payroll that would have been far less punitive than the owners' proposal.</p>
        <p>When the two sides convened today, the players made their offers on the elements of the revenue-sharing plan, saying they would eliminate the gate-sharing and pay-cable aspects of their revenue-raising proposal, changing the way the recipients of the revenue-sharing would be determined and accepting the clubs' definition of payroll.</p>
        <p>But they had no new tax proposal.</p>
        <p>"We felt there might be a little bridge there," Chuck O'Connor, the chief management lawyer, said, discussing the tax issue. "We had a technical session and felt this might be the way to cross that gap. When they came back today and reaffirmed their position by saying we can't respond to that issue, that bridge isn't there yet."</p>
        <p>O'Connor said the owners had asked the players to come with a proposal "and that's fully what we expected, but they didn't come back with it."</p>
        <p>Stan Kasten, the president of the Atlanta Braves, said he concluded the union was stalling, and O'Connor said that possibility "wouldn't be out of the question."</p>
        <p>Neither said why he thought the players would stall, but presumably it would be to try to force the owners to delay impasse/implementation.</p>
        <p>Fehr, looking at the idea from the opposite direction, scoffed at the suggestion of a stall.</p>
        <p>"Why would we be stalling?" he asked. "We're stalling because we want them to go implement? If you think we're stalling, don't you say, 'You're stalling. Can we have it now? Can we have it later? I thought something's coming. Where is it?' They said we expected an offer and we're going to Chicago."</p>
        <p>Another union person compared the owners' action to the bargaining session Sept. 9, the day after the players made their first tax proposal. Bud Selig, the acting commissioner, flew to New York from Milwaukee to attend his first negotiating session and promptly announced the clubs' rejection of the proposal.</p>
        <p>If the clubs implement the salary cap, they will tender contracts under the new system -- by next Tuesday's deadline -- to the more than 80 percent of their players who are unsigned.</p>
        <p>It is not certain that players will sign contracts on that basis.</p>
        <p>"We will ask players and agents at least initially to give us the opportunity to review what it is that comes out of the meetings tomorrow and have us tell them what we think of it," Fehr said. "We will have to review what they do and let them know what we think it means in the short term. Then they can make their decision."</p>
        <p>The clubs, meanwhile, most likely will make plans to open spring training camps and open next season with replacement players.</p>
        <p>"Major league baseball," Harrington said, "is committed to bringing about baseball on the field in 1995. We're very confident that we will present a game that will be competitive, accessible and affordable to all our fans."</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
