<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ranking Bus Official Resigns Under Pressure</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="731288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY TRANSIT AUTHORITY (NYCTA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EDWARDS, VELVA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIEPPER, ALAN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DF1738F936A25751C1A962958260" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ranking Bus Official Resigns Under Pressure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The top official in charge of New York City's bus service resigned yesterday under pressure from the Transit Authority's president, who said he was dissatisfied with the deteriorating quality of the service.</p>
        <p>The official, Velva Edwards, who was appointed to head the authority's Department of Buses two and half years ago, offered her resignation yesterday afternoon and gathered her staff to announce she was leaving. She did not give a reason and declined to be interviewed by reporters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The top official in charge of New York City's bus service resigned yesterday under pressure from the Transit Authority's president, who said he was dissatisfied with the deteriorating quality of the service.</p>
        <p>The official, Velva Edwards, who was appointed to head the authority's Department of Buses two and half years ago, offered her resignation yesterday afternoon and gathered her staff to announce she was leaving. She did not give a reason and declined to be interviewed by reporters.</p>
        <p>Her resignation comes after months of labor strife at some bus depots as managers have tried to force mechanics to finish jobs in less time. Management has accused the Transport Workers Union of sabotaging buses to increase overtime and of slowing work unnecessarily. The union has accused management of harassing union officials and blaming them for delays that are actually caused by parts shortages and poor management.</p>
        <p>In some parts of the city, especially the Bronx and Manhattan, depot managers have been having increasing trouble getting enough buses in good repair to meet the demands of the morning rush hour.</p>
        <p>More and more buses are breaking down as the city bus fleet has aged, and two bus manufacturers under contract with the Transit Authority -- TMI of Rosedale, N.M., and Bus Industries of America, a Canadian company -- have failed to meet their obligations to provide new buses, transit officials said.</p>
        <p>About 45 percent of the 3,600 buses are more than 12 years old. The average distance the buses go between repairs has declined 6 percent since last year.</p>
        <p>Since early spring, the authority's president, Alan Kiepper, has been pressuring Ms. Edwards to crack down on unproductive mechanics in Manhattan and Bronx bus depots and to improve service.</p>
        <p>"It was a mutually agreed-upon departing," Mr. Kiepper said. "It's clear the Department of Buses is not performing to the level that we want it to."</p>
        <p>Ms. Edwards's resignation follows several other management changes in the department. Eighteen months ago, Mr. Kiepper brought in two well-known managers from the subway division, Charles Monheim and Lars Updale, and gave them orders to improve the quality of work in the depots.</p>
        <p>Since then, the borough managers have been replaced in the Bronx, Queens and Manhattan. New managers have also been brought into several troubled depots.</p>
        <p>Transit officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, said that Mr. Kiepper had not forced Ms. Edwards to resign, but they had reached an agreement last week.</p>
        <p>In those talks, the officials said, Mr. Kiepper said he was generally unhappy with the direction of the bus division. Ms. Edwards, they said, told Mr. Kiepper she did not want to take on the formidable challenge of an all-out battle with the union over work rules. One reason was her family. She recently had a baby and last year went through a tough custody battle over an adopted child, the officials said.</p>
        <p>"At her meeting, she told him that this was too much for her, that she wanted to leave," said a senior transit official, speaking on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiepper said he will place Mr. Monheim in charge of the department until a new manager can be found.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
