<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S., in a Shift, Backs U.N. Move to Curb Illicit Trade in Guns</title>
    <meta content="Y25ARM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Rifle Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonner, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DC133FF936A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S., in a Shift, Backs U.N. Move to Curb Illicit Trade in Guns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND BONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bonner, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA, April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration, in major move against international crime, is co-sponsoring UN resolution aimed at curbing illicit trafficking in firearms; resolution drafted by Britain and Canada is rewritten to appease US gun lobbyists, by clarifying that it does not call for action on possession of handguns or domestic sales; NRA still opposes any UN role in firearms issues (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a major step against international crime, the Clinton Administration is co-sponsoring a United Nations resolution aimed at curbing illicit trafficking in firearms. It is the first time the United States has endorsed a United Nations resolution on firearms regulation, American officials said.</p>
        <p>The action came after a week of intense negotiation here among the delegates to the United Nations Commission on Crime Prevention and Criminal Justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a major step against international crime, the Clinton Administration is co-sponsoring a United Nations resolution aimed at curbing illicit trafficking in firearms. It is the first time the United States has endorsed a United Nations resolution on firearms regulation, American officials said.</p>
        <p>The action came after a week of intense negotiation here among the delegates to the United Nations Commission on Crime Prevention and Criminal Justice.</p>
        <p>Late Thursday, the Clinton Administration agreed to support the resolution, drafted by Canada and Brazil, but only after it had been rewritten to clarify that it does not call for action on possession of handguns or domestic sales of guns. The resolution urges governments to adopt measures, including an international accord, aimed at ''combating illicit trafficking in firearms.''</p>
        <p>The United States also joined Canada in recruiting other sponsors, and by the end of the day 21 countries had agreed, including Russia, Germany, Britain, Japan, Australia and Argentina.</p>
        <p>''The phenomena of transnational crime is causing a ratcheting up of international cooperation against trafficking,'' said Jonathan Winer, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International Narcotics and Law and Anti-Crime Enforcement Affairs and the head of the American delegation.</p>
        <p>The resolution is expected to be approved when it is put before the 40 members of the Commission on Monday, delegates said.</p>
        <p>''This is quite a dramatic change for governments,'' said James Hayes, coordinator for international firearms issues in the Canadian Department of Justice. ''They are now accepting that they must take accountability for guns going out of their countries.''</p>
        <p>''In an era of globalization and easier flow of goods, firearms are going to be treated as different than other commodities,'' said Mr. Hayes. He and a United States Customs agent, James McShane, have promoted United Nations action to curb firearms trafficking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes said the resolution, along with a treaty on firearms regulations adopted last November by the Organization of American States, would make it easier to combat crime. ''There will be more transparency in the movement of firearms,'' he said. ''It will be far easier to trace them.''</p>
        <p>It is largely because of the difficulty of tracing firearms once they have been sold to countries in the European Union that the Clinton Administration decided on Wednesday to suspend the sale of American weapons to British companies.</p>
        <p>Even though the resolution is not as tough as many gun-control advocates would have liked, they were generally pleased.</p>
        <p>''It's the best we could expect,'' said Philip Alpers, a gun policy researcher from New Zealand. ''It is the next stage in a long process that will eventually make it more difficult to move guns across borders.''</p>
        <p>He and representatives of other nongovernmental organizations said the American decision was a defeat for their antagonists, like the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>Though acknowledging that she was ''not happy'' with the outcome, the N.R.A.'s chief lobbyist, Tanya Metaksa, said the group had achieved some victories in the process, like defeating a Japanese proposal that dealt with possession of firearms. The organization is opposed to any United Nations involvement in firearms issues.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that the U.N. should respect the sovereignty of countries, on all issues, and that for them to tread on national policy is bad international policy,'' said Mrs. Metaksa.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Metaksa turned her criticism to the process that produced the resolution. ''There were not open and fair discussions,'' she said. ''These are not open meetings.''</p>
        <p>The N.R.A., however, was an accredited participant at the meetings, which were open to journalists and generally more open than most United Nations deliberations. Between September and January, the United Nations held workshops on firearms regulations in Lubliana, Slovenia; Arusha, Tanzania; Sao Paolo, Brazil, and New Dehli.</p>
        <p>The process alone, even before today, has been salutary, advocates of domestic gun-control laws said.</p>
        <p>''It has encouraged governments to focus on gun laws and adopt tougher ones,'' said Rebecca Peters, an Australian who represented the International Alliance of Women. She said, for example, that after the workshop in New Delhi, in January, Mongolia banned the import of all firearms.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
