<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thousands Celebrate the Life Of a Famed Crocodile Hunter</title>
    <meta content="20Irwin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/20/nyregion/20Irwin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1791496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Irwin, Steve</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DF1131F933A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thousands Celebrate the Life Of a Famed Crocodile Hunter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thousands Celebrate the Life of a Famed Crocodile Hunter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you say about a death-defier who dies? You pledge to celebrate his life. You acknowledge that death cannot be defied. And finally you conclude that zest of a certain magnitude -- enthusiasm for mortal danger, say -- offers its own kind of immortality.</p>
        <p>Such, at least, were the rhetorical strategies on display at the almost unnervingly sunny memorial tribute for Steve Irwin, 44, the renowned crocodile hunter, who was killed on Sept. 4 when a stingray stabbed him in the chest on the Great Barrier Reef.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tribute took place at Australia Zoo, north of Brisbane and was televised live last night in the United States on Animal Planet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What do you say about a death-defier who dies? You pledge to celebrate his life. You acknowledge that death cannot be defied. And finally you conclude that zest of a certain magnitude -- enthusiasm for mortal danger, say -- offers its own kind of immortality.</p>
        <p>Such, at least, were the rhetorical strategies on display at the almost unnervingly sunny memorial tribute for Steve Irwin, 44, the renowned crocodile hunter, who was killed on Sept. 4 when a stingray stabbed him in the chest on the Great Barrier Reef.</p>
        <p>The tribute, which took place at Mr. Irwin's Australia Zoo, north of Brisbane, was televised live last night in the United States on Animal Planet, which kept its broadcast simple, though it did assign a title and logo to the presentation: ''Steve Irwin: He Changed Our World.''</p>
        <p>The program featured the Australian prime minister, John Howard, who praised Mr. Irwin for being a great Australian. Mr. Irwin's international appeal then came through in taped interludes from celebrities like Cameron Diaz, Kelly Ripa, Justin Timberlake, Kevin Costner, Hugh Jackman, Larry King and Russell Crowe. Mr. Crowe remarked on the news coverage of Mr. Irwin's death. ''There are not so many zookeepers who can command that kind of attention, mate,'' he said, addressing Mr. Irwin directly.</p>
        <p>For the cameras, a stadium was packed with more than 5,000 mourners, most of them wearing safari clothes. The ceremony became increasingly festive, with clapping, cheering, whooping and standing ovations. When a camera panned over Mr. Irwin's family -- his wife, Terri, his father, Bob, and his children, Bindi and Bob -- they looked stoic and appreciative. Periodically a pop singer sang of candle-in-the-wind sorrows; this was perhaps the least affecting part of the tribute.</p>
        <p>It is hard to imagine a public figure more deserving of a eulogy that invokes the natural world. Many admirers clearly identified Mr. Irwin as the avatar of a kind of Australian Eden, a place wilder and more exhilarating than any biblical paradise.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Irwin's friend and colleague Wes Mannion, director of the Australia Zoo, described his first glimpse of that zoo as ''a place where reptiles and wildlife reigned supreme, where creatures that were persecuted and hated because of human ignorance and misunderstanding were loved and nurtured.''</p>
        <p>The idea that Mr. Irwin was a champion of dangerous animals who are difficult to love appeared to touch a wide range of people. But the words of Mr. Mannion particularly conveyed the force of Mr. Irwin's devotion to his cause. ''Steve's enthusiasm was instantaneously infectious,'' Mr. Mannion said. ''His love and passion for wildlife was so enveloping that at the time I found it difficult to breathe.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Eve Fesl, the matriarch of the indigenous Gubbi Gubbi tribe who appeared with two shirtless and paint-streaked sons, delivered her eulogy in her tribal language, which she then rendered in English. Something in the recitation of the animal names seemed especially moving, and to the point.</p>
        <p>''At dawn, the magpie sings,'' Dr. Fesl said. ''And by day the black cockatoo wing their way across a sunny sky. The koala, possum, dingo and carpet snake are silent on the land below. A mist covers the mountains. We and our land are crying for you.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
