<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bill to Allow Slot Machines Is Passed in Pennsylvania</title>
    <meta content="05SLOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/05/national/05slots.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1594597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slot Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rendell, Edward G (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slot Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DC163BF936A35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bill to Allow Slot Machines Is Passed in Pennsylvania</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bill to Allow Slot Machines Is Passed in Pennsylvania</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pennsylvania lawmakers enact legislation that authorizes as many as 61,000 slot machines, in most expansive gambling measure to be enacted by any state in several years; passage is major political victory for Gov Edward Rendell, whose efforts to pass legislation last year were rejected; officials estimate that slot machines in 14 locations will pour $1 billion annually into state budget; revenue will be used to reduce property taxes around state and for economic development programs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pennsylvania lawmakers enacted sweeping legislation yesterday that authorizes as many as 61,000 slot machines -- the most in any state east of Nevada -- for horse tracks, resorts and slot parlors across the state, and will generate $1 billion a year, officials say, for reducing taxes.</p>
        <p>The plan is the most expansive gambling measure to be enacted by a state in several years, coming one year after New York and Maine legalized slot machines at race tracks, known as ''racinos.'' The vote is likely to put pressure on the Maryland legislature to enact similar legislation, some analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The legislation authorizes as many as 61,000 slot machines - the most in any state east of Nevada - for horse tracks, resorts and slot parlors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pennsylvania lawmakers enacted sweeping legislation yesterday that authorizes as many as 61,000 slot machines -- the most in any state east of Nevada -- for horse tracks, resorts and slot parlors across the state, and will generate $1 billion a year, officials say, for reducing taxes.</p>
        <p>The plan is the most expansive gambling measure to be enacted by a state in several years, coming one year after New York and Maine legalized slot machines at race tracks, known as ''racinos.'' The vote is likely to put pressure on the Maryland legislature to enact similar legislation, some analysts said.</p>
        <p>Passage of the measure was a major political victory for Gov. Edward G. Rendell, a Democrat who championed property tax relief during his 2002 campaign. The Republican-controlled legislature rebuffed Mr. Rendell's gambling proposal last year, but he cobbled together enough Republican votes to win solid majorities in both houses this time.</p>
        <p>''Tonight the people of Pennsylvania are true winners,'' Mr. Rendell said after the House passed the bill early Sunday morning. The Senate passed it on Friday. ''We are beginning to reverse the tide of unfairly burdening Pennsylvania homeowners.''</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania officials estimate that within three years, slot machines in 14 locations will pour $1 billion a year into the state budget for reducing local property taxes around the state and income taxes in Philadelphia. Some revenue will be used for economic development programs.</p>
        <p>State officials contend homeowners in communities that agree to participate in a new tax-relief program will see their property taxes, which finance public schools, fall by an average of about $330 a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rendell had to overcome stiff opposition from conservatives, religious groups and government watchdog organizations who argued that gambling would increase corruption, crime and social problems like gambling addiction and bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Slot machines now account for about three-quarters of casino revenues nationwide. Critics argue the entrancing machines take advantage of older, less sophisticated and poorer people. But gambling proponents contend that studies show that many slot players are relatively well educated and middle class.</p>
        <p>''Slots are the most addicting'' of all gambling machines, said Representative Paul Clymer, a Republican who had led opposition to the bill. ''We're going to take money from the disadvantaged, the poor and the uneducated. We're preying on human weakness. This is a sad day for Pennsylvania.''</p>
        <p>To win over balky lawmakers, Mr. Rendell and his bipartisan legislative allies included a plan to use some gambling revenues to help finance the kinds of development projects that are important to lawmakers' re-election campaigns, including sports arenas, convention centers and tourism programs.</p>
        <p>The bill's authors had also included a provision that would have allowed legislators to own as much as 5 percent of gambling companies. But when The Philadelphia Inquirer revealed the provision last week, legislative leaders reduced the amount to 1 percent. Still, anti-corruption groups said lawmakers should not be allowed to own any part of a gambling operation.</p>
        <p>Casino companies weighed in with huge lobbying operations, fighting both for and against the measure. Officials and gambling firms in Delaware and West Virginia, which have racinos, as well as in Atlantic City argued that their areas would be hurt by gambling in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City, just an hour from the Philadelphia area, which could get four or more slot sites, may be hardest hit, experts said. With that in mind, several firms, particularly Harrah's Entertainment, have begun acquiring interests in Pennsylvania racetracks and businesses that are eligible for gambling licenses.</p>
        <p>Maryland is considering a plan advocated by Gov. Robert L. Ehrlich Jr., a Republican, to legalize slot machines to help finance education. Democrats blocked the measure earlier this year. But Mr. Ehrlich has sought to use Pennsylvania's moves to pressure the legislature to relent, arguing that state residents already spend $309 million at racinos in Delaware and West Virginia, and will soon spend more in Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>''The question is not whether Marylanders will play slots,'' Mr. Ehrlich said in a recent statement. ''The question is where they will play and who will benefit.''</p>
        <p>But critics of gambling argued that racinos in West Virginia and Delaware were already convenient for Maryland residents. It is unlikely, they said, that there will be a new outflow of Maryland dollars to Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>''Anyone who wants to go play slots is already doing so,'' said Jeff Hooke, chairman of the Maryland Tax Education Foundation, who has been critical of Maryland's and Pennsylvania's gambling plans. ''Why should they drive another 30 to 50 miles?''</p>
        <p>The efforts by Mr. Rendell and Mr. Ehrlich are indicative of a broad trend among state officials in recent years to solve pressing budget problems through measures other than raising sales or income taxes.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger of California struck a deal that granted five American Indian tribes unlimited slot machines and is to bring the state an immediate cash infusion of $1 billion.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly more palatable to push the gambling issue when it is presented as a choice between either raising taxes or expanding gambling,'' said Ian Pulsipher, a policy analyst with the National Conference of State Legislatures. ''You hear a lot of legislators arguing: 'The budget's a mess. What else can we do?'''</p>
        <p>That is precisely how Mr. Rendell argued the issue in Pennsylvania. He initially advocated raising income taxes and legalizing slots to help shift the cost of schools away from property taxes. But when Republicans balked, he dropped the tax proposal.</p>
        <p>''Right now, there is no feasible way to get property tax relief other than gaming,'' Mr. Rendell said last week.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the gambling bill argued that the state would not earn enough revenue from the plan. The state will receive 34 percent of annual gambling revenues and about $600 million in one-time licensing fees. But some experts contended that the state could earn more than $2 billion in fees if it auctioned the licenses.</p>
        <p>The legislation authorizes seven racetracks and five slot parlors to get 3,000 video slot machines each, with the potential to increase to 5,000 machines after six months. Two resorts will be granted 500 machines each.</p>
        <p>Slots are likely to go to racetracks in or near Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Erie, Harrisburg and Wilkes-Barre. A seven-member board appointed by the governor and legislature will license and regulate the gambling operations.</p>
        <p>Under the tax relief plan, school districts can receive state money from gambling provided they institute local income taxes or increase existing taxes. Those districts would have to submit future tax increases above the inflation rate to a referendum, except in certain emergency situations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
