<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group Linked to Al Qaeda Seen Behind Jakarta Blast</title>
    <meta content="Y07INDO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/07/international/asia/07INDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE ATTACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Jemaah Islamiyah</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D61631F934A3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group Linked to Al Qaeda Seen Behind Jakarta Blast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Group Linked to Al Qaeda Seen Behind Jakarta Blast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Aug. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The terror attack at the J. W. Marriott Hotel that killed at least 16 people and wounded 150 on Tuesday was almost certainly the work of Jemaah Islamiyah, a group terror experts have linked closely to Al Qaeda, American officials said today.</p>
        <p>Most of the senior members of Jemaah Islamiyah, including its top operations officer and its most skilled bomb makers, remain at large even though about 50 members of the group have been arrested since the attack on a Bali nightclub 10 months ago, they said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The terror attack at a hotel in Jakarta was almost certainly the work of Jemaah Islamiyah, a group linked closely to Al Qaeda.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The terror attack at the J. W. Marriott Hotel that killed at least 16 people and wounded 150 on Tuesday was almost certainly the work of Jemaah Islamiyah, a group terror experts have linked closely to Al Qaeda, American officials said today.</p>
        <p>Most of the senior members of Jemaah Islamiyah, including its top operations officer and its most skilled bomb makers, remain at large even though about 50 members of the group have been arrested since the attack on a Bali nightclub 10 months ago, they said.</p>
        <p>The blast at the Marriott illustrated what had been known for months, the officials said: that Jemaah Islamiyah, a group intent on achieving an Islamic state in Indonesia and other parts of Southeast Asia, consisted of many independent cells, each with the capacity to mount attacks. Indonesia is the most populous Muslim country, and its sprawling archipelago with 220 million people provides near perfect cover for fugitives.</p>
        <p>The group's operations officer, known as Hambali, is among the ''top echelon'' of Qaeda members wanted by the United States, an American official said. The bomb experts, Dulmatin and Azahari Husin, who the Indonesian authorities have said made the bomb for the Bali explosion, have been the targets of searches by the Indonesian authorities for many months.</p>
        <p>Another bomb expert, Fathur Roman al-Ghozi, was allowed to escape from a Philippine jail last month, according to the Philippine government.</p>
        <p>A defendant in the Bali bombing trials and a suspected member of Jemaah Islamiyah, Amrozi, is to appear in a Bali court on Thursday to hear the verdict in his case. There was some speculation that the Marriott attack was timed as a warning to the government not to impose the death penalty, which Mr. Amrozi could face if convicted.</p>
        <p>Another defendant in the Bali attack, Imam Samudra, told reporters in Bali today that he was ''happy'' about the attack in Jakarta, the Indonesian capital.</p>
        <p>The center of the city returned to a sense of normalcy today as Indonesian officials said they would impose new security measures at major hotels and businesses. But precisely what those measures would be was not immediately clear.</p>
        <p>The choice of the 33-story Marriott, the most visibly American building in the city, left little doubt about the intentions of the terrorists.</p>
        <p>''In 20-20 hindsight, the Marriott was an obvious choice,'' said Ken Conboy, who heads a security company, Risk Management Advisory. ''It had a reputation as an American brand; it flaunted its American connection.''</p>
        <p>Interrogations of Jemaah Islamiyah members who have been arrested showed that they tended to give considerable thought to their choice of targets and the aftereffects, Mr. Conboy said.</p>
        <p>The Marriott, which was often the site of American events, was considered to have some of the best security in the capital. Even so, the trunks and undercarriages of cars were not inspected before they drove up to the front door, and the floor-to-ceiling windows of the coffee shop that bore the brunt of the attack on Tuesday faced the driveway. Guests at a Fourth of July celebration at the Marriott this year had to leave their cars at the foot of the driveway and walk 100 yards to the hotel entrance.</p>
        <p>A Jakarta police spokesman, Prasetyo, said the Indonesian authorities had found information about a planned attack on the Marriott when the police raided a Jemaah Islamiyah hideout in Semarang in central Java last month. Nine suspected members of Jemaah Islamiyah were arrested in Jakarta and Semarang at or around the same time.</p>
        <p>But the United States ambassador, Ralph L. Boyce, dismissed the notion that there was prior knowledge. ''We didn't have any information that the Marriott was targeted,'' he said today.</p>
        <p>Because of mounting information from Indonesian sources of possible new attacks by Jemaah Islamiyah, he said, the United States Embassy has been at a ''very high state of alert'' and warnings had been in place for Americans living in and visiting Indonesia. ''Soft targets'' where foreigners gathered -- hotels and restaurants, for example -- have been of particular concern.</p>
        <p>The Australian foreign minister, Alexander Downer, took the unusual step of predicting a possible terrorist attack in Indonesia ''in the next day or so,'' and on Aug. 17, when Indonesia celebrates its independence. ''That is a day when we think it's possible there could be a terrorist attack in the central Jakarta area,'' he said.</p>
        <p>American officials said they preferred not to be so precise about possible attacks but, instead, to emphasize precaution at all times.</p>
        <p>The methods used in the Bali and Jakarta attacks were similar, the head of the Jakarta criminal investigation department, Erwin Mappaseng said today.</p>
        <p>Both involved a vehicle packed with explosives being driven to the site. The police said today that potassium chloride and TNT, both substances used in the Bali bomb, were found on the Marriott driveway, where an Indonesian brand sport utility vehicle packed with explosives blew up. The bomber appears to have been in the S.U.V., Indonesian officials said. A suicide bomber was involved in the Bali attack.</p>
        <p>A senior Australian official said today he was not surprised by the Marriott blast. ''Everyone has been waiting for another attack,'' he said. ''This is no more and no less than a reminder that Jemaah Islamiyah is still there, has the capability, and will use that capability from time to time.''</p>
        <p>But the Australian warned that the Jakarta attack showed a ratcheting up of Jemaah Islamiyah's tactics. ''Bali was rationalized by the expatriates as being a tourist place, of being Hindu,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Senior Australian officials said that by attacking a Western institution in the heart of the capital, the Islamic group was trying to create fear in the expatriate community. By intimidating foreigners, the militants would drive the struggling economy into deeper trouble, a goal that was consistent with their ideal of wanting to establish a radical Islamic state in a place where most of the population is moderate in its religious beliefs.</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE ATTACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
