<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC Is Said To Be Close To Signing Private Lynch</title>
    <meta content="Y07LYN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/07/national/07LYNC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Lynch, Jessica</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DE1731F934A3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC Is Said To Be Close To Signing Private Lynch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NBC Is Said to Be Close to Signing Private Lynch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER and JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representatives of Pfc. Jessica D. Lynch are close to concluding a deal with NBC for her paid cooperation in the making of its television movie about her experiences as a prisoner of war in Iraq, two executives involved in the proposed deal said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The fee NBC will pay Private Lynch, whose rescue from an Iraqi hospital became one of the most celebrated, then disputed, events of the war in Iraq, is still under discussion, the executives said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representatives of Pfc. Jessica D. Lynch are close to concluding a deal with NBC for her paid cooperation in the making of its television movie about her experiences in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representatives of Pfc. Jessica D. Lynch are close to concluding a deal with NBC for her paid cooperation in the making of its television movie about her experiences as a prisoner of war in Iraq, two executives involved in the proposed deal said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The fee NBC will pay Private Lynch, whose rescue from an Iraqi hospital became one of the most celebrated, then disputed, events of the war in Iraq, is still under discussion, the executives said.</p>
        <p>NBC will begin production on the movie, to be called ''Saving Private Lynch,'' in the next two weeks. Yesterday it named an actress, Laura Regan, to play her in the film.</p>
        <p>The agreement, which could be completed by tomorrow, would mean that NBC's previously unauthorized movie becomes an authorized version, with the emphasis shifting more to Private Lynch's personal story. NBC had said it would emphasize the story of an Iraqi lawyer who helped in her rescue.</p>
        <p>Jeff Zucker, the president of NBC Entertainment, would not confirm a deal was about to be concluded, but said, ''We have been seeking a deal with Jessica for some time and we are hopeful that it will happen.''</p>
        <p>Randy Coleman, a spokesman for the Lynch family, said, ''The family has not agreed at this time to participate in an NBC movie.''</p>
        <p>One executive involved in the movie deal said that Private Lynch's representatives hope to sell a book about her ordeal that can be published quickly enough to coincide with the November broadcast of the television movie. Several people close to the talks said Rick Bragg, the author and former reporter for The New York Times, has been chosen by Private Lynch's representatives to write her authorized story if and when a book deal is struck. Mr. Bragg had already spent time with her and her family, these people said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coleman declined to characterize Mr. Bragg's involvement except to say, ''Rick Bragg has talked with members of the Lynch family.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragg would not comment.</p>
        <p>Knopf, part of the Random House division of Bertelsmann, is considered the most likely publisher of an authorized book. The company already has Mr. Bragg under contract for two other books.</p>
        <p>The book deal has not yet been completed in part because Private Lynch has not yet left the Army on a medical discharge, two executives involved in the deals said. The Department of Defense prohibits personnel to profit from their experiences while in the service.</p>
        <p>As companies have sought book and film deals with Private Lynch, the networks' news divisions have pursued the first interview with her. CBS News was widely criticized for offering to help set up other deals with sibling divisions of its parent company, Viacom. The CBS proposals included a television movie, appearances on MTV and a potential book deal with Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
        <p>Executives at rival news organizations said yesterday that if the movie deal was completed they expected NBC to secure the first interview with Private Lynch, a development they said would suggest the existence of a quid pro quo.</p>
        <p>NBC has made no deal with the Lynch family regarding an interview, Mr. Zucker said. ''No interview is set,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added that he and other NBC entertainment executives would not be involved in steering Ms. Lynch to NBC News. ''The news folks are chasing her on their own,'' Mr. Zucker said.</p>
        <p>Any interviews would be tied to the book's release, the executives in the book deal said. That might give NBC News an advantage because the network's ''Today'' program is considered by publishers a favored location for author interviews.</p>
        <p>Executives from other networks said they believed they might still have a chance for the interview because NBC News might want to avoid accusations it was essentially paying for interviews.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
