<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rumsfeld Defense</title>
    <meta content="13FRIE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/13/opinion/13FRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1308934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Foreign Affairs"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D8143BF930A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rumsfeld Defense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Rumsfeld Defense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says Bush administration came into office with no integrated political-strategic vision, but rather with set of positions--on taxes, missile defense and trade--some of which clearly contradict others; cites several examples where he claims fuzzy math has met fuzzy strategy since George W Bush took office (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fuzzy math, meet fuzzy strategy.</p>
        <p>A month after President Bush's $1.35 trillion tax cut was rushed through Congress, we now hear that the math was indeed, well, a little fuzzy, and that the budget could fall short by some $50 billion, thus increasing the deficit. But the Bush budget isn't the only thing that's fuzzy in Washington these days. The Bush strategic vision doesn't add up either. Not only do many of its policies clash with one another, but the fuzzy math that was used to slash taxes is going to limit some of the truly innovative things Mr. Bush wants to do on the strategic side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fuzzy math, meet fuzzy strategy. The Bush budget isn't the only thing that's fuzzy in Washington these days. The Bush strategic vision doesn't add up either</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fuzzy math, meet fuzzy strategy.</p>
        <p>A month after President Bush's $1.35 trillion tax cut was rushed through Congress, we now hear that the math was indeed, well, a little fuzzy, and that the budget could fall short by some $50 billion, thus increasing the deficit. But the Bush budget isn't the only thing that's fuzzy in Washington these days. The Bush strategic vision doesn't add up either. Not only do many of its policies clash with one another, but the fuzzy math that was used to slash taxes is going to limit some of the truly innovative things Mr. Bush wants to do on the strategic side.</p>
        <p>That's what happens when you have an administration that comes into office with no integrated political-strategic vision, but rather with a set of theological positions -- on taxes, missile defense and trade -- some of which clearly contradict others.</p>
        <p>Grover Norquist, meet Don Rumsfeld.</p>
        <p>Mr. Norquist, the Republican tax-cutting zealot who drove Bush budget policy, will be remembered as the biggest enemy of Defense Secretary Rumsfeld's plans for a ''Revolution in Military Affairs'' and a revamping of America's strategic forces.</p>
        <p>''I voted against the tax cut,'' Senator John McCain, a member of the Armed Services Committee, told me the other day, ''because I felt that it would not protect Medicare, it would not protect Social Security and I didn't feel that there was going to be sufficient money for defense. We've had the Joint Chiefs up here [seeking additional funds] to cover spending shortfalls in just operations, maintenance, readiness and personnel issues -- let alone paying for national missile defense and new programs.''</p>
        <p>That's not the only place where fuzzy math meets fuzzy strategy:</p>
        <p>* President Bush vowed in an address at the Naval Academy to rebuild the U.S. military into a fighting machine ''that relies more heavily on stealth, precision weaponry and information technologies.'' But the $18 billion in additional spending for 2002 that the Pentagon requested barely covers the increased costs of spare parts, pay and better housing for troops -- and it's not even clear that this defense increase can be fitted into the tax-reduced Bush budget without tapping Medicare and Social Security. How they are going to raise the $60 to $100 billion for missile defense is a mystery, especially since Congress is resisting cutting any old programs.</p>
        <p>* Mr. Bush called for expanding NATO all across the frontier with Russia. At the same time he urged Russia's president, Vladimir Putin, to support a U.S. plan at the U.N. for revamping sanctions on Iraq. Yes, Russia has its own cash incentives for protecting Saddam. But it seems never to have occurred to anyone on the Bush team that Mr. Putin might not have any interest in cooperating with us on Iraq while we are expanding NATO up to his doorstep. We may not connect the two issues, but he does.</p>
        <p>* Mr. Bush is a strong, anti-protectionist advocate of free trade, but his first trade act as president was to do something that President Bill Clinton always resisted -- erect a formal trade barrier to protect U.S. steel companies from foreign competition. This was done in part to neutralize opposition to the Bush global free-trade agenda, but since that agenda has not been fully spelled out or decisively pushed, the steel protection act stands out alone.</p>
        <p>* Mr. Rumsfeld's Pentagon said yesterday that it was soon to begin building the Alaska portion of the missile shield, whether the technology works or not. Two weeks ago, in the face of threats by agents of Osama bin Laden, Mr. Rumsfeld hastily withdrew U.S. marines who were exercising in Jordan and also pulled the U.S. Fifth Fleet from its base in the Persian Gulf. Message: We will deploy weapons that don't work against an enemy that doesn't exist, and we will withdraw forces that do work against an enemy that does exist.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the Bush team is still getting its ideas together, said Senator McCain, and clearly, Mr. Rumsfeld is committed to radical changes, ''which is refreshing.'' But for now, Mr. McCain added, ''except for national missile defense, I don't know what the Rumsfeld vision is. We have all these commissions, but so far nothing has come out of the Pentagon that adds up to a blueprint yet. That has paralyzed the process, because if we don't know what we're going to do it is hard to shape a defense policy. Hopefully, soon, we'll have that blueprint.''</p>
        <p>Hopefully, Mr. Rumsfeld will provide it. But I hope he checks first with Grover.</p>
        <p>Foreign Affairs</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
