<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Olympians Learn Lessons In Sacrifice</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="WINTER OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1994)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D81638F934A35751C0A962958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Olympians Learn Lessons In Sacrifice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
      <dateline>ROUEN, France, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first, they cavorted on Utah Beach.</p>
        <p>The young men who, on Monday, will officially be named the United States Olympic hockey team visited the Normandy beaches today. And what had been planned by Coach Tim Taylor as a prod to their patriotism and pride somehow became something more by the end of the day -- for him and his players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At first, they cavorted on Utah Beach.</p>
        <p>The young men who, on Monday, will officially be named the United States Olympic hockey team visited the Normandy beaches today. And what had been planned by Coach Tim Taylor as a prod to their patriotism and pride somehow became something more by the end of the day -- for him and his players.</p>
        <p>This was their final day in France after a three-game exhibition series that ended with a disappointing 4-4 tie with the French in Rouen Saturday night. These same two teams will meet next Sunday in Lillehammer, Norway, when they open their Olympic run. The Mood Changes</p>
        <p>The Americans might have been young men at play anywhere today as they snapped photos of one another and loped along the sands where United States forces came ashore in the D-Day invasion 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>But at the American cemetery overlooking Omaha Beach, where more than 9,000 soldiers are buried, their mood changed.</p>
        <p>"I thought that, even beyond sports, this was a momentous event in history," explained Taylor, when asked his reasons for the trip. "There are 9,000 stories out there, and the players are embarking on one of the most important adventures of their lives, just like those 9,000 were at the time."</p>
        <p>At a team meeting on Saturday, Taylor had asked the players if they wanted to visit the beaches. It is a two-hour ride from their hotel here. They had to practice today. On Monday, their day begins at 6 o'clock for the drive to the airport and the plane to Oslo, where they will register as Olympians. Still, the players voted for the trip, and Taylor rearranged their practice schedule.</p>
        <p>An official from the Lower Normandy tourist bureau said the players were the first American group to visit this year. The six-month-long series of events marking the invasion of June 6, 1944, and its aftermath begins in April.</p>
        <p>"Everyone wanted to see what it was all about," said David Sacco of Medford, Mass., a 23-year-old forward who played for Boston University. "I was looking at those crosses and thinking those guys paid the ultimate sacrifice for freedom."</p>
        <p>A teammate, Jeff Lazaro, is a peppery, fun-loving forward known as Lizard. The 25-year-old from Waltham, Mass., and the Ottawa Senators of the National Hockey League, said of the experience: "It made me feel very proud of being an American. We've all sacrificed this year on the team, giving up family, girlfriends. Some guys are making marriage plans over the phone."</p>
        <p>As Lazaro and his teammates looked at the rows of crosses and the Stars of David, the trainer Ed Maturo, of Hamden, Conn., told them, "These guys were all about your age, and you're playing hockey now and they died defending their country."</p>
        <p>The players are young, bright and curious. They read the inscriptions and they were moved by the sight of a 22-foot bronze statue that faced the graves and is called "The Spirit of American Youth Rising from the Waves." Recognizing the Differences</p>
        <p>The captain, Peter Laviolette, is the team's oldest player at 29. A defenseman, he is a career minor leaguer but has established himself as the Olympians' leader.</p>
        <p>"It made me feel that no matter what we'll do, we'll never be a national hero like these guys were," said Laviolette. "There's a big difference with playing and fighting. We're playing hockey. It's for fun."</p>
        <p>They still were tourists, though, and under the huge German gun that was pointed out to sea at Arromanches, in a British invasion sector, they formed a team picture.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, they made allusions to hockey. Joe Bertagna, the traveling secretary, regarded the huge cannon and had an idea after thinking about how much difficulty the club had in losing to the defensive-minded Swedish team.</p>
        <p>"This is how you run the Swedish trap," said Bertagna.</p>
        <p>Overlooking the beach at Arromanches, where the British forces had constructed an artificial harbor to handle invasion supplies, the players posed at the edge of the cliff for another team picture.</p>
        <p>When Taylor had left the American cemetery, he told the associate coach, John Cunniff, "How does what we're doing compare to their sacrifice?"</p>
        <p>He said on the way back to the hotel: "I believe there was a tie-in between patriotism and sacrifice for those that gave their lives for the country and the world -- and all we're asking is three weeks of sacrifice out of our players. I think we were moved by the whole experience. But look at how insignificant you feel in the bigger picture."</p>
        <p>Then Taylor told the players as they left the bus: "Remember, guys, you're registering tomorrow in Norway. You'll be getting your Olympic stuff. I want you standing tall."  WINTER OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
