<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weighing Death Sentence In State Without That Penalty</title>
    <meta content="Y20DEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/20/national/20DEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1279277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Carey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilbert, Kristen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Northampton</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Massachusetts</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Medical Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D6103DF933A15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weighing Death Sentence In State Without That Penalty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Carey</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, Mass., March 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal jury in Springfield, Mass, weighs whether to impose death penalty on former nurse even though state has not executed anyone for more than 50 years; convicted 33-year-old Kristen Gilbert on three counts of first-degree murder and one of second-degree murder for giving four patients at veterans' hospital lethal injections of powerful stimulant; crimes make Gilbert eligible for prosecution and thus death penalty since they were committed on federal property; no one has ever been sentenced to death from state lacking death penalty since its reinstatement in 1970's; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here in a state that has no death penalty and has not executed anyone for more than a half century, a federal jury today began to consider whether to sentence a former nurse to death.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, the jury convicted the nurse, 33-year-old Kristen Gilbert, on three counts of first-degree murder and one of second-degree murder for giving four patients at a veterans' hospital lethal injections of epinephrine, a powerful stimulant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here in a state that has no death penalty and has not executed anyone for more than a half century, a federal jury today began to consider whether to sentence a former nurse to death.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, the jury convicted the nurse, 33-year-old Kristen Gilbert, on three counts of first-degree murder and one of second-degree murder for giving four patients at a veterans' hospital lethal injections of epinephrine, a powerful stimulant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilbert's crimes made her eligible for federal prosecution, and thus the death penalty, because she committed them on federal property, the Veterans Affairs Medical Center in nearby Northampton.</p>
        <p>No one has ever been sentenced to death from a state that lacks the death penalty since its reinstatement in the 1970's, said David I. Bruck, an expert who assists defense lawyers in federal death penalty cases.</p>
        <p>It is not unusual for federal prosecutors to seek a death sentence in the 12 states without a death penalty, Mr. Bruck said. But the only other time they got to a penalty phase in a case, he said, was in a 1992 trial in New York, when the state lacked the death penalty; it ended in a hung jury and so the defendant was sentenced to life imprisonment.</p>
        <p>In the Massachusetts trial, the prosecution argued that Ms. Gilbert, caught up in a love affair with a hospital security officer in the mid-90's, injected patients with epinephrine to induce emergencies that would let her show off in front of him.</p>
        <p>Today, the penalty phase began, with the two sides arguing whether Ms. Gilbert's crimes crossed the threshold for consideration of a death sentence: that the murders had been intentional and had involved ''aggravating factors.''</p>
        <p>The prosecution argued that the ''aggravating factors'' were that the murders had been particularly cruel because of the victims' suffering as they felt themselves dying, that they had been highly premeditated and that the victims, as patients, had been particularly vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Assistant United States Attorney William M. Welch II called the murders barbaric and morally repugnant, and described some of the victims' suffering. One was burned by defibrillators, he said; the son of another victim testified that his father sat up in bed and cried, ''I don't want to die!''</p>
        <p>Harry Miles, a defense lawyer, implored the jurors, who began deliberating this afternoon, to think carefully before they considered using ''the godlike power to snip the thread of a life before it has run its natural course.'' They needed a far greater degree of certainty to put someone to death than to convict, Mr. Miles said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilbert's lawyers argued in the trial that all the men who died on her watch were extremely ill and died naturally. They portrayed Ms. Gilbert as the victim of hostile colleagues, and emphasized that the evidence in the case was all circumstantial; there were no witnesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miles also argued today that even in the prosecution's view, Ms. Gilbert had never intended to kill, only to create medical emergencies.</p>
        <p>It would be punishment enough, he said, for Ms. Gilbert to lead a life ''where you can't walk out into a field, or see the snow or play with a puppy.''</p>
        <p>That plea won little sympathy from some of the victims' relatives.</p>
        <p>''Given the condition of my son, it's hard to believe that someone could bring themselves to do something like that,'' said Walter Cutting, whose blind, paralyzed and yet perennially cheerful son, Kenneth, was one of Ms. Gilbert's victims.</p>
        <p>But outside, Ms. Gilbert had strong defenders among a half-dozen protesters who have been gathering regularly to campaign against the death penalty.</p>
        <p>If the jury decides that the ''threshold'' has been met, there would be several days of testimony on whether Ms. Gilbert should be executed or given a life sentence.  Defense lawyers have said they may introduce testimony about how an execution would affect Ms. Gilbert's two young sons.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
