<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anlong Veng Journal; Praying to Pol Pot, Seeking Health and Good Luck</title>
    <meta content="Y23CAM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/23/world/23CAMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cambodia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Anlong Veng (Cambodia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Khmer Rouge (Cambodia)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pol Pot</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Cambodia/Angkor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cambodia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Angkor (Cambodia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Thailand</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Khmer Rouge</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DD1530F930A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anlong Veng Journal; Praying to Pol Pot, Seeking Health and Good Luck</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>ANLONG VENG, Cambodia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some residents of area around Anlong Veng, Cambodia, come to pray at site where Pol Pot was cremated in disgrace in 1998; Pol Pot, who headed Khmer Rouge government responsible for over million deaths, has become something of patron saint in region, where he is remembered by many with respect and some with reverence; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only the buzz of cicadas and the croaking of frogs break the silence here in the remote Dangrek Mountains. The damp monsoon air is filled with black butterflies.</p>
        <p>Grinning and chattering about his war wounds like a man who has seen too much death, a villager named Som Neum, wearing only a dirty sarong around his waist, pushed aside reeds and brambles as he led a visitor up a rocky path to a small clearing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only the buzz of cicadas and the croaking of frogs break the silence here in the remote Dangrek Mountains. The damp monsoon air is filled with black butterflies.</p>
        <p>Grinning and chattering about his war wounds like a man who has seen too much death, a villager named Som Neum, wearing only a dirty sarong around his waist, pushed aside reeds and brambles as he led a visitor up a rocky path to a small clearing.</p>
        <p>Here, under a makeshift tin roof, lies the grave of one of the 20th century's worst mass killers, Pol Pot, who died three years ago leaving behind him a country stunned and ruined, where every person is a shattered survivor or the child of one.</p>
        <p>From 1975 to 1979, Pol Pot ruled Cambodia, heading the Khmer Rouge government, which was responsible for more than a million deaths. The country has never recovered.</p>
        <p>At the grave, Mr. Son Neum, 40, bent and with careful fingertips brushed away a scattering of twigs and leaves. Pol Pot was a good man, he said, so he has taken it on himself to tend this all but abandoned plot.</p>
        <p>This is the place where Pol Pot, rejected at the end even by his Khmer Rouge followers, was cremated in disgrace on top of a stack of old tires and debris, the acrid black smoke curling up above the jungle trees.</p>
        <p>There is still a rubble of black cinders among the sand and pebbles under the little roof, and strips of tire treads that survived the flames, as well as a tangle of thin radial wire salvaged from the burned tires.</p>
        <p>Nearby is a wood marker reading, ''Pol Pot's cremation site.'' Nailed beneath the roof is a sign that says, ''Please help maintain this.''</p>
        <p>What is most unsettling to an outsider is not that the grave has been forgotten, but that it has been remembered; people have come here to pay their respects.</p>
        <p>At the head of the grave is a small cluster of their offerings: an empty Angkor beer can, a plastic water bottle, an unopened chocolate wafer bar, five cigarette butts on little skewers, a tin of joss sticks, a spray of wilted flowers.</p>
        <p>Who has prayed here?</p>
        <p>''They come for lottery numbers,'' said Mr. Som Neum, spitting out seeds from a handful of small blue berries. ''They pray to him. They ask his soul to tell them the winning numbers and the numbers come to them in dreams.''</p>
        <p>And these are not necessarily hard-core Khmer Rouge. Like Mr. Som Neum, they include the villagers and soldiers who call these mountains home.</p>
        <p>There are those in the mountain villages nearby who say they have won with the lottery numbers Pol Pot has given them. Others say they pray to him for health and good luck. Some say his spirit can cure disease.</p>
        <p>In death, it seems, Pol Pot has become something of a patron saint of the Dangrek Mountains. Here along the northern border with Thailand, in one of the last strongholds of his Khmer Rouge movement, he is remembered by many with respect and by some with reverence.</p>
        <p>It was here, just a few steps from the cremation site, that Pol Pot lived out his final days under house arrest after his subordinates turned against him. He died on April 18, 1998, at the age of 73, still professing his innocence and complaining about his confinement. His followers said he had died of a heart attack, but many others believe that he was killed by his own men to prevent his capture and a trial that could have implicated them.</p>
        <p>Almost nothing is left of his small hut, which he shared with his wife and 14-year-old daughter, apart from a broken porcelain toilet bowl and some empty bottles of medicine and cooking spices. One bottle is marked ''ultracarbon tablets.'' There is a flattened tube of toothpaste.</p>
        <p>In the bushes nearby lie a half of a rubber sandal and several scraps of clothing, not unlike the scraps that can be found among the still unburied bones of the Khmer Rouge killing fields.</p>
        <p>It was an anticlimactic end for a man who had destroyed his country.</p>
        <p>During the years he ruled Cambodia, as many as one-fifth of its population died from torture, execution, untreated illness and the exhaustion of slave labor.</p>
        <p>With a mad vision of a Communist agrarian utopia, he emptied the country's cities and massacred its educated people, abolishing commerce, religion, the arts and family life. Then, for some 18 years after his government was ousted by a Vietnamese invasion, he led a Khmer Rouge guerrilla movement that continued to ravage Cambodia until the insurgency collapsed within months after his death.</p>
        <p>His name has become a code word for horror in Cambodia: ''the Pol Pot time.'' And yet many Cambodians, their history buried in silence and denial, say they do not know whether to blame him for what happened. Even at the time, few understood what was happening or why, only that they were sick, starving, exhausted and in fear for their lives.</p>
        <p>Because of continuing political turmoil in Cambodia, there has never been a full accounting or a trial to clarify the historical record. And so the Cambodian people are free to reinvent their past in an attempt to ease the pain.</p>
        <p>As he led his visitor up the trail to the grave, Mr. Som Neum came upon a friend, Chhoeng Sophal, 34, who emerged from a pond where he had been hunting for frogs to eat.</p>
        <p>''Pol Pot's pond,'' Mr. Chhoeng Sophal said. ''He always liked to dig ponds like this for bathing and swimming. He dug ponds all around here. I only saw him from a distance. He was very handsome.''</p>
        <p>The two friends are true children of Pol Pot. Until peace came to Cambodia three years ago, they knew nothing but fighting and privation. Recruited successively by the various armies that passed through the jungles -- including the Khmer Rouge -- they were at times enemies, at times allies. On occasion, they said, they shot at each other.</p>
        <p>''It didn't matter to me who won,'' Mr. Som Neum said. ''If they ordered me to fight, I fought. I wasn't trying to make anybody win.''</p>
        <p>Then he stood ramrod straight and pointed to his wounds: forehead, B-40 rocket, 1983; right temple, shrapnel, 1985; right leg, shrapnel, 1988; right forearm, B-40 rocket, mid-1980's.</p>
        <p>But he does not blame Pol Pot for his harsh life. ''He was a great leader, but the people under him were very bad,'' Mr. Som Neum said. ''I had no problem with him. I liked Pol Pot. I liked everybody.''</p>
        <p>In these dangerous mountains, that may have been a formula for survival.</p>
        <p>At the bottom of the trail that leads to the grave is a border patrol outpost where the deputy commander, Hak Sokhon, rocks in a hammock with his baby son. He was never a member of the Khmer Rouge, he said, but in the three years he has been posted here, he has joined the villagers in their beliefs.</p>
        <p>''I used to be against Pol Pot,'' he said. ''Now I think of him as a hero and a patriot who defended the nation. This was his territory, so I pray to him for protection. Sometimes I see him in my dreams.''</p>
        <p>Sak Chheun, 42, who lives nearby, said she had never dreamed about Pol Pot. But she said she had had personal experience of his miracle-working.</p>
        <p>''I had malaria, with fever and shivering,'' she said. ''We bought incense, a candle and some bananas and prayed to him. After praying I felt better and better. After a few days I prayed again and I recovered -- not 100 percent, but better. Then I prayed to him in thanks.''</p>
        <p>One man who knew Pol Pot in his final days is Khun Ly, 50, a former member of the Khmer Rouge who was assigned to assist him during his house arrest. He said he had run errands and gone shopping for supplies.</p>
        <p>''My children liked him,'' Mr. Khun Ly recalled. ''He gave them candy and advised them to work hard and be polite.''</p>
        <p>Visiting the remains of the hut where Pol Pot died, he muttered to himself as he rummaged through the nearby bushes, pulling out the bits of clothing, then tossing them back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khun Ly said that at Pol Pot's cremation he had been one of the few mourners, a small circle of men who stood in the clearing and watched as Khmer Rouge soldiers tossed gasoline and branches onto the pyre.</p>
        <p>As the orange flames rose and the tires and the kindling burned away, Pol Pot's blackened skeleton could be seen for a moment, its right arm and fist raised upward.</p>
        <p>Even though Pol Pot is dead, Mr. Khun Ly says he still feels a bond with him. ''Once, about two or three months after he died, he came to me in a dream,'' Mr. Khun Ly said. ''He was wearing a long-sleeved shirt. He smiled at me and said, 'Bye-bye,' and then he disappeared.''</p>
        <p>When he awoke, Mr. Khun Ly said, he felt calm and refreshed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
