<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Plan Would Move Meat and Poultry Inspections to F.D.A.</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POULTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANITATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AGRICULTURE DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE1139F930A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Plan Would Move Meat and Poultry Inspections to F.D.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the recommendations announced by the Clinton Administration to streamline Government is one that would have serious health consequences for anyone who roasts a chicken, boils an egg or grills a hamburger.</p>
        <p>In the wake of several recent incidents of deadly bacterial poisoning from commercial meats, the Administration wants to move the inspection of meat, poultry and eggs from the Department of Agriculture to the Food and Drug Administration, where all other food is regulated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the recommendations announced by the Clinton Administration to streamline Government is one that would have serious health consequences for anyone who roasts a chicken, boils an egg or grills a hamburger.</p>
        <p>In the wake of several recent incidents of deadly bacterial poisoning from commercial meats, the Administration wants to move the inspection of meat, poultry and eggs from the Department of Agriculture to the Food and Drug Administration, where all other food is regulated.</p>
        <p>The move has been hailed by many food-safety experts, who say the Agriculture Department has the dual and sometimes conflicting roles of promoting the meat and poultry industries while guarding public safety. The industries, which see the Agriculture Department as their advocate, have vowed to fight the plan.</p>
        <p>Agriculture Secretary Mike Espy said that while he disagreed with the move, as "part of the team" he would not oppose it. But two top Congressional leaders on agricultural issues are said to oppose the idea. Series of Food-Poisoning Scares</p>
        <p>Even those who support the move acknowledge that giving the task to the F.D.A. is, in a sense, the gnat swallowing the elephant: Under the current system the Agriculture Department's Food Safety and Inspection Service's 9,000 employees inspect 6,100 meat and poultry processors a year, while the Food and Drug Administration's staff of 1,000 is responsible for 53,000 nonmeat food producers, as well as drugs and medical devices.</p>
        <p>But supporters of the consolidation say meat and poultry inspections, currently budgeted at $600 million, could be simultaneously streamlined and made more effective under the F.D.A.</p>
        <p>A recent series of food-related scares have increased public concern over the safety of meat and poultry. Contaminated hamburgers from a fast-food chain in the Northwest were believed responsible for the deaths of three children and for making hundreds of others sick earlier this year.</p>
        <p>In addition, a significant number of other animal products -- including eggs, pre-cooked hot dogs and up to 60 percent of poultry -- are known to be contaminated with disease-causing bacteria.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem with the Agriculture Department's inspection program is that it operates the same way it did 50 years ago, when most unhealthy meat could be spotted by the naked eye: inspectors look for signs of disease as carcasses speed down production lines. But most of today's safety hazards can be detected only by a trained scientist looking through a microscope.</p>
        <p>Two former Agriculture Department officials argue that the agency lacks the scientific skills and commitment to assure the safety of meat and poultry. 'No Public Health Capacity'</p>
        <p>Carol Tucker Foreman, an Assistant Secretary of Agriculture in the Carter Administration, says that a public health agency like the F.D.A. would put consumers first, while the Agriculture Department "has no public health capacity at all."</p>
        <p>"For the last dozen years, the Secretary of Agriculture and the assistant secretaries have put producers above public health," said Ms. Foreman, now a consultant in Washington.</p>
        <p>Lester Crawford, former head of the Food Safety and Inspection Service and former director of the F.D.A.'s Bureau of Veterinary Medicine, agreed that the F.D.A., part of the Department of Health and Human Services, was more qualified to inspect food.</p>
        <p>"The F.D.A. commissioners are all M.D.'s or Ph.D.'s," said Dr. Crawford, now the executive director of the Association of American Veterinary Medical Colleges. Unlike the Agriculture Department, he said, "they are used to dealing with scientific and technical matters, to dealing with public health issues."</p>
        <p>Burton Eller, president of the National Cattlemen's Association, acknowledged serious deficiencies in the inspection service but said that he and a large majority in the industry strongly opposed removing inspection from the Agriculture Department.</p>
        <p>"The F.D.A. is not in the safe-food and safe-health inspection business," he said, "It would take us five years to change the meat inspection system, and we don't have five years." Allies in Congress</p>
        <p>The American Meat Institute and the National Broiler Council have also vowed to fight the move, and the industry has powerful allies in Congress.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Senator Patrick J. Leahy of Vermont, chairman of the Senate Agriculture Committee, said Mr. Leahy planned to hold a hearing and "would have to be convinced." A spokesman for Representative Charles W. Stenholm of Texas, chairman of the subcommittee on Agriculture Department operations and nutrition, would say only that Mr. Stenholm was inclined to let meat inspection "remain where it is."</p>
        <p>Even so, Ms. Foreman, the former Agriculture official, gave the proposal "a slightly better than even chance."</p>
        <p>"Every month brings a report of food-borne illness, horrible violations of the law, an aging population more susceptible to food poisoning," she said. "Bacteria kills 9,000 people a year and makes 6.5 million sick."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
