<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rypien Goes Out; Redskins Go Under</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHOENIX CARDINALS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON REDSKINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDD173CF930A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rypien Goes Out; Redskins Go Under</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What's the worst thing that could happen here in the nation's capital?</p>
        <p>The Administration's losing an election? One tax increase on top of another? A beverage shortage at Georgetown watering holes?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What's the worst thing that could happen here in the nation's capital?</p>
        <p>The Administration's losing an election? One tax increase on top of another? A beverage shortage at Georgetown watering holes?</p>
        <p>How about something worse, like the city's beloved Redskins being outplayed and outsmarted by a 10-point underdog?</p>
        <p>Yes, the same Redskins who punished the Dallas Cowboys last Monday night managed to lose, 17-10, today to the Phoenix Cardinals, a team that had played badly in its opener and had been defeated here every year for the last 14 years.</p>
        <p>Adding injury to insult, the Redskins lost their quarterback, Mark Rypien, early in the second quarter when he was tackled on a scramble by defensive tackle Eric Swann. Set for Tests</p>
        <p>Rypien suffered a sprained medial collateral ligament in the right knee, and he watched the second half in street clothes, a brace protecting the knee and crutches to keep his 234 pounds off the knee.</p>
        <p>Rypien will undergo a magnetic resonance imaging test on the knee on Monday. Coach Richie Petitbon said the best scenario was that Rypien would be ready for the Miami Dolphins three weeks from today and the worst was that he would be gone for the season. Dr. Charles Jackson, the Redskins' orthopedic surgeon, said all early signs were positive.</p>
        <p>"We just didn't play well and we lost our quarterback," Petitbon said. "That's a bad combination."</p>
        <p>Coach Joe Bugel of the Cardinals, a longtime Redskins' assistant, seemed fulfilled by today's results. His team, picked by many to finish last in the National Conference Eastern Division, confused and overran the Redskins in taking a 17-0 halftime lead and held on in the second half. Then two of his happy players doused him with water. Bugel thought it was funny.</p>
        <p>"Probably everybody outside our room last night didn't believe we could win," he said. "But we played great." They've Come Undone</p>
        <p>If anyone became unglued, it was the Redskins. When their first possession of the game was stopped, newcomer Reggie Roby outpunted the coverage with a low 54-yarder, and Johnny Bailey of the Cardinals returned it 58 yards for a touchdown. Seven minutes later, Greg Davis kicked a 53-yard field goal, the longest in the Cardinals' history. Twelve minutes later, Ron Moore ran 18 yards for a touchdown.</p>
        <p>And the Cardinals' halftime lead could have been higher. On the team's first possession of the game, Garrison Hearst -- who ran for 76 yards on the day -- carried the ball three times from the Redskins' 2-yard line and could not score. Late in the half, Steve Beuerlein was intercepted on the Redskins' 7-yard line.</p>
        <p>"They jumped out on us early and got us on our heels," said Carl Banks, the Redskins' new outside linebacker. "We spent the first half trying to stop the bleeding. Hearst gave us a lot of trouble with his cutbacks. The linebackers and ends would make adjustments to stop him, and then he would run into another hole and they would have to make adjustments there."</p>
        <p>In the second half, to the screams of the crowd of 53,525 at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium, the Redskins rebounded. The untested Conklin threw a 9-yard touchdown pass to a wide-open Ricky Sanders and Chip Lohmiller kicked a 23-yard field goal to make it 17-10. But after a Cardinals' field goal was wiped out by a holding penalty, the Redskins could not move past their 26. And they probably would not have fared better with Rypien in there. No Cheap Shots</p>
        <p>Rypien was hurt when Swann made a necktie tackle and rolled over on the quarterback's knee.</p>
        <p>"I didn't think there was anything cheap at all about it," Rypien said.</p>
        <p>Swann said the same.</p>
        <p>"I took the pressure of the blow," said the 295-pound Swann. "I just tackled him. It was clean. He didn't say anything. I didn't even know he was hurt."</p>
        <p>But Rypien's knee and the Redskins' egos were hurt, and the Cardinals' egos were magnified by a road victory over one of the National Football League's quality teams.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Three key Cardinals who played badly last Sunday had big games here. In addition to GARRISON HEARST, who got his 76 yards on 22 carries, quarterback STEVE BEUERLEIN completed 17 of 26 passes for 164 yards and wide receiver GARY CLARK, a former Redskin, caught 6 passes for 93 yards. . . . REGGIE ROBY's five punts for the Redskins sailed 54, 55, 51, 45 and 52 yards. . . . KEN HARVEY, the Cardinals' quick outside linebacker, sacked CARY CONKLIN three times.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
