<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Delay of Months, Shuttle Is Off to Good Start</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVANCED COMMUNICATIONS TECHNOLOGY SATELLITE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMUNICATIONS SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCOVERY (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD123BF930A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Delay of Months, Shuttle Is Off to Good Start</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Sept. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ending a string of bad luck, the space shuttle Discovery and five astronauts shot into space today on a 10-day mission that features a space walk and the deployment of two satellites, including one built by NASA for $600 million to test advanced types of communications.</p>
        <p>Tinged with gold by the rising sun, the winged spaceship lifted off on time at 7:45 A.M. to cheers and rounds of applause, thundering into space on a thick column of smoke and flame. The virtually flawless countdown today came after two months of launching delays and after the failures of a weather satellite that cost $67 million and a Mars probe that cost nearly $1 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ending a string of bad luck, the space shuttle Discovery and five astronauts shot into space today on a 10-day mission that features a space walk and the deployment of two satellites, including one built by NASA for $600 million to test advanced types of communications.</p>
        <p>Tinged with gold by the rising sun, the winged spaceship lifted off on time at 7:45 A.M. to cheers and rounds of applause, thundering into space on a thick column of smoke and flame. The virtually flawless countdown today came after two months of launching delays and after the failures of a weather satellite that cost $67 million and a Mars probe that cost nearly $1 billion.</p>
        <p>"As this business goes, there's ups and downs," Robert B. Sieck, launching director at the Kennedy Space Center, told reporters shortly after the liftoff. "But the team at this point is, what I call, riding on a high. We're looking forward to a safe and successful mission."</p>
        <p>This is the 57th flight of a shuttle, the 32d since the Challenger explosion in 1986 and the 17th flight of this shuttle.</p>
        <p>Although the mission was delayed five times, twice by management decisions and three times by equipment failures, the postponements set no record. A mission in 1990 was delayed more than six months.</p>
        <p>After a minor communications problem delayed the satellite launching for one orbit, the astronauts nudged the space agency's Advanced Communications Technology Satellite into orbit at 5:13 P.M. An attached rocket engine began boosting the $600 million craft from Discovery's 184-mile-high altitude to a 22,300-mile-high orbit. Once there, the satellite, which has been under development since the late 1970's, will unfurl to its full 47-foot length.</p>
        <p>The satellite, by perfecting advanced methods of transmitting information, is meant to help the American satellite industry maintain its competitive edge.</p>
        <p>Officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration say the craft will pave the way for a new generation of communication satellites that are faster, stronger and cheaper in relaying data. But industry giants like Hughes, the Loral Corporation and TRW, which collectively dominate the world market in communications satellites, have all ignored the ACTS project, saying its gadgetry is either irrelevant to their needs or far too late to be of any use. Those who have signed up to test the spacecraft and its features are academic and governmental experts as well as companies on the fringes of the satellite industry.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the astronauts are to place in space a second satellite, an $80 million reusable craft made by Germany. It has an ultraviolet telescope and a spectrograph to study interstellar gas, and the space agency plans to send it back into space but has not yet determined how many flights it will make. The craft, on its first mission, is to be retrieved by the astronauts six days later for the trip home.</p>
        <p>By having the craft measure ultraviolet radiation emitted from extremely hot stars and dense clouds of gas between stars, astronomers hope to learn more about processes like star formation. Such observations can be made only above Earth's obscuring atmosphere.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, two astronauts are to make a space walk to try out tools to repair the $1.5 billion Hubble Space Telescope, whose main light-gathering mirror is flawed. It is the last practice session before the formidable repair job itself, which is scheduled for December. A record five and possibly seven space walks are planned for that mission.</p>
        <p>After 10 days in space, early on the morning of Wednesday, Sept. 22, Discovery and its crew are to land at the Kennedy Space Center in Florida in the first night landing there.</p>
        <p>Discovery's commander is Capt. Frank L. Culbertson Jr. of the Navy, 44, who is making his second space flight. The pilot is William F. Readdy, 41, a civilian, also making his second voyage. The other crew members are space rookies: Dr. James H. Newman, 36, a physicist, Comdr. Daniel W. Bursch, 36, of the Navy, and Maj. Carl E. Walz, 38, of the Air Force.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
