<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Plunge in a Selling Surge, Swamping Rally</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950721T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="776292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARD &amp; POOR'S STOCK INDEX</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D6163FF933A15754C0A963958260" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Plunge in a Selling Surge, Swamping Rally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Riding one of the most powerful rallies in their history, the stock and bond markets stumbled badly yesterday in one of the busiest trading days ever, raising the specter in some quarters of what Wall Street calls a correction -- a sharp retreat in stock and bond prices.</p>
        <p>But because the Dow Jones industrial average made up more than half its losses in the last 90 minutes of trading, it was not clear which way investors would jump this morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Riding one of the most powerful rallies in their history, the stock and bond markets stumbled badly yesterday in one of the busiest trading days ever, raising the specter in some quarters of what Wall Street calls a correction -- a sharp retreat in stock and bond prices.</p>
        <p>But because the Dow Jones industrial average made up more than half its losses in the last 90 minutes of trading, it was not clear which way investors would jump this morning.</p>
        <p>Until Tuesday, when the stock market also declined, share prices had been vaulting upward on the expectation of higher earnings and lower interest rates. But the profits reported by two leading companies, Microsoft and Intel, and the cautionary notes subsequently sounded by their executives, cast doubt on how robustly growth would continue -- and created a broad shift out of technology stocks.</p>
        <p>And that trend turned into a stampede of sell orders across much of the market after Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve, gave Congress an optimistic assessment of the nation's economy. His remarks were widely interpreted to mean that no additional interest rate cuts were likely any time soon -- and the markets' fall accelerated.</p>
        <p>Bond prices fell sharply; the 30-year Treasury bond dropped 19/32 , to 10921/32 , while its yield -- which moves in the opposite direction from its price -- surged to 6.86 percent, from 6.76 percent on Tuesday. The long-bond yield is at its highest since May 23.</p>
        <p>And as bonds slumped, so did stocks. About 2 P.M., the Dow Jones industrial average was down as much as 132 points, or nearly 2.9 percent, before recovering more than half that ground to close down 57.41 points at 4,628.87.</p>
        <p>But the fall of the Dow, where technology has relatively little weight, was modest compared with the Nasdaq composite index, which is rich in technology stocks. The index, tracking more than 5,700 stocks, dropped more than 51 points before settling at 949.76, down 38.77 points -- 3.92 percent, or triple the Dow's drop of 1.23 percent.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 7.48 points, to 550.98, for a 1.34 percent decline.</p>
        <p>On all exchanges, volume was extremely high. On the New York Stock Exchange, more than 483.4 million shares changed hands, third behind the 604 million shares traded on Oct. 19, 1987, and 608 million shares on the following day.</p>
        <p>More than 573 million shares were traded on the Nasdaq, straining the capacity of the exchange's computer network, which is in the process of being expanded. Early in the day, Nasdaq put trading curbs on its system, known as Select Net. The current system was designed to handle 450 million shares a day.</p>
        <p>Nasdaq volume may have been held down by brokerage firms that refused to take investors' calls. James Spellman, a Nasdaq spokesman, said Nasdaq examiners had asked a handful of market-makers -- firms that are required to buy and sell shares in select companies -- whether they were declining calls and were assured by the firms that "steps were being taken" so phone calls could get through from the public.</p>
        <p>A growing number of analysts have described the stock market as rising too far too fast in recent weeks, and one of them, Gregory Nie, senior vice president for technical research at Kemper Securities Inc., predicted that this morning the Dow Jones industrial average would begin a 300-point decline over the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Drew Peck, an analyst with Cowen &amp; Comany in Boston, said that while the semiconductor stocks might bounce back in the next couple of days, more rough times could be ahead. "I still think there is a less dramatic but more protracted correction coming before the summer is over," he said.</p>
        <p>Combined with Tuesday's fall in blue-chip stock prices, the stock market's most closely watched index has fallen more than 107 points, the worst two-day fall since the Dow dropped more than 94 points on May 17 and 18 and approaching the 137-point drop on Nov. 21 and 22, 1994.</p>
        <p>Of course, no one knows for certain whether the next few weeks will bring on the much anticipated correction. But large holders of stocks certainly felt the drop. William H. Gates, Microsoft's chairman and its largest individual stockholder, saw his 142.66 million shares fall in value from $15.5 billion on Monday to $13.5 billion yesterday, a loss of $2 billion, at least on paper.</p>
        <p>The late-afternoon recovery in the Dow, which tracks only 30 blue-chip stocks, masked the sudden and violent drop in a broad variety of stocks, especially in technology stocks, which have led the market this year by a wide margin.</p>
        <p>"This market has been living on momentum alone," said Michael Metz, chief investment strategist for Oppenheimer &amp; Company. "Today it hit a brick wall and the brick wall was made up of a weak bond market and doubts about earnings growth in the third quarter."</p>
        <p>Moreover, with more than 6,000 mutual funds and only 8,000 stocks listed on the New York and Nasdaq stock exchanges, portfolio managers have been finding it harder and harder to beat the market. "These big fund managers behave more like traders, getting in and out of stocks quickly, so you see more big swings in the market," said Mr. Nie of Kemper.</p>
        <p>Of the top 100 Nasdaq stocks, by far the bulk of the exchange's market capitalization, all of the top 10 declining issues were technology stocks, led by Intel, which dropped 8 points, to 65 1/4. Intel was also the most active stock on any exchange, with at 55.9 million shares changing hands.</p>
        <p>On the Big Board, 2,142 stocks declined, compared with only 344 that advanced -- one of the greatest gaps between gaining and declining stocks on record. Only 530 Big Board stocks closed unchanged.</p>
        <p>The trading day started ominously.</p>
        <p>After the market closed Tuesday, Intel reported second-quarter earnings of 99 cents a share, below the $1.02 a share expected by Wall Street. On Monday, also after the market closed, Microsoft had reported record earnings but indicated to analysts that some of their higher estimates for 1996 earnings were too high.</p>
        <p>In the first 45 minutes of trading yesterday, the Nasdaq composite index dropped more than 10 points. In the first 20 minutes of trading, the Dow dropped 30 points.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the bond market began falling around 10:30 a.m., weighed down in part by several factors, including a bumper crop of $15 billion in new corporate debt.</p>
        <p>But bonds began to fall in earnest around noon as Mr. Greenspan seemed to send out mixed signals in his testimony to Congress about the economy. He seemed to say that inflation was slowing, which would normally cheer the bond markets, but dropped no obvious hint that the Fed was ready to cut interest rates a second time after its cut on July 6.</p>
        <p>"When we saw the details of his testimony," said Barry Kirschner, senior bond trader at Chase Securities Inc., "they seemed less favorable to bonds than the initial headlines on the wire services might indicate."</p>
        <p>The weakening bond market began to seize the attention of stock traders yesterday afternoon, since rising bond yields tend to siphon cash to bonds that might have gone to stocks.</p>
        <p>"Because of the Fed and the bond market, what was a 50-point decline in the Dow by 1 o'clock was a 130-point decline by 2 o'clock," said Edward Laux, senior managing director for equity trading at the Chicago Corporation.</p>
        <p>At 12:58 P.M., the Dow fell 50 points, triggering the New York Stock Exchange's "circuit breaker" rules designed to slow high-speed computer-guided trading and calm a volatile market. In a down market, a stock may only be sold when its price is unchanged or rising slightly.</p>
        <p>But investors came back in buying the suddenly cheaper stocks and helped pull up the Dow and the S.&amp; P. 500, which are components of many computer-guided trading programs.</p>
        <p>"If the past is any guide, there'll be some more bargain hunting" today, said Mr. Nie of Kemper. "What is more likely is that the Dow will retrace anywhere from a third to half of its advance. Since the Dow rose 1,000 points since November, I see a drop of maybe 300 points over a few weeks."</p>
        <p>The key, he said, would be high trading volume. "If we see another trading day above 400 million shares, prices will come down," Mr. Nie said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 21, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>Two articles in Business Day yesterday about the stock market's selloff, and several related charts, misstated Wednesday's closing figure for the Nasdaq composite index. It was 952.83, down 35.70 points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 21, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>Two articles in Business Day yesterday about the stock market's selloff, and several related charts, misstated Wednesday's closing figure for the Nasdaq composite index. It was 952.83, down 35.70 points.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
