<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspend Shanahan, Nordiques Urge</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="316965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">QUEBEC NORDIQUES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D6133EF936A25752C0A966958260" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspend Shanahan, Nordiques Urge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Brendan Shanahan, an integral part of the Devils' top line, faces a suspension from the league for a high-sticking major penalty he drew in Saturday night's 5-4 triumph over the Nordiques in Quebec City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Brendan Shanahan, an integral part of the Devils' top line, faces a suspension from the league for a high-sticking major penalty he drew in Saturday night's 5-4 triumph over the Nordiques in Quebec City.</p>
        <p>Brendan Shanahan, an integral part of the Devils' top line, faces a suspension from the league for a high-sticking major penalty he drew in Saturday night's 5-4 triumph over the Nordiques in Quebec City.</p>
        <p>Coach Michel Bergeron of the Nordiques said yesterday that a videotape of the incident would be sent to the league's headquarters in Montreal today and Quebec would request that Shanahan be suspended.</p>
        <p>The videotape clearly shows Shanahan hitting Michel Petit of the Nordiques in the face with his stick with 3 minutes 55 seconds left in the game. What the tape does not show clearly is Petit's stick hitting Shahanan in the mouth just seconds earlier and causing an injury that later required 11 stitches.</p>
        <p>While Shanahan flew back to New Jersey on the team's charter flight after the game, Petit was kept overnight in a Quebec hospital for observation. Nicole Bouchard, a spokesman for the Nordiques, said by telephone yesterday that Petit had a concussion and a cut in his mouth.</p>
        <p>Bergeron Aggravated</p>
        <p>Shanahan and Petit were both assessed high-sticking major penalties and automatic game misconducts in the incident, which occurred near Quebec's blue line. Shanahan also drew an additional five minutes for fighting with Steven Finn.</p>
        <p>The sellout crowd at the Colisee threw debris onto the ice when the referee, Denis Morel, penalized Petit with the high-sticking major and the automatic game misconduct as the bleeding and dazed Petit was helped off the ice.</p>
        <p>Bergeron was more aggravated than the crowd because, he said, the penalties to Petit were not called until two minutes after the penalities were handed out. He also said he believed that Shanahan should be suspended.</p>
        <p>''The referee made a bad decision,'' Bergeron said. ''He didn't call the penalty to Petit until at least two minutes later.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan's 3d Game Misconduct</p>
        <p>Shanahan said of the incident with Petit: ''I was forechecking and he put his head down. I really don't remember most of it because my mouth was full of blood.''</p>
        <p>For the 20-year-old Shanahan, the game misconduct was his third of the season, but the first stick-related. His other misconducts were both for fighting. Since his latest game misconduct was for a stick-swinging incident and not fighting, he will not be subject to the automatic one-game suspension given for accumulating three game misconducts for fighting.</p>
        <p>Shanahan, who has 44 points from 18 goals and 26 assists, was not involved in any of the scoring against the Nordiques.</p>
        <p>John MacLean, who plays on the right side of Shanahan's line, was assisted on the game-winning goal by Patrik Sundstrom, the center. The line, which has been together from the beginning of the season, has produced 155 points. #500th Point for Johnson The goal by MacLean was his ninth game-winner, the most in the league, and his 25th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Sylvain Turgeon, Vyacheslav Fetisov, Kirk Muller and Janne Ojanen had the other goals in that order before MacLean's winner gave the Devils (22-20-4) their fourth victory in the last six.</p>
        <p>Mark Johnson earned his 500th point in the league with his assist on Turgeon's 24th goal of the season. Aleksei Kasatonov also had an assist on Turgeon's goal for his second point of the season and played another strong game.</p>
        <p>The best player for the Devils, however, was Fetisov, the other Soviet defenseman, who also had an assist on Ojanen's goal besides scoring his second goal in three games.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
