<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sealing Nuclear Waste, Ending an Atomic Dream</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="863400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST VALLEY (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NUCLEAR FUEL SERVICES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROCKEFELLER, NELSON ALDRICH (1908-79)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DC1139F93AA35754C0A960958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sealing Nuclear Waste, Ending an Atomic Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WEST VALLEY, N.Y., July 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using giant mechanical arms controlled from behind 4-foot-thick steel and concrete walls, technicians welded shut a five-ton canister of intensely radioactive waste from a rusting steel tank here today. In so doing, the Federal Government began to back out of one of the greatest dead ends in American industrial history.</p>
        <p>The waste was left by a private company, Nuclear Fuel Services, which was encouraged to come here, to the rolling hills amid the dairy farms 35 miles south of Buffalo, by Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller, who wanted western New York to  get in on the ground floor of a growing new nuclear industry. The factory opened in 1966 to take in spent reactor fuel, chop it up and dissolve it in acid, and recover uranium and plutonium for re-use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using giant mechanical arms controlled from behind 4-foot-thick steel and concrete walls, technicians welded shut a five-ton canister of intensely radioactive waste from a rusting steel tank here today. In so doing, the Federal Government began to back out of one of the greatest dead ends in American industrial history.</p>
        <p>The waste was left by a private company, Nuclear Fuel Services, which was encouraged to come here, to the rolling hills amid the dairy farms 35 miles south of Buffalo, by Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller, who wanted western New York to  get in on the ground floor of a growing new nuclear industry. The factory opened in 1966 to take in spent reactor fuel, chop it up and dissolve it in acid, and recover uranium and plutonium for re-use.</p>
        <p>The factory is an artifact of the Atoms for Peace era when nuclear electricity was supposed to be "too cheap to meter." Planners thought that there would be 1,000 reactors in the United States by now and that uranium would be scarce and valuable, but they were wrong on both.</p>
        <p>The factory shut in 1972, ostensibly for expansion, but never reopened. A rusting steel tank at the plant holds material that contains about half as much  radiation as was released at Chernobyl, material that will stay dangerously radioactive for thousands of years, but the tank itself was designed to last for only about 50 years, 30 of which have passed. The plant cost $32 million to build. Cleaning up the waste left behind will cost nearly 50 times that much, $1.5 billion, 90 percent of it paid by the Federal Government and 10 percent by  New York State. Nearly $1.1 billion has already been spent.</p>
        <p>What took six years to make will take 19 to undo, if all goes well, with about 300 more canisters to be sealed over the next three years, each filled with waste mixed with a glass similar to pyrex, but the black color of obsidian. Engineers here had to treat the wastes chemically to make them suitable for mixing with glass and reduce the volume of wastes to avoid the need for thousands of canisters.</p>
        <p>None of this will cut the radioactivity to safe levels -- only the eons will  do that. The finished product, a 10-foot-high canister with its exterior charred in stripes by batch upon batch of molten glass, gives off so much radiation that a person standing next to it would get a lethal dose in five minutes. But solidified in glass, the waste will be hard to spread, even if the stainless steel eventually rusts away and the glass breaks into pieces.</p>
        <p>"It was somewhat costly and took quite a period of time, but at least it's not going to go down Cattaraugus Creek and into Lake Erie," said John Chamberlain, a spokesman for West Valley Nuclear Services Company, a subsidiary  of Westinghouse that was brought in to build the processing plant.</p>
        <p>The canisters will be stored in a building where Nuclear Fuel Services used to chop up nuclear fuel. They may eventually go to Yucca Mountain, a site in the Nevada desert that the Energy Department is studying for a long-term repository for highly radioactive waste from around the nation, but it is not clear when the site would open, if at all.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Hazel R. O'Leary, the Secretary of Energy, said in a telephone interview that the opening of the plant kept a promise to neighbors of the plant, and that it was worth the price. She said the new plant would reduce the  risk that, while the country looks for a burial place for high-level radioactive wastes, the rusting steel tank would get older and finally leak, releasing some  of its contents to underground water supplies.</p>
        <p>"That's an easy conclusion to reach about every tank filled with this witches' brew," she said.</p>
        <p>Local environmentalists have been waiting for this day since 1980, when President Jimmy Carter signed legislation for what was expected to be an eight-year, $400 million project to put the waste into glass.</p>
        <p>"We're delighted that they're doing it, but nervous," said Carol Mongerson, a leader of the Coalition on West Valley Nuclear Waste. Earlier this year the system was tested with non-radioactive waste and a weld broke because a support bracket was missing. It created a problem that could not have been fixed by remote control.</p>
        <p>"It was kind of disturbing they had gone through all these tests and hadn't found this until just before they went hot," she said.</p>
        <p>Westinghouse recently opened a similar, larger plant that started work on military wastes at the Savannah River site, near Aiken, S.C. Mrs. O'Leary said that the technology demonstrated there and here could also play a role in reducing the risk of nuclear war, providing a way to dispose of excess weapons plutonium. The plutonium could be put in the canisters with the waste, making it very difficult to retrieve.</p>
        <p>The plant here is remarkable. Since radioactive material was introduced a few days ago, no human can set foot inside the main room, a chamber 70 feet long, 43 feet wide and 46 feet high. Its gleaming steel walls reflect the orange overhead lights, visible through radiation-shielding windows four feet thick. Working there is like building an ocean liner in a bottle, each part with oversized handles and bolts so they can be grasped by artificial, remote-controlled hands.</p>
        <p>Since July 3, a pencil-thin stream of waste mixed with glass, cherry-red at 2,000 degrees, has been flowing from a glass-making machine into stainless steel canisters and left to cool. It goes to the glass-making machine from the old waste tank through a 75-yard pipeline buried in a concrete trough.</p>
        <p>Late this morning, a technician sitting in front of a row of six joysticks, with two video monitors and the controls for swiveling and zooming 19 cameras, gingerly raised the first filled canister with a crate, as it trailed a few wisps of what looked like fishing line or fiberglass, left over from the glass pouring. Then he set it on a stand where it was welded shut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
