<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isolated and Corrupt, Serbia's Economy Stagnates</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="863450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEDGES, CHRIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILOSEVIC, SLOBODAN (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB1139F93AA35754C0A960958260" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isolated and Corrupt, Serbia's Economy Stagnates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEDGES, CHRIS</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, July 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You can still buy a small, boxy Yugo car here, but you have to wait for months. When cars are finally delivered, the more fortunate buyers find they are missing mirrors, upholstery panels or ash trays. The unfortunate ones must clank their way to the nearest garage, where work immediately begins under the hood.</p>
        <p>"As soon as I drove away, I had a leak in the fuel hose," Branislav Cuckovic, 23, said of his Yugo. "A week later the brakes failed, the window handles broke  off and the transmission went. I've spent all my money just to keep it going."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You can still buy a small, boxy Yugo car here, but you have to wait for months. When cars are finally delivered, the more fortunate buyers find they are missing mirrors, upholstery panels or ash trays. The unfortunate ones must clank their way to the nearest garage, where work immediately begins under the hood.</p>
        <p>"As soon as I drove away, I had a leak in the fuel hose," Branislav Cuckovic, 23, said of his Yugo. "A week later the brakes failed, the window handles broke  off and the transmission went. I've spent all my money just to keep it going."</p>
        <p>The stripped-down car, with a Fiat engine, was once the pride of Yugoslavia. The huge Zastava Yugo Automobile plant in Kragujevac rolled out 200,000 vehicles a year beforecivil war broke out five years ago. The cars, which cost about $5,000, were exported to other Eastern European countries and the United States.</p>
        <p>But the plight of Zastava, where production has fallen to 3,500 cars in the first six months of this year, is indicative of the deep economic and political  crisis brewing in Yugoslavia, which now comprises only two republics, Serbia and Montenegro.</p>
        <p>The break-up of Yugoslavia in 1991 destroyed its industrial sector as large manufacturing centers in Serbia were cut off from their suppliers and outlets. International sanctions imposed because of Belgrade's support for the Bosnian Serbs, together with the refusal by the Government to relinquish its grip on state industries, contributed to the withering of manufacturing. (The sanctions, imposed in June 1992, were lifted in January of this year.)</p>
        <p>The central bank's hard currency is almost gone, bringing enormous pressure on the Yugoslav Government to print more money to pay salaries and keep businesses open, but so far officials have resisted increasing the money supply. Once that begins, economists say, the days of hyperinflation are not far away.</p>
        <p>If things do not improve soon -- and there are few signs they will -- the president of Serbia, Slobodan Milosevic, could face "serious political unrest within six to nine months," according to United States intelligence reports. Union leaders, who led a series of strikes this spring, have given the Yugoslav  Government until September to raise salaries and create new jobs, or face renewed nationwide protests.</p>
        <p>As many people in Belgrade remind visitors, the war in the former Yugoslavia  was as much about the control of diminishing resources, jobs and industries as about nationalist ideologies peddled to whip up popular support.</p>
        <p>An economic disaster here could spell real trouble in flash points like the Kosovo region, where ethnic Albanians, who make up more than 90 percent of the population, are under the thumb of repressive Serbian police and officials sent  from Belgrade.</p>
        <p>"Foreign companies come in here, take one look at what is going on and pack up and leave," a Western diplomat said. "We don't even bring in trade delegations now; it's no use."</p>
        <p>Dragoslav Avramovic recently lost his job as governor of the central bank after criticizing the Government for economic mismanagement and its failure to reform the economy -- a failure that has seen Yugoslavia shunned by every major  international lending institution. Mr. Avramovic, 76, a former World Bank official, now warns that catastrophe looms.</p>
        <p>"The Government has two ways left to manage the deficit," he said. "Either print more money or stop paying the bills. I am not sure which is worse. The Government has stopped, for now, paying its bills, but we are running into trouble. The Government does not generate any savings. It is barely able to pay  pensions."</p>
        <p>The country's infrastructure is crumbling: Belgrade's bus fleet is down to 750, from 900, because of the need to cannibalize vehicles for spare parts. There are increasing power failures. The rail system, with 50 engines that are more than five decades old running on hundreds of miles of poorly kept track, can no longer haul products reliably. The water system works sporadically.</p>
        <p>Salaries are paid months late, if at all. The average wage, rural or urban, is about $100 a month, a drop of 80 percent in the last decade.</p>
        <p>"I earn $140 dollars a month, and even then my check comes three months late," said Milanka Bojanovic, 44, who works for the port authority. "I have neighbors who have not been paid for six months."</p>
        <p>Institutional Investor, the trade magazine, recently ranked Yugoslavia Number 129 of 137 countries as a prospect for foreign investment. Among the countries rated less attractive were Libya, the Sudan, Zaire and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>There never were many foreign companies here. Those that have looked into investment say the import-export process is cumbersome, with many bureaucratic restrictions and paperwork. The Government makes it tough to get hard currency.  Taxes and fees, piled one on the other, are also barriers to doing business. Nor was there much direct foreign investment; most foreign companies here handled only sales and distribution.</p>
        <p>And there is a powerful lobby, built up in the last five years, that vigorously opposes economic reform, despite the threat of political upheaval.</p>
        <p>"Milosevic's power is based, as it was under Communism, on nepotism," an American businessman said. "Those who support him get rich, really rich. Those who do not, starve. The middle class is being wiped out, and a new, powerful oligarchy rules this place like a feudal estate."</p>
        <p>Nearly every major state industry is now headed by a senior government official. Prime Minister Mirko Marjanovic is the director of Progres, the oil-importing company; the Deputy Prime Minister, Slobodan Radulovic, runs the largest chain of supermarkets.</p>
        <p>Given the political and economic muscle the state-run corporations wield, local rivals are easily squashed. New businesses that find a niche are quickly absorbed in the maw of government-run monopolies.</p>
        <p>For example, when farmers began to make money by selling raspberries to Germany, trade that was not permitted under the sanctions, the farms were simply taken over by government officials or their cronies, or growers were forced to sell to the state. Not a raspberry leaves this country now without the profits going to one of the huge agricultural conglomerates, including Pik Takovo, which is run by the Agriculture Minister, Ivko Djonovic.</p>
        <p>"A large proportion of the so-called socially owned firms, or government-owned firms, are losing money," Mr. Avramovic said. "These are very inefficient industries. Companies constantly raise prices to keep up, and this has been one of the major causes of inflation."</p>
        <p>The latest row, between wheat farmers and the Government, has many in the countryside seething and could lead to unrest this fall.</p>
        <p>Wheat farmers, many of whom cut back on the number of acres they planted this year because they are being forced to sell their harvests at below-market prices to state-run export companies, warn that they are being pushed over the brink.</p>
        <p>"Never have I seen such anger," said Momir Crnogorac, 32, a farmer from Vojvodina, the major wheat-producing region. "Milosevic, who got away during the war by blaming all this on sanctions, is now playing a very dangerous game. People no longer believe him. They are fed up with being robbed."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
