<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Times Square, With Ketchup; No Cloning, Lots of Razzle-Dazzle at New McDonald's</title>
    <meta content="25MCDO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/25/nyregion/25MCDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1426490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcdonald's Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mount, Charles Morris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6D71239F936A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Times Square, With Ketchup; No Cloning, Lots of Razzle-Dazzle at New McDonald's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Times Square, With Ketchup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>McDonald's Corp opens</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is commonplace for new restaurants in New York to hire publicists, to have the tryout periods known as soft openings and to wallow in industrial materials, plasma screens and bare brick walls. So the surprise at the splashy 17,000-square-foot restaurant in Times Square that officially opens today with such pretensions (but without a red velvet rope) is the name over the door: McDonald's.</p>
        <p>The décor -- big on I-beams, rivets and brushed steel -- is a leap from the red and yellow plastic of the earlier McDonald's, and far from the mass fabrication of the restaurant's food. That's because the McDonald's corporation, once the enforcer of a clonelike 1950's uniformity, now takes a do-your-own-thing attitude about decoration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest in nouveau cuisine in Times Square is a bigger-than-life neon lit McDonald's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is commonplace for new restaurants in New York to hire publicists, to have the tryout periods known as soft openings and to wallow in industrial materials, plasma screens and bare brick walls. So the surprise at the splashy 17,000-square-foot restaurant in Times Square that officially opens today with such pretensions (but without a red velvet rope) is the name over the door: McDonald's.</p>
        <p>The décor -- big on I-beams, rivets and brushed steel -- is a leap from the red and yellow plastic of the earlier McDonald's, and far from the mass fabrication of the restaurant's food. That's because the McDonald's corporation, once the enforcer of a clonelike 1950's uniformity, now takes a do-your-own-thing attitude about decoration.</p>
        <p>Long gone are the days when historic towns worried about a McDonald's adapting and blending in. In Port Jefferson, N.Y., a McDonald's is tucked behind a dormered roof and coach lights. A McDonald's in Phoenix went with an Aztec theme, and included an original earthenware mosaic from Puebla, Mexico, of the Virgin of Guadalupe. And a McDonald's that opened last December in Orlando, Fla., hoped to attract older and wealthier patrons with its French provincial décor, tea-stained lighting, framed Impressionist reproductions, flower arrangements and marble-topped buffet.</p>
        <p>In Times Square, where the neighbors sport neon walls beneath five-story television screens, fitting in means showing off. Thus a giant new marquee on West 42nd Street spells out McDonald's in 7,500 lights, more wattage than required by the 42nd Street Redevelopment Project.</p>
        <p>''You could get a sunburn standing under it,'' said Charles Morris Mount, the restaurant's designer.</p>
        <p>The three-story interior of the restaurant is meant to look like the backstage of a Broadway theater, complete with theatrical light fixtures with ''barn door'' flaps and colored gels. And the 12-foot-wide doorway to this McDonald's will always remain open, in blazing heat and bitter cold, thanks to a million-B.T.U. curtain of air that will keep outside weather outside -- ''unless there's a windstorm,'' said Irwin Kruger, 54, who owns this location and six others in Manhattan. (In case of foul weather, giant folding doors can be closed.) The restaurant, which has 300 seats, hopes to entice customers through the air curtain with the smell of fresh minidoughnuts made at a rate of 2,000 an hour by a machine visible from the street.</p>
        <p>Things have been rough in McDonaldland for several years. Too many fast-food competitors and a sagging economy have led to a poor outlook on earnings. (McDonald's stock has recently been trading at a seven-year low.) The company has settled suits over too-hot coffee and beef flavoring in its fries. Last year the Federal Bureau of Investigation arrested eight people in connection with fraud in a McDonald's promotional Monopoly game. And last week the company recalled a pair of bobble-head figurines of football players because they contained lead paint.</p>
        <p>As of last year, Subway sandwich shops had surpassed the number of McDonald's restaurants in the United States (perhaps that's because no one has yet invented the McDonald's Diet).</p>
        <p>In an attempt to cover its bets, McDonald's has invested in some nonhamburger fast-food businesses, including Prêt à Manger sandwich shops, Donato's pizza and Chipotle Mexican food. Nonetheless, with the right location and razzle-dazzle, a McDonald's can still be a gold mine. Mr. Kruger says that his six other McDonald's restaurants, all designed by Mr. Mount, earn considerably more than the $1.5 million average for American McDonald's sites. The 42nd Street location, he says, is on track to earn $5 million a year.</p>
        <p>A born New Yorker, he put his new McDonald's in the landmark Candler Building, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, which has a historic connection to McDonald's official soft drink purveyor. The 23-story skyscraper was built in 1914 for the head of the Coca-Cola Company, Asa Candler, and once included the Sam H. Harris theater, where in 1922 John Barrymore and Tyrone Power Sr. performed in ''Hamlet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kruger and his designer knew that the restaurant materials would have to stand up to kicking toddlers, bored teenagers, umbrellas, briefcases and mischief. On top of this, they are offering what may be the most accessible new restrooms in the city, just steps from the 41st Street entrance. ''They are heavily used, and convenient,'' said Mr. Kruger, whose restaurant has been open unofficially for weeks. ''You see people hurrying in, and they have that look.''</p>
        <p>The restrooms have resilient porcelain pavers on the floor, and the mirrors are small rather than continuous, so damaged panels can be replaced inexpensively.</p>
        <p>In a long corridor running from 42nd Street to 41st Street, plasma screen monitors above a Corian counter have been encased in brushed steel boxes and covered with a quarter-inch plate of clear Lexan. Music videos, movie trailers, clips from Broadway shows and historical tidbits will play on the monitors.</p>
        <p>''You can hang on them, stand on them, they won't break,'' Mr. Kruger said.</p>
        <p>In the front of the store, the walls were stripped back to bare brick and sealed. Soaring columns are clad in blue reflective glass tile. The walls in the corridor to 41st Street are covered in a gray vinyl called Lonseal that looks like diamond-plate subway grating. The material, much lighter than steel diamond plate, is used as flooring on Navy submarines, but Mr. Kruger said he thought it needed to be tested further. ''We put it down on a driveway, and an employee ran his car over it,'' Mr. Kruger said. ''We tried to gouge it with a knife and a couple of screwdrivers. I'm sure it will withstand the busy customer flow we're going to have.''</p>
        <p>The most prominent structural change was cutting away part of the second floor to create a space nearly 40 feet tall -- Beyer Blinder Belle is the architect -- and the building of twin staircases that climb three floors. (An elevator provides handicapped access, but escalators were deemed ''too much like a mall,'' Mr. Mount said.)</p>
        <p>The staircase railings were made of rebar, the twisted steel rods used to reinforce concrete. A mezzanine level has small tables and aluminum chairs made in Italy. At the top, near the windows on 42nd Street, are two communal tables, where 40 customers may dine together.</p>
        <p>Down the road, Mr. Kruger said, why not send 10-second video postcards by computer to friends all over the world from the Times Square McDonald's? Why not offer space for PowerPoint presentations in a private dining room on the top floor? And what would Times Square be without entertainment? ''It could be a lot of fun to find actors 'in transition' who've got outgoing personalities,'' Mr. Kruger said, ''who could engage some of our customers in a karaoke moment.''</p>
        <p>With all the new buildings in Times Square, he said, foot traffic will only increase to the Port Authority bus terminal down the block. ''There's Condé Nast and the new Boston Properties,'' he said. ''We've got white collar, tourists, theatrical, blue collar. I'm thrilled to be in the location we're in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
