<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Accuses Lincoln Of Misleading Bond Buyers</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORPORATE BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN CONTINENTAL CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEATING, CHARLES H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEV, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE143FF930A35750C0A966958260" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Accuses Lincoln Of Misleading Bond Buyers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LEV, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEV, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A California agency said today that it had filed a multimillion-dollar lawsuit against Charles H. Keating Jr. and the American Continental Corporation, contending that the company put pressure on unsophisticated investors to buy its ''junk bonds'' by saying they were insured by the Government and were free of risk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A California agency said today that it had filed a multimillion-dollar lawsuit against Charles H. Keating Jr. and the American Continental Corporation, contending that the company put pressure on unsophisticated investors to buy its ''junk bonds'' by saying they were insured by the Government and were free of risk.</p>
        <p>A California agency said today that it had filed a multimillion-dollar lawsuit against Charles H. Keating Jr. and the American Continental Corporation, contending that the company put pressure on unsophisticated investors to buy its ''junk bonds'' by saying they were insured by the Government and were free of risk.</p>
        <p>The California Department of Corporations charged in the lawsuit, filed Thursday in Los Angeles County Superior Court, that American Continental and its top executives, including Mr. Keating, had lied to the state in disclosure forms and misled investors who bought the bonds from branches of Lincoln Savings and Loan, a subsidiary of the company.</p>
        <p>The department said it had conducted an eight-month investigation and interviewed more than 100 holders of the now-worthless bonds and a dozen present and former employees. Many investors - a large number of them elderly people - lost their life savings.</p>
        <p>Vital Information</p>
        <p>The suit contends that American Continental withheld vital information from investors and never disclosed that its bonds were uninsured.</p>
        <p>Christine Bender, the Department of Corporations commissioner, said she had forwarded the charges to law enforcement officials for possible criminal prosecution. The Los Angeles County District Attorney's office said today that it had asked for a special grand jury for Lincoln.</p>
        <p>While the department's lawsuit seeks the restitution of $200 million invested by California bondholders, and penalties that could add millions more, the agency conceded that it might be difficult to recover the money. American Continental sought bankruptcy court protection from creditors last year. The Government seized Lincoln Savings last spring.</p>
        <p>Series of Lawsuits</p>
        <p>The lawsuit is the latest in a series of actions against Mr. Keating and his companies. One of the suits by the holders also charges the state agency with failing to identify the problem. Ms. Bender is scheduled to give a deposition in that suit within two weeks.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for both Mr. Keating and the bondholders said the lawsuit was politically motivated. Several officials involved in investigations of Mr. Keating and his companies are running for political office this year. A spokesman for American Continental, Brad Boland, said Mr. Keating was not available to comment. He said the company strongly denied that it had ever misled bond buyers.</p>
        <p>''We have not seen the filing, but I find it very perplexing that the same agency that over the years gave us numerous approvals to sell bonds turns around and sues us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>James Ham, an attorney for Mr. Keating, said: ''The bond salesmen were scrupulous in advising people that these were subordinated debentures and were not insured by the Federal Government. There always may be a small group who honestly felt they were misled, but as to the vast majority I think it's a case of conveniently selective memory.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
