<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Investor Groups Go To Waterford's Aid</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WATERFORD WEDGWOOD PLC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MORGAN STANLEY &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'REILLY, ANTHONY J F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PROKESCH, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE143FF930A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Investor Groups Go To Waterford's Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN PROKESCH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PROKESCH, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, March 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Investor groups led by Morgan Stanley &amp; Company and Anthony J. F. O'Reilly have come to the rescue of Waterford Wedgwood P.L.C., the troubled maker of crystal and china.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Investor groups led by Morgan Stanley &amp; Company and Anthony J. F. O'Reilly have come to the rescue of Waterford Wedgwood P.L.C., the troubled maker of crystal and china.</p>
        <p>Investor groups led by Morgan Stanley &amp; Company and Anthony J. F. O'Reilly have come to the rescue of Waterford Wedgwood P.L.C., the troubled maker of crystal and china.</p>
        <p>Under the investment plan anounced today in Dublin, the two groups will together hold a 29.9 percent stake in the company, which is staggering under a burden of $233.7 million in debt.</p>
        <p>Both Morgan Stanley and Mr. O'Reilly, who is chairman of the Pittsburgh-based H. J. Heinz Company and a leading industrialist in his native Ireland, said they were eager to invest in a company with luxury brands. ''There are 250 quintessential brands in the world,'' Mr. O'Reilly said in a telephone interview from Dublin, ''With Waterford and Wedgford, we have two of those.''</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Leveraged Equity Fund II L.P. and Fitzwilton P.L.C., the group led by Mr. O'Reilly, will each pay about $61.5 million for their stake. They also plan to raise about $35.8 million through a share offering to Waterford shareholders. A substantial portion of the $158.9 million will be used to reduce Waterford's debt to about $80 million.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to spending more of my time on operations and less on servicing an untenable level of debt,'' Patrick P. Bryne, Waterford Wedgwood's chief executive, said today in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The heavy debt - a result of the $360 million-plus purchase of the British Wedgwood by the Irish Waterford in 1986 - proved to be too much as the company was hit by a host of problems.</p>
        <p>When they merged, Waterford and Wedgwood had hoped to modernize their production and increase their worldwide marketing power. But the company found itself spending more time digging out of problems than exploiting opportunities.</p>
        <p>Last April the Waterford crystal unit was found to be suffering from serious accounting and operation problems and had overstated 1988 earnings by some $21 million. That produced deep losses for the unit, largely offsetting the record operating earnings of Wedgwood.</p>
        <p>Patrick Hayes, who was then chairman and chief executive, resigned, as did the finance director. The head of the crystal unit retired.</p>
        <p>The company was dealt another blow when the crucial American and British markets softened last year. With Waterford's losses remaining high and Wedgwood's profits sinking, the company had a pretax loss of $32 million in 1989 on sales of $542.5 million.</p>
        <p>The United States accounts for 40 percent of total sales and 70 percent of crystal sales. Britain accounts for about a third of total sales and 32 percent of china sales.</p>
        <p>Labor Troubles</p>
        <p>The company's problems have been compounded by an exodus of Wedgwood management and labor difficulties. After agreeing to a three-year wage freeze last summer, the 2,100 workers at Waterford crystal, who are among the highest paid in Ireland, rebelled when asked to make further concessions to increase productivity and lower costs.</p>
        <p>Although the reduction in debt will certainly help, ''there are formidable problems to overcome,'' said John Hogan, head of research at Riada &amp; Company, a Dublin brokerage.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the labor impasse remains to be broken. The American and British economies are barely growing. Several department store chains in the United States are in bankruptcy proceedings or on the auction block. Dr. Hogan believes the company will be lucky to break even on a pretax basis in 1990.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the leaders of Morgan Stanley and Fitzwilton say they are confident Waterford Wedgwood will become highly profitable. A Record of Winners Both Morgan Stanley and Fitzwilton have a strong record of picking winners. Morgan Stanley's first leveraged fund invested $30 million and returned $700 million.</p>
        <p>The current Morgan Stanley fund, which is two years old, has invested about $900 million in 12 companies, including big American corporations like Colt Industries, the diversified manufacturer, and Fort Howard, the paper-products maker. The fund has a target rate of return of 40 percent pretax a year. ''To date, all of the investments, except one, are on track,'' said Robert H. Niehaus, a managing director of Morgan Stanley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Niehaus is optimistic that Waterford will not be the second disappointment.</p>
        <p>''Almost all the problems and losses are on the crystal side, and we are confident that the new management team will get that business to a reasonable cost position,'' he said. ''We see significant growth potential in the china business in the United States and Japan and we see additional growth opportunites in both the United States and Britain for the crystal business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Reilly will be applying his marketing skills to helping Waterford Wedgwood exploit those opportunities. He will be one of the four non-executive directors of Waterford Wedgwood from Fitzwilton and Morgan Stanley.</p>
        <p>To Help Map Strategy</p>
        <p>While he does not intend to play a day-to-day role, Mr. O'Reilly made it clear that he intended to help Wedgwood with its marketing strategy ''particularly in the North American market, with which I have considerable familiarity,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also intends to push management to do what he did successfully at Heinz: cut costs and increase volume to raise profit margins substantially, and then plow much of that cash into ''extra marketing.''</p>
        <p>Another way to increase profits, he said, is to expand in Japan, where Wedgwood china is already doing well and where Waterford crystal has recently been introduced. Other makers of luxury goods - including Cartier, Dunhill and LVMH - have made ''very, very substantial profits'' by selling to the Japanese, he noted.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Reilly, 53 years old, is one of Ireland's leading press entrepreneurs. He also has interests in hotels and oil prospecting and owns a 500-acre estate in County Kildare, with a 28-room, 18th-century mansion.</p>
        <p>He owns 10 percent of Fitzwilton, as does Metromedia, which is headed by John Kluge, and the Power Corporation, the Canadian company headed by Paul Demarais.</p>
        <p>Diversified Investments</p>
        <p>Fitzwilton's investments include Ford and General Motors dealerships in Britain, an Irish exporter of commercial freezers, a manufacturer of reflective materials and a big distributor of food and non-food cash-and-carry goods. Its companies have sales of about $600 million, and analysts estimate it earned $20 million in 1989. After the $61.5 million it plans to spend on Waterford Wedgwood, its investment will total about $190 million.</p>
        <p>The price of 37.5 Irish pence, or 58 cents, a share that the two groups are paying for their stake in Waterford compares with the stock's peak of 150 pence in 1987. Fitzwilton initially began talks with Waterford two and a half years ago, but dropped out when the stock reached 140 pence.</p>
        <p>On the London Stock Exchange, the stock closed today at 47 pence, up 2 pence.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
