<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CROAT ARMY TAKES REBEL STRONGHOLD IN RAPID ADVANCE</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="780757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CROATIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KNIN (CROATIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KRAJINA (CROATIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONNER, RAYMOND</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DA1231F935A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CROAT ARMY TAKES REBEL STRONGHOLD IN RAPID ADVANCE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND BONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONNER, RAYMOND</byline>
      <dateline>ZAGREB, Croatia, Aug. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Croatian Government forces routed rebel Serbs today from Knin, the 13th-century fortress that had served as the insurgents' headquarters for four years.</p>
        <p>The Serbs gave up the town without much of a fight on the second day of a Croatian offensive to retake a swath of Serb-held territory that the rebels call Krajina, and the Serbian political leaders there have fled, Croatian and United Nations officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Croatian Government forces routed rebel Serbs today from Knin, the 13th-century fortress that had served as the insurgents' headquarters for four years.</p>
        <p>The Serbs gave up the town without much of a fight on the second day of a Croatian offensive to retake a swath of Serb-held territory that the rebels call Krajina, and the Serbian political leaders there have fled, Croatian and United Nations officials said.</p>
        <p>For more than 24 hours, Knin was subjected to "indiscriminate" shelling, the United Nations said, with shells landing on the rail yard, hospital and residential areas.</p>
        <p>Though the number of casualties is not known, a United Nations official in Knin, Alun Roberts, said that there were "quite significant numbers of bodies in the streets" and that many of them were women and children.</p>
        <p>A Croatian Defense Ministry spokesman, Gen. Ivan Tolj, said this evening, "We have proceeded twice as fast as we expected." The exultant general reeled off a list of towns that he said Croatian forces had "liberated" in the previous 36 hours. The region has been under Serb control for four years.</p>
        <p>In two days, the Croatian Army had "carried out 80 percent of its set tasks," General Tolj said. "These are historic days, for Croatia, Europe and the whole world.,"</p>
        <p>At 5 P.M. today, he said, Croatian forces linked up with Bosnian Army troops in Bihac, the Muslim enclave across the border in Bosnia that includes a United Nations-protected "safe area" and has been under siege by the Bosnian Serbs.</p>
        <p>"Bihac has been saved," General Tolj declared. "The Croatian army has done what we believed the world should have done."</p>
        <p>Western Governments have said in recent days that they would authorize NATO air strikes to protect the remaining four "safe areas" in Bosnia, after two others fell to the Bosnian Serbs last month.</p>
        <p>[ President Clinton said the Croatian offensive could prove helpful in resolving the Balkan conflict, but he again called on Croatia "to exercise real restraint." Page 9. ]</p>
        <p>The United States and Germany had been sympathetic to a military action by Croatia. But they and other Western allies had feared that the Croatian offensive would widen the war in the Balkans, which has been largely confined to Bosnia during the last three years.</p>
        <p>The United States had hoped the Croatian advance would be quick and clean. The operation has been quick, but not clean.</p>
        <p>In the offensive today in Knin, one shell exploded about 100 yards from the United Nations base there, killing seven civilians and wounding dozens more, United Nations officials said.</p>
        <p>Two Czech peacekeepers also died today from injuries sustained in a Croatian artillery attack on another United Nations position, and more than 200 United Nations troops have been forced by the Serbs to abandon their posts, the United Nations said.</p>
        <p>Croatia sent more than 100,000 troops into battle in Krajina, along with tanks, armored personnel carriers, fighter jets and helicopters. The rebel Serb forces had only half that number of men, and while it is no ragtag guerrilla army, it did not have an arsenal to match Croatia's.</p>
        <p>It is not clear why the Serb forces in Knin capitulated so quickly, but it may have been because they were seriously outgunned. It also appears that they realized they were not going to get any meaningful assistance from President Slobodan Milosevic of Serbia, and that the Bosnian Serb army was stretched too thin in its war with the Bosnian Government to provide any real help.</p>
        <p>Nor has it been possible to explain why the Serbs did not launch rocket attacks on the Croatian capital, Zagreb, and other cities. It may be that the Croatian Army destroyed the Serbian rocket launchers early in the war, though it has not said so.</p>
        <p>The fear of a missile attack has clearly diminished in Zagreb. The United Nations soldiers have already shed their flak jackets, and the quiet of the capital was the serenity of August in Europe, rather than the silence of fear.</p>
        <p>In addition to protecting its territorial integrity, Croatia has many reasons for wanting to get Krajina back. It sits astride vital oil and rail routes. And the alluring Adriatic beaches, which bring in millions of dollars of foreign exchange, are most easily reached through Krajina.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the many Croatians who lived in the region before they were forced to flee by the Serbs want their homes and land back.</p>
        <p>Many international officials and diplomats here say they believe that the Croatian Government intends to turn Krajina, which was once predominately Serbian, into a region in which few if any Serbian pockets remain.</p>
        <p>General Tolj said the army had opened two corridors through which civilians may leave; both lead into Serb-controlled areas of Bosnia.</p>
        <p>While the military offensive was clearly going in Croatia's favor, Zagreb also launched a political and diplomatic offensive today.</p>
        <p>The Government denied its forces had been responsible for the death of a Danish peacekeeper on the first day of the operation. General Tolj contended that the peacekeeper had been seized by the Serbs and tied to his tank.</p>
        <p>A United Nations spokesman, Philip Arnold, said however that the United Nations continued to support the statement Friday by General Bernard Janvier, the commander of United Nations forces in the Balkans. The General said the Danish soldier had been "deliberately" killed by the Croatian forces.</p>
        <p>The ringing condemnation of the Krajina offensive by Carl Bildt, the principal European Union negotiator for the Balkans, was even more bothersome for the Croatian Government.</p>
        <p>On Friday Mr. Bildt said the attack would "cast a dark shadow over Croatia for a long time" and compared President Franjo Tudjman of Croatia with the rebel Croatian Serb leader, Milan Martic, who has been charged by an international war crimes tribunal in The Hague.</p>
        <p>The Government sent a formal letter of protest to Mr. Bildt, which it released to the news media. At a news conference today, another senior Foreign Ministry official, Ivan Senander, said that if the Croatian Government did not receive a formal apology, the consequences would be "serious." He declined to elaborate.</p>
        <p>The best antidote to any further criticism will be for Croatia to finish its operation in a few days.</p>
        <p>The Croatian military had advised the President that it would take four to seven days for the war, including mopping up, said a knowledgeable Western observer. "It is going even faster than we thought," he said.</p>
        <p>In the last four years, in spite of an arms embargo, the Croatians have built a military force that is one of the strongest in Europe, said one diplomat. "Even the Americans might not want to toy with it on the battlefield," he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
