<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earnhardt Trashes Talk About His Demise</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="780429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRICKYARD 400 (AUTO RACE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANAPOLIS SPEEDWAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIANO, JOSEPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EARNHARDT, DALE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDB1E38F935A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earnhardt Trashes Talk About His Demise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH SIANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIANO, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Aug. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In case anyone forgot, Dale Earnhardt issued a reminder in the Brickyard 400 today: talk is cheap, and a lot slower than what it takes to beat him and his team.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, who took the lead in his Chevy Monte Carlo after the final round of pit stops, held off Rusty Wallace's Ford Thunderbird over the last 28 laps to win by 0.426 seconds, with Dale Jarrett right behind in third.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In case anyone forgot, Dale Earnhardt issued a reminder in the Brickyard 400 today: talk is cheap, and a lot slower than what it takes to beat him and his team.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, who took the lead in his Chevy Monte Carlo after the final round of pit stops, held off Rusty Wallace's Ford Thunderbird over the last 28 laps to win by 0.426 seconds, with Dale Jarrett right behind in third.</p>
        <p>It took Earnhardt a while to do it -- first because of a 4-hour-2-minute rain delay and then because of a poor-handling car once the race started. But as the sun set over the Indianapolis Motor Speedway, he showed that it wasn't setting over his career.</p>
        <p>"Do you think people have really forgotten about me?" he asked. The response came when someone suggested this victory could help re-establish his credibility as a championship contender against Jeff Gordon and Sterling Marlin. The two have surged ahead of Earnhardt, a seven-time Winston Cup champion, in recent races as they try to win their first championship.</p>
        <p>Gordon, who celebrated only his 24th birthday on Friday, has been a particular irritant lately to Earnhardt. When someone told Earnhardt that he had won $565,600 today, he said jokingly "That's a little short of what Jeffrey won last year." Actually, $47,400 short, to be exact, because Gordon led for more laps last year than Earnhardt did today.</p>
        <p>But Earnhardt's crew showed this weekend that it never jokes about winning and is not to be forgotten as a title contender. The team came here with a new car. Despite practice time that was limited to about 15 minutes on Friday because of rain, it had the car running like a winner less than 100 miles into today's race. "Our guys are confident," he said. "They're hard workers. And you're not going to beat us by talking about us."</p>
        <p>Earnhardt left here in third in the title standing, 121 points behind Gordon and 39 behind Marlin, who was seventh today.</p>
        <p>With 32 laps to go today, Earnhardt's crew completed his last pit stop in 18 seconds, faster than the 20.9 seconds Wallace's crew needed.</p>
        <p>"The last stop was the key," Earnhardt said. "The guys did a great job getting us off pit road."</p>
        <p>But he had another advantage on that stop, too. As the defending Winston Cup champion (two-time, actually), he gets first choice of pit positions. As usual, his team chose the stop at the exit of pit lane, giving him a clear shot out of the pits. Today, it paid off.</p>
        <p>Wallace was hurt by being farther back on the pit road.</p>
        <p>Wallace, who led for 22 laps today, made his last pit stop a lap after Earnhardt did. Wallace's pit crew was midway along pit lane, and as he left the pits, he was behind Rich Bickle. Joe Nemechek, whose pit position was four behind Earnhardt's, pulled out in front of Bickle. The two collided, and the brief traffic jam slowed Wallace.</p>
        <p>"I really thought I had it locked up," said Wallace, who was ahead of Earnhardt before the final pit stops, but not after them. "But when I went to leave pit road, they crashed in front of me. It was a roadblock. Dale just got out in front of me, and track position was everything."</p>
        <p>It meant so much to be ahead today because as soon as anyone pulled within four car lengths of someone else in an attempt to pass, the turbulent air off the back of the leading car made the front end of the trailing car lift slightly, disturbing its handling.</p>
        <p>"The front end of my car was pushing real bad," Wallace said, referring to the situation when a car's front tires aren't gripping enough. "When I got behind Earnhardt, it just washed out all the downforce."</p>
        <p>The same thing happened to the car driven by Jarrett. The two of them started well back in the 41-car lineup -- Wallace 24th and Jarrett 26th. But they fought all day to be contenders in the final 24-lap sprint after the race's only caution flag. The yellow flag came out when Jeff Burton's Thunderbird spun in front of Earnhardt in Turn 2 of Lap 132. Earnhardt dodged the car, and Burton kept going.</p>
        <p>"Running someone down and passing them were two different things," Jarrett said of his pursuit of Earnhardt and Wallace, "especially those two guys. The last 10 laps, I must have tried 10 different lines trying to make something work."</p>
        <p>"If you were out front, you were the guy in command," said Gordon, who was in command for 35 laps. But a combination of a poorly handling car and a problem changing the lug nuts on one of his wheels in his final pit stop prevented Gordon from repeating as winner here. He finished sixth in his Chevy.  AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
