<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New and Improved Agassi Is Working Harder to Succeed</title>
    <meta content="10TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agassi, Andre</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5DA1230F933A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New and Improved Agassi Is Working Harder to Succeed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>INDIAN WELLS, Calif. March 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses recent improved play of tennis player Andre Agassi; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stasis has never interested Andre Agassi. Blue hair, blond hair, Mohawk hair, no hair, he has taken every hair on his head to extremes. On the tennis court, he has pretty much gone in the same direction. A dedicated recycler of himself, Agassi has performed every way but predictably in his 13 years on the stump, but this latest reincarnation, one that has him leading the pack with a 17-2 record and an 11-match winning spree after doing a dead man's float in 1997, may be his most ingenious.</p>
        <p>Fitness, focus and a fanatical desire to compete have ganged up on him with the force of a religious conversion. And Agassi is ready to be converted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stasis has never interested Andre Agassi. Blue hair, blond hair, Mohawk hair, no hair, he has taken every hair on his head to extremes. On the tennis court, he has pretty much gone in the same direction. A dedicated recycler of himself, Agassi has performed every way but predictably in his 13 years on the stump, but this latest reincarnation, one that has him leading the pack with a 17-2 record and an 11-match winning spree after doing a dead man's float in 1997, may be his most ingenious.</p>
        <p>Fitness, focus and a fanatical desire to compete have ganged up on him with the force of a religious conversion. And Agassi is ready to be converted.</p>
        <p>''This is new to me,'' the 27-year-old Agassi said today after opening his campaign at the Newsweek Champions Cup with a 7-6 (7-3), 6-4 expulsion of 34th-ranked Todd Woodbridge. ''I'm out there not just focused, but looking forward to it. I mean, there's still more tennis in me, and I'm going to go in there and get it. Today was about me showing up and getting the job done.''</p>
        <p>Agassi on Sunday wore his hard hat and carried his lunch pail to work in Scottsdale, Ariz., where he won his second title of the year, the 36th of his artfully checkered career. ''It wasn't easy to get in shape, to stop taking it out on the knife and fork; it's been nothing short of hard work,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A scant year after hitting No. 1 in 1996, at the close of last season, Agassi went all the way off the map to the tennis version of skid row, the Challenger circuit, to try to repair a triple-digit ranking. He had lost that winning feeling, and if he had to demote himself to the minors to retrieve it, so be it. He convinced himself that a change of pace and place would do him good.</p>
        <p>''It was a calculated decision to make the steps necessary to get back to a place where I could step on the court and feel good about myself,'' he said. ''It was the marking period at the end of the year.''</p>
        <p>Six months ago, he was shagging balls, ''eating processed chicken and flipping the score card myself'' in Burbank, Calif., uncertain if he would ever rejoin the big circuit. But after winning a title there, his first since he followed up his 1996 Olympic gold medal with a victory in Cincinnati, Agassi zipped into 1998 like a man who, if not reborn again, was on the rebound.</p>
        <p>''I'm feeling like I'm moving well, reading the ball, picking it up,'' he said. ''I have shots that guys can't hit, things that are weapons, and I've been looking forward to that feeling for a long time, and now it's there.''</p>
        <p>Like Agassi, who is now ranked 40th, 100 spots above last season's nadir, Thomas Muster has been ranked No. 1. That is a more imposing position than the final rung of the top 20, which is the slot Muster, an unseeded Austrian, occupies now. At 30, Muster is the oldest man in the top 20, and just a week ago a physician with the Davis Cup team said that it was high time Muster did his body a favor and retired. But after giving Chris Woodruff a 6-4, 6-4 thumping today, Muster said he did not plan to take the doctor's advice.</p>
        <p>''Maybe some people wish I'd retire,'' he said, ''but this is unfortunately not going to happen yet for them.''</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>STEFFI GRAF trounced AI SUGIYAMA of Japan, 6-0, 6-1, in the third round Monday night. Graf, who is ranked 45th but seeded third based on the ranking she held when she left the circuit last year because of knee surgery, was visibly impressed, and relieved, after her rout of the 11th-seeded Sugiyama. ''It felt great that I was going for my shots, played very hard, very deep,'' said Graf, who needed just 43 minutes to advance to play NATASHA ZVEREVA. Graf, who had not won three successive matches since last May, said she was drawing no assumptions from her steady progress and was in no hurry to test herself against MARTINA HINGIS, the player who supplanted her at the top. ''I'm very much aware that I'm going to need time,'' Graf said. ''Hey, I'm just starting again. I don't see myself being able to be at that level right now.''</p>
        <p>Hingis breezed through her third-round meeting with MEIKE BABEL of Germany, 6-2, 6-0, but there were a couple of upsets to the seeded ranks on both the men's and women's sides Monday. The French Open champion, 10th-seeded GUSTAVO KUERTEN of Brazil, hampered by a lower-back strain, was upset in the first round, 6-4, 6-7 (4-7), 6-2, by 27th-ranked NICOLAS KIEFER of Germany. And sixth-seeded IRINA SPIRLEA of Romania sprayed her forehand everywhere but inside the lines and was ousted by the 15th-seeded Zvereva, 6-3, 7-5.  TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
