<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Police Seek Link Between Rapes and Death of Teen-Ager</title>
    <meta content="10ATTA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D91230F933A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Police Seek Link Between Rapes and Death of Teen-Ager</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC police are investigating possible link between recent rapes of two women in Tremont section of Bronx and body of unidentified slain teen-age girl that was found in neighborhood two weeks ago (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police are investigating a possible link between recent rapes of two women in the Tremont section of the Bronx and the body of an unidentified slain teen-age girl that was found in the neighborhood two weeks ago, investigators said.</p>
        <p>Capt. John Creegan, Commander of the Bronx Detective Bureau, said yesterday that investigators believe a single suspect could be responsible for the rapes and the murder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The police are investigating a possible link between recent rapes of two women in the Tremont section of the Bronx and the body of an unidentified slain teen-age girl that was found in the neighborhood two weeks ago, investigators said.</p>
        <p>Capt. John Creegan, Commander of the Bronx Detective Bureau, said yesterday that investigators believe a single suspect could be responsible for the rapes and the murder.</p>
        <p>The first attack occurred on Feb. 23, when a woman was taken into an alleyway at 2302 Valentine Avenue at 1:30 A.M. and raped, Captain Creegan said. The police did not identify the woman.</p>
        <p>That night, the body of the teen-age girl was found less than a block away on the corner of Valentine Avenue and 183d Street at 11:20 P.M. The captain said the girl had been choked to death and might have been sexually assaulted. The girl has still not been identified.</p>
        <p>''It's a few doors down from the scene of the first incident,'' Captain Creegan said.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, a woman who worked for the city's Housing Authority was badly beaten and raped a block away from where the teen-ager's body was discovered, he said.</p>
        <p>The woman was thrown onto the ground and then beaten and raped at the Twin Park East Housing Development at 365 Ford Street, at 6 A.M. on Sunday. The victim, whom the police have not identified, was still hospitalized yesterday.</p>
        <p>''We believe there is a possible connection because of the nature of the assault,'' Captain Creegan said.</p>
        <p>The police said that no identification had been found on the teen-age girl's body and that no one fitting her description had been reported missing.</p>
        <p>The girl was 5-feet-5, weighed 100 pounds and had curly brown hair, brown eyes, a scar on her left leg and a scar on her right elbow. She was dressed in dark green pants when she was found, he said.</p>
        <p>In an unrelated case, the police said yesterday that they were searching for another man for questioning in two rapes in the Morrisania section of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Captain Creegan said a 22-year-old woman and a 41-year-old woman were raped at gunpoint in the same building at 3204 Park Avenue on Jan. 13 and March 4. The women were not identified because of the nature of the crime.</p>
        <p>Both attacks occurred at 1:30 A.M. and both victims were taken upstairs to a stairwell and raped at gunpoint.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
