<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preparing Classic Italian Dishes, but With a Twist</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE153DF930A35755C0A966958260" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preparing Classic Italian Dishes, but With a Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR a number of years, cooks and chefs have been taking some Italian classics as inspiration and giving them a new twist. Pesto is a good example.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR a number of years, cooks and chefs have been taking some Italian classics as inspiration and giving them a new twist. Pesto is a good example.</p>
        <p>FOR a number of years, cooks and chefs have been taking some Italian classics as inspiration and giving them a new twist. Pesto is a good example.</p>
        <p>The traditional pesto sauce is made with basil in Italy but now Americans are substituting other herbs, often fresh coriander or mint. Similarly, the dish called scampi, made with shrimp-like crustaceans from Adriatic waters and simply prepared with butter or oil and garlic, appears on American menus as a similar preparation using regular shrimp. A ''scampi sauce'' is often served over chicken or fish.</p>
        <p>Purists might lament this practice, but Italian food is not the only cuisine involved. Chefs have even taken liberties with some American classics: the club sandwich, for example. Club sandwiches today are made with lobster instead of chicken or turkey and even with soft-shell crabs.</p>
        <p>The following recipes can be added to the list of variations on an Italian scene. Saltimbocca, a dish usually made with pieces of veal, prosciutto and sage, works extremely well when firm-fleshed fish like monkfish is substituted for the veal.</p>
        <p>Some typical pasta sauces are also excellent served with chicken or fish instead of pasta. Amatriciana is the name of a popular spicy tomato, onion and pork combination usually tossed with bucatini, a type of thick spaghetti. The sauce originated in the town of Amatrice, not far from Rome, hence the name. It is an easy sauce to prepare and delicious used for baking fish like fluke or tilefish.</p>
        <p>Finally, puttanesca is a well-known, vibrant Neapolitan sauce for spaghetti but it also does a fine job as a flavoring for grilled chicken.</p>
        <p>Saltimbocca of Monkfish</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 10 minutes</p>
        <p>1 pound monkfish, in 8 thin slices</p>
        <p>16 leaves fresh sage</p>
        <p>8 slices prosciutto, about 2 ounces</p>
        <p>Flour</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons sweet butter</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>Y cup dry white wine.</p>
        <p>1. Pat the monkfish slices dry. Top each with two sage leaves, then place a slice of prosciutto, folded to fit the slice of fish if necessary, over the sage. Secure with a toothpick. Dredge lightly with flour on both sides and season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the butter and oil in a large, heavy skillet. Add the fish and prosciutto slices and saute over high heat, about three minutes on each side, until lightly browned. Remove from the pan and set aside on a warm platter.</p>
        <p>3. Add the wine to the skillet, swirl and bring to a simmer. Pour a little of this sauce over each piece of fish and serve at once.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Chicken Puttanesca</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 10 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>1/4 cup extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon lemon juice</p>
        <p>2 pounds skinless and boneless chicken breasts</p>
        <p>Freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>3 large garlic cloves, sliced</p>
        <p>4 anchovies, mashed</p>
        <p>1 pound ripe tomatoes, peeled, cored and finely chopped, or substitute well-drained canned tomatoes, chopped</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon drained capers</p>
        <p>Red pepper flakes to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Combine two tablespoons of the oil with the lemon juice. Brush over the chicken breasts, season with pepper and set aside to marinate about 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, heat two tablespoons of the oil in a large, heavy skillet. Add the garlic and cook until it just begins to color, then stir in the anchovies.</p>
        <p>3. Add the tomatoes and cook over medium heat for 10 to 15 minutes, until the sauce begins to thicken. Stir in the capers and season with red pepper flakes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>4. Preheat grill or broiler. Grill or broil the chicken breasts until they are just cooked through and lightly browned, about six minutes on each side. Transfer to a serving platter.</p>
        <p>5. Reheat the sauce, spoon over the chicken and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Fluke, Amatriciana Style</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>2 pounds fluke fillets</p>
        <p>Juice of 1 lemon</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>4 ounces pancetta, diced (unsmoked Italian bacon)</p>
        <p>$2 medium onions, sliced thin</p>
        <p>2 cups finely chopped ripe plum tomatoes or chopped well-drained canned tomatoes</p>
        <p>Red pepper flakes to taste</p>
        <p>2 Tablespoons flat-leaf parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Brush a baking dish that will hold the fish in a single layer lightly with a little of the oil. Place the fish in the dish and sprinkle with the lemon juice. Season with salt and pepper. Cover and refrigerate while preparing the sauce.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the remaining oil in a heavy skillet. Add the pancetta and saute until lightly browned. Add the onion and continue to saute over low heat until the onions are golden.</p>
        <p>3. Stir in the tomatoes, increase the heat to medium-high and cook, stirring, for 10 to 15 minutes, until the sauce begins to thicken. Season to taste with salt and red pepper flakes.</p>
        <p>4. Remove the fish from the refrigerator. Preheat oven to 425 degrees.</p>
        <p>5. Spoon the sauce over the fish. Place the fish in the preheated oven and bake for 15 to 20 minutes, until it is just cooked through. Sprinkle with parsley and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
