<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Male Athlete and Sexual Assault</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D7123CF930A35755C0A966958260" item-length="1807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Male Athlete and Sexual Assault</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Once revered as much for his manly image as for his on-the-field performance, the male athlete is receiving increased scrutiny for his off-the-field behavior with women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Once revered as much for his manly image as for his on-the-field performance, the male athlete is receiving increased scrutiny for his off-the-field behavior with women.</p>
        <p>Once revered as much for his manly image as for his on-the-field performance, the male athlete is receiving increased scrutiny for his off-the-field behavior with women.</p>
        <p>Interviews with rape-crisis counselors as well as results of studies of assaults on college campuses indicate that athletes are involved in a disproportionate number of rapes and other sexual assaults, but there is an absence of programs at the high school, college and professional levels to prevent such attacks.</p>
        <p>Although exact figures on such crimes by athletes are difficult to obtain, changes in society's awareness of women's concerns and the wider attention accorded an athlete's private life have heightened the attention these incidents receive. Until recent years, this part of the athlete's life was often winked at, covered up or simply ignored.</p>
        <p>Now, several studies, as well as anecdotal evidence from counselors on campuses and in rape treatment centers and recovery programs, indicate that this is becoming a more significant and visible problem for the athlete. Many experts believe that sensitivity training would be the most successful remedy, and at least one college has such a program. But the vast majority of athletes and coaches receive no such training.</p>
        <p>''I'd say a significant number of our clients have been gang-raped by athletes,'' said Marybeth Roden of the Rape Treatment Center at Santa Monica (Calif.) Hospital, where patients from U.C.L.A. are often brought. ''I think it would be great if more athletic directors got involved in raising athletes' consciousness to the problem. The best people to teach men are other men.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, researchers say a crime is often not even perceived by society as having occurred when an athlete, or group of athletes, is involved.</p>
        <p>''The entire group will fall behind the accused and deny an offense has been committed,'' said Dr. Claire Walsh, who directs the sexual assault recovery program at the University of Florida. ''The entire community associated with this group will come to its defense. In every single case they will deny there was gang rape but that there was group sex.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Walsh also cautioned against viewing the problem as an athlete's problem and forgetting that the real victim is the woman. ''In almost all cases, there was drinking, and that creates a negative image of the victim, because we have ideas of how a 'young lady' should behave,'' she said. ''But who do people think is getting raped? It's their daughters. It's their sisters. Often, they're attacked because of the qualities parents try to instill in them, such as trust.''</p>
        <p>In a pioneering work on sexual assault on campuses started three years ago by the National Institute of Mental Health, and completed while she taught at Kent State University, Dr. Mary P. Koss found that, of the cases studied, athletes were involved about a third of the time.</p>
        <p>''My gut feeling about gang rape is that it takes place in front of guys who know each other; they live together, have a way that they become bonded together,'' said Dr. Koss, now at the University of Arizona. ''They need a culture that supports treating women this way.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Koss said that, on a college campus, groups of men that might bond in this way and extoll this view of women would include fraternities and sports teams.</p>
        <p>Intensity of Groups</p>
        <p>Dr. Chris O'Sullivan of the psychology department at Bucknell University studied 26 sexual-assault incidents on campuses around the country that involved groups of men.</p>
        <p>''Most involved fraternities or athletic team members, football or basketball,'' Dr. O'Sullivan said. ''It usually occurs in a group of young men with a team spirit and usually living together. I think they end up relating to each other so intensely even their sexual experiences become shared.''</p>
        <p>But Len Elmore, a former pro basketball player, said the athlete should not be singled out for sexual-assault problems.</p>
        <p>''I believe that there should be more awareness, but no more than for other young men coming into sexual awareness,'' said Elmore, a lawyer and CBS basketball analyst. ''It's usually one strong personality who steps over the line and the others follow. I don't think you can separate this behavior from the athlete or the policeman or the construction worker.''</p>
        <p>Allegations Against Pros</p>
        <p>Reports of abuse by athletes have not been limited to college campuses. Several weeks ago, a 17-year-old girl alleged that four members of the Washington Capitals hockey team attacked her in a limousine following a team party after its elimination from the Stanley Cup playoffs. A grand jury is hearing the evidence, but the players have denied any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>The incident in Washington followed charges by a female student at St. John's University in Jamaica, Queens, that she was sexually assaulted in an off-campus residence by a group of students, five of them members of the university's lacrosse team.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Philip Fogliare, referred to the athletes as ''college jocks'' and contended that they had called in friends to watch. The athletes have been indicted on various sexual assault charges, but deny criminal activity.</p>
        <p>Many Incidents Unreported</p>
        <p>In another highly publicized case, four former football players from Glen Ridge (N.J.) High School, including twins who were the team's co-captains, have been indicted on charges that they sexually assaulted a mildly retarded girl while nine other young men watched or participated.</p>
        <p>These incidents are among at least 15 reported in the last year involving about 50 athletes at every level. The number of athletes who commit sexual assaults may be significantly greater, according to counselors and at least one survey, since many incidents remain unreported.</p>
        <p>A survey by Ms. magazine of 7,000 women conducted several years ago found that only 1 percent to 5 percent of all rape or molestation cases are reported. In the case of gang rape, the experts say, the percentage is probably lower.</p>
        <p>High-Profile Athletes</p>
        <p>Some counselors, as well as athletic officials, say that because of an athlete's high profile, charges against him become known more readily. The actual number involved is a very small percentage of the athletic population, they say.</p>
        <p>Michael J. Cleary, the executive director of the National Association of Collegiate Directors of Athletics, said of the recent cases: ''Not trying to brush it off, but I think because athletes are involved it received notoriety. If it followed a debating club meeting, it wouldn't receive the notice.''</p>
        <p>Dave Cawood, the assistant executive director of the National Collegiate Athletic Association, added: ''It's a major problem for higher education. But it's a concern the N.C.A.A. has no jurisdiction over. It's unfortunate that athletics bring focus to the problem that doesn't get noticed otherwise.''</p>
        <p>But many people believe that athletes, especially those in college and living in special dormitories for team members only, develop a sense of entitlement that is hard to counter.</p>
        <p>Ken Dryden, the lawyer, Cornell University graduate, and Hall of Fame goalie who played for the Montreal Canadiens, said, ''It's really a sense of power that comes from specialness, reputation, money, whether it's an athlete, businessman, or entertainer - anyone who finds himself at the center of the world they're in has a sense of impunity.''</p>
        <p>Matters of Controversy</p>
        <p>In recent years, several coaches created controversy by involving themselves in the defense of athletes who were charged with crimes involving sexual assaults.</p>
        <p>Lefty Driesell, the former basketball coach at the University of Maryland, was censured for telephoning a woman and asking her to drop charges she had brought against one of his players.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the present and former head basketball coaches at the University of Minnesota were disciplined for lying about fund-raising efforts to help one of their players who was charged with rape.</p>
        <p>And Bobby Knight, basketball coach at Indiana University, stirred a debate on that campus for a glib remark he made on rape.</p>
        <p>Trying to use an analogy, he told the broadcaster Connie Chung, who asked about stress, during a 1988 interview, ''I think that if rape is inevitable, relax and enjoy it.''</p>
        <p>Knight was censured by the university president, Thomas Ehrlich, who in turn was criticized by some students for jeopardizing the basketball program.</p>
        <p>Rape Awareness Program</p>
        <p>It is believed that the University of Rochester ran the first widespread program to heighten students' awareness of rape on campus. The athletic community played a major role.</p>
        <p>''About six years ago we became aware that students were arriving on campus with different value systems and we were finding that freshman women were being forced into situations,'' recalled Jody Asbury, the associate dean of students at the University of Rochester.</p>
        <p>''We found it happening more with fraternities and athletes,'' Asbury said. ''We asked who they listened to. It didn't make sense for me to talk to a fraternity. We decided to go for role models. I asked the head football coach, the women's track coach, the captain of the football team. I think we were the first university to do this in depth.''</p>
        <p>The football coach was Ray Tellier, who has since shifted to Columbia.</p>
        <p>''When we did work with athletes, the fact we were in an authority role got their attention,'' Tellier said. Did it work?  ''I think the goals of the program were to make them aware,'' he said. ''If we just accomplished that, it's a start.''</p>
        <p>Dilemma for Coaches</p>
        <p>But there is also a paradox in sensitivity training of athletes, said Dr. O'Sullivan.</p>
        <p>''I don't think an outsider can stop the athletes,'' she said. ''It has to come from within the group. But I see the dilemma of the coach. What he wants is for them to relate to each other intensely and he also wants them to be aggressive. Ideally, you get one guy from the group and train him. The trouble is that the guy most likely to be admired is the one most aggressive, and he may not be a candidate for this training.''</p>
        <p>But Doug Allen, former Penn State and Buffalo Bills linebacker and now the assistant executive director of the National Football League Players Association, said: ''An athlete's attitude toward women comes not from his sport, but from his life. Most players get cultural values from someplace other than teams.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernice Sandler, who says her 1985 study for the Association of American Colleges was the first report on gang rape in America, has investigated more than 100 cases. ''The tip of the iceberg,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sandler is concerned because not many schools have rape-prevention courses or seminars.</p>
        <p>When she learned of the recent charges involving athletes, she recalled, ''I thought, no difference. Same scenario.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
