<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Fare With Views of the Sound</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAPPORO (STRATFORD, CONN, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1538F930A35755C0A966958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Fare With Views of the Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WATERFRONT dining is at a premium in Connecticut, reason enough to savor the experience of Sapporo in Stratford. The Japanese restaurant, which faces Long Island Sound at the mouth of the Housatonic River, is at the very end of Sniffen Lane; Milford Point is directly across the water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WATERFRONT dining is at a premium in Connecticut, reason enough to savor the experience of Sapporo in Stratford. The Japanese restaurant, which faces Long Island Sound at the mouth of the Housatonic River, is at the very end of Sniffen Lane; Milford Point is directly across the water.</p>
        <p>WATERFRONT dining is at a premium in Connecticut, reason enough to savor the experience of Sapporo in Stratford. The Japanese restaurant, which faces Long Island Sound at the mouth of the Housatonic River, is at the very end of Sniffen Lane; Milford Point is directly across the water.</p>
        <p>Not content with a smashing waterside view through large windows in the rectangular main dining room, Sapporo has added a Japanese garden at the water's edge and an atrium. The indoor-outdoor effect is visually satisfying.</p>
        <p>There is no question about the restaurant's intended theme: rice-paper globe lanterns, shoji screen separators, six cozy tatami rooms for private dining at low Japanese-style tables and branches of artificial cherry blossoms are all reminders of Japan. Formerly the restaurant was called Tomiko's, with much the same decor but a quasi-Japanese menu.</p>
        <p>Sapporo's menu reinforces the theme, as does a small sushi bar in an interior room. Unfortunately, as the dishes begin to emerge from the kitchen, it becomes apparent that all is not what it at first seems. While the dishes are Japanese, the preparation of some of them has more than a hint of a Chinese accent, a reflection, perhaps, of the current ownership.</p>
        <p>Indisputably Japanese is the new sushi bar, which has a sushi chef in residence. While the selection of seafood for sashimi and sushi was limited to two or three fish plus smoked salmon, shrimp, octopus and eel, the various types of sushi were professionally prepared, though it was somewhat off-putting to see that the raw fish displayed had been pre-cut into individual pieces, thus reducing the prospects of maximum freshness. In fact, on one occasion, we found the sushi freshness to be borderline. And you may have to request gari, the pink pickled ginger in razor-thin slices that is an essential accompaniment to sushi. If you do so, ask for it in English; our Chinese waitress was unfamiliar with the Japanese name.</p>
        <p>As for the rest of the menu, you will do best if you order with care. Salmon teriyaki was a successful choice, with high-quality fresh salmon carefully broiled, even if the soy-based teriyaki sauce was added after the broiling, rather than applied in the marinade and basting process. Eel kabayaki, also broiled, was brushed with a soy-mirin (sweet sake) sauce, and it proved tasty, though it was served on a plate with stir-fried vegetables, instead of being presented on top of white rice in a bowl or lacquered box. Sukiyaki beef, though not prepared at tableside as tradition dictates, had a good mixture of glass noodles and vegetables and was another acceptable choice.</p>
        <p>Served with each entree were a small bowl of miso soup, a tangy ginger-dressed salad and a bowl of seasoned rice.</p>
        <p>The dish to avoid at all costs is tempura. Instead of the expected wispy light batter that makes Japanese tempura so ethereal, Sapporo uses a heavy, bready batter reminiscent of the casing that smothers shrimp puffs in many a Chinese restaurant. In an order of soft-shell crab tempura, the crab retained crunchiness, but the vegetables accompanying it were totally obfuscated by thick breading. In the regular tempura, it was difficult to unearth the shrimp; the doughy crust was so thick, and the greasy batter enveloping the broccoli, onion and other vegetables was similar to the thick wrapping around fried onion rings in short-order restaurants.</p>
        <p>As for appetizers, the best - excluding the sushi, which is available as a starter, entree or a la carte by the piece - was the buttery-smooth fresh bean curd, or tofu, called hiyadofu, served in squares either icy cold or hot. Either way, it was simple and excellent. Another prudent choice was yakitori, chicken bits broiled on matchstick-thin skewers. Gyoza, a Japanese spinoff of the Chinese fried dumplings called jao tzes, consisted of six warm dumplings, with bland minced-meat filling and wrappers wrinkled and tough from reheating or freezer burn.</p>
        <p>It is wise to skip desserts altogether. The choices consisted of chocolate cake and fried bananas. The latter were subjected to the same heavy batter treatment as the tempura and were undercooked, doughy and pale in color.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averaged $23 a person recently, with tax, tip and beverages extra. There is no charge for the view, and on an early summer evening, it is a knockout - so serene and tranquil it makes Sapporo well worth the caution required to order carefully.</p>
        <p>SAPPORO</p>
        <p>Satisfactory</p>
        <p>520 Sniffen Lane, Stratford (off Main Street, between Short Beach and Access Roads). 375-3986.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Japanese lanterns, shoji screens, gardens, private mat rooms and one of the state's most appealing waterside dining sites.</p>
        <p>Service: Cheerful but lacking knowledge about the cuisine.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Hiyadofu; yakitori; sushi; sukiyaki; eel kabayaki; salmon teriyaki.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch entrees $4.75 to $12.95; dinner entrees $11.50 to $18.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: American Express, Mastercard, Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: 11 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. Monday through Friday; 4:30 to 9:30 P.M. Monday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Accepted.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Five steps at entrance.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
