<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tracking a Tale of Violence Into the Everglades</title>
    <meta content="24Footsteps" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/24/travel/24Footsteps.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1813967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTSTEPS: PETER MATTHIESSEN'S FLORIDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chokoloskee (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ten Thousand Islands (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthiessen, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Footsteps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Everglades National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Thousand Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Everglades National Park</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D91331F937A15751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="2064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tracking a Tale of Violence Into the Everglades</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Peter Matthiessen’s Florida: Tracking a Tale of Violence Into the Everglades</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Schneider travel article on visit to Ten Thousand Islands and Chokoloskee, Fla, setting for three historical novels about serial killer by Peter Matthiessen; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEAR the end of ''Bone by Bone,'' the final volume of Peter Matthiessen's trilogy of historical novels tracing the brutal life and violent death of a reluctant serial killer in frontier Florida, the protagonist drives his boat in circles somewhere near Pavilion Key. He's not lost in any geographical sense; after decades of living in Ten Thousand Islands, Ed Watson knows precisely where he is on the planet. But having finally run out of options, he can't make up his mind where he wants to go.</p>
        <p>So he doubles back and doubles back again, lost in indecision, before winding up in Chokoloskee, where the townsfolk have finally had enough of his killing his sugar-cane workers at the end of the season instead of paying them. The townsfolk gun him down in his own personal ''Watson payday.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Visiting an oozy corner of Florida where the brutal life and violent death of a reluctant serial killer are retold in the author’s trilogy of historical novels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEAR the end of ''Bone by Bone,'' the final volume of Peter Matthiessen's trilogy of historical novels tracing the brutal life and violent death of a reluctant serial killer in frontier Florida, the protagonist drives his boat in circles somewhere near Pavilion Key. He's not lost in any geographical sense; after decades of living in Ten Thousand Islands, Ed Watson knows precisely where he is on the planet. But having finally run out of options, he can't make up his mind where he wants to go.</p>
        <p>So he doubles back and doubles back again, lost in indecision, before winding up in Chokoloskee, where the townsfolk have finally had enough of his killing his sugar-cane workers at the end of the season instead of paying them. The townsfolk gun him down in his own personal ''Watson payday.''</p>
        <p>This is not exactly the kind of romantic literary image one might expect would draw travelers to this oozy corner of Florida, where the great and endangered River of Grass that is the world's only everglades gives way to the Gulf of Mexico in a maze of mangrove islands and mysterious shallow bays. Not the way, say, ''Tender Is the Night'' might lure you to the South of France, or even, for that matter, the way Mr. Matthiessen's own masterful ''Snow Leopard'' has inspired pilgrims to the Himalayas. Still, there is something about his telling and retelling, and finally re-retelling of the Watson story in the three books -- ''Killing Mr. Watson,'' ''Lost Man's River'' and ''Bone by Bone'' -- that makes some fans want to drive on past Fort Myers to the end of the road and then get into a small boat and go on even a bit farther.</p>
        <p>The people of Chokoloskee don't quite call it ''the book,'' the way the Chamber of Commerce and others in Savannah are said to refer to John Berendt's ''Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil.'' But if you ask enough questions about Watson there, particularly at the old Smallwood store, site of vigilante justice and now a marvelous museum of old times on the islands, you're likely to draw a knowing nod.</p>
        <p>The locals have seen your type before, mixing in among the sport fishermen and eco-paddlers who frequent Chokoloskee and nearby Everglades City. They may not entirely understand your goals, but they're happy to rent out a canoe and point you toward the far shore, with its tidal-river mouths leading into the heart of the maze.</p>
        <p>In our case, we stopped on our way south in the former cattleman's town of Arcadia, where Watson was once deputized and sent out to kill a local bully. ''For a few years in the early nineties, the range wars around Arcadia beat anything the Wild West had to offer,'' says Mr. Matthiessen's Watson, who's on the lam from prison in Arkansas at the time. ''With so many rough men in the saloons, a man could get his fill of fighting any time he wanted, and be lulled to sleep at night by the pop of gunfire.''</p>
        <p>Today, the few blocks that constitute the historic section of Arcadia still have an Old West look and feel, but the saloons and whorehouses have been replaced by dozens of antiques stores. ''Used to be a cow town,'' the proprietor of one explained as she made change for some vintage post cards of Old Miami Beach, ''then it was a phosphate town and now it's an antique town.''</p>
        <p>We also swung through Fort Myers, where Watson's daughter married the local banker and soon became too ashamed of her father's reputation for murder to let him in the house, and where the mega-developments in progress on the outskirts of town are evidence that Florida is still, in many ways, the land of grand speculators of the sort that Watson both hated and emulated.</p>
        <p>Eventually, like Watson, we ran out of other places to go and ended up at Chokoloskee. The village, which still shows signs of the direct hit it took from Hurricane Wilma in 2005, sits on a giant mound of shells that was piled up by the Calusa Indians who lived in the vicinity for at least 2,000 years before the Spanish arrived in the early 1500s. ''Them redskins set there shucking a good long while, to fling a forty-acre shell pile over their shoulders,'' a character in ''Killing Mr. Watson'' says of a mound nearby.</p>
        <p>Though connected by a causeway to Everglades City and the mainland, Chokoloskee remains, as it has been for millenniums, a place of boats. There are boats on trailers, boats on docks, boats on car tops, boats under tarps and boats in pieces on the ground.</p>
        <p>Terrestrial housing appears to be largely an afterthought, much of it capable of being driven away as the next storm approaches. Nonetheless, looking back at the town over our shoulders as it disappeared behind the first curve of mangroves, the place looked like a gleaming metropolis.</p>
        <p>Then, with a few strokes of the paddle and gentle push from the rising tide, Chokoloskee was gone and there was nowhere to look but at the territory ahead. Nowhere to look, that is, but down at the compass, and up at the coast, and down at the waterproof chart and the hand-held G.P.S., and up at the coast, and down at the chart.</p>
        <p>''Just don't forget to keep track of where you are on that map as you go along and you'll be fine,'' said the friendly equipment kid from the Ivey House Bed &amp; Breakfast in Everglades City, were we rented the canoe, a big raccoon-proof five-gallon jug for fresh water, and miscellaneous camping gear. ''If you forget to check and just paddle for a couple of hours, that's when you'll look down and say, 'Where the heck are we?' ''</p>
        <p>Where the heck, indeed? It takes a few hours for the rhythm of paddling to work its way up your arms into your brain, so that you are fully engaged in the journey at hand. Or perhaps it's the reverse: hours must pass before the busy little distractions of life on land leak out through your palms and run down to the tip of the paddle and trail away behind the boat. Whichever it is, by the time we had our lunch of cheese and pita on an exposed sand bar in the company of a colony of egrets and an asocial pelican, we had stopped wondering what possessed us to go see the Watson Place and were glad to be out in the big world.</p>
        <p>PUSHING a canoe through Ten Thousand Islands and the Everglades Wilderness Waterway feels at times like a metaphor for a journey through a complicated mind, or through Mr. Matthiessen's books. There are openings in the coast, and like ideas or schemes, the largest and most promising of them often lead to dead ends. They are full of jumping fish and perhaps some strange birds, and in one case a dead manatee attended by a flock of buzzards. Worth a look, maybe, but there is no healthy way out of these places but to backtrack.</p>
        <p>''It,'' says Watson of his violent demon. ''I've tried over and over to find words for this It. I don't know how. It is just there, it is always there behind my brain, ringing and intense. Like death in life. The one hope was to seize it quick, meet its force and twist that force back upon itself, before it unraveled beyond reach.''</p>
        <p>Other openings are modest, only worth entering because the map promises they will circuitously lead where you want to go. Or at least to a resting place like the Sunday Bay chickee, where we pitched our tent on a platform in the middle of the water, boiled our evening tea and watched the sun go down. The first hours of darkness belonged to the mosquitoes that drove some of Watson's women nearly out of their minds and drove us to our tent. But later,when the coolness had driven the hordes off, the miraculous trailing flares of swimming fish as they set off bioluminescent organisms were like underwater fireworks.</p>
        <p>The Watson Place, when we eventually got there, was suitably eerie. Not much more than a clearing on the edge of a great curve in the Chatham River, there is little today to suggest that anyone tried to build an empire here. The rusting remains of an old one-cylinder make-and-brake steam engine, a cauldron that Watson presumably used to boil his cane syrup, a cistern and a few other pieces of iron are all that remain.</p>
        <p>That, and the lingering reputation. As we pitched our tent a pair of unshaven fishermen stopped for a late lunch in the meager shade. While one spread peanut butter on a piece of bologna with his finger -- ''Oh hell, where's that knife when you need it?'' -- the other called out to offer us a can of beer and ask if we knew anything about the 50 graves of Watson's victims that were never found. We thought 50 might be high, but merely nodded. Lunch over, they shoved off in their absurdly overloaded aluminum boat and puttered on in search of snook, while we decided that if there was any more to see in the dense thicket that had taken over the rest of the 40-acre farm, we were certainly not the people to push into it to look.</p>
        <p>But the Watson Place is also where a quartet of dolphins came down the river in the late afternoon, lolling and playing and letting us know they were on their way with blows of mist that could be heard while they were still around the corner. And it's where a dozen cheerful teenagers paddled up in war canoes, and laughed on into the evening while their counselor kept promising the food was on the way. It's also where, in the quietest moment of the dawn, a rare American crocodile slid down the river just a few feet off of the dock. With Watson long gone, life goes on at Chatham Bend.</p>
        <p>''Then the bend was gone, and the Watson Place, the past and future,'' says Watson near the end of his life, when he leaves for the last time. ''Ahead was the endless falling of the river to the sea, and the lonesome mangrove clumps of the salt estuary, and the horizon where dark high clouds of drought surveyed the battered coast and empty Gulf.''</p>
        <p>His world was closing in. For us, though, sliding down the Chatham River not far behind the rare croc, the sudden appearance of the sea around a mangrove had the feeling of the whole world opening up. The Gulf of Mexico was blue to the horizon and the sky was bluer above. Dolphins were there, perhaps waiting for a change of tide. And farther on toward the long beach campground at Pavilion Key, we spotted a manatee or two, alive enough to look at us until they caught us looking back at them. Then, with a splash, they were gone.</p>
        <p>NAVIGATING AROUND THE MANGROVES</p>
        <p>You will need a permit from the National Park Service to camp at the Watson Place or any of the 46 other backcountry sites in the Everglades and Ten Thousand Islands. They must be applied for in person at the Flamingo or Gulf Coast Visitor Centers either the day before or the day of your trip and cost $10 a permit and $2 a person a night (www.nps.gov/ever, 239-695-3092 or 2945).</p>
        <p>Once you get to Everglades City, you'll need a boat and paddles, which can be rented along with other gear from North American Canoe Tours (www.evergladesadventures.com). It's at the Ivey House (www.iveyhouse.com, 239-695-3299; rooms starting from $70 and $140), which has an inn and a rustic lodge. It is a fine place to eat and sleep the nights before or after your trip.</p>
        <p>Hemingway, John Wayne, and five presidents have stayed at the Rod &amp; Gun Club (239-695-2101; rooms are $140).</p>
        <p>Over at Chockoloskee, don't miss the creamy crab chowder with cornbread on the side ($6.50) at Big House Coffee (238 Mamie Street, 239-695-3633).</p>
        <p>Lastly, you can have your mosquito bites mudpacked at the Everglade Spa &amp; Lodge in the beautiful old Bank of Everglades building in Everglades City (www.evergladesspa.com, 239-695-1006; starting at $65).</p>
        <p>FOOTSTEPS: PETER MATTHIESSEN'S FLORIDA PAUL SCHNEIDER is the author of ''Brutal Journey'' (Henry Holt, 2006), about a 16th-century Spanish expedition into Florida.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">PAUL SCHNEIDER is the author of ''Brutal Journey'' (Henry Holt, 2006), about a 16th-century Spanish expedition into Florida.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
