<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Ringside Seat For Murrow Versus McCarthy</title>
    <meta content="18carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/18/movies/18carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1703018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Communism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Communism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House Un-American Activities Committee</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS News</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clooney, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Murrow, Edward R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Strathairn, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Murrow, Edward R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCarthy, Joseph R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Friendly, Fred W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDE1131F93BA2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Ringside Seat For Murrow Versus McCarthy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Ringside Seat for Murrow Versus McCarthy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the success of ''Ocean's Eleven'' and ''Ocean's Twelve,'' George Clooney's Danny Ocean has become the king of the caper, a guy who finds a tiny weakness in the system and exploits it for his own ends. But even Danny would have to marvel at Mr. Clooney's most recent second-story job. Using the leverage of his stardom and the connections developed over his years in the business, Mr. Clooney has actually managed to make and distribute a black-and-white film about issues of historic and civic moment. ''Ocean's Thirteen'' it ain't.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clooney is the co-writer, the director and a star of ''Good Night, and Good Luck,'' about a seminal moment in the life of Edward R. Murrow, the revered CBS journalist who arguably did more than anyone else to establish television as a serious news outlet. Set in 1953, it focuses on Murrow's ferocious battle with Senator Joseph R. McCarthy, network sponsors and even his employers as he tries to expose the tactics of the House Un-American Activities Committee. The movie, which will open the New York Film Festival on Friday, is set to be released on Oct. 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With "Good Night, and Good Luck," about a seminal moment in the life of Edward R. Murrow, George Clooney directs a close-up look at an epic fight in the struggle over American democracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the success of ''Ocean's Eleven'' and ''Ocean's Twelve,'' George Clooney's Danny Ocean has become the king of the caper, a guy who finds a tiny weakness in the system and exploits it for his own ends. But even Danny would have to marvel at Mr. Clooney's most recent second-story job. Using the leverage of his stardom and the connections developed over his years in the business, Mr. Clooney has actually managed to make and distribute a black-and-white film about issues of historic and civic moment. ''Ocean's Thirteen'' it ain't.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clooney is the co-writer, the director and a star of ''Good Night, and Good Luck,'' about a seminal moment in the life of Edward R. Murrow, the revered CBS journalist who arguably did more than anyone else to establish television as a serious news outlet. Set in 1953, it focuses on Murrow's ferocious battle with Senator Joseph R. McCarthy, network sponsors and even his employers as he tries to expose the tactics of the House Un-American Activities Committee. The movie, which will open the New York Film Festival on Friday, is set to be released on Oct. 7.</p>
        <p>A hermetic, gimlet-eyed look at a rare time in American life when even lawful citizens quaked before their government, ''Good Night'' is certainly a worthy undertaking, but that hardly guaranteed it would be produced. Its only special effect is its knitting of archival television and contemporary filmed reconstruction into a believable narrative.</p>
        <p>''No one is encouraging me or anyone else to do things that aren't going to make any money,'' Mr. Clooney said, speaking recently by telephone from his home in Italy. ''On the other hand, 20 years from now, you want to be able to say to people that you stood for something besides your own career.''</p>
        <p>''Good Night'' is about journalism, not as a subject of parody, but of inquiry. With various reporters and news anchors splashing into fetid waters to save victims of Hurricane Katrina, ''Good Night'' serves as a reminder that it may take a different kind of journalistic courage, a willingness to risk career and more, to bring government to account. At a time when the news media are being denied access to everything from pictures of imprisoned foreign nationals to critical government security documents, Mr. Clooney, without pressing the analogy, has made a movie that reminds that government needs a vigorous, even oppositional press to find its best nature.</p>
        <p>Like Murrow's reports, the $8 million film, distributed by Warner Independent Pictures, uses McCarthy's own words to demonstrate that his stated effort to save the United States from Communist infiltration was itself a far more insidious threat. And this is not the first time that Mr. Clooney has delved into cold-war dynamics in search of contemporary resonance: in 2000, he was an executive producer and a star of a live broadcast of ''Fail Safe,'' the cautionary tale about how fear can metastasize into destruction.</p>
        <p>In ''Good Night,'' David Strathairn renders Murrow as a reluctant hero, and a twitchy, dark one at that. His Murrow, with the fatalism of Eeyore, is a journalist who reflexively expects the worst, but responds by doing his best, steeling those around him even as McCarthy's gun sights are trained on his forehead.</p>
        <p>''There is always something ticking with Murrow,'' Mr. Strathairn said in a telephone interview. ''He was described as a prince of doom, a man carrying a crown of thorns. I tried to show what was going on in his head.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clooney, the son of a broadcaster and a college journalism dropout himself, is on screen as Fred W. Friendly, the Murrow producer who eventually became president of CBS News. But as a director, Mr. Clooney was preoccupied with coming up with portraits of Murrow and McCarthy that were both vivid and truthful.</p>
        <p>''There has been a lot of revisionist history about McCarthy,'' Mr. Clooney said, pointing to ''Treason,'' a 2003 book by Ann Coulter that suggested that McCarthy was mostly right about Murrow's supposed Communist sympathies. ''In the same way that Murrow did, I wanted to use McCarthy in his own words.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clooney seems to be the one Big Star, give or take a Bono, who has managed to have his cake and credibility, too. His 2003 HBO series, ''K Street'' -- made with Steven Soderbergh, who serves as an executive producer on ''Good Night'' as well -- was not a great success, but it did peel back the covers on Washington. He has also put in significant time on international debt relief and has plans to build a retro Las Vegas casino that will dedicate 25 percent of its profits to charity.</p>
        <p>''He paid a lot of dues to get where he is, and now there are a lot of doors open to him,'' Mr. Strathairn said. ''The one he has chosen to walk through throws down a gauntlet. He has the good luck, the charm and the guts to do what he wants, and this film is what he chose to do.''</p>
        <p>But his ability to wear stardom as a loose garment -- People magazine might as well forgo the suspense over its Sexiest Man Alive feature until Mr. Clooney starts to grow ear hair -- obscures a serious film wonk within. His 2002 directorial debut, ''Confessions of a Dangerous Mind,'' a movie that took the game show host Chuck Barris at his word that he was also once a Central Intelligence Agency hit man, left many scratching their heads, but little doubt that Mr. Clooney, who has a reputation as a prankster, is plenty serious behind the camera. And when he first got started on ''Good Night,'' in search of an urgent, documentary feel, he tried, without success, to hunt down the exact lenses Godard used in his 16-millimeter films. In conversation, he riffs about film stocks, the documentary aesthetic and the exigencies of contemporary moviemaking.</p>
        <p>Having made the judgment that no actor could convey McCarthy's banal, relentless menace, Mr. Clooney was determined to portray him exclusively with archival shots -- he has joked about taking out an ad in the trade publications at Oscar time to push the nomination of McCarthy as best supporting actor -- and in his mind, it followed that the rest of the feature should be shot in black and white as well. The result is a film that looks like a better, scary version of early television, a kinescope to the past.</p>
        <p>''Good Night'' never reaches for the present in arch or ungainly ways, which is partly what makes it seem less like propaganda and more like a movie. Even though civil liberties advocates have sounded alarms over the current effort to strengthen the Patriot Act, Mr. Clooney said he did not set out to construct an allegory.</p>
        <p>''This is a movie about broadcast journalism and its responsibilities, which I think have been shirked,'' he said. ''I think a good many people would admit that they dropped the ball. This is a reminder of what is possible. It has been a passion of mine -- my father was an anchorman for 25 years, and Murrow was his hero, and, by proxy, mine.''</p>
        <p>Murrow, a war hero in his own right, recognized McCarthyism as a domestic echo of Nazism. In the events depicted in ''Good Night,'' he -- along with Friendly and the reporter Joe Wershba -- investigates the investigator, questioning why McCarthy is able to destroy people's careers by merely suggesting that they have ties to the Communist Party. In particular, he asks why Milo Radulovich, a Michigan meteorologist with no apparent taint of Communist involvement, has been kicked out of the Air Force as a security risk. Along the way, Murrow plays peek-a-boo with his wavering network executives, goading them into continuing to support ''See It Now,'' his news program, by not telling them what comes next. William S. Paley, chairman of CBS, takes the heat, albeit screaming bloody murder along the way.</p>
        <p>''I think it has a lot of resonance to today, both in terms of what is going on with the government and what is going on in the media,'' said Shirley Wershba, a former CBS producer and a consultant on the film with Mr. Wershba, her husband. ''It brought back great and horrible memories for both of us.''</p>
        <p>Many others were asked for opinions as well, including David Friendly, a film producer and the son of Fred W. Friendly, who died in 1998. ''I think it was a bold choice to make it in black and white, to integrate the actual hearings, not for a haughty, artistic reason, but so that the movie feels real,'' he said. ''This is a story about a specific moment in time, when there was terror in the room. And I think the movie really captures it. My brother and I saw it with Milo Radulovich, and he came up to us and put his arms around us and cried. He said that my dad was a hero.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clooney has an odd relationship with the press -- he reveres its role, but has been a victim of some of its less noble reflexes. (He has been a persistent critic of out-of-hand paparazzi even as he has defended their right to do their job.)</p>
        <p>''In this and all the rest of journalism, I think the issues are complicated,'' he said. ''I don't think that there are truly bad guys or truly good guys. If you look at Paley, he is in a very complex situation. He was getting clobbered, but he was also enjoying all the notoriety that Murrow was bringing CBS. There is always a split in these things, but hopefully the need for entertainment does not push news off the screen.''</p>
        <p>Murrow said as much in a famous speech he gave at the Radio-Television News Directors Association annual meeting in 1958. Part of the speech, a reminder that television should and could produce important journalism, closes the film:</p>
        <p>''To those who say people wouldn't look; they wouldn't be interested; they're too complacent, indifferent and insulated, I can only reply: there is, in one reporter's opinion, considerable evidence against that contention. But even if they are right, what have they got to lose?</p>
        <p>''Because if they are right, and this instrument is good for nothing but to entertain, amuse and insulate, then the tube is flickering now and we will soon see that the whole struggle is lost.</p>
        <p>''This instrument can teach, it can illuminate; yes, and it can even inspire. But it can do so only to the extent that humans are determined to use it to those ends. Otherwise, it is merely wires and lights in a box.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
