<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>John J. McMullen Dies at 87; Ex-Owner of Devils and Astros</title>
    <meta content="18mcmullen" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/18/sports/18mcmullen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1703283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">John J. McMullen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Houston Astros</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED91F31F93BA2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>John J. McMullen Dies at 87; Ex-Owner of Devils and Astros</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">John J. McMullen Dies at 87; Ex-Owner of Devils and Astros</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD GOLDSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John J. McMullen, who brought the National Hockey League to New Jersey in 1982, then presided over Devils teams that won two Stanley Cup championships, died Friday at his home in Montclair, N.J. He was 87.</p>
        <p>His death was announced by the Devils.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John J. McMullen brought the National Hockey League to New Jersey in 1982, then presided over Devils teams that won two Stanley Cup championships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John J. McMullen, who brought the National Hockey League to New Jersey in 1982, then presided over Devils teams that won two Stanley Cup championships, died Friday at his home in Montclair, N.J. He was 87.</p>
        <p>His death was announced by the Devils.</p>
        <p>McMullen, a career naval officer who founded a marine engineering firm after leaving military service, turned to the sporting world in the early 1970's. He became a limited partner in the group headed by George Steinbrenner that purchased the Yankees from CBS, but he famously remarked that ''nothing is as limited as being a limited partner of George's.''</p>
        <p>A far larger role in sports ownership arrived for McMullen in 1979, when he became the owner of baseball's Houston Astros.</p>
        <p>In 1982, McMullen bought the Denver-based Colorado Rockies, a floundering hockey franchise, and moved them to the Meadowlands. Renamed the Devils, the team operated in its early years in the shadow of the Rangers and perhaps the Islanders as well, but it went on to win the N.H.L. championship in 1995 and 2000 under McMullen.</p>
        <p>John Joseph McMullen, a native of Jersey City, graduated from the United States Naval Academy in 1940, served in combat during World War II and retired from military service in 1954 with the rank of commander.</p>
        <p>He founded John J. McMullen Associates, an international firm of naval architects and marine engineers, in 1959, and acquired Norton Lilly International, a shipping agency, in 1972, operating it until 2002. He was president and chief executive of the United States Lines from 1968 to 1971.</p>
        <p>He received a Master of Science degree from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and a doctorate in mechanical engineering from the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich.</p>
        <p>McMullen was part of an investment group that bought the Astros from the Ford Motor Credit Corporation in the summer of 1979 for an estimated $13 million. The next season, the Astros won a division title for the first time in their 19-year history and drew a club-record attendance of almost 2.3 million to the Astrodome.</p>
        <p>But McMullen came under sharp criticism for dismissing Tal Smith as the club president early in his ownership, and the Astros never won a pennant under him. They did complete smart deals bringing in Jeff Bagwell, Steve Finley and Curt Schilling, and many Astros players remained close to McMullen after he sold the team. He gave Bob Watson an executive position that led to his becoming general manager of the Astros in October 1993. Watson was the lone African-American at the time to hold such a post.</p>
        <p>McMullen sold the Astros to Drayton McLane Jr. in 1992. By then, the Devils were on their way to becoming a leading N.H.L. franchise after the hiring of Lou Lamoriello as general manager in the late 1980's. The Rangers, though, remained in the spotlight with their marquee home, Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''The Rangers are in the most dominant position of any New York team from the standpoint of fan base and adoration,'' McMullen told Dave Anderson of The New York Times in April 2000, when the Devils were en route to their second Stanley Cup title. ''I've had to live in their shadow all this time.''</p>
        <p>But the Devils flourished that season with a $37.6 million payroll compared with the Rangers' payroll of $61.2 million for a team that did not make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Having spent about $30 million to buy his N.H.L. franchise, McMullen sold the Devils to the YankeeNets organization for $176 million in the summer of 2000 after being unable to obtain state assistance toward building a new arena in Hoboken.</p>
        <p>In his final months as the Devils' owner, McMullen looked beyond pro sports in assessing the franchise's impact.</p>
        <p>''I think our legacy is the proliferation of junior hockey in New Jersey,'' he said. ''I think more kids under 15 can name more Devils players than they can any other professional team in this area.''</p>
        <p>McMullen is survived by his wife, Jacqueline; his sons, Peter and John Jr.; a daughter, Catherine McMullen; and five grandchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
