<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About Cars</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHUON, MARSHALL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D71F3AF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About Cars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Schuon;
&lt;br&gt;
Oldsmobile's Line of 'Trucks'</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A truck from Oldsmobile?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A truck from Oldsmobile?</p>
        <p>A truck from Oldsmobile?</p>
        <p>Well, yes. Olds used to sell trucks. And if you look it up in the Standard Catalog of American Light Duty Trucks from Krause Publications of Iola, Wis., you will find such gems as a commercial version of the 1904 curved-dash Olds and that other hot-ticket item, the Economy Canopied Express, meant for vending fruits and vegetables.</p>
        <p>True, the last of those came off the line 66 years ago. And, true, Oldsmobile's best-selling truck was a 1920 model. True, too, the 1990 version is only sort of a truck. But it surely isn't a car.</p>
        <p>Olds calls it a Silhouette, and it is one of three new vans from General Motors, the others being the Chevrolet Lumina APV (for all-purpose vehicle) and Pontiac's Trans Sport. They roll like peas off the same conveyor belt at Tarrytown, N.Y., and the big difference between them is their equipment and resultant window stickers.</p>
        <p>These vans are straight out of the space age, with beautiful plastic bodies over steel frames, a la the sadly defunct Pontiac Fiero. They have fuel-injected V6 engines, front-wheel drive, acres of windshield, and a profile that would do a monorail proud.</p>
        <p>Silhouette is, in fact, the most apt of names for a design that Oldsmobile would like to think is one giant step for van-kind.</p>
        <p>Swoopy and innovative as it is, one might question its effect on sales of conventional Olds station wagons. Obviously, the question has occurred to Oldsmobile's brass, but the division's general marketing manager, Michael Grimaldi, said he is confident in his brave new world.</p>
        <p>''There is a stable group of buyers out there who want the traditional station wagon,'' he said, noting that Olds will continue to offer its midsize and fullsize wagons, the Cutlass Cruiser and Custom Cruiser. ''But the minivan market has exploded. Sales now are about 800,000 a year, and we see that growing to a million or more in the 90's.''</p>
        <p>For this first year of the decade, Olds hopes to sell 30,000 Silhouettes, and Grimaldi was frank about the lack of outward difference among the three G.M. minivans.</p>
        <p>''What we are offering is a fully equipped van, a leading entry in the upscale market,'' he said. That means a vehicle with a base price of $17,195 and a high end approaching $20,000.</p>
        <p>The standard van has two bucket seats aft and a middle bench that seats three. The more expensive tester, maroon with matching leather interior, had four buckets in back. Leather was a $650 option and then there was the ''touring'' suspension that cost $232. What with other items, it added up to a take-home price of $19,587.</p>
        <p>From the side, the Silhouette features a smooth upper surface that sweeps from front bumper to the trailing edge of the roof. The windshield is raked at a 66-degree angle, and the clean exterior produces a very low .30 coefficient of drag.</p>
        <p>The windshield measures 17.25 square feet, about a third larger than a full-size sedan's, and that creates problems at the same time that it produces fuel-saving aerodynamics and space-capsule good looks. For one thing, it could easily have meant an interior for growing orchids.</p>
        <p>The hothouse problem was headed off with a layer of metallic film embedded in the glass to reduce solar rays by about 60 percent. But the effort to create some sort of sensible interior was less successful, and the sheer sprawl of the dash is the thing that gives pause to every first-time occupant.</p>
        <p>Behind the wheel, you stare out at a 3-foot-deep plain of matte black, and the thought occurs that it is totally wasted space - and space that will be very hard to clean. What doesn't occur at first glance - but what becomes painfully obvious the first time that you drive into the sun - is the size of the vents needed to defrost so much glass. The vents reflect perfectly on the inside of the windshield and create large blind spots.</p>
        <p>Then there was the way the van felt on the road.</p>
        <p>Even with the optional larger wheels and stiffer suspension, the Silhouette wallows. It nibbles this way and that. It feels top-heavy and it behaves even worse than most vans, which generally are no great shakes in the handling department.</p>
        <p>The problem is not peculiar to Oldsmobile, however, and I know that because I had the same difficulty with a preproduction Pontiac Trans Sport last year. At the time, I forgave the bad manners because it was a hand-built prototype. But it is hard to forgive in a production model.</p>
        <p>Still, the Silhouette cruises easily at 65 or 70 on smooth pavement, and its 120-horsepower engine makes it economical, if not quick off the mark. The roofline is low enough to make it suitable for most garages, and the seats, which weigh only 34 pounds, are easy to remove when you want to carry cargo instead of cronies.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to one more complaint - one that this time can't be made.</p>
        <p>For years, I have grumbled about cars that have no place to put coffee cups. But the Silhouette's seatbacks fold to create trays, each with two cupholders. There are, further, dual cupholders in a dashboard tray, two cupholders molded into the glovebox lid and twin cupholders in the left rear wheelhousing, meaning that the Olds van offers accomodation for 14 cups and cans.</p>
        <p>In a six-passenger vehicle, that satisfies even me.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
