<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A SOFT FOCUS ON A SHARP CONFLICT HAS ITS RISKS</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="TV VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUKAS, J ANTHONY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">COMMON GROUND (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">COMMON GROUND (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D9113AF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A SOFT FOCUS ON A SHARP CONFLICT HAS ITS RISKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Even a generally first-rate television production can leave the impression of an opportunity missed - especially when the focus in on the extraordinarily urgent subject of racial tensions in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Even a generally first-rate television production can leave the impression of an opportunity missed - especially when the focus in on the extraordinarily urgent subject of racial tensions in the United States.</p>
        <p>Even a generally first-rate television production can leave the impression of an opportunity missed - especially when the focus in on the extraordinarily urgent subject of racial tensions in the United States.</p>
        <p>Issued only two months before the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. was assassinated in 1968, the Kerner Commission report warned: ''Our nation is moving toward two societies, one black, one white - separate and unequal.'' Of all the subsequent events that would reinforce this bleak fact, none was more vividly unsettling than the eruption of violence in Boston in the mid-1970's when court-ordered busing was imposed to facilitate the desegregation of public schools. Generating international headlines, the story as covered by television, always hungry for powerful visuals, generally tended to pit angry, sometimes ferocious whites against frightened black schoolchildren. The culprit was racism, pure and simple. The reality, of course, was far more complicated and messy.</p>
        <p>The sprawling story was chronicled brilliantly by the journalist J. Anthony Lukas in his Pulitzer Prize-winning 1985 book ''Common Ground: A Turbulent Decade in the Lives of Three American Families.'' The families were the Irish-Catholic McGoffs, the black Twymons and the Yankee Divers. Devoting alternating chapters to each, Mr. Lukas traced their roots back to the 18th and 19th centuries, in the process painstakingly fleshing out a portrait of the entire city of Boston. The families were not selected as statistical averages or norms. The author was simply impressed with their ''special intensity.'' In a prefatory note, Mr. Lukas wrote that ''the more time I spent with them, the harder it became to assign easy labels of guilt or virtue.''</p>
        <p>Now adapted for television, with a script by Edward Hume (''The Day After''), the two-part ''Common Ground'' is being presented on CBS tonight and Tuesday, from 9 to 11 each night. The director is Michael Newell. Here, certainly, was an opportunity for a mini-series that would capture both the scope and incisive detail of the book. And indeed, ''Common Ground'' started out as a seven-hour project, only to be cut back finally to four hours (or, minus commercials, about three hours and 15 minutes).</p>
        <p>The character of upscale Colin Diver (Richard Thomas), the idealistic Harvard Law graduate whose integration efforts include moving his family to the racially mixed and harshly eye-opening South End section of Boston, is almost reduced to a walk-on. Overall, the condensed version of the story - much of it filmed in Toronto because of Boston's nervousness with the project - has its moments of power, thanks to a strikingly capable cast, and many of the book's major themes and insights can be caught in bits of dialogue, if you listen carefully.</p>
        <p>In Part Two, for instance, the frustrated Mr. Diver, who once saw the ''American dilemma'' in exclusively racial and legal terms, tells an increasingly waffling Mayor Kevin White (James Farentino) that the ''real issue'' is the separation of rich and poor, locked together. ''Those who can afford it, get out,'' he says. As Robert Coles put it in a 1974 interview: Working-class whites and blacks are ''both competing for a very limited piece of the pie, the limits of which are being set by the larger limits of class, which allow them damn little, if anything.'' Even Mr. Diver ends up moving his family to the affluent suburbs (today he is dean of the University of Pennsylvania Law School).</p>
        <p>Obviously more comfortable with personal angles and emotional payoffs, television's ''Common Ground'' focuses on the McGoffs and Twymons. The widowed Alice McGoff, played with perfect Boston Irish shadings by Jane Curtin, struggles to raise her seven children in a Charlestown housing project. The divorced Rachel Twymon, captured in yet another wonderful performance by C. C. H. Pounder, lives with her six children in the mostly black neighborhood of Roxbury. Each woman wants only what she thinks is best for her children. But caught up in the busing controversy, which will bring Rachel's daughter Cassandra (Erika Alexander) to Charlestown's high school, they find themselves being reduced to easy stereotypes.</p>
        <p>Predictably, the film manages to find uplifting moments. Reluctantly entering a school variety show, Cassandra gets a standing ovation from the predominantly white audience for singing ''Reach Out, I'll Be There'' (actually she took second prize for ''You Are My Shining Star''). And as class president, Alice's daughter Lisa (Georgia Emelin), having put her outspoken bigotry behind her, makes a graduation speech - embellished in the film - imploring parents and children to ''care about that person beside you.'' Like those schools that had earlier objected to black students hearing the ''negative'' poetry of Langston Hughes, television entertainment is intent on accentuating what it considers the positive. The conclusion of ''Common Ground'' does manage to be restrained as Cassandra wonders aloud: ''Better off? I don't know. Maybe it will be better for those who come after us. I hope so.''</p>
        <p>In short, Mr. Lukas's monumental study has been reduced to a skeletal outline, in the end telling the viewer not much more than could have been learned about the same events in a half-hour review carried on the public-TV documentary series ''Eyes on the Prize II.'' The Diver family was only one victim of all the chopping and snipping. Virtually eliminated from the screen treatment are Louise Day Hicks, the unlikely politician who became the city's most prominent anti-busing symbol; Richard Cardinal Cushing and his successor, Humberto Cardinal Madeiros, who watched their attempts to be evenhanded set off waves of anti-clericalism in Irish-Catholic neighborhoods, and Thomas Winship, editor of The Boston Globe, who had to confront charges of bias in coverage of the story.</p>
        <p>The mini-series is not likely to change minds or alter attitudes. The McGoffs and Twymons emerge as more understandable and sympathetic figures. Poor but proud, Alice places her faith in the American flag and Jesus Christ. Fighting the odds, tough Rachel is adamantly practical: ''I'm not talking brotherhood week, honey, I'm talking survival - and in Boston, not some make-believe Africa.'' Nevertheless, the busing confrontation leaves them, as Alice says, ''bringing out so much stuff, the worst in everybody.'' That reminder is what makes ''Common Ground'' unusually pertinent television.</p>
        <p>TV VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
