<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Swindler the Second Time Around Is Also a Witness for the Prosecution</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INFORMERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUBASCH, ARNOLD H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAPP, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HELLERMAN, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9153DF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Swindler the Second Time Around Is Also a Witness for the Prosecution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARNOLD H. LUBASCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LUBASCH, ARNOLD H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Two decades ago, a swindler named Michael Hellerman carried out a series of stock frauds involving top mobsters and then became an informer who testified against his former associates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Two decades ago, a swindler named Michael Hellerman carried out a series of stock frauds involving top mobsters and then became an informer who testified against his former associates.</p>
        <p>Two decades ago, a swindler named Michael Hellerman carried out a series of stock frauds involving top mobsters and then became an informer who testified against his former associates.</p>
        <p>Last month, a swindler named Michael Rapp testified in a Brooklyn trial about carrying out a series of bank frauds involving several defendants and the loss of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The stock swindler and the bank swindler were the same man. Mr. Hellerman had disappeared into the Government's witness protection program and changed his name to Rapp. But he did not change his penchant for swindling, informing and enjoying costly hotels, high-stakes gambling and chauffeur-driven limousines.</p>
        <p>In the bank-fraud trial, which is continuing in Federal District Court in Brooklyn, the prosecution has acknowledged that its star witness, Mr. Rapp, is ''a world-class con man.'' And modesty is not one of his strong points.</p>
        <p>Over $7 Million in Loans</p>
        <p>''I was good at conning him,'' Mr. Rapp said, in his recent testimony about the main defendant in the trial, Carl Cardascia. ''I was very good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cardascia, was president of the Flushing Federal Savings and Loan Association, which lent more than $7 million to Mr. Rapp and his associates in 1984. Mr. Cardascia is accused of failing to follow bank regulations and of misapplying bank funds.</p>
        <p>Pointing at a large chart prepared by the prosecution, Mr. Rapp described in detail how he helped arrange the loans, using virtually worthless stock in shell corporations as collateral.</p>
        <p>The 52-year-old witness, gray haired and sun tanned, talked rapidly and gestured frequently with his hands as he explained that he arranged for brokers to deposit millions of dollars in the financially troubled Flushing Federal. In return, he said, Mr. Cardascia approved his request for loans amounting to 25 percent of the deposits.</p>
        <p>The loans were obtained to finance ''venture capital deals'' that ranged from a resort in the Poconos to oil and gas property in Texas, he testified. But the business ventures failed to materialize, much of the money from the loans paid for the expensive tastes of the Rapp group, the loans were not repaid and the bank became insolvent.</p>
        <p>'Are You Still a Con Man?'</p>
        <p>Mr. Rapp testified that he had revealed his criminal past to Mr. Cardascia and even identified himself as ''the Wall Street swindler'' but that the banker was completely willing to do business with him.</p>
        <p>In cross-examination, Mr. Cardascia's lawyer, Joseph W. Ryan Jr., sought to discredit Mr. Rapp's testimony.</p>
        <p>''Now, are you still a con man?'' Mr. Ryan asked. ''Yes,'' Mr. Rapp answered. The lawyer then asked if Mr. Rapp was ''trying to con this jury into believing that Mr. Cardascia is corrupt.''</p>
        <p>''I can only tell the truth, Mr. Ryan,'' he replied. ''The jury has to judge for themselves.''</p>
        <p>''What I'm trying to tell you, if a banker is willing to do business with me, knowing who I am,'' he said, ''I'm going to do anything the bank wants to get that money. And if they're willing to take that collateral, so be it. That's not my problem.''</p>
        <p>''It's Mr. Cardascia's problem, right?'' the lawyer interjected. ''It sure is,'' Mr. Rapp replied. But Mr. Rapp went out of his way to defend the virtue of another defendant, Jilly Rizzo, an old friend of his who had once been his partner in a restaurant. Mr. Rizzo became involved in loans to build a resort in the Poconos.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Rizzo is completely innocent,'' Mr. Rapp asserted. He said Mr. Rizzo merely signed some loan documents to accommodate business associates.</p>
        <p>'They Indicted Jilly'</p>
        <p>''Jilly Rizzo was a celebrity'' who gave credence to business ventures, Mr. Rapp testified, because ''people associate Jilly Rizzo with Frank Sinatra'' and other celebrities.</p>
        <p>''Isn't it a fact, sir,'' Mr. Ryan asked, ''that you have taken it upon yourself to manipulate the F.B.I. and the prosecutors in this case to exonerate your friend of 30 years, Jilly Rizzo?''</p>
        <p>''I guess I didn't do too good a job,'' he retorted. ''They indicted Jilly, didn't they?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rapp, who has pleaded guilty in the Flushing Federal case and two recent bank frauds in Florida, is serving a 15-year prison sentence, but he said he expects to be paroled in 1992.</p>
        <p>Earlier, as Michael Hellerman, he served nine months in a ''safe house'' operated by Federal marshals, after he pleaded guilty to stock frauds in Manhattan and testified against John (Johnny Dio) Dioguardi and other mobsters.</p>
        <p>In the intervening years, while in the witness protection program, he moved away from New York City, settling on Cape Cod and later in the Miami area, where he operated restaurants.</p>
        <p>Responding to questions in the current trial, Mr. Rapp acknowledged his early stock frauds and his false statements to investors, brokerage houses and business partners.</p>
        <p>''About how much money did you make?'' a lawyer asked.</p>
        <p>''Over $3 million,'' Mr. Rapp answered.</p>
        <p>''Did you pay taxes on that money?'' he was asked. ''No,'' he answered. Mr. Rapp also acknowledged his fondness for gambling. In 1984, he said, he gambled at Caesar's Palace in Las Vegas, using a $150,000 cashier's check of Flushing Federal to back his credit.</p>
        <p>''Were you a winner or a loser?'' he was asked.</p>
        <p>''I think I lost $75,000 to $76,000,'' he answered.</p>
        <p>Jury deliberations in the trial of Mr. Cardascia, Mr. Rizzo and the other defendants are expected to begin in a few days.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
