<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="28DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DA1638F93BA15754C0A96E958260" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bell Atlantic Buying GTE For $52.8 Billion in Stock  Bell Atlantic, which dominates the local telephone business from Maine to Virginia, plans to acquire GTE, the nation's largest independent local and long-distance communications company, for $52.8 billion in stock. The companies plan to announce the deal this morning.</p>
        <p>The acquisition is the latest in a torrent of multibillion-dollar mergers in the telecommunications industry. By acquiring GTE, Bell Atlantic would become the nation's largest local phone company, serving more than 62 million customers. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bell Atlantic Buying GTE For $52.8 Billion in Stock  Bell Atlantic, which dominates the local telephone business from Maine to Virginia, plans to acquire GTE, the nation's largest independent local and long-distance communications company, for $52.8 billion in stock. The companies plan to announce the deal this morning.</p>
        <p>The acquisition is the latest in a torrent of multibillion-dollar mergers in the telecommunications industry. By acquiring GTE, Bell Atlantic would become the nation's largest local phone company, serving more than 62 million customers. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>American Express Beats Estimates  American Express reported an 11 percent gain in second-quarter earnings, mainly because of heavy use of its credit card and record purchases of mutual funds. The results at the travel and financial services company exceeded expectations, and its stock rose 5.37 percent. [D3.]</p>
        <p>The strong earnings at American Express lifted stocks. The Dow Jones industrial average leaped above 9,000, rising 90.88 points, to 9,028.24. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 6.47 points, to 1,147.27, and the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index gained 2.27 points, to 1,933.26. [D9.]</p>
        <p>Deal Near in Strike at 2 G.M. Plants  Negotiators are putting in long hours trying to resolve strikes at two General Motors parts factories in Flint, Mich. Union officials, with much to lose and little to gain, had a particularly strong incentive to settle before an arbitration ruling on the strikes' legality that could come as soon as tomorrow. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Slump in Russia  Russian stocks, which fell 17 percent last week, dropped another 9.1 percent, putting prices back to levels before the International Monetary Fund pledged to help avert default with more loans. The market selloff reflected resilient investor doubts about whether the Government can extricate Russia from seemingly intractable debts. [A5.]</p>
        <p>A Nasdaq Market Maker Is Fined  The regulatory arm of the National Association of Securities Dealers censured and fined Troster Singer Corporation, one of the nation's oldest and largest market making firms, for fraud in connection with 28 intentional Nasdaq trade reporting violations during 1994. The firm agreed to pay $950,000. Six Troster Singer employees were sanctioned and fined a total of $100,000. Gretchen Morgenson: Market Place. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Home Resales Fell Slightly in June  Sales of existing single-family homes slipped 2.3 percent in June, but remained robust. The seasonally adjusted annual sales rate was 4.72 million homes. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Wolf Group Buys Other Agencies  Larry Wolf, the chief executive of privately held Wolf Group Integrated Communications, has been described as ''the most successful unknown advertising man in Canada.'' But he is trying to change that by buying advertising agencies in this country and Canada with the goal of becoming a top-20 agency company in billings. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [D7.]</p>
        <p>CBS Retreats From Cable Channel  CBS will cede management of the CBS Eye on People cable channel to Discovery Communications because of what the network called significant losses. Discovery will acquire a 50 percent interest in what will become a joint venture, and CBS will be dropped from the name. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Sweepstakes Focus on Elderly  Fraudulent copycats and telemarketers are increasingly using the techniques of legitimate sweepstakes, and lists of their contestants, to prey on elderly people, law enforcement authorities say. But recently even the well-known legitimate sweepstakes have come under scrutiny because of concern that they promise too much. [A1.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
