<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Negotiators in G.M. Strike Press On as Arbitration Nears</title>
    <meta content="Y28AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DD1638F93BA15754C0A96E958260" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Negotiators in G.M. Strike Press On as Arbitration Nears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER with NICHOLE CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith; Christian, Nichole M</byline>
      <dateline>FLINT, Mich., July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Negotiators, seeking to resolve strikes at two General Motors Corp parts factories in Flint, Mich, continue to put in long hours, as union officials, in particular, have incentive to settle before arbitration ruling on strikes' legality that could come as soon as July 29; outside labor lawyers hired by GM argued before arbitrator last week that UAW is emphasizing only investment issues and is therefore in violation of national agreement; if union loses arbitration, it would face pending Federal lawsuit in which GM had demanded that workers be forced to return to their jobs; GM has also sought to have financial penalties imposed on union, but labor lawyers give it little chance of collecting damages (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Negotiators, seeking to resolve strikes at two General Motors parts factories here, continued to put in long hours today, as union officials, in particular, had an incentive to settle before an arbitration ruling on the strikes' legality that could come as soon as Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Talks continued at both struck factories, at a suburban Flint hotel and at three other factories where the United Automobile Workers union has also threatened strikes. People involved in the bargaining said that an overall agreement was close, but cautioned that it was impossible to predict when the last details would be resolved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Negotiators, seeking to resolve strikes at two General Motors parts factories here, continued to put in long hours today, as union officials, in particular, had an incentive to settle before an arbitration ruling on the strikes' legality that could come as soon as Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Talks continued at both struck factories, at a suburban Flint hotel and at three other factories where the United Automobile Workers union has also threatened strikes. People involved in the bargaining said that an overall agreement was close, but cautioned that it was impossible to predict when the last details would be resolved.</p>
        <p>The strikes here have forced G.M. to close most of its North American factories and lay off close to 200,000 workers. But today, using replacement parts from outside suppliers. G.M. reopened two of its 29 assembly plants, a sport utility vehicle factory in Silao, Mexico, and a Chevrolet Corvette factory in Bowling Green, Ky.</p>
        <p>U.A.W. officials criticized these moves and warned that workers in Bowling Green might not cooperate. But Billy Jackson, the president of the U.A.W. local in Bowling Green, said that only one worker there was involved in the installation of replacement parts -- gas pedals that would normally come from a struck factory here and are now being purchased from another company. The worker did not reject the parts because G.M. could try to dismiss him in retaliation, Mr. Jackson said.</p>
        <p>The current round of negotiations here picked up speed rather suddenly on Saturday evening, at the end of four days of legal arguments before an arbitrator, Thomas Roberts. A person briefed on the arbitration said that the U.A.W. had filed several procedural motions on Saturday, mainly seeking more time to respond to the documentation that G.M.'s lawyers had presented. Mr. Roberts turned down all the motions and indicated that he would rule as soon as Wednesday, said the person, who insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W. has little to gain from a ruling and much to lose, and has been eager for a settlement since Saturday evening. A settlement before Wednesday would be likely to include G.M.'s withdrawal of the grievance in arbitration, which would forestall a precedent-setting ruling on the strikes' legality.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W.'s national contract with G.M., which runs through September 1999, allows local strikes only over increases in assembly line speed, subcontracting disputes and health and safety issues. The U.A.W. has cited all these issues here, and has also demanded that G.M. invest more money here and guarantee that jobs be preserved. Those are the same demands that the union has made in more than a dozen other local strikes over the last five years.</p>
        <p>A battalion of outside labor lawyers hired by G.M. argued before the arbitrator last week that the U.A.W. was really emphasizing only the investment issues and was therefore in violation of the national agreement. The U.A.W. denied this. But if the union loses the arbitration, it would face a pending Federal lawsuit in which G.M. has demanded that workers be forced to return to their jobs. G.M., having suffered heavy losses during the strike, has also sought to have financial penalties imposed on the union, but labor lawyers give it little chance of collecting damages.</p>
        <p>Wary of settling the strikes here only to face walkouts elsewhere, G.M. is demanding that the U.A.W. reach agreements at as many factories as possible, and not just at the two struck here. The other three factories where intensive bargaining is under way are parts factories in Indianapolis and Dayton, Ohio, and a car assembly plant here. The U.A.W. had tried to keep threats of local strikes alive to discourage G.M. from trying to sell or close the factories.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Lobaccaro, an auto analyst at Merrill Lynch, estimated that the strike had already cost G.M. at least $3.2 billion in after-tax losses in the second and third quarters. But he added that G.M. might be able to shave the final loss to $1.8 billion if it settled now and ran a lot of overtime in its factories to refill its dealerships quickly.</p>
        <p>G.M. executives have been hinting that they might stop production of some money-losing models after the strikes, reduce the work force more rapidly through attrition and perhaps close or sell a few small factories. But such actions might have been inevitable regardless of the strikes, and the potential gains of up to $500 million cannot fairly be offset against the cost of the strike, Mr. Lobaccaro said.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea this restructuring has something to do with the strike is just giving Wall Street something to chew on as it looks at the bill'' for the strike, he said.</p>
        <p>While U.A.W. leaders are eager for an end to the strike, and while G.M. executives would like to stem the company's losses, many strikers are less enthusiastic about returning to work soon after nearly two months of showing up only once a week for two-hour stints on the picket lines. With cool, crisp weather here, many of the strikers have been taking summer vacations, after five years of working six or seven days a week to keep up with an unusually strong auto market. While the workers' strike benefits are only $150 a week, most have ample savings from their years of extensive overtime.</p>
        <p>''Give me a couple more weeks as long as this weather holds out,'' said Jeff Irish, a 43-year-old heavy equipment repairman, who has spent much of the last two months camping and sailing but was in Flint this morning picketing an auto body parts factory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
