<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fed Expected To Continue Same Course</title>
    <meta content="17FED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, Alan (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DF1431F934A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fed Expected To Continue Same Course</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wall Street experts doubt Federal Reserve chairman, Alan Greenspan, will change policy in response to sharp stock slide; expect him to continue series of small interest rate increases to cool economy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the markets reopen today, one of the biggest questions weighing on investors' minds is what the Federal Reserve might do. The answer: no change in policy.</p>
        <p>Certainly that is the expectation on Wall Street. Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, has committed the central bank to a series of small interest rate increases until the economy slows and stock markets, in response, calm down. The sell-off Friday does not alter that policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the markets reopen today, one of the biggest questions weighing on investors' minds is what the Federal Reserve might do. The answer: no change in policy.</p>
        <p>Certainly that is the expectation on Wall Street. Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, has committed the central bank to a series of small interest rate increases until the economy slows and stock markets, in response, calm down. The sell-off Friday does not alter that policy.</p>
        <p>''Unless there is evidence that the financial markets are under more strain than we have seen so far, there is no reason to believe that the Fed will alter course,'' said John Lipsky, chief economist at Chase Manhattan Bank. What is required is evidence of a panic in which lending and borrowing dry up and markets cease to function.</p>
        <p>That did not happen Friday. As Albert Wojnilower, an economist at Craig Drill Capital and the Clipper Group, put it, ''As long as you were willing to sell at $5 or $10 or $15 down, there were buyers.''</p>
        <p>Through statements and actions, Mr. Greenspan has locked the Fed into a fairly predictable approach. He has argued that investors' enthusiasm for stocks is largely a rational response to rising productivity and to expectations of rising profits. But even rational markets can get ahead of themselves, and investors' gains from rising stock prices have created more demand for goods and services than the economy can continue to supply. The result is likely to be inflationary pressure.</p>
        <p>Or so Mr. Greenspan has argued. As a result, the Fed has raised rates by a quarter of a percentage point on five occasions since last June. In this context, Friday's sell-off can be viewed as part of the change that the rate increases are intended to bring about.</p>
        <p>Even after Friday's tumble, the major indexes are still far from reversing the gains of the 1990's. The Dow Jones industrial average and the Wilshire 5000, a very broad stock measure, are now only back to where they were a year ago, Mr. Lipsky noted, and the Nasdaq is still up nearly 34 percent since last spring.</p>
        <p>For the Fed to change course now -- either cutting rates or even failing to go up another quarter point at the next Fed policy-making meeting on, on May 16 -- would be a signal to investors that the Fed stands ready to bail them out, Mr. Roach and others on Wall Street argued yesterday. That would cause stock prices to shoot up again, most analysts believe.</p>
        <p>''The typical risk taker will say, 'Oh, that is nice, the Fed will bail us out,' '' said David M. Jones, chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston, a Wall Street bond firm.</p>
        <p>The Fed has supplied relief to offset past panics, which it has defined as moments in which markets seize up. In panics, buyers all but disappear despite plunging stock prices. Lenders also pull back or seek the safe haven of Treasury securities. And markets, in effect, cease to function.</p>
        <p>''Borrowers won't borrow, lenders won't lend and investors find themselves unable to buy and sell securities in the desired volumes, regardless of price,'' Mr. Lipsky said.</p>
        <p>That happened on Oct. 19, 1987, when the Dow Jones industrial average fell by 21 percent -- far beyond the 5.66 percent decline on Friday. Reversing course -- then like now, Mr. Greenspan had been trying to slow the economy through interest rate increases -- the Fed cut rates and promised lenders plenty of liquidity to stay afloat if borrowers defaulted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan, appointed Fed chairman only a few months earlier, fashioned that strategy, and he invoked the same rate-cutting policy again in the fall of 1998, after Russia defaulted on its debts and Long Term Capital Management, a hedge fund, almost failed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
