<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Appraisal; From the Guggenheim, a Bold Vision for a Lower Manhattan Museum</title>
    <meta content="17MUSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metro Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guggenheim, Solomon R, Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gehry, Frank O</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EEDC1431F934A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Appraisal; From the Guggenheim, a Bold Vision for a Lower Manhattan Museum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article appraises design by Frank O Gehry for new Guggenheim Museum that is proposed for new site on East River in lower Manhattan; photomap (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How many ways can you say ''Wow''? In the weeks ahead New Yorkers will certainly find more articulate words to describe Frank O. Gehry's design for a museum that the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation hopes to build along the East River in Lower Manhattan. Silence would be eloquent, too. But only for the repressed. Otherwise, this is the moment to look for noisemakers left over from New Year's Eve and give them one more toot. Here comes architecture.</p>
        <p>Models of the design by Mr. Gehry, the architect of the acclaimed Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, Spain, will be presented in ''Project for a New Guggenheim Museum in New York City,'' which opens on Wednesday at the Guggenheim's main building on Fifth Avenue at 89th Street, designed in 1959 by Frank Lloyd Wright. The featured attraction is a large model, 12 feet long and 5 feet high, which displays the design in close-up detail. Other models present the project as it would appear in the Lower Manhattan cityscape, though there is no guarantee it will ever be built. The proposed site, near the foot of Wall Street, is occupied by three piers scheduled for development by the New York City Economic Development Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How many ways can you say ''Wow''? In the weeks ahead New Yorkers will certainly find more articulate words to describe Frank O. Gehry's design for a museum that the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation hopes to build along the East River in Lower Manhattan. Silence would be eloquent, too. But only for the repressed. Otherwise, this is the moment to look for noisemakers left over from New Year's Eve and give them one more toot. Here comes architecture.</p>
        <p>Models of the design by Mr. Gehry, the architect of the acclaimed Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, Spain, will be presented in ''Project for a New Guggenheim Museum in New York City,'' which opens on Wednesday at the Guggenheim's main building on Fifth Avenue at 89th Street, designed in 1959 by Frank Lloyd Wright. The featured attraction is a large model, 12 feet long and 5 feet high, which displays the design in close-up detail. Other models present the project as it would appear in the Lower Manhattan cityscape, though there is no guarantee it will ever be built. The proposed site, near the foot of Wall Street, is occupied by three piers scheduled for development by the New York City Economic Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>Even as a purely speculative idea, however, this museum project performs an important civic service. A steel-plated vessel, floating atop a vast outdoor skating rink, this is an icebreaker of a design, a plan for crunching through rigid streetscapes and frozen minds.</p>
        <p>And it is a test of the city's willingness to think big. Will it get built? The question is a waste of energy. Like other sideshows that have kept New York in denial about the mediocrity of the buildings it puts up, the feasibility question distracts from the challenge presented by the design. This is the top form architecture comes in these days. Want some?</p>
        <p>Thomas Krens, the director of the Guggenheim Museum, said that the institution is committed to building another museum in Manhattan. The Fifth Avenue building is too small to display more than a fraction of the museum's permanent collection, which also includes examples of large-scale contemporary art. Mr. Krens envisions an arrangement in which the Wright building would display work from the late 19th century to 1945 while the downtown building would present art from 1945 to the present.</p>
        <p>''Project for a New Guggenheim Museum in New York City'' presents the record of a creative process leading to the birth of an idea. If this one doesn't fly, we can count on Mr. Krens to have others. In 1998 he set his eye on another waterfront site, on the Hudson River. Local opposition helped deflate that dream and it could shatter this one, too. Financial and government support are also hurdles.</p>
        <p>Lower Manhattan is well stocked with cherished landmarks like the Brooklyn Bridge, the World Trade Center, the Woolworth Building, Trinity Church and 70 Pine Street. But it has been some time since the district's architecture has risen to their iconic level. One of the charms of Mr. Gehry's design is that it would recast mediocre towers in the supporting roles for which they are better suited.</p>
        <p>If New York is a perpetual gift to the future, this design is its bow: a flourish of titanium ribbons (Mr. Gehry calls them wrappers) curled around half a million square feet of gallery space. The composition is roughly triangular, a pediment on square columns. The triangle is anchored at the northern and southern corners by two low-rise structures of boxy silhouette. The southern structure houses a terminal for a ferry that would take visitors to a sculpture garden on Governors Island. The northern structure contains a 1,200-seat theater.</p>
        <p>Thirty-six galleries, ranging from 1,300 to 20,000 square feet, would be housed on three levels within the cloudlike tangle of ribbon and a 450-foot tower rising above it. The galleries would serve various uses. In addition to the permanent collection and temporary shows, they would present exhibitions for three departments: education, architecture and design, and art and technology.</p>
        <p>As at the Guggenheim in Bilbao, the previous collaboration between Mr. Krens and Mr. Gehry, the museum's major space would be an atrium bathed in natural light; 26,000 square feet of gallery space would overlook the atrium's well. Escalators, forming a dramatic diagonal at the base of the space, would move visitors up from the open areas beneath the museum into the building's heart.</p>
        <p>Six massive square columns, steel and concrete superpylons, would hold the mass aloft. Gardens, bridges, a waterside promenade and other public spaces would occupy petal-shaped platforms extending into the river. The free-form rink, beneath the museum's soaring underside, would be equipped with ''Knife Ship I,'' a kinetic sculpture by Claes Oldenburg that was the focus of a performance piece created by Mr. Gehry, Mr. Oldenburg and Coosje van Bruggen for the 1985 Venice Biennale.</p>
        <p>Looking at the models could give you whiplash. In New York architects have spent the last two decades viewing the present through a rearview mirror, as if the city came to a halt in the Art Deco era.</p>
        <p>As with the Bilbao Guggenheim, Mr. Gehry shows that one of the purest ways to honor context is to play against it. Many have seen the Manhattan skyline as a geological formation of cliffs, peaks and canyons. Mr. Gehry treats the site as a natural wonder, a spot where mountains cascade into the sea. He has raised the horizon of the water, in waves that lap against the base of the cliffs, and pulled the sky down to the canyons, with changing light reflected in the museum's wavy metal surface. Expanses of glass, articulated with diagonal mullions, splash upward like jets of water formed by a Manhattan-bound meteor's narrow miss.</p>
        <p>With the tower, the vertical dimension of the skyline reverberates into the foreground. The tower's leaning silhouette and flaring top talk back to the World Trade Center's scaleless, impersonal thrust.</p>
        <p>Some architects, who still regard the Trade Center as an aesthetic abomination, have championed a revival of building crowns, by which they mean paperweights blown up to skyscraper scale. Here is another way to top a tower. Rip off roof. Cut jaggedly above penthouse. Let curtain walls droop. Instead of hiding structural spines behind marble and steel, as Mies van der Rohe did with the Seagram Building, just let them hang out there in the breeze.</p>
        <p>Ordered complexity, not chaos, is the fundamental principle of this work. We should be used to this by now. It has been 35 years since Robert Venturi introduced the concepts of complexity and contradiction as an alternative to the unified simplicity of the International Style. Mr. Gehry's work, like Venturi's and Denise Scott Brown's, aims for the maximum complexity that can be transmitted through habitable space.</p>
        <p>The wrappers are the most eye-catching element of the Guggenheim design, but it would be a mistake to think the project's importance rests entirely on Mr. Gehry's ability to sculpture arresting shapes. What matters here is the physiognomy of the shapes.</p>
        <p>Intersubjectivity -- the idea that multiple perspectives can render a truth -- is the central concept governing this and other projects that Mr. Gehry has designed for the last 25 years. It is also the idea that many people find hardest to take. We still look to architecture to embody some ideal of external authority: history, science, nature and religion, to name a few. This Gehry declines to provide. Though he makes fleeting formal allusions to other times, other buildings, these images are mutable. They rise to the surface and sink back. Tell me what you see and I will tell you -- with wild inaccuracy, no doubt -- who you are.</p>
        <p>Scale and relationship to context are two of the Rorschach tests this project must pass in the eye of the beholder. But the Guggenheim faces even bigger obstacles. Some will object that the design looks too much like Bilbao; New York, ever mindful of its uniqueness, deserves better than a remake of something designed for provincial Spain. Some will not want to invest hope in a project that has yet to obtain the required permits and financial and government support.</p>
        <p>I wouldn't worry too much about the design's uniqueness. To philistines all modern glass towers are identical. When you've seen one titanium wrapper, you've seen 'em all. A model of the Bilbao museum, included in the exhibition, will enable viewers to compare the designs. But carping about formal similarity may just be part of the Nimby syndrome. Architecture is fine for Bilbao, but we don't want it here.</p>
        <p>Since the demolition of Pennsylvania Station, the troops can be counted on to protest tinkering with a lamppost. We've only begun to awaken to the loss of heritage that occurs when a city is frozen in time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
