<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Chilly Winds That Come and Go</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFMANN, DEBORAH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FASHION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D9173AF937A15751C0A967958260" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Chilly Winds That Come and Go</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH HOFMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOFMANN, DEBORAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With weather that not only shifts from day to day but varies according to the side of the street, many men would welcome the layering a windbreaker provides.</p>
        <p>Windbreakers today are more stylish and versatile. They are more likely to be made of coated cottons, reversible washed silks or microfibers -- very thin, tightly woven polyester fibers -- than of nylon or cotton. Some can be worn under a winter coat for extra warmth on a really bitter day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With weather that not only shifts from day to day but varies according to the side of the street, many men would welcome the layering a windbreaker provides.</p>
        <p>Windbreakers today are more stylish and versatile. They are more likely to be made of coated cottons, reversible washed silks or microfibers -- very thin, tightly woven polyester fibers -- than of nylon or cotton. Some can be worn under a winter coat for extra warmth on a really bitter day.</p>
        <p>There are many styles. "Blousons, baseball, safari, field and cardigan silhouettes are all updated with detail work," said Tom Julian, a spokesman for the Men's Fashion Association, a trade group. "And microfiber is the buzz of 90's outerwear, rejuvenating the windbreaker, with its feel of suede, drape of silk and the way it takes to bright as well as muted spring colors in a strong way." From Sporting Fields</p>
        <p>Ruff Hewn is known for outerwear that evokes a sense of ruggedness and appropriates its fabric from sporting contexts. The company's unlined spring jacket is 32 inches long and is made of polymer-coated cotton, the fabric used for tents, marquees and canteen covers. It gradually softens with wear, and might easily become a man's favorite throw-on.</p>
        <p>The body of the jacket is ivory, with the collar and inside cuffs in dark tan. It is single-breasted, with copper-colored buttons like the ones on blue jeans running up to the neck. The four big patch pockets have small utility pockets inside. Small side vents with button closures add style.</p>
        <p>This safari-inspired Ruff Hewn windbreaker is sporty and flattering.  It is for year-round wear and looks great over a sweater or sport jacket as a waterproof layer, or over a T-shirt in summer. It is $130 at Outfitters, 250 Vesey Street (4 World Financial Center), and Camouflage Clothing, 139 Eighth Avenue (18th Street).</p>
        <p>Pendleton Woolen Mills, known for its winter woolens, has slowly and with growing confidence ventured, like a groundhog, into spring. The company's windbreaker under the Lobo label ($100) epitomizes the color-block trend in green, navy and white. It has a zipper front with a snap-front storm fly, a drawstring collar and an elasticized waistband and cuffs. The fabric is a machine-washable twill blend of 60 percent cotton, 40 percent nylon.</p>
        <p>Stores carrying a wide selection of Lobo windbreakers include Galeria Pendleton in Pittsburgh; Rugged Boot in Mohegan Lake, N.Y.; Hoffman's Ltd. in Latham, N.Y.; McCurdy's in Rochester, and the Hess store in Allentown, Pa. The Chicago Pendleton Products Store carries the entire line. Names of other retailers carrying the Lobo windbreaker are available from Pendleton at (212) 661-1670 in Manhattan or (503) 226-4801 in Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>Robert Comstock has a hooded bomber-style windbreaker in brushed cotton poplin, lined in washed cotton. It has a zipper front and a high-button collar, and comes in colors that the maker calls pinon green and clay. It is $200 at Bloomingdale's, Macy's and Saks Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Regatta Sport makes a windbreaker with a zip-close gusset neck, a drawstring waist and chest pockets. Made of navy blue microfiber, it is $120 at Bloomingdale's and Macy's.</p>
        <p>The Andrew Fezza Sportswear Collection offers a sophisticated version of the windbreaker: a versatile washed-indigo blouson in hopsack linen with buttons carved from black nutshells. It is $310 at Bloomingdale's. It would look as good over a sweater as over a T-shirt.</p>
        <p>Richard Mishaan's single-breasted safari jacket is made of rayon and polyester microfibers in a sueded gabardine texture. The buttons are horn. The colors are called putty, bay blue, maize and cream. It is $250 at Carol Rollo/Riding High, 1147 First Avenue (62d Street)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
