<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California's Flowering Pinnacles</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910324T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PINNACLES NATIONAL MONUMENT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENCHER, MELVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DC1F31F937A15751C0A967958260" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California's Flowering Pinnacles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELVIN MENCHER; MELVIN MENCHER is a professor emeritus at the Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MENCHER, MELVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a map of the western United States the Pinnacles National Monument -- a volcanic remnant of spires, crags, caves and colorful spring wildflowers -- is an insignificant speck 135 miles south of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Its 17,000 acres are dwarfed by Yosemite's 761,000 acres and Death Valley's 2 million-acre spread along the California-Nevada border. Indeed, the National Park Service lists Pinnacles in its booklet, "The National Parks; Lesser-Known Areas."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a map of the western United States the Pinnacles National Monument -- a volcanic remnant of spires, crags, caves and colorful spring wildflowers -- is an insignificant speck 135 miles south of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Its 17,000 acres are dwarfed by Yosemite's 761,000 acres and Death Valley's 2 million-acre spread along the California-Nevada border. Indeed, the National Park Service lists Pinnacles in its booklet, "The National Parks; Lesser-Known Areas."</p>
        <p>But to those who have happened on the Pinnacles or who have driven over from the Bay Area, the postage-stamp sized monument is a jewel.</p>
        <p>Unlike its sister parks, Pinnacles can be sampled in a day. In fact, the park service describes the Pinnacles as primarily a day-use area. Its miles of trails -- from easy walking to strenuous, for experienced hikers only -- offer access to a wide range of plant life, interesting geology, good birding and ample photographic opportunities. And for those who simply enjoy a stroll along a shaded path, Pinnacles does not press itself on the visitor.</p>
        <p>Pinnacles is open year round, but most of the 220,000 annual visitors are spring migrants -- through mid-April, possibly into May -- who are lured by the 50-plus species of wildflowers. Unlike the flowering carpets that rains bring out of the desert, Pinnacles' flowers display themselves in small patches. Some of the plant species are unique in this part of the state, thriving in the soils that began as volcanic rock.</p>
        <p>Pinnacles itself looks as though it does not belong here. Its spirelike rock formations jut a thousand feet into clear-blue sky from nearby smooth, rolling hills and rangeland where cattle graze. The fact is that Pinnacles does belong elsewhere, 195 miles to the southeast. Its present location is the result of two geological upheavals that began about 23 million years ago after the Pacific Plate collided with the North American Plate and tore off a part of the North American Plate.</p>
        <p>In the space where the earth's crust was broken, magma boiled upward and this molten rock built up until a volcano formed. In Southern California, where the Pinnacles originated, a volcanic mountain some 8,500 feet high was formed on the Pacific Plate. The plate and its mountain slowly drifted northwest, leaving a section behind, near Lancaster, 45 miles northeast of Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>As it moved, erosion went to work, breaking down the mountain. Today, the highest point in the monument is the North Chalone Peak, 3,304 feet high and still eroding . . . and still moving as well, for Pinnacles sits alongside the San Andreas Rift Zone.</p>
        <p>For the present, however, the Pinnacles stands majestic and solid, its red rock spires attracting rock climbers as well as hikers, nature lovers and campers.</p>
        <p>Pinnacles has two entrances. The east entrance is the better known as it leads to a visitor center, and the road into the monument has the only commercial campground near the Pinnacles. The east entrance is 35 miles south of Hollister via state roads 25 and 146. The west entrance is 40 miles south of Salinas by way of U.S. 101 and 146. The only National Park Service campgrounds in the monument are available through the west entrance. There is no through road connecting the two sides.</p>
        <p>For those who want to sample Pinnacles, the half-mile Moses Spring Trail that begins near the visitor center is ideal. Many of the plants in the chaparral, foothill-woodland and riparian plant communities are represented. The moist environmental zone covers about 80 percent of the Pinnacles, and the chaparral plants are the most common in the zone: the holly-leaf cherry in moist areas, chamise in dry areas and buckbrush and the manzanita on north-facing slopes.</p>
        <p>On the hillsides, the major tree species is the blue oak, with buckbrush, mountain mahogany and redberry. The digger pine, whose roots can penetrate a hundred feet through fissures in the rocks in search of water, is also present.</p>
        <p>The monument has seasonal creeks and permanent springs that create a riparian plant community. Along the creeks are the sycamore, cottonwood and coast live oak. A trickle of water from a spring gives the chain fern a chance to flourish.</p>
        <p>From the visitor center up along the Moses Spring Trail, the spring hiker can spot the mariposa lily, wild onion, larkspur, wild phlox, buttercup, fiesta flower and others. On the west side, the Juniper Canyon Trail displays poppies, bitterroot, baby blue eyes, golden star and the popcorn flower, among others.</p>
        <p>The monument has two sets of caves, one on each side. The Bear Gulch Caves are a short distance up the Moses Spring Trail. On the west side, the Balconies Caves are less than a mile from the ranger station. Flashlights are necessary; the visitor center offers them for sale.</p>
        <p>The center and the ranger station also have maps and self-guiding trail brochures. Recommended: loose-fitting clothing, water and a hat to keep off the sun. Also, camera and binoculars.</p>
        <p>For bird watchers, the variety of habitats means a diversity of birds. The monument has 45 year-round resident species, among them the sharp-shinned, red-tailed and Cooper's hawk, the roadrunner, common barn and great horned owl, and the colorful and abundant acorn woodpecker. One hundred other birds are spring or winter residents. The white-throated swift is abundant in the spring, and the watcher might spot the Allen's, Costa's and black-chinned hummingbird. The Anna's hummingbird is an abundant year-round resident, as is the colorful western bluebird and the melodious California thrasher.</p>
        <p>The Pinnacles Campground, which is adjacent to the east-side boundary, is an excellent birding area. Here the visitor can spot coveys of California quail feeding in the open and the yellow-billed magpie, which is local only to the northern and central Sacramento Valley foothills, rangelands and valleys.</p>
        <p>The park service recommends spring and fall visits, when the daytime temperatures are in the 70's or thereabouts. In July and August, the temperature can reach 100 degrees, and December, January and February is the rainy season. And yet, some prefer these off-seasons. There are fewer visitors, and in the summer the nights are cool. Winter days can be bracing.</p>
        <p>Given the small size of the monument and the limited parking, those who intend to visit in spring and fall are best off trying weekdays. Weekends can be crowded. The day-use fee is $3.</p>
        <p>Rangers advise those who want to climb the rocks to bring the proper equipment. Others should stay on the trails, some of which offer plenty of opportunities for steep climbs through picturesque rocks, shaded woodlands and even through a rock tunnel. THE PINNACLES MONUMENT Getting There</p>
        <p>The Pinnacles is easily accessible for those driving north or south in California on U.S. 101 or U.S. 5. All the roads into the monument are paved and well maintained. Driving time from San Francisco is about three hours, from San Jose about two. Accommodations</p>
        <p>For those who want to spend more than a day in the monument or want to stay nearby, there are good motels in Hollister, King City, Salinas and Soledad -- each within an easy drive of the monument.</p>
        <p>Prices are $80 for two on Friday and Saturday ($5 less Sunday and weekdays) at the Ridgemark Guest Cottages in Hollister, telephone (408) 637-8151, to $55 for two at the Best Western King City Inn, (408) 385-6733, and $48 to $75 for two at the Courtesy Inn in King City, (408) 385-4646.</p>
        <p>Salinas has a Best Western, telephone (408) 424-1741, a Ramada Inn, (408) 424-8661, and several other good motels. Rates vary widely. In Soledad, the Best Western Valley Harvest Inn, (408) 678-3833, has rates from $54 to $64 for two.</p>
        <p>Reservations are recommended during the spring and early summer. For those with campers or who have tents and want to stay at the commercial campground, write Pinnacles Campground, 2400 Highway 146, Paicines, Calif. 95043; (408) 389-4462.  Steinbeck Country</p>
        <p>For fans of John Steinbeck, Salinas, his birthplace, might be worth a visit. The public library has first editions, letters, photographs and other material on display. Soledad offers the ruins of the Mission Nuestra Senora de la Soledad, founded in 1791, and a restored chapel. Another mission is 20 miles southwest of King City. Mission San Antonio de Padua, founded by Junipero Serra in 1771, is restored and features the original grist mill, well, tannery and parts of the aqueduct system. It is in Fort Hunter Liggett.  -- M. M.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 24, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Feb. 24 about the Pinnacles National Monument in California misidentified a bird. It was an acorn woodpecker, not a yellow-billed magpie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 24, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Feb. 24 about the Pinnacles National Monument in California misidentified a bird. It was an acorn woodpecker, not a yellow-billed magpie.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
