<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fine Fish in an Airy and Bold Setting</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RIVERBAY SEAFOOD BAR AND GRILL (WILLISTON PARK, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARKEY, JOANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED61038F937A15751C0A967958260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fine Fish in an Airy and Bold Setting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STARKEY, JOANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUPERIOR seafood should be a given on Long Island. Instead, terrific fish is a rare find at area restaurants. Those that label themselves seafood houses are often an especially dreary lot. The Riverbay Seafood Bar and Grill in Williston Park is a welcome exception.</p>
        <p>Riverbay is less than two years old, but its origins are deeply rooted in Sheepshead Bay. In the 60's and 70's, the same family owned the Pappas seafood restaurant there. In the 80's, they opened a Pappas in Williston Park, where Riverbay stands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUPERIOR seafood should be a given on Long Island. Instead, terrific fish is a rare find at area restaurants. Those that label themselves seafood houses are often an especially dreary lot. The Riverbay Seafood Bar and Grill in Williston Park is a welcome exception.</p>
        <p>Riverbay is less than two years old, but its origins are deeply rooted in Sheepshead Bay. In the 60's and 70's, the same family owned the Pappas seafood restaurant there. In the 80's, they opened a Pappas in Williston Park, where Riverbay stands.</p>
        <p>Riverbay is not the proverbial undiscovered little gem. The word is out. As a result, this sparkler is often packed. Its no-reservations policy results in waits of about 15 minutes on most nights. But the wait is worth it.</p>
        <p>Airy, attractive, masculine and bold, Riverbay seduces diners with a turn-of-the-century glow. Its rich mahogany beams, dark wood wainscotting, sepia photographs, antique light fixtures, high -backed booths and beveled glass recall steakhouse trappings. Yet, there are enough seascapes, mounted fish, ice-filled display cases bursting with sparkling seafood and blackboard listings of featured oysters to rivet Riverbay firmly to the fish-house tradition.</p>
        <p>Oyster lovers will revel in the wide selection. From Maine belons to Florida Appalachacolas and a half-dozen locations in between, the aggregation is unrivaled at Long Island restaurants. More common but equally fine appetizers are the no-filler, lightly packed crab cakes, the sweet tiny steamers and the pristine seafood salad starring baby calamari. Say no to the bland New England clam chowder and the not-so-special special of stone-crab claws, which were overpriced at $13.50 for an appetizer portion, watery and sticking to their shells.</p>
        <p>Every salad at Riverbay is a fine fresh catch. They are reasonably priced at $3 to $5, abundant and feature top-quality produce. The tomato, cucumber and red onion was a standout, with its seeded-cucumber half-moons, sweet onions and summery ruby tomatoes.</p>
        <p>Fish has the edge over shellfish at entree time. Every flat fish sampled was a cooked-to-perfection flaky delight: lotte, or monkfish, teamed with lobster sauce over a mound of braised red cabbage, simply and lightly broiled whole Florida pompano, sauteed Mingo snapper napped with a creamy dill sauce and melt-in-the-mouth poached salmon.</p>
        <p>Our steamed lobster, though, was slightly chewy, and tender fried Ipswich clams and plump fried oysters would have benefited from a lighter batter.</p>
        <p>Diners might be surprised to find superior prime beef at a fish house. Both sirloin steak and prime rib were meltingly tender, full of flavor and everything they should be. But it is understandable because Bryant &amp; Cooper, the splendid Roslyn steakhouse, and Riverbay are commonly owned.</p>
        <p>The menu's supporting cast helps make Riverbay what it is. Every entree is accompanied by great creamy cole slaw and either rice, an admirable baked potato or sensational long, slim and crisp french fries. Substantial peasant bread, pumpernickel rolls dotted with plump raisins, chunky tartar sauce chock full of flavor and cocktail sauce zippy with horseradish also do their part.</p>
        <p>Diners who view dessert as a reward for choosing a low-calorie fish entree will gravitate to two luscious chocolate possibilities, mud pie under a drift of real whipped cream and truffle cake, a dense fudgy ganache atop a raspberry sauce. The truly righteous will be happy with fresh pineapple, melon or berries. A bountiful bowl of summer-sweet raspberries for $4 was a reasonable midwinter-blues buster. Skip the too-sweet airy Key lime pie and the pecan pie, which was hot from the microwave.</p>
        <p>Fittingly, there are more than twice as many whites as red wines offered. Two of the most appropriate, muscadet and fume blanc, are only $13 each. A midprice choice, perfect with seafood, is the clean, light, charming, dry Sancerre, Michel Redde, 1989, for $22. Riverbay</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>700 Willis Avenue (a mile south of Northern State Parkway or 1 1/4 miles south of the Long Island Expressway), Williston Park. 742-9191.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Appealing seafood restaurant with an authentic turn-of-the-century look.</p>
        <p>Service: Informed, informal, offering good suggestions.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Oysters, crab cakes, steamers, seafood salad, all salads, salmon, lotte, pompano, Mingo snapper, sirloin steak, prime rib, chocolate mud pie, chocolate truffle, fresh fruit.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch entrees are $5 to $13. Dinner: Appetizers are $3 to $20 (one pound of shrimp); entrees, $7 (hamburgers) to $18. Lobsters are higher.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours: Lunch, noon to 3 P.M., Mondays through Fridays. Sunday brunch, 11:30 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. Dinner: 5 to 10 P.M., Mondays through Thursdays; 5 to 11 P.M., Fridays; 5 P.M. to midnight Saturday and 3 to 10 P..M. Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Taken only for eight or more.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Six steps at entrance. Ratings: Poor Satisfactory Good Very Good Excellent Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings are based on the reviewer's reaction to food and price in relation to comparable establishments.</p>
        <p>The Times Restaurant Line offers capsule reviews by cuisine, price and location (in New York City and suburbs), published in the last 18 months. Touch-line telephones only: 1-900-988-0101 (75 cents a minute).</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
