<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asians Spread Across a Land, and Help Change It</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASIAN-AMERICANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENSUS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, LYNDON BAINES (1908-73)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DC143DF937A15751C0A967958260" item-length="1624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asians Spread Across a Land, and Help Change It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</byline>
      <dateline>BAYOU LA BATRE, Ala.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Birmingham, where eating out long meant barbecue, there are now 60 Chinese restaurants. In Huntsville, Korean managers at the Korean-owned Gold Star television factory give orders to their American workers. And here in Bayou La Batre, at the tip of Mobile Bay, a third of the old Cajun fishing village's 2,600 inhabitants are now Vietnamese or Cambodian.</p>
        <p>In a state that a quarter-century ago was a symbol of racism, these new settlers are part of a wave of immigrants that has increased the Asian-American share of Alabama's population by 124 percent in the past decade, according to figures recently made public by the Census Bureau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Birmingham, where eating out long meant barbecue, there are now 60 Chinese restaurants. In Huntsville, Korean managers at the Korean-owned Gold Star television factory give orders to their American workers. And here in Bayou La Batre, at the tip of Mobile Bay, a third of the old Cajun fishing village's 2,600 inhabitants are now Vietnamese or Cambodian.</p>
        <p>In a state that a quarter-century ago was a symbol of racism, these new settlers are part of a wave of immigrants that has increased the Asian-American share of Alabama's population by 124 percent in the past decade, according to figures recently made public by the Census Bureau.</p>
        <p>And they reflect one of the most dramatic findings of the 1990 Census -- the explosion of Asian and Pacific Islanders around the United States. Although Asian-Americans were once largely confined to a few states, like California and Hawaii, and clustered in urban centers like the Chinatowns of New York and San Francisco, they have now spread to virtually every part of the nation.</p>
        <p>So far, the Census Bureau has released ethnic statistics for about half the states. But Frederick W. Hollmann, a demographer with the Census Bureau, has estimated that around the country the Asian population increased by 79.5 percent in the 1980's, rising to 6.88 million from 3.83 million. That is seven times faster than the general population and "makes them far and away the most rapidly growing" ethnic group in the country, Mr. Hollmann said.  Some Figures Are Startling</p>
        <p>In some of states, the growth of the Asian-American population is stunning: New Jersey, up 162 percent to 272,521; Texas, up 165.5 percent to 319,459, and Rhode Island, up 245 percent to 18,325.</p>
        <p>The 124 percent increase in Alabama means there are now about 22,000 Asian-Americans in this state, whose overall population increased by 3.6 percent in a decade. The Asian-American population in Mississippi went up almost 76 percent, to about 13,000, while the overall state population increased 2.1 percent. Louisiana's Asian-American population went up almost 73 percent, to just over 41,000, while the overall population went up only three-tenths of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>The figures for California, home to about one-third of all Asian-Americans, have not yet been released. But in 1988, state researchers estimated that Asians had reached 9.3 percent of the state's population, surpassing the black population of 7.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Over all, the growth of the Asian-American population has been so large and widespread that "Asians are just becoming part of the landscape," said Stanley Karnow, the Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist and author who is writing a book about Asians in America. "Where in the past they were odd and exotic, now they are accepted."</p>
        <p>And in many ways, they are changing the landscape. On Feb. 15, firecrackers pierced the morning in Bayou La Batre as Tu Phuc and other immigrants celebrated Tet, the Vietnamese lunar New Year festival. Until recently, most people here associated Tet with the 1968 Communist offensive that changed the course of the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tu, a refugee from Saigon, settled here in 1985 as Vietnamese, Cambodians and Laotians flocked to the warm climate and jobs in the shrimp and crab business that were being abandoned by white and black workers who left for higher-paying jobs in Mobile.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tu, an ethnic Chinese who fled Vietnam on a small fishing boat in 1977, now runs the grocery store, which sells sacks of rice from Thailand, chili sauce and cassette tapes of Vietnamese music stars. He also owns a pool hall frequented by Vietnamese, and some fishing boats, trailers and apartments.</p>
        <p>"It is just like in Saigon; the Chinese ran the stores there, and they run the stores for Vietnamese here," Mr. Tu said, speaking in Chinese. He sends his three children to a Roman Catholic school 40 minutes away. "I am a Chinese and want them to get the best education," he said.</p>
        <p>The heavy influx of immigrants has sharply altered the composition of the Asian population in the United States. Until 1970, two-thirds of all Asian-Americans were of Japanese or Chinese descent, and most were members of families that had been here since the late 19th or early 20th century. Most also lived in urban concentrations, like the Chinatowns in New York and San Franciso.  Is a Term a Myth?</p>
        <p>The flow of immigrants has changed the ethnic balance radically. Whereas in 1970, Japanese formed the largest group, in 1980 Chinese surpassed them, and in 1990 Filipinos jumped over them, according to a report by Leon F. Bouvier for the Center for Migration Studies in New York. Mr. Bouvier estimated that in 1990 there were 1.4 million Filipinos, 1.26 million Chinese, 859,000 Vietnamese, 814,000 Koreans, 804,000 Japanese, 684,000 Asian-Indians and 706,000 others, including Cambodians, Laotians and Pacific Islanders.</p>
        <p>Given this diversity of national origins -- and perhaps an even greater diversity in social classes among the immigrants between peasants and nuclear physicists -- some Asian-American leaders say it is misleading to use the term "Asian-American" at all.</p>
        <p>"Asian-American is a myth," said K. W. Lee, editor of The Korea Times in Los Angeles. "You have Chinese who have lived here for 100 years, Koreans who have just arrived, and poor Cambodian and Laotian refugees who are living lives of quiet desperation."</p>
        <p>From 1985 to 1989, Asian immigration figures ranged from 268,000 to 281,000l annually, said Michael Hoefer, chief of demographic statistics for the Immigration and Naturalization Service. The Philippines, with an average of 50,000 immigrants a year in the latter half of the decade, was the leadig source of Asian and Pacific Island immigrants.  Turning Point in 1965</p>
        <p>The combined annual figures for China, Taiwan and Hong Kong from 1985 to 1989 averaged more than 40,000, while the number of immigrants from South Korea averaged 35,000 a year, Mr. Hoefer said.</p>
        <p>The key to this surge was a 1965 change in the immigration law by President Lyndon B. Johnson that removed restrictions on Asians that had been in place since early in the century.</p>
        <p>As a result, the number of Asian-Americans jumped from 891,000 in 1960 to 1.4 million in 1970, and then to 3.8 million in 1980, according to the Census Bureau. Demographers say it may be close to 7 million for 1990.</p>
        <p>Another change in the immigration law last year, giving greater preference to applicants with certain skills, is expected to further increase the flow of Asians, many of whom are nurses, doctors, engineers and scientists, Mr. Hoefer said.</p>
        <p>The new Asian immigrants have tended to cluster in towns or cities where a friend or relative first settled, following patterns of earlier waves of Irish, Italian, Polish and Jewish immigrants from Europe.  Drawn by Countrymen</p>
        <p>In Rhode Island, much of the growth of the Asian population began with two Cambodian students who found themselves unable to return to their homeland after it fell to the Khmer Rouge in 1975. They then offered to sponsor Cambodian refugee families, who in turn sponsored other families, said Sophai Moeuy, a former sergeant in the Cambodian army who fled to a refugee camp in Thailand in 1978.</p>
        <p>"When my time came to leave the camp, I did not know where I was supposed to go," said Mr. Moeuy, who is now a postal worker in Providence. "But when I went to my interview, I told them I had a friend named Pally Nak who had lived in the camp before who was now in the United States. I showed them a piece of paper with his address in the United States, and they took me here. I didn't now if it was cold or snow or hot here. I didn't know anything. But here I am."  Starting a Community</p>
        <p>In the pine woods of Alabama between Bayou La Batre and Mobile, a group of Cambodian families have bought 200 acres of land, started their own crab processing plant, moved in some trailers and erected a makeshift Buddhist temple.</p>
        <p>The Cambodians, like many of the Vietnamese, were originally brought to the area by the Mobile office of Catholic Social Services, which helps them with English classes and job counseling. The Cambodians also renamed the dusty road where the temple sits, calling it South Angkor Street, after the medieval capital of Cambodia.</p>
        <p>In Birmingham, many Chinese and Koreans and some Japanese have come as students or scholars to the University of Alabama at Birmingham and its large medical center. Yoshimi Saito, a gentle, graying 52-year-old professor of mathematics arrived in 1983 from Kyoto, at first somewhat skeptical. "I had never heard of a Southern mathematician," he said in the living room of his comfortable ranch-style house in the hilly suburb of Homewood.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Saito expresses satisfaction with his move now. He says he has felt no racial prejudice. He is a member of a Southern Baptist church. And his daughter, Yoriko, did so well in high school that the school sent her to the University of Alabama for her science classes starting in her sophomore year. When she graduated, she finished third nationally in the Westinghouse Science Talent Search. She is now part of a special joint graduate program at the Harvard Medical School and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>At the Great Wall restaurant in Birmingham, Candice Diong and Jet Wee Ong are the managers, as well as being husband and wife. They are both Chinese from Malaysia who met after they came to Alabama to college.</p>
        <p>"Birmingham sure has changed since I came here in 1984," Mr. Ong said. "There were only a half dozen Chinese restaurants here then; now there are 60. It used to be quite difficult to explain to people what an egg roll is. Now they're just like french fries."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
