<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets' Brogna Hits the Scene With Some Lofty Goals</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="829936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS ATLANTA BRAVES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIS, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROGNA, RICO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DC1239F937A25751C0A960958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets' Brogna Hits the Scene With Some Lofty Goals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE WILLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILLIS, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla., Feb. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rico Brogna is a fitting prototype to the Mets' youth movement: 20-something  yet disciplined, even tempered and cerebral.</p>
        <p>Like his teammates, he understands the expectations they have generated for themselves after fashioning a 44-31 record after the All-Star break last season  and tying the Philadelphia Phillies for second place in the National League East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rico Brogna is a fitting prototype to the Mets' youth movement: 20-something  yet disciplined, even tempered and cerebral.</p>
        <p>Like his teammates, he understands the expectations they have generated for themselves after fashioning a 44-31 record after the All-Star break last season  and tying the Philadelphia Phillies for second place in the National League East.</p>
        <p>With the pitchers and catchers scheduled to report Wednesday, and full squad workouts to begin next Monday, there is talk within the clubhouse of the Mets earning a wild-card berth in 1996, a goal set primarily because the World Series champion Atlanta Braves are the overwhelming favorite to repeat as division winners.</p>
        <p>Call it youthful bravado, February optimism or maybe the sudden exposure to the 70-degree Florida sun, but Brogna thinks the Mets can do better than a wild-card berth. He sincerely believes the Mets can dethrone the Braves in the East and he wants his teammates to believe it, too.</p>
        <p>"Why should we set our sights on a wild card when we can get the pennant?" Brogna said today in the middle of the clubhouse at the Mets' spring training facility. "Everybody expects the Braves to win it and no doubt they're solid. But we have to feel as though we can win it, too. We've got to set our goals high and that means being the best team in the division."</p>
        <p>The Braves finished 21 games ahead of the Mets and Phillies before disposing  of the Rockies, Reds and Indians in the post-season. For the Mets to make up that kind of ground, it will take a near-perfect season, something that may be hard to attain for a team that figures to be one of the youngest in baseball.</p>
        <p>"Sure, it's going to take a lot of things to get there," Brogna said. "We have to remain healthy and we have to have good seasons from a lot of people. But if we get the kind of pitching I think we're going to get, and play the kind of defense I think we can play, we'll be successful. The main thing is we have to maintain the kind of work ethic we had last season. We have to remember why we were successful in the second half last year."</p>
        <p>That work ethic and enthusiasm were evident today. Brogna, coming off a season in which he solidified himself as the team's first baseman by hitting .289 with a team-leading 22 home runs and 76 runs batted in, arrived last Wednesday to begin workouts. Infielder Jeff Kent arrived four days before him.</p>
        <p>Also arriving before Wednesday's reporting date were pitchers Bill Pulsipher, Jason Isringhausen, Jerry DiPoto, Blas Minor, Bobby Jones, Dave Mlicki and the highly touted prospect Paul Wilson.</p>
        <p>Catcher Todd Hundley has checked in along with the veteran closer John Franco. "I'm at my fighting weight, 185," Franco said as he stepped on the scales.</p>
        <p>Entering his 12th major league season, Franco knows all too well how quickly  spring optimism can turn to false hopes by June or July. A sign in the clubhouse alludes to that: "If what you did yesterday still looks big, you haven't done much today."</p>
        <p>"Hope is good, but talk is cheap," said Franco, who had 29 saves and a 2.44 earned run average last year. "You have to go out there and do it. We can't look ahead and figure out whether we should be a wild-card team or whatever."</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
