<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Return From an Injury, Pianist Switches to Mozart</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="829918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA, PA, USA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PERAHIA, MURRAY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA ORCHESTRA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLAND, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAWALLISCH, WOLFGANG MURRAY PERAHIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5DC1239F937A25751C0A960958260" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Return From an Injury, Pianist Switches to Mozart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLLAND, BERNARD;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Murray Perahia returned to Carnegie Hall on Monday night, playing the piano with the Philadelphia Orchestra under Wolfgang Sawallisch. His absence these past few seasons has been troubling. Various explanations have been given for the hand injury that laid Mr. Perahia low, but it is hard not to suspect that his determined forays into the heaviest piano literature played a part.</p>
        <p>It was originally to have been an all-Beethoven evening, with Mr. Perahia playing the "Emperor" Concerto. Mozart was offered in substitution: the E Flat Concerto (K.271). It was good to hear this musician of the piano. Flawless technical clarity and elegant poetry rarely converse so naturally. Mr. Perahia strips music making of every pretentious gesture. His respect for rhythm and note values is exemplary, and on Monday he invested this respect with a special  sense of joy. He seemed glad to be back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Murray Perahia returned to Carnegie Hall on Monday night, playing the piano with the Philadelphia Orchestra under Wolfgang Sawallisch. His absence these past few seasons has been troubling. Various explanations have been given for the hand injury that laid Mr. Perahia low, but it is hard not to suspect that his determined forays into the heaviest piano literature played a part.</p>
        <p>It was originally to have been an all-Beethoven evening, with Mr. Perahia playing the "Emperor" Concerto. Mozart was offered in substitution: the E Flat Concerto (K.271). It was good to hear this musician of the piano. Flawless technical clarity and elegant poetry rarely converse so naturally. Mr. Perahia strips music making of every pretentious gesture. His respect for rhythm and note values is exemplary, and on Monday he invested this respect with a special  sense of joy. He seemed glad to be back.</p>
        <p>The Mozart is not a small piece, but a large, unexpected explosion emerging  from a 21-year-old and seemingly out of nowhere. At the first bars, the solo piano steps out and announces what is to come. It is a gesture against all convention of the time and not really repeated until Beethoven's G Major Concerto almost 30 years later. The slow movement is vast and operatic. I think  Mr. Perahia makes the finale too fast, rendering quick passage work a rhythmic blur and creating impossible tasks of articulation for the corresponding violin  parts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perahia's agility seems intact. His tone color has the same inner life it always had. And the concerto at hand was the music that he has always served most faithfully. In the recent past, he showed us and himself that he can indeed play the Brahms concertos and the Liszt "Mefisto Waltz." I hope he did not pay too high a price in the process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sawallisch continues to serve this wonderful orchestra in the happiest of ways. The "Egmont" Overture was full of dignity and good sense and utilized the  natural sonorous qualities of the string sections. I would have preferred a little less haste in the opening movement of the "Pastoral" Symphony and a little relief from the long, unbroken legato phrases. One can disagree with what Mr. Sawallisch does and still admire the sincere thinking behind it.</p>
        <p>The first movement of the "Pastoral" was also an example of how beautiful execution can work against music. What empowers Beethoven's descriptive writing  here is the metric argument of two beats against three beats. These "incompatible" metric cells compete; they call to one another throughout the orchestra and often talk at the same time.</p>
        <p>It is this indivisibility of two against three that stirs the juices of this  wonderful music, gives it its gently roiling energy. Yet so smooth, homogeneous  and warm is the Philadelphia sound that the disputes are barely noticed, smothered instead in all-consuming loveliness. Period-instrument orchestras, with their grittier sound and stark separations of color, do not always have the winning arguments at musicological debates, but in the case of the "Pastoral" they score a few points.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
