<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Korea Chief Says North Received Cash in Bid for Peace</title>
    <meta content="Y14KORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/14/international/asia/14KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roh Moo Hyun</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Korea</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kim Dae Jung</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D7153AF937A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Korea Chief Says North Received Cash in Bid for Peace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">South Korea Chief Says North Received Cash in Bid for Peace</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Friday, Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South Korean Pres Kim Dae Jung, whose term ends Feb 25, apologizes to his country over scandal involving large transfers of cash to North Korea; says he sought to promote 'peace and the national interest'; admits no wrongdoing; does not directly address core allegation that cash payments of $192 million yielded Seoul landmark summit meeting with North Korea in 2000; opposition politicians have hammered away at Kim, saying his Nobel Peace Prize in 2000 was 'bought'; Roh Moo Hyun, Kim's successor, has sent mixed signals about mounting scandal, both promising an investigation and saying matter must be resolved through political settlement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting to blunt opposition calls for a criminal investigation, the South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, apologized to the country today over a scandal involving large transfers of cash to North Korea, saying he had sought only to promote ''peace and the national interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim, whose term ends on Feb. 25, admitted no wrongdoing in his address, and appealed to South Korean political parties to ''make a special political decision in the national interest'' and drop the case, invoking an increasingly tense standoff between North Korea and the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, apologized to the country over a scandal involving large transfers of cash to North Korea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acting to blunt opposition calls for a criminal investigation, the South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, apologized to the country today over a scandal involving large transfers of cash to North Korea, saying he had sought only to promote ''peace and the national interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim, whose term ends on Feb. 25, admitted no wrongdoing in his address, and appealed to South Korean political parties to ''make a special political decision in the national interest'' and drop the case, invoking an increasingly tense standoff between North Korea and the United States.</p>
        <p>''Now is a time of rising tensions on the Korean peninsula and the serious North Korean nuclear issue, as well as an impending Iraq war, which will have a huge impact on our country,'' Mr. Kim said.</p>
        <p>The issue of Hyundai Merchant Marine sending money to North Korea caused ''great controversy and concern'' among the people, he said in a televised address. ''I feel very sorry about this. I shall take responsibility for this situation, but I ask the people to understand that this was done in sincerity in the interest of peace and the national interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim did not directly address the core allegation that cash payments of $192 million yielded Seoul a landmark summit meeting with the North. Senior presidential advisers denied that, saying the payments went toward a South Korean industrial park in North Korea, which Hyundai would operate exclusively.</p>
        <p>The scandal, which has unfolded with North Korea's nuclear brinkmanship, has badly tarnished the reputation of the outgoing president. Opposition politicians, in particular, have hammered away at Mr. Kim saying that his Nobel Peace Prize in 2000 was ''bought.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim has been shielded from attack to some extent by the election of his successor, Roh Moo Hyun, who is a member of the ruling Millennium Democratic Party, and has sworn to pursue the strategy of engagement with North Korea, known as sunshine policy.</p>
        <p>Since his election in December, Mr. Roh has sent mixed signals about the mounting scandal, both promising an investigation, and saying that the matter must be resolved through a political settlement.</p>
        <p>Last month, South Korean government auditors announced an investigation had shown a unit of the Hyundai conglomerate had funneled about $192 million from a government-supplied loan to North Korea.</p>
        <p>At issue is how the money was used and the role of government officials in a web of cash transfers, some of which took place just a day before Kim met the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il in Pyongyang in June 2000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
