<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earnhardt Rolls, but Big Race Is Sunday</title>
    <meta content="14AUTO$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/14/sports/othersports/14AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budweiser Shootout (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Daytona 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Earnhardt, Dale Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Earnhardt, Dale Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D6153AF937A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earnhardt Rolls, but Big Race Is Sunday</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before Big Race, Earnhardt Rolls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla., Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr wins Budweiser Shootout auto race and 125-mile qualifying race for Daytona 500; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second time in five days, Dale Earnhardt Jr. won the privilege today of standing atop the door of his red Chevrolet at Daytona International Speedway and whooping.</p>
        <p>He would say later that getting to do all this whooping before the Daytona 500, and not after it, kind of scares him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dale Earnhardt Jr. has been nearly invincible in preparation for the Daytona 500, which is to be run Sunday for the 45th time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second time in five days, Dale Earnhardt Jr. won the privilege today of standing atop the door of his red Chevrolet at Daytona International Speedway and whooping.</p>
        <p>He would say later that getting to do all this whooping before the Daytona 500, and not after it, kind of scares him.</p>
        <p>''It seems like every time we do something good, it stacks the odds against us even worse to win the 500,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt has been nearly invincible in preparation for the Daytona 500, which is to be run Sunday for the 45th time. Earnhardt, who won the Budweiser Shootout here on Saturday, rolled to victory in the second of two 125-mile qualifying races today.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt did not even have to win today's race to make the field because he had posted the second-fastest speed in time trials on Monday, and the top two qualifiers are guaranteed spots in the 43-car field.</p>
        <p>He admitted he was disappointed with qualifying second because he had lost the pole to Jeff Green. Although Green drives for Richard Childress Racing, a good team, Earnhardt said politely that Green never should have beaten him.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt said he did not think it was out of the question to win the Budweiser Shootout, the 125-mile qualifying race, a Busch Grand National race Saturday and the Daytona 500. No one has done that.</p>
        <p>''You spend an awful lot of money to come down here to finish second,'' Earnhardt said.</p>
        <p>Yet one more time, he sounded like the son of a legend.</p>
        <p>His father, Dale Earnhardt Sr., won a record 34 races at Daytona International Speedway. But Earnhardt Sr. won the Daytona 500 only once, in 1998.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt Jr., 28, remembered today how bitter some of his father's losses were. Earnhardt Sr. lost a race in 1990 to Derrike Cope, a Nascar journeyman, when one of his tires went flat on the last lap.</p>
        <p>And Earnhardt Sr. died here two years ago, on the last lap of a race in which Michael Waltrip beat Earnhardt Jr. to the finish line. Waltrip and Earnhardt Jr. still drive for the team started by Earnhardt Sr.</p>
        <p>''It means as much to me,'' Earnhardt Jr. said of the Daytona 500. ''The strange thing about it is that I have a chance to win it so early.''</p>
        <p>That is because Dale Earnhardt Inc. has become a force on the two Winston Cup racetracks, Daytona and Talladega, that mandate using restrictor plates, which limit the flow of air from the carburetor to the engine. Either Waltrip or Earnhardt Jr. has won three of the last four races at Daytona; Earnhardt Inc. drivers have won six of the last eight at Daytona and Talladega. Waltrip was second to Earnhardt today.</p>
        <p>''We have an unbelievable engine room,'' Waltrip said. ''I wish everybody could see it. But you can't.''</p>
        <p>Earnhardt Jr. and Waltrip are considered the favorites to win Sunday. The only others given a chance are employed by Childress: Green, Kevin Harvick and Robby Gordon, the winner of today's first race.</p>
        <p>Asked to gauge the importance of his victory, Gordon said: ''I don't know if it means anything, other than we have a fast race car. Perception is kind of reality in this garage.''</p>
        <p>Rusty Wallace, who finished fourth to Earnhardt, was delighted to keep pace. Then Nascar officials discovered that Wallace may have used illegal equipment. He will not be disqualified, a Winston Cup spokesman said, but his starting position is in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Earnhardt cruises along. He is bothered. Sometimes, he said in much saltier language, the fastest car does not win the race. Tony Stewart won the Winston Cup championship last year after finishing last in the Daytona 500.</p>
        <p>''When you've got 43 players here at the poker table, it's a little harder,'' said Stewart, who finished fifth in the race won by Earnhardt Jr.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt had a strong car last year, but he ran over debris dropped from Waltrip's car and finished 29th. It was the start of a frustrating season in which Earnhardt won only two races and finished 11th in the drivers' standing.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to put together a year that we need,'' Earnhardt said.</p>
        <p>Waltrip could help by providing drafting help. But he is here to win, too. He had a chance to pass Earnhardt for the lead today but figured it was not worth tearing up his car in a qualifying race. Sunday, Waltrip said, will be different.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, whose father drove for Childress, said that Green and Harvick did not get along, then playfully hinted that Childress would eventually need to change his drivers.</p>
        <p>That was pure gamesmanship. The truth is that Earnhardt is not sure he will ever have another chance to win the Daytona 500. Maybe 15 years from now, he said, he will look back at the opportunity that slipped away now.</p>
        <p>''Well, hopefully, I'll win it, and I won't have to worry about that,'' Earnhardt said.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
