<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NICARAGUA USING A NEW CURRENCY</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="384448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NICARAGUA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">UHLIG, MARK A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHAMORRO, VIOLETA BARRIOS DE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB173CF935A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NICARAGUA USING A NEW CURRENCY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK A. UHLIG, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UHLIG, MARK A</byline>
      <dateline>MANAGUA, Nicaragua, Sept. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the bitterest days of the conflict between this country's former Sandinista leaders and American-backed rebels, all Nicaraguans shared one crucial piece of common ground: their reliance on the American dollar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the bitterest days of the conflict between this country's former Sandinista leaders and American-backed rebels, all Nicaraguans shared one crucial piece of common ground: their reliance on the American dollar.</p>
        <p>In the bitterest days of the conflict between this country's former Sandinista leaders and American-backed rebels, all Nicaraguans shared one crucial piece of common ground: their reliance on the American dollar.</p>
        <p>Against a background of economic sanctions and hyperinflation, Sandinistas and contra supporters alike scrambled to convert their Nicaraguan cordobas to American currency. Sandinista leaders created an elaborate empire of official dollar-based stores and enterprises to help keep their cash-starved government afloat.</p>
        <p>Now, with the war years presumably behind it, Nicaragua's new Government is attempting to break free from the economic legacy of that chaotic era - not by breaking the country's addiction to the dollar, but by embracing it.</p>
        <p>Gradual Introduction</p>
        <p>Backed by $900 million in foreign commitments to help shore up the country's foundering economy, economic advisers to President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro have inaugurated an entirely new, convertible hard currency that is to be pegged permanently to the value of the American dollar.</p>
        <p>The new money, known as the gold cordoba, is being introduced gradually as a complete replacement for the current inflation-battered cordoba. Government officials say it is to be backed on a strict one-to-one basis with official dollar reserves, making it, in effect, a direct local substitute for the American bills that Nicaraguan black-marketers now wave at potential buyers on street corners throughout the country.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the old cordoba, which does not circulate internationally and is thus considered a ''soft'' currency, the gold cordoba is to remain freely convertible with American dollars.</p>
        <p>Economic Straitjacket</p>
        <p>The rigid, one-for-one structure would have the effect of imposing an economic straitjacket on the new government, eliminating its ability to finance its future deficits simply by printing money. But Government economists assert that such a radical, self-imposed solution is the only reliable means of choking off annual inflation that has reached as high as 36,000 percent in recent years.</p>
        <p>''What we want to do with the gold cordoba is to erase the memory of hyperinflation in the people's minds,'' said Francisco Mayorga Balladares, the new president of Nicaragua's central bank, who has been the driving force behind the new currency. ''No one will believe a promise to allow just a little inflation. If you want to convince people in a country like this, you have to have a firm commitment that inflation will disappear.''</p>
        <p>The introduction of the new currency, which was first suggested by Mr. Mayorga in his capacity as chief economic adviser to Mrs. Chamorro's election campaign in February, began in May with the introduction of the gold cordoba as a unit of account for Government bank credits.</p>
        <p>Transition Produces Hardships</p>
        <p>Beginning July 1, the Government began calculating taxes in the new currency. The new bills themselves then began appearing on the street last month, and the new money now accounts for $2.5 million of the $50.7 million in national currency now in circulation, according to the central bank.</p>
        <p>The switch to accounting with the gold cordoba has produced an immediate crisis for hundreds of thousands of Nicaraguans who are paid in old cordobas and must pay for electric power, telephone services, gasoline and other necessary purchases in the new currency. The old cordoba floats against the new currency in the same way as it did for years against the dollar on the black market.</p>
        <p>Since May, inflation has already stripped the old cordoba of five-sixths of its value relative to the new currency. The resulting hardships have produced a sharp political backlash that has been reflected in Sandinista slogans and widespread graffiti declaring that ''The cordoba of gold is the cordoba of hunger,'' and ''We aren't paid in gold; we don't pay in gold.''</p>
        <p>Officials Discount Opposition</p>
        <p>''It is not possible to tranquilize an entire people with the fetish of a new currency, one that today scarcely exists and that tomorrow will inevitably be devalued,'' declared the official Sandinista newspaper, Barricada, in a recent editorial.</p>
        <p>Government officials discount the opposition to the new currency, arguing that some degree of public shock was inevitable, and that economic indicators show that the country is quickly adjusting to the new money.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the gold cordoba say its ultimate effect will be to move Nicaragua's economy closer to the model of Panama, which uses the American dollar as its official currency.</p>
        <p>Praise From Other Countries</p>
        <p>Nicaragua's public sector deficit has been reduced from $35 million a month in May to $11 million in August, largely through the effect of the new currency in eliminating indirect subsidies that had been created through exchange rate fluctuations. Savings in the new cordoba have grown rapidly with each passing month, according to central bank figures.</p>
        <p>The new currency has also received strong praise from foreign countries, including the United States, which has pressed the Government to speed up the transition to the new currency. Government officials have insisted that a full transition must follow, not lead, other progress toward economic recovery, and have set no firm date for achieving it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
