<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Lots of People Feel pain, Is That a Recession?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="384425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB163CF935A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Lots of People Feel pain, Is That a Recession?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Whatever the statistics say, millions of Americans have concluded in recent weeks that the United States is in a recession. They are probably overstating the case. But if the word recession is heard more and more, it certainly reflects the hardship, both actual and anticipated, that is spreading across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Whatever the statistics say, millions of Americans have concluded in recent weeks that the United States is in a recession. They are probably overstating the case. But if the word recession is heard more and more, it certainly reflects the hardship, both actual and anticipated, that is spreading across the country.</p>
        <p>Whatever the statistics say, millions of Americans have concluded in recent weeks that the United States is in a recession. They are probably overstating the case. But if the word recession is heard more and more, it certainly reflects the hardship, both actual and anticipated, that is spreading across the country.</p>
        <p>Consider these numbers:</p>
        <p>* Employment is shrinking in most of the nation. Until May, this had been the case only in New England and a few Midwestern states. But by August, the Labor Department found that over the previous year employment had fallen in six of the nation's nine regions, covering 33 states. ''The story isn't so much layoffs as companies not replacing people who leave,'' said Thomas Plewes, a Labor Department economist.</p>
        <p>* Consumer confidence, as measured by various national polls, plunged steeply in August, after the Mideast shock. In past recessions, such sudden drops often appeared in the early months. What happens is that people become fearful about their jobs and the future and they stop making purchases. ''My sense is that the Mideast shock has not worn off and confidence remains very low in September,'' says Richard T. Curtin, director of the University of Michigan's consumer survey.</p>
        <p>* Retail sales, as if on cue, dropped sharply in August, the Commerce Department reported Friday. The total spent on gasoline should have risen enough, because of higher fuel prices, to offset lower spending elsewhere. But cutbacks in other categories were so sharp that total sales fell six-tenths of 1 percent -resuming a decline that had been in progress all year, except for June and July.</p>
        <p>* In August, for the first time in a year, household income failed to rise in tandem with inflation. Smaller raises, fewer new jobs, less overtime, higher inflation from rising gasoline prices all combined to reverse the pattern. Personal disposable income, which is what people have left to spend after paying their taxes, fell by roughly six-tenths of 1 percent, after adjustment for inflation, said Stephen S. Roach, a senior economist at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company. ''When you have a really ugly turn on the income front, like this one, that is a classic signal that the economy is in trouble,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There was, of course, bad news before August. Construction spending dried up last spring, and the real estate market softened in much of the country. Defense cutbacks brought thousands of layoffs. And budget cutting meant the Government would play a shrinking role in the spending that keeps an economy going. Still, the view that a recession has arrived meets with considerable resistance at the Federal Reserve, an arbiter of economic trends, and among economists in general. ''The economy is like a taut cord: you have to keep pushing it down to make it stay down,'' said Paul Samuelson, the Nobel laureate in economics. ''It simply does not have a tendency to stagnate on its own. That is a notion we inherited from the 1930's that does not apply to the postwar period.''</p>
        <p>For a recession to occur, the economy has to contract for six straight months, a phenomenon that by definition is hard to document until well after it's happened. A prestigious research institute, the National Bureau of Economic Research, rules on when recessions begin and end, delegating this task to a committee of seven prominent economists. But the committee hasn't met since July 8, 1983, when it declared that the 1981-82 recession had ended the previous November.</p>
        <p>The committee members do not like to meet until they have agreed among themselves, in telephone conversations, that enough evidence exists to pinpoint a turn in the economy. ''It is certainly possible that we might have another meeting soon if conditions continue to develop as they are,'' said Geoffrey Moore, a member from Columbia University. ''We generally wait until the evidence is pretty decisive before we spend the money on plane fares and hotel rooms.''</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Moore, who runs Columbia's Center for International Business Cycle Research, isn't ready to insist on a gathering, he is gradually coming to the view that a recession has started. ''It is not at all certain,'' he said, ''but if a recession is under way, the likely starting month was probably June.''</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve, more than any other Government body, has the power to reverse the deterioration, by lowering interest rates. Lower rates, in turn, encourage people and companies to borrow and spend, thus stimulating the economy. But the Fed has lately resisted making any rate changes. As a result, interest on most mortgages and consumer loans remains above 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The prevailing view among the Fed's 18 policymakers, as expressed by several of them in interviews, is that inflation - currently averaging more than 5 percent this year, as measured by the Consumer Price Index - is a greater long-term threat than recession. Specifically, they worry that stimulating the economy by trying to push down interest rates would only increase the odds of severe inflation in 1991.</p>
        <p>The Middle East crisis has exacerbated the Federal Reserve's concern over inflation and so, undoubtedly, did the report Friday that the Producer Price Index for finished goods had risen by an alarming 1.3 percent in August, mostly because of higher oil prices. ''Monetary policy has to be patient and not darting here to there based on the latest statistics,'' said Wayne Angell, a Federal Reserve governor. ''There are signs,'' he added, ''that there will be some upward movement in the economy early next year.''</p>
        <p>In a similar vein, Robert Black, president of the Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond, said: ''Most of us at the Federal Reserve would take a little economic sacrifice in the short run if we thought the long-term trade-off, in reduced inflation, far exceeded the short-term discomfort.''</p>
        <p>What the Federal Reserve is counting on, of course, is that the discomfort will not turn into official recession. A recession requires quite a bit of deterioration. The nation's wealth, as measured by the Gross National Product, would have to contract for six straight months. For the first time in years, there would be an end to the ever greater production of manufactured goods and the rising outlays for the thousands of services that Americans perform.</p>
        <p>Through most of the 1980's, the G.N.P. grew by 3 percent a year or more, and many economists thought that the strong performance had continued well into 1989 - until the Commerce Department revised its figures in July. The new numbers showed that the economy, instead of growing strongly, had expanded since March of 1989 by just enough to stave off recession.</p>
        <p>Most recently, in the second quarter of this year, the G.N.P. rose by only $12 billion, after adjustment for inflation, representing a minuscule annual growth rate of 1.2 percent for an economy that generates $4.16 trillion a year in wealth.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the case for no recession has some arguments going for it. Auto and truck sales, for example, are holding steady at an annual rate of more than 14 million units, although many of the buyers are car rental companies. ''Sales to individuals have weakened, but not to recession levels,'' said Wynn Van Bussman, an economist at the Chrysler Corporation. More important, inventories have not shot up.</p>
        <p>Indeed, inventories in all industries have not shot up. That is what ushers in a classic recession: Goods pile up, orders are canceled, factories slash production and lay off workers, and unemployment surges.</p>
        <p>Such havoc has not yet appeared, perhaps because exports have taken up the slack as domestic retail sales have declined. Or perhaps Americans have not felt compelled to economize, although events in the Persian Gulf and the tight job market might now be changing their minds.</p>
        <p>Or perhaps the current economic slowdown will develop differently from those of the past because of the huge debts that consumers have accumulated. The argument here is an ironic one. If a recession developed, many indebted companies and individuals might be forced into bankruptcy, making the recession unusually severe.</p>
        <p>But some economists argue that Americans are well along in the process of working their way out of their debt problems. Just as the boom years of the 1980's reflected the big spending that rising debt made possible, the economic sluggishness of the last 18 months reflects a steady decline in new borrowing, particularly by the private sector.</p>
        <p>Total debt rose at 12 percent or more a year in the mid-1980's, according to Federal Reserve data. But since 1987, there has been a sharp decline, and in the first quarter of 1990, debt for all sectors of the economy except the Federal Government rose at an annual rate of only 6.3 percent, the lowest since 1982, a recession year.</p>
        <p>''Rather than a severe recession, we are going to have a long workout from the excesses of debt,'' says Albert T. Sommers, a senior economist at the Conference Board. ''And we won't have an upturn until people feel able to borrow easily again.''  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
