<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Your Corner Drugstore</title>
    <meta content="11DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="N.J. AND COMPANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Willingboro (Nj)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merck-Medco Rx Services (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Warner, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DB1F39F932A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Your Corner Drugstore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN WARNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Warner, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>WILLINGBORO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Merck-Medco Rx Services, new mail order prescription center that is opening in Willingboro, NJ; facility, when it is fully operational in 2003, will be world's largest pharmacy, dispensing 700,000 prescriptions a week; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALVIN G. WASDYKE is no corner druggist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasdyke is the registered pharmacist at Merck-Medco Rx Services' new mail order prescription center here, and by 2003 -- when the facility is fully up and running -- it will be the world's largest pharmacy, dispensing 700,000 prescriptions a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALVIN G. WASDYKE is no corner druggist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasdyke is the registered pharmacist at Merck-Medco Rx Services' new mail order prescription center here, and by 2003 -- when the facility is fully up and running -- it will be the world's largest pharmacy, dispensing 700,000 prescriptions a week.</p>
        <p>And each bottle will have Mr. Wasdyke's name on it.</p>
        <p>''I never met another Wasdyke,'' he said. ''Now the name will be everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Wasdyke will have some help filling those bottles when the pharmacy opens tomorrow. Already, 50 pharmacists and 400 other employees are working at the pharmacy site -- or about half the full complement that will be on the job by the time the operation is at capacity.</p>
        <p>Merck-Medco of Franklin Lakes serves 65 million Americans as a pharmacy benefit manager, which administers prescription drug plans for private insurance companies, corporations and governments. With revenue of $23 billion last year, it is the nation's largest pharmacy benefit manager measured by sales.</p>
        <p>A subsidiary of Merck &amp; Company, the drug manufacturer Merck-Medco already operates 12 mail-order pharmacies from its headquarters in Whitehouse Station. Last year it filled 450 million prescriptions through its own pharmacies and a network of retailers.</p>
        <p>To develop the pharmacy here -- which the company said would generate $35 million a year in wages and benefits -- Merck-Medco received a $2.8 million state grant.</p>
        <p>With the new center, the company said it expected to continue to gain share in the country's growing prescription drug market. According to the National Institute for Healthcare Management Foundation, the number of prescriptions filled in the United States is expected to rise to four billion a year by 2005, from three billion last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasdyke said the new automated facility would help Merck-Medco cut down on human error. And by operating on huge volumes, he said it would run more efficiently, saving consumers time and money.</p>
        <p>In 1998 Merck and Merck-Medco settled charges brought by the Federal Trade Commission stemming from Merck's 1993 acquisition of Medco. The commission had accused Merck of giving Medco an advantageous price to promote its drugs over competitors'.</p>
        <p>To try to prevent such charges from being leveled again, Mr. Wasdyke said the companies would operate with a firm boundary between them. ''To Merck we are basically another retail pharmacy,'' he said. ''There is a firewall for information that is passed between Merck and Merck-Medco.''</p>
        <p>The 282,000-square-foot building -- the first phase of a redevelopment plan for a 1950's-era shopping plaza on Route 130 that will also include a local college, township library and an amphitheater -- -- is filled with a maze of automatic filling equipment linked by conveyor belts and controlled by bar-code scanners. To guarantee that patients end up with the correct right medication, each prescription is scanned several hundred times as it makes its half-hour journey through the building.</p>
        <p>''The scanners are constantly feeding back the information on where the patient's order is and where it is going to go next,'' said Mr. Wasdyke.</p>
        <p>The site, which was once home to a Boscov's Department Store, had been vacant for five years. Merck, now poised to become one of Willingboro's five largest employers,  added an additional 100,000 square feet to the structure, which now has a checkerboard facade.</p>
        <p>The process of filling an order begins when Merck-Medco receives a prescription by mail, through a customer call center or over the Internet. Pharmacists at one of Merck-Medco's 12 other mail-order pharmacies check the prescription for problems: Is the doctor's signature legible? Will the medicine interact with another drug the patient is taking? Will the patient's insurance pay?</p>
        <p>If everything checks out, the prescription is relayed by computer to Willingboro. There, a white pill bottle begins its journey through the facility nestled in a pre-assigned location in a rubber case with room for 24 bottles.</p>
        <p>In the main dispensing room, Merck-Medco pharmacists in white coats load 1,920 metal boxes, or one-by one-foot ''cells'' -- with 900 different types of medications. To enter the room, employees must lay their right hand on a security sensor that takes a three-dimensional reading of their palms.</p>
        <p>When a prescription bottle passes under the right cell, a scanner announces its presence and the correct amount of medication is automatically released.</p>
        <p>Just to be sure, workers called ''bottle stoppers'' lean over the cases as they emerge from under the filling cells. They are looking for such obvious problems as an empty bottle or a pile of pills lying loose. They cannot tell, however, if the right medicine is in the patient's bottle. That is up to the scanners who monitor what is happening to the bottle based on its position in the carrier case.</p>
        <p>After a robotic arm snaps a cap on, the bottle heads into a machine where it gets a label. The machine then drops the medication, along with a custom pre-printed pack of patient literature into a plastic mailing envelope. The machine, relying again on scanners, prints the patient's address on the envelope.</p>
        <p>''This is the moment of truth,'' said Mr. Wasdyke.</p>
        <p>Even with all of its equipment, Merck-Medco will still have 26 pharmacists filling orders by hand for medication that is ordered infrequently, or is too cumbersome to merit space in a cell.</p>
        <p>Yet amid the millions of dollars of high-tech equipment at this sprawling facility, some things nevere change. Like a corner drugstore, there is a long wall nearby with several dozen framed pharmacists' licenses.</p>
        <p>Once sealed in a mailer, prescriptions then travel by conveyor to Merck-Medco's in-house post office, which is operated by employees of the United States Postal Service. The envelopes are then presorted, again by scanners, and grouped for mail to 652 of the company's busiest zip codes. From there, mail trucks transport the bags directly to a postal service hub at Philadelphia International Airport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasdyke said presorting the mail shaves a half-day off delivery time, helping to meet the company's goal of getting the medication to customers within 72 hours of receiving a prescription.</p>
        <p>''We worked very closely with the post office,'' said Mr. Wasdyke. ''They knew we were going to be a large contributor.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, he said Merck-Medco chose the site because New Jersey was one of only a handful of states that allowed mail-order pharmacies. Merck-Medco also wanted to locate in a part of the state where it would not be competing with itself or its parent company.</p>
        <p>''The township is pleased,'' said Denise Rose, the township administrator, ''to have been able to bring Merck to Willingboro and serve as the anchor for the Route 130 Corridor.''</p>
        <p>N.J. AND COMPANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
