<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Rebuilding From Back To Front</title>
    <meta content="T09SOC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="994162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7DA1E3DF93AA35751C0A96E958260" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Rebuilding From Back To Front</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., Feb. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on MetroStars preparing for upcoming Major League Soccer's season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The MetroStars are busy trying to make amends for last season's last place finish in Major League Soccer's Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>During training here at Disney's Wide World of Sports complex for a regular season that begins March 28 at Los Angeles, MetroStars General Manager Charlie Stillitano is constantly studying potential roster moves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The MetroStars are busy trying to make amends for last season's last place finish in Major League Soccer's Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>During training here at Disney's Wide World of Sports complex for a regular season that begins March 28 at Los Angeles, MetroStars General Manager Charlie Stillitano is constantly studying potential roster moves.</p>
        <p>It is already evident that the MetroStars will have a fortified defense, with the standout defenders Jose Arley Palacios and Alexi Lalas set to play.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the MetroStars are expected to announce the signing of midfielder Wellington Sanchez, an Ecuadorean national team starter who, like Palacios, is 24 years old. Among his accomplishments, Sanchez scored the game's only goal in Ecuador's victory over the United States in a friendly match at Baltimore last August.</p>
        <p>Stillitano is being extremely selective about the five foreign players he can carry on his 22-player opening-day roster.</p>
        <p>''In past years we were overloaded up front,'' Stillitano said. ''The teams that have the most success have very good American players around very capable foreign players. Too often, we had one or two of our foreigners sitting on the bench, because of the overload up front.''</p>
        <p>Stillitano is searching now for another midfielder and a forward, to fill the spots of the midfield playmaker Roberto Donadoni, who has returned to A.C. Milan in Italy, and the South African forward Shaun Bartlett, whose availability is in question.</p>
        <p>Chances are, too, that forward Antony De Avila will be transferred elsewhere, perhaps to Barcelona of Ecuador. Stillitano wonders how much value De Avila can provide the MetroStars, inasmuch as he will be playing 6 to 10 World Cup preparation games with the Colombian national team and then will participate in the World Cup tournament itself.</p>
        <p>Stillitano is now looking at two recently acquired Argentines, forward Jorge Strange and midfielder Dario Grioni. Strange scored the winning goal today on a header in the team's 2-1 exhibition victory over the Dallas Burn.</p>
        <p>''The good thing about this year is a lot of guys are fighting for a job,'' Stillitano said. ''I think we've created a competitive environment. That always hasn't been the case in the past. There's been a disparity between guys like Tab Ramos and Donadoni and the Nos. 19 and 20 players.''</p>
        <p>Stillitano is also intent on ''changing the character of this team.'' He mentioned Lalas, now with the United States national team, as an example of ''a good guy on the field and a good guy off the field.''</p>
        <p>Stillitano seemed adamant about this. ''We want our fans to feel they're in every game when they see the MetroStars,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''That hasn't always been the case. Certainly against D.C. United, our guys always got up for the game and we played well. But often in games at home we felt we should have won, we didn't give a great performance.''</p>
        <p>Another player drawing interest here is midfielder Alan Valderrama, the 31-year-old younger brother of the celebrated Colombian international Carlos Valderrama.</p>
        <p>''He's a guy with a great shot,'' Stillitano said. ''Obviously he's not his brother. That would be too much to ask. I guess it's a little like Joe and Dom DiMaggio. From what I heard from the coach, he's a good person, works hard. We're going to take a look at him and see if he fits in.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars play the Kansas City Wizards here Wednesday in another exhibiton game, and will play an undetermined opponent on Saturday or Sunday here. Then they will play in Italy from March 1 to March 19.</p>
        <p>The Italian trip has a twofold purpose, according to Stillitano: to prepare the MetroStars for their season and, perhaps just as important, to impress upon their players the organization's commitment to win.  SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
