<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>London Journal; Diana's Hereafter, an Eternity of Newsstand Life</title>
    <meta content="Y09LOND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="994143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diana, Princess of Wales</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DD1E3DF93AA35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>London Journal; Diana's Hereafter, an Eternity of Newsstand Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Feb. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British tabloids are recycling news about late Princess Diana and are casting about for stand-in figures to halt flagging circulation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Diana gone, a new press code in place and the comparatively strait-laced officials of Prime Minister Tony Blair's New Labor Government offering scant opportunities for keyhole discoveries, the British press has had to extend even its storied reach to turn up front page notoriety.</p>
        <p>Newspapers have sought to exploit the only lapse thus far in Mr. Blair's  ranks -- Foreign Secretary Robin Cook's leaving his wife to marry his secretary -- but it has simply amounted to giving Mr. Blair some practice at damage control of a kind that is quaint compared with what he witnessed at the White House this week. To halt flagging circulation, magazines and newspapers are recycling news about the late Princess and are casting about for stand-in figures, usually blond ones, for the day, evidently still distant, when every Diana tale has been told.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Diana gone, a new press code in place and the comparatively strait-laced officials of Prime Minister Tony Blair's New Labor Government offering scant opportunities for keyhole discoveries, the British press has had to extend even its storied reach to turn up front page notoriety.</p>
        <p>Newspapers have sought to exploit the only lapse thus far in Mr. Blair's  ranks -- Foreign Secretary Robin Cook's leaving his wife to marry his secretary -- but it has simply amounted to giving Mr. Blair some practice at damage control of a kind that is quaint compared with what he witnessed at the White House this week. To halt flagging circulation, magazines and newspapers are recycling news about the late Princess and are casting about for stand-in figures, usually blond ones, for the day, evidently still distant, when every Diana tale has been told.</p>
        <p>Recent weeks have seen ''So, Did Diana Really Love Charles Until the Day She Died?'' and ''Queen Fights to Stop New Diana Secrets'' in The Daily Mail, ''The Diana Conspiracies'' and '' 'Di' Ecstasy Tablets Being Sold in London'' in The Evening Standard, ''How Safe Are the Secrets of Diana?'' in The Daily Telegraph, ''Diana Song No. 1 for Funerals'' in The Independent, ''Di Butler: I Want to Run Fund'' in The Sun, and ''5 Million Calls to Di Grave Hotline'' in The Mirror.</p>
        <p>The Daily Mail has begun a 200-page series on ''the full untold story of her life'' accompanied by offers of ''Diana Rose Bushes'' and ''Fabulous Diana Video.'' On successive days The Sun and The Mirror devoted their front pages first to a supposed feud between the businessman Richard Branson and the newly knighted Sir Elton John over the recording of the song he performed at her funeral (''Wrangle in the Wind'' said The Sun), and then to the $800,000 bill the Princess's lawyers submitted for 11 days of work on her memorial fund (''Shameful'' said The Mirror.)</p>
        <p>The article with top play in The Daily Telegraph raised an issue that the press itself has apparently not yet contemplated. The headline read, ''Royal Family to Look to Their Future Without Diana.''</p>
        <p>Roy Greenslade, the press critic of The Guardian, commented, ''The way papers are maintaining Diana's status as a sales gimmick, quite apart from its tastelessness, smells of ingenuity at best and desperation at worst.''</p>
        <p>There is no more competitive newspaper market in the world than Britain, with its 11 national dailies and 9 national Sunday papers. They fight one another with drastic price cuts, beefed-up weekend papers, cross-promotional gimmicks like cheap travel tickets and human interest stories whose detail outweighs their consequence. Their circulations are enormous and sensitive to stories that keep reader interest, producing fluctuations that can quickly get into hundreds of thousands of readers.</p>
        <p>The Audit Bureau of Circulation figures for September, the month that attention to Diana was the highest, showed The Sun at 3.9 million, The Mirror at 2.4 million, The Daily Mail at 2.3 million and The Daily Telegraph at 1.1 million. By December, those papers had declined by 5, 9, 7 and 4 percent respectively, resulting in the loss of 565,000 copies among them.</p>
        <p>There may have been a brief recovery in the last 10 days with the broad attention the papers have paid to the Washington sex scandal, but the only sustainable subject British editors seem to trust is Diana.</p>
        <p>The search for stand-ins settled at first on Anthea Turner, a television breakfast-show hostess with Diana-like cropped blond hair and a professed faith in family values who left her husband to run off with a married millionaire father of three.</p>
        <p>Other blond candidates drawing newspaper attention as substitutes for the dead Princess included Lauren Booth, a writer and former model who is the half-sister of Cherie Blair, wife of the Prime Minister; Jemima Khan, the daughter of the late Sir James Goldsmith who was said to be having marital problems with her husband, the Pakistani politician and former cricket star Imran Khan;  Sheryl Gascoigne, the wife of the soccer star Paul Gascoigne who accused him of beating her and said she was leaving the marriage to become a talk-show hostess on Rupert Murdoch's Sky television, and a true Diana lookalike, Amy Seccombe, an actress who will play the lead in a television movie about the romance between the late princess and Emad (Dodi) al-Fayed.</p>
        <p>The need for new talent has obliged the press to begin rehabilitating Diana's former sister-in-law, Sarah Ferguson, the Duchess of York, who after a period of being dismissed as too lightweight to be of interest to anyone but Americans was pictured in Tuscany with a favorably portrayed 48-year-old millionaire Italian nobleman.</p>
        <p>The press has maintained the discretion it promised in its treatment of the royal family. Over the Christmas holidays, Prince Charles asked that photographers confine to one posed photo session their coverage of a vacation he and his sons, Princes William and Harry, took to the Swiss ski resort of Klosters, and the only violators were French paparazzi whom royal security men chased off the mountain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's earnest ministerial crew has afforded the press no opening for the kind of sex scandal that has occurred regularly with Conservatives. Newspapers have tried to make an issue of the decision by Mr. Cook, 51, to divorce his wife of 28 years and marry 41-year-old Gaynor Regan, his secretary. Mr. Cook preempted tabloid torment by revealing the news himself after being warned that the mass market News of the World was about to publish details. But the press seized upon a months-old television interview with Mrs. Cook in which she said he had a big ego and was a womanizer, and disregarded her subsequent assertion that he was a good public official and ought to be left alone to do his job. Despite a press code that went into effect on Jan. 1 barring intrusion into private lives without compelling public reasons, the papers gave their front pages over to reports about Mr. Cook -- ''Romeo Rascal Robin'' to The Express -- and to speculation about who his other lovers might have been.</p>
        <p>''Can he still do his job?,'' The Sunday Telegraph asked and then posited an unintended howler, imagining that leaders of Europe, a continent famously underwhelmed by Anglo-Saxon sexual escapades, might treat the Foreign Secretary with diminished respect because of the revelations of his racy background.</p>
        <p>Peter Riddell, the chief political writer of The Times of London, brought perspective. ''Britain has had 21 Foreign Secretaries since 1945, of whom at least four besides Robin Cook probably have been adulterers, and another three are renowned 'gropers','' he said. ''In no case, however, have these private peccadilloes affected their public performances or reputations overseas.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
