<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indians' New Money Buys Lobbying Power</title>
    <meta content="09INDI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="994181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oneida Tribe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1D81E3DF93AA35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indians' New Money Buys Lobbying Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on increasing number of American Indian tribes such as Oneida Indians of central New York, flush with huge gambling profits, undergoing political makeovers in Washington, DC, where they are using high-priced lobbyists, savy public relations firms and big campaign contributions to win influence, make friends and crush opponents; examples of Indian's new lobbying power discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five short years ago, a lobbying excursion to Congress for the Oneida Indians of central New York went something like this: Tribal officials would pile into an old car, endure the eight-hour drive to Washington, sleep on a friend's floor and dine on peanut butter sandwiches, all for the chance to catch some Congressional aide on the fly.</p>
        <p>How quaintly remote all that now seems to the Oneidas who flew into Washington last week, stayed four nights in a first-class hotel, co-sponsored a splashy reception for two dozen members of Congress and brought along two lobbyists, a tax lawyer and a publicist to their meetings on the Hill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five short years ago, a lobbying excursion to Congress for the Oneida Indians of central New York went something like this: Tribal officials would pile into an old car, endure the eight-hour drive to Washington, sleep on a friend's floor and dine on peanut butter sandwiches, all for the chance to catch some Congressional aide on the fly.</p>
        <p>How quaintly remote all that now seems to the Oneidas who flew into Washington last week, stayed four nights in a first-class hotel, co-sponsored a splashy reception for two dozen members of Congress and brought along two lobbyists, a tax lawyer and a publicist to their meetings on the Hill.</p>
        <p>''We're a bit more sophisticated these days,'' said Keller George, a member of the Oneidas' ruling council.</p>
        <p>A bit more wealthy, too.</p>
        <p>Flush with huge gambling profits, tribes like the Oneidas have undergone political makeovers in Washington, where they are using high-priced lobbyists, savvy public relations firms and big campaign contributions to win influence, make friends and crush opponents.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Oneidas were one of nearly two dozen tribes from along the Eastern Seaboard and as far west as Texas who flew to Washington for a week of lobbying and political power building. As a sign of their influence, their advocacy association, the United South and Eastern Tribes, drew not only members of Congress to their events, but also the Interior Secretary, Bruce Babbitt, and Attorney General Janet Reno, who electrified the crowd by saying she opposed taxing Indian casinos.</p>
        <p>Indians, of course, have been coming to Washington for as long as it has existed, to talk over treaty rights and other issues. And since the early 1990's at least, tribes have been using newfound gambling wealth to expand their political muscle.</p>
        <p>But, concerned that momentum is building behind a wide range of Republican bills they consider anti-Indian, tribal leaders have been stoking up their lobbying operations earlier and more forcefully this year than in the past, Congressional officials and tribal leaders say.</p>
        <p>''There are more harmful bills out there,'' said Charles Hobbs, a partner in the lobbying firm of Hobbs, Straus, Dean &amp; Walker, which represents several Eastern tribes.</p>
        <p>Chief among their concerns are bills that would authorize the Federal Government to tax profits from casinos, enable states to block new Indian casinos, allow citizens to sue Indian tribes and make it easier for local governments to collect sales taxes from Indian businesses that sell to non-Indians.</p>
        <p>In a sign of their growing sophistication, Indians are also weighing in on issues that seem, on the surface, unrelated to tribal affairs. For instance, many tribes are opposing portions of a proposed national tobacco litigation settlement because it might authorize government agencies to regulate Indian tobacco shops -- a violation of their sovereignty, tribes say.</p>
        <p>A look inside the United South and Eastern Tribes, whose members include the Mashantucket Pequots and Mohegan Indians of Connecticut and the Seneca Indians and St. Regis Mohawks of New York, shows the changing face of Indian lobbying in Washington.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, only 5 of the group's 23 tribes had Washington lobbyists, but by last year 14 did, from the Seminoles in Florida to the Wampanoags in Massachusetts. And while few tribes could afford major campaign contributions a few years ago, the Pequots, Mohegans and Oneidas -- who all run casinos -- have contributed a total of more than $800,000 to state and Federal candidates since 1994, according to public records.</p>
        <p>''The sad fact of life throughout the United States is that having money, or being perceived as having money, does seem to give people more of a voice,'' said Jayne Fawcett, vice chairwoman of the Mohegan Tribe in Uncasville, Conn.</p>
        <p>The Pequots, who run the largest casino in the nation, have also opened a Washington office with full-time staff. And the Oneidas have not only retained law, lobbying and public relations firms in Washington, but also hired a former top Commerce Department official to run their communications operation in New York.</p>
        <p>Some Congressional officials contend that the slickness of Indian lobbying is creating a political backlash.  And a Justice Department inquiry into whether Mr. Babbitt denied a gambling permit to one Wisconsin tribe because of contributions from a rival tribe has cast shadows over Indian political activity here.</p>
        <p>''A lot of their political capital stems from being poor tribes that have been disenfranchised and beat up for 300 years,'' said John Albaugh, an aide to Representative Ernest J. Istook, Republican of Oklahoma. ''Then they hire the biggest firms in town and hold fancy events, and that cuts against their message.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hobbs agreed, saying, ''Indians have always gotten an extra measure of sympathy from people in Congress.'' But that factor often disappears, he said, ''when a Robert Strauss or someone like that shows up.''</p>
        <p>For that reason, lobbyists urge their clients to plead their cases face to face with Congressmen. So Mr. George, dressed in a blue jean shirt and alligator boots, his hair pulled taut into a ponytail, did almost all the talking when he led a delegation of Oneida leaders into meetings on Capitol Hill last Thursday.</p>
        <p>In session after session, Mr. George told of the dire economic consequences Indians would face if the tax bills were enacted. He offered gifts of fragrant sweetgrass. And he urged an aide to Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, Republican of New York, to persuade Gov. George E. Pataki to settle an Oneida land dispute.</p>
        <p>Throughout the meetings, the Oneidas' battery of lawyers and publicists remained silent. Their responsibility will be to block the secret deals and catch the bad amendments after the Oneidas have left town.</p>
        <p>''I don't fault our opponents for strong lobbying -- it's in their business interests,'' said Ray Halbritter, the Oneida Nation representative, an elected official. ''But we have to look out for ours, too.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
