<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reds Stump McGwire; It's 59 and Counting</title>
    <meta content="05MARK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1044017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgwire, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDB173EF936A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reds Stump McGwire; It's 59 and Counting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cincinnati Reds defeat St Louis Cardinals, 3-2, and deny Mark McGwire his 60th home run; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Cincinnati Reds saw Mark McGwire in July, they walked him, then walked him again, walked him some more, and kept on walking him. With McGwire going into a three-game series with the Reds only two home runs away from Roger Maris's home run record, Jack McKeon, the Reds' manager, was asked whether he planned to have his pitchers repeat their July performance.</p>
        <p>''The game situation will dictate it,'' McKeon said tonight before the Reds played the St. Louis Cardinals. ''I can't tell you anything now.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Cincinnati Reds saw Mark McGwire in July, they walked him, then walked him again, walked him some more, and kept on walking him. With McGwire going into a three-game series with the Reds only two home runs away from Roger Maris's home run record, Jack McKeon, the Reds' manager, was asked whether he planned to have his pitchers repeat their July performance.</p>
        <p>''The game situation will dictate it,'' McKeon said tonight before the Reds played the St. Louis Cardinals. ''I can't tell you anything now.''</p>
        <p>McKeon's pitchers, Pete Harnisch and Scott Sullivan, spoke volumes. They pitched to McGwire and held him hitless in three at-bats. Each struck him out once, and the only time McGwire reached base was when Harnisch walked him on a 3-2 pitch. McGwire flied out to right field his first time up.</p>
        <p>McGwire, who entered the game with 12 home runs in the Cardinals' previous 17 games and his previous 52 at-bats, did not become the third player in major league history to hit 60 home runs, and he also lost a bit of his lead over Sammy Sosa because Sosa hit his 57th home run in Pittsburgh. They are both chasing Roger Maris's record of 61.</p>
        <p>Sosa's home run was his first in six games against the Pirates this season, but the Reds continued to confound McGwire. They are the only National League team he has not hit a home run against this season, and they extended his failure to seven games and 16 at-bats.</p>
        <p>McGwire opted not to talk to the more than 600 reporters who were at Busch Stadium, but his manager, Tony La Russa, credited Harnisch and Sullivan with doing a good job.</p>
        <p>Asked after the Reds' 3-2 victory whether he thought McKeon had the Reds going at McGwire tonight more than they had in July when they walked him 11 times, La Russa said: ''Yeah, I wish he hadn't done it so much. I wish they had walked him three times. Harnisch made very good pitches. Then Sullivan made three Hall of Fame pitches. They were really nasty pitches.''</p>
        <p>Each time McGwire walked to the plate, the sellout crowd of 48,076 stood and cheered loudly. Cameras flashed from all points of the stadium with each pitch, fans hoping to get lucky and get some minuscule image of the swing that produced No. 60.</p>
        <p>In the first inning, McGwire came to bat with Brian Jordan at second. He lofted a fly ball that the fans thought was headed for the right-field fence, but it turned out to be a routine fly ball that Reggie Sanders caught easily.</p>
        <p>''I knew that ball wasn't a home run,'' Harnisch said. ''But when he hit it, it went so high the crowd went berserk. But I knew he hit it straight up in the air.''</p>
        <p>In the third and fifth innings, McGwire did not hit the ball at all. He struck out swinging in the third; his walk in the fifth loaded the bases and preceded a sacrifice fly by Ray Lankford for the Cardinals' second run in the inning and the game.</p>
        <p>McGwire got his last chance, for this night, to match Babe Ruth's 60 home runs in 1927, in the seventh inning. But Sullivan did not give him much of a chance. Sullivan, who relieved Harnisch at the start of that inning, threw three pitches, and McGwire swung at all three and missed.</p>
        <p>''McGwire is at kind of a disadvantage in the sense that the spotlight's on him,'' said Sullivan, a 27-year-old right-hander. ''The average player might elevate his game to a higher level to get him out.''</p>
        <p>Sullivan said he threw a fastball on the first pitch just to try to get ahead of McGwire.</p>
        <p>''That probably was the best pitch to hit,'' Sullivan said. ''I don't know if he was going to do much with the sliders. They were down and away. I was lucky enough to have a little bite on the sliders and he chased them.''</p>
        <p>Each time McGwire came to bat the pitchers were given new balls to use. The balls are the same as the others used in games, but they are specially marked with serial numbers so that if McGwire does hit a home run, officials will be able to determine which ball is legitimate when a fan claims he caught it.</p>
        <p>Brett Tomko, the Reds' scheduled starting pitcher for Sunday's third game of the series, acknowledged that he and his teammates have discussed the scenario in which McGwire would break the record against them.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people have chatted about it,'' Tomko said. ''What would they do if he hits the home run? If you're playing third, would you high-five him? It's a monumental thing. It doesn't happen very often that someone is going to achieve this feat, so everyone is sort of preparing how they're going to feel and how they're going to react when this happens.''</p>
        <p>When he realized that he would be pitching Sunday's game, Tomko said, he started thinking about the game and the possible ramifications.</p>
        <p>''I sat back and said, well, if he gets a couple the first couple games he's going to be sitting on 61,'' Tomko said. ''You play the little games, the scenarios, and try to think how you would feel.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
