<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice/Film; Subversive Intentions Behind the Humor</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="719632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PAPP, JOSEPH, PUBLIC THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PLACIDO (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EL VERDUGO (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LLANTO POR UN BANDIDO (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LA PRIMA ANGELICA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MI QUERIDA SENORITA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DB1F3CF932A15753C1A962958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice/Film; Subversive Intentions Behind the Humor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the best ways of insinuating subversive messages into a repressive culture has always been to present them in a humorous guise. Take, for example, two pitch-black comedies by the Spanish director Luis Garcia Berlanga that are included in the series Spanish Eyes III: Classics of the Spanish Cinema, 1960-1975, which opens today at the Joseph Papp Public Theater. On the surface, both films, which were made during the waning years of the Franco dictatorship, don't seem particularly political. But peel away the humor, and you will find acerbic critiques of Spanish culture under Franco in which the bitterness is masked by farcical loquacity and absurdism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlanga's 1961 film, "Placido," which begins a six-night engagement this evening, is a chattery comedy about an impoverished man who spends the day before Christmas trying to avoid foreclosure on his motorbike. The character's frantic dealings with bankers and lawyers are set against the film's satirical canvas of a provincial town putting on a showy Christmas campaign called "Seat a Poor Man at Your Table." With its harshly funny portrait of the penny-pinching gentry, of greedy nuns and aggressive salespeople pushing pressure cookers as miraculous kitchen tools, the film offers a scabrously mocking portrait of officialdom putting on a display that is as grotesque as it is hypocritical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the best ways of insinuating subversive messages into a repressive culture has always been to present them in a humorous guise. Take, for example, two pitch-black comedies by the Spanish director Luis Garcia Berlanga that are included in the series Spanish Eyes III: Classics of the Spanish Cinema, 1960-1975, which opens today at the Joseph Papp Public Theater. On the surface, both films, which were made during the waning years of the Franco dictatorship, don't seem particularly political. But peel away the humor, and you will find acerbic critiques of Spanish culture under Franco in which the bitterness is masked by farcical loquacity and absurdism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlanga's 1961 film, "Placido," which begins a six-night engagement this evening, is a chattery comedy about an impoverished man who spends the day before Christmas trying to avoid foreclosure on his motorbike. The character's frantic dealings with bankers and lawyers are set against the film's satirical canvas of a provincial town putting on a showy Christmas campaign called "Seat a Poor Man at Your Table." With its harshly funny portrait of the penny-pinching gentry, of greedy nuns and aggressive salespeople pushing pressure cookers as miraculous kitchen tools, the film offers a scabrously mocking portrait of officialdom putting on a display that is as grotesque as it is hypocritical.</p>
        <p>"El Verdugo" ("The Executioner"), which plays Nov. 4 to 6, was made two years later and is no less cynical. Jose Luis, the main character, is an assistant to an undertaker who falls in love with the daughter of the local executioner. To be able to marry her, he agrees to become the executioner's apprentice and eventual successor. When his father-in-law retires, Jose Luis, who has fooled himself into believing that he will never have to kill anyone, travels to Majorca to preside over a possible execution. In the film's most harrowingly funny scene, he is dragged kicking and screaming across the floor to perform his homicidal duty.</p>
        <p>Another significant film in the series, "Llanto por un Bandido" ("Lament for a Bandit"), is a 1963 spaghetti western by the highly esteemed Spanish director Carlo Saura. The lushly photographed film, which was censored at the time, is set in the early 19th century. It treats the story of an Andalusian bandit, who becomes a symbol of liberty, and an escaped political prisoner as an allegory of contemporary Spanish politics. (The film is to be shown on Nov. 4 to 6 and Nov. 8 to 10.)</p>
        <p>More famous is Mr. Saura's 1973 film, "La Prima Angelica" ("Cousin Angelica"), which won him a best director award at the Cannes International Film Festival. The film, which is to be shown Oct. 25 to 27, was banned by the Spanish Government but went on to become the director's first international box-office hit. The movie tells the story of a middle-aged man who returns to the small town he grew up in during the Spanish Civil War and becomes obsessed with the teen-age daughter of his childhood sweetheart. Along the way, the film pokes vicious fun at the fascist military structure.</p>
        <p>Because it deals with gender identity, Jaime de Arminan's 1971 film, "Mi Querida Senorita" ("My Dear Lady"), which plays Oct. 28 to 30 and Nov. 1 to 3, is in some ways the most contemporary of all the films in the series.  Adela, the central character, is a spinster who lives a retiring life with her devoted maid, Isabel. When the widower of a friend proposes marriage to Adela, who has never been attracted to men, she consults a doctor, discovers that she is actually a man, and leaves town. Dressing in male attire and calling himself Juan, but lacking an official identity, Adela establishes a sewing business in Madrid. Things become complicated when Isabel appears, and a romance develops between the two. The lighthearted, gender-bending comedy ends with a terrific punch line.</p>
        <p>The series was organized by the Spanish Ministry of Culture, the Institute of Cervantes in New York and the S.G.A.E., the Sociedad General de Autores de Espana.</p>
        <p>The Papp Public Theater is at 425 Lafayette Street in the East Village. Tickets for each film are $7.50. Information and screening times: (212) 598-7171 or 598-7150. STEPHEN HOLDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
