<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="595280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DF133AF932A25750C0A965958260" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-17  U.S. SEEKS NATO BOSNIA FORCE  The U.S. is urging allies to prepare an international force that would be sent the Bosnia immediately after a peace settlement there, but planning is being hampered by a dispute between the U.S. and France over who would command it.  A1  The U.N. military chief in Bosnia is headed for besieged enclave.  A16</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-17  U.S. SEEKS NATO BOSNIA FORCE  The U.S. is urging allies to prepare an international force that would be sent the Bosnia immediately after a peace settlement there, but planning is being hampered by a dispute between the U.S. and France over who would command it.  A1  The U.N. military chief in Bosnia is headed for besieged enclave.  A16</p>
        <p>Bosnia's President delayed his return to talks in New York.  A17  SHOULD YELTSIN BE U.S. FOCUS?  News analysis: The Administration's campaign to help Boris Yeltsin comes as his political future is again precarious and he is engaged once again in the trenches with a hostile Russian Congress.  A1  Boris Yeltsin won a crucial vote in the Russian Congress.  A14  EGYPT KILLS 21 MILITANTS  Egyptian security forces killed 21 people and wounded two dozen in nine raids in Cairo and Aswan against Islamic militants seeking to overthrow the Government.  A1  STRICT ABORTION LAW IN POLAND  The Polish Government gazette will soon publish the latest laws approved by Parliament. Two weeks later Poland will have the most restrictive law on abortion of any country in Eastern Europe.  A3  PALESTINIANS REJECT INVITATION  Palestinian leaders rejected an invitation to a new round of Middle East peace talks, citing Israel's deportation of Muslim fundamentalists, but did not rule out ultimately rejoining the negotiations.  A8  LIBERIAN REBELS ON THE RUN  After three years of warfare in Liberia, the rebel leader Charles Taylor's military position is deteriorating rapidly, reports from West Africa and U.S. officials say.  A10  BRITISH PREMIER UNDER SIEGE  The British Prime Minister's grip on government has slipped, strained by a growing rebellion within his party over Europe and deepening public dismay over his failure to revive the country's moribund economy.  A15  DOUBT ON ITALY'S FUTURE  News Analysis: The bribery and corruption scandal enveloping Italy has struck both the public and private sectors, undermining both and casting doubt on the nation's future.  A6  GAINS AGAINST BASQUE REBELS  A string of arrests of leading guerrillas in France has stirred cautious optimism in Spain that the end of the Basque terrorist movement may finally be in sight.  A5  The former chief of the East German secret police is on trial.  A4  President Suharto was re-elected to a sixth five-year term.  A13  Beijing is going all out to be host of the Olympics in 2000.  A12  National A18-21, B10-13  JUDGE RULES ON HEALTH PANEL  A Federal judge ruled that Hillary Rodham Clinton's health panel must announce its meetings and open some to the public, but can meet privately when formulating recommendations.  A1  A committee approved of Janet Reno as Attorney General.  A21  Democrats won a first round for Clinton's deficit plans.  A20  Aspin could be on a collision course with the Joint Chiefs.  A20  Clinton plans an effort to cushion the affects of base closings.  A20  ABORTION DOCTOR IS KILLED  An anti-abortion demonstrator shot and killed a doctor during a protest outside his clinic, then surrendered, the police said.  A1  NEGOTIATING WITH A 'MESSIAH'  Like a game of three-dimensional chess, conversations between Federal agents and the leader of the cult in Waco veer from haggles over milk to Biblical discourses. After 11 days, the agents have no idea what he wants.  A1  KING ADMITS LYING  Rodney G. King conceded that he had lied about his beating and that he was not really sure whether the officers who beat him had used racial epithets or threatened to kill him, as he had testified.  A18  The retrial of a Miami police officer is moved again.  A18  N.A.A.C.P. LOOKS AT JACKSON  As the N.A.A.C.P., searches for a new executive director, the possibility of the Rev. Jesse Jackson's getting the job is a hot topic at the association.  A18  HOUSING AGENCY UNDER FIRE  Four years after HUD became a symbol of ineptitude and graft, a succession of reports has warned that another scandal "is a distinct possibility." A21  The chief of the Federal Centers for Disease Control quits.  B12  Astronomers clock a star moving faster than any ever seen.  B13  New evidence that opening plugged arteries with balloons works.  B13  Debunking an AIDS myth about recreational drug use.  B13  Metro Digest B1  ANOTHER ARREST IN BOMBING  A chemical engineer of Palestinian descent, who had studied the principles of explosives, was arrested and charged yesterday with aiding in the World Trade Center bombing.  A1  TRACING THE MONEY TRAIL  Federal investigators say they believe that money used to finance the bombing of the World Trade Center was transferred in recent months from Europe to a New Jersey bank account used by the two suspects now under arrest.  A1  Business Digest D1  Home Section C1-13  Designed with tongue in chic.  C1  At home with Michael Douglas.  C1  Breast-feeding strategies for busy mothers.  C1  Shopping for a dictionary?  C2  Currents C3  Review/Fashion: In Milan, a costume party.  C6  Review/Fashion: Sexy Austerity from Jil Sander.  C6  Parent &amp; Child C12  Arts/Entertainment C15-24  Italian cinema's everyman.  C15  For Rolf Hochhuth, a new play, a new furor.  C15  Arts grants for New York City groups.  C20  Music: Gang of Four returns.  C15  Dance: Premiere of Merce Cunningham's "Enter." C15  Word and Image: Home Video C18  Sports B14-19  Baseball: Meet the new Bonilla.  B15  Abbott hopes for long-term stay.  B19  Basketball: Much to prove in Big East.  B15  Nets defeat Clippers.  B18  Close-game drills for Knicks.  B18  Column: Anderson on Manhattan College.  B15  Football: Giants pool for free agents.  B15  Hockey: Rangers out of sick bay.  B19  Islanders lose to Canadiens.  B14  Obituaries D23  Andrea Boroff Eagan, a writer and women's advocate.</p>
        <p>Bob Crosby, swing band leader.</p>
        <p>Don Barksdale, one of the first blacks to play in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>Max A. Zorn; developed a theory that changed math.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23  Editorials  The Republicans strike back.  More Twin Tower mysteries.  Bungee jumping at the U.N.  Letters  William Safire: Communostalgia.  Leslie H. Gelb: Where's Bill?  Garrison Keillor: Notes on a new and improved era.  Linda Aiken and Claire Fagin: More nurses, better medicine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
