<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators Question Handling of Cole Case</title>
    <meta content="Y04COL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/04/world/04COLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1290488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cole (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelton, Henry H (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Vern (Adm)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lippold, Kirk S (Comdr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Greeneville</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Virginia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Shelton</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Aden</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Yemen</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Clark</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hawaii</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Capitol</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DB1338F937A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators Question Handling of Cole Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gen Henry H Shelton, chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff, and Adm Vern Clark, chief of naval operations, come under sharp questioning before Senate Armed Services Committee for not punishing Cmdr Kirk S Lippold for failing to follow certain security guidelines before destroyer USS Cole was attacked by suicide bombers last October (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Navy's top admiral came under sharp questioning on Capitol Hill today for not punishing the commander of the destroyer Cole, who failed to follow certain security guidelines before the ship was attacked by suicide bombers last October.</p>
        <p>In a hearing before the Senate Armed Services Committee, senior lawmakers suggested that the Navy and other military services might have relaxed accountability standards for commanding officers, citing the case of the submarine Greeneville as another example.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Navy's top admiral came under sharp questioning on Capitol Hill today for not punishing the commander of the destroyer Cole, who failed to follow certain security guidelines before the ship was attacked by suicide bombers last October.</p>
        <p>In a hearing before the Senate Armed Services Committee, senior lawmakers suggested that the Navy and other military services might have relaxed accountability standards for commanding officers, citing the case of the submarine Greeneville as another example.</p>
        <p>''Military personnel in positions of responsibility must be accountable for their actions or failure to act, if we are to maintain the order and discipline essential to successful military operations,'' said Senator John W. Warner, Republican of Virginia, who is chairman of the committee. ''Has that changed?''</p>
        <p>Army Gen. Henry H. Shelton, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said no. ''Everybody in the chain of command could have done better,'' he said. ''However, I think that as you look at that chain, there was no dereliction and there was certainly no criminal intent or any criminal actions or anything else that warranted punishment.''</p>
        <p>The Navy's initial inquiry into the Cole bombing found that the captain and crew of the warship were lax about following a number of strict security procedures before a skiff packed with explosives exploded alongside it in Aden, Yemen, killing 17 sailors and severely damaging the ship.</p>
        <p>The Cole, like all warships at sea, filed a detailed security plan before it stopped in Aden to refuel, based on guidelines set by the Joint Chiefs of Staff for dealing with ''shipboard terrorist threat conditions.''</p>
        <p>Under the threat condition in Aden -- bravo, the third highest -- the ship's crew was required to follow at least 62 separate measures. But investigators found that the commander, Cmdr. Kirk S. Lippold, failed to follow about half of those procedures, including 12 that might have prevented or mitigated the explosion.</p>
        <p>For instance, the ship's watchmen did not properly identify and monitor harbor boats coming near the destroyer, and Commander Lippold did not order the crew to prepare fire hoses that could have been used to repel attackers. The investigation raised the possibility that Commander Lippold be disciplined for his lapses.</p>
        <p>But Adm. Vern Clark, the chief of naval operations, argued that while Commander Lippold's actions were not entirely satisfactory, they ''did not rise to the level of punitive action.''</p>
        <p>That conclusion was upheld by William S. Cohen, who was defense secretary at the time and said that responsibility for not preventing the suicide attack extended throughout the Pentagon, citing shortcomings in training, intelligence, equipment and security support for the Cole's crew.</p>
        <p>But some Mr. Cohen's decision has been somewhat controversial in Congress, where some lawmakers have questioned whether the military has become too hesitant to discipline commanders for serious mishaps that occur on their watch.</p>
        <p>Today, Senator Warner cited the example of the submarine Greeneville, whose chief officer escaped a court martial although his vessel rammed a Japanese training ship near Hawaii and killed nine people. The officer, Cmdr. Scott Waddle, received a reprimand last month and will resign with his full rank and pension.</p>
        <p>In questioning Admiral Clark today, Mr. Warner described strict accountability as ''an integral part of command,'' and asked whether the Navy's handling of the Cole or Greeneville cases had weakened ''that doctrine that has been at the heart of our Navy since its very inception.''</p>
        <p>Admiral Clark replied: ''It is my view that we have, in this case, held all of the parties accountable for their actions. There are some who believe that because they were not punished somehow they were not held accountable, and I do not agree with that.''</p>
        <p>Explaining why he decided not to punish Commander Lippold, Admiral Clark said that one of his main criteria was whether any of the procedures Commander Lippold ignored could have prevented the attack.</p>
        <p>''All of the endorsers in the chain of command and those that reviewed this investigation above me agreed with my conclusion that they would not have changed the outcome,'' he said.</p>
        <p>General Shelton and Admiral Clark asserted that the services have made strides in improving security on American ships and other military installations around the world since the Cole attack.</p>
        <p>Asked why some of those actions had not been taken earlier, General Shelton said the military had become ''fixated'' with protecting large bases, while failing to pay more attention to smaller installations or movable ones, like destroyers.</p>
        <p>''It was a matter of not having ignored it, but probably not having paid as much attention to our vulnerabilities, to the seams that the terrorists could find for the in-transit units that we probably should have been paying attention to,'' General Shelton said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
