<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cartoon Characters Are at Home, Home on the Veldt</title>
    <meta content="20WILD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/20/movies/20WILD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1450129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgrath, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malkasian, Cathy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wild Thornberries Movie, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nickelodeon</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Everett, Rupert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tomei, Marisa</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blethyn, Brenda</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DE113DF933A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cartoon Characters Are at Home, Home on the Veldt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cartoon Characters Are at Home, Home on the Veldt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE KEHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Kehr reviews animated film The Wild Thornberries Movie, directed by Jeff McGrath and Cathy Malkasian; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A blend of ''Dr. Dolittle'' and ''Family Ties,'' the animated series ''The Wild Thornberrys'' has been a staple of the Nickleodeon children's cable network since 1998. Never shy about exploiting its brand names, Nickelodeon has now turned the program into a feature film, carrying over most of the creative personnel of the series.</p>
        <p>On screen, ''The Wild Thornberrys'' looks just as it does on television, only wider. The directors, Jeff McGrath and Cathy Malkasian, use a Cinemascope-like frame to create a cartoon Africa with a greater sweep than its television counterpart, though the visuals inevitably fall short of their obvious model, Disney's ''Lion King.'' Without the financial or creative resources of the Disney animators, ''The Wild Thornberrys Movie'' remains essentially an extended Saturday morning cartoon -- which is to say, a series of hastily executed illustrations matched to a voice track.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On screen, "The Wild Thornberrys Movie" is essentially an extended Saturday morning cartoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A blend of ''Dr. Dolittle'' and ''Family Ties,'' the animated series ''The Wild Thornberrys'' has been a staple of the Nickleodeon children's cable network since 1998. Never shy about exploiting its brand names, Nickelodeon has now turned the program into a feature film, carrying over most of the creative personnel of the series.</p>
        <p>On screen, ''The Wild Thornberrys'' looks just as it does on television, only wider. The directors, Jeff McGrath and Cathy Malkasian, use a Cinemascope-like frame to create a cartoon Africa with a greater sweep than its television counterpart, though the visuals inevitably fall short of their obvious model, Disney's ''Lion King.'' Without the financial or creative resources of the Disney animators, ''The Wild Thornberrys Movie'' remains essentially an extended Saturday morning cartoon -- which is to say, a series of hastily executed illustrations matched to a voice track.</p>
        <p>The Thornberrys are an Anglo-American family of five. Dad Nigel is a blustery upper-class Englishman (entertainingly voiced by Tim Curry with the rolling vowels of C. Aubrey Smith) who with his plucky American wife, Marianne (Jodi Carlisle), makes nature documentaries for public television. They have two daughters, 12-year-old Eliza (Lacey Chabert), a shy girl with glasses, braces and spots on her face that could be either freckles or acne, and Debbie (Danielle Harris), a hormonally charged teenager who pines for American shopping malls. Their little brother, Donnie (played in grunts and squeals by the rock star Flea), is a still-unsocialized wild child, discovered and adopted by the Thornberrys during one of their expeditions.</p>
        <p>The series hangs on Eliza's magical ability to talk to the animals, granted to her by an African shaman on the condition that her special skills must always remain a secret. This allows her to communicate with her favorite pet, a chimpanzee named Darwin (Tom Kane), whose posh British accent and relentless snobbishness suggest that he, too, has spent some time on the playing fields of Eton.</p>
        <p>Eliza and Darwin set out to rescue a cheetah cub who has been snatched from the veldt by a pair of high-tech poachers (Rupert Everett and Marisa Tomei). They do, though it takes them a little longer than it would on television, involving as it does the need to escape from an oppressive British boarding school (where the headmistress has the voice of Brenda Blethyn) and beat it back to the cartoon Congo.</p>
        <p>The film, which opens nationally today, is bland but harmless.</p>
        <p>''The Wild Thornberrys Movie'' is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). Some of the action scenes may be too suspenseful for tiny viewers.</p>
        <p>THE WILD THORNBERRYS MOVIE</p>
        <p>Directed by Jeff McGrath and Cathy Malkasian; written by Kate Boutilier; edited by John Bryant; music by Drew Neumann; production designer, Dima Malanitchev; produced by Arlene Klasky and Gabor Csupo; released by Paramount Pictures. Running time: 80 minutes. This film is rated PG.</p>
        <p>WITH: Brenda Blethyn (Mrs. Fairgood), Rupert Everett (Sloan Blackburn), Lynn Redgrave (Cordelia Thornberry), Marisa Tomei (Bree Blackburn), Alfre Woodard (Akela), Michael Balzary a k a Flea (Donnie Thornberry), Jodi Carlisle (Marianne Thornberry), Lacey Chabert (Eliza Thornberry), Tim Curry (Nigel Thornberry), Danielle Harris (Debbie Thornberry), Tom Kane (Darwin) and Obba Babatundé (Boko).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
