<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Yale, Wedding Band Takes On a New Meaning</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE PRECISION MARCHING BAND</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORDHAM UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYERS, RORI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOCKMAN, JIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D81438F933A25753C1A964958260" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Yale, Wedding Band Takes On a New Meaning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, Oct. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Yale is the Mercedes of American universities, the Yale Precision Marching Band is the Edsel of marching bands, a little bizarre and, always, a little out of step.</p>
        <p>Musical talent is not a prerequisite for membership, and the 100 or more students who march every weekend are as likely to carry couches and stuffed bananas onto the field as they are to play the trumpet or the trombone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Yale is the Mercedes of American universities, the Yale Precision Marching Band is the Edsel of marching bands, a little bizarre and, always, a little out of step.</p>
        <p>Musical talent is not a prerequisite for membership, and the 100 or more students who march every weekend are as likely to carry couches and stuffed bananas onto the field as they are to play the trumpet or the trombone.</p>
        <p>But this weekend, the band will blaze a new trail into the unconventional. During its halftime show on Saturday at the Yale Bowl, two former band members will hold their wedding on the 50-yard line.</p>
        <p>"It's not the craziest thing the band has ever done," the bride, Rori Myers, said. "Blowing up a drum on the field; that, I'd say, was crazier."</p>
        <p>Thomas C. Duffy, the band's director, said, "This is more in the range of cute and touching than hysterical."</p>
        <p>Ms. Myers, class of '92, and her fiance, Jim Lockman, class of '89, met as members of the band when Ms. Myers was a freshman who coordinated props and Mr. Lockman was a senior and the drum major. Where It All Began</p>
        <p>Having shared this common ground during their Yale careers, Ms. Myers and Mr. Lockman decided to start off married life where it all began.</p>
        <p>"He thought of it first as a joke," Ms. Myers said. "One day he said, 'Wouldn't it be funny if . . .' and I said, 'Hey, that's a great idea.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Duffy, the band director, said he was skeptical when Ms. Myers approached him with the idea.</p>
        <p>"My reaction as a married person, someone who had gone through this myself, was that it seemed like kind of a bizarre setting for such an intimate service," Mr. Duffy says. "She and Jim managed to convince me, however, that they wanted to share this intimate moment with the Yale band."</p>
        <p>So on Saturday, during the Yale-Fordham game, Ms. Myers, Mr. Lockman and their 15-member wedding party will arrive at the field in limousines. She plans to wear a full-length formal wedding gown; he will wear a top hat and tails. Judge Robert Riley of the State Superior Court will perform the five-minute ceremony, and then the newly married couple will leave the stadium for a private reception.</p>
        <p>The band will plan the musical accompaniment during the rehearsal on Friday. "We'll provide them with an intro and an interesting formation," Mr. Duffy says.</p>
        <p>It's a good bet that the music will be nontraditional.</p>
        <p>The band's musical selections, ever eclectic, range from the themes from "The Simpsons" and "The Love Boat" to "The Imperial March" from "Star Wars" and Pink Floyd's "Another Brick in the Wall." During renditions of the Rolling Stones' "Sympathy for the Devil," the sousaphone players traditionally set their instruments on fire.  A Yale Bowl First</p>
        <p>Mr. Duffy said that Ms. Myers and Mr. Lockman were not the first band members to marry, but the wedding will be the first at the Yale Bowl and the first in which the marching band has taken part.</p>
        <p>Kate Alton, a Yale senior and the band's former historian, said the setting was fitting. "He was a sousaphone and she was the 'props goddess,' " she said. "Both were very dedicated bandies. It makes tremendous sense."</p>
        <p>Topping it all off, this is Yale's parents' weekend, when hundreds of parents will add to the crowd at the Yale Bowl.</p>
        <p>"I think they'll think it's kind of neat," Ms. Myers says. "Parents are more likely to like weddings."</p>
        <p>Both Ms. Myers and Mr. Lockman work at Worcester Academy in Worcester, Mass., where she is the assistant director of student activities and he teaches physics.</p>
        <p>Ms. Myers said the full impact of the event had not hit her yet.</p>
        <p>"Right now it's just a part of our halftime show," she said. "I guess it just hasn't occurred to me yet that it's my wedding."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
