<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="11FCAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1495899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDA1339F932A25755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wines of Germany</p>
        <p>A class about German wines will be given this evening from 6:30 to 9 at Jolly Hotel Madison Towers, 22 East 38th Street, by the PJ Wine School, which is owned by PJ Liquor Warehouse in Upper Manhattan. The fee is $65. For information: (212) 567-5500 or www.pjwine.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wines of Germany</p>
        <p>A class about German wines will be given this evening from 6:30 to 9 at Jolly Hotel Madison Towers, 22 East 38th Street, by the PJ Wine School, which is owned by PJ Liquor Warehouse in Upper Manhattan. The fee is $65. For information: (212) 567-5500 or www.pjwine.com.</p>
        <p>Dinner in the Park</p>
        <p>A tasting of foods from Greenwich Village restaurants will take place tomorrow from 5:30 to 8:30 p.m. in Washington Square Park. Tickets, to benefit restoration of the park, are $25 at the event. The tasting's sponsor is the Village Alliance Business Improvement District. For information: (212) 777-2173.</p>
        <p>Up the Hudson</p>
        <p>The Hudson Valley Wine and Food Festival will be Saturday and Sunday from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. at Montgomery Place Historic Estate, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. Local producers and restaurants will offer foods to sample, wines for tasting, a farmer's market and cooking demonstrations. Admission is $10 for adults, $5 for children under 12 and free for members of Historic Hudson Valley. Information: (845) 758-5461 or www.hudsonvalley.org.</p>
        <p>In the Parking Lot</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Barbecue of Syracuse will offer samples of pork and chili on Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m., in the parking lot at Fairway, 132nd Street and Broadway.</p>
        <p>Olé Olé Foods, a distributor of Spanish foods, will hold a sale and tasting of its products on Saturday from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. in its parking lot at 54 Schuyler Street, Belleville, N.J. Information: (973) 759-0333.</p>
        <p>At the Palace</p>
        <p>A food and wine tasting benefiting the School of Hospitality at Boston University will be Monday from 6 to 9 p.m. at the New York Palace hotel. Among the chefs will be Rocco DiSpirito of Rocco's and Union Pacific, Brian Bistrong of Citarella, Bryan Calvert of Cafe Atlas and Scott Cutaneo of Le Petit Chateau in Bernardsville, N.J., all B.U. graduates. Tickets are $125: (800) 800-3466 or www.bu.edualumnieventschefs.</p>
        <p>Still Life With Chef</p>
        <p>An auction of photographs, many of them on the subject of food, wine and chefs, will take place during a food and wine tasting Tuesday from 6:30 to 10 p.m. at the One Club, 21 East 26th Street. The event is a benefit for the International Center of Photography. Tickets are $175: (212) 857-0043.</p>
        <p>For City Harvest</p>
        <p>A tasting and auction benefiting City Harvest will be June 24 starting at 6 p.m. at the Artisanal Cheese Center, 500 West 37th Street. Tickets, $75, will be sold at the door. Information: (212) 982-8300, extension 108.</p>
        <p>Hamptons on a Plate</p>
        <p>A Taste of the Hamptons will be June 28 from 5 to 8 p.m. at the Wölffer Estate in Sagaponack, N.Y. The event, to benefit the Family Service League, will focus on food and wine from purveyors and restaurants in the Hamptons. Tickets are $150 in advance from (631) 427-3700, extension 255, or $175 at the door.</p>
        <p>FLORENCE FABRICANT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
