<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>War in Eastern Zaire Leaves Relief Agencies Scrambling</title>
    <meta content="04ZAIR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zaire</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rwanda</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Goma (Zaire)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations (Un)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Rwanda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Rwanda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DE1538F937A35752C1A960958260" item-length="1392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>War in Eastern Zaire Leaves Relief Agencies Scrambling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <dateline>GISENYI, Rwanda, Nov. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations aides, relief workers and diplomats are scrambling to find way to intervene in civil war in eastern Zaire and restore flow of aid to million Hutu refugees; it is unclear who leads rebel force that captured Goma, severing refugees from outside world; Rwanda denies reports its soldiers took part in battle, but admits shelling Goma in retaliation for Zaire's earlier mortar attack; denies covertly backing rebels; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a million Hutu refugees engulfed in a growing civil war in eastern Zaire, United Nations officials, relief workers and diplomats were scrambling today to find some way to intervene in the conflict and restore the flow of aid.</p>
        <p>But even as calls for an international rescue operation grew, the situation inside Zaire's eastern state of Kivu remained murky and there were no obvious solutions to the crisis short of a military intervention, United Nations officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a million Hutu refugees engulfed in a growing civil war in eastern Zaire, United Nations officials, relief workers and diplomats were scrambling today to find some way to intervene in the conflict and restore the flow of aid.</p>
        <p>But even as calls for an international rescue operation grew, the situation inside Zaire's eastern state of Kivu remained murky and there were no obvious solutions to the crisis short of a military intervention, United Nations officials said.</p>
        <p>To begin with, it was still unclear today who commanded the rebel force that captured the Zairian border town of Goma on Saturday morning, prompting the evacuation of aid workers and severing the refugees from the outside world. Nor was it known where the retreating Zairian Army was or if the fighting was  continuing.</p>
        <p>Though witnesses said that Rwandan troops took part in the battle for Goma -- a headquarters for the international relief operations --  Rwanda continued to deny that its soldiers had crossed the border or had taken Zairian territory. Those assertions were impossible to verify since Rwandan troops sealed the border this morning and would not let journalists cross.</p>
        <p>''We have no interest in going to Zaire,'' said Maj. Emmanuel Ndahiro, a spokesman for the Rwandan Ministry of Defense. ''Our forces are limited to our side of the border.''</p>
        <p>Major Ndahiro acknowledged that  Rwanda's army had shelled Goma on Saturday in retaliation for Zaire's mortar attacks earlier that day, but he said it did not invade Zaire. He also denied that his Government was covertly supporting the rebels. He said he did not even know who commanded the rebel force.</p>
        <p>''I actually don't know who is in charge,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most of the proposals being floated in Western capitals for aiding the refugees involve sending in an international peacekeeping force that would provide a safe passageway for people to march back to Rwanda, diplomats said. Food aid would be used to encourage the refugees to return, rather than to fuel perpetual camps.</p>
        <p>''People are talking about some kind of intervention that would allow the peaceful return of the refugees to Rwanda.'' said a diplomat in Kigali, speaking on the condition of anonymity. ''The things I have heard is that some kind of international force would create a safe corridor.''</p>
        <p>In Geneva, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, Sadako Ogata, called today for an outside force to set up ''emergency lifelines'' to the refugees, zones  through which food and medicine could pass to refugees or could allow refugees to return to Rwanda.</p>
        <p>''We must open humanitarian corridors to enable refugees to return in safety to Rwanda and Burundi,'' she said in a statement. ''Unless we reach the refugees soon, many women and children, the elderly, the sick and the wounded are going to die.''</p>
        <p>The French have also urged action. In Paris, a senior French Cabinet member, Xavier Emmanuelli, urged other European Union countries to be prepared to begin a huge  relief effort for Zaire, though he fell short of suggesting military action.</p>
        <p>Much is at stake. United Nations officials say a catastrophe is developing in Kivu that could rival the crisis in the summer of 1994, when thousands of Hutu refugees from Rwanda died every day of cholera in the camps around Goma.</p>
        <p>Since rebels began an offensive against the Zairian Government here two weeks ago, more than 700,000 of the 1.1 million Hutu refugees who fled to Zaire from Rwanda and Burundi have been pushed out of United Nations camps along the border and are now trekking farther westward into Zaire's interior. They have been joined by thousands of Zairians fleeing the violence.</p>
        <p>When the last foreign aid workers pulled out yesterday, the refugees were left to fend for themselves. Officials estimate that most of the refugees in southern Kivu have run out of the food they were given two weeks ago. In the north, refugees should have enough food to last about a week. But clean water is in short supply in both regions, and epidemics are certain to ravage the ragged columns of fleeing people.</p>
        <p>''I think it's likely people are already dying,'' said Paul Stromberg, a spokesman for the United Nations refugee agency in Kigali.</p>
        <p>The Rwandan refugees first arrived in July 1994, when more than a million Hutu poured into Zaire ahead of an advancing Tutsi rebel army. The exodus included thousands of soldiers, militiamen and civil servants who had taken part in a genocide against Tutsi in which an estimated 500,000 people perished. They have been an unsettling influence on the region ever since.</p>
        <p>Because the United Nations never separated the war criminals from other refugees, aid workers said, some camps became centers for Hutu guerrillas who raided Rwanda and Burundi. The Hutu ideologues in the camps also stirred up resentment against Tutsi living in Zaire.  Thousands of Tutsi were massacred or driven from their homes by Hutu in the Masisi region last spring.</p>
        <p>The current crisis started in September, when local officials in southern Kivu, who were allied with the former Hutu rebel groups, tried to expel Tutsi who had lived in the region for more than 200 years. Those Tutsi, known as Banyamulenge, resisted and, within a week, they pushed the Zairian Army out of a 60-mile-long region south of Lake Kivu and captured town of the Bukavu.</p>
        <p>But in northern Kivu, the rebellion appears to have been spearheaded by people from the Masisi region.  The rebels include not only Tutsi but also members who come from other ethnic groups, notably the Nande and Hunde, who oppose the Zairian Government and resent the Hutu refugees. Those groups also suffered at the hands of Hutu guerrillas in the Masisi violence last spring, diplomats say.</p>
        <p>The rebels who have captured Goma call themselves ''Bangilima'' or ''Ingilima,'' a catch-all phrase recalling a rebellion in Zaire in the 1960's. They have apparently formed an ad-hoc alliance with the rebels in southern Kivu.</p>
        <p>''It is two separate rebellions that came together, the coalescing point being their common unhappiness with the refugee presence,'' a diplomat said.</p>
        <p>Zaire has accused Rwanda of being behind both movements, asserting that the Rwandans have not only armed and trained the rebels but have also sent troops to fight alongside them. Rwanda's Tutsi-controlled Government has steadfastly denied the accusations, though it has expressed support for the rebels' cause and has accused Zaire of persecuting Tutsi.</p>
        <p>For Zaire's Government, the rebellion may have opened a Pandora's box. President Mobutu Sese Seko, the 66-year-old strongman who has held Zaire together for 31 years, has been in Switzerland for three months, fighting cancer. His absence has left a power vacuum.</p>
        <p>There are signs that Mr. Mobutu's hold on the country is loosening, even if he survives his illness. On Friday, about 10,000 students angry about the war in Kivu marched through the capital, Kinshasa, demanding the resignation of Mr. Mobutu's Government. Yesterday, in a rare display of disloyalty, the army chief of staff, Maj. Gen. Eluki Monga Aundu, accused the Government of not giving it enough financial and moral support in the Kivu region.</p>
        <p>The events in Kivu have also undercut the power of Prime Minister Leon Kengo wa Dondo, whose mother is a Rwandan Tutsi. Mr. Kengo wa Dondo has come under criticism  from students and opposition leaders for not declaring war on Rwanda and Burundi. ''Of Tutsi Origin, Kengo Must Go,'' said the three-inch-high headline on Saturday's front page of the independent Le Potential newspaper.</p>
        <p>For an international relief operation to work, the United Nations would need Rwanda's cooperation, aid officials said. The rebels have cut the road from Uganda to Goma over which most of the food for the camps was trucked, so food aid and medicine would have to be brought through Rwanda.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ndahiro said Rwanda would be willing to allow relief supplies through, but only if the aid remained in Rwanda, as a lure to bring refugees back.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
