<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an Era When the Polls Are King, Cookie-Cutter Campaigns</title>
    <meta content="04SURV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="POLITICS: POLITICAL MEMO" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Market Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Market Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4DC1538F937A35752C1A960958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an Era When the Polls Are King, Cookie-Cutter Campaigns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Both Pres Clinton and Bob Dole make significant use of public opinion polls and market research surveys in their campaigns (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When poll after poll tells voters that Bob Dole is running far behind in the Presidential race, do the surveys create a self-fulfilling reality?</p>
        <p>Most pollsters say no, and even those who think that a sense of an inevitable outcome can affect voter behavior say they cannot tell who would be more affected: those who believe that their candidate cannot win, or those who believe that their candidate will sail to victory whether they go to the polls or not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When poll after poll tells voters that Bob Dole is running far behind in the Presidential race, do the surveys create a self-fulfilling reality?</p>
        <p>Most pollsters say no, and even those who think that a sense of an inevitable outcome can affect voter behavior say they cannot tell who would be more affected: those who believe that their candidate cannot win, or those who believe that their candidate will sail to victory whether they go to the polls or not.</p>
        <p>But it seems a fitting question with which to end a Presidential race that may be remembered as so infused by polls and survey research findings that President Clinton actually turned a standard polling question about whether the country is ''on the right track'' into a campaign slogan. Mr. Dole, meanwhile, broke a cardinal rule of politics and talked about his survey research, explaining publicly several times that a campaign tactic was or was not followed because of what had been found in focus groups.</p>
        <p>In fact, polls -- and their survey research cousins, focus groups -- have become so all-pervasive this year in both politics and journalism that even some of the academics and political professionals who rely on them are starting to question their effects.</p>
        <p>''It's creating a climate where candidates and their counselors and reporters and the pundits all focus, from moment to moment, their framework for discussion, their analysis, their whole lives around these polls,'' said Norman J. Ornstein, a resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute.</p>
        <p>Carter Eskew, a Democratic political consultant, wonders whether the day is fast approaching when candidates will make a campaign appeal out of unpolled spontaneity.</p>
        <p>''I think it's interesting to see,'' he said, ''whether or not you'll have a wave of candidates in the year 1998 or 2000 who say, 'I'm not going to take polls and use focus groups -- I'm going to speak from the heart,' and whether that resonates with people.''</p>
        <p>It sometimes seems hard to remember that modern political polling -- its techniques taken from market research -- has been around for little more than half a century. And it was not until the Carter Administration that a political pollster, Patrick Cadell, reached the status of icon.</p>
        <p>These days, however, political candidates so poll-test their words and phrases that they can become mirrors of the public mood and political speech can sound like an echo chamber.</p>
        <p>''Everyone drives the message to the same place, and everyone begins to sound the same,'' Mr. Eskew said. As a result, a political theme ''wears out very quickly -- first it becomes mundane and then it becomes annoying,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''People don't know why, but they hear a lot of politicians using the same words,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Take Mr. Dole's charge that Mr. Clinton is ''liberal, liberal liberal.'' President Reagan used the same chant on the stump for George Bush in 1988. In fact, crying liberal is a Republican staple. Remember ''Mario Cuomo: too liberal for too long,'' which George E. Pataki wielded to win New York's governorship? What about ''liberal to a T,'' which the commercials of Representative Dick Zimmer use to describe his Democratic opponent, Representative Robert G. Torricelli, in the race for New Jersey's open Senate seat?</p>
        <p>The reason for the epithet is clear to pollsters. Only about 20 percent of the American public describes itself as liberal, so the label puts a candidate out of touch with majority sentiment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, on the other hand, brought something new to the campaign. His cry of ''we're on the right track and we're not going back'' marked the ultimate apotheosis of a polling question.</p>
        <p>For while the public may have taken the slogan as a railroad pun -- Mr. Clinton was riding his campaign train into the convention at the time -- pollsters recognized in his refrain the classic question many of them use to take the public pulse.</p>
        <p>When polls indicate that more than 50 percent of the public believes that the nation is ''on the right track,'' it is considered a favorable political climate for the incumbent. That is the sentiment Mr. Clinton exploited with his slogan and perhaps even tried to intensify.</p>
        <p>Even if his theme may have seemed like a pollster's private joke, Mr. Clinton has learned -- by being viewed early in his Administration as a man who shifts with the polls -- not to showcase the daily polling taking place inside his campaign organization or the mechanics of his campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, however, has had some extraordinary moments of public wrestling with survey results.</p>
        <p>In the spring, after he rather perplexingly asked supporters at a rally whether they would feel more comfortable leaving their children with Mr. Clinton or with him, Mr. Dole explained, ''It's what a couple of people have told me who had focus groups.''</p>
        <p>And last month, discussing with the talk show host Don Imus how strongly he would go on the offensive against his opponent, Mr. Dole said, ''We found in our surveys if you go on attack with Clinton -- maybe it's the same if he attacks me, but we haven't seen it -- that the first people who jump overboard are women.''</p>
        <p>As the race draws to a close, the candidates themselves, at least, are acting as if the polls could affect turnout and skew the outcome. ''All these polls are pictures of horse races that aren't over,'' Mr. Clinton warned a crowd recently. And Mr. Dole urged his supporters even more sharply not to heed the news media. ''You make up your mind,'' he urged. ''Don't let them make up your mind for you!''</p>
        <p>POLITICS: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
