<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Junior Colleges Supply Crew for Major Match</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT: EAST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL COLLEGIATE ATHLETIC ASSN (NCAA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D6113DF932A15750C0A965958260" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Junior Colleges Supply Crew for Major Match</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</byline>
      <dateline>SYRACUSE, March 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cincinnati Coach Bob Huggins has quit defending his use of junior college transfers to bolster his Bearcats squad. He doesn't even like to talk about the philosophical ramifications anymore.</p>
        <p>New Mexico State Coach Neil McCarthy believes there is still a certain stigma attached to recruiting junior college players. He feels an ugly prejudice at work in college basketball that says it is somehow unsavory to take JUCO's -- as they are euphemistically referred to -- because it sullies the time-honored approach of slowly building a championship team with high school recruits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cincinnati Coach Bob Huggins has quit defending his use of junior college transfers to bolster his Bearcats squad. He doesn't even like to talk about the philosophical ramifications anymore.</p>
        <p>New Mexico State Coach Neil McCarthy believes there is still a certain stigma attached to recruiting junior college players. He feels an ugly prejudice at work in college basketball that says it is somehow unsavory to take JUCO's -- as they are euphemistically referred to -- because it sullies the time-honored approach of slowly building a championship team with high school recruits.</p>
        <p>Whatever the arguments, junior college recruiting seems to be working for Cincinnati, 25-4 and a Final Four team last year, and New Mexico State, 26-7 and making its fourth consecutive appearance in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament.</p>
        <p>The two teams, who both play high-flying, pressure-filled basketball, meet in the second round of the East Region at the Carrier Dome here Sunday. Nine of the 12 Aggies are junior college transfers, while 6 of 14 came to Cincinnati from junior colleges.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the Massachusetts-Virginia game that starts the afternoon doubleheader features two teams laden with freshmen and sophomores recruited from high schools. From Both Angles</p>
        <p>McCarthy, who has been at New Mexico State for seven seasons, has seen both sides of the coin when it comes to recruiting. He spent 10 years at Weber State, recruiting high school players. But because Weber State wasn't a major-college powerhouse, McCarthy wasn't landing blue-chip players.</p>
        <p>"We were big, tall, slow and could shoot real well," McCarthy said of his Weber State teams.</p>
        <p>Those are the kind of teams that don't cut it on the major-college level -- not when entertainment value rates right up with there with academic integrity. So, McCarthy started searching for high-octane players at junior colleges in California and the Southwest.</p>
        <p>"The junior college players were already more physically and mentally developed than the players we were able to bring in as freshmen," McCarthy said. "I'll always stick with the junior college guys. They've got their associates degree and got two years left to graduate and they're motivated. Most of them have had to struggle to get where they've gotten." Help From Knight</p>
        <p>He believes Indiana Coach Bob Knight may have taken some of the stigma away from recruiting junior college players when he took guard Keith Smart and Smart helped the Hoosiers win a N.C.A.A. championship in 1987.</p>
        <p>Recruiting junior college players has forced McCarthy to simplify his offense, which relies on quickness in penetrating the lane, flying to the basket for put-backs on rebounds and a lot of slam dunks. And because of the physical and mental development, his JUCO's are more prepared for the rigors of that style of play.</p>
        <p>Unlike transfers from other Division I colleges, players who transfer from junior colleges do not have to sit out for a season.</p>
        <p>Some of the key matchups in the game will feature junior college players that were recruited by both McCarthy and Huggins. Bearcats guard Nick Van Exel, who attended Trinity (Texas) Junior College, and Aggies guard Sam Crawford, who went to Moorpark (Calif.) Junior College, are considered two of the best point guards in the nation. Both are silky smooth penetrators with a velvet touch on their jump shots, and they unselfishly run their respective offenses. A Dunk-o-rama?</p>
        <p>And the matchup of New Mexico State forward Cliff Reed and Cincinnati forward Eric Martin, a pair of flying wrecking balls who delight in raining down slam dunks on opponents' heads, could be entertaining.</p>
        <p>"They're very athletic," Martin said. "Seeing them play is like watching us practice. If we don't box out, a few of our players might get embarrassed and dunked on."</p>
        <p>When Martin, who transferred to Cincinnati from Rancho Santiago (Calif.) College, was asked about going up against Reed, he sounded like the critics of recruiting junior college players.</p>
        <p>"I've seen New Mexico State play before, but I've never noticed him," Martin said. "When I saw them play the other night, I was like, 'What did they do? Go out and get a guy to come in and play for them these last few weeks?' "  N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT: EAST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
