<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manhattan Quartet in Season Finale</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DC1038F932A15750C0A965958260" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manhattan Quartet in Season Finale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO sources of free concerts are ready to call it a season, but not before offering a final dash of chamber music.</p>
        <p>The Pleasantville Chamber Music Society has rung up a proud record of presenting top-notch ensembles, but the unquestioned favorite for about a dozen years has been the Manhattan String Quartet. In what has come to be an annual event, the quartet returns to the Pleasantville Presbyterian Church this afternoon at 3 o'clock. Eric and Roy Lewis, violinists; John Dexter, violist, and Christopher Finckel, cellist, will play Schubert's A minor Quartet and two Shostakovich quartets, Nos. 11 and 12. No tickets are needed, but to learn more about the society, the number to call is 769-1827.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO sources of free concerts are ready to call it a season, but not before offering a final dash of chamber music.</p>
        <p>The Pleasantville Chamber Music Society has rung up a proud record of presenting top-notch ensembles, but the unquestioned favorite for about a dozen years has been the Manhattan String Quartet. In what has come to be an annual event, the quartet returns to the Pleasantville Presbyterian Church this afternoon at 3 o'clock. Eric and Roy Lewis, violinists; John Dexter, violist, and Christopher Finckel, cellist, will play Schubert's A minor Quartet and two Shostakovich quartets, Nos. 11 and 12. No tickets are needed, but to learn more about the society, the number to call is 769-1827.</p>
        <p>In Ossining, the Great Music in a Great Space series presents its final concert of the season this afternoon at 3:30 P.M. at the Public Library, with the violinist Rachel Varga and the pianist Audrey Axinn collaborating on sonatas by Bartok, Beethoven and Richard Strauss. The number to call for more information is 949-2416.</p>
        <p>Two events of high promise that require tickets are scheduled today. The Concordia Choir under Ralph Schultz performs selections of sacred music spanning almost four centuries on the theme Sing for Joy at 3 o'clock in the college's Sommer Center in Bronxville. More information is available by calling 337-9300.</p>
        <p>The Eroica Trio of Adela Pena, violinist; Sara Sant'Ambrogio, cellist, and Erika Nickrenz, pianist, plays trios by Ravel, Beethoven and Martinu for the Westchester Chamber Music Society tonight at 8:30 at Congregation Emanu El in Rye. More details are available by calling 948-6533 or 723-0222.</p>
        <p>Monday afternoon recitals are the norm for the Hudson Valley Music Club, and two outstanding artists -- Rosemary Glyde and Diana Kacso -- are collaborating tomorrow at 2 P.M. in the club's headquarters at 54 Clinton Avenue, Dobbs Ferry. In addition to the Hindemith Sonata for Viola and Piano, the duo is presenting something of a concert novelty, a transcription of the Rachmaninoff G minor Cello Sonata. For more details, the number to call is 693-1489.</p>
        <p>At Grace Episcopal Church in White Plains, the cycle of Wednesday matinees continues at 12:35 P.M. with the wife-husband, violin-piano team of Barbara and Edward Nord. Sonatas by Handel and Beethoven are scheduled along with the Heifetz transcription of selections from Gershwin's "Porgy and Bess" and Falla's "Ritual Fire Dance." For three years, Mrs. Nord played in Heifetz master classes in Los Angeles. The number to call for more information is 949-0384.</p>
        <p>Next weekend, the keyboard reigns in Katonah, Peekskill and Purchase. The spring recital series at Caramoor in Katonah continues Saturday evening at 8 o'clock when the pianist Yefim Bronfman plays two sonatas by Prokofiev and one by Beethoven in the Music Room. For further details, the number to call is 232-1251.</p>
        <p>Philharmonia Virtuosi is scheduled to appear in both Peekskill and Purchase with the pianist Lisa Moore playing the Shostakovich Concerto No. 1 and another pianist, Shauna Eberhard, a 16-year-old student at the Hoff-Barthelson School, playing Saint-Saens's perky "Wedding Cake." Gustav Holst's "St. Paul's Suite" adds further charm to the program. The Peekskill performance takes place Saturday at 8 P.M. at the Paramount Center. The program is being repeated next Sunday afternoon at 2 o'clock in Theater C of the Performing Arts Center at the State University of New York at Purchase.  For reservations, the numbers to call are 739-2333 (Paramount Center), 251-6200 (SUNY Purchase) or 693-5595 (Philharmonia Virtuosi offices).</p>
        <p>Coco is the whimsical acronym for the Children's Opera Company of Ossining, established by Arthur Jay to give youngsters first-hand understanding of opera as a dramatic form. Second and third graders are used as chorus members; fourth and fifth graders take most of the major roles, and middle school students who have sung in past productions become apprentices who handle technical aspects. The high school orchestra provides accompaniment, both for auditorium previews and for the free public performance of "Sticks and Stones" on Thursday at 7:30 P.M. at Ossining High School.</p>
        <p>"About 15 years ago, I directed a production of James Reaney's play 'Names and Nicknames' and somehow knew even then that the script was well on its way to being an opera libretto," Mr. Jay said. "I created such a libretto in 1990, and even visited Mr. Reaney that summer, walking the farm he had in mind when he wrote the play. The score, now called 'Sticks and Stones' was written last year, and was ready for rehearsal this past September.</p>
        <p>"We are extremely pleased with the results to date. The work makes a more direct emotional connection with the young performers than did any of our previous productions, and the kids have been troupers, working very hard at getting it right. I think I have finally gotten close to the style and form which will really introduce children to the joy of opera."</p>
        <p>For those considering taking their offspring, Mr. Jay said, "The opera is suitable for young children and their families." More information may be obtained by calling Mr. Jay at the Brookside School, 762-5780.</p>
        <p>Tania Halko, a sophomore at the Juilliard School of Music, will return to her alma mater, Fox Lane High School, as soloist in the Hummel Fantasy for Viola and Strings. The program on Friday at 8 P.M., part of the subscription season of the Mount Kisco Concert Association, also features Gene Forrell conducting the chamber orchestra, which calls itself the Vivaldi Traveling Circus. Works by Vivaldi are scheduled along with Samuel Barber's "Adagio for Strings," a C. P. E. Bach symphony and pieces by Tchaikovsky and Bartok. The reservations number in Mount Kisco is 666-9181.</p>
        <p>On the folk music circuit tonight at 7 o'clock in the Uptown Coffeehouse (in the Ethical Culture Building on Fieldston Road in the Bronx) are two singer-songwriters from Seattle: Heidi Muller, who grew up in New Jersey but moved to the West Coast about 10 years ago, and Stanley Greenthal. For driving directions, the numbers to call are 682-0484 and (718) 543-3474.</p>
        <p>In Tarrytown, the Music Hall will be alive with folk song and stories next Saturday evening at 8 o'clock and next Sunday evening at 7 o'clock in what the Twin Cloud Concerts producer, Thom Wolke, calls "an acoustic music indoor festival." The participants: the guitar virtuoso Leo Kottke, John McCutcheon, master of the hammered dulcimer and composer of some of the most poignant of all contemporary folk songs, and the Story, otherwise known as Jonathan Brooke and Jennifer Kimball. Mr. Wolke says of the duo, "Their music can alternate between heart-rending poetry and infectious flights of fancy." More information is availabale by calling 332-8497.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
