<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Radio Rights: A Move to Auction Licenses That Sell</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LICENSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUCTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC1731F932A15750C0A965958260" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Radio Rights: A Move to Auction Licenses That Sell</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, the Federal Government has auctioned off timber rights in the national forests and offshore oil and gas leases on the continental shelf.</p>
        <p>Now the Clinton Admininstration is pushing hard to auction off what is arguably the Federal Government's biggest remaining free-lunch program for the rich: rights to the airwaves of the radio spectrum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, the Federal Government has auctioned off timber rights in the national forests and offshore oil and gas leases on the continental shelf.</p>
        <p>Now the Clinton Admininstration is pushing hard to auction off what is arguably the Federal Government's biggest remaining free-lunch program for the rich: rights to the airwaves of the radio spectrum.</p>
        <p>Borrowing an idea from the Reagan and Bush Administrations, President Clinton hopes to raise $4.4 billion over four years by auctioning off all radio licenses for new communication services to the highest bidder. Secretary of Commerce Ronald Brown told Congress last week that auctions should apply to everybody seeking new licenses: broadcasters, satellite services and the emerging "personal communication services" that include low-cost pocket telephones and wireless computers.</p>
        <p>In a sharp departure from the views of many Congressional Democrats, Mr. Brown argued that auctioning the radio spectrum would be fairer to taxpayers, lead to more efficient use of the crowded airwaves and discourage the rampant speculation spawned by today's system of awarding licenses through sweepstakes-like lotteries.</p>
        <p>The idea of auctions has long drawn fire from Congressional Democrats who fear that open bidding would squeeze out cash-strapped entrepreneurs and turn a valuable national resource over to big corporations. But many corporations don't like paying for the spectrum. And smaller players question whether they, too, will have a role in the new communications marketplace. Underlying the debate is a sense that it is unseemly to treat a public resource as a crass commodity.</p>
        <p>But that opposition is softening quickly and not just out of deference to President Clinton. A growing number of Democrats are convinced that the current system desperately needs an overhaul and that auctions may be the only logical alternative.</p>
        <p>Though they are intangible, the radio frequencies are in many respects a form of real estate. Like a patch of prime property in midtown Manhattan, radio frequencies are in scarce supply because the most desirable ones have already been licensed.  And, like real estate, licenses to use the airwaves are routinely bought and sold in a market that totals tens of billions of dollars. Merit, Not Money</p>
        <p>Under current law, the Federal Communications Commission hands out new licenses at no charge, using one of two approaches. Licenses to run television or radio stations are awarded through a protracted process of public hearings to determine the merits of the applicants.</p>
        <p>Licenses to operate most other for-profit services, from paging systems to cellular telephones, are handed out through lotteries. Lotteries are potentially much faster than comparative hearings and are based on the premise that trying to weigh the public spiritedness of rival paging companies is pointless .</p>
        <p>But the lotteries have attracted thousands of speculators who file dozens of applications in the hope of "winning" a license that they can then resell for a quick profit. Indeed, the lotteries used to hand out cellular licenses during the 1980's generated scores of professional "application mills" that filed hundreds of applications at a time.</p>
        <p>The resale value of these licenses can be astronomical. The Commerce Department estimated in 1991 that the market value of cellular telephone licenses handed out at no charge during the 1980's was at least $46 billion. Last year, the Congressional Budget Office estimated that auctioning off a band of frequencies equal in size to the band now reserved for cellular phones would bring the Government $1.3 billion to $5.7 billion.</p>
        <p>"It's a national scandal that we gave away that cellular spectrum," said Henry Geller, a former general counsel to the F.C.C. who adamantly supports the Government auctions.  Rather than protecting people with limited resources, he said, license lotteries simply lead to "private auctions" that let lucky speculators make a quick killing. "Nobody would do that with offshore oil leases," he said. "Why should we do it here?"</p>
        <p>The idea is catching hold in Congress. In the Senate, a bill sponsored by Daniel K. Inouye, Democrat of Hawaii, and Ernest F. Hollings, Democrat of South Carolina, would reassign a big block of Government frequencies for new commercial technologies and would create an experimental auction for part of that block. In the House of Representatives, lawmakers on the Energy and Commerce Committee are drafting a bill that would authorize auctions for many of the new frequencies.</p>
        <p>As a practical matter, no one is talking about auctioning licenses already assigned to radio and television broadcasters, which command a powerful grass-roots lobbying force.  Many lawmakers remain convinced that broadcasters have special obligations to balance public service with their quest for profits, and worry that auctions would undermine that goal.</p>
        <p>Opposition to auctions comes from many quarters. Broadcasters don't want to pay for frequencies for new digital audio formats that promise a quality of sound that is as good as that on compact disks. Rural telephone companies fear they will be unable to outbid big corporations on new wireless phone services. "Without a rural program, rural areas will not be served as they should because small telephone companies won't be able to compete in auctions against corporations with deep pockets," said Lisa Zaina, general counsel for the Organization for the Protection and Advancement of Small Telephone Companies, a trade group representing 430 firms.</p>
        <p>But some huge companies are also opposed. G.T.E. Corporation, which owns local telephone companies around the country, has consistently opposed auctions. The company argues that auctions would put providers of new service at a disadvantage to cellular companies and broadcasters did not pay the Government for their licenses.</p>
        <p>But many traditional opponents say the debate is not over whether auctions will occur, but how. "Those with deep pockets do not always have the best ideas," wrote Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts, to the Administration. "How can we construct an auction system that does not simply ask, 'Who is the wealthiest among you?' "  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
