<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Talks With Torre, Pinstripes For Pavano</title>
    <meta content="12YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/sports/baseball/12yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1634399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pavano, Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavano, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DF1F31F931A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Talks With Torre, Pinstripes For Pavano</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Talks With Torre, Pinstripes for Pavano</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Dec. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees sign pitcher Carl Pavano to four-year contract; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carl Pavano talked pitching over lunch at Curt Schilling's house outside Boston. In Detroit, the Hall of Famer Al Kaline showed him around town. The Baltimore Orioles and the Seattle Mariners also played host to him.</p>
        <p>But on Saturday morning, from his off-season home in the woods near Montreal, Pavano told his agent to negotiate a deal with the Yankees. The sides were closing in on a four-year contract for just under $40 million, pending a physical, and Manager Joe Torre made the difference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carl Pavano and the Yankees are closing in on a four-year contract for just under $40 million, and Manager Joe Torre made the difference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carl Pavano talked pitching over lunch at Curt Schilling's house outside Boston. In Detroit, the Hall of Famer Al Kaline showed him around town. The Baltimore Orioles and the Seattle Mariners also played host to him.</p>
        <p>But on Saturday morning, from his off-season home in the woods near Montreal, Pavano told his agent to negotiate a deal with the Yankees. The sides were closing in on a four-year contract for just under $40 million, pending a physical, and Manager Joe Torre made the difference.</p>
        <p>''His conversations with Joe Torre, who spoke with him again by phone in the last couple of days, really were impactful,'' Pavano's agent, Scott Shapiro, said. ''Carl told me point-blank that he would go to war for the man. You can't say anything bad about the decision of wanting to play for Joe Torre.''</p>
        <p>Pavano, who turns 29 next month, went 18-8 for the Florida Marlins last season after dominating the Yankees in Game 4 of the 2003 World Series. He will join a rotation that is slated to have Mike Mussina, Kevin Brown, Javier Vazquez and Jaret Wright, and might not have room for Eric Milton.</p>
        <p>Yankees General Manager Brian Cashman said he hoped to complete Pavano's deal as soon as possible. ''My intent is not to wait,'' Cashman said. ''We'll try to push through this sooner rather than later.''</p>
        <p>Milton, a left-hander, has not budged from his desire for a three-year, $24 million contract. With Pavano in the fold, Milton might have missed his chance to rejoin the Yankees, the team that signed him in 1996.</p>
        <p>Rumblings among baseball officials, scouts and agents on Saturday indicated that Wright had failed his physical, which would negate the three-year, $21 million deal he agreed to last week.</p>
        <p>''He was great for us, but with baseball physicals, you never know,'' Atlanta Braves General Manager John Schuerholz said. ''He passed one physical, but I don't know. He was healthy for us.''</p>
        <p>Wright's agent, Craig Landis, refused to comment, and Cashman said that the Yankees were still ''very interested'' in Wright. The Yankees were planning more extensive tests on Wright, but several baseball officials said they expected Wright to pass.</p>
        <p>Still, Wright's medical history was an obvious issue for the Yankees. They had a folder of information on Wright in their hotel suite, and Stuart Hershon, the team doctor, conferred with Cashman during the day.</p>
        <p>Wright has had two operations on his right shoulder, but he made 32 starts for Atlanta last season. The Yankees have not announced his signing, and an official from another team said they could back out by citing a failed physical if they were to reach agreements with Pavano and Milton.</p>
        <p>Cashman said Friday that he planned to meet with Milton's agent, Casey Close. But Milton has long held that he should be paid $8 million a season. His old team, the Philadelphia Phillies, turned away from him when the former Yankee Jon Lieber agreed to sign for $7 million a year for three seasons.</p>
        <p>Milton's stance could leave the Yankees without a left-hander in their rotation again. But Cashman said, ''I have no problem with that whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>Signing Pavano would be a coup for the Yankees, although some people in baseball questioned whether a pitcher with a 57-58 career record was worth almost $10 million a season.</p>
        <p>Still, Pavano has improved his victory total and earned run average in each of the past three seasons. He worked 2221/3. innings last season, which would have easily led the Yankees' staff. He is said to have the makeup to handle New York; Pavano grew up in Southington, Conn.</p>
        <p>''Carl is a pretty level-headed kid,'' said Jack McKeon, his manager with the Marlins. ''He has a lot of pride and a tremendous desire to get better. He's not satisfied with winning 18. He wants to get better. Nothing is going to bother him.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have built no momentum in a possible trade for the Arizona Diamondbacks' Randy Johnson. The St. Louis Cardinals asked the Yankees on Saturday about participating in a three-way trade, suggesting that the Yankees trade Vazquez, Brad Halsey, Felix Rodriguez and cash in a deal. But the Yankees said they had no interest in resuming trade talks with Arizona.</p>
        <p>''We are not re-engaging,'' Cashman said. ''The call would have to come from them.''</p>
        <p>Cashman said he was still talking to the free agents Orlando Hernández and Matt Clement, and he had a meeting last night with Fernando Cuza, the agent for Pedro Martínez.</p>
        <p>The Mets still held out hope of signing Martínez. The Boston Red Sox have guaranteed a third year in their effort to keep Martínez, but Cuza said the Mets were still ''very much'' a possibility to sign him.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the meetings, we'll find out where we are and make a decision and evaluate where he'll end up,'' Cuza said. ''But it could take longer than the weekend.''</p>
        <p>Cuza said he would meet on Saturday night with Mets General Manager Omar Minaya, who has also asked about another Cuza client, outfielder Moises Alou. Asked if he would soon have to present his final offer to Martínez, Minaya said, ''We're getting close to doing that.''</p>
        <p>The Mets could sign the veteran shortstop Barry Larkin, who could receive significant playing time if injuries again limit José Reyes.</p>
        <p>The Mets are also looking for a first baseman, with the free-agent sluggers Carlos Delgado and Richie Sexson available. Both players were at the winter meetings on Saturday, although Minaya would not say if he had met with either of them. The Yankees, however, met with them, even though they seem to prefer signing Tino Martinez for first base.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph said he would be satisfied with a defensive specialist at first base. That could point to a trade for Boston's Doug Mientkiewicz.</p>
        <p>''I'm a defense guy, especially with a young infield,'' Randolph said. ''Ideally, you want power at first base, and that's nice, but you want a guy who's going to catch the ball. I think defense first.''</p>
        <p>Randolph said that he had spoken with about half the players on the Mets since his hiring on Nov. 3, but that he had not yet reached the team's marquee player, catcher Mike Piazza.</p>
        <p>''He could be on some island somewhere sipping piña coladas,'' Randolph said. ''I know Mike. I'm going to assume he's busy and keep trying.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
