<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paris in All Her Shades</title>
    <meta content="12BOOK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/fashion/12BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1634213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Penelope</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilton, Paris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mair, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions of an Heiress (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Paris Hilton: The Naked Truth (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hilton, Paris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DA1131F931A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paris in All Her Shades</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paris in All Her Shades</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Penelope Green</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Penelope</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Penelope Green Books of Style column reviews Paris Hilton book Confessions of an Heiress and George Mair book Paris Hilton: The Naked Truth; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONFESSIONS OF AN HEIRESS  A Tongue-in-Chic Peek Behind the Pose  By Paris Hilton with Merle Ginsberg  Fireside, $22.</p>
        <p>PARIS HILTON  The Naked Truth  By George Mair  Chamberlain Brothers, $9.95.</p>
        <p>LAST Wednesday, Paris Hilton told Barbara Walters that she doesn't just sit around saying ''That's hot!'' all day. Oh, no: she's an avid reader, Ms. Walters's interview disclosed, and a hard worker. Ms. Hilton joined Michael Moore and the founders of Google, Larry Page and Sergey Brin, as one of Ms. Walters's choices for the 10 most fascinating people of 2004, rather exalted company for a 23-year-old heiress with a sprayed-on tan, a voracious appetite for pink clothing and a teacup Chihuahua named Tinkerbell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two books, one of which is a memoir, look at the life of Paris Hilton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONFESSIONS OF AN HEIRESS  A Tongue-in-Chic Peek Behind the Pose  By Paris Hilton with Merle Ginsberg  Fireside, $22.</p>
        <p>PARIS HILTON  The Naked Truth  By George Mair  Chamberlain Brothers, $9.95.</p>
        <p>LAST Wednesday, Paris Hilton told Barbara Walters that she doesn't just sit around saying ''That's hot!'' all day. Oh, no: she's an avid reader, Ms. Walters's interview disclosed, and a hard worker. Ms. Hilton joined Michael Moore and the founders of Google, Larry Page and Sergey Brin, as one of Ms. Walters's choices for the 10 most fascinating people of 2004, rather exalted company for a 23-year-old heiress with a sprayed-on tan, a voracious appetite for pink clothing and a teacup Chihuahua named Tinkerbell.</p>
        <p>Of course, Ms. Hilton has had an awfully exciting year: She was a star, with her best friend, Nicole Richie, of her own reality television show (they have filmed a second season, ''The Simple Life 2'') and of her own homemade sex video (which added that all-important Rob Lowe-Tonya Harding-Pamela Anderson chiaroscuro to a glittery public persona); she became a Guess girl, all fluffy, pink and white and snuggling a teddy bear, and a recording artist (her album is not out yet but her first single is called -- perhaps this was not such a felicitous choice -- ''Screwed''); and, finally, Ms. Hilton is now a memoirist.</p>
        <p>''Confessions of an Heiress'' is deliciously pink, frosted with photos (more than 300) and larded with tasty revelations. Here are some:</p>
        <p>The title of her single, well, she didn't think about its double meaning. ''It's not what you think!'' she writes. ''It's about a girl who really falls for a guy and knows she's emotionally in too deep and in trouble, so she's screwed.''</p>
        <p>That being an heiress is good for traveling, but it's hard work. That being an heiress means being in charge, though it's not that easy.</p>
        <p>That an heiress should always be more important than her clothes.</p>
        <p>That it's a good investment to have your makeup applied by a professional. That way you can sleep in it, and the stuff is on the next day. (The spray-on tan is from Mystic Tan.)</p>
        <p>That even an heiress like Paris has flaws; hers are big feet.</p>
        <p>That the jet-set life is paling a bit. ''The ones who are in their 30's and 40's who do it now were high school nerds,'' she sniffs. Ms. Hilton is dreaming of finer things these days, like puppies and babies.</p>
        <p>That it's important to keep people wondering. Say little, smile a lot and don't give too much away -- for free. Don't be one of those heiresses who talk about every tight T-shirt they have to buy and every carbohydrate they eat. (For the record, Ms. Hilton is pro-carbohydrate, pro-fast-food. ''Always order the largest portion of French fries. Otherwise you'll just want more.'')</p>
        <p>That she takes her dog, her work and her family seriously, but she doesn't take herself all that seriously.</p>
        <p>''And that's the bottom line for me. While the stuff printed about me over the last few years is amusing and makes me laugh, I've finally decided to let the world know: O.K., I get it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hilton's dark side -- she went to . . . private school, she has . . . a silly name, people think she is . . . trashy -- is the subject of a hilarious exposé, ''Paris Hilton: The Naked Truth,'' by George Mair, whose journalistic skills seem drawn from the Weekly World News school. The book seems not to have been copy edited (Blythe Danner's famous daughter's first name is not spelled ''Gweneth''), nor even looked over by its author, who appears to have confused his research and writing files, like a bad student tipping the entire contents of a Google search into his senior paper on current affairs.</p>
        <p>There are three full pages devoted to the high jinks of students and parents at some of Manhattan's private schools, none of which Paris attended. There is even a lively discussion of the Prep for Prep program, in which gifted minority students leaven the mix and force rich people to fight even harder to secure a spot for their progeny, asserts Mr. Mair, ''with some even finding their way into the so-called Jewish schools.'' Huh? And what's he on about with this line? ''J.A.P. used to stand for Jewish American Princess, but now it's lost its religious and gender overtones to refer to prep school students generally.''</p>
        <p>Such weirdnesses debase Mr. Mair's docudrama, which is nonetheless riveting for its howlers (Paris, you can rest easy). Here are some:</p>
        <p>Ms. Hilton, who has become famous in paparazzi shots for her sway-back swagger and pivot-pose, was trained, says Mr. Mair, by Willi Ninja, the voguing star of the Jennie Livingston documentary ''Paris Is Burning.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mair also asserts that negotiations with Guess tottered ''around and dwindled to nothing.'' His Guess homework includes two press-stopping details: that when you Google Guess jeans, the most popular hits are not for Paris Hilton, but for Claudia Schiffer and Anna Nicole Smith. He has unearthed, too, the results of a national survey indicating that Paris Hilton is the most common name for phony deliveries.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mair is deeper than you think. He gnaws over Freud's theories regarding toilet training and money, and puts forth the notion that scions of rich families who wrestle over wills yearn to return to the womb. Finally, he worries that Ms. Hilton will give short shrift to acting, modeling and jewelry design, and then hop on the marriage-divorce treadmill, just as the famous Hilton brides Elizabeth Taylor and Zsa Zsa Gabor did, ''thus cementing a quasi-psychic connection with Hilton family karma.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
