<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Divorce, Seventh Avenue Style</title>
    <meta content="12PATR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/fashion/12PATR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1634222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ellis, Perry, International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Ferla, Ruth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Perry Ellis International Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DA1131F931A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Divorce, Seventh Avenue Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Divorce, Seventh Avenue Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH LA FERLA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Ferla, Ruth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rift between designer Patrick Robinson and Perry Ellis International, which ended in Robinson's departure, is one example of fashion industry's frequent disconnect between art and commerce; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY most accounts, Patrick Robinson's spring 2005 collection for Perry Ellis was stellar: 18 looks enlivened by Mr. Robinson's whimsical touches: frills and ruching set off by crisp tailored pieces. The line was unveiled in September to positive reviews and a flurry of interest from some of the nation's most powerful stores.</p>
        <p>But when those merchants flocked to the designer's showroom the following day, they were brusquely turned away, informed that the clothes were not for sale. Perry Ellis International had decided, without explanation, not to produce the line. The last week in November, Mr. Robinson abruptly resigned, leaving in doubt the future of the label.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Was Patrick Robinson's departure from Perry Ellis emblematic of the industry's failure to nurture its own or the fallout of a bad match?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY most accounts, Patrick Robinson's spring 2005 collection for Perry Ellis was stellar: 18 looks enlivened by Mr. Robinson's whimsical touches: frills and ruching set off by crisp tailored pieces. The line was unveiled in September to positive reviews and a flurry of interest from some of the nation's most powerful stores.</p>
        <p>But when those merchants flocked to the designer's showroom the following day, they were brusquely turned away, informed that the clothes were not for sale. Perry Ellis International had decided, without explanation, not to produce the line. The last week in November, Mr. Robinson abruptly resigned, leaving in doubt the future of the label.</p>
        <p>Predictably, the news gave rise to murmurs that Mr. Robinson's departure, which capped six months of fraught negotiations over creative control of the brand, was emblematic of fashion's ills and, in particular, the industry's failure to nurture its own.</p>
        <p>There are intimations, however, that the story is more complex. Mr. Robinson's exit appears to have been the fallout of a bad match, the sort endemic to the fashion world, in which alliances are often forged between partners with widely divergent expectations. In this instance, the marriage of Mr. Robinson, who aspired to produce a sophisticated designer collection, and his mass-oriented employer, was probably destined to fail, its collapse resulting from an ill fit between the wares and the stores where they were sold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson said little to counter the impression that he was but the latest casualty in the battle of art versus commerce. He confirmed that he would take a design post at Puig, the Paris-based fashion house that produces collections for Carolina Herrera, Nina Ricci and Paco Rabanne. He described his three-season tenure with Perry Ellis as ''a fantastic opportunity,'' but added somewhat darkly, ''I don't think I've ever gotten along with the suits.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps for good reason. ''There is nothing about the industry that encourages people to think in the long term, to foster talent for more than a season or two,'' said Sally Singer, the fashion features director of Vogue, which had championed Mr. Robinson in its pages. (Mr. Robinson's wife, Virginia Smith, is the market fashion director at the magazine.) Joan Kaner, the fashion director of Neiman Marcus, recalled a time, before luxury giants and other corporate entities began gobbling up labels, when designers like Calvin Klein owned their brand. ''They could gamble on their talent with their own money,'' she said. ''Now, when you sell to the big guys with the big bucks, you have to toe their line.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson maintained he had done just that, adhering to a mandate to produce a moderately priced collection for Public Clothing Company, a Perry Ellis licensee, and a higher-priced collection for Perry Ellis International, which owns the Perry Ellis name. (Mr. Ellis died in 1986.) Mr. Robinson carried on, he said, despite his frustrations over budgetary restrictions, which on occasion forced him to stint on fabrics and workmanship and, at one point, to produce the music for his runway show on his iPod.</p>
        <p>Yet some people who worked closely with Mr. Robinson said that talk about his artistry is a smoke screen obscuring the real issue: his clothes simply failed to sell. A former Perry Ellis executive, who still works in the industry and insisted on not being named, termed Mr. Robinson's stint at the company an outright disaster, charging that he had catered exclusively to an elite circle of buyers and editors. The executive added that the designer simply had no interest in the bottom line.</p>
        <p>''At some point, retailers felt that there was a disconnect between the mainstream stores and some of the products Patrick was designing,'' said George Feldenkreis, the chief executive of Perry Ellis International. Indeed, portions of the fall 2004 collection hang forlornly on the racks at Macy's and other high-volume department stores. Mr. Feldenkreis said sales fell far short of expectations, explaining that a brand like Perry Ellis must generate about $20 million in annual sales simply to cover expenses.</p>
        <p>That disappointing performance and Mr. Robinson's growing disenchantment with Public Clothing led to a rupture. ''Perry Ellis International and Public Clothing, who I worked for, wanted to go in different directions, so I stopped working for Public,'' he said. Mr. Feldenkreis said the moderate line had in fact sold so poorly that Public Clothing fired Mr. Robinson last summer.</p>
        <p>At that point, Perry Ellis International stepped in and offered the designer a job as a consultant, with carte blanche to purchase the fabrics and hire the staff needed to develop a designer collection called Perry Ellis Signature. The company paid for the runway designs but, for reasons it did not disclose, declined to produce the line, reversing itself only at the insistence of influential retailers, including Barneys, Neiman Marcus, and Saks Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feldenkreis professes to have been impressed with Mr. Robinson's flair, adding that he had intended to stand by him for the long haul. ''While we knew in the short run we would be losing money, we felt that retaining Patrick would enhance the value of the brand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Robinson was not given a long-term contract, an omission he interpreted as a sign of bad faith. ''I never knew if a collection would actually be produced,'' he said. There were failures, he conceded, on his part as well.</p>
        <p>''I never spent time getting to know the nuts and bolts of the business, the bottom line,'' he said. ''I was too focused on the product. It took up a lot of my time.'' People familiar with the designer note that he also took time to market himself, rarely missing a chance to pose for cameras with fashion's power brokers.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Robinson's champions ascribe his problems to his corporate employers' failure to recognize his star quality and to position his collection where it belonged, with similar labels aimed at young, fashion-conscious working women.</p>
        <p>''For a midprice line, it was the first really interesting launch in the American market since Marc by Marc Jacobs,'' Ms. Singer said. ''It appeals to an adventurous customer shopping at a price, but clearly that's not what that company wanted.''</p>
        <p>It is telling, some said, that the moderate line performed robustly at stores like Henri Bendel, where it was shown alongside other stylish, youthful labels. ''Patrick blew the dust off,'' said Ed Burstell, a retail consultant who, in his former post as the general manager of Bendel, had purchased the collection. The store placed multiple reorders, he said.</p>
        <p>Some merchants had high hopes for the new Signature collection, confident that they could showcase it with higher priced lines. Robert Burke, the fashion director of Bergdorf Goodman, was among the first to buy the designer collection, which was intended to sell for several hundred dollars to about $1,500, comparable to European labels like Marni. ''Patrick's clothes were wearable and original,'' Mr. Burke said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson's defection leaves Perry Ellis International, a $700 million public company -- it also owns Jantzen, John Henry and Munsingwear -- somewhat adrift. ''Perry Ellis does not have an exit strategy,'' Mr. Feldenkreis said. ''If Patrick is not there, I don't have a designer. For him to leave meant that we had to close that group.'' The day after Mr. Robinson left, the company suspended delivery of the Perry Ellis Signature line. A moderate price line from Public Clothing will sell under the Perry Ellis label.</p>
        <p>In his new job, which Mr. Robinson said would be announced this week, he expects to be provided with the requisite tools for developing a designer collection: the support of a business partner with a long-term vision and a generous marketing budget. The speculation is that he will be the designer for Paco Rabanne.</p>
        <p>''To learn in this business, you need to get bumped on the head a few times,'' Mr. Robinson said. ''I've been bumped.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
