<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harassment Questions Kill 2 Admirals' Promotions</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAVIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEXUAL HARASSMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TUTTLE, JERRY O (VICE ADM)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRUEHER, JOSEPH W (REAR ADM)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD133DF93BA25754C0A964958260" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harassment Questions Kill 2 Admirals' Promotions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the broadening aftermath of a sexual harassment scandal, the Navy is canceling the promotions of two of the service's most senior admirals who were involved in two other sexual harassment incidents.</p>
        <p>One officer is Vice Adm. Jerry O. Tuttle, a three-star admiral whomPresident Bush had nominated to become the chief of naval aviation, one of the top dozen posts in the Navy. The other is Rear Adm. Joseph W. Prueher. Mr. Bush had chosen him to be promoted two grades, from one star to three, and to assume command of the Third Fleet, based in San Diego.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the broadening aftermath of a sexual harassment scandal, the Navy is canceling the promotions of two of the service's most senior admirals who were involved in two other sexual harassment incidents.</p>
        <p>One officer is Vice Adm. Jerry O. Tuttle, a three-star admiral whomPresident Bush had nominated to become the chief of naval aviation, one of the top dozen posts in the Navy. The other is Rear Adm. Joseph W. Prueher. Mr. Bush had chosen him to be promoted two grades, from one star to three, and to assume command of the Third Fleet, based in San Diego.</p>
        <p>The nominations are subject to Senate approval. The Senate has already held up thousands of Navy and Marine Corps promotions until the Defense Department certifies that each officer was not implicated in the assault of 26 women at a convention of naval aviators last year, or in the subsequent cover-up.</p>
        <p>In the cases of Admiral Tuttle and Admiral Prueher, though, lawmakers have also been examining complaints about other incidents. In Admiral Tuttle's case, Navy officials said, the concern was about offensive jokes about women in his command's monthly newsletter, which he writes; the Navy chastised him for that last October, but there was no indication then that further action was being considered.</p>
        <p>The withdrawal of Admiral Prueher's nomination stems from actions he took in a case of sexual harassment at the Naval Academy in 1989, when he was commandant of midshipmen. The case involved a female midshipman who was handcuffed to a urinal by a group of male midshipmen. Her father says that when he complained to Admiral Prueher about the incident, the Admiral threatened to make public photographs of her smiling as the apparent assault took place.</p>
        <p>Adm. Frank B. Kelso 2d, the chief of naval operations, decided to make the highly unusual move of withdrawing the admirals' nominations when it became clear that the lengthy Senate confirmation process could leave two important Navy positions vacant for several weeks or months, Navy officials said.</p>
        <p>The decision makes it appear that the Navy is reconsidering sexual harassment reports that it had initially paid little attention to. But Navy officials asserted that they had acted mainly out of concern that the Senate would hold up the promotions, leaving two senior positions vacant for months.  Time Was Factor</p>
        <p>"Given the likelihood of a lengthy confirmation process and a pending internal reorganization that affects the nominations, the Navy decided that the nominations be pulled," said a Navy official, who added that Acting Navy Secretary Sean O'Keefe had approved the action.</p>
        <p>The Navy official said the service would formally request, through the Pentagon, that the White House withdraw the nominations or ask the Senate not to act on them. There are now 31 three-star Navy admirals on active duty.</p>
        <p>The Senate has approved 1,126 nominations but has delayed acting on those of 3,430 other officers, including 62 admirals and Marine Corps generals, until the Pentagon clears the officers of any involvement in the scandal at the convention of the Tailhook Association, an organization of active and retired naval aviators.</p>
        <p>Admiral Prueher and Admiral Tuttle are the highest-ranking naval officers to suffer the fallout of a scandal that had already resulted in the transferral of one admiral to a lesser job last December and forced resignation of Navy Secretary H. Lawrence Garrett 3d last month.</p>
        <p>In addition, four Navy officers in San Diego have been relieved of their commands and disciplined for their involvement in a bawdy skit about Representative Patricia Schroeder, Democrat of Colorado, performed at an officer's club.</p>
        <p>The Tailhook incident, and an ongoing investigation of the affair by the Defense Department Inspector General, has also heightened awareness to the problems of sexual harassment in the Army and Air Force.  Respected Officers</p>
        <p>The canceled promotions of Admiral Prueher and Admiral Tuttle hurt the careers of two of the Navy's most respected officers.</p>
        <p>Admiral Tuttle, who is 57 years old, landed in trouble last October for including jokes that offended some female officers in a monthly newsletter he writes for the Navy's Space and Electronic Warfare Command that he heads.</p>
        <p>The jokes were: "Beer is better than women because beer doesn't get jealous when you grab another" and "Beer is better than women because beer never has a headache."</p>
        <p>In the next issue of the newsletter, Admiral Tuttle, who is one of the Navy's top computer and communications experts, apologized for the jokes, saying, "My intent was certainly not to offend!"</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview on Thursday, Admiral Tuttle said he had not been notified of the Navy's action. He would not comment further. Father Was Told to 'Back Off'</p>
        <p>Admiral Prueher's problems began when Midshipman 3d Class Gwen Dreyer was handcuffed to a urinal in a men's bathroom at the Naval Academy on Dec. 8, 1989. The Academy's subsequent investigation penalized five male midshipmen, but only two received reprimands on their official records.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the incident, Midshipman Dreyer's father, Gregory, a 1967 Naval Academy graduate and a captain in the Naval Reserve, telephoned Admiral Prueher, who was a captain at the time and commandant of midshipmen, the second-in-command at the Naval Academy, to express his concern about the seriousness of the matter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dreyer said Captain Prueher "told us 'to back off, we'll take care of things.' " Mr. Dreyer wrote Mr. Garrett, the Secretary of the Navy, about the response to his complaint, and he confirmed the account in a telephone interview today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dreyer said that Captain Prueher "threatened" to make public photographs that the male midshipmen had taken of his daughter in the bathroom, smiling during the ordeal, if Mr. Dreyer continued to press the Academy's handling of the matter.</p>
        <p>The dispute died down when Midshipman Dreyer resigned from the academy at the end of the 1989-90 academic year. She will be a senior this fall majoring in mechanical engineering at California Polytechnic State University at San Luis Obispo.</p>
        <p>The case resurfaced three weeks ago when a staff member on the House Armed Services Committee noticed Admiral Prueher's name on the promotion list. Committee officials notified their Senate counterparts and Navy officials of their concerns.</p>
        <p>Admiral Prueher, 49, who is commander of a carrier battle group based in San Diego, was aboard the carrier Kitty Hawk conducting training exercises in the Pacific today and was unavailable for comment, said Comdr. Mark Van Dyke, a Navy spokesman.</p>
        <p>Navy officials said that Admiral Prueher and Admiral Tuttle would remain in their current positions for now. There has been no decision on who will now be nominated for the two positions.</p>
        <p>Colleagues of the two admirals expressed outrage and amazement at the Navy's action. "This is an un-American purge," said one Navy admiral.  "It's like something out of Stalin."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Crimes in Gulf Cited</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, July 17 (AP) -- Army soldiers are accused of committing at least 31 sex crimes against female soldiers in the Persian Gulf, a published report says.</p>
        <p>An article to be published in Monday's Army Times says one incident involved a married sergeant who was charged with rape, indecent assault and adultery after he allegedly raped several female soldiers at the Saudi port of Al Jubayl in February 1991.</p>
        <p>Some of the victimized women did not report the incidents for weeks or months, the report said.</p>
        <p>An Army spokesman, Maj. Rick Thomas, said he had no reason to challenge the accuracy of the report by the independent weekly newspaper.</p>
        <p>"In the Army, not only do we not condone sex crimes, but we condemn them," Major Thomas said.</p>
        <p>Army Times wrote its article after using the Freedom of Information Act to acquire records of investigations by the Army's Criminal Investigation Command.</p>
        <p>Few of the documents noted what, if any, steps were taken to prosecute or punish the people allegedly involved. The Army deleted the names of the soldiers involved.</p>
        <p>The reported incidents occurred from August 1990, when American troops were first sent to the Persian Gulf, through July 1991, five months after full-scale fighting ended.</p>
        <p>About eight of the crimes involved consensual acts that are prosecuted in the military, such as adultery or homosexual sex, said Greg Seigle, the reporter who wrote the story.</p>
        <p>At the height of the buildup, the Army had 305,000 troops in the gulf region, 26,000 of them women.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
