<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Democrats; With No Break, Clinton Initiates Campaign Tour</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CAMDEN (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">IFILL, GWEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD123CF93BA25754C0A964958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Democrats; With No Break, Clinton Initiates Campaign Tour</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GWEN IFILL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IFILL, GWEN</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Clinton and his running mate, Al Gore, rallied the Democratic faithful today, using the first full day of their campaign to romance supporters of Ross Perot and open a six-day bus tour that will carry them through nine states.</p>
        <p>"This is our chance to change America," Mr. Clinton said at a meeting of the Democratic National Committee before leaving New York this morning. "Let's take it."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Clinton and his running mate, Al Gore, rallied the Democratic faithful today, using the first full day of their campaign to romance supporters of Ross Perot and open a six-day bus tour that will carry them through nine states.</p>
        <p>"This is our chance to change America," Mr. Clinton said at a meeting of the Democratic National Committee before leaving New York this morning. "Let's take it."</p>
        <p>The new Democratic ticket left midtown Manhattan in a caravan of eight buses that took them from a confetti-strewn rally to the outskirts of Camden in about two hours.</p>
        <p>Governor Clinton of Arkansas, Senator Gore of Tennessee and their aides were ebullient today, telling their supporters that the Presidency was within reach if they could persuade Mr. Perot's supporters to join the Democrats. Playing Down Polls</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Clinton and his strategists played down the latest public opinion polls showing that they have surged to a remarkable lead over President Bush in the last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton had 56 percent to Bush's 33 percent in a USA Today-CNN poll by the Gallup Organization of 602 voters.ABC News polled 527 voters, who gave Mr. Clinton a 54-to-31 percent lead. He enjoyed an even bigger lead among "likely voters," who favored the Arkansas Governor, 58 percent to 29 percent, ABC said. Both polls had a margin of sampling error of plus or minus five percentage points.</p>
        <p>The Democrats proudly marched out two Perot-to-Clinton converts at their East 48th Street rally today. Matthew L. Liflander and Thomas Hoving, two Perot organizers in New York State, appeared to announce their decision to embrace the Clinton-Gore ticket.</p>
        <p>"All those people who thought Ross Perot had guts -- and he don't -- must go back to the obvious choice, who has guts," said Mr. Hoving, a former New York City Parks commissioner and former director of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. "He's proven it. Leadership is courage and persistence in times of adversity."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that Mr. Perot gave Democrats the "ultimate compliment" when he said during a surprise news conference on Thursday that he was abandoning his Presidential bid in part because the Democratic Party had appeared to be revitalizing itself.</p>
        <p>"It is for us now to show that we can be trusted to do what we say and to run this country," Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, Mr. Gore and their wives traveled in a custom-fitted bus for the first leg of the tour. Their first stop was an aerospace plant here, where employment has dropped from 5,000 workers to 1,600 in five years.</p>
        <p>The 1,000-mile itinerary includes stops in New Jersey, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Ohio, Kentucky, Indiana, Illinois and Missouri. Winning those states along the route is crucial to the Democrats' chances of defeating President Bush in November.</p>
        <p>"This will be a campaign of action, words of movement, not just talk," Mr. Clinton said before he left on his bus tour. "We are going to change this country with your help. That is what this whole convention has been about."</p>
        <p>The two Democrats continued their theme this afternoon at the Camden stop, where they met with Gov. Jim Florio of New Jersey and Representative Robert E. Andrews, both Democrats.</p>
        <p>Repeating the theme that Clinton strategists believe is their best weapon against President Bush, Mr. Clinton described the plant's program to retrain space technology workers as an example of the best kind of change.</p>
        <p>"Change is the key to your security," Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>"The other side is saying we've been in charge for 12 years and if you want change, vote for more of the same," Mr. Gore said. "That doesn't make sense. Their approach has failed."</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio made a pitch that Mr. Clinton is certain to hear more of as he travels the country. "It's been a lonely, lonely effort having every state take care of its problems by itself," the New Jersey Governor said. "We need some help from Washington."</p>
        <p>The Clinton campaign has learned well from the mistakes made by Michael S. Dukakis, the 1988 Democratic Presidential nominee, when he disappeared from the campaign trail after the convention. His 17-point lead in the polls subsequently disappeared as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore have set a busy schedule for themselves this week, and both received a road map and instant camera to take along as they left New York. Reading material on their luxury bus included Jules Witcover's book, "Crapshoot: Rolling the Dice on the Vice Presidency."</p>
        <p>Their final stop of the day was at Steelworkers Hall in Coatesville, Pa., where the caravan was to stay for the night. Plans called for the tour to visit the Pennsylvania cities of York, Carlisle, McKeesport and Pittsburgh on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton had a much better time in New York this time than he did when he campaigned there during the April primary and was greeted by hecklers at nearly every stop. Today, hundreds of people cheered as he left his midtown hotel, and hundreds more crowded the street outside for the send-off rally.</p>
        <p>"I want to begin by saying a heartfelt welcome for this wonderful city that has been somewhat rough to me but in the end always good to me," he said. "New York, I love you. Thank you."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
