<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Republicans; G.O.P. Asks Perot Backers To Give Its Ticket a Chance</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WYOMING</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROHTER, LARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUAYLE, DAN (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DF173EF93BA25754C0A964958260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Republicans; G.O.P. Asks Perot Backers To Give Its Ticket a Chance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROHTER, LARRY</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a campaign foray across three Southern states, Vice President Dan Quayle courted supporters of Ross Perot today and vowed to "peel back the veneer to find out what is underneath" Gov. Bill Clinton, whom the Democrats anointed this week as their Presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>Almost a continent away, President Bush took much the same tack toward supporters of the Texas billionaire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a campaign foray across three Southern states, Vice President Dan Quayle courted supporters of Ross Perot today and vowed to "peel back the veneer to find out what is underneath" Gov. Bill Clinton, whom the Democrats anointed this week as their Presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>Almost a continent away, President Bush took much the same tack toward supporters of the Texas billionaire.</p>
        <p>In Jackson, Wyo., President Bush ended an idyllic two days of trout fishing. Using barbecue and contrition as his lures, he went off in pursuit of the wily Perot supporter.</p>
        <p>In a lunchtime appearance before about 1,000 people at the airport in Jackson Hole, Mr. Bush pleaded for Mr. Perot's supporters to give the Republicans a chance to "complete the dream" of his first term.</p>
        <p>"Today I have a message for anyone who supported Ross Perot, and any American who identifies with that frustration that brought them together: I hear you, and you've come through loud and clear," Mr. Bush said. "I hear the voices, in so many accents, say that attention must be paid to our jobs, our schools, our families. Attention must be paid to our future. And I hear that call. And more than that, I share your frustration."</p>
        <p>Yet it was Mr. Quayle, at stops in Kentucky, Mississippi and Florida, who laid out what are likely to become the principal themes in the campaign. He portrayed Mr. Clinton and his running mate, Senator Al Gore, as traditional tax-and-spend Democrats who have adopted moderate language to mask their underlying liberalism.  Putting G.O.P. Label on Issues</p>
        <p>He said he had been surprised to hear Mr. Clinton speak of subjects ranging from family values to national security in his acceptance speech Thursday night."These are all very much Republican issues," Mr. Quayle said. The Vice President said that as he watched Democratic delegates applaud Mr. Clinton's emphasis on the family, he had been amused because "many in that same audience ridiculed me for bringing it up" during his Murphy Brown speech in California this spring.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle particularly criticized Mr. Clinton's pro-choice position on abortion. He described the Democratic nominee's pledge to appoint Supreme Court justices who will uphold a woman's right to an abortion as "a very extreme statement," and he ridiculed the Democrats' endorsement of family leave in their platform as "a typical big-Government paternalistic response" to an important social issue.</p>
        <p>The Vice President also sought to portray Mr. Clinton as unable to lead the economy back to prosperity. He recalled high inflation and interest rates under former President Jimmy Carter and said that Mr. Clinton planned to raise taxes, which "is not the way to create jobs."</p>
        <p>Speaking of the Bush Administration, he said, "We have the plan for economic growth. Please look at our program." He added that it was "important for the American people to know who Bill Clinton is, what damage he will do to the economy."</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle also said that he and Mr. Bush planned to "reach out to the volunteers of Ross Perot." Reversing earlier criticism in which he had described Mr. Perot as a "temperamental tycoon" with no respect for the Constitution, Mr. Quayle praised the Texas billionaire for having "energized a lot of people."</p>
        <p>At a news conference late this afternoon, Mr. Quayle urged Mr. Perot's supporters not to become disillusioned with the political process and to bring their energy to the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>"If you want change, you have to have a united Government," Mr. Quayle said. "Divided Government does not serve us well." Blaming the Democrats</p>
        <p>As he has done repeatedly in the past, Mr. Quayle blamed the Democratic majority in Congress for the impasse in Washington that Mr. Perot made the centerpiece of his now-abandoned crusade.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Quayle met with leaders of the Perot campaign in Kentucky to seek their support. He said that he had answered their questions about issues, and he predicted that with enough encouragement, they would eventually be coaxed into the Republican fold.</p>
        <p>"It is especially important to have the Ross Perot supporters come our way, and I think they will," he said. "But it will take time."</p>
        <p>In President Bush's appearance, his oratory bore a telling similarity to some early campaign speeches in New Hampshire last January, when he allowed that he had underestimated public dismay over the state of the economy and told one crowd, "Message: I care."</p>
        <p>The apologies helped little in New Hampshire, where Patrick Buchanan, a conservative commentator, gave Mr. Bush a brief scare.</p>
        <p>Today's blue-jeans and T-shirt crowd munched appreciatively on barbecue and baked beans, toe-tapped to Western music and applauded politely, but otherwise seemed little moved by the President's pleas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's appearance today overflowed with political symbolism and stunning patriotic scenery. It began with a dramatic drop from the sky in a Marine helicopter to an airport runway flanked by the towering Grand Teton Mountains, and it ended with Mr. Bush leaping off a Western-style wagon, loaded with hay bales, to pump hands and kiss children.</p>
        <p>But substance sometimes seemed lacking. He seemed unable to offer any detailed answer to some of the frustrations that he raised in his speech. Asking, "What do you say to an elderly woman" who is afraid to leave her home, or a child who must pass through metal detectors to go to school, the President answered his own question by responding: "You say, 'Enough is enough!' And, 'Let's put an end to the lawlessness.' "</p>
        <p>His campaign chairman, Robert M. Teeter, who is accompanying Mr. Bush on a two-day swing through Wyoming and Utah, said the President's message today began a strong White House push to lure Mr. Perot's backers to the Republican cause.</p>
        <p>He dismissed new opinion polls that show Mr. Clinton leading Mr. Bush by as many as 22 percentage points, noting that Mr. Bush had trailed his Democratic foe by 17 points at this time in 1988 and still won in a walk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
