<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Midst of Desire and Frustration, Questions of What Might Have Been</title>
    <meta content="26vany" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/26/theater/reviews/26vany.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chekhov, Anton (1860-1904)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edelstein, Gordon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blum, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Uncle Vanya (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Wharf Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blum, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Uncle Vanya (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DE1730F935A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Midst of Desire and Frustration, Questions of What Might Have Been</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Midst of Desire and Frustration, Questions of What Might Have Been</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews production of Chekhov play Uncle Vanya at Long Wharf Theater in New Haven, Conn; Gordon Edelstein directs and Mark Blum stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lone tree, denuded of greenery and casting a spindly shadow on the gray wall behind it, sets the stark, melancholy tone for Gordon Edelstein's new production of ''Uncle Vanya'' at the Long Wharf Theater.</p>
        <p>As the characters in this Chekhov play move across the wide expanses of the set's wooden flooring, making their way through days darkened by disappointment, they come to seem as frozen in place as that forlorn tree. They are people with minds full of ideas and hearts full of yearning, occasionally roused to declarations of love and even a gunshot or two, but they are never really going to shake the sense of stasis in their souls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lone tree, denuded of greenery and casting a spindly shadow on the gray wall behind it, sets the stark, melancholy tone for Gordon Edelstein’s new production of “Uncle Vanya” at the Long Wharf Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lone tree, denuded of greenery and casting a spindly shadow on the gray wall behind it, sets the stark, melancholy tone for Gordon Edelstein's new production of ''Uncle Vanya'' at the Long Wharf Theater.</p>
        <p>As the characters in this Chekhov play move across the wide expanses of the set's wooden flooring, making their way through days darkened by disappointment, they come to seem as frozen in place as that forlorn tree. They are people with minds full of ideas and hearts full of yearning, occasionally roused to declarations of love and even a gunshot or two, but they are never really going to shake the sense of stasis in their souls.</p>
        <p>Using his own economical adaptation of the play, based on a literal translation of the original, Mr. Edelstein situates his production somewhere between tradition and modest innovation. A few contemporary colloquial phrases make subdued but significant appearances in the text. (Dr. Astrov remarks half-mockingly that he's on a ''liquid diet.'') The set appears to expose the theater's industrial-looking infrastructure -- that tree is framed by what looks like the entry to an old loading dock -- but the wooden furnishings scattered around are period-appropriate. Jane Greenwood's handsome costumes, in mostly somber tones, likewise dress up 19th-century silhouettes with contemporary touches.</p>
        <p>The aim is to underscore the timelessness of a play whose characters all seem to be living somehow out of time, unable to engage with life in the present as they pine for a promising future that will be forever out of reach.</p>
        <p>The most reliable manner of getting through the days -- work -- has abruptly stopped on the estate where Vanya (Mark Blum) and his niece, Sonya (Jennifer Dundas), have been quietly and happily toiling away. The arrival of Sonya's father, Serebryakov (William Biff McGuire), and his new young wife, Yelena (Elisabeth Waterston), has upended routine, jostled everyone out of the grind that blinds them to their secret sadness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blum's Vanya, anxious and with a careworn face that crinkles in irritation whenever he thinks of his many grievances, reacts most violently to the unpleasant discovery of his own unhappiness. His outrage at the fatuousness of Serebryakov is fueled both by his own frustration and wounded pride and his tender infatuation with Yelena, whom he regards with the pleading eyes of a hungry puppy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blum's performance is proficient and often amusing, but Vanya's petulance overshadows the deeply felt grief that should give his character a dignity that touches the heart. It's funny but dry, and we see little of what makes him so dearly lovable to his niece.</p>
        <p>If the arrival of Yelena and her ailing husband has awakened Vanya to the futility of his life, Sonya briefly feels a kindling of hope as Serebryakov calls for Astrov (Marco Barricelli), whom she has long adored. But Ms. Dundas's girlish looks and diminutive stature stand in poignant contrast to the womanly elegance of Ms. Waterston's Yelena. Astrov, bewitched by Yelena, seems to look straight through poor little Sonya into Yelena's eyes.</p>
        <p>The scene between Yelena and Sonya, one of the sudden flashes of intimacy that brings the play's characters together for a moment of true connection, opens a window onto a little sunlight, but it is abruptly shut. When Sonya returns with the sad news that Serebryakov won't allow music to be played, she delivers the line -- ''He says no'' -- and darkness falls abruptly as the first act ends.</p>
        <p>But then shadows are never far away in Mr. Edelstein's production. Christopher Akerlind's intricate lighting rarely rises to anything brighter than a soft golden glow, and a harsher gray light from outside often seems to be warring with the warmer tones indoors.</p>
        <p>When the characters gather at center stage, they are surrounded by a wide gulf of darkness. Telyegin (a softly buffoonish Larry Block) quietly strums away at his guitar in the dimness behind them, at what seems a half-mile from the action, while Vanya's mother, Maria (Waltrudis Buck), sits quietly reading in the far distance, in the fine sliver of shade cast by that bare tree, presumably.</p>
        <p>The performances are virtually all solid and effective, but the full humanity of these delicately drawn characters never really shines forth. Mr. Blum's Vanya is not the only character lacking the banked inner fires to draw us into deep sympathy. Ms. Waterston's Yelena, lovely to look at in her gowns, possesses little of the natural radiance you hope for. Ms. Dundas capably communicates Sonya's warm efficiency and quiet longing, but her delivery of the famous final soliloquy has a monotonously mournful quality.</p>
        <p>In that sense it is in keeping with Mr. Edelstein's production as a whole. Although there are some inventive comic touches -- Telyegin shuffling back and forth to talk to Yelena as she whooshes languidly on a swing -- the production sustains an air of subdued anguish that signals from the start that there's little hope for any of these characters. It is intelligent and beautifully designed (Michael Yeargan did the sets), but it often feels airless.</p>
        <p>As Serebryakov, Mr. McGuire contributes one of the more fully rounded portraits, and is unexpectedly moving in the scene in which Serebryakov confesses his fear of mortality. In Mr. McGuire's dignified interpretation, this selfish and self-pitying old man comes across here as a rather more sympathetic figure than the more stridently self-pitying Vanya.</p>
        <p>But best of all is Mr. Barricelli as Astrov, one of the more natural and wholly realized portraits I've seen in a Chekhov production. Exhausted and subdued in the play's first scene, as he complains to the servant Marina (Zoaunne LeRoy) of the tedium of his life, Astrov is fired with enthusiasm and a reckless happiness under the influence of vodka. The embers of his hopes for his life may be dying, but drink brings back a vestige of the heat his idealism once gave him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barricelli makes us feel both the sturdy beauty of that idealism -- his talk of man's destruction of the world's resources makes him sound like a 19th-century Al Gore -- and the quiet tragedy of his inability to fulfill it. Astrov's anguish at the death of a patient, which interrupts his drunken effusions, is among the production's most affecting moments, as he buries his face in his hands. Underneath the cynicism and professions of indifference, Astrov's heart is still capable of feeling real anguish.</p>
        <p>And his rejection of Sonya is infused with a lovely compassion. In the last scene, as Astrov takes his leave, he gently puts his hand on her shoulder from behind. A simple, almost impersonal gesture, it is infused with more warmth than the passionate kiss he has just shared with Yelena.</p>
        <p>It's quintessentially Chekhovian too. The great highs and lows of life are storms that pass quickly and leave behind an empty feeling, but a gentle pat on the shoulder can be enough to see you through until tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Uncle Vanya</p>
        <p>By Anton Chekhov; adapted and directed by Gordon Edelstein; sets by Michael Yeargan; costumes by Jane Greenwood; lighting by Christopher Akerlind; sound by Daniel Baker; production stage manager, Bret Torbeck; assistant stage manager, Amy Patricia Stern; dramaturge, Beatrice Basso. Presented by the Long Wharf Theater, Mr. Edelstein, artistic director; Joan Channick, managing director. At the Long Wharf Theater's Mainstage, 222 Sargent Drive, New Haven; (203) 787-4282. Through June 3. Running time: 2 hours 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Marco Barricelli (Astrov), Larry Block (Telyegin), Mark Blum (Vanya), Waltrudis Buck (Maria), Jennifer Dundas (Sonya), William Biff McGuire (Serebryakov), Zoaunne LeRoy (Marina), Charles Tirrell (Worker) and Elisabeth Waterston (Yelena).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
