<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anthony Proves to Be Right Medicine for Knicks</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INDIANA PACERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, CLIFTON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANTHONY, GREG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8143EF933A05751C1A964958260" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anthony Proves to Be Right Medicine for Knicks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, CLIFTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks had one guard who was injured, one guard who was ill and several players who were in foul trouble. None of that kept the Knicks from winning.</p>
        <p>Halting a two-game losing streak and improving on their impressive home record (13-1), the Knicks (17-9) outlasted the Indiana Pacers, 97-91, last night before a capacity crowd at Madison Square Garden. With Doc Rivers (slightly seperated shoulder) sidelined and John Starks playing with the stomach flu, other players stepped up. The most notable was Greg Anthony, who started at point guard and scored a career-high 23 points and added 8 assists in 38 steady minutes. After shooting 1 for 11 in his last two games, Anthony shook his slump and answered the heavy criticism he had received recently with a strong performance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Knicks had one guard who was injured, one guard who was ill and several players who were in foul trouble. None of that kept the Knicks from winning.</p>
        <p>Halting a two-game losing streak and improving on their impressive home record (13-1), the Knicks (17-9) outlasted the Indiana Pacers, 97-91, last night before a capacity crowd at Madison Square Garden. With Doc Rivers (slightly seperated shoulder) sidelined and John Starks playing with the stomach flu, other players stepped up. The most notable was Greg Anthony, who started at point guard and scored a career-high 23 points and added 8 assists in 38 steady minutes. After shooting 1 for 11 in his last two games, Anthony shook his slump and answered the heavy criticism he had received recently with a strong performance.</p>
        <p>"It was a reality check for us," Anthony said of the Knicks' two-game losing streak. "Everyone was saying that we don't have this, or I'm not that, because we lost two games. I've to see any team not lose two games in a row. I didn't like to see it happen, but sometimes it's good because it gets you back to working hard."</p>
        <p>Coach Pat Riley said he never lost faith in Anthony despite his recent struggles. It was Anthony's second career start.</p>
        <p>"I thought he was really criticized unfairly for two games," Riley said of Anthony. "If there's somebody in this league who had 82-straight great games in a row, I'd like to know who it is. There isn't anybody. He's a young player, and point guards in this league are hard to come by. I thought he played a very solid game, very solid."</p>
        <p>While Anthony and Patrick Ewing (29 points) carried the offense, the Knicks leaned on their defense. They tied a season high with 14 steals, including a career-high 5 by Ewing, and they held an opponent to under 100 points for the 19th time this season. Reggie Miller (23 points) and Detlef Schrempf (19 points) never exploded, and while former St. John's star Malik Sealy (16 points) had an effective homecoming, it was not enough to keep the Pacers (13-14) from losing their foruth consecutive game.</p>
        <p>"I thought we played extremely well defensively," said Riley. "At times we overhustled, which is why some of our big guys got in foul trouble. But the effort was there."</p>
        <p>It was not a fluid game, as both teams shot poorly and foul trouble kept the Knicks from establishing an offensive rhythym. Charles Oakley (13 rebounds), Charles Smith (13 points) and Anthony Mason all fouled out.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Riley knew he would have to watch Starks's minutes carefully. But Starks played the final 13 minutes and said his stomach felt better as the game progressed.</p>
        <p>"He's carrying the bug, he's been sick for about a week," Riley said of Starks. "He has lost about six or seven pounds; he can't keep anything down. Today in practice, about 30 minutes in, he looked like he was turning green. He's been going through that for about four or five days. But he gave us a nice lift."</p>
        <p>Leading by 79-70 after three quarters, the Knicks held off Indiana's final challenge. After the Pacers closed to 73-70 with 8 minutes 13 seconds to play, New York went on a 6-0 run to go ahead by 9 again. The Pacers never got closer than 6 points the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>The Knicks led at intermission, 43-37, after a first half dominated by defense. No one was more active defensively than Ewing, whose 5 steals all came in the first half. Ewing displayed his quickness and anticipation, getting his hands on numerous entry passes into the low post. With Ewing and Charles Smith choking off the Pacers inside, most of Indiana's first-half offense came from the perimeter. Knicks Go On 11-0 Run</p>
        <p>But the Knicks needed that kind of defensive effort because their first-half offense was sluggish. Rolando Blackman (18 points) started slowly, and Starks did not play with his usual zest, still bothered by the stomach flu that forced him to miss Monday's practice. New York shot just 41.5 percent in the first half, not good enough to take control of the game. New York threatened to take charge with an 11-0 run, holding Indiana scoreless for 5 minutes and 8 seconds to take a 26-16 lead. But the Pacers immediately answered with an 8-0 run to make the game close again. After two disappointing losses last weekend, the Knicks could have used an convincing win. But a win in any form was better than a loss. The Knicks play the Pacers again on Wednesday in Indiana.</p>
        <p>Said Ewing, "Hopefully this was a game that will get his back on our winning ways."</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>DOC RIVERS hopes to return to action on Saturday. Although he planned to make the trip on Wednesday to Indiana, he did not expect to play. "I might be limited on Saturday, but I expect I'll be able to play by then," Rivers said. "I don't think I'm going to hurt it anymore by coming back early. It's just a pain thing now. It's right by the nerves in your neck and it's painful."  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
