<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: ATTRACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="05SPAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1022289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED7113BF936A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="2960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: ATTRACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>ABIGAIL ADAMS SMITH MUSEUM, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan. The structure, built in 1799 as the carriage house for the estate of Abigail Adams and Col. William Smith, was also the Mount Vernon Hotel from 1826 to 1833. ''Sitting in Style,'' an exhibition of 19th-century painted fancy chairs, includes rarely seen pieces of silver from the museum's collection that relate in style to the furniture. Through July 31. Hours: Tuesdays, 11 A.M. to 9 P.M. Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; closed Mondays. Museum admission: $3; students and the elderly, $2; 12 and under, free. Tuesday's admission after 4 P.M.: $5; students and the elderly, $3; 12 and under, free. Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>ABIGAIL ADAMS SMITH MUSEUM, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan. The structure, built in 1799 as the carriage house for the estate of Abigail Adams and Col. William Smith, was also the Mount Vernon Hotel from 1826 to 1833. ''Sitting in Style,'' an exhibition of 19th-century painted fancy chairs, includes rarely seen pieces of silver from the museum's collection that relate in style to the furniture. Through July 31. Hours: Tuesdays, 11 A.M. to 9 P.M. Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; closed Mondays. Museum admission: $3; students and the elderly, $2; 12 and under, free. Tuesday's admission after 4 P.M.: $5; students and the elderly, $3; 12 and under, free. Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
        <p>ALICE AUSTEN HOUSE, 2 Hylan Boulevard, Rosebank, Staten Island. This 17th-century farmhouse, converted in the 19th century to a Victorian cottage, was the home of the photographer Alice Austen. On view is her parlor, filled with period furniture. On Sunday, from 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., there will be a re-enactment of the Draft Riots of 1863, in which common citizens revolted against conscription into the Civil War, with infantrymen dressed in authentically reproduced uniforms, military drills and demonstrations of skills needed in wartime. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 P.M. Admission: $2. Information: (718) 816-4506.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West at 79th Street. Recently opened, the new 11,000-square-foot Hall of Biodiversity, focusing on the variety and interdependence of Earth's living things. Tomorrow, from noon until 7 P.M., the museum presents ''Pagdiriwang,'' activities and celebrations in honor of 100 years of Philippine independence. Free with admission. ''Spirits in Steel: The Art of the Kalabari Masquerade,'' an exhibition featuring 13 steel sculptures by Sokari Douglas Camp, drawing on themes from her homeland in Nigeria, and 25 Nigerian masks from the museum's collection. On view through Oct. 12. ''The Nature of Diamonds,'' an exhibition exploring various aspects of the mineral, from its geologic origins to its uses in technology and research. Through Aug. 30. Admission is by timed ticket only. ''Africa: Explorations and Expeditions,'' featuring firsthand accounts of European and American exploration, as depicted in selections from the museum's rare-book collection. Through Sept. 30. ''Kings, Chiefs and Women of Power,'' featuring Phyllis Galembo's photographs of Nigerian leaders. Through June 28. The Imax films are ''Cosmic Voyage'' and ''Amazon.'' In the Imax Theater on Fridays and Saturdays at 9 P.M., ''Led Zeppelin in 3-D'' and at 10 P.M., ''Pink Floyd's 'Dark Side of the Moon' '' in 3-D. Tickets: $9. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 5:45 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 8:45 P.M. Suggested admission: $8; students and the elderly, $6; children 12 and under, $4.50. A combination ticket including museum admission and one film: $12; students and the elderly, $8.50; children 12 and under, $6.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100; to buy tickets by phone: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Washington Heights. The society has the most extensive coin collection in North America; its library is open to the public. On permanent display is ''American Numismatic Design, 1892-1922,'' which includes all coins issued during this period. Also on view is ''The World of Coins,'' a history since 600 B.C. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. Information: (212) 234-3130.</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST, 18 First Place (West Street and Battery Place), Battery Park City. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videotapes and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. Exhibitions include ''Life a Century Ago,'' featuring memorabilia from Jewish rituals and celebrations in Europe in the early 1900's; ''War Against the Jews,'' detailing the years 1933 to 1945, and ''Jewish Renewal,'' focusing on life after the Holocaust. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursdays, 9 A.M. to 8 P.M.; Fridays and eve of Jewish holidays, 9 A.M. to 2 P.M.; closed Saturdays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; 5 and under, free. Some same-day tickets are available at the museum; because of heavy attendance, tickets should be purchased in advance through Ticketmaster: (212) 307-4007. Information: (212) 968-1800.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN, Alexander Hamilton United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, lower Manhattan. Through Aug. 2, an exhibition on Indian humor, including paintings, photographs, sculptures and mixed-media works by 38 artists, countering the stereotype of Indians as always stoic and serious. On exhibit, ''All Roads Are Good: Native Voices on Life and Culture,'' an exhibition with more than 300 objects of significance from the museum's collection, chosen by 23 Indians. Films and videos by and about Indians are shown daily from 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., with additional screenings on Thursday at 5:30 P.M. Hours: daily, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursdays, until 8 P.M. Free. Information: (212) 514-3888.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY FIRE MUSEUM, 278 Spring Street, SoHo. In a renovated 1904 firehouse is a collection of fire-related art and artifacts from the 18th century to the present, including a firetruck, hose wagons, hats, toys, paintings and hand-drawn pumpers. Also, an exhibition, ''Fire Marks: Emblems of Insurance,'' features a selection of 18th- and 19th-century British and American fire marks from the museum's collection. Insurance agencies would give bonuses to firefighters when they saved the premises of a policyholder. The decorative emblems were used to distinguish policyholders from the uninsured. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Suggested admission: $4 for adults; $2 for students and the elderly; $1 for children under 12. Information: (212) 691-1303.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK TRANSIT MUSEUM, Boerum Place and Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn. ''Steel, Stone and Backbone,'' a display tracing the construction of the subway system from 1900 to 1925, with photographs, construction tools, films and other objects; ''Ceramic Ornamentation,'' a look at the mosaics, tiles and terra cotta used to adorn subway stations from 1904 to the present, and ''Here to There: Signs for Moving Around Underground,'' a display of more than 100 subway signs, continuing. Also on view are 19 restored subway cars dating from 1903 to 1960. Tomorrow at 11 A.M., a tour of ''The Brooklyn Els,'' the elevated train tracks over East New York that date back to 1885. Reservations are required. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.; closed Mondays and holidays. Admission: $3; the elderly and ages 6 to 17, $1.50; 5 and under, free. On Wednesday from 12 to 4 P.M., admission is free for the elderly. Information: (718) 243-8601.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND INSTITUTE OF ARTS AND SCIENCES, 75 Stuyvesant Place, St. George. Cultural museum and library with artistic, scientific and environmental collections. ''Moles, Voles and Mastodons: Mammals of Staten Island'' traces the history of mammals through mounted specimens, skulls, photos, fossils and murals. Through July 2. ''In the Eyes of the Beholder: American Female Portraiture, 1830-1914.'' Through Aug. 30. The Family Gallery Hands-On Exhibit features specimens, art, artifacts and activities. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: $2.50; students and the elderly, $1.50; children under 12, $1.25. Information: (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>THEODORE ROOSEVELT BIRTHPLACE, 28 East 20th Street, Manhattan. This reconstructed brownstone is the site of the birth of the only native of New York City to become President. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $2. Information: (212) 260-1616.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>AVON RUNNING -- NEW YORK MINI MARATHON (10K) AND FITNESS WALK (5K), Central Park. Tomorrow at 8:50 A.M. (fitness walk) and 9:30 A.M. (10K). Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Registration fee, $18; $10 for members of the New York Road Runners Club. Information: (212) 860-4455.</p>
        <p>''SUPER ROLL II FOR MS,'' a fund-raising event for the National Multiple Sclerosis Society, beginning at the Roller Rinks at Chelsea Piers, Hudson River and 23d Street. Sunday at 8:30 A.M. Three in-line skating courses (8-mile, 13-mile and 26.2-mile) on the West Side from the Chelsea Piers to the George Washington Bridge that can be crossed by experienced skaters. Each skater should have at least $50 in pledges for the 8-mile course, $75 for the 13-mile course and $100 for the 26.2 course. Registration fee: $20 today and tomorrow; $30 on Sunday. Information: (212) 463-9791.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>FIFTH CHANGE YOUR MIND DAY, Central Park, Great Hill, entrance at Central Park West and 106th Street. A daylong festival of meditation, music and exercise. Tomorrow from 12:30 to 5:30 P.M. Sponsored by Tricycle: The Buddhist. Free. Information: (800) 950-7008.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINE DAY PARADE, Madison Avenue, from 39th to 27th Streets. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>WALL STREET COMMUNITY DAY FAIR, from South to Water Streets. Today, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>CO-OP CITY SECTION 5 FAIR, Greenway, Co-op City, the Bronx. Sunday, noon to 6 P.M. Rain date, June 14. Sponsored by the Riverbay Fund. Information: (212) 671-7777.</p>
        <p>ST. JOSEPH'S SCHOOL FESTIVAL, Washington Place, from Grove Street to Macdougal. Tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 7 P.M. Sponsored by St. Joseph's School.</p>
        <p>13TH JEWISH HERITAGE STREET, Johnson Avenue and 235th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Sponsored by the Riverdale Jewish Community Council. Information: (718) 548-8200, extension 216.</p>
        <p>FIFTH BROADWAY SUMMER FESTIVAL, Broadway, from 66th to 71st Streets. Sunday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Sponsored by Project Open at Lincoln Towers.</p>
        <p>QUEENS FESTIVAL '98, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Flushing, Queens. Tomorrow and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>SEVENTH REGIMENT ARMORY, Manhattan. An architectural history tour of the armory, which was built as a private club for such families as the Astors and the Vanderbilts. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. in the lobby of the armory, 643 Park Avenue, at 66th Street. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee, $15; members of the Municipal Arts Society, $12. Reservations: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>SOHO. A tour that explores SoHo's collection of cast-iron buildings built during the second half of the 19th century. Led by Matthew Postal. Meets today at 12:30 P.M. at the Canal Street Post Office, Canal and Church Streets.  Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee: $10; students, the elderly and members, $8. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>''LOVE, NEW YORK STYLE,' WALKING TOUR,'' Greenwich Village. Love stories of the rich and famous will be covered in a a walk that will pass the homes of Eleanor Roosevelt, John Barrymore and John Reed. Tomorrow and Sunday at noon and 2:30 P.M. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Gothamwalk. Information: (212) 629-1886.</p>
        <p>''THE FIFTH AVENUE YOU NEVER KNEW,'' Manhattan. A look at the humble beginnings of one of the city's most notable avenues, with stops at the mansions of Payne Whitney and Henry Clay Frick. Tomorrow and Sunday at 12:30 P.M Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Fee, $12. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''LOWER EAST SIDE II,'' lower Manhattan. A tour of sites notable in radical politics from the late 1800's to early 1900's with stops at places frequented by Emma Goldman, the activist and writer, and Meyer London, a Socialist Party congressman, as well as meeting places for the Workmen's Circle and the location of the Bank Riots of 1910. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. in front of the Educational Alliance, 197 East Broadway. Fee, $6. Sponsored by Radical Walking Tours. Information: (718) 492-0069.</p>
        <p>''MILLIONAIRES' ROW,'' Manhattan. A tour of Fifth Avenue in midtown, past the Plaza Hotel and the former residences of the Rockefellers, Vanderbilts and Hearsts. Sunday at 2:30 P.M. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Fee, $5. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''THE ROOSEVELTS AND THE KENNEDYS,'' Upper East Side. An historical walk past sites associated with the two political families. Tomorrow and Sunday at 3 P.M. Fee, $12. Sponsored by N.Y.C. Discovery Tours. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''HIDDEN TREASURES OF CHINATOWN.'' A tour of more than just restaurants. Meets tomorrow at 10:30 A.M. at the Bruce Lee Shrine, 66 Bowery, at Canal Street. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Fee, $10. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>''GOTHAM CITY GHOST TOUR,'' Greenwich Village. A walking tour of infamous and macabre sites, including the cemetery at St. Mark's Church in the Village, the ''hanging elm,'' and the burial ground at Washington Square Park. Tomorrow at 6 P.M. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''SCENIC SOHO.'' A tour that includes stops at the site of the former Singer Sewing Machine Building (Broadway and Prince Street); the Leo Castelli Gallery on West Broadway and a ''haunted'' restaurant. Tomorrow at 12:15 P.M. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''RADICAL UNION SQUARE.'' A look at the political events that helped shape the history of the park, with a stop at the green market there, followed by a high tea. Meets tomorrow at 1:30 P.M at the Washington Square Hotel, 103 Waverly Place. Sponsored by Arthur Marks and C3 Restaurant. Fee, $20. Information: (212) 254-1200.</p>
        <p>''HAUNTED GREENWICH VILLAGE.'' A tour that includes stops at the Washington Mews, the Jefferson Market Courthouse Library and the former homes of Washington Irving and Aaron Burr. Sunday at 4:45 P.M. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Meeting places and reservations:  (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''WALKING THE HUDSON I: FROM THE BATTERY TO THE PENN YARDS.'' A walk along the lower portion of the river, with a discussion of the political forces that have affected its existence. Meets on Sunday at 1 P.M. in front of the Staten Island Ferry Terminal. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee, $15; members of the Municipal Art Society, $12. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>SEPHARDIC AND ROMANIOTE TOUR OF THE LOWER EAST SIDE. A walking tour of some of the sites of importance to Sephardic and Romaniote Jews, including the Kehila Kedosha Janina Synagogue and the site of an informal immigrant aid society. Meets on Sunday at 1:30 P.M. at the Lower East Side Tenement Museum, sponsor of the walk. Fee, $10;  students and the elderly, $6. Information: (212) 431-0233.</p>
        <p>''TRIBECA -- THE CREATIVE EXPLOSION.'' A look at the area that was transformed from an estate into an industrial center and then a chic residential and artistic enclave. Meets on Sunday at 1 P.M. at the intersection of Duane and Hudson Streets. Fee: $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>UPPER EAST SIDE WALKING TOUR I. A tour that combines the history and architecture of the area and includes sights like the Sara E. Roosevelt Memorial House, the Colony Club, the Elizabeth Street Gardens and the Thomas R. Howell Mansion. Meets on Sunday at 2 P.M. at the southwest corner of East 58th Street and Park Avenue. Sponsored by New York City Cultural Walking Tours. Fee, $10. Information: (212) 979-2388.</p>
        <p>COBBLE HILL AND CARROLL GARDENS, Brooklyn. A walking tour of the brownstone communities. Meets on Sunday at 10:30 A.M. at the Clark Street subway station. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Fee, $3 for nonmembers of the Outdoors Club. Information: (718) 855-1466.</p>
        <p>''JEWISH LOWER EAST SIDE TOUR,'' a tour of more than 150 years of Jewish settlement, including stops at The Forward building and the founding site of B'nai B'rith. Meets on Sunday at 1 P.M. at the southeast corner of Essex and Delancey Streets. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Fee, $10;  students and the elderly, $8. Information: (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>''HELL'S KITCHEN HIKE,'' a tour of the midtown West Side area, now known as Clinton, with stops at the Worldwide Plaza, St. Malachy's Church, the Actors Studio and a haunted town house. Tomorrow at 2:30 P.M. Fee: $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Meeting place and reservations: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''GREENWICH VILLAGE: NEW YORK'S LEFT BANK,'' a tour of the streets that have been home to writers and artists like Eugene O'Neill, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Edgar Allan Poe and Edward Hopper. Meets tomorrow and Sunday at noon at the Washington Arch. Sponsored by Mainly Manhattan Tours. Fee, $10. Information: (212) 755-6199.</p>
        <p>''BROOKLYN BRIDGE TALK AND WALK,'' a discussion about the building of the Brooklyn Bridge, followed by a walk across and back. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. inside 110 Church Farms, 110 Church Street, at Murray Street, lower Manhattan. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>''EAST VILLAGE TALES AND TAVERNS,'' a tour of four of the area's historic taverns. Meets tomorrow at 6 P.M. at the Astor Place subway kiosk. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Fee, $10 (does not include cost of refreshments.) Information: (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>''JEWISH EAST VILLAGE'' AND ''JEWISH LOWER EAST SIDE,'' lower Manhattan. Two tours of areas central to Jewish civilization in America. The first begins on Sunday at 10:30 A.M. inside the Second Avenue Deli at 10th Street. The second, which includes a kosher wine sampling, begins on Sunday at 2 P.M. inside Schapiro's Wine Cellars, 126 Rivington Street. The fee for each is $10. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
