<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EATING OUT</title>
    <meta content="05EATI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1022127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Balthazar (Manhattan Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barney Greengrass (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carmichael's Diner (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carnegie Deli (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cucina (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fifty-Seven Fifty-Seven (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fitzers (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Restaurant (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gamin, Le (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kitchenette (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NoHo Star (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDD103BF936A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="1581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EATING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Summaries of reviews of 12 Manhattan restaurants notable for breakfast fare; map</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Breakfast</p>
        <p>Breakfast is too often the forgotten meal, skipped in the morning rush or eaten on the run, in the subway or at a desk. But if you can take the time, pause and savor breakfast at these 12 restaurants. (Here are some summaries, written by Eric Asimov, taken from Ruth Reichl's and Mr. Asimov's dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Breakfast</p>
        <p>Breakfast is too often the forgotten meal, skipped in the morning rush or eaten on the run, in the subway or at a desk. But if you can take the time, pause and savor breakfast at these 12 restaurants. (Here are some summaries, written by Eric Asimov, taken from Ruth Reichl's and Mr. Asimov's dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times.)</p>
        <p>1. Balthazar  **  [RATING: Two Stars]  (212) 965-1414  80 Spring Street, at Crosby Street  SoHo  $$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Breakfast? At Balthazar? In fact, this is a full-service trendy restaurant, opening its doors early in the morning with a limited but delectable menu that includes delicious breads and pastries from Balthazar Bakery next door, coddled eggs and slender, wonderfully delicate waffles, served wrapped in a brown napkin. The morning is an odd time to view Balthazar. Only the bar and a dozen or so tables are in use. Otherwise, chairs are stacked and remnants of last night's smoky haze are still detectable. It's like a restaurant with a mild hangover. Cafe au lait helps.</p>
        <p>2. Barney Greengrass</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 724-4707</p>
        <p>541 Amsterdam Avenue, near 86th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ Mastercard and Visa (cash only on weekends)</p>
        <p>This New York institution, which calls itself the Sturgeon King, opened in 1908 and may not have been redecorated since. The dilapidated dining room, next to a thriving bagel-and-smoked-fish shop, is a study in brown, with Formica tables, peeling wallpaper, dingy linoleum-tile floor and bright fluorescent lights. But you don't go for style, you go for classic Jewish breakfasts, like platters of bagels and cream cheese with lox, sturgeon and other staples. A Barney specialty, Nova Scotia salmon scrambled with eggs and onions is slightly greasy and utterly delicious, with chunks of smoked fish and scads of sauteed onions. A portion looks small until you realize you've been eating for 10 minutes without making much of a dent in it.</p>
        <p>3. Carmichael's Diner</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(718) 723-6908</p>
        <p>117-08 Guy Brewer Boulevard, near Baisley Boulevard</p>
        <p>Jamaica, Queens</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>Carmichael's Diner is a classic, old-style rectangular diner with a counter that holds a fountain and glossy cakes under plastic domes. Booths are covered in orange vinyl, and each has its own jukebox. But ceiling fans keep things cool, the Formica tables and terrazzo floors are sparkling, and service is friendly and gracious.</p>
        <p>This is one of the few places in New York where you can get slices of authentic country ham, tough, leathery and salty but wonderful with grits and red-eye gravy. Salmon croquettes, a Southern breakfast staple, are flat, meaty and delicious. Home fries are savory and biscuits are buttery. Go with an appetite.</p>
        <p>4. Carnegie Deli  +++  (212) 757-2245  854 Seventh Avenue, near 55th Street  Manhattan  $ Cash only</p>
        <p>You think the Carnegie serves only pastrami? Well, a fat pastrami sandwich wouldn't make a bad breakfast, but if you'd like something a little more moderate, say, with only about half a million calories, try a trio of cheese blintzes (with sour cream, please, not applesauce). By arriving early for breakfast, you beat the lines, which start around 11 and last all day. It's less noisy in the morning, too.</p>
        <p>5. Cucina &amp; Company  +++  (212) 682-2700  200 Park Avenue, at 45th Street  Manhattan  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>This bustling, efficient little cafe behind a bakery in the Met Life Building is just an escalator ride up from Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>For the convenience of commuters, there's a big clock on the wall, visible from each of the small marble tables. Nothing here is rushed, but everything is done quickly.</p>
        <p>A waitress is ready with a menu and coffee before you are seated in one of the comfortable wood-and-wicker chairs. Within five minutes, a complete breakfast arrives: perfectly poached eggs on nutty seven-grain toast, slightly peppery thin Italian sausage links and a wonderful cake of rosti potatoes, fried crisp on the outside and soft within. Orange juice is fresh squeezed, and coffee is rich. French toast and pancakes are also fine.</p>
        <p>6. Fifty-Seven Fifty-Seven  ***  [RATING: Three Stars]  (212) 758-5757  Four Seasons Hotel  57 East 57th Street  Manhattan  $$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>With its high ceilings and stark surfaces, Fifty-Seven Fifty-Seven is one of the city's stateliest dining rooms, a memorable public space that is impossible to ignore. It is also one of the most pleasant places for a fancy hotel breakfast, partly because the service is so friendly and relaxed, and partly because the food is so good, starting with the glazed Krispy Kreme doughnuts included in the bread basket. Highlights include the pancakes -- buttermilk, lemon-ricotta or banana-cream -- thick cinnamon-walnut french toast and any of the delectable pastries.</p>
        <p>7. Fitzers  +++  (212) 355-0100  Fitzpatrick Manhattan Hotel  687 Lexington Avenue, near 56th Street  Manhattan  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>The Irish breakfast at Fitzers is a different kind of hotel experience, devoted to excess rather than to elegance. First comes orange juice and a basket of bread, including thick slices of a yeasty, dense multigrain loaf with golden marmalade, as well as white toast, croissants and pastry. Then a big bowl of Irish oatmeal. Just as you're ready to get up, the main course comes, a small mound of scrambled eggs surrounded by not only thin breakfast sausages but also a rasher of Irish bacon, a slice of black pudding, as blood sausage is also known, and a slice of white pudding, a cereal-like sausage. A grilled tomato is superfluous, as is any thought of lunch.</p>
        <p>8. 14 Wall Street Restaurant  *  [RATING: One Star]  (212) 233-2780  31st Floor  14 Wall Street, near Broadway  Financial district  $$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Thirty-one floors above the morning bustle of a Wall Street workday, in what was once J. P. Morgan's private apartment, lies this pleasant refuge where breakfast is a bargain at $10. On the minus side, the orange juice isn't fresh and the coffee is only fair, but the plus side includes very light whole-wheat pancakes surrounded by fresh fruit and served with a pitcher of warm maple syrup. Omelets, which are accompanied by fine sauteed potatoes and toast, are competently made and come with any number of fillings. They are good even when made only with egg whites. Dieters can choose yogurt and fruit, and those with no concern for calories can feast on eggs, french toast and assorted muffins.</p>
        <p>9. Le Gamin  +++  (212) 254-4678  50 Macdougal Street, near Prince Street  SoHo  $ Cash only</p>
        <p>Le Gamin is a little sliver of France in SoHo where the Parisian atmosphere is as thick as the Gitane smoke rising to the pressed-tin ceiling. There's a map of the Paris Metro on one wall, an ad for Vittel water and a clock set to Paris time. Crepes are the thing to eat here. The ham-and-cheese crepe is wonderful, a huge, thin layer of dough grilled and folded into a broad rectangle, leaving layer upon airy layer of ham and melted cheese. With a frothy bowl of cafe au lait and topped off with a lemon crepe, a conical fold of dough drizzled with lemon juice and powdered sugar, it makes a wonderful breakfast. Le Gamin has another, bigger branch in Chelsea at 183 Ninth Avenue, at 21st Street.</p>
        <p>10. Home  +  (212) 243-9579  20 Cornelia Street  Greenwich Village  $ American Express</p>
        <p>With blues playing softly in the background, Home, which serves stylish interpretations of Middle American food, is a relaxed oasis in the morning, with a terrific breakfast. The small menu includes excellent french toast served with maple-apple syrup, an irresistibly sweet granola topped with sliced strawberries and bananas, and sagey sausage fresh from Faicco Pork Store around the corner. Coffee is rich and the juice is fresh-squeezed.</p>
        <p>11. Kitchenette  +++  (212) 267-6740  80 West Broadway, at Warren Street  TriBeCa  $ American Express</p>
        <p>This formerly tiny restaurant is now in bigger quarters on the west side of West Broadway, but the breakfasts are as good as ever with such standouts as light, thin orange-and-poppy-seed waffles, wonderful blueberry pancakes, and terrific biscuits and scones. Everything is fresh, hearty and flavorful, made with care rather than mass-produced.</p>
        <p>12. NoHo Star  +  (212) 925-0070  330 Lafayette Street, at Bleecker Street  East Village  $ All major cards</p>
        <p>For a quiet, reflective breakfast, this big, airy room with its colorful columns and beautiful pressed-tin ceiling is hard to beat. The food, from a freshly made hazelnut waffle to brioche french toast with thick-cut bacon to a simple fruit-and-yogurt shake, is satisfying and delicious, while service is efficient and unobtrusive. Only a subway rattling underneath reminds you that the rest of the world is in a hurry.</p>
        <p>Summaries of reviews use the star system; others are culled from articles (indicated by +), the $25 and Under column (++) and Diner's Journal (+++).</p>
        <p>The Star System  The New York Times's star system rates restaurants on the following scale.</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  The price symbols are based on the cost of a three-course dinner with tax and a 15 percent tip (drinks not included).</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews. Hundreds of Times restaurant reviews are available from The New York Times on America Online. Information and software: (800) 548-5201.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
