<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Football's Wheel Of Fortune</title>
    <meta content="13RHOD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="908574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parcells, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EED7163FF930A25751C0A961958260" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Football's Wheel Of Fortune</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column notes that New York Jets recently held 'carnival-like' news conference to introduce Bill Parcells as head coach and vice president of football operations, and New York Giants recently held 'family day-like get-together' to introduce staff assembled by their new coach Jim Fassel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRAINING camp doesn't begin for another five months, but the Jets and Giants are already engaged in full contact, of sorts.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the Jets held a carnival-like news conference on Long Island to introduce Bill Parcells as head coach, vice president of football operations and savior. Barely 24 hours later, Parcells began swinging the axe, cutting the veteran place-kicker Nick Lowery and safety Lonnie Young.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRAINING camp doesn't begin for another five months, but the Jets and Giants are already engaged in full contact, of sorts.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the Jets held a carnival-like news conference on Long Island to introduce Bill Parcells as head coach, vice president of football operations and savior. Barely 24 hours later, Parcells began swinging the axe, cutting the veteran place-kicker Nick Lowery and safety Lonnie Young.</p>
        <p>That announcement came only hours after the Giants held a family day-like get-together to introduce the staff assembled by their first-year head coach, Jim Fassel. The environment was as laid back as the Jets' was frenetic. Instead of the cluster of TV trucks that had gathered outside the Jets' headquarters, there was just a handful of camera crews at Giants Stadium. Instead of reporters standing rib to rib with microphones, pads and pens jabbing into each other, there was plenty of room.</p>
        <p>The Giants' 12 assistant coaches took their places behind large placards with their names and titles printed boldly on the front. Only three faces were familiar: Dave Brazil was the Giants' linebacker coach and Dick Rehbein coached their tight ends. The third familiar face belonged to Johnnie Lynn, who was a defensive back for the Jets from 1979 to 1986, an era in which the Jets actually produced some competitive teams. Brazil and Rehbein were the only ones in familiar surroundings, though. Last year at this time, the other 10 assistants were with nine different teams: Lynn was defensive backfield coach for the San Francisco 49ers, John Fox was defensive coordinator with the Oakland Raiders, Jim Skipper was the offensive running backs coach with the Arizona  Cardinals; Rod Dowhower was head coach at Vanderbilt, Denny Marcin was defensive line coach at Illinois, John Dunn was the strength coach with the San Diego Chargers, Mike Haluchak was linebackers coach with the Washington Redskins, Milt Jackson was the receivers coach for the Atlanta Falcons, Larry MacDuff was defensive line coach for the University of Arizona and John Matsko was offensive line coach for the New Orleans Saints.</p>
        <p>In this year of transformation, the greatest symbol of the Giants' aspirations may be John Fox. The franchise is digging in and making a stand after more than a decade on the run, and so is he. Fox stunned the Raiders when he abruptly resigned as defensive coordinator two weeks before the regular-season opener last year. The situation in Oakland had grown increasingly uncomfortable for him. The attacking style of defense he preferred had been replaced by a pass-contain system. He felt the team was pushing him; he wanted to go. Finally, he did. ''I always told myself that if I ever got to that point, rather than be unhappy I was better off moving on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Fox took his family to St. Louis, where he served as a consultant with the Rams. He watched more film than ever before, but watched in a different way. He studied what the defenses were doing. ''When you are coaching defense, you're always watching offense,'' Fox said. ''It was a nice break, it was the first time I had really not coached. Basically it was a long off-season study for me.''</p>
        <p>During the course of the season he redefined career priorities and refused to take the first football job that came along.</p>
        <p>Fox looked at the arc of his career during the past 17 years: the United States Football League to the University of Kansas to the University of Pittsburgh to the Pittsburgh Steelers to the Chargers to the Raiders. When he walked away from the Raiders, Fox said that it was time to stop.</p>
        <p>That is what defense is, after all: stopping. Fox had decided he was tired of running. This is where he will fight, where he will put down roots with his wife and three sons. Fox is looking for a home.</p>
        <p>''Believe me,'' he said, ''what I put my family through in San Diego, then Los Angeles, we move the team to Oakland, then I leave, we go to St. Louis. It hasn't been easy on them. The adventures are hopefully over.''</p>
        <p>The Giants and the Jets have made different statements, but are trying to make the same point: They're tired of being kicked around.</p>
        <p>This is going to be an emotional football campaign in New York. So many have so much invested in the success or failure of Parcells, in the Giants' changing fortunes.</p>
        <p>Everyone seems to be digging in.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
