<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinkins Takes Parting Shot, but Won't Run</title>
    <meta content="13DINK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="908588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dinkins, David N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2D6163FF930A25751C0A961958260" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinkins Takes Parting Shot, but Won't Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former New York City Mayor David N Dinkins, says he will not run for mayor but will do all he can to help unseat Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani; Dinkins photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a 15-minute parting assault on Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, David N. Dinkins ended his two-week flirtation with a return to City Hall yesterday, saying he would not run for mayor but would do all he could to help unseat Mr. Giuliani this fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins, speaking at the midpoint of his hourlong noontime radio program on WLIB-AM, took advantage of what seems certain to be one of the last high-profile moments of his political career to deliver a dense and sweeping attack on Mr. Giuliani.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a 15-minute parting assault on Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, David N. Dinkins ended his two-week flirtation with a return to City Hall yesterday, saying he would not run for mayor but would do all he could to help unseat Mr. Giuliani this fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins, speaking at the midpoint of his hourlong noontime radio program on WLIB-AM, took advantage of what seems certain to be one of the last high-profile moments of his political career to deliver a dense and sweeping attack on Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>''Our Mayor today is not the product of a political clubhouse, he is the product of polls and coaching and tailoring and crafting and the best spinning Madison Avenue has to offer,'' Mr. Dinkins said.</p>
        <p>The former Mayor went on to mock Mr. Giuliani's character as he read his statement. ''Every public policy dispute, every question, every constructive criticism leads to a Vesuvius-like explosion or a to-the-death verbal duel,'' Mr. Dinkins said. ''So all I can say is: Relax, Rudy. I'm not angry with you. I'm just sorry you've let us down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins left the actual disclosure of his statement for the end of his remarks. Before that, he attempted to tweak his audience by building up tension (''in about 120 seconds, I'm going to commence this statement,'' he told listeners).</p>
        <p>He also attempted to squeeze one more day out of the drama: he said he would announce today which Democratic candidate he would endorse for mayor. It seems most likely that he will support Ruth W. Messinger, the Manhattan Borough President, over the other major contender for the nomination, Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx Borough President.</p>
        <p>At City Hall, Mr. Giuliani bristled at Mr. Dinkins's attack. ''Well, if he wants to run for mayor, he should run for mayor,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''If he doesn't, he shouldn't take cheap shots.''</p>
        <p>He predicted that Mr. Dinkins would endorse Ms. Messinger. The Mayor seemed happy at the prospect, as he contrasted his years in office with Mr. Dinkins's term.</p>
        <p>''Those are all things that will be part of this campaign,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''I would like to raise those questions in a debate with David Dinkins, but if someone accepts his endorsement, you can be sure I'm going to raise it with them.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Dinkins finally out of the race, attention turned to how this episode had affected Mr. Giuliani's Democratic challengers. ''Objectively, I think he hurt Ruth and Freddie,'' said one of the candidates, the Rev. Al Sharpton, referring to Ms. Messinger and Mr. Ferrer. ''He took a lot of the attention away from them.''</p>
        <p>But there was considerable sentiment in political circles that Mr. Dinkins may have helped the field by focusing attention on a race that until now had been mostly ignored.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
