<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="831862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHILANTHROPY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WILLS AND ESTATES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEUM OF MODERN ART (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HIGH MUSEUM OF ART (ATLANTA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEUMOF CONTEMPORARY ART (LOS ANGELES)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOGEL, CAROL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MATISSE, HENRI (1869-1954)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PICASSO, PABLO (1881-1973)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLANAGAN, BARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISMAN, MARCIA SIMON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wills and Estates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DC1039F930A15751C0A960958260" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VOGEL, CAROL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lending Out Matisse and Picasso</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lending Out Matisse and Picasso</p>
        <p>To solve severe space problems, many major museums lend portions of their collections to smaller institutions. The arrangement often offers artistic and financial benefits to both the lender and the borrower.</p>
        <p>In the latest pairing, announced this week, the Museum of Modern Art will lend the High Museum of Art in Atlanta portions of its Matisse and Picasso collections during the next 18 months.</p>
        <p>The works will form two separate shows: "Henri Matisse: Masterworks From the Museum of Modern Art," which will be at the High from Nov. 2 through Jan. 26, 1997, and "Pablo Picasso: Masterworks From the Museum of Modern Art," from Nov.  4, 1997, through Feb. 15, 1998.</p>
        <p>The Matisse exhibition will include about 100 works, spanning the artist's entire career. There will be such well-known paintings as "The Red Studio" (1911), "The Swimming Pool" (1952) and "The Piano Lesson" (1916), as well as a selection of drawings, sculpture, cutouts, prints, illustrated books, liturgical vestments and a stained-glass window. Officials at the Modern said they had not  determined which Picassos were to be included.</p>
        <p>The shows will be the first of works by Matisse or Picasso to be held in the  Southeast. And while the Modern has lent parts of its permanent collection before, these loans are the most extensive for these particular artists that the Modern has made to any institution.</p>
        <p>The collaboration comes at a fortuitous time for both museums. Until the Modern expands into the recently purchased Dorset Hotel and two adjacent brownstones -- a project that could easily take 10 years -- it can show only about 10 percent of its permanent collection at any one time. So loans to other  institutions give it wall space to show other portions of the permanent collection. And as the Modern prepares to begin a major capital fund drive to finance its expansion, putting these major works on view in other parts of the country will help to broaden its visibility and, perhaps, support.</p>
        <p>"We don't want our permanent collection to be permanently on the road," said  Glenn D. Lowry, the Modern's director. "This is a one-shot initiative. However,  we are beginning to look into forming a series of ongoing relationships with other institutions." The Modern has not decided how it will fill the spaces when the works going to Atlanta are taken down after the first week of October, Mr. Lowry added. Only three Matisses going to the High are now on view at the Modern. After its Brancusi show closes on April 23, several more Matisses are to be added, including the popular "Piano Lesson" and "Red Studio."</p>
        <p>John Elderfield, the Modern's chief curator at large, said he had worked with the High Museum to choose works that would make two comprehensive survey shows.  While some of the popular works that will travel are now on view at the Modern, others are not. Matisse's "Swimming Pool," for instance, has not been seen at the Modern since 1993.</p>
        <p>"This arrangement," Mr. Elderfield said, "is something that goes back to MOMA's original mission: to be a national institution that has a strong presence in other cities." While the Matisse show will go only to Atlanta, the Picassos are to travel to a second place, which has not yet been named.</p>
        <p>The chance to hold two such important shows will benefit the High Museum, which is trying to become the principal museum for modern art in the Southeast as it works on elevating its profile in general. Ned Rifkin, the High's director, purposely scheduled the Matisse exhibition on the heels of "Rings: Five Passions in World Art," which coincides with the 1996 Summer Olympics in Atlanta. That blockbuster, organized by J. Carter Brown, director emeritus of the National Gallery of Art in Washington, closes on Sept. 29.</p>
        <p>"This is a great way of uplifting the city, which will be in a postpartum depression after the Olympics and 'Rings,' " Mr. Rifkin said. "We've already increased our membership because of 'Rings'; now the trick is how to sustain it. These shows are going to do a lot for commerce, tourism and education, as the museum has risen to a new level on the international museum scene."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rifkin and officials at the Modern declined to say how much the High would pay the Modern for the two loan shows, but Mr. Rifkin said the High was looking for sponsorship. "This is an investment that is well worth it," he said. "It will certainly pay for itself in the long run."</p>
        <p>Bunnies Are Staying On for a While</p>
        <p>The bronze rabbits that have adorned Park Avenue from 54th Street to 59th Street for the last five months were supposed to have left Manhattan on Jan. 15. But the sculptures, the work of the English artist Barry Flanagan, have been so  well received that they are staying put until planting season begins on March 8.</p>
        <p>"It was my idea to keep the rabbits up until as close to Easter as possible," said Henry J. Stern, Commissioner of Parks and Recreation. "The idea of rabbits  scurrying across Park Avenue is a curious juxtaposition when you consider the surrounding construction and civilization." The project was organized by Mr. Stern's department, which oversees the malls on Park Avenue, in collaboration with the British Council and the artist's dealer, Waddington Gallery.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, sculpture by the Colombian artist Fernando Botero was exhibited along the Park Avenue malls. Mr. Stern said his office was flooded with proposals by other artists. "It's a great public space," he said. "We have  no immediate plans for another show, but we're open to offers as long as they are totally unique."</p>
        <p>Los Angeles Museum Gets 83 Works</p>
        <p>The Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles received a windfall this week  that will considerably strengthen its holdings: a collection of 83 works, primarily drawings and prints, from the estate of Marcia Simon Weisman, a founder of the museum, who died five years ago. Valued at $6 million to $8 million, the works are by such artists as Willem de Kooning, David Hockney, Jasper Johns and Jackson Pollock. As a condition of the gift, the museum must establish a study center for works on paper.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
