<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Racing World Grieves, It Also Goes On</title>
    <meta content="20DAYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/20/sports/20DAYT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1272280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Daytona 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">North American Sports Car Racing Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helton, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Earnhardt, Dale</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D81F30F933A15751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Racing World Grieves, It Also Goes On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla., Feb. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nascar President Mike Helton announces next race in Winston Cup series will proceed as scheduled in spite of fatal crash of Dale Earnhardt during Daytona 500 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The infield parking lots at Daytona International Speedway that had been packed with stock car trailers and the drivers' mobile homes this weekend had cleared out this morning. And the Nascar Winston Cup series will move on, too, heading to its next stop this weekend despite the death of Dale Earnhardt during the Daytona 500 on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Nascar President Mike Helton said at a news conference today that next Sunday's race in Rockingham, N.C., will be held as scheduled. No consideration was given to postponing or canceling the Dura Lube 400, said Jim Hunter, a vice president for International Speedway Corporation, which owns North Carolina Speedway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The infield parking lots at Daytona International Speedway that had been packed with stock car trailers and the drivers' mobile homes this weekend had cleared out this morning. And the Nascar Winston Cup series will move on, too, heading to its next stop this weekend despite the death of Dale Earnhardt during the Daytona 500 on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Nascar President Mike Helton said at a news conference today that next Sunday's race in Rockingham, N.C., will be held as scheduled. No consideration was given to postponing or canceling the Dura Lube 400, said Jim Hunter, a vice president for International Speedway Corporation, which owns North Carolina Speedway.</p>
        <p>Earnhardt, 49, who won a record seven Winston Cup championships and more than $41 million in his career, died at a Daytona Beach hospital after his black Chevrolet thudded into the outside wall on the final lap of the race.</p>
        <p>Funeral arrangements and plans for a possible memorial service for Earnhardt were not completed today, Helton said. He said it was also too early to decide whether Earnhardt's familiar No. 3 would be retired.</p>
        <p>''I can't think of any time that has been more tough,'' Bill France Jr., the chairman of the board of Nascar, said today at the news conference, which was held in a tent not much farther than a half-mile from where Earnhardt was fatally injured. ''This is certainly going to be one of the big events, if you want to call it that, in the history of Nascar.''</p>
        <p>Four Nascar drivers, including Adam Petty, the grandson of Richard Petty, have died in accidents in the last 10 months. Helton said driver safety would not necessarily become a more important issue as a result of Earnhardt's crash because, he said, driver safety is always paramount.</p>
        <p>Helton said Nascar officials have already examined the wreckage of Earnhardt's car -- which is being kept in a secret location -- to see if they can determine more about what caused the accident. He also said that Nascar would continue investigating the use of soft walls, which are made of Styrofoam and lessen the force of impact. Earnhardt was an advocate of such walls.</p>
        <p>''We're always investigating safety issues,'' Helton said. ''We don't accelerate it, and we don't slow it down. It's a work in progress all the time.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Steve Bohannon, who is the director of emergency medical services at Daytona International Speedway, said an autopsy performed today showed that Earnhardt died of head injuries, particularly to the base of his brain.</p>
        <p>Bohannon said that when he arrived at the scene of the accident, he could tell it was serious. ''I feel like anything that possibly could have been done was done for him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bohannon said it could not be determined if Earnhardt's life would have been saved had he been wearing one of the new head-and-neck-support collars, known as HANS, which are available to Nascar drivers for the first time this year.</p>
        <p>The collar fits over the driver's shoulders and includes tethers that are attached to a driver's helmet. The device is designed to prevent a driver's head from snapping forward or backward in an accident. Only a handful of drivers wore the device in the Daytona 500 this year, including Kyle Petty, Adam Petty's father.</p>
        <p>Michael Waltrip, who won Sunday's race, his first victory in 463 Winston Cup races, did not wear the device, but he said he planned to try it again during testing next week. He said the device had received mixed reviews among drivers. Helton said that Nascar would not make the device mandatory.</p>
        <p>Waltrip said, ''It's something drivers should investigate and find out if it's right for them.''</p>
        <p>A series of rule changes were implemented for this year's race at Daytona to slow the cars down and provide for a close, exciting race. Among the adjustments were an aerodynamic package that included a bigger spoiler in the back of the cars and a thin metal strip, called a blade, atop the cars.</p>
        <p>''I think racing's all about being close,'' Hunter said. ''Part of their talent is being able to race close together at tremendous speeds.''</p>
        <p>The changes produced 49 lead changes, 40 more than last year's  Daytona 500. Several drivers, Rusty Wallace and Dale Jarrett among them, said pointedly that the tightly bunched cars left no room for error and might have been responsible for an 18-car accident late in Sunday's race. But Waltrip said he did not believe the new rules were responsible for the accident that involved Earnhardt.</p>
        <p>He also said that Sterling Marlin, who tapped into Earnhardt's car to send it into a spin that resulted in the accident, should not be blamed for the crash.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that wreck looked to me anything other than guys wanting to get to the checkered flag,'' Waltrip said.</p>
        <p>Waltrip said he would miss Earnhardt, a longtime friend who hired him this year to drive one of his three powerful Chevrolets. His celebration in victory lane, the first of his career, had been spoiled by the news that Earnhardt had been in a serious accident and would not be there.</p>
        <p>''I just couldn't wait until I got that big grab on the back of the neck and a hug,'' Waltrip said.</p>
        <p>Upon hearing the news of Earnhardt's death, Waltrip tried to console himself by saying that Earnhardt was with Waltrip's late father, celebrating the victory. ''And that ain't a bad thing, either,'' Waltrip said, as his eyes began to water.</p>
        <p>In Earnhardt's Memory</p>
        <p>In lieu of flowers for Dale Earnhardt's services, Michael Waltrip, who won the Daytona 500 on Sunday, asked that contributions be made to the Carolinas Foundation, P.O. Box 34769, Charlotte, N.C. 28234-4769.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
