<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Candidates Emerge to Take on Hoffa</title>
    <meta content="Y20TEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Teamsters</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leedham, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cashman, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffa, James P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carey, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DE143BF933A15752C1A961958260" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Candidates Emerge to Take on Hoffa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas Leedham, Ken Hall and George Cashman emerge as most likely reform candidates to vie against James P Hoffa to replace Ron Carey as teamsters union head; Carey backers, damaged by Carey's disqualification, admit any reform candidate faces uphill battle against Hoffa; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Ron Carey barred from running for re-election as teamsters president, a former oilfield repairman from West Virginia, a former truck driver from Boston and a former warehouse worker from Oregon have emerged as the most likely candidates to challenge James P. Hoffa for the teamsters' presidency.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Carey's supporters scramble for a stand-in, these three are increasingly regarded as the leading contenders to hold together his coalition, which largely consists of reformers, East Coast union members, and United Parcel Service drivers encouraged by his success in their strike earlier this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Ron Carey barred from running for re-election as teamsters president, a former oilfield repairman from West Virginia, a former truck driver from Boston and a former warehouse worker from Oregon have emerged as the most likely candidates to challenge James P. Hoffa for the teamsters' presidency.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Carey's supporters scramble for a stand-in, these three are increasingly regarded as the leading contenders to hold together his coalition, which largely consists of reformers, East Coast union members, and United Parcel Service drivers encouraged by his success in their strike earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The battle to take up Mr. Carey's mantle takes on added significance because Mr. Hoffa, son of the notorious teamsters president, is being investigated for possible campaign irregularities, which could catapult his opponent from a long shot at present to a strong favorite if Mr. Hoffa is barred from running.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey's supporters acknowledge that whichever candidate they back faces an uphill battle because Mr. Hoffa has amassed a sizable war chest, has a well-oiled campaign organization in place and has the most famous last name in American labor.</p>
        <p>The disqualification of Mr. Carey also costs his forces a powerful campaign issue. They have always sought to portray Mr. Hoffa as a representative of the corrupt old guard. Now, Mr. Hoffa is expected to assert that he is the anti-corruption candidate.</p>
        <p>The election, scheduled for February and March, is likely to be postponed. But potential challengers are  somewhat in limbo because Mr. Carey has vowed to appeal last Monday's ruling disqualifying him.</p>
        <p>Ken Paff, national coordinator of Teamsters for a Democratic Union, a Detroit-based group that backed Mr. Carey in previous elections, said, ''If Carey's not allowed to be the candidate, the reform forces need to put forward a strong candidate that members can rally around and that members see as a continuation of the reform process.''</p>
        <p>In the feverish political discussions that are taking place within the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Carey supporters have focused on three union officials as the best bets to keep Mr. Hoffa and his faction from gaining control of a union that was synonymous with labor corruption when it was headed by his father.</p>
        <p>The three are: Thomas Leedham, a former warehouse worker from Oregon, who runs the teamsters' 250,000-member warehouse division; Ken Hall, a former Pennzoil worker from West Virginia, who heads the union's small package division and was Mr. Carey's right-hand man during the United Parcel Service strike in August, and George Cashman, a former truck driver from Boston, who is president of the largest teamsters' local in New England, one that has already produced three presidents of the 1.4 million-member union.</p>
        <p>''I don't think members will let this union slide back to the way it was before Carey,'' said Mr. Leedham. ''I think they like the direction of the union. They want a stronger union, they want better contracts, and they see that reform and democracy in the union is the way to get that.''</p>
        <p>The disqualification of Mr. Carey makes Mr. Hoffa the odds-on favorite, but the Carey wing of the union hopes that whatever candidate it rallies around can pull off an upset. Although whoever is chosen will be far less known than Mr. Carey or Mr. Hoffa, Carey supporters say their ability to mobilize the rank and file might offset Mr. Hoffa's greater fame and finances.</p>
        <p>There are two potential kingmakers who might select Mr. Hoffa's opponent. One is Mr. Carey himself, because the candidate he favors is expected to have a leg up in being nominated as Mr. Hoffa's challenger. The other is the Teamsters for a Democratic Union, a 10,000-member reform group whose grass-roots activities were instrumental in Mr. Carey's victories in 1991 and again last year.</p>
        <p>In August, a court-appointed election monitor overturned last year's election, finding that Mr. Carey's aides diverted hundreds of thousands of dollars in union funds to help his campaign. Last Monday, a former Federal judge helping oversee the teamsters barred Mr. Carey from running again, finding that he participated in the fund-raising scheme.</p>
        <p>The new election is scheduled for February and March, but on Tuesday, the Federal election monitor indicated she might ask a Federal judge to delay the election to give her more time to investigate Mr. Hoffa's finances. Several Carey and Hoffa backers said Federal officials might be eager to disqualify Mr. Hoffa under the belief that the last thing the Government wants to see after spending eight years and millions of dollars overseeing the teamsters is Jimmy Hoffa's son elected.</p>
        <p>The elder Hoffa, who Federal prosecutors said was close to many mobsters, led the union from 1957 to 1971, went to prison for jury tampering and fraud and disappeared in 1975 in what was widely viewed as a gangland execution.</p>
        <p>Carey supporters say Mr. Hall, 40, who played the quiet second to Mr. Carey's flamboyant star turn in the 15-day U.P.S. strike, can trade on that success. In a showdown with Mr. Hoffa, he can count on strong support from 180,000 U.P.S. workers who were Mr. Carey's base and who vote in higher percentages than other teamsters. Mr. Hall is considered an expert practitioner of Mr. Carey's policy of educating and mobilizing members to enable them to stand tough in a strike.</p>
        <p>A big advantage held by Mr. Leedham, 46, is that he heads the union's largest division, comprised of 250,000 warehouse workers. He is respected for mounting successful contract battles against Banquet Foods and the Fred Meyer grocery chain and for using such tactics as mobilizing members, seeking cooperation from other unions and running slick advertising campaigns to put pressure on corporate adversaries.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Hall and Mr. Leedham say it is premature to discuss whether they are candidates, Mr. Cashman, who is one of New England's most visible union leaders, has repeatedly indicated he would run if Mr. Carey was disqualified.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cashman, the 48-year-old son of a teamster, began driving trucks at the age of 18, and in 1991 won the presidency of New England's largest local, defeating William McCarthy, a former general president of the teamsters. A powerful presence, Mr. Cashman maintains ties to some old guard teamsters derided by Mr. Carey, and as a result, Mr. Cashman said he could win by forging a unity ticket that could attract pro-Carey reformers and more traditional teamsters.</p>
        <p>Many Carey supporters say Teamsters for a Democratic Union would be delighted with Mr. Hall or Mr. Leedham, but would be uncomfortable with Mr. Cashman because he has ties to the old guard and is known or running a traditional top-down union local that does not involve the rank and file in union affairs, as much as Carey supporters like.</p>
        <p>There are two other strikes against Mr. Cashman. He once used  $25,000 from his local's health and welfare fund to settle a sexual harassment claim against him by a union employee -- he has repeatedly insisted the claim was unfounded. In addition, the Hoffa camp has protested a $25,000 donation that Mr. Cashman made to the Carey campaign, $22,500 of which was lent by the manager of his local's building.</p>
        <p>Three other teamsters have been mentioned as dark horse candidates. Diana Kilmury, a resident of Vancouver, British Columbia, is a member of the teamsters' executive board and spoke out against corruption when the mob largely controlled the union. Richard Nelson, an Oklahoman who heads the union's freight division, might be able to attract votes from Mr. Hoffa. Tom Gilmartin, a former warehouse worker from South Windsor, Conn., heads the union's 140,000-member industrial trades division and is close to Teamsters for a Democratic Union.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
