<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tender Said to Yield 64.1% of Norton Stock</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTON CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BTR PLC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD163EF937A25757C0A966958260" item-length="356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tender Said to Yield 64.1% of Norton Stock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Reuters</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: BTR P.L.C., the British industrial conglomerate, announced today that almost two-thirds of the common stock of the Norton Company had been tendered under BTR's $1.64 billion buyout offer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: BTR P.L.C., the British industrial conglomerate, announced today that almost two-thirds of the common stock of the Norton Company had been tendered under BTR's $1.64 billion buyout offer.</p>
        <p>BTR P.L.C., the British industrial conglomerate, announced today that almost two-thirds of the common stock of the Norton Company had been tendered under BTR's $1.64 billion buyout offer.</p>
        <p>While a number of obstacles to a takeover remain, the tender result was another setback in Norton's effort to remain independent.</p>
        <p>BTR said it had received 64.1 percent of the stock and was extending its $75-a-share purchase offer for the Worcester, Mass., plastics and ceramics company.</p>
        <p>But BTR fell short of its requirement that two-thirds of the stock be tendered. And it has conditioned the purchase of stock on the removal of certain anti-takeover provisions that would increase the cost of a hostile takeover.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, Norton lost a legal fight over a key part of its anti-takeover strategy. A Federal judge on Wednesday denied the company's attempt to postpone the annual shareholders meeting scheduled for April 26. At the meeting, BTR intends to try to oust Norton's board.</p>
        <p>After the court ruling, Norton's shares jumped $3.125 as investors bet it would now be harder for the company to thwart BTR. The price rose another $1.125 a share, to $77.125, on Thursday, when BTR said it might be ready to negotiate a higher offer.</p>
        <p>Even though the conditions that BTR put on its tender offer have not been met, a source close to BTR said the heavy tendering was significant ''because it certainly shows where the cards are held.''</p>
        <p>The tender results may put new pressure on the Norton board to negotiate, a takeover speculator said. The company also faces the possible loss of board seats at the annual meeting.</p>
        <p>Norton's last lines of defense are legal maneuvers, which include appealing the court's ruling and asking the Massachusetts State Legislature to block the takeover.</p>
        <p>The sides remain far apart. Norton has stonewalled BTR in its attempts to get the companies together and Norton's chairman, John Nelson, has not responded to telephone calls and letters from BTR's chairman, John Cahill.</p>
        <p>Norton employs 16,000 and is known for exploiting niches in slowly growing markets. It had no comment on the tender results.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
