<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="05QNA.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DA123FF936A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Freireich</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>South Africa Garden Route</p>
        <p>Q.  During a tour of South Africa in October, my husband and I would like to visit the Garden Route for three days. Can you recommend agencies that start from George and list the highlights? -- Ethel Rosenthal, Bayonne, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>South Africa Garden Route</p>
        <p>Q.  During a tour of South Africa in October, my husband and I would like to visit the Garden Route for three days. Can you recommend agencies that start from George and list the highlights? -- Ethel Rosenthal, Bayonne, N.J.</p>
        <p>A.  Stretching for about 125 miles, the Garden Route, where trees rise like cathedral columns in some places, includes such highlights as Oudtshoorn, the home of ostrich farms; the Little Karoo, a semiarid region adjoining lush areas; the lagoons at Plettenberg Bay and Knysna; the Cango Caves; a steam train ride of about two hours from George to Knysna, and Tsitsikamma National Park.</p>
        <p>Tours of the route run three or four days and cover many of the highlights cited. They usually go from Cape Town to Port Elizabeth, or vice versa, or start and end in Cape Town. Vehicles you would take  range from a minivan for 7 to a bus seating 18 or more.</p>
        <p>If you're committed to starting in George and prefer not to drive -- having to drive on the left may be enough cause for reluctance -- you could arrange a tour with a local operator, which is what is suggested by Selma Edwards of E-Z Travel, 1540 Broadway, New York, N.Y. 10036; (212) 246-2116, fax (212) 977-4248. She recommends Eileen Bell at Zwelitsha (New Era) Tours, Post Office Box 450, Constanta 7848, South Africa; (27-21) 797-0392, fax (27-21) 797-7251.</p>
        <p>Or, you might be able to make the Garden Route, starting in George, an add-on to your current itinerary; that would probably cost less than a separate trip of three or four days.</p>
        <p>If starting from Cape Town or Port Elizabeth can be made to work, here are some agencies you could use, with rates given per person for double occupancy.</p>
        <p>Africa Tours, 875 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10001; (800) 235-3692 or (212) 563-3686, fax (212) 563-4459. Four days. Departing from Cape Town on Tuesday and returning to Cape Town. Lodgings: Riempie Estate Hotel, Oudtshoorn; two nights at the King George Hotel, George. Ten meals. $865.</p>
        <p>African Travel, 1100 East Broadway, Glendale, Calif. 91205; (800) 421-8907 or (818) 507-7893, fax (818) 507-5802. Four days. Departing from Cape Town on Wednesday and from Port Elizabeth on Monday. Lodgings: Queens Hotel, Oudtshoorn, and Holiday Inn Garden Court, in the Wilderness area, for two nights. Eight meals. $585.</p>
        <p>Classic Encounters, 50 East 42d Street, New York, N.Y. 10017; (888) 808-1999 or (212) 972-0031, fax (212) 972-0032. Four days. Departing from Cape Town on Wednesday and from Port Elizabeth on Monday. Tanya Nel of the agency said she could not specify for certain what the lodgings would be. Eight meals. $650.</p>
        <p>Travel Beyond, 214 South Minnetonka Avenue, Wayzata, Minn. 55391; (800) 823-6063 or (612) 475-2565, fax (612) 475-1029. Four days. Departing from Cape Town on Tuesday and returning to Cape Town. Dropoff in Port Elizabeth can be arranged. Lodgings: Riempie Estate Hotel, Oudtshoorn; two nights at the King George Hotel, George. Eight meals. $530.</p>
        <p>The Concorde on the Cheap</p>
        <p>Q.  I would like to experience flying on the Concorde but can't afford to spend thousands of dollars. What is the least expensive Concorde trip one can take? -- Fred Bernstein, New York, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A.  So that you get the big picture, it seems worth mentioning that a regularly scheduled round trip flight costs $10,384 between New York and Paris on Air France and $9,165 between New York and London on British Airways. On Air France, the fare to Paris to $9,346 if a ticket is bought four days ahead. Between July 1 and Aug. 31, members of the Air France frequent flier club can take a companion along at half price, which comes to $7009.50 apiece. If the fares seem steep, bear in mind that the flight time to Paris, gate to gate, is a  3 hours and 40 minutes -- and a half-hour less to London -- since you're traveling as fast as 1,340 miles an hour, or twice the speed of sound.</p>
        <p>For a taste of the Concorde, an hour-and-40-minute flight operates about twice a month from Heathrow Airport outside London. The cost is $1,125 and, in December, $1,141 (at 60 pence to the dollar). The flight takes you out over the Atlantic and includes a champagne breakfast and a  visit to the flight deck. It is organized by Goodwood Travel, St. Andrew's House, Station Road East, Canterbury, Kent CT1 2WD; telephone (44-1227) 763336, fax (44-1227) 762417.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, you can take a one-hour flight on Aug. 1 or 2 aboard a British Airways Concorde at the Experimental Aircraft Association's annual meeting in Oshkosh, Wis. Flights will operate twice a day and cost $715. Note, however, that because of Federal Aviation Administration regulations flights may not exceed the speed of sound.</p>
        <p>A bargain is to be had on Aug. 3 when a British Airways Concorde returns to Europe from Wisconsin. The fare is $2,222 from Oshkosh to Heathrow via Kennedy Airport or $1,925 from Kennedy to Heathrow. Information: Travel Service Corporation, (800) 634-2153 or (312) 726-3290, fax (312) 726-1189. While gloating about the saving, don't forget about the cost of getting back: Subsonic one-way flights start at $440.</p>
        <p>Van Goghs to Washington</p>
        <p>Q.  In the fall the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam is scheduled to be renovated. Part of the collection is to be on display in Washington during the closing. How can I get tickets? -- Arlene Copeland, Clifton Springs, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A.  Seventy-two paintings from the Van Gogh Museum, the largest number the museum has lent since its opening in 1973, will be shown at the National Gallery of Art from Oct. 4 to Jan. 3 and then at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art from Jan. 17 to April 4.</p>
        <p>The exhibitions will coincide with a $15 million renovation of the Van Gogh Museum, which will be adding a new wing. The museum is expected to reopen in April.</p>
        <p>At the National Gallery, starting Aug. 30, advance passes for the show, ''Van Gogh's Van Goghs,'' will be available free at the East Building, Fourth Street and Constitution Avenue, N.W., on Monday through Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. and on Sunday from 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.  Same-day passes -- no more than six per person -- will be available free every day. (202) 737-4215.</p>
        <p>Another source, starting Aug. 30, is Ticketmaster, which will charge $4 per order. The number is (800) 551-7328 nationwide, (202) 432-7328 in Washington, (410) 481-7328 in Baltimore and (703) 573-7328 in northern Virginia.</p>
        <p>PAUL FREIREICH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
