<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No More Pencils, No More Books? Try TV</title>
    <meta content="05COVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980712T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D6153EF936A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No More Pencils, No More Books? Try TV</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New and revised children's television series offers educational programming; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The O. J. Simpson murder trial had at least one result that no lawyer could have predicted: an educational television series for children.</p>
        <p>''I noticed a lot of people who were kind of down at the heels watching the trial,'' said Tom Snyder, a television producer and writer who was observing the proceedings in a Massachusetts bar one evening. ''A lot of these people, who probably had no high school education, were suddenly talking in a very sophisticated way about DNA testing. It occurred to me that if you had a court about science that was just a little bit goofy, you could have your own expert witness come in, and everyone would hang on his every word.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The O. J. Simpson murder trial had at least one result that no lawyer could have predicted: an educational television series for children.</p>
        <p>''I noticed a lot of people who were kind of down at the heels watching the trial,'' said Tom Snyder, a television producer and writer who was observing the proceedings in a Massachusetts bar one evening. ''A lot of these people, who probably had no high school education, were suddenly talking in a very sophisticated way about DNA testing. It occurred to me that if you had a court about science that was just a little bit goofy, you could have your own expert witness come in, and everyone would hang on his every word.''</p>
        <p>That's how ''Science Court'' was born. An animated series for 7- to 11-year-olds that began last fall, it revolves around fictional cases that are only slightly more outrageous than those in the news. A typical scenario: a rich Scrooge type slips in a puddle and claims that leaky pipes are the culprit. But the water was really the result of condensation. The trial, presided over by Judge Stone (the voice of the comedian Paula Poundstone), turns into an explanation of the water cycle, with the jury foreman issuing not only a verdict but also a recommendation that the plaintiff's lawyer ''never wear that shirt and pants together again.''</p>
        <p>''Science Court,'' on ABC Saturdays at 12:30 P.M., is far from the only series with educational promise. Several children's shows recently had premieres or began a new season, and some of the older educational series are offering fresh fare.</p>
        <p>One of the more publicized new series is ''Teletubbies,'' a PBS program developed not just for preschool, but also preverbal, children. Broadcast on Channel 13 weekdays at 9 A.M. in the New York area, ''Teletubbies'' features four little creatures who could be junior E.T.'s, with antennae and stomachs that display television screens. Inhabiting an intensely colored landscape, the Teletubbies speak baby talk and use their tummies to switch on videos that include real children. The series, a British import, has been criticized for its rudimentary language and for appealing to viewers who can barely walk. But Alice Cahn, the director of children's programming at PBS, said ''Teletubbies'' teaches or reinforces valuable concepts like object permanence, which is the understanding that things continue to exist even when they have disappeared from view.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea that something goes away and comes back is repeated throughout the show,'' Ms. Cahn said. As for the language, ''I defy you to find a parent who doesn't use the warm, comforting language of motherese or fatherese that the Teletubbies speak,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Another recent arrival speaks directly to small children in English no one can quibble with. ''Bear in the Big Blue House,'' a production of Jim Henson Television, features the company's signature Muppetry in the form of cuddly characters like its host, the seven-foot-tall Bear who greets (and sniffs) the viewer and makes preschooler pronouncements to Treelo, a lemur, like ''You're too big to go down the drain, even if you wanted to.''</p>
        <p>What's unusual about Bear is that he can move all the features of his face, which Big Bird can't, said Rich Ross, senior vice president for programming and production at the Disney Channel, which broadcasts the show daily (10 A.M. weekdays and 8 A.M. weekends). ''I think that is what connects with kids,'' Mr. Ross said. ''Then we get to do great subject matter, like teach gravity to 4-year-olds.''</p>
        <p>The second season of ''Bear,'' which began three weeks ago, includes subjects like babies and time, as well as new characters like Dr. Hogg, a physician pig, and Ray, the sun.</p>
        <p>''It's a very nice show, and it helps you understand why 'Barney' isn't,'' said Peggy Charren, a longtime advocate for quality children's television and a visiting scholar at the Harvard University Graduate School of Education. ''I think the tone of 'Barney' is condescending.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Charren, however, gives high marks to most PBS children's programming. (She is ambivalent about ''Teletubbies,'' but ''I don't think it's dangerous,'' she said.) She is also enthusiastic about ''Blue's Clues,'' Nickelodeon's top-rated mini-mystery for preschoolers, and the Cartoon Network's ''Big Bag,'' a Muppet show. As for ''Science Court,'' she is a die-hard fan.</p>
        <p>''It not only entertains, it educates, and it educates me, too,'' Ms. Charren said.</p>
        <p>Science, with its explosive (literally) potential, has long been a way to draw older children to educational programming. CBS's ''Beakman's World'' and PBS's ''Bill Nye the Science Guy'' are two acclaimed examples. And next month, the Discovery Channel will broadcast the pilot of ''Sci Squad,'' a series it plans to introduce next year. A kind of cross between ''Mission: Impossible'' and ''Power Rangers'' (minus the violence), ''Sci Squad'' will feature a group of savvy teen-agers investigating a scientific mystery: sharks will be the focus of the pilot, to be shown on ''Super Shark Sunday,'' Aug. 16, as part of Discovery Kids, the channel's Sunday-morning block.</p>
        <p>Another show in that lineup will be ''Real Kids, Real Adventures: Shark Attack.'' The ''Real Kids'' series, which began in April, recreates an actual child's brush with danger (picture a junior ''Rescue 911''), combining it with an interview with the youngster and a surprising amount of science.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to use stories to also communicate information,'' said Marjorie Kaplan, senior vice president for children's programming at Discovery Networks. That philosophy also underlies ''Adventures of ARK'' (Animal Rescue Kids), a Discovery series about fictional teen-agers aiding animals (Sundays at 10:30 A.M.).</p>
        <p>''Kids really connect with animals,'' Ms. Kaplan said. ''There's a whole 'us versus them' feeling among kids, and animals are on the 'us' side.''</p>
        <p>Animals are also the stars of ''Omba Mokomba,'' which just began its second season on the Disney Channel. (The title means ''Ask Mokomba'' in Swahili.) ''If we can have 'Hakuna Matata,' we can have 'Omba Mokomba,' '' Mr. Ross said, referring to a popular song from ''The Lion King.'' Benjamin Brown plays Makomba, an African broadcaster and zoological expert. Shown on Sundays at 7:30 P.M., the series explores answers to questions sent in by children, like ''Do any male animals give birth?'' (seahorses) and ''How many ants does an anteater eat a day?'' (35,000 or so).</p>
        <p>Although directed toward school-age children, the series crosses generations, with animal antics for preschoolers (the newest cast member is Mr. Plunkett, a capuchin monkey) and parodies of adult television for their parents (a recent segment called ''Cats'' was a takeoff on the Fox series ''Cops'').</p>
        <p>Fall promises additional educational programming, including ''Noddy'' on PBS, an animated musical adventure, and ''Warner Brothers' Histeria,'' an animated series about history on Kids WB. ''Science Court'' will also be reincarnated as ''Squigglevision,'' a title reflecting Mr. Snyder's signature animation. A science trial will still be its core, but it will also feature a math segment, ''See You Later, Estimator,'' and a vocabulary spot, ''The Last Word.''</p>
        <p>Despite so much innovative programming for children, there is a noticeable lack of new current-events shows. The award-winning ''Nick News,'' while far from a recent series, is still the only television news magazine for the young. Broadcast on Sundays at 4 P.M. in the summer, the 6-year-old program features the journalist Linda Ellerbee as host and has explored topics ranging from Arab-Israeli relations to the school killings in Jonesboro, Ark.</p>
        <p>''I've been working for years to get news programming for children,'' Ms. Charren said. ''So it's nice that 'Nick News' exists.''</p>
        <p>Although last year the Federal Communications Commission required all broadcast stations to feature at least three hours of educational programming each week for viewers under 16, it is still a struggle to get informational shows on the air, Ms. Charren said. ''There's an idea that education is 'Don't hit your best friend in the eye with your elbow,' '' she said, noting that many stations fulfill the F.C.C. mandate with shows about social values. ''They say, 'Oh, real education, kids won't watch,' '' she said. ''But if it's done well, kids love it.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY  Correction:  July 12, 1998, Sunday  An article in the Television section last Sunday about children's programs described the coming PBS series ''Noddy'' incorrectly. It is a live-action comedy with animation, puppetry and music, not an animated musical adventure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 12, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the Television section last Sunday about children's programs described the coming PBS series ''Noddy'' incorrectly. It is a live-action comedy with animation, puppetry and music, not an animated musical adventure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
