<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day of High Security Proves Mostly Uneventful</title>
    <meta content="12WARN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="A Nation Challenged" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/12/national/12WARN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1423036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="VIGILANCE AND MEMORY: THE ALERT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Great Britain-International Relations-Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Great Britain-International Relations-Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Newark</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jakarta (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia/Jakarta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4D61231F931A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day of High Security Proves Mostly Uneventful</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Day of High Security Proves Mostly Uneventful</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON with JOHN BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John; Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First anniversary of terrorist attacks passes without serious incident, but senior Bush administration officials continue to warn of possibility of attack and nation's alert condition remains high; cargo ships off Port Newark are subjected to high level of scrutiny; there are various incidents throughout country but increased reporting may be response to alert status; security measures and embassy closings noted; Britain closes embassies in Jakarta and Singapore (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With security at its tightest levels in a year at government installations in the United States and abroad, the first anniversary of the hijackings passed without serious incident today, but senior administration officials continued to warn of the possibility of an attack.</p>
        <p>On a day when federal authorities girded for the worst, when emergency command posts at government agencies were heavily staffed by intelligence and law enforcement officials, the day offered more tedium than tension.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With security at its tightest levels in a year at government installations in the United States and abroad, the first anniversary of the hijackings passed without serious incident.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With security at its tightest levels in a year at government installations in the United States and abroad, the first anniversary of the hijackings passed without serious incident today, but senior administration officials continued to warn of the possibility of an attack.</p>
        <p>On a day when federal authorities girded for the worst, when emergency command posts at government agencies were heavily staffed by intelligence and law enforcement officials, the day offered more tedium than tension.</p>
        <p>''We're tearing around, but it's just really quiet out there,'' said one senior law enforcement official.</p>
        <p>Teams of federal agents, some with radiation detection gear, scoured a Liberian-flagged cargo ship that was detained off the Port Newark/Elizabeth Marine Terminal. The ship was stopped before it was to dock, when traces of radioactivity were detected in its cargo and unexplained sounds, possibly from stowaways, were heard in the vessel's cargo areas. The ship, M/V Palermo Senator, was ordered to a security zone six miles out to sea.</p>
        <p>In Columbus, Ohio, police evacuated the 41-story James A. Rhodes State Office Tower after an employee encountered a man behaving suspiciously on the 28th floor. When questioned by the employee, the man said he was ''looking for someplace to hide a bomb,'' said Lt. Gary Lewis, a state police spokesman. State police and federal bomb experts cleared the building and began searching a van belonging to the man's employer.</p>
        <p>Bomb-sniffing dogs reacted on several occasions to substances in the van, but the authorities did not find a bomb. The suspect, Oscar Sesmas, 35, was charged with inducing panic, a felony.</p>
        <p>''It has been a somewhat busy day across the country,'' said Gordon Johndroe, spokesman for the White House Office of Homeland Security.</p>
        <p>There were daily reports of incidents across the country, Mr. Johndroe said, but the volume had been slightly higher today. ''While we have no incidents that immediately indicate terrorism, there are some people who are being interviewed by authorities to track all information down necessary to conclude the investigations,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johndroe said the increased reporting might have been the result of nervousness on the part of citizens and greater numbers of law enforcement officers deployed to protect memorial gatherings.</p>
        <p>Air combat patrols, which resumed over Washington and New York last Friday, expanded today to include about 10 additional cities, military officials said. Fighter jets were placed on alert at more than a dozen other locations.</p>
        <p>Increased police presence was visible in cities around the country, missile launchers were positioned around Washington and federal and city police were out in force around the monuments. In Los Angeles, city police were at full deployment throughout the day, in part because of the federal action and in part to monitor the numerous commemorative events taking place citywide.</p>
        <p>Evidence of the Bush administration's edgy observance of the Sept. 11 hijackings was most noticeable abroad. Nine American embassies remained shut, including diplomatic posts in Southeast Asia. It was the possibility of Al Qaeda attacks in that region that prompted the Bush administration on Tuesday to ratchet up the threat alert level. The level was raised to code orange, the second highest risk level in the color-coded threat warning system.</p>
        <p>Today, the precautionary steps spread throughout the world. Pentagon officials said that commanders in charge of a region that sweeps from East Africa to Central Asia increased its security level to the military's highest threat level.</p>
        <p>In Europe, three embassies and four consulates received envelopes in the mail containing an unidentified white powder, government officials said. None of the diplomatic posts were closed. In each case, officials removed the powder and envelopes to a secure location and tests were planned to determine whether the powder was anthrax or another lethal substance, the official said.</p>
        <p>The identities of the countries that received the envelopes were not disclosed. But an embassy official in Rome said that one of the mailings had been received there: ''Some time this morning, late in the morning, we got a batch of international mail -- not diplomatic, not military -- from outside Italy. There was a letter addressed generically to the embassy, which is unusual in itself. When the mailroom people picked up the letter, they could tell there was some kind of granular stuff inside.''</p>
        <p>Other countries also reacted to the threat warnings. British officials closed their embassies in Jakarta and Singapore, as a ''precautionary measure,'' an official said. Australia closed its embassy in East Timor, the former Indonesian province that acquired its independence earlier this year, and closed except for emergencies in Singapore.</p>
        <p>As Western governments continued to investigate the intelligence that led to the concerns about a terrorist attack, they are finding parallels to a plot to blow up the American, British and Australian embassies in Singapore last year, Western officials said today.</p>
        <p>That plot, which was thwarted, was the work of Jemaah Islamiyah, a militant organization with deep roots in Indonesia, officials said.</p>
        <p>''They have shown a sophistication and level of capability to carry out an attack like this,'' said a Western diplomat in Singapore speaking about the current threat. ''They have to be taken very seriously.''</p>
        <p>Australian officials said that Jemaah Islamiyah, which is headed by an Indonesian cleric, Abu Bakar Bashir, was behind the threats that led to the decision to close their embassy in East Timor.</p>
        <p>The Australian and British embassies in Singapore flank the American embassy, which remained open today, following a brief outdoors memorial ceremony. Diplomats said the American embassy was better protected -- higher on a hill and a virtual fortress -- while the two other embassies were more vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johndroe did not say when the threat condition would return to its previous alert level, but many local and state officials said they intended to return to normal police staffing levels on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Gov. Gary Locke of Washington said that he had already ordered more state police staffing for the Sept. 11 ceremonies before the federal government ratcheted up its threat assessment. He said he planned to return duty rosters to normal on Thursday or Friday.</p>
        <p>''No one can guarantee there won't be an attack in their own community at some point,'' Mr. Locke said. ''But if there is, we're much better prepared to prevent or respond to such an attack than we were before Sept. 11.''</p>
        <p>VIGILANCE AND MEMORY: THE ALERT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
