<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classical Music in Review</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="600488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND CONSERVATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAVENER, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, MICHAEL TILSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D7103DF935A35757C0A965958260" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classical Music in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'The Piatigorsky Legacy'  Michael Tilson Thomas Conductor Carnegie Hall</p>
        <p>There were just a few moments Friday night when the program, titled "The Piatigorsky Legacy," earned its name. One was the showing of an unidentified film fragment from 1949, showing the great cellist playing Schubert. The performance was theatrical yet without sentiment or artifice, combining a thrilling muscularity with an almost unassuming intelligence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'The Piatigorsky Legacy'  Michael Tilson Thomas Conductor Carnegie Hall</p>
        <p>There were just a few moments Friday night when the program, titled "The Piatigorsky Legacy," earned its name. One was the showing of an unidentified film fragment from 1949, showing the great cellist playing Schubert. The performance was theatrical yet without sentiment or artifice, combining a thrilling muscularity with an almost unassuming intelligence.</p>
        <p>The other moments were when the conductor Michael Tilson Thomas and Laurence Lesser, the president of the New England Conservatory, offered some recollections of the cellist. Jacqueline de Rothschild Piatigorsky, the cellist's widow, then presented Steven Isserlis with the 1993 New England Conservatory/Piatigorsky Award. Given every three years by the conservatory to a cellist under 35, the award includes $10,000 and concert engagements.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, this was a peculiar program. Neither Mr. Thomas's conducting of the conservatory's student orchestra in Stravinsky's "Firebird," nor the New York premiere of John Tavener's much-acclaimed work "The Protecting Veil," with Mr. Isserlis as soloist, had much to do with Piatigorsky, his temperament or his legacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tavener, an intriguing composer, can sometimes seem like an English version of Arvo Part; he is a convert to Russian Orthodoxy and disdains the secular path that Western music has often taken. This is a deliberately archaic work, based on a 10th-century appearance of the Virgin at a church in Constantinople. It attempts to create an almost static world of faith and devotion, evoked through unearthly melodic lines and slowly shifting sustained chords. The music, scored for string orchestra with a solo cello, is programmatic, meant to illustrate events in the Virgin's life. Interrupting the meditative texture is the striking of dissonant bells, signs of earthly trials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Isserlis is a master of the cello part, which he has recorded on a best-selling Virgin release: its high-lying tessitura created a ghostly aura, evocative of something insubstantial, haunting but comforting as well. During the opening pages of the score, in fact, the chantlike lines and sense of mystery in the music portend something astonishing. The popularity of this work has some relation to the frequent repetition of the opening section's elemental motifs and contrasts.</p>
        <p>For this listener, though, the music seems both too much and not enough. Mr. Tavener, who has said that he wished to construct an icon in sound, does not provide enough musical material to warrant the contemplation an icon might inspire; repetition is not sufficient. The 45-minute work seemed always on the verge of promising much more, teasing with its implied narrative that was not delivered. Without the suspension of time, time makes demands: everything that was said could have been said more briefly. This icon inspired as much frustration as fascination. I certainly can't imagine Piatigorsky responding to it.</p>
        <p>But he might have been pleased with the fervor Mr. Thomas brought to Stravinsky's "Firebird" (conducted without a score) and the "Imaginary Coney Island Scene" from Bernstein's "On the Town." Many refined details were coaxed from the student orchestra; despite some drift and preciousness, Mr. Thomas and the players honored the cellist's memory with earnest enthusiasm.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
