<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Birdmen of Royal St. George's Ravage Par</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="621863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRITISH OPEN (GOLF)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAZ, JAIME</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D81631F935A25754C0A965958260" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Birdmen of Royal St. George's Ravage Par</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAIME DIAZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAZ, JAIME</byline>
      <dateline>SANDWICH, England, July 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With its flinty linksland softened into a verdant dartboard, Royal St. George's fairways were plundered like so many aisles in a supermarket sweep today as players stocked up on birdies in the first round of the 122d British Open.</p>
        <p>Leading the raid were two Australians, 1986 champion Greg Norman and Peter Senior, and two Americans, Mark Calcavecchia and Fuzzy Zoeller, all of whom shot four-under par 66's on the usually diabolical 6,860-yard par-70 layout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With its flinty linksland softened into a verdant dartboard, Royal St. George's fairways were plundered like so many aisles in a supermarket sweep today as players stocked up on birdies in the first round of the 122d British Open.</p>
        <p>Leading the raid were two Australians, 1986 champion Greg Norman and Peter Senior, and two Americans, Mark Calcavecchia and Fuzzy Zoeller, all of whom shot four-under par 66's on the usually diabolical 6,860-yard par-70 layout.</p>
        <p>The quartet represented only the tip of an iceberg of red numbers, as no fewer than 49 players among the starting field of 156 broke par, including Bernhard Langer at 67; Nick Price, Fred Couples and Seve Ballesteros at 68; and defending champion Nick Faldo and Jack Nicklaus at 69. Damp and Incongruous</p>
        <p>Given all the fire-breathers St. George's had slain the last two times the Open was held here, the figures injected a thick layer of incongruity into the damp air. In 1981, only one player, little known Nick Job, equalled par in the first round. And in 1985, no one finished four rounds under par.</p>
        <p>But the 106-year-old course was bone dry in those events, and heavy winds whipping off the Straits of Dover made keeping the ball in the bumpy fairways or on the humpbacked greens problematic.</p>
        <p>The course played that way in this year's practice rounds, but heavy rain pelted the course on Wednesday, and a foggy mist kept the soaked turf from drying today. Licking their chops, players quickly abandoned all the tricky run-up shots they had been practicing and began a vigorous aerial attack on the pins.</p>
        <p>"I walked around here Tuesday and my spikes wouldn't even go into the ground, that's how hard it seemed," said Nicklaus, who had his best opening round in a British Open since 1977. "But the rain really softened it up. I'm color-blind, and even I can see the grass has turned from brown to green."</p>
        <p>Even with a strong afternoon wind, St. George's turned into a tepid test, as only 15 players shot worse than a four-over-par 74. Zoeller spoke for the most of the field when he said: "It was a very enjoyable day at the links."</p>
        <p>For all the bunching, it is the British Open's particular habit to get formidable players at the top of the leader board, and this was no exception.</p>
        <p>Norman has been having one of the most consistent seasons of his career, and is coming off a second place finish two weeks ago at the Western Open. But he has not been a factor in a major championship since 1990, in part because of a disturbing pattern of poor opening rounds. So when he double-bogeyed St. George's 441-yard par-4 first hole today, he took a moment to calm himself.</p>
        <p>"I said to myself, 'There are 71 holes to go, so be patient,' " said Norman. "I just focused on getting back to even par." Four More Birdies</p>
        <p>By the fifth hole, he was. He played steadily until the 443-yard 13th, where he made an 18-footer for a birdie to get to even par again. Quickly, four more birdies followed, beginning with a wedge chip-in from 45 feet on the par-5 14th and ending with a 5-footer on the par-4 17th. Norman closed out his round by making a 15-footer for a par at the 468-yard final hole.</p>
        <p>"You have to guess a lot around here, but if you get into the right zone you get a feel," said the 37-year-old Norman. "I played well today but I try to play it down as much as I can. You must keep calm inside."</p>
        <p>Ironically, the other three co-leaders all have the distinction of having beaten Norman in playoffs: Zoeller at the 1984 United States Open, Calcavecchia at the 1989 British Open at Troon and Senior at the 1991 Australian Masters.</p>
        <p>Calcavecchia, 33, has not attained the star status that was predicted for him after Troon, winning only once since. 'I Still Have Dreams'</p>
        <p>"Maybe my brain did not allow me to be that way," he said today. "I might have gotten satisfied with what I had. I still have dreams. I want to win majors. It's just not easy."</p>
        <p>But in the first round Calcavecchia took inspiration from one of his playing partners, the insular Faldo.</p>
        <p>"Nick does not play to have converstions and I don't worry about that," said Calcavecchia. "He is the best. He is a lot I would like to be more of. Very smart, very consistent, very brave, a gutsy player. Maybe I concentrate more when I am playing with Nick."</p>
        <p>Senior, 33, would be the most surprising winner among the first-round leaders. Although he has won tournaments this year in Australia and Japan, the resident of Brisbane, Australia, had not finished better than 29th in a European event this year until last week's Scottish Open. But at Gleneagles, Senior got hot on the greens with his overlength putter to close with a 65 that put him 13th.</p>
        <p>"My form had not been too good coming in, but for some reason these events lift you a little higher," said Senior, whose best finish in a major championship was a tie for sixth in the 1988 British Open.</p>
        <p>Amid all this introspection, Zoeller, 41, provided the light entertainment. When he entered the interview room and saw the 53-year-old Nicklaus, he piped: "I can only hope I live that long." Nicklaus came right back: "If you continue to live the way you've been living, you'll be lucky."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Zoeller has been without a PGA Tour victory since 1986, with most of his problems stemming from chronic back pain. But he is the winner of two major championships (the Masters in 1979 and the United States Open in 1984), and the British Open would give him a third major title.</p>
        <p>Zoeller likes the challenge of St. George's, and is anxious to see it return to its ornery self. "Normally at St. George's, you don't have to make birdies," he said. "Sometimes, bogey is a good score."  GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
