<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tougher Standards Urged For Federal Education Law</title>
    <meta content="14child" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/14/education/14child.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1826099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2D9163EF937A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tougher Standards Urged For Federal Education Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tougher Standards Urged for Federal Education Law</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Private bipartisan commission on No Child Left Behind law urges that measure be toughened to judge teachers and principals by students' test scores; says it should block chronically ineffective educators from working in high-poverty schools; Congress is preparing to consider renewal of law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No Child Left Behind, the federal education law, should be toughened to judge teachers and principals by their students' test scores, and to block chronically ineffective educators from working in high-poverty schools, a private bipartisan commission recommended on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The recommendations were in a report released here by the Commission on No Child Left Behind, a 15-member group led by former Gov. Roy E. Barnes of Georgia and Tommy Thompson, the former secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services, and financed by private foundations. The report is meant to be a blueprint for Congress as it prepares to consider renewal of the law, President Bush's signature education initiative, later this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A private bipartisan commission recommended to block chronically ineffective educators from working in high-poverty schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No Child Left Behind, the federal education law, should be toughened to judge teachers and principals by their students' test scores, and to block chronically ineffective educators from working in high-poverty schools, a private bipartisan commission recommended on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The recommendations were in a report released here by the Commission on No Child Left Behind, a 15-member group led by former Gov. Roy E. Barnes of Georgia and Tommy Thompson, the former secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services, and financed by private foundations. The report is meant to be a blueprint for Congress as it prepares to consider renewal of the law, President Bush's signature education initiative, later this year.</p>
        <p>The commission also proposed that states revamp their testing systems to track individual student progress from year to year, and to give schools credit if students are within sight of achievement targets, rather than only if they reach them.</p>
        <p>The report drew praise from the leaders of the Congressional education committees and the administration, but it was immediately attacked by the teachers' unions and others.</p>
        <p>Edward J. McElroy, president of the American Federation of Teachers, said there were no reliable assessment systems to tie student achievement to teacher performance. Currently the law calls for low-income schools to have ''highly qualified'' teachers, with degrees in the subjects they are teaching. The proposals would ratchet up that criteria.</p>
        <p>''The highly qualified measure was only just introduced, and we're just coming to terms with that,'' Mr. McElroy said. ''To add another hoop at this point in time just demoralizes people. It's the opposite of what you'd want to do if you want the system to work.''</p>
        <p>Joel Packer, a lobbyist for the National Education Association, the nation's largest teachers' union, also criticized the proposals, saying factors outside of school affect how children fare academically.</p>
        <p>Monty Neill, executive director of the National Center for Fair and Open Testing, which is skeptical of standardized exams, said the recommendations ''will only intensify teaching to the test.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference to release the report, Mr. Barnes said, ''We believe our recommendations will help improve academic achievement for our nation's students and, most importantly, quicken the closing of the achievement gap.''</p>
        <p>The chairmen and ranking members of the House and Senate education committees promised that the recommendations would be part of the debate over renewing the law. That set this report apart from the flurry of proposals on updating No Child Left Behind coming out in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>''I believe so many of their recommendations are going to see light,'' said Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, and the chairman of the education committee.</p>
        <p>Margaret Spellings, the education secretary, said in a statement that the recommendations ''recognize the solid foundation built by N.C.L.B. and reaffirm the law's core principles.''</p>
        <p>No Child Left Behind, enacted in early 2002, demands that all schools test students annually in reading and math, and break down the results by ethnic, racial and income groups. Schools where too few students reach state-established targets for proficiency face penalties, ranging from paying for private tutoring to reopening the school under new management.</p>
        <p>That number would surely grow with the commission's recommendations, which were largely aimed at raising standards and closing loopholes in the law.</p>
        <p>For example, the commission said the law should require more uniformity in how states report student performance. Each state now chooses the minimum number of students who must be present for a school to report on test results by ethnic and other groups. Some states set the bar so high that they largely sidestep the law's full scrutiny. Texas, for example, sets the minimum at 200 students, while Maryland, at the other end, sets it at 5.</p>
        <p>Citing broad variations in achievement standards between states, the commission also recommended that states adopt a national standard of achievement, pegged to the National Assessment of Educational Progress.</p>
        <p>Its report compared the way in many states, students considered proficient in reading on the state tests were not considered proficient on the National Assessment. In Mississippi, for example, the state test found that 87 percent of fourth graders were proficient in reading. According to the national test, only 18 percent were.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
