<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Principal Who Left New York Will Return, to a Private School</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DALTON SCHOOL (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILL, NAOMI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD1F3EF934A15751C0A964958260" item-length="345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Principal Who Left New York Will Return, to a Private School</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Naomi Hill, a New York City school principal who took early retirement in June and joined the school system in Tenafly, N.J., will return to Manhattan in July as director of the Dalton School program for students in kindergarten through third grade.</p>
        <p>She decided on her second move in a year, Mrs. Hill said yesterday, because Dalton had recruited her just as New Jersey rejected her petition for certification as a principal for "the second or third time."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Naomi Hill, a New York City school principal who took early retirement in June and joined the school system in Tenafly, N.J., will return to Manhattan in July as director of the Dalton School program for students in kindergarten through third grade.</p>
        <p>She decided on her second move in a year, Mrs. Hill said yesterday, because Dalton had recruited her just as New Jersey rejected her petition for certification as a principal for "the second or third time."</p>
        <p>"It's been very discouraging after all my years as a principal," Mrs. Hill said, "to face having to take law and finance courses in order to get certification."</p>
        <p>That issue, combined with news that the Tenafly School Superintendent, Gerald DeGrow, would leave in June, prompted her to consider moving to Dalton, she said, adding: "If it weren't for those factors, I would never consider leaving. I like it here."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hill started at Malcolm Mackay School in Tenafly in July after having worked 11 years as principal of Public School 87 on the Upper West Side of Manhattan and 35 years in the schools in the city. She attracted widespread attention for turning P.S. 87 into a model of academic diversity and innovation, and her departure was seen by many people as a blow to the school system.</p>
        <p>In an interview with The New York Times in the first week in February and in conversations on Feb. 13 and 14 for an article on Feb. 15, Mrs. Hill said that she was happy in Tenafly. In response to a question, she said she had not begun to institute curriculum changes because she wanted to earn the trust of her new district first.</p>
        <p>She made no mention of the contract she had signed with Dalton, she said yesterday, because Mr. DeGrow had asked her not to mention it. In an interview on Tuesday, Mrs. Hill said she had not made a final decision on the Dalton offer and had not mentioned her negotiations with the school in the first week of Feburary because the talks were just beginning.</p>
        <p>The Dalton headmaster, Gardner Dunnan, said Mrs. Hill signed the contract with the school about a month ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
