<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Suffolk Heavyweights Square Off in Court</title>
    <meta content="11SUFF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1276960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheriffs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mahoney, Patrick (Sheriff)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Catterson, James M Jr (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DA1F3BF932A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Suffolk Heavyweights Square Off in Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming trial of Sheriff Patrick Mahoney of Suffolk County, NY, who has been acused of misconduct, fraud and corruption charges in connection with campaign finance abuses; Mahoney and others contend his chief accuser, District Attorney James Catterson Jr, should stand trial or be removed from office for abusing his power; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN its long and sometimes sordid history, Suffolk County has witnessed its share of high-profile feuding and fighting among its top officials. One of the bitterest battles is scheduled to spill over into a courtroom in Central Islip on Monday.</p>
        <p>That's when the Suffolk County sheriff, Patrick A. Mahoney, will go on trial on misconduct, fraud and corruption charges that could send him to jail for four years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN its long and sometimes sordid history, Suffolk County has witnessed its share of high-profile feuding and fighting among its top officials. One of the bitterest battles is scheduled to spill over into a courtroom in Central Islip on Monday.</p>
        <p>That's when the Suffolk County sheriff, Patrick A. Mahoney, will go on trial on misconduct, fraud and corruption charges that could send him to jail for four years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney says the authorities have the wrong man. He says it is his chief accuser, District Attorney James M. Catterson Jr., who really must be brought to justice. And in this opinion Mr. Mahoney is not alone. Over the years, there have been officials, lawyers and probably a few judges in Suffolk County who wanted nothing more than for Mr. Catterson to stand trial or be removed from office for abusing his powers as chief prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catterson and prosecutors are letting the indictment talk for them. It depicts a flagrant, years-long pattern of abuse by Mr. Mahoney.</p>
        <p>The 90-count indictment, returned in June by a grand jury that heard more than 130 witnesses over 15 months, charges that Mr. Mahoney, in concert with former Undersheriff Edward J. Morris, ran his election campaigns out of the sheriff's office, using on-duty county workers as his campaign staff and squeezing subordinates for contributions in exchange for good job assignments and promotions.</p>
        <p>The indictment said that in one instance in 1994, Mr. Morris told union officials to contribute $30,000 to the Mahoney campaign in return for better labor relations.</p>
        <p>William J. Maggi, president of the 714-member Suffolk County Correctional Officers Association, said the pressure for officers to contribute to Mr. Mahoney's campaigns was ''the worst-kept secret in the world'' and began almost as soon as Mr. Mahoney was elected. He said Mr. Morris was the conduit.</p>
        <p>''We were told it was a two-way street, you scratch my back I scratch yours, and that it was a show of loyalty,'' Mr. Maggi said. ''It was the perception among the majority of members that giving was the way to move ahead.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maggi said officers also received political flyers and invitations to Mahoney fundraisers that were mailed to their homes. ''It made you uncomfortable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he said it was ''hard to say'' whether officers who declined to contribute suffered as a result.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney, 58, a former police detective and county legislator first elected sheriff in 1990, said he and Mr. Morris never put pressure on anyone to contribute.</p>
        <p>''It's absolute rubbish,'' he said. ''Anyone who testifies that they have been forced to make donations to our campaigns for better jobs or better positions is an outright liar.''</p>
        <p>Among those who know the county and its ways, there were murmurings that Mr. Mahoney may have only followed common practice in a ''pay-to-play'' environment, and that Mr. Catterson had selectively cracked down on what was, after all, just another hand in the cookie jar.</p>
        <p>Jury selection begins on Monday, with state Supreme Court Justice Richard Buchter, who normally works in Queens, presiding as part of an effort to avoid any suggestion of judicial bias.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney has cast himself as the victim of what he called ludicrous charges trumped up by an out-of-control district attorney relentlessly bent on payback, but so powerful and vindictive that none dared try to stop him.</p>
        <p>''Everybody in county government is in fear of this man,'' Mr. Mahoney said in an interview last week. ''They all know what he is. The man is psychotic. It's frightening that he can get away with this kind of terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Catterson, 70, who is seeking election to a fourth four-year term, has said that the notion of a feud between the two men is all in Mr. Mahoney's mind. He declined through a spokesman, Drew Biondo, to comment further in view of the pending trial.</p>
        <p>In announcing the indictments in June, Mr. Catterson said in a statement that he was ''deeply saddened'' to bring such charges against a law enforcement official. ''It is a very unpleasant chore and I am sorely burdened by it,'' he said. But, he said, he believed very strongly that ''one of my duties is to protect decent government workers from intimidation by any superior.''</p>
        <p>It is Mr. Catterson who is often accused of being the intimidator. In the early 1990's, five top county officials, including Mr. Mahoney and other prominent Republicans, said Mr. Catterson had threatened during the course of various disputes to bring them in front of grand juries.</p>
        <p>One dispute involved an investigation by the county Legislature into a county car-leasing deal that Mr. Catterson's son, James M. Catterson, then an assistant county attorney, had played a leading role in negotiating. Donald R. Blydenburgh, then the presiding officer of the county Legislature, said at the time that the senior Mr. Catterson told him to drop the car-lease investigation or be hauled before a grand jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney said Mr. Catterson made a similar threat during their first public dispute: the 1993 case of Katie Beers, a 10-year-old who survived 16 days of imprisonment by a pedophile in an underground chamber in Bay Shore in a story that drew national attention. Each man accused the other of trying to invade Miss Beers's privacy by arranging a press photo opportunity of the child reuniting with her mother. Mr. Catterson has said he was particularly irked by the charge and had gone to extraordinary lengths to protect the child.</p>
        <p>In 1995, a state report noted that Mr. Catterson conceded he might have lost his temper with some of the officials and mentioned subpoenas and grand jury investigations, but concluded that there was insufficient evidence to warrant criminal action against Mr. Catterson or his removal from office.</p>
        <p>Charges that Mr. Catterson continues to use intimidation are still being voiced.</p>
        <p>''He goes after anyone who chooses to disagree with him,'' said Richard H. Schaffer, the supervisor of Babylon and the Democratic Party leader in Suffolk. ''He is a bully and a thug, and he has proven it time and time again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaffer said Mr. Catterson brought politically motivated improper filing and corruption charges against Democratic town officials in Babylon in 1997. The crackdown produced one misdemeanor conviction, but one official had $150,000 in legal expenses, he said.</p>
        <p>''He can ruin you financially and bankrupt you emotionally,'' Mr. Schaffer said.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Spota, a lawyer and former county prosecutor who is the first Democrat to declare his candidacy for district attorney, said Mr. Catterson had ''a penchant for criminalizing political differences'' and ran his office ''with a political, self-serving agenda that seeks to intimidate, threaten and even indict political opponents.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Biondo, Mr. Catterson's spokesman, said Mr. Catterson was ''a highly respected and nationally recognized crime fighter'' who had ''presided over the largest decrease in crime in Suffolk County's history.''</p>
        <p>''Mr. Spota is one more political turncoat former Republican like Mike Forbes, switching parties to promote their own political ambitions,'' he said. Michael P. Forbes is the former congressman who lost a Democratic primary in the First Congressional District last year after switching from the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney, a longtime Republican, also switched his enrollment to Democrat to run unsuccessfully in 1999 against the Republican incumbent, Robert J. Gaffney, for Suffolk County executive.</p>
        <p>The combative Mr. Mahoney, who said he faces $150,000 in legal expenses and weeks in the courtroom as his trial unfolds, has sought to turn the tables on Mr. Catterson.</p>
        <p>In a letter dated Feb. 13 to Governor Pataki, Mr. Mahoney said that Mr. Catterson had committed illegal acts including ''soliciting and encouraging perjured testimony by witnesses in the grand jury'' that returned the 90-count indictment against him and Mr. Morris, who resigned as undersheriff in 1999 and is currently the executive director of the Suffolk County Sports Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>The sheriff also said Mr. Biondo seemed to be engaging in political campaigning on county time. ''He is an employee of the district attorney and he's also running Catterson's campaign out of the D.A.'s office as we speak,'' he said. ''When does one stop and the other begin?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Biondo responded: ''I am not running Mr. Catterson's campaign. I am merely a spokesman for his office, and Mr. Mahoney is really, really reaching.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney also said that his own investigation, carried out with legal authority he had as sheriff, showed that Mr. Catterson made false filings on ownership of the Printer's Devil, a pub in Port Jefferson whose ownership Mr. Catterson said he turned over to his wife upon assuming the office of district attorney in 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney said his investigation showed that Mr. Catterson had subsequently filed papers with the state Liquor Authority listing himself as owner, while in disclosures to the Suffolk County's Ethics Commission he said he had divested ownership.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the state Division of Alcoholic Beverage Control in June 1997, Mr. Catterson acknowledged that in 1990, ''in the rush to close out my private law practice and prepare to assume my new responsibility'' as district attorney, he failed to file for approval of the ownership change. His office described it as a minor oversight that had been rectified.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biondo said that on the eve of his trial, Mr. Mahoney ''now publicly states he used Suffolk County investigators to prepare a criminal defense by investigating the district attorney.''</p>
        <p>''This appalling misuse and abuse of public employees is only the latest of a series of bizarre acts the defendant has exhibited,'' Mr. Biondo said.</p>
        <p>While the upcoming trial is riveting attention within the sheriff's department and the district attorney's office, elsewhere it has brought world-weary shrugs and embarrassment.</p>
        <p>''Suffolk County politics has been rotten and continues to be rotten and everybody in the state knows it,'' said Robert C. Gottlieb, a criminal defense lawyer in Commack who ran as a Democratic candidate against Mr. Catterson in 1989. ''There is nothing unique about this that puts any greater blemish on Suffolk County than is already there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottlieb said the trial ''certainly will give people a bird's-eye view of what goes on with public officials, Republicans and Democrats alike.''</p>
        <p>''Historically, in Suffolk County public officials of both parties have been willing to use their offices in ways to perpetuate themselves in office,'' he said. But he added that arguing that others did the same thing would be no benefit to Mr. Mahoney in the courtroom.</p>
        <p>Arthur J. Kremer, a lawyer in Uniondale and a political commentator, said prosecutors may face a challenge. ''These cases of using employees in elections generally become very hard to prove,'' he said. ''Generally the candidates get a lot of leeway.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney showed no sign he would plead guilty to lesser charges. ''I know that I haven't done anything wrong,'' he said. ''There are times in an individual's life that he has to put him or herself in harm's way.''</p>
        <p>But he said he was dismayed by a lack of support. ''I expected a little bit more in the way of support not only from our elected officials but from people sworn to uphold the law,'' he said. ''And there has been nothing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
