<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shouts and Scuffles at White Supremacy Rally</title>
    <meta content="11WALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/11/nyregion/11WALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1277203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wallingford (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Church of the Creator</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hale, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Akron</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ohio</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bridgeport</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Church</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Town Library</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Assembly</org>
        <org class="online_producer">church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D7123AF932A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shouts and Scuffles at White Supremacy Rally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>WALLINGFORD, Conn., March 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Hale, national leader of World Church of the Creator, speaks at meeting of white supremacists at Wallingford, Conn, Town Library; police use pepper spray to repel protesters, but demonstration ends peacefully with only one arrest; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As could be expected from a well-publicized meeting of white supremacists in a town known for its history of racial conflict, there was hate, there were fistfights, there were police officers and there were protesters. There was even a bloody lip or two.</p>
        <p>But in the end, aside from a brief melee between pepper-spraying police officers and a few anti-racist demonstrators, the latest flourish of a few white-power advocates here ended rather peacefully, with one arrest and no major injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As could be expected from a well-publicized meeting of white supremacists in a town known for its history of racial conflict, there was hate, there were fistfights, there were police officers and there were protesters. There was even a bloody lip or two.</p>
        <p>But in the end, aside from a brief melee between pepper-spraying police officers and a few anti-racist demonstrators, the latest flourish of a few white-power advocates here ended rather peacefully, with one arrest and no major injuries.</p>
        <p>Today's encounter was the culmination of a weeks-long plan by a local racist group to present a speech by Matt Hale, the national leader of the World Church of the Creator, which claims to be one of the most popular white supremacist groups in the United States. After news spread that the Wallingford Town Library had allowed the group and Mr. Hale to reserve a meeting space, a counterdemonstration was organized and today's battle lines were drawn.</p>
        <p>''We have good support in Wallingford,'' said Kenneth A. Molyneaux, 23, who said he drove nine hours from Akron, Ohio, to help organize Mr. Hale's visit. Mr. Molyneaux said Mr. Hale chose Wallingford after hearing about the controversy last year surrounding the mayor's refusal to grant city workers a paid holiday for the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday.</p>
        <p>''It shows that Wallingford is fertile ground for our ideas,'' Mr. Molyneaux said, as a bank of skinheads began scuffling with a larger crowd of mostly white college-aged objectors. ''We can do things in a polite civil way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The dispute over Dr. King's birthday, which drew a visit from the Rev. Jesse Jackson, ended after Connecticut's General Assembly passed, and Gov. John G. Rowland signed, a bill that required all cities and towns to recognize Dr. King's birthday with a holiday. The bill was aimed at Wallingford, which had been the only municipality of Connecticut's 169 towns and cities that did not recognize the holiday with a paid day off.</p>
        <p>But legislation was unlikely to prevent today's kind of conflict, in which a handful of young white men wearing black jackets and clean-shaven heads were drawn into repeated shouting matches, and a few fights, with a much larger crowd of about 50 mostly white, young self-described left-wing opponents of racism.</p>
        <p>About two dozen police officers in full riot gear from Wallingford and the Connecticut State Police looked on as the competing groups hurled insults and a few snowballs at each other.</p>
        <p>''He's profiting off your ignorance.  How does that feel?'' Matt Flood, a  graduate student at Sacred Heart University in Bridgeport, shouted at the skinheads. ''He's exploiting you.''</p>
        <p>At 2 p.m., Mr. Molyneaux and a retinue of young white men with shaved heads, many dressed from neck to toe in black, were allowed past a barricade of Wallingford police officers gripping batons. Minutes later, the police repelled a wall of advancing protesters, many of them also clad in black with camouflage bandannas over their faces, with squirts of pepper spray that left many young men and women gasping and searching for snow to cake on their stinging eyes.</p>
        <p>Shortly thereafter, about a dozen black men, women and children, who had been attending a church service down the street to discuss Mr. Hale's presence today, filed into the library to attend his speech. But the children and two of the women left minutes later.</p>
        <p>Indeed, inside the library's community room, Mr. Hale's voice was repeatedly drowned out by chants of ''Go home'' from a dozen or so people in attendance. Mr. Hale, whose two-hour speech attacked everything from what he called the United States Border Patrol's coddling of  illegal immigrants to the characterizations of his movement by the ''Jewish-controlled press,'' seemed flustered, even after he began using a bullhorn to address the 40 or so  supporters seated before him.</p>
        <p>''The idea of racial equality is one of the most absurd ever created in this world,'' said Mr. Hale.</p>
        <p>''We didn't oppress other races,'' he said. ''The blacks sold themselves into slavery. All over Africa, white countries had to tell them to stop enslaving blacks. We must understand history.''</p>
        <p>At 4 p.m., the Wallingford police told Mr. Hale his allotted time was up and hustled him out a side door and into a patrol car, which was  briefly blocked by protesters.</p>
        <p>Police Lt. Thomas Curran said one person was arrested for disorderly conduct inside the community room, and the police, who searched everyone with hand-held metal detectors, had temporarily confiscated a loaded and licensed .357 Magnum handgun and ''an assortment of knives.''</p>
        <p>''I think it went extraordinarily well,'' Lieutenant Curran said as the meeting ended. ''The crowd got a little angry, but it wasn't anything we couldn't control.''</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Hale left and most of his followers were told to leave the library parking lot, the police, lined up in attack formation, pushed into a band of protesters, firing blasts of pepper spray and poking their batons at anyone who moved too slowly. Five police dogs were also at the ready.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
