<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Instincts Give Rise To the 'Little Intimidator'</title>
    <meta content="11LIPS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/11/sports/11LIPS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="A YEAR AT SPEED: Following His Father Behind the Wheel" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1277171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Daytona Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Apopka</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Daytona Beach</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Smyrna</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hollywood</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Quaker Oats Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Mark</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1DC123AF932A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Instincts Give Rise To the 'Little Intimidator'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>NEW SMYRNA BEACH, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eighth article in series A Year at Speed discusses racing circuit for youngsters, ages 5-13, who drive small fiberglass racers equipped with 2.4-4 hp engines that can reach speeds of almost 40 mph; says it is training ground for Nascar; follows 9-year-old Matt Martin, son of racer Mike Martin, who has been racing for two years; comments from family; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Little Intimidator, as his grandmother calls him, lost concentration in the middle of his first race of the night, and an older, more experienced driver bumped him out of the way and took the lead. But not for long. The Little Intimidator, as his father put it, ''just doesn't give,'' and his red No. 6 Cap'n Crunch car seemed to snort and buck as he bumped right back, regained the lead and swept to victory.</p>
        <p>Then the Little Intimidator, better known in the third grade as Matt Martin, pulled off his helmet, climbed out of his quarter-midget car, and ran off to play with his friends. He had plenty of time before his next race. Who wants to sit around watching the pit crew change tires and tweak engines when you are 9 years old?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Little Intimidator, as his grandmother calls him, lost concentration in the middle of his first race of the night, and an older, more experienced driver bumped him out of the way and took the lead. But not for long. The Little Intimidator, as his father put it, ''just doesn't give,'' and his red No. 6 Cap'n Crunch car seemed to snort and buck as he bumped right back, regained the lead and swept to victory.</p>
        <p>Then the Little Intimidator, better known in the third grade as Matt Martin, pulled off his helmet, climbed out of his quarter-midget car, and ran off to play with his friends. He had plenty of time before his next race. Who wants to sit around watching the pit crew change tires and tweak engines when you are 9 years old?</p>
        <p>''He's aggressive and you can't teach that,'' said his father, Mark Martin, the 42-year-old Nascar star. ''Matt's like Dale Earnhardt that way. With Earnhardt, if you stood up to him, you'd wreck. But they're pretty careful at this level. They won't let you spin people out.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to tell Matt to drive differently, not now while he's fearless. Time enough after he gets his heart broken a few times, he'll learn to have better judgment.''</p>
        <p>Matt is one of an estimated 4,000 American youngsters ages 5-13 driving the little fiberglass racers with their 2.5- to 4-horsepower engines that can reach speeds of almost 40 miles an hour. Some of them go on to race late-model cars at 14, modified pickup trucks at 16, Winston Cup at 18, or even Indy cars and Formula One. This may be the future of American auto racing in the same way that Little League became the Head Start program for American-born baseball players. Such Nascar headliners as Jeff Gordon, Tony Stewart and the Labonte brothers, Terry and Bobby, the defending Winston Cup champion, started out strapped into these snarling machines, caged by padded roll bars, supported by pit parents.</p>
        <p>''It's the biggest family sport you will see,'' said Bonnie Henry, the self-described ''pit mom'' of 12-year-old Kevin and the wife of Kim, Matt's full-time crew chief. ''I call football and baseball the 'drop-off sports,' because parents leave their kids at the field and drive away.</p>
        <p>''We know where our kids are and who they're with because we're here, too,'' Henry said. ''They learn sportsmanship and valuable morals. We meet other families. The rewards are high.''</p>
        <p>So are the costs: about $5,000 to start and at least several hundred a month for fuel and repairs, not to mention travel and time spent. And you need a one-twentieth of a mile banked track. Until this year, the nearest was in Apopka, an hour from here, open for racing on Friday nights when Mark Martin was off on the big tracks in his No. 6 Viagra Ford. Led by Martin, who lives in nearby Daytona Beach, local parents raised enough money to carve out a midget track in an infield corner of the half-mile New Smyrna Speedway. Not surprisingly, races are on Wednesday nights, when Martin is usually home.</p>
        <p>''After the season was over last November, I started spending time with Matt and his cars,'' Mark Martin said. ''I began to understand how my father, Julian, felt. He worked so hard on my race cars, he was so proud, and I took it for granted.</p>
        <p>''You don't appreciate your parents until you have a child,'' Martin said, ''and then if you do something with your kid that your parents did with you, it really deepens that appreciation.''</p>
        <p>Jackie Martin, who married and divorced Mark's late father twice, said: ''Mark's a better father to Matt than Julian was to Mark. He sets a better example; he's quieter, more patient. Mark was always a very responsible kid who wanted to please his dad -- who would have been a kamikaze if he'd been a driver. Julian would have been so proud of Matt, that little intimidator.''</p>
        <p>Unlike Mark -- a patient and cunning driver willing to let someone go, then catch him napping later -- Matt, who started driving at 7, has a quick jugular instinct for that moment when he can dive under an opponent on a turn and pass.</p>
        <p>''It happened when he was 8, as if a light bulb went on over his head,'' said Matt's mother, Arlene. ''It started as a game. He wasn't that serious, and then suddenly he wanted to do it and he wanted to win every time.''</p>
        <p>Mark said: ''Once that happened, it became my charge to get him the best equipment I can. If he gets beaten by cars faster than his, that's my fault. But once I get his cars in shape, it's his job. He's talented and he's salable.''</p>
        <p>He is salable enough to afford two full-time employees as crew for Matt's Wednesday and Friday night races: 51-year-old Kim Henry, a former electronics engineer, and Henry's 24-year-old son, Shane. They also work on Matt's and other cars in Mark's garage. While most of the youngsters here (the vast majority of whom are buzz-cut white boys) were alone with Dad in the pit area, Matt had the Henry family and his own around his cars before and after the 10- to 20-minute races. But that befits the most bankable non-Hollywood 9-year-old in the country.</p>
        <p>Next summer, pictures of Matt and Mark will appear on 10 million cereal boxes (''Be pretty cool,'' Matt said, in one of his most extensive interviews.) His two quarter-midget cars are sponsored by Quaker Oats brands, Cap'n Crunch and Life. These deals are not Matt's per se; they were spawned by Mark's sponsorship package with Gatorade, another Quaker Oats product, and Dad is characteristically reluctant to discuss specific numbers. Still, Matt was the only midget racer with national signage on his car; other youngsters' cars had advertising, but it was of the local gas station variety.</p>
        <p>Despite the corporate sponsorship and professional crew, Matt was still a 9-year-old, playing hide and seek in the chilly darkness among the vans and haulers and chasing off a 5-year-old girl who wanted an autograph. When his parents asked him to hand out boxes of cereal, he managed to start a food fight. His mother and grandmother did not seem disturbed that he was acting his age.</p>
        <p>''It's no secret, I don't want him to race,'' said Arlene Martin, who has four daughters from a previous marriage. ''And it's not just the safety. It's a demanding, time-consuming, stressful life. Of course, I worry about Mark. But what kind of life can you have, you would be nutty, if you thought about it all the time.''</p>
        <p>Jackie Martin, who works part time in her son's office, said: ''I believe -- and I believe it because I need to believe it -- it's safer on the track than on the interstate. Actually I worry about Matt more than Mark, although I know that in all the years of quarter-midget racing, there has never been worse than a few broken bones.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, organizers in Apopka said that in 40 years of midget racing, a broken rib was the worst injury to young drivers.</p>
        <p>''You get hurt worse falling off a bike,'' Jackie Martin said.</p>
        <p>As if to prove the point, Matt was suddenly crying and holding an ice bag to his right eye. This was no racing injury. He had been accidentally kicked in one of those routine boy pile-ons. The 13-year-old he had narrowly beaten in that early race rolled his eyes at such immaturity and swaggered out to his car. Mark sat Matt down, hugged him and began whispering.</p>
        <p>''This is the point where you have to be a father,'' said Kim Henry, whose own son had won his race. ''You need to push the boy to be just a little more than he thinks he can be, but not so much that he becomes an animal. Mark's going to ask Matt what he wants to do, but he knows the answer because boys want to please Dad.''</p>
        <p>After a few minutes, his eye swollen but open, Matt squared his shoulders and marched off to the red car. Early in the race, four cars tangled, one turning over, and Mark led the dads leaping over the wall and rushing onto the track.</p>
        <p>No one was hurt. Mark pulled Matt out of the car. In a few minutes, Mark and Arlene, with Matt between them, were heading for their car and home. Matt had school in the morning, and Mark, whose Winston Cup season is starting slowly, was flying off in his private jet to Atlanta, where he races Sunday. He will be back in time for the Little Intimidator's comeback.</p>
        <p>The Series So Far</p>
        <p>This is the eighth article in a series following auto racing, its safety, sense of family and popularity. Previous articles were about Nascar's appeal to a crossover audience, the search for the sport's Tiger Woods, a veteran driver's view, how insiders deal with death on the track, and religion under the checkered flag.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
