<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jail Term for Former Penny-Stock Tycoon</title>
    <meta content="27BREN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/27/nyregion/27BREN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1312553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brennan, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Garrett E (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Trenton</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDC153DF934A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jail Term for Former Penny-Stock Tycoon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jail Term for Former Penny-Stock Tycoon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>District Court Judge Garrett E Brown sentences former penny-stock tycoon Robert E Brennan to nine years and two months in federal prison for money-laundering and bankruptcy fraud, Trenton, NJ; also orders Brennan to pay restitution of nearly $4.6 million; sentencing ends only one phase of legal and financial problems awaiting Brennan; case reviewed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After making a tearful apology to his family, friends and officials of the federal bankruptcy court, a once-flamboyant penny-stock tycoon, Robert E. Brennan, was sentenced today to nine years and two months in federal prison for money-laundering and bankruptcy fraud.</p>
        <p>Moments after denouncing Mr. Brennan for committing crimes marked by ''the stench of sophisticated fraud'' and saying he did not deserve leniency, Judge Garrett E. Brown of United States District Court seemed swayed by Mr. Brennan's emotional statement and sentenced him to 11 months less than the maximum term he faced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A once-flamboyant penny-stock tycoon, Robert E. Brennan, was sentenced today to nine years and two months in federal prison for money-laundering and bankruptcy fraud</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After making a tearful apology to his family, friends and officials of the federal bankruptcy court, a once-flamboyant penny-stock tycoon, Robert E. Brennan, was sentenced today to nine years and two months in federal prison for money-laundering and bankruptcy fraud.</p>
        <p>Moments after denouncing Mr. Brennan for committing crimes marked by ''the stench of sophisticated fraud'' and saying he did not deserve leniency, Judge Garrett E. Brown of United States District Court seemed swayed by Mr. Brennan's emotional statement and sentenced him to 11 months less than the maximum term he faced.</p>
        <p>Judge Brown also ordered Mr. Brennan, 57, to pay restitution of nearly $4.6 million -- about $100,000 more than the amount he was convicted last April of fraudulently failing to list on a 1995 federal bankruptcy petition.</p>
        <p>The sentencing ended only one phase of the legal and financial problems awaiting Mr. Brennan.</p>
        <p>He has a contempt proceeding pending in federal court for using $500,000 from funds that a judge had ordered frozen to pay his lawyer, Michael Critchley. A second contempt order has been filed by another federal judge for Mr. Brennan's refusal to return millions from one of his overseas trusts. Since mid-1995, the Securities and Exchange Commission has been trying to collect a $75 million judgment it won against Mr. Brennan for defrauding investors of his brokerage firm, First Jersey Securities, which is defunct. He also owes the State of New Jersey $100 million for defrauding investors in another case.</p>
        <p>The bankruptcy trustee hopes to obtain some of this money through the sales this fall of two lavish projects Mr. Brennan financed in recent years -- Due Process Stables Golf Club in Colts Neck, N.J., where he once lived, and a casino boat, the Palm Beach Princess, in Florida.</p>
        <p>Today's daylong hearing was one full of contrasting images of Mr. Brennan. In a letter, the Securities and Exchange Commission denounced him for ''blatant defiance'' of the nation's securities laws, defrauding investors and committing a ''direct assault'' on the country's securities industry and bankruptcy courts for the last two decades.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Critchley presented his client as one of nine children who grew up in a three-bedroom apartment in Newark and, throughout adolescence and adulthood, was always eager to help his parents and siblings emotionally and financially, in good times and bad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Critchley also pointed out his client's years of philanthropy in New Jersey and his far less publicized willingness to provide money and homes for poor black children. The lawyer appealed to the judge to remember what he called Mr. Brennan's ''quiet good works'' and asked him to impose a 97-month sentence, the minimum called for by federal sentencing guidelines in the case.</p>
        <p>For his part, Judge Brown described Mr. Brennan as persuasive, eloquent and complex, with a personality marked by ''two halves that don't seem to fit.'' The judge said: ''There is a lot of good this man has done. There's also a lot of bad. The bad half is pretty bad.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan called the day gut-wrenching and suggested he had been humbled by the 100 days spent in jail since the day after his conviction on April 16. Upon reflection, he said, he realized he should have changed his life of ''extravagance and extremes'' after filing his bankruptcy petition in August 1995. A week later, he said he was at a racetrack, gambling and entertaining friends. Over that Labor Day weekend, he went to casinos in Las Vegas, a ''horrible decision.''</p>
        <p>He said he has shown disrespect to the bankruptcy court where he sought protection from creditors. ''I'm a high-profile person, and I should have been more sensitive to my obligations and responsibilities,'' he told Judge Brown.</p>
        <p>He called his decision to place millions of dollars in offshore trusts, beyond the reach of creditors, a ''horrible judgment.'' He said he was proud of his charitable works. But then, after noting that his parents had raised him to respect the law, he said he also made decisions that he was ashamed of, particularly those made in his bankruptcy case.</p>
        <p>He also asked his family and friends forgiveness. ''I failed you, the ones I love the most,'' he said, pausing for seconds to fight back tears.</p>
        <p>Moments later, Mr. Brennan, whose lawyer said suffers melanoma, said he has thought about dying in prison. Then, closing his remarks, he said: ''I have a lot of work to do to repair the damage and the hurt I've done. I'm going to do it.''</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, Judge Brown paused and seemed to be thinking aloud about Mr. Brennan's remarks. ''Is Mr. Brennan genuine in his apology?'' he asked. Was he being ''remorseful,'' or ''just eloquent,'' the judge said.</p>
        <p>''Is he going to use his future years in an attempt to help people and not at the same time hurt other people?'' the judge said. ''I don't know. I don't have a crystal ball.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
