<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>England Says No Soccer for Hitler's Birthday</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTHDAYS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HITLER, ADOLF (1889-1945)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birthdays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D71F3FF934A35757C0A962958260" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>England Says No Soccer for Hitler's Birthday</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The English Football Association announced today that it was pulling out of a soccer match with Germany on April 20, saying there was too much danger of violence because the date is Hitler's birth date. The football association also said there was evidence that pro- and anti-Nazi demonstrators were planning to converge in Berlin on the day of the game.</p>
        <p>"For a period of over three months, since this match was moved to Berlin, we have been fully aware of the risks of disorder," Sir Bert Millichip, president of the association, said in announcing the decision in London. "We had hoped that these risks might have receded. Unfortunately, in our opinion, they have not."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The English Football Association announced today that it was pulling out of a soccer match with Germany on April 20, saying there was too much danger of violence because the date is Hitler's birth date. The football association also said there was evidence that pro- and anti-Nazi demonstrators were planning to converge in Berlin on the day of the game.</p>
        <p>"For a period of over three months, since this match was moved to Berlin, we have been fully aware of the risks of disorder," Sir Bert Millichip, president of the association, said in announcing the decision in London. "We had hoped that these risks might have receded. Unfortunately, in our opinion, they have not."</p>
        <p>"I am sure that as soon as there is an acceptable date, another friendly match will be arranged," he added.</p>
        <p>Graham Kelly, chief executive of the association, said members feared that the match would become "a focus for disorder" and "an unnecessary flash point."</p>
        <p>The match was originally to have been held in Hamburg, but the Hamburg police said they could not provide enough security. Berlin officials volunteered to play host for the game, and scheduled it for Olympic Stadium, the city's largest, which was built by Hitler's Government for the 1936 Olympic Games. Sixty-thousand tickets had already been sold.</p>
        <p>Today, German soccer officials were indignant at England's decision to withdraw.</p>
        <p>"It's an outrage," said Otto Johne, head of the Berlin branch of Germany's soccer federation. "We are extremely disappointed and depressed by this decision. It's bad for sport when a tiny minority of extremists succeed like this. They're making April 20 a day of glory for the Nazis again."</p>
        <p>Many prominent Germans had echoed the same view in recent days. They said that canceling the game would implicitly acknowledge Hitler's birthday as a day different from other days.</p>
        <p>"It would be odd to give this date the meaning of a holiday like Christmas," Walter Jens, a writer and professor, said in a televised interview. "I am opposed to letting a mass murderer like Hitler determine when matches can be played and when celebrations can take place."</p>
        <p>Berlin's city government issued a statement saying it regretted the cancellation and understood "the disappointment of everyone" who had looked forward to the game.</p>
        <p>Sepp Maier, a former German soccer star, deplored the decision and said English officials were "playing right into the hands of the hooligans." A former English goalie, Gordon Banks, said the decision "makes me angry because we are bowing down to a minority, a very small minority."</p>
        <p>But the chief executive of the English professional Footballers' Association, Gordon Taylor, praised the decision as "a victory for common sense."</p>
        <p>"It is a sensible and correct decision," Mr. Taylor said. "We had everything to lose and nothing to gain. It is a shame that a major sport should be dictated to like this, but if you are going to choose such an insensitive date, it is inevitable. To consider it in the first place was a gross error of judgment."</p>
        <p>Both pro-Nazi and anti-Nazi groups had appealed to their supporters to come to Berlin on the day of the match.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
