<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Pact, Buses Face Border Barrier</title>
    <meta content="09BUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greyhound Lines Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2D61E39F93AA35752C0A961958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Pact, Buses Face Border Barrier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN R. MYERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>While North American Free Trade Agreement gave United States and Mexican bus lines right to carry passengers across border and throughout each other's lands, Mexican Government requires all bus lines to use central terminals; Mexican position means it is not yet possible to buy Greyhound Lines ticket to cities in Mexico because central terminals there are controlled by Greyhound's Mexican rivals; Greyhound executives say that after several requests, company has not received applications for using those terminals or for starting new routes; American bus operators say Mexican officials are holding them hostage to stalemate over rights trade pact granted Mexican truckers; map of route Greyhound will run between Los Angeles and Ciudad Obredon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Jan. 1, the North American Free Trade Agreement gave United States and Mexican bus lines the right to carry passengers across the border and throughout each other's lands.</p>
        <p>But that does not mean it is possible to buy a Greyhound ticket from, say, Dallas to Monterrey or Mexico City just yet. The Mexican Government requires all bus lines to use central terminals, which are controlled by Greyhound's Mexican rivals. After several months of requests, executives at Greyhound Lines Inc. said, their Dallas-based company has not received the applications for using those terminals or for starting new routes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Jan. 1, the North American Free Trade Agreement gave United States and Mexican bus lines the right to carry passengers across the border and throughout each other's lands.</p>
        <p>But that does not mean it is possible to buy a Greyhound ticket from, say, Dallas to Monterrey or Mexico City just yet. The Mexican Government requires all bus lines to use central terminals, which are controlled by Greyhound's Mexican rivals. After several months of requests, executives at Greyhound Lines Inc. said, their Dallas-based company has not received the applications for using those terminals or for starting new routes.</p>
        <p>Thus the booming market for rides across the border is being dominated by buses and vans widely advertised in Spanish-language newspapers and radio stations, which often appear to operate without a license from either country, Greyhound said.</p>
        <p>The best Greyhound can do in the meantime is to begin a single, once-a-day route on Saturday between Los Angeles and Ciudad Obregon, Mexico, roughly 300 miles south of Tucson, Ariz., through a complicated partnership with a Mexican company that probably could have been arranged without the trade agreement. Greyhound plans to announce the new service on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''The concept of Nafta is, 'Oh, you open the borders and let everybody compete,' '' Craig R. Lentzsch, Greyhound's chief executive, said. ''Nice concept. But out in the real world, it doesn't work that way.''</p>
        <p>American bus operators said that Mexican officials were holding them hostage to a stalemate over the rights the trade pact granted Mexican truckers a year ago to cross the border -- rights that United States officials, with an election year approaching, had refused to put in place.</p>
        <p>In December 1995, the United States won Mexico's agreement to delay putting into effect a provision of the trade pact that opens border states of both countries to trucking, and no effective date is in sight.</p>
        <p>Not that Greyhound was reluctant to press its cause at home. Using the same safety arguments that American trucking companies and unions used to lobby against allowing Mexican trucks to enter the United States, Greyhound and the American Bus Association asked the Government to withhold permission for Mexican buses to operate in the United States.</p>
        <p>But the Administration let the new provisions take effect. The Department of Transportation said that no Mexican bus lines have filed to enter the United States so far, but Greyhound said that some had bought buses that could meet America's tougher safety standards.</p>
        <p>Bill Schulz, a Transportation Department spokesman, would only confirm that negotiations over the trade agreement's implementation were continuing. Officials at the Mexican Embassy in Washington also had no comment.</p>
        <p>When it comes to bus service in Mexico, Greyhound executives said that if anything, they have been losing ground. Greyhound continues to carry passengers just across the California border into the Tijuana, Mexico, terminal, but no farther, under permission granted before the new trade pact. But about two years ago, Mexican bus operators kicked Greyhound out of the terminal in Ciudad Juarez, which is across the Rio Grande from El Paso, and is the biggest Mexican border city.</p>
        <p>For Greyhound, gaining access to Mexico could be critical. As the only coast-to-coast American bus line, struggling to revive itself after years of management chaos and labor turmoil, Greyhound faces a United States market that is at best stagnant. Americans take only about 25 to 30 million bus trips of more than 100 miles a year, which is less than 2 percent of all long-distance travel.</p>
        <p>But Mexicans climb aboard about 250 million times a year, riding buses for about 98 percent of their longer trips. Long-distance travel across the border is growing by about 20 percent a year, Greyhound estimated.</p>
        <p>Greyhound executives want to form enough partnerships with their counterparts to funnel busloads of Mexicans into their American route system. For the 700-mile route beginning on Saturday, Greyhound bought a small United States bus line that will join with a unit of Estrella Blanca, the largest Mexican bus line, to run buses that will display the word ''Crucero,'' or ''Crosser,'' on the sides of the buses.</p>
        <p>Mexicans would drive and manage the buses south of the border, Americans to the north. The round-trip fare, for a 21-hour ride each way, will be $115. The partners agreed to make investments in each other's cross-border units and also to run more frequent service between Los Angeles and Tijuana, Mexico.</p>
        <p>Other Mexican bus lines have balked at forming partnerships, so Greyhound has been seeking permission to travel other Mexican routes alone. The company has also been pressuring the Transportation Department and several states to crack down on unlicensed operations based in both countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
