<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Vows Property Tax Cut and Rise in School Spending</title>
    <meta content="09PATA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">State of the State Message (NYS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB1F39F93AA35752C0A961958260" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Vows Property Tax Cut and Rise in School Spending</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Gov George Pataki, setting an agenda with broad appeal to middle-class and suburban voters in his third annual State of the State Message, vows to cut property taxes while increasing amount of money spent on school textbooks and computers; says he plans to induce school districts around state to freeze and even reduce property taxes and that state would offer schools more money to offset loss of property tax revenue; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Setting an agenda with broad appeal to middle-class and suburban voters, Gov. George E. Pataki today vowed to cut property taxes while increasing the amount of money spent on school textbooks and computers.</p>
        <p>In his third annual address to the Legislature, Mr. Pataki said he had a plan to induce school districts around the state to freeze and even reduce property taxes, though the specifics will have to wait until he releases his proposed budget next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Setting an agenda with broad appeal to middle-class and suburban voters, Gov. George E. Pataki today vowed to cut property taxes while increasing the amount of money spent on school textbooks and computers.</p>
        <p>In his third annual address to the Legislature, Mr. Pataki said he had a plan to induce school districts around the state to freeze and even reduce property taxes, though the specifics will have to wait until he releases his proposed budget next week.</p>
        <p>His aides say the Governor's plan would offer the local districts more state money to make up for the loss of property tax revenue.</p>
        <p>''Property taxes in New York State are too high,'' Mr. Pataki said. ''The budget plan I will release next week will begin a multi year program to stop the continual increase in school taxes, reverse that trend and actually begin to lower these taxes for every homeowner.''</p>
        <p>But the Democrats who control the Assembly were quick to say that until they see the Republican Governor's budget, they will not be convinced that property taxes can be cut without hurting education.</p>
        <p>''I welcome the Governor, his words, in concept,'' said the Assembly Speaker, Sheldon Silver, a Democrat of Manhattan. ''I await the details of his real property tax plan. But I won't accept a shell game.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's 58-minute speech offered several initiatives that fit neatly into potential gaps in his political armor. Indeed, Mr. Silver called it ''a campaign speech'' delivered in preparation for the 1998 governor's race.</p>
        <p>The tax plan could blunt the charge by Democrats in the Legislature that the Governor is to blame for the rapid rise in property taxes in some localities since Mr. Pataki took office.</p>
        <p>They argue that, to accommodate the income tax cuts that Mr. Pataki championed early in his administration, the state has not increased school aid fast enough to keep up with expenses, forcing local districts to raise property taxes.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pataki's message dealt with more than taxes. At a time when Republicans fare far better at the polls among men than women, the Governor appealed to the Legislature for tougher sentences and higher bail in domestic violence cases, and for longer hospital stays for women who have had mastectomies. Last year, the state mandated that new mothers be allowed at least two days in the hospital, not one.</p>
        <p>And, like Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, Mr. Pataki appears determined to make himself appear more friendly to the public schools. Last year, he proposed what he said was a slight increase in education money, but Democrats in the Legislature charged that at a closer look, it was a decrease. School spending was increased in the budget that was eventually enacted.</p>
        <p>The Governor said that this year, he wanted to increase state aid to public schools, which stands at $10.2 billion this year, by $250 million. Much of that money would go toward keeping his promises to double state spending on textbooks, $114 million this year, and triple state spending on classroom computers, now $21 million, over several years. He also said that districts that cut administrative waste would be rewarded, but he did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki spoke at some length about the Internet, calling it ''a powerful and promising tool'' for children.</p>
        <p>''With private help, labor and volunteer support,'' he said, ''let's pledge today that between now and the turn of the century, we will have a computer available for every student in every school. And that every student will know how to tap into its limitless resources.''</p>
        <p>But Louis Grumet, executive director of the New York State School Boards Association, said that he, like Mr. Silver, could not be confident until he saw the budget that the Governor's new tax and spending proposals would mean more aid to schools.</p>
        <p>The Governor is expected to propose a budget keeping state spending at this year's level, about $65 billion, and he must close a gap estimated at $3 billion, so any new state spending on education would have to come out of other programs.</p>
        <p>That could add tension to a legislative session that already promises to be as contentious as last year's, when the budget was passed 102 days late.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki spoke at length on the achievements of the last two years, stating repeatedly that lower taxes and less business regulation had meant job growth in New York, which he and his aides have said is the ultimate measure of his performance.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly cast taxation and big government as enemies not just of prosperity, but also of liberty, saying that his term will be remembered as a time ''when freedom prevailed over bureaucracy.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver charged that the Governor was taking credit that belonged to others for achievements ranging from lower crime to new rights for patients in managed-care programs, and he noted that New York still lags behind the nation as a whole in job growth.</p>
        <p>''While the nation has been riding the train of economic recovery for the last two years,'' Mr. Silver said, ''New York is still waiting at that station.''</p>
        <p>But Senator Joseph L. Bruno of Brunswick, leader of the Senate's Republican majority, said, ''I really think the Governor did a remarkable job in putting together a vision, not just for the next couple of years, but literally to lead us into the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>The Governor urged the Legislature to adopt the proposal he made last year to overhaul welfare programs, which is expected to be one of the most acrimonious issues of the coming session.</p>
        <p>A law passed last year by Congress and signed by President Clinton hands over much of the responsibility for setting welfare policy to the states, while mandating that, with some exceptions, families spend no more than five years on welfare.</p>
        <p>Under the Governor's plan, each year a family remained on welfare, its benefits would shrink, to barely half the starting level in the fifth and final year. Cash payments to able-bodied, childless adults would be replaced with vouchers for food and shelter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki added a new feature today, a program employing welfare recipients to renovate derelict housing, teaching them building trades in the process. He did not say how it would be financed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki made a substantial shift in tone, if not in substance, on welfare, perhaps seeking to deflect charges of meanness from advocates for the poor.</p>
        <p>In the past, he has derided New York's as the ''Cadillac'' of welfare systems, a wasteful burden on society and one that drew people to the state for its generous benefits.</p>
        <p>Today, he said the true victims are welfare recipients. ''The welfare system we are presiding over today is democracy's Berlin Wall,'' he said, separating ''those who are free to pursue and follow opportunities and those who are denied even the chance.''</p>
        <p>Though he looked worn after staying up until 12:30 A.M. rehearsing his address, Mr. Pataki, dressed in his usual plain gray suit with a yellow tie, showed flashes of wit.</p>
        <p>At one point, a state trooper fainted and fell against the Governor as he spoke, and had to be helped from the chamber.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think the speech was that long,'' Mr. Pataki said. It was not clear why the trooper, whose name was not released, collapsed.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Pataki's tax cut proposal drew booming applause and cheers from Republicans on the right side of the Assembly chamber but blank-faced silence from the Democrats on the left, he said, ''It's great to see clapping from both sides.''</p>
        <p>In His Own Words</p>
        <p>GOV. GEORGE E. PATAKI</p>
        <p>''We stand at the edge of a new era, a new century and a new millennium.</p>
        <p>There is only one way to enter this new era. We must go roaring into the next century, bold, confident and determined, accepting every challenge that comes before us.</p>
        <p>When future generations look back at this period in our state's history, they will recall these years as the years when hope prevailed over fear, when confidence prevailed over cynicism, when freedom prevailed over bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>They will know these as the years when the Empire State, led by the irrepressible spirit of its people, roared back to life and laid the foundation for a brighter future.</p>
        <p>The past two years have prepared us well for our passage into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>A great shift of power has taken place, from the government back to the people. And because this historic transfer of power has taken place, the future of our state is in good hands. It is in the hands of the people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
