<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Texaco Moves Against Four Captured on Bias-Suit Tapes</title>
    <meta content="09TEX.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texaco Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ulrich, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keough, J David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lundwall, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meade, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDE1F39F93AA35752C0A961958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Texaco Moves Against Four Captured on Bias-Suit Tapes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Texaco Inc, acting on report by Michael Armstrong, Manhattan attorney hired as an outside investigator by company, dismisses David Keough, senior executive, cuts off benefits to Robert Ulrich, former company treasurer, and Richard Lundwall, former senior coordinator for personnel services in Texaco's finance department, and suspends without pay Peter Meade, manager in marketing department; report is immediately turned over to Federal prosecutors who are investigating possible obstruction of justice by company executives; Texaco declined to make report public, fearing it would interfere with criminal investigation, but documents obtained by The New York Times indicate that Armstrong found executives made statements that violated company policy and failed to report any conversations to company officials (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting on the conclusions of an outside investigator hired by the company, Texaco Inc. dismissed one senior executive yesterday, suspended another and cut off benefits to two retirees for engaging in improper conduct that was secretly recorded.</p>
        <p>The final report by Michael Armstrong, a prominent Manhattan lawyer, was immediately turned over to Federal prosecutors who are investigating possible obstruction of justice by company executives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acting on the conclusions of an outside investigator hired by the company, Texaco Inc. dismissed one senior executive yesterday, suspended another and cut off benefits to two retirees for engaging in improper conduct that was secretly recorded.</p>
        <p>The final report by Michael Armstrong, a prominent Manhattan lawyer, was immediately turned over to Federal prosecutors who are investigating possible obstruction of justice by company executives.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Texaco said that the prosecutors feared that the release of the Armstrong report, which was said to be several hundred pages long, would interfere with the criminal investigation. As a result, the company for now will not make the report public.</p>
        <p>But documents obtained by The New York Times indicate that Mr. Armstrong concluded that three executives from Texaco's finance department improperly participated in a plan to withhold documents demanded in a racial discrimination suit. The documents also indicate that Mr. Armstrong found the executives had made statements that violated company policy and failed to report any of the conversations to company officials.</p>
        <p>The actions yesterday culminated weeks of controversy that swept over Texaco after the disclosure in November that senior executives had been secretly recorded as they planned to destroy the documents for the lawsuit and made comments belittling members of minorities.</p>
        <p>In a letter to employees yesterday, Peter I. Bijur, Texaco's chairman, said that the company had dismissed David Keough, a former member of the finance department who was chief financial officer of a company subsidiary in Bermuda.</p>
        <p>It also permanently suspended all benefits that could legally be cut off to Robert Ulrich, the former corporate treasurer, and Richard Lundwall, senior coordinator for personnel services in Texaco's finance department, who took forced retirement in August as the result of reductions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lundwall was the executive who secretly recorded the conversations, and gave the tapes to plaintiffs' lawyers in the discrimination case after he lost his job.</p>
        <p>In his letter, Mr. Bijur said that the termination of benefits for Mr. Ulrich and Mr. Lundwall was the ''strongest action available to us under our code of conduct and corporate policies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keough and the two retirees who received the strictest punishment were the executives who actively participated in the meetings where the document destruction was discussed. No other executives spoke during those discussions, according to a transcript of an enhanced copy of the recordings. That transcript was compiled by Mr. Armstrong during his investigation; a copy of it was obtained by The Times.</p>
        <p>The fourth executive, Peter Meade, a manager in the fuel and marine marketing department, was suspended without pay for two weeks. On his return, Mr. Meade will be required to attend a sensitivity and interaction training program.</p>
        <p>Based on the transcript obtained by The Times, Mr. Meade apparently was not present during the meeting where document destruction was discussed. The tapes recorded a number of meetings that took place over an extended period of time.</p>
        <p>But the transcript also shows that Mr. Meade was present during a later meeting when executives discussed minorities. Mr. Meade's participation in that conversation was modest, according to the transcript, and it was not clear whether he was suspended for statements he made in that conversation or for his failure to report the racial comments made by his superiors that apparently violated company policy.</p>
        <p>''Their reinstating him is recognition that he had little involvement in anything that could deemed offensive by anyone,'' said Stephen R. Lewis, Mr. Meade's lawyer.</p>
        <p>In his letter to employees, Mr. Bijur said that the actions of the four employees ''clearly violated'' company policies and guidelines.</p>
        <p>''Behavior which violates the company's policies will not be tolerated,'' he added. ''Each of us must maintain the highest ethical standards in the way we conduct ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Texaco and Federal prosecutors first obtained a draft of the final report on Tuesday, and had begun discussions about whether it would be released then. By the time the formal version of the Armstrong report was delivered yesterday, the company had agreed not to release it and was proceeding to take action against the four executives.</p>
        <p>Late yesterday, the company had delivered letters to the executives, informing them of its decision.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for some of the executives reacted angrily to the company's decisions, saying that their clients were being punished without the benefit of seeing the report that led to Texaco's decision.</p>
        <p>''It's an outrage that they are taking this action to begin with, since Mr. Lundwall was the person who stepped forward with the truth,'' said Peter Gass, one of Mr. Lundwall's lawyers. ''But it's doubly outrageous that they do this on the basis of a report by their hired investigator, and then refuse to provide us with a copy of the investigator's report.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keough's lawyer did not return a phone message. Jonathan Rosner, Mr. Ulrich's lawyer, said he would be saving his comments for Texaco.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
