<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dollar Is Lower Overseas, Then Turns Mixed in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CURRENCY MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL MONETARY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DD1439F935A15752C1A967958260" item-length="365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dollar Is Lower Overseas, Then Turns Mixed in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After settling lower in foreign markets yesterday, the dollar turned mixed in United States trading as dealers concentrated on other currencies.</p>
        <p>The dollar fell against the Japanese yen and rose against the German mark, but the trading focus was each of the other two currencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After settling lower in foreign markets yesterday, the dollar turned mixed in United States trading as dealers concentrated on other currencies.</p>
        <p>The dollar fell against the Japanese yen and rose against the German mark, but the trading focus was each of the other two currencies.</p>
        <p>The Japanese yen moved higher following comments overnight by Yasushi Mieno, Bank of Japan governor, who said he preferred a stronger yen.</p>
        <p>"The yen broke through key technical support levels, and the dollar came down sharply," said Randolph Donney, research director at Pegasus Econometric Group in Hoboken, N.J.</p>
        <p>The dollar rose, however, against the German mark. Analysts said Germany's Bundesbank entered the market to sell marks and buy the British pound, which was tumbling. The intervention was successful, and the pound began to strengthen again.</p>
        <p>"The move was somewhat expected," Mr. Donney said. "There is an obligation on the part of central banks within the European Monetary System to come to the aid of other currencies to keep them supported."</p>
        <p>The Bundesbank is considered a powerful force within the market, and the move had a deeper impact than similar moves by other European banks over the last few weeks.</p>
        <p>Much of the day's action occurred overnight in Asian trading and in Europe. Trading became more subdued when activity shifted to domestic markets.</p>
        <p>Traders in New York "really did nothing but lighten up on long mark positions," said Stephen Flanagan, a vice president at Mitsubishi Bank Ltd.</p>
        <p>In Tokyo, the dollar fell 1.12 yen, to a closing 128.53 yen. Later in London, it was quoted at 127.75 yen. In New York the dollar settled at 127.90 yen, down from 129.40 yen on Friday.</p>
        <p>In London, the British pound rose to $1.7995, from $1.7975 late Friday. In New York it cost $1.7945 to buy one pound, unchanged from Friday.</p>
        <p>Against the German currency, the dollar rose in New York to 1.5885 marks, from 1.5835 late Friday.</p>
        <p>Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late Friday's rates, included: 1.4125 Swiss francs, up from 1.4090; 5.4290 French francs, up from 5.4135; 1,201.75 Italian lire, up from 1,199.50, and 1.1383 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1390.</p>
        <p>CURRENCY MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
