<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>International Paper To Restate Results</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPER AND PULP</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL PAPER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA1039F935A15752C1A967958260" item-length="439" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>International Paper To Restate Results</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The International Paper Company, the nation's largest paper producer, said yesterday that it was cutting 1,000 positions from its worldwide work force and that it would adopt an accounting change that would force it to restate its results for the first three quarters of 1991.</p>
        <p>The Purchase, N.Y., company, which has been hurt by sluggish demand for some products, said it was adopting the accounting rule, known as Financial Accounting Standard No. 106, before 1993, when the rule will become mandatory for all companies. The new standard requires that the costs of providing life and medical insurance coverage for a retired employee be accrued over the employee's active career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The International Paper Company, the nation's largest paper producer, said yesterday that it was cutting 1,000 positions from its worldwide work force and that it would adopt an accounting change that would force it to restate its results for the first three quarters of 1991.</p>
        <p>The Purchase, N.Y., company, which has been hurt by sluggish demand for some products, said it was adopting the accounting rule, known as Financial Accounting Standard No. 106, before 1993, when the rule will become mandatory for all companies. The new standard requires that the costs of providing life and medical insurance coverage for a retired employee be accrued over the employee's active career.</p>
        <p>As a result, the company said it would restate its first-quarter results to include a $215 million charge, resulting in a loss for that period. Originally, International Paper reported net income for the period of $132 million, or $1.20 a share, on sales of $3.1 billion.</p>
        <p>Additional charges totaling $15 million will be spread across the last three quarters of the year. But the company said it would still report net income for its second and third quarters.</p>
        <p>"By adopting the new accounting standard early, we get this charge behind us and remove uncertainty from future periods," a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The company will establish a $60 million reserve to cover severance costs of the 1,000 job cuts. That will result in a $37 million charge against after-tax earnings in the fourth quarter, the company said.</p>
        <p>The cutbacks, which are likely to occur by the end of the year, represent a fraction of the company's 70,000 employees worldwide. But they are considered significant because they represent the company's largest personnel cutback in recent years. The company said it had not yet determined which employees would be affected or the areas where the cuts would take place.</p>
        <p>"Like many other companies in this difficult year, we carefully examined all of our activities," said John A. Georges, the company's chairman and chief executive. "The purpose was to identify areas where we can improve productivity or operate efficiently." He added that the employee cuts would reduce costs by about $50 million a year.</p>
        <p>The share price of International Paper fell $1.25, to $67.50, in trading yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>International Paper has been especially hurt by declining demand and prices for uncoated free sheet, the product used in business and copier paper. Prices declined this year from about $830 a ton in January to $630 a ton in June, although prices have risen to a current level of about $700 a ton.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
