<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks and Anderson Part Ways, at a Cost</title>
    <meta content="11ANDE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/11/sports/basketball/11anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1626462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Shandon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Shandon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DF1F3CF932A25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks and Anderson Part Ways, at a Cost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finally, the Knicks Waive Anderson</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK; Liz Robbins contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks put Shandon Anderson on waivers after trying to trade him since last season; buyout agreement gives Anderson $17 million to $20 million and forces Knicks to pay that much in dollar-for-dollar luxury tax (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shandon Anderson got his freedom yesterday, and the Knicks got some roster flexibility. All it cost the team was about $40 million, give or take a few million.</p>
        <p>Under a buyout agreement reached late yesterday afternoon, Anderson will receive between $17 million to $20 million -- a marginal pay cut from the $24 million he was owed for the three years left on his contract. Because the Knicks are also paying a dollar-for-dollar luxury tax, the amount spent to make Anderson go away essentially doubled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shandon Anderson got his freedom yesterday, and the Knicks got some roster flexibility. All it cost the team was about $40 million, give or take a few million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shandon Anderson got his freedom yesterday, and the Knicks got some roster flexibility. All it cost the team was about $40 million, give or take a few million.</p>
        <p>Under a buyout agreement reached late yesterday afternoon, Anderson will receive between $17 million to $20 million -- a marginal pay cut from the $24 million he was owed for the three years left on his contract. Because the Knicks are also paying a dollar-for-dollar luxury tax, the amount spent to make Anderson go away essentially doubled.</p>
        <p>That the Knicks were willing to swallow such a large sum speaks to how desperate they were to dump Anderson, a 30-year-old swingman who fell out of favor last season with Isiah Thomas, the team president, and then forever alienated the organization by failing to show for a postseason exit interview.</p>
        <p>''It just wasn't the best fit, and we decided it was time to separate,'' Anderson's agent, Dan Fegan, said.</p>
        <p>Thomas spent months trying to trade Anderson, but teams were unwilling to take on his hefty contract. Only a month ago, Thomas said that an expensive buyout was ''not an option,'' but the organization changed philosophy when it became clear it was the only option.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, the Knicks offered to buy out Anderson for a fraction of what he was owed. Anderson balked, saying he would rather be stuck with a team that did not want him than surrender so much money. Talks resumed about a week ago, according to a person close to the negotiation.</p>
        <p>Thomas was not available for comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>Anderson was immediately placed on waivers and will become a free agent if no team claims him in 48 hours. The amount of the buyout will decrease if another team claims him, but given the size of his contract, that is unlikely.</p>
        <p>Anderson should be free and clear late tomorrow afternoon. Among the teams expected to pursue him are the Houston Rockets, the Miami Heat, the Denver Nuggets, the Golden State Warriors and the Chicago Bulls. The veteran's minimum for a player of Anderson's experience would be about $1 million.</p>
        <p>In Houston, Anderson would be reunited with Jeff Van Gundy, the former Knicks coach. The Rockets need a steady veteran to back up the All-Star swingman Tracy McGrady, who has a history of back problems and who missed part of practice yesterday with hip and groin injuries.</p>
        <p>Releasing Anderson leaves the Knicks' active roster at 11 players and gives them some needed flexibility. They could sign another player, possibly Eddie Robinson, who was recently bought out of his contract by the Chicago Bulls. Robinson is holding a workout today in Chicago, and the Knicks are among the teams who will be watching.</p>
        <p>Alternatively, the Knicks could choose to activate one of their injured players when they become eligible this weekend. Given their need for size, the Knicks might consider activating Bruno Sundov, a 7-foot 2 center.</p>
        <p>They could also leave the spot open until Allan Houston is ready to rejoin the team. Had Anderson still been on the roster, it would have forced the Knicks to deactivate a player they valued when Houston returned.</p>
        <p>Long term, waiving Anderson actually saved the Knicks between $8 million and $14 million -- the millions they will not be paying him, plus the luxury tax on that sum.</p>
        <p>Anderson's release nearly completes the 11-month purge of players tied to Scott Layden, the former Knicks general manager. Of the players acquired by Layden from 2001 to 2003, only the young power forward Mike Sweetney, a first-round pick, remains.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
