<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nanny Says Pelosi Admitted Killing and Threatened Her</title>
    <meta content="11PELO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/11/nyregion/11pelosi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1626378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Hampton (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beller, Peter C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ammon, R Theodore</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ammon, Generosa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayne, Kathryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pelosi, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1D81E3CF932A25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nanny Says Pelosi Admitted Killing and Threatened Her</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nanny Says Pelosi Admitted Killing and Threatened Her</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER C. BELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beller, Peter C</byline>
      <dateline>RIVERHEAD, N.Y., Nov. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R Theodore and Generosa Ammon's former nanny Kathryn Ann Mayne testifies that Daniel Pelosi admitted that he killed Theodore Ammon; Pelosi is on trial for beating Ammon to death in his East Hampton (NY) home, three months before he married Ammon's ex-wife Generosa; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A British nanny who cared for Theodore and Generosa Ammon's children testified on Wednesday that a drunken Daniel Pelosi sidled up to her one night and whispered in her ear that he had beaten Mr. Ammon to death. The next day, she said, he threatened to do the same to her.</p>
        <p>The nanny, Kathryn Ann Mayne, is the second witness at Mr. Pelosi's murder trial to testify that he admitted killing Mr. Ammon, a wealthy New York financier, and she also said Mr. Pelosi claimed that the victim had offered him money to spare his life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>RIVERHEAD, N.Y., Nov. 10 - A British nanny who cared for Theodore and Generosa Ammon's children testified on Wednesday that a drunken Daniel Pelosi sidled up to her one night and whispered in her ear that he had beaten Mr. Ammon to death. The next day, she said, he threatened to do the same to her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A British nanny who cared for Theodore and Generosa Ammon's children testified on Wednesday that a drunken Daniel Pelosi sidled up to her one night and whispered in her ear that he had beaten Mr. Ammon to death. The next day, she said, he threatened to do the same to her.</p>
        <p>The nanny, Kathryn Ann Mayne, is the second witness at Mr. Pelosi's murder trial to testify that he admitted killing Mr. Ammon, a wealthy New York financier, and she also said Mr. Pelosi claimed that the victim had offered him money to spare his life.</p>
        <p>At the time of the October 2001 killing, Mr. Pelosi was having an affair with Ms. Ammon, who was estranged from her husband and in the middle of a bitter divorce. They married three months after Mr. Ammon, 52, was found beaten to death in his East Hampton home.</p>
        <p>Last month, a former girlfriend of Mr. Pelosi's testified that he had admitted killing Mr. Ammon.</p>
        <p>In her testimony in Suffolk County Court here, Ms. Mayne, who inherited $1 million from Ms. Ammon's estate, said Mr. Pelosi came home drunk one night to the house he shared with Ms. Ammon in Center Moriches. ''I was sleeping on the couch,'' Ms. Mayne said. ''Generosa didn't want to be alone in the house when he came home.</p>
        <p>''He came and sat right next to me and whispered in my ear about how he had beaten him and beaten him,'' she said, referring to Mr. Ammon. The next day, she said, Mr. Pelosi told her, '''I'm going to kill you.'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pelosi, now 41, and Ms. Ammon began their affair in the fall of 2000, when he was renovating her Upper East Side town house. Prosecutors say Mr. Pelosi romanced Ms. Ammon, then killed her husband to get at his $80 million fortune. He is charged with second-degree murder.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mayne described Mr. Pelosi, a Long Island electrician, as an angry man whose marriage to Ms. Ammon disintegrated as he spent millions of her money. '''I gave this woman money, killed her husband, and now she won't give me a few hundred thousand dollars,''' Ms. Mayne said Mr. Pelosi told her one afternoon.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mayne, who had managed the Ammons' 22-acre estate in England, said she brought the couple's children to the United States in 2002 for the summer and stayed on to care for the family after Ms. Ammon received a diagnosis of breast cancer. She died last year at 46 and was never charged in her husband's death.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mayne said the only peace in the household came when Mr. Pelosi was sentenced to serve four months in jail for a drunken-driving conviction in 2003. Mr. Pelosi called to say that his incarceration was damaging his health and that he was worse off than his cancer-stricken wife, the nanny said.</p>
        <p>After his release, Ms. Ammon told him to get a job, Ms. Mayne said, and he complied for a few days. But that weekend, Ms. Mayne said, he came home drunk after a night out. ''She asked me to stay,'' Ms. Mayne said. ''She was frightened.''</p>
        <p>Under cross-examination by Mr. Pelosi's lawyer, Gerald L. Shargel, Ms. Mayne admitted that at first she did not believe that Mr. Pelosi had committed murder, despite his comments, and offered no explanation for her testimony that Mr. Pelosi told her that Mr. Ammon had offered him money to spare his life. The account contradicted her grand jury testimony, in which she said Mr. Pelosi had not told her that Mr. Ammon said anything as he was being killed.</p>
        <p>She testified that she did not think Mr. Pelosi could kill Mr. Ammon, a larger, athletic man, until she read an Internet report that a stun gun had been used in the attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shargel showed the court a letter Ms. Mayne had written to Mr. Pelosi in jail in which she said the family was looking forward to seeing him, and pointed to sparring between Ms. Mayne and Mr. Pelosi over the fate of the Ammon children as proof that she hated his client.</p>
        <p>In addition to money, Ms. Ammon's will left the nanny with lifetime use of the East Hampton home and guardianship of the children, now living with Mr. Ammon's sister in Alabama. Crying as she described how Ms. Ammon's body had been ravaged by cancer, Ms. Mayne said she took her to a Manhattan hospital to die, bought a bouquet of orchids and forged Mr. Pelosi's signature in a card. ''We're soul mates,'' the nanny wrote in Mr. Pelosi's stead.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mayne said Ms. Ammon read the card and said, ''It's a shame, because I really loved him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
