<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Dispute Said to Delay Report on Prison Uprising</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="478895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONS AND PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHPORT CORRECTIONAL FACILITY (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAAB, SELWYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COUGHLIN, THOMAS A 3D (COMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D71330F935A35753C1A967958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Dispute Said to Delay Report on Prison Uprising</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELWYN RAAB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAAB, SELWYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The release of a report on the causes of an inmate uprising at New York State's high-security prison in May has been delayed in large part because of a dispute over portions that are highly critical of the state's top prison official, officials say.</p>
        <p>The report by the Commission on Correction, which has the responsibility for monitoring state prisons, on the circumstances and implications of the uprising at the Southport Correctional Facility has been held up by wrangling between its two members, the chairman, William G. McMahon, and Deborah A. Reyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The release of a report on the causes of an inmate uprising at New York State's high-security prison in May has been delayed in large part because of a dispute over portions that are highly critical of the state's top prison official, officials say.</p>
        <p>The report by the Commission on Correction, which has the responsibility for monitoring state prisons, on the circumstances and implications of the uprising at the Southport Correctional Facility has been held up by wrangling between its two members, the chairman, William G. McMahon, and Deborah A. Reyes.</p>
        <p>A central issue in the disagreement is the extent of criticism that should be directed at the state's top prison official, Thomas A. Coughlin 3d, the Commissioner of Correctional Services, say state officials who have knowledge of the internal disagreements. Sensitive Issue</p>
        <p>A draft report that was said to be highly critical of Mr. Coughlin was completed by the commission's staff last month. State officials, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said that Mr. McMahon generally agreed with the findings but that Ms. Reyes objected to many of the principal conclusions.  The report on the Southport uprising is one of the most sensitive issues to confront the commission in the last decade because it concerns a new strategy for dealing with disruptive inmates and will affect Mr. Coughlin's reputation. As the head of the state's prisons since 1979, Mr. Coughlin has a largely unblemished record as an innovative and pragmatic administrator of one of the country's largest penal systems.</p>
        <p>The Southport Correctional Facility, near Elmira in the southwest part of the state, opened in January as an experimental, super-secure prison to house disruptive inmates from other state prisons. At Southport, prisoners can be confined up to 23 hours a day in their cells and can be temporarily denied most prison privileges.</p>
        <p>In a 26-hour rebellion on May 29 and May 30, five guards were taken hostage by 53 inmates who broke through the flimsy fences of a recreational yard.  Planning Is Criticized</p>
        <p>There were no deaths, but one guard was seriously injured. The inmates surrendered after being allowed to broadcast on television their grievances about substandard food and living conditions.</p>
        <p>The preliminary report concluded that plans approved by Mr. Coughlin for operating Southport and for insuring security were flawed, people familar with the report said. The preliminary report asserted that inadequate planning and the lack of services for inmates had contributed heavily to unrest among 700 inmates and to poor morale among 230 correction officers at Southport.</p>
        <p>The report found that the concept of consolidating unruly inmates for short-term segregation at one prison was a justifiable penal experiment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coughlin replied in a written rebuttal last month, contending that many of the findings were based on innaccuracies or false assumptions, officials who have knowledge of the dispute said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMahon, in an interview last week, acknowledged that Ms. Reyes had "concerns with parts of the report" based mainly on a response to the draft by Mr. Coughlin. Mr. McMahon said he would meet with Ms. Reyes tomorrow at the commission's offices in Albany in an effort to resolve the deadlock.</p>
        <p>"There is a lack of consensus in certain areas," Ms. Reyes said in an interview. "We are still discussing matters, but I don't know what the next few days will bring."</p>
        <p>Ms. Reyes and Mr. McMahon both declined to specify their disagreements.  2-Year Vacancy</p>
        <p>The independent commission has the authority to investigate conditions and grievances in state prisons and local jails and to report on problems. The agency normally has three commissioners, who are appointed by the Governor, and whose votes are equal in administrative matters. A vacancy has existed for two years while Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has tried to get approval from the Legislature for a plan to reorganize the agency.</p>
        <p>The Governor's Criminal Justice Director, Richard H. Girgenti, said, "If there is disagreement, we hope they resolve it quickly."</p>
        <p>Mr. Girgenti added that the Governor expected "a balanced, thorough and professional report and to the extent we agree with the recommendations, we will act upon them."</p>
        <p>The officials said Mr. Coughlin was angered by the draft report and saw it as a personal attack by Mr. McMahon.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Coughlin, James B. Flateau, said Mr. Coughlin would withhold comment until a final report is made public.</p>
        <p>But officials said Mr. Coughlin, in replying to the preliminary report, repeated his earlier contention that the uprising had resulted mainly from the actions of seven guards who, he asserted, took an unauthorized lunch break, leaving the inmates unsupervised in the recreation area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coughlin, the officials noted, took some responsiblity for poor officer morale at Southport. He said in the rebuttal that he might have undermined the authority of Southport administrators by dealing personally on several staffing and working condition issues with the union that represents guards, rather than allowing these matters to be resolved by Southport supervisors.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMahon said the commission staff has been researching the legal options if a deadlock continues. He said it was unclear if findings and recommendations could be made without a majority decision or if separate reports could be issued if he and Ms. Reyes are unable to resolve their differences.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
