<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Yorkers, etc.</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="478510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEMY, ENID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D71339F935A35753C1A967958260" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Yorkers, etc.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NEMY, ENID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's nice to know whether it's acceptable to pick up asparagus with your fingers, who is introduced to whom when distinguished personages are involved, and how to address British royalty and the President of the United States. Such knowledge can be invaluable when chatting with the Queen or visiting the White House, introducing Brooke Astor to Colin Powell, or simply at a black tie dinner when holding aloft a stalk of asparagus could seriously detract from the overall effect.</p>
        <p>These and other tricky behavior niceties are covered, happily, in many books and articles on etiquette. What these books fail to address are the little niggles that come up constantly, particularly in a big city. Most of these niggles, which are not quite problems but are something more than pinpricks, provoke not so much ire as resentment coupled with resignation. It's impossible to say anything without looking nasty and mean. A show of temper for something so small would appear foolish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's nice to know whether it's acceptable to pick up asparagus with your fingers, who is introduced to whom when distinguished personages are involved, and how to address British royalty and the President of the United States. Such knowledge can be invaluable when chatting with the Queen or visiting the White House, introducing Brooke Astor to Colin Powell, or simply at a black tie dinner when holding aloft a stalk of asparagus could seriously detract from the overall effect.</p>
        <p>These and other tricky behavior niceties are covered, happily, in many books and articles on etiquette. What these books fail to address are the little niggles that come up constantly, particularly in a big city. Most of these niggles, which are not quite problems but are something more than pinpricks, provoke not so much ire as resentment coupled with resignation. It's impossible to say anything without looking nasty and mean. A show of temper for something so small would appear foolish.</p>
        <p>Jerry Stiller, the actor, describes these situations as "dilemmas that test the urban psyche," things that theoretically shouldn't be minded, but sometimes are. For instance, his neighborhood store, Zabar's, happens to be popular with a considerable number of other people, and in busy departments, like smoked fish, customers are asked to take a number.</p>
        <p>What often happens when customers have numbers considerably higher than the one being served is that rather than wait in line, they'll go off to other sections. Often when they return, their number has been passed, usually when Mr. Stiller's number is next. Chances are the errant customer nevertheless protests that he's next: "I'm 380. I'm first."</p>
        <p>It's possible to say: "No, you're not. You missed your turn." It's possible but it's almost never done because it sounds so petty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiller, who is in "The Pickle," the Paul Mazursky movie now being filmed in New York, has three reasons for rationalizing his silence. One, he considers the practice "part of life in New York," and two, he is occasionally the guilty party, returning to find his number passed by, going to the head of the line, holding up his number, maybe saying "excuse me," but generally just looking imploring. But the most important reason that he's so amenable when his place is usurped by a latecomer is image; he is widely recognized.</p>
        <p>"I'm usually so interested in maintaining my good name that I tell whoever asks to go ahead," he said. "But it drives me nuts."</p>
        <p>Still, he added philosophically, he tries to remember that there are worse things that can happen, like getting to the head of a long line only to see someone put up a sign reading, "Sorry, register closed."</p>
        <p>Anne Meara, an actress who was in the recent movie "Awakenings" and who is also Mrs. Stiller, has had her urban psyche tested in numerous ways, one of them not at all uncommon. This occurs after she has found a good seat in a rapidly-filling movie theater and she is asked by a stranger to save the two empty seats beside her -- he's waiting for someone or he's going to buy candy or whatever. She agrees but she also gets a slightly sinking feeling because she takes the responsibility seriously -- "awesome" is how she describes it, acknowledging only slight exaggeration.</p>
        <p>The result is that she spends the next minutes fending off scores of men and women who want to sit there. "Taken," she says. "I'm saving them. The house darkens and she misses the first minutes of the picture keeping her word and waving away people. She finally gives up and releases the seats, and not infrequently it doesn't matter one whit because the person who made the original request never reappears.</p>
        <p>"It's horrible," she said. "I once got so fed up explaining and waving off people that I just got up myself and moved."</p>
        <p>A similar situation occurs in buses when someone who has forgotten to get a transfer gets up and asks that you hold the seat. "Taken," you repeat as others approach, and sometimes it works. But sometimes you're simply ignored and the newcomer plunks down. When the person who made the request returns, who gets the looks that could kill? Not the seat appropriator, but you.</p>
        <p>And who hasn't been in a supermarket line when someone with one or two items asks to go ahead? Why not the express line? It's too long.</p>
        <p>Leida Snow, a journalist and critic for 1010 WINS Radio, says her reaction depends on her mood. Like most people, she's inclined to give in, but sometimes she's had it when she hears, "Do you mind?"</p>
        <p>"Yes, I do mind," she says. "I've been waiting on line, too."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
