<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chinese-Japanese Spot Proves a Puzzle</title>
    <meta content="21CART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1385818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A LA CARTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eastern Palace (Farmingdale, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DE163FF932A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chinese-Japanese Spot Proves a Puzzle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scholem, Richard Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Jay Scholem reviews Eastern Palace Restaurant in Farmingdale, Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE new Eastern Palace Restaurant, at 283 Main Street in Farmingdale (516) 777-3888, is a puzzle. It's a Chinese-Japanese spot with Chinese owners where the Japanese food is better than the Chinese. Its surroundings are rather grand, but its prices are manageable. The dishes marked spicy aren't.</p>
        <p>At the restaurant's center, a stream flows through a Japanese rock garden to a small pool. There are blond wood beams and pagoda roofs overhead, private tatami rooms with sliding rice-paper partitions and a long wall-length Chinese countryside mural. Yet the ventilation system doesn't prevent cooking odors (some of it off-putting, like fish and cooking oils) from frequently filtering into the dining room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE new Eastern Palace Restaurant, at 283 Main Street in Farmingdale (516) 777-3888, is a puzzle. It's a Chinese-Japanese spot with Chinese owners where the Japanese food is better than the Chinese. Its surroundings are rather grand, but its prices are manageable. The dishes marked spicy aren't.</p>
        <p>At the restaurant's center, a stream flows through a Japanese rock garden to a small pool. There are blond wood beams and pagoda roofs overhead, private tatami rooms with sliding rice-paper partitions and a long wall-length Chinese countryside mural. Yet the ventilation system doesn't prevent cooking odors (some of it off-putting, like fish and cooking oils) from frequently filtering into the dining room.</p>
        <p>Waiters are always affable, but tend to clear tables while some diners are still eating.</p>
        <p>The waiters are sometimes vague, as in this conversation:</p>
        <p>Me: ''What's the appetizer of the day that comes with the bento box?''</p>
        <p>Waiter: ''It changes every day.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''What is it today?''</p>
        <p>Waiter: ''I don't know.''</p>
        <p>When it was served, he said, ''I think it's a Chinese won ton, but I'm not sure.'' (It was deep fried, filled with melting cheese and crab meat and quite good, though unexpected with a Japanese, not Chinese, entree).</p>
        <p>Aside from that mystery starter, Japanese appetizers easily trumped Chinese ones once we got past the faintly flavored miso soup ($2.50) and nondescript iceberg lettuce-dominated salad ($2.50) with its sesame and ginger dressing.</p>
        <p>A fresh, crunchy seaweed salad ($3.50) on a platform of lettuce, dressed with sesame oil and seeds, was the best opener sampled. Steamed shumai ($4.50), or delicate shrimp-filled dumplings, were a bit better than six steamed, crescent-shaped Chinese dumplings ($5) with a savory ground pork and vegetable stuffing but a slightly rubbery wrapper.</p>
        <p>Pay attention to the sushi bar at the far end of the restaurant. It turns out exemplary sushi and sashimi appetizers and entrees. All were fresh and lively with the cool of the sea evident in every morsel. The sushi deluxe plate ($17), an assortment of about 20 pieces of five different selections, was an excellent main-course choice.</p>
        <p>Combination servings of cut and hand rolls are on a par with the sushi and sashimi. The crisp batter-fried shrimp tempura roll ($6), with its contrasting tastes and textures of lettuce, avocado, scallion and mayonnaise, was a satisfying starter, and the refreshing cucumber and salmon roll ($5.50) was another.</p>
        <p>Most of the Chinese possibilities were more mellow than lively. The lone exception was hot and sour soup that generated heat, though little or no sourness. Both won-ton and egg-drop soups were standard issue (all three soups were $2.50 a cup and $5 a bowl). Tasty egg rolls and especially shredded vegetable-filled shrimp rolls (both $1.50) were a little better than that, while soothing white-meat chicken in a lettuce wrap (usually listed as chicken soong) needed salt to bring it to life. That was also true of bland fried rice that required a dose of Chinese hot mustard to kick it up a notch.</p>
        <p>At lunch, shrimp in garlic sauce ($7), despite its few finely minced red peppers, delivered flavor but no punch. Royal Delight Spicy ($15), or General Tso's shrimp, chicken and snow peas, presented with a white radish bird sculpture, was an appealing-looking, flavorful pick. But its crunchy snow peas and velvety strips of chicken breast certainly had no firepower, and the crusty, sweet shrimp offered only a smidgen of zing from its chili peppers.</p>
        <p>The Chinese entrees not designated as spicy filled diners' expectations most often. A nest of wispy pan-fried noodles ($11), blanketed with pork and an Oriental garden of mixed vegetables, was first-rate.</p>
        <p>The best-buy, best-taste double play at the Eastern Palace was the makunouchi dinner box. This beautifully presented bento box was preceded by salad, miso soup and the appetizer of the day. The box contained two long, thin shrimp tempura cylinders with a lighter-than-air batter, three cloud-like pockets of shumai and chicken teriyaki with a slight glaze from its marinade of soy sauce, sugar, sake, ginger and seasonings. All this, followed by ice cream, was $17.50.</p>
        <p>Desserts, like the Eastern Palace itself, followed the safe suburban route: Jell-O, canned pineapple, fresh orange sections and vanilla, chocolate, pistachio, green tea or red bean ice cream.</p>
        <p>Chef's Corner</p>
        <p>One of Long Island's top chefs, Michael Meehan, will soon be the executive chef at the Seafood Barge, 62980 Main Road, Southold (631-765-3010). Mr. Meehan has an outstanding reputation for his cooking at the Mill River Inn, Tupelo Honey and Veritage. His menu at the Seafood Barge will include cedar-planked salmon with grilled baby leeks and roasted East End potatoes, bibless Maine lobster with local corn pudding soufflé, Crescent Farm duck breast with fig chutney and potato parsnip purée, and Miloski Farm chicken with spring garlic mashed potatoes and natural jus. Mr. Meehan takes over the kitchen on May 1.</p>
        <p>Potpourri</p>
        <p>Ecco, at 2370 Jericho Turnpike in Garden City Park (516-739-0505), will hold an $80, seven-course wine and food tasting highlighting the cuisine and wines of Tuscany, Veneto, Piedmont and Sicily on April 30 at 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>A LA CARTE E-mail: licarte@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: licarte@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
