<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Hope for Talks on Ulster Rule</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19900622T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHERN IRELAND</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">IRISH REPUBLICAN ARMY (IRA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PROKESCH, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D81430F932A15755C0A966958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Hope for Talks on Ulster Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN PROKESCH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PROKESCH, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The British Government is expected to announce in early July that the political parties in Northern Ireland have agreed to negotiations intended to return a large degree of self-rule to the strife-torn province, British officials said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The British Government is expected to announce in early July that the political parties in Northern Ireland have agreed to negotiations intended to return a large degree of self-rule to the strife-torn province, British officials said today.</p>
        <p>The British Government is expected to announce in early July that the political parties in Northern Ireland have agreed to negotiations intended to return a large degree of self-rule to the strife-torn province, British officials said today.</p>
        <p>Peter Brooke, Britain's Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, said today in a brief interview that he was ''guardedly optimistic'' about success in his efforts in the last six months to persuade the parties of Northern Ireland to agree to negotiations. Until now, he has been saying that such talks were ''possible rather than probable.''</p>
        <p>One of his aides said Mr. Brooke could announce an agreement in the House of Commons as early as the first week of July. The aide said the talks could begin in the fall.</p>
        <p>Three Sets of Talks Likely</p>
        <p>While any such talks will certainly be difficult, if they succeed in creating a Northern Ireland government that has the backing of both the majority Protestants and minority Catholics, the British Government could eventually end direct rule, which was imposed in 1972, three years after the sectarian strife known as ''the troubles'' began.</p>
        <p>The talks about talks are not expected to involve Sinn Fein, the political arm of the outlawed Irish Republican Army. The British Government's current position is that it will not negotiate with the group unless it renounces violence.</p>
        <p>The current thinking is that there will be three sets of talks, at least two of which would take place concurrently: those among the province's political parties and others between the British and Irish Governments, which would deal with their relations and with the Anglo-Irish agreement, which was signed in November 1985, giving Ireland a consultative role in running Northern Ireland.</p>
        <p>A third set of talks would be between leaders of Ireland and Northern Ireland and would focus on the relationship between the two parts of the island. These talks would probably be held after the two others were either concluded or at least well-advanced.</p>
        <p>Minor Local Power</p>
        <p>Since London's direct rule was imposed in 1972, local governments in Northern Ireland have had only minor power - over things like park maintenance and garbage collection. Britain's Parliament and the ministers appointed by the British Government have overseen security, housing, education, economic development and other things. Various attempts in the 1970's and early 1980's to return political power to Northern Ireland all ended in failure.</p>
        <p>The two main unionist parties, which represent most of the Protestants in Northern Ireland, are adamant about not wanting Dublin to have any say running the province and want to get rid of the Anglo-Irish agreement.</p>
        <p>The Social Democratic and Labor Party, led by John Hume, represents most Catholics in Northern Ireland and seeks a united Ireland through nonviolent means.</p>
        <p>There is even a split between the two main Protestant parties. The larger, the Ulster Unionist Party, is led by James Molyneaux, an ''integrationist'' who does not want Northern Ireland to be treated any differently than the rest of the United Kingdom. If a provincial government were set up, he is believed to prefer that it be relatively weak in its legislative powers.</p>
        <p>Strong Power Urged</p>
        <p>The leaders of the smaller Democratic Unionist Party, which was once also integrationist, have recently been sounding more like ''devolutionists,'' who favor a provincial government with relatively strong administrative and legislative powers.</p>
        <p>The Social Democratic and Labor Party has not articulated its position on a provincial government, saying that the first step is to talk not about solutions but about the problem: the relationships between the people of Northern Ireland, between the north and south, and between Ireland and Britain. That appears to be the approach Mr. Brooke has adopted.</p>
        <p>A Shift in 2 Parties</p>
        <p>Northern Ireland politicians and analysts say a change in the climate in Northern Ireland during the last year has made a breakthrough possible. Many Protestants, who account for about 60 percent of the province's 1.5 million people, and Catholics have tired not only of the violence, which claimed 62 lives in the province last year and 27 so far this year, but also of the political stalemate.</p>
        <p>But what precisely enabled Mr. Brooke to make headway was a significant shift over the last couple of years in the position of the Ulster Unionists and Democratic Unionists. They had at first refused to hold talks until the British-Irish agreement was abandoned. That was unacceptable to the Social Democratic and Labor Party and to the British and Irish Governments, although both Governments have said since early this year that they were open to replacing the agreement with an alternative at some point.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 22, 1990, Friday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>Because of a mechanical error, an article yesterday about talks on Northern Ireland carried a subheading from another article in some copies. The subheading should have read, ''London could eventually end direct rule.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 22, 1990, Friday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>Because of a mechanical error, an article yesterday about talks on Northern Ireland carried a subheading from another article in some copies. The subheading should have read, ''London could eventually end direct rule.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
