<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF1F30F932A15755C0A966958260" item-length="333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: * Adobe Systems Inc., Palo Alto, Calif., a software company, said it had acquired BluePoint Technologies, a New Hampshire-based maker of computer chips, for undisclosed terms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: * Adobe Systems Inc., Palo Alto, Calif., a software company, said it had acquired BluePoint Technologies, a New Hampshire-based maker of computer chips, for undisclosed terms.</p>
        <p>* Adobe Systems Inc., Palo Alto, Calif., a software company, said it had acquired BluePoint Technologies, a New Hampshire-based maker of computer chips, for undisclosed terms.</p>
        <p>* CAE Industries Ltd., Toronto, a holding and management company, said one of its units had been awarded a $120 million contract to provide weapons systems trainers to the Navy.</p>
        <p>* Flightsafety International Inc., an aviation training company, said it had terminated its agreement to acquire certain assets and liabilities of Bicoastal Corp.'s Simuflite division.</p>
        <p>* HTM Sports Holding B.V., an Austrian sporting goods company, completed the acquisition of Calzaturifico Brixia S.p.A., an Italian manufacturer of ski boots, for undisclosed terms.</p>
        <p>* Jaguar P.L.C., Coventry, England, the auto maker, said it laid off 4,200 workers, more than half its total manufacturing force, after a strike by 300 workers at its Birmingham paint shop. Jaguar is a subsidiary of Ford Motor Co.</p>
        <p>* Polaris Aircraft Leasing Corp., San Francisco, announced the purchase and leaseback of eight 737-236ADV jet aircraft with a combined value of $124 million to British Airways P.L.C., Middlesex, England.</p>
        <p>* Procordia A.B., a Swedish drug maker, said it would cut 1,300 to 1,500 jobs in its new Kabi Pharmacia Pharmaceutical health care division over two years.</p>
        <p>* Reed International P.L.C., London, a publishing and information company, said it would sell its stake in Reedpack Ltd., an office supplies concern, to Svenska Cellulosa A.B., a Swedish forest-products company, for $:94.9 million.</p>
        <p>* Solvay &amp; Cie S.A., Brussels, a chemical group, said its Solvay America Inc. unit would buy the blow-molded plastics operations of Kuhlman Corp., Troy, Mich., for $45 million.</p>
        <p>* TW Holdings Inc. said its TW Services subsidiary had completed a territory development agreement with Hardee's Food Systems Inc., Rocky Mount, N.C., a fast-food chain, allowing TW Services to add 145 new Hardee's restaurants over the next five years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
