<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moscow Threatens to End Peace Talks With Chechen Rebels</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="782615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDEPENDENCE MOVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHECHNYA (RUSSIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STANLEY, ALESSANDRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD8163DF936A2575BC0A963958260" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moscow Threatens to End Peace Talks With Chechen Rebels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STANLEY, ALESSANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moscow threatened to cut off peace negotiations in Chechnya tonight after Chechen rebels refused to agree to Russian terms for putting a demilitarization agreement signed on July 30 into effect.</p>
        <p>And it also warned that the war in the breakaway republic could start up again. Trying to press the Chechen rebels to lay down their weapons, Prime Minister Viktor S. Chernomyrdin said that Russia would take "extreme measures" unless the Chechens reaffirmed their commitment to disarm their troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moscow threatened to cut off peace negotiations in Chechnya tonight after Chechen rebels refused to agree to Russian terms for putting a demilitarization agreement signed on July 30 into effect.</p>
        <p>And it also warned that the war in the breakaway republic could start up again. Trying to press the Chechen rebels to lay down their weapons, Prime Minister Viktor S. Chernomyrdin said that Russia would take "extreme measures" unless the Chechens reaffirmed their commitment to disarm their troops.</p>
        <p>The Chechens rejected the Russian ultimatum, leaving open the possibility of a showdown. Aslan Maskhadov, the commander of Chechen rebel forces, said he would not sign a protocol setting out mechanisms for implementing the military deal because he objected to some of its demands.</p>
        <p>But he stressed that he remained committed to the overall military agreement reached with Russia last month.</p>
        <p>Moscow was not mollified.</p>
        <p>A Government statement released after Mr. Maskhadov's remarks said that the rebels led by Dzhokhar M. Dudayev were "trying to radically change the content of the agreement on a peaceful settlement on the Chechen republic.</p>
        <p>"The continuation of talks on the peaceful settlement of the situation in the Chechen republic is impossible unless Dudayev's supporters take real and urgent steps to implement the agreement on military issues which was signed in Grozny on July 30th," it said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chernomyrdin's ultimatum was issued amid complaints by each side that the other has violated the disarmament accord. Mr. Chernomyrdin did not spell out what he would do, but other Russian officials have said that unless Chechens submitted, Russian troops would disarm them by force.</p>
        <p>And after Russia's threat, nerves were on edge in Chechnya and Moscow. On its late news program tonight, the Russian television network NTV reported that Russian troops had intercepted a radio message from the Chechen leadership to field commanders to be on alert and to prepare for a resumption of hostilities.</p>
        <p>Vesti, another Russian news program, reported that Russian troop commanders in Chechnya held a meeting in Grozny.</p>
        <p>The disarmament plan calls for Chechen forces to turn in their weapons gradually in exchange for the withdrawal of most of the Russian troops based in Chechnya. But how, when and where Chechen rebels would begin laying down their weapons was not spelled out.</p>
        <p>The procedure for laying down arms stalled even before it began. Each side suspects the other of taking advantage of the relative lull in the hostilities to regroup its forces and fight again.</p>
        <p>A cease-fire and a full exchange of prisoners were prerequisites for starting the disarmament process. There have been outbreaks of shooting for weeks.</p>
        <p>Last week, Russian commanders in Chechnya complained that Chechens had neglected to provide a full list of prisoners or maps to their mine fields. On Sunday, Chechen leaders charged that the Russians tried to assassinate Mr. Dudayev, the rebel leader, over the weekend.</p>
        <p>Peace talks in Grozny have been under way since June. Each side has complained that the other has violated the fragile cease-fire that has been in operation since peace talks began.</p>
        <p>Negotiations over Chechnya's future status -- Russia insists Chechnya must remain within the federation and Chechens demand independence -- have bogged down.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
