<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lot Tastier Than a Jack-o'-Lantern</title>
    <meta content="27NIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1622406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="AT MY TABLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawson, Nigella</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Nigella Lawson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5DE173DF934A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lot Tastier Than a Jack-o'-Lantern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nigella Lawson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lawson, Nigella</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nigella Lawson column on making roasted stuffed pumpkin and monster Halloween cookies; recipes; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is something about the bulging brightness of a pumpkin that is fabulously compelling. Just seeing pumpkins piled high in the stores fills me with harvest festival spirit. I do not have anything against a gloriously spooky Halloween pumpkin, but I've always felt it was a pity to use this fruit for decoration alone.</p>
        <p>Pumpkin soups there are aplenty, and I make them often at this time of year. I'm fond of a roasted wedge in place of potatoes, too. But I knew it was possible to cook the whole pumpkin, to make a proper meal of it stuffed with rice and spices and dried fruit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is something about the bulging brightness of a pumpkin that is fabulously compelling. Just seeing pumpkins piled high in the stores fills me with harvest festival spirit. I do not have anything against a gloriously spooky Halloween pumpkin, but I've always felt it was a pity to use this fruit for decoration alone.</p>
        <p>Pumpkin soups there are aplenty, and I make them often at this time of year. I'm fond of a roasted wedge in place of potatoes, too. But I knew it was possible to cook the whole pumpkin, to make a proper meal of it stuffed with rice and spices and dried fruit.</p>
        <p>I have been dying to do this for some time but thought an altogether different person -- someone less clumsy -- was the sort to scrape out pumpkins, stuff them and bake them. I also suspected I was too lazy for this work, but the strange truth is that the recipe here is one of the simplest you can imagine. And the result is magisterial, beautiful and inviting.</p>
        <p>The quantity of rice specified in the recipe is what I needed for the pumpkin I stipulate, but I should say two things here. One is that you might not find (or want) a pumpkin of exactly the same weight. The other is that different pumpkins have different-size cavities. The easiest way to find out how much rice you need is as follows:</p>
        <p>When you have cut the top off and scraped out the seeds, take a plastic freezer bag and line the cavity with it. Pour rice into the bag to about halfway up the cavity, then pour out the rice into a measuring cup. Double the measurement to determine how much stock or water to cook the rice in. The plastic liner is not a hygiene thing: it is just that if you don't use it, you will spend ages scraping out the rice. I know whereof I speak.</p>
        <p>The result is beautiful, whole and oven-scorched. It is very gratifying to slice through the pumpkin and hand out glorious coral-fleshed, rice-nubbly wedges to a tableful of hungry guests. The pumpkin's skin softens enough as it bakes, making cutting easy.</p>
        <p>I like to eat this dish just as it is -- it makes a warm, welcoming meal after a chilly evening of trick-or-treating -- but it is also very good with a tomato sauce poured over each slice as you serve. To make the sauce, you need do no more than finely chop an onion and soften it in a little oil in a pan. Then mince in a clove of garlic, add a can or two of chopped canned tomatoes, a teaspoon of sugar and salt and a grinding of pepper, and cook for 20 minutes until everything has amalgamated into a thick red sauce. Sometimes I add half a teaspoon of ground ginger to it along with the garlic. Sometimes I throw in an inch of fresh garlic, removing it once the sauce is cooked.</p>
        <p>With or without the sauce, this is a fine meal, worth bearing in mind to serve at Thanksgiving if you have vegetarians at your table: it is quite as spectacularly celebratory as a roast turkey.</p>
        <p>The cookies here have none of the pumpkin's autumnal majesty, but Halloween is not one of the most dignified of festivals. These monster cookies, studded with colored candies (delicious if they are peanut-filled, too), are an amazing way to end a grown-up supper, and a very useful way to keep a roomful of boisterous children happy.</p>
        <p>ROASTED STUFFED PUMPKIN  Time: About 2 hours</p>
        <p>1 6 1/2- to 7-pound sugar pumpkin, or other pumpkin suitable for eating  1 tablespoon vegetable oil  1 onion, finely chopped  3 cloves garlic, 2 minced, 1 halved  1 cup dried cranberries  1 teaspoon ground ginger  1 teaspoon allspice</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon saffron threads  Finely grated zest of half an orange  2 cups basmati rice  4 cups vegetable stock  Salt.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oven to 400 degrees. Fill a kettle with water, and bring to a boil. About an inch below the top of the pumpkin's ''shoulders,'' about where it would be cut to carve a jack-o'-lantern, slice a lid from top of pumpkin, and set it aside. Remove seeds and fibrous flesh from inside.  2. In a large saucepan over medium-low heat, heat the oil, and sauté the onion until it is softened. Add 2 minced garlic cloves, and sauté for 30 seconds. Stir in the cranberries, ginger, allspice, saffron and orange zest. Add the rice, and stir until it is glossy. Pour in stock, and bring to a boil. Cover, and reduce heat as low as possible. Cook for 15 minutes. Meanwhile rub the inside of pumpkin with cut garlic clove, and rub with some salt to taste.  3. When rice has cooked for 15 minutes, it will be damp and not very fluffy. Adjust seasoning to taste, and spoon into pumpkin cavity. Press lid firmly on top. It may sit above stuffing a bit like a jaunty cork. Wrap bottom two to three inches of pumpkin in a double layer of foil to protect it from contact with water during baking. Place in a roasting pan, and add about 1 inch of boiling water to pan.  4. Bake the pumpkin until it is tender when pierced with a knife, about 1 1/2 hours. (If there is resistance when pumpkin is pierced, allow more baking time.) To serve, remove pumpkin from pan, and allow it to rest for about 10 minutes. Discard foil, and place pumpkin on a serving platter. Slice into segments like a cake. Place a wedge of pumpkin on each serving plate, and mound with rice stuffing.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 to 10 servings.</p>
        <p>MONSTER HALLOWEEN COOKIES  Time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>1 cup flour</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon baking powder</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon salt  1 cup rolled oats  9 tablespoons butter, at room temperature</p>
        <p>1/2 cup light brown sugar</p>
        <p>1/2 cup superfine sugar  1 large egg  1 teaspoon vanilla extract</p>
        <p>3/4 cup chopped pecans  1 cup M&amp;M's or other sugar-coated candies in Halloween colors.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oven to 350 degrees. In a small bowl combine flour, baking powder, salt and rolled oats. Set aside. In the bowl of an electric mixer combine butter, light brown sugar and superfine sugar. Beat until creamy. Add egg and vanilla, and beat again until smooth.  2. Add flour mixture to butter mixture, and beat until smooth. By hand, fold in chopped pecans and M&amp;M's.  3. Roll quarter-cup measures of dough into balls and flatten them into fat disks (about  1/2 inch thick). Place on a parchment-lined or greased baking sheet, about 6 at a time, so they have room to spread.  4. Bake until cookies are risen, dry on surface and very lightly browned, 15 to 20 minutes. They will be too soft to lift from baking sheet. Set aside to harden for 5 minutes, then transfer to a wire rack to cool.</p>
        <p>Yield: 12 3 1/2- to 4-inch cookies.</p>
        <p>AT MY TABLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
