<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stella McCartney: Ready for Chloe</title>
    <meta content="22DRES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="924607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Fashion Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Stella McCartney</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chloe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spindler, Amy M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccartney, Stella</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D9143EF931A15757C0A961958260" item-length="1534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stella McCartney: Ready for Chloe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY M. SPINDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spindler, Amy M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amy M Spindler reviews fashions designed by Stella McCartney for Chloe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Bernard Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moet Hennessy-Louis Vuitton, chose two young British designers to head up Christian Dior and Givenchy, the French Establishment could be a bit blithe. Mr. Arnault is press hungry, shows off his power, thrives on doing the unthinkable.</p>
        <p>But when yet another big luxury goods house, the Vendome Group, put Stella McCartney, 25 and British, in charge of its Chloe collection, it seemed like more than one man's eccentricities. It seemed like a trend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Bernard Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moet Hennessy-Louis Vuitton, chose two young British designers to head up Christian Dior and Givenchy, the French Establishment could be a bit blithe. Mr. Arnault is press hungry, shows off his power, thrives on doing the unthinkable.</p>
        <p>But when yet another big luxury goods house, the Vendome Group, put Stella McCartney, 25 and British, in charge of its Chloe collection, it seemed like more than one man's eccentricities. It seemed like a trend.</p>
        <p>How will the French Establishment rationalize it this time?</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that it is the age, more than the nationality, that is hitting a nerve.</p>
        <p>When the usually composed Karl Lagerfeld, being replaced at Chloe, sniped at the fresh young woman who will take his post, it was a bit like the Beatles sniping at Oasis.</p>
        <p>''I think they should have taken a big name,'' Mr. Lagerfeld said to Women's Wear Daily. ''They did -- but in music, not fashion. Let's hope she is as gifted as her father.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McCartney's father is, of course, Paul McCartney, and her mother is Linda McCartney, who bought some of Mr. Lagerfeld's Chloe pieces in the 1970's and stored them in a trunk. It was as if the clothes were waiting for Ms. McCartney, whose first fashion memory is of stomping around in the gold platform boots her mother wore to the premiere of ''Easy Rider,'' to reclaim them.</p>
        <p>''What's funny about Chloe is I grew up knowing it on that level,'' Ms. McCartney said. ''Friends of my parents have called and have been so over the moon and proud because when they were growing up it was a hot label. My generation has no idea of that. It's not doing that at the moment.''</p>
        <p>In Ms. McCartney, Chloe has found a designer who seems to have the passion and the steely nerve for the uneasy position of taking over from Mr. Lagerfeld, who presided over the hottest years of Chloe, from 1965 to 1983, and then was rehired by Mounir Moufarrige in 1992, with less success. The Independent of London underlined the age issue this week: ''While Karl Lagerfeld prides himself on how up-to-date he is with MTV, Stella McCartney doesn't need to watch it -- she lives it anyway.''</p>
        <p>Putting designers with so little experience in creative control of such big corporations seems a heavy proposition. Ms. McCartney's name clearly gave her a short-cut in the publicity-driven fashion world, but she was not the only 20-something designer interviewed; Antonio Berardi was as well.</p>
        <p>''If they went for the name thing, what they also get with Stella McCartney is a good designer,'' said Elizabeth Tilberis, the editor of Harper's Bazaar, who once hired Ms. McCartney as an intern at British Vogue. ''Someone young, but who has loved fashion since she was little. Linda never took part in fashion. At the end of the Beatles heyday and beginning of Wings, when I was in London, she wasn't in that scene. So she didn't get it from Linda. It came from someplace all her own.''</p>
        <p>As a student at Central St. Martin's College of Art and Design, the fashion school that also produced John Galliano, now at Dior, and Alexander McQueen, at Givenchy, she asked her close friends from the London scene -- Kate Moss, Yasmin Le Bon and Naomi Campbell -- to model her graduation collection. Her parents and Twiggy were in the front row. Marlon Brando crying ''Stella'' in ''A Streetcar Named Desire'' was on the soundtrack, along with a song her father wrote for the occasion,  ''Stella Mayday.''</p>
        <p>The resulting hype in 1995 upstaged the shows of all her fellow graduates, and had made her lose some sleep beforehand.</p>
        <p>''Coming from my background, I don't want to be punished for it,'' she said. ''If I say no to that kind of thing, I'm being punished. I don't think people should have the upper hand on what I want to do. I'm not trying to shove it into people's faces. But there's a certain amount of people controlling your life, and at the end of the day, you do what you want if you don't offend too many people.''</p>
        <p>At the idea that she might be relieved to close the house with her father's last name and hide behind the Chloe label, Ms. McCartney said: ''I think it's actually worse. Until now, I was in control of what I was doing; little shows, taking it slowly, choose who I want to see the collection. Now, they'll all be there, people I'd never have shown my clothes to. I think people are going to be ready to shoot me down.''</p>
        <p>Those people will find a fairly unsinkable target. When she felt she wasn't learning enough at St. Martin's, she apprenticed herself out to a tailor to learn Savile Row suit making. Compulsive visits to the flea market inspired the lace-trimmed slip dresses that are the core of her house's style, and an important part of the Chloe look as well. Despite her father's estimated worth of $600 million, she financed her first collection by selling her St. Martin's work.</p>
        <p>And she has a good brain for marketing, as even the student show proved. ''My mind does work like that,'' she said. ''I'm very much like, 'STELLA!' '' she said, doing the Brando wail, ''or use your initials.'' Her initials are S.N.M., and the sadomasochistic wordplay has been embroidered on her shirts.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to try to entertain the world's press, if they're all expecting some kind of freak-show event,'' she said. Her first Chloe show will be in October. ''But then my marketing mind says, let's do it outside at the Eiffel Tower with helicopters,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Last week, Ms. McCartney was on the front page of every newspaper in London, making Mr. Moufarrige, the man who hired her, look like a genius to rival Mr. Arnault. At least he seems to have taken a page from Mr. Arnault's book.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen Mr. Arnault's book, so I don't know how many pages are in it,'' Mr. Moufarrige, the president of Chloe, said. ''Our main priority in getting Stella in was for her talent to get the product. If that's helped by publicity and media excitement, we're privileged, but in the end of the day, what helps is selling the product.''</p>
        <p>It was Ms. McCartney herself who suggested to Mr. Moufarrige that she take the top job. She was approached originally to design a younger, second line for the company. ''They thought, 'She'll be great for the young thing,' '' she said. ''And I said, 'I'll do the old thing.' Hopefully, we'll do the young thing and the old thing.''</p>
        <p>Which has made her the Peggy Lipton figure in a trio that might just become a sartorial Mod Squad.</p>
        <p>''I'm so surprised to be linked with McQueen and Galliano,'' Ms. McCartney said. ''They're the two dudes, aren't they?''</p>
        <p>Mr. McQueen senses a bond: he sent her flowers and went out with her the night after the announcement, to offer her words of advice.</p>
        <p>She has been part of a revolutionary first-time collection before. When she was 15, she worked for a summer in the studio of Patou, when Christian Lacroix was producing his first collection, a fairy tale beginning that ended with Mr. Arnault financing him in his own house.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, it had a bit of fur in it,'' Ms. McCartney said of that collection, something she does take from her vegetarian mother.</p>
        <p>Until now, it's just been Ms. McCartney and Phoebe Philo, who will have the title of first design assistant at Chloe, in the Notting Hill studio above Ms. Philo's house, where they have tripped their way through the land mines of the industry.</p>
        <p>''People are always ringing up, and we don't know who they are,'' Ms. Philo said. ''Sometimes it's bad, and sometimes it's cool, because we treat them as equals. No hierarchy malarkey.''</p>
        <p>There will certainly be plenty of hierarchy malarkey at Chloe.</p>
        <p>''They seem very aware that it's going to be Stella McCartney for Chloe, not Stella McCartney trying to keep everyone happy at Chloe,'' Ms. McCartney said. ''I wouldn't have closed down my own thing if I didn't believe that. And I wouldn't have taken the job if I thought I was going to be restricted. I think about the customer because I'm a girl.''</p>
        <p>Girl, of course, is the operative word.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
