<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance; Ferocious, As Becomes The Tyger</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="416264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY BALLET</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOTO, JOCK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALEGARI, MARIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6173CF93AA25752C0A967958260" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance; Ferocious, As Becomes The Tyger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Fearful Symmetries" is exciting but, fortunately, not dangerous. One of Peter Martins's best pieces of choreography, the work unites total control with the illusion of reckless abandon. Its performance by the New York City Ballet on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater was a fine example of disciplined energy.</p>
        <p>The piece takes its title from that of its propulsive score by John Adams. He, in turn, borrowed the title from a phrase in "The Tyger," the poem by William Blake. There is nothing literally feline about either the music or the choreography. Nevertheless, the work does have a tigerish ferocity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Fearful Symmetries" is exciting but, fortunately, not dangerous. One of Peter Martins's best pieces of choreography, the work unites total control with the illusion of reckless abandon. Its performance by the New York City Ballet on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater was a fine example of disciplined energy.</p>
        <p>The piece takes its title from that of its propulsive score by John Adams. He, in turn, borrowed the title from a phrase in "The Tyger," the poem by William Blake. There is nothing literally feline about either the music or the choreography. Nevertheless, the work does have a tigerish ferocity.</p>
        <p>For much of the time, its dancers leap in and out, hurtling along in diagonal patterns or rushing in horizontal lines across the stage. Three couples are given prominence.</p>
        <p>Making debuts in their roles, Helene Alexopoulos and Philip Neal looked assured. Heather Watts and Jock Soto invested the choreography with hard-edged dramatic tension. Margaret Tracey and Albert Evans triumphed over all the work's technical difficulties.</p>
        <p>To a comparatively slow musical passage, Mr. Neal danced with Ms. Watts instead of Ms. Alexopoulos, who then became Mr. Soto's partner. The partner swapping is somewhat puzzling. Nothing that precedes it in this plotless ballet hints at the possibility of such a development and Mr. Martins has not created consistently inventive choreography for the sequence. But when Mr. Adams's tempo picks up again, so does the choreographic interest.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, "Fearful Symmetries" comes to a calm conclusion that suggests that unruly passions have been sufficiently tamed so that they do not lead to catastrophe.</p>
        <p>The evening's other works were buoyant. Jerome Robbins's "I'm Old Fashioned" is splendid entertainment that also teaches an esthetic lesson. It begins with a film: the dance to Jerome Kern's song "I'm Old Fashioned" that Fred Astaire and Rita Hayworth performed in "You Were Never Lovelier," a movie of 1942. Their witty duet is filled with moments of hesitation, separation and reunion. Then Hayworth and Astaire give way to live dancers.</p>
        <p>Although Lourdes Lopez and Damian Woetzel looked nothing like the film stars, they looked very good. And they danced very well through sequences choreographed by Mr. Robbins that were variations on some of the movements introduced in the film. So, too, Morton Gould's score consisted of variations on the Kern song. Other solo dancers were also admirable. Maria Calegari and Mr. Soto were lyrical. Ms. Alexopoulos and Robert La Fosse were playful in one duet, wistful in another.</p>
        <p>If no one was as dapper as Astaire or as glamorous as Hayworth, these dancers were attractive, nonetheless. That is what helped make the ballet entertaining. Moreover, Mr. Robbins's use of movements derived from the film made one realize that Astaire and Hayworth were not simply charismatic personalities. They performed imaginative and well-crafted choreography -- choreography capable of inspiring another imaginative choreographer. In "I'm Old Fashioned," Astaire, Hayworth and Mr. Robbins unite to remind the audience that fine dancers need fine choreography.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tracey and Peter Boal appeared in the leading roles of George Balanchine's "Square Dance," which opened the program. Ms. Tracey's remarkable clarity made every step and pose seem an illustration from a technique manual. But she danced too much like a dutiful student. Now she must find a way to use her discipline as the root from which a sense of delight can blossom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boal was equally correct, but far more engaging in his dancing. He served as an elegant partner to Ms. Tracey and also gave a convincing interpretation of the ballet's tender solo. Some dancers emphasize the choreography's melancholy. But the way Mr. Boal stretched outward implied that, although he may have been a pensive young man, he was also reaching toward an ideal.</p>
        <p>Gordon Boelzner and Hugo Fiorato were the program's conductors. Although the orchestra was competent in "Fearful Symmetries" and "I'm Old Fashioned," its string tone sounded unpleasantly harsh in "Square Dance."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
