<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parents Sue Alabama Over School Financing</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="416208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALABAMA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CELIS, WILLIAM 3D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDA1438F93AA25752C0A967958260" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parents Sue Alabama Over School Financing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM CELIS 3d</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CELIS, WILLIAM 3D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alabama education officials were sued yesterday by parents who charge that the school finance system is unconstitutional because it distributes an inadequate amount of state money to public schools and does so inequitably.</p>
        <p>The suit, filed in State Circuit Court in Montgomery by a group of parents representing 37 children, was the second case in nine months against the Alabama Department of Education and other agencies and officials in charge of public schools finances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alabama education officials were sued yesterday by parents who charge that the school finance system is unconstitutional because it distributes an inadequate amount of state money to public schools and does so inequitably.</p>
        <p>The suit, filed in State Circuit Court in Montgomery by a group of parents representing 37 children, was the second case in nine months against the Alabama Department of Education and other agencies and officials in charge of public schools finances.</p>
        <p>The state superintendent of schools, Wayne Teague, was not available for comment yesterday. But last May after a suit was filed by the Alabama Coaltion for Equity Inc., a group of parents and school districts, he said he supported efforts to overhaul the finance system. He termed it unfortunate that the issue would be addressed in court.</p>
        <p>The issue of public school financing has increasingly drawn states into court as more parents and school districts challenge finance systems. Alabama became the 14th state since 1987 to be sued over the issue, according to the Education Commission of the States, a research and policy group in Denver.  Spending Per Student Varies</p>
        <p>In Alabama, as in most of the other states being sued, the money spent per student by the state's 129 school districts is at issue. For example, the Mountain Brook City School System spends $4,302 annually on each student, while $2,563 is spent on each student in the Lee County Schools, one of the poorer districts in the state and the home of the parents who sued.</p>
        <p>Sixty-five percent of local school district financing comes from the state, while 18.4 percent comes from local sources like property taxes, according to the Alabama Department of Education. The rest is mostly Federal aid.</p>
        <p>Although state aid is based on the daily average attendance of students in each district, local contributions vary greatly because property-rich school districts can raise more school taxes at lower rates than property-poor school systems can. The suit asks that this system be declared unconstitutional. If that happened, it would have to be revised by new state legislation.</p>
        <p>The suit also claims that a 1956 amendment to the state constitution helped create inequities in the state school finance formula by absolving the state of any obligation to provide a public education.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit says the amendment was an attempt by state officials to evade the 1954 Brown v. Board of Education ruling of the Supreme Court, which required desegregation of public schools. The Alabama amendment created a string of private all-white schools, leaving public schools largely underfinanced and black.</p>
        <p>The new suit, as well as the one filed last spring, underscored longstanding concerns in Alabama over a school system that by virtually every national benchmark is deficient. The United States Department of Education says that in 1988, the most recent year for which the department has figures, Alabama ranked 48th among states in public school spending per student, and 25 percent of the state's public school students did not finish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
