<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Storm Floods Many Areas And Kills 4</title>
    <meta content="21WEAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="884848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DF1730F932A15753C1A960958260" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Storm Floods Many Areas And Kills 4</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City metropolitan area begins cleaning up from ferocious Northeaster that pelted area with record amounts of rain; waters recedes and transit service and travel resume as 54,000 homes remain without power; widespread damage from water and wind-toppled trees is reported; there have been four storm-related deaths; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sun peeked out, floodwaters receded, transit and travel resumed and the World Series finally got under way yesterday as the metropolitan area's worst rainstorm in years churned off, leaving almost 52,000 homes still without power, widespread damage from water and wind-toppled trees, and four storm-related deaths.</p>
        <p>The ferocious northeaster on Saturday dropped record-for-the-date rains in Central Park and Newark, and deluged other parts of New Jersey with up to 8.6 inches; cut power to 341,000 homes in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, and flooded coasts, rivers and low-lying homes and highways across the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sun peeked out, floodwaters receded, transit and travel resumed and the World Series finally got under way yesterday as the metropolitan area's worst rainstorm in years churned off, leaving almost 52,000 homes still without power, widespread damage from water and wind-toppled trees, and four storm-related deaths.</p>
        <p>The ferocious northeaster on Saturday dropped record-for-the-date rains in Central Park and Newark, and deluged other parts of New Jersey with up to 8.6 inches; cut power to 341,000 homes in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, and flooded coasts, rivers and low-lying homes and highways across the region.</p>
        <p>It also disrupted commuter trains and subway service, curtailed flights at La Guardia, Kennedy and Newark airports, forced hundreds to evacuate flooded homes and lashed the region with howling winds of 50 to 60 miles an hour that uprooted trees and brought down utility poles. One hurricane-force gust of 81 miles an hour was reported on Fire Island.</p>
        <p>''This is the worst, I would say, in 20 years,'' Ralph Nalepka, the owner of the Millstone Sports Shop in Millstone, N.J., said as he looked out on North Street, which was still under four feet of water yesterday from the overflowed confluence of the Raritan and Millstone Rivers.</p>
        <p>But as the storm trailed off into New England and waters receded across the region, pale lemon sunlight found breaks in the canopy of charcoal gray, lifting spirits, especially at Yankee Stadium, where the wash from helicopter blades helped dry a soggy field in time for last night's World Series opener.</p>
        <p>Coming on a weekend, the storm caused minimal disruptions for those lucky enough to be snug in dry homes, and the rain was an awesome spectacle: it fell in great sheets that thundered on pavements, hissed like surf against windows, beat a tattoo on rooftops and stripped the bronze and russet leaves of autumn.</p>
        <p>But the authorities said the storm was also responsible for at least four deaths in the metropolitan area. The New Jersey State Police said Jose Acosta, 47, of Paterson, was killed when he lost control of his car on rain-slicked Route 80 and was struck by a bus.</p>
        <p>And three people were killed by falling trees: 12-year-old James Cummings, as he stood with friends in a driveway in Babylon, L.I., waiting for a ride home; Silvio P. Marino, 79, of Bedford Hills, N.Y., whose car was crushed on a highway in Hawthorne, N.Y., and Glenn A. Deatcher, 40, of South Salem, N.Y., whose pickup truck was struck in New Canaan, Conn.</p>
        <p>The Long Island, Connecticut and New Jersey shores were hit hard by the storm, whose winds hurled high tides and pounding rain against the coasts. Flooding hit Bayville, Lindenhurst, Massapequa and Freeport on Long Island; Norwalk, Westport, Stamford and Greenwich in Connecticut, and towns along the Raritan, Millstone, Rahway, Ramapo and Saddle Rivers in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, 300 residents of Manville, Bound Brook and Cranford were evacuated from flooded homes. Gov. Christine Todd Whitman visited some of the stricken areas yesterday. In New York City, scores of homes were flooded in Springfield Gardens, Queens; in Edgewater Park in the Bronx, and in the Sea Gate and Gerritsen Beach sections of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>P.J.'s Restaurant on City Island in the Bronx, which lost a pier and dining area in a comparable 1992 storm, stayed open through the tempest, serving patrons who ate with their feet in six inches of water. ''When I rebuilt the place, I put the wall up here and thought I was home free,'' John Piro, the owner, said with a nod of gratitude for his soggy clientele. ''This bothers me.''</p>
        <p>As the sun came out and residents across the region returned home to assess the flood damage, the National Weather Service confirmed that the rains had been the heaviest in years. Central Park had 4.35 inches of rain, and Newark had 4.04 inches, both eclipsing records for the date set in 1966.</p>
        <p>More than 4 inches fell in each of the five boroughs of New York City, and the totals were 5.15 inches in White Plains, 3 to 5 inches on Long Island, and more than 4 inches in Waterbury and Bridgeport, Conn. The heaviest rains fell in New Jersey: 8.6 inches in Passaic Township, 7.68 inches in Verona, 7.41 in West Orange, 6.36 inches in Wayne, 6.88 inches in Canoe Brook and 6.98 inches in Elizabeth.</p>
        <p>Power problems were still widespread yesterday, although utilities across the region had hundreds of crews working around the clock to clear fallen trees and rebuild collapsed utility lines, and officials said many customers were not expected to be back on line until late today.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, where power to 91,000 homes and businesses failed in the storm, 33,600 customers of Northeast Utilities, mostly in Fairfield County, were still without electricity.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Lighting Company, which had 145,000 customers lose service during the storm, reported 12,800 still without power late last night.</p>
        <p>Consolidated Edison, which reported 48,000 customers without power in the storm, mostly in coastal Westchester County, had all but about 6,000 back in service by last night. Of 45,000 customers of New Jersey Electric and Gas who had lost power in Bergen, Hudson and Passaic Counties, all but about 1,500, mostly in Bergen County, were back in service late yesterday.</p>
        <p>Most highways were again clear and subway and bus service resumed normal schedules. Flights left the airports with minimal delays. La Guardia Airport, closed Saturday afternoon after a Delta Air Lines plane skidded off a runway, reopened in stages yesterday. And rail commuters were expected to see near-normal service at the start of the work week this morning.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road, which reported 90-minute delays on all lines in the storm, cleared trees from tracks and was almost back on schedule yesterday when a washout was discovered on the Port Jefferson branch between Northport and Kings Park. Buses were provided yesterday, but Susan McGowan, a spokeswoman, said the line would run normally today.</p>
        <p>Metro-North, which reported 45-minute delays as scores of trees toppled over tracks and signals on the New Haven and Harlem lines Saturday, was back on schedule yesterday.</p>
        <p>But repairs to power lines were still under way at Pelham, N.Y., and buses were being run on the tree-damaged New Canaan branch of the New Haven line, Dan Brucker, a spokesman, said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
