<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What It Means to Be Both Cuban and American</title>
    <meta content="27GENE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1179786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPRING THEATER/VISIONS OF AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fornes, Maria Irene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Nilo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D81230F934A15751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What It Means to Be Both Cuban and American</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuban-American playwrights Maria Irene Fornes and Nilo Cruz talk about influence of their homeland and adopted country on their playwriting; excerpts from their tape-recorded conversation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A GENERATION separates the Cuban-American playwrights Maria Irene Fornes and Nilo Cruz. Ms. Fornes was 15 when she left Cuba in 1945 -- long before Fidel Castro seized power in the 1959 revolution. Mr. Cruz was 9 when he and his parents left in 1970.</p>
        <p>Today, nearing 70 and epitomizing the outsider tradition of the Off Off Broadway theater movement, Ms. Fornes is being celebrated by the Signature Theater Company with a seasonlong festival of her work. The world premiere of her latest play, ''Letters From Cuba,'' continues through March 12 at the Signature. Directed by the author, it is based on more than 200 letters she received over 30 years from an older brother who remained in Cuba. After writing some 30 plays, musicals and operas, ''Letters From Cuba'' is the first time that Ms. Fornes has dealt directly in her work with her Cuban heritage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A GENERATION separates the Cuban-American playwrights Maria Irene Fornes and Nilo Cruz. Ms. Fornes was 15 when she left Cuba in 1945 -- long before Fidel Castro seized power in the 1959 revolution. Mr. Cruz was 9 when he and his parents left in 1970.</p>
        <p>Today, nearing 70 and epitomizing the outsider tradition of the Off Off Broadway theater movement, Ms. Fornes is being celebrated by the Signature Theater Company with a seasonlong festival of her work. The world premiere of her latest play, ''Letters From Cuba,'' continues through March 12 at the Signature. Directed by the author, it is based on more than 200 letters she received over 30 years from an older brother who remained in Cuba. After writing some 30 plays, musicals and operas, ''Letters From Cuba'' is the first time that Ms. Fornes has dealt directly in her work with her Cuban heritage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cruz, who is almost 40, has explored his own sociopolitical roots in such plays as ''Dancing on Her Knees'' and ''A Park in Our House.'' He discovered theater in 1981 as a member of a local troupe in Miami, and in the late 1980's directed Ms. Fornes's play ''Mud'' at the South End Alternative Theater there. Ms. Fornes saw it and invited him to become a member of her Intar Hispanic Playwrights Laboratory, now defunct, where he started to write seriously. His current play, ''Two Sisters and a Piano,'' directed by his frequent collaborator, Loretta Greco, runs through March 12 at the Joseph Papp Public Theater. It is based in part on the lives of his sisters and a cousin in Miami and on the house arrest of the dissident Cuban poet Maria Elena Cruz Varela, who in 1991 was forced by Cuban security agents to eat some of her political writings and was sentenced to two years in prison.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fornes and Mr. Cruz talked recently in Manhattan with Randy Gener, a reporter for Theatre.com and a freelance theater critic, about the influences of their homeland and adopted country on their playwriting. Here are edited excerpts from the tape-recorded conversation.</p>
        <p>Q.  As Cuban-Americans and as dramatists, how strongly have you taken on social and political matters in your two new plays?</p>
        <p>MARIA IRENE FORNES.  My play never mentions Castro.</p>
        <p>NILO CRUZ.  Neither does mine.</p>
        <p>FORNES.  Your play mentions a person in prison. So it is more directly about politics. My play deals with life in Cuba but it is set in two places -- Cuba and America. On the stage set, there is a regular apartment in New York but only a roof in Cuba. The Cuban world on the roof has stars above it all the time. There is a girl who receives letters in America written by my brother in Communist Cuba. But he could be living in another city where there aren't too many advantages. It could be a small Italian village. It's not that I was avoiding talking about politics. It just didn't seem to be the energy of the play. What interested me was that all of my family had left Cuba, and my brother was still there. Yet he was never a sympathizer with the Castro regime.</p>
        <p>Q.  Why did he choose to remain in Cuba?</p>
        <p>FORNES.  To me, it has to do with attachment. It's something that we usually don't think of: place as a love. It seems almost corny -- I don't know why I'm crying. But I'm so moved by the idea of loving a place. Usually you love a person and you cannot live without them. People have an attachment to their animals, their dogs, there's a love there. But the love for place is so hard and so beautiful.</p>
        <p>The New York characters in my play are artists: there is a poet, a painter, and the girl who is a dancer -- my alter ego. In Cuba, there is my brother and his son. In the play, the character who is my brother usually has a letter in his hand, and as he speaks to the person in the New York apartment, he reads the actual text of my brother's letters. We have been corresponding for the last 30 years.</p>
        <p>My brother is now 80. Rafael is the oldest and I am the youngest of six brothers and sisters. In the play, he is called Luis. I guess in some ways I have wanted to write about Cuba but I did not know exactly how.</p>
        <p>Q.  Nilo, your play, too, has your family stitched into it -- the two sisters are based on your own -- although the story also involves the experiences of a real-life dissident poet under house arrest who received letters from her husband in France.</p>
        <p>CRUZ.  Yes, the character Maria Celia, the older sister in the play, writes letters to her husband, and the substance of the play is the letters he writes to her from France. I come from the Irene Fornes school of playwriting. She was my professor and my mentor. I pretty much assemble my plays in the same way Irene does because that's what I learned. I think it's the only way to write.</p>
        <p>As Irene was talking, I was realizing that there are so many parallels. Of course, her play is very different from mine, but my characters go up to the roof, even though they are under house arrest. It's a way to feel outside, in the world; it's almost like getting away with murder, to write while on the roof. In fact, the first line of the script is: ''My dear husband, I am standing on top of this roof wanting to leap into the sky and send you this letter.''</p>
        <p>Although my sister Marilyn was not under house arrest, she was never able to leave the country. She always wanted to leave. She got married when she was 16. My older sister, Martha, who was 19, got to leave Cuba for the United States via Spain.</p>
        <p>Q.  How come Martha left earlier than Marilyn did?</p>
        <p>CRUZ.  She left in 1980 with her husband because she didn't have any children. My sister Marilyn didn't leave because her child was 8 years old. The government always kept people tied to Cuba. Marilyn came to visit us once with a special permit, but she could not come to this country with her husband and child. Since they were left behind, she had to go back. She's 46 now. She has two children and they have both been able to leave Cuba. It was all a scheme: she had to divorce her husband so he could leave Cuba first and she could come back here and remarry him.</p>
        <p>In writing ''Two Sisters and a Piano,'' which is set in 1991, I also drew on the life of a cousin who left a marriage behind in Cuba. I remember her in Miami, always anxious to get mail from her husband. She lived through his letters.</p>
        <p>Q.  How do generational differences affect your identity as Cuban-Americans?</p>
        <p>FORNES.  I came to the United States with my mother. My father had died. We had no means of support in Cuba. We came here for economic reasons. It might not be ideal, but you can work here and earn a living. In Cuba, it wasn't so. When we came here, there was no sadness whatsoever. My mother loved it. I thought I was in a Hollywood movie.</p>
        <p>CRUZ.  Irene is more of an immigrant. I'm more of an exile. I came to the United States with my mother and father. My father was in prison for two years because he was very outspoken about politics. I grew up with my mother, two sisters and my grandmother. My mother had to wash clothes to earn a living. We were not wealthy. I lived about 10 years under Castro, and that's all I knew. I would overhear my parents talking about getting their passports together, but I could not talk about it to friends. I remember having to lie in school.</p>
        <p>FORNES.  The difference between Cubans who leave because they had to, because Cuba under Castro is unbearable, it's such a different story from mine. It must be the most painful thing in the world to leave a place that you love.</p>
        <p>CRUZ.  People might think that my plays are about politics, but the politics are very simple. ''Two Sisters and a Piano'' is about two women who, even though they live in very harsh conditions, make the best of their lives. They create a little paradise in their house. Even though they are under house arrest, they bring out the beautiful china and use a tablecloth. It's the integrity of that, the dignity of it, that moves me.</p>
        <p>Q.  When you write, do you feel a greater responsibility to Cubans or to Cuban-Americans in the United States?</p>
        <p>FORNES.  I don't feel any responsibility at all. If I write something about Hispanic people, it's because I am attracted to writing about it. It may sound selfish, but in my workshops I teach people to write about whatever comes to their minds. You have to approach the state of dreaming, where you put yourself into contact with things that are saying something. The only way to do it is by allowing part of your mind to dream.</p>
        <p>Many Cuban-Americans are too obsessed with Castro. I don't blame them -- they have lost what they knew, their home, their jobs, everything in their whole lives has been taken away. If I lost that, I don't know what I'd do. But sometimes I don't think they are interested in anything else. Their minds have been frozen, almost.</p>
        <p>I remember when I went to Havana in 1962. It was the first celebration after Castro took over. There were all these slogans. People would say slogans to identify themselves, or identify something they liked.</p>
        <p>New York has a number of Cuban-American playwrights who are emerging, but because of the revolution of 1959 I think in some ways the question of a writer's politics becomes an obstacle to developing a real Cuban-American style: either you are anti-Castro if you live here or pro-Castro if you are there.</p>
        <p>In spite of this, some Cuban-American writers here have been able to develop their own personal voice, imagery and style. I would say that Cuban artists tend to display a light surrealism, as opposed to Mexican surrealism, which feels heavier -- in epic rituals, there are always images of skeletons and candles.</p>
        <p>Cuban-Americans put on view an almost subconscious imagery that is a mixture of African culture and Catholic spirituality. In the home of any Cuban family, very middle-class and very white, you will see, for instance, on an altar, a picture of the Santa Barbara [a Roman Catholic saint]. But everybody knows that the picture does not represent an incarnation of the Catholic Virgin Mary. That picture is a disguise for a Yoruban deity, like a double exposure. They see one image, but they are really dancing to another. The two images have blended together. When you think of a Cuban-American style, it has to do with a different coloring, a different tempo.</p>
        <p>CRUZ.  My identity as an artist is what defines who I am more than anything else. I don't identify with a lot of Cuban-Americans in Miami, or with Cubans in Cuba. I find that Cubans in Miami tend to be too radical. I also feel that some people in Cuba are still very dogmatic. Lately, I've been writing a lot about Cuba. I feel that my own reality was so tinged by the political situation of my country that I have to reflect on it. I'm interested in documenting history, but ultimately my plays are about being an individual. Belonging to a particular group, left or right, entails a political loss. When you embrace your whole being and all that you can be in this world, that's the strongest position.</p>
        <p>SPRING THEATER/VISIONS OF AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
