<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop/Jazz; A New Generation Of Performers Is Revitalizing Cabarets</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="172340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FASCINATING AIDE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAUX, ANGELINA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEGERE, PHOEBE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAUGHERTY, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FIELD, ROBIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARNAR, JEFF</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D71638F93AA2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop/Jazz; A New Generation Of Performers Is Revitalizing Cabarets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: EXCEPT for Teresa Stratas, no singer in recent memory has brought to the music of Kurt Weill the combination of vocal bravura and fiery theatricality that the young soprano Angelina Reaux infuses into the composer's songs. In ''Stranger Here Myself,'' her one-woman cabaret show at the Public Theater, the singer and actress interprets some two dozen</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: EXCEPT for Teresa Stratas, no singer in recent memory has brought to the music of Kurt Weill the combination of vocal bravura and fiery theatricality that the young soprano Angelina Reaux infuses into the composer's songs. In ''Stranger Here Myself,'' her one-woman cabaret show at the Public Theater, the singer and actress interprets some two dozen</p>
        <p>EXCEPT for Teresa Stratas, no singer in recent memory has brought to the music of Kurt Weill the combination of vocal bravura and fiery theatricality that the young soprano Angelina Reaux infuses into the composer's songs. In ''Stranger Here Myself,'' her one-woman cabaret show at the Public Theater, the singer and actress interprets some two dozen Weill songs from the point of view of a suicidal bohemian rebel thrashing through her memories alone in a hotel room.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reaux is a Leonard Bernstein protegee who sings the role of Mimi in his new recording of ''La Boheme.'' She stands as a vivid and heartening reminder that cabaret, which is often thought of as a fading art form kept alive by middle-aged female Broadway performers, continues to attract young talent. Most, if not all, are in it for love, not money.</p>
        <p>In clubs around New York, the kind of young performers whom the cabaret world needs to renew itself are unusually visible this weekend. At Michael's Pub, Phoebe Legere, a flamboyantly gifted singer, composer and performance artist, is singing with the Hot Club of France, a Long Island acoustic jazz band named after the gypsy guitarist Django Reinhardt's legendary ensemble. The band, which is rapidly becoming the club's house band, is led by Frank Vignola, a Long Island-based guitar whiz who happens to be in his early 20's.</p>
        <p>This evening at Eighty Eight's, a comfortably appointed new Greenwich Village club, the young male duo Daugherty and Field will perform their musical Bob and Ray-style act, which interweaves witty repartee with elegant two-part singing. Jeff Harnar, who will appear at Eighty Eight's tomorrow evening, is, at age 29, an equally talented singer whose heartfelt renditions of pop and show tunes recall Larry Kert in ''West Side Story.'' British music hall silliness glitters on the stage of the Ballroom in Chelsea, where three sequin-clad singing comediennes who call themselves Fascinating Aida perform a frothy revue of original satirical songs.</p>
        <p>A former musical-comedy belter who has re-directed her career toward the opera, Ms. Reaux has long been fascinated with Kurt Weill's music. She was a student of Martha Schlamme, one of the foremost Weill interpreters. In December 1986, Ms. Reaux created a splash singing two Weill songs at the Public Theater's star-studded AIDS benefit organized by her mentor, Mr. Bernstein. ''Stranger Here Myself,'' which she created with the director Christopher Alden, evolved out of a concert program of Weill songs that she presented outside of New York.</p>
        <p>''Some people don't seem to understand that the show is a theater piece with a plot line,'' Ms. Reaux emphasized the other day. ''A woman near the end of her rope enters a hotel room where she contemplates suicide. Catching a reflection of herself in the mirror, she begins wondering how she got into this state. The songs, all sung with no dialogue and no break, become a capsulization of her life. We've deliberately tried to take the concert cabaret form into another dimension.''</p>
        <p>As an interpreter of Weill, Ms. Reaux is markedly different from singers like Lotte Lenya, Miss Schlamme and Julie Wilson, who brought more theatricality than vocal refinement to the composer's songs. Ms. Reaux, who has the endorsement of the Kurt Weill Foundation, possesses a rich, luscious soprano that caresses Weill's melodies. Even the most caustic Brecht-Weill collaborations assume a tinge of sweetness when she performs them, always in their original keys, which are higher than what we have grown used to from the many husky-voiced interpreters who transpose them down in pitch. For an encore, Ms. Reaux performs the American premiere of a lovely early Weill rarity, ''Die Stille Stadt'' (''The Silent City''), which the composer wrote when he was 18 years old. The song was a gift from the Weill Foundation, which is devoted to the propagation of the composer's legacy.  Phoebe Legere</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Reaux, Phoebe Legere has also inhabited more than one musical world. A singer with a four-octave range, she is a trained pianist, cellist and composer who has written both experimental art songs and rock. Her large-scale experimental opera, ''Hello, Mrs. President,'' about the first woman to be President of the United States (a 280-pound cleaning woman selected by computer to ''clean up America''), has been presented at St. Mark's Church. In the movie ''Mondo New York,'' she performs a song from that opera. And in the forthcoming movie ''The Toxic Avenger II,'' she portrays a blind accordionist. At Michael's Pub, Ms. Legere is revealing the more conservative side of her musical sensibility.</p>
        <p>''I've spent an enormous amount of money entertaining my friends with spectacles that mixed the intellectual and the erotic,'' Ms. Legere said last week. ''But so many people seem to want me just to sing a song. It really seems to work better than having nubile nymphs writhing on the floor in diaphanous costumes to atonal music.''</p>
        <p>At Michael's Pub, Ms. Legere, whose provocatively sexy demeanor evokes a post-hippie Marilyn Monroe, concentrates on singing pop standards - from ''Anything Goes'' to the Patsy Cline hit ''Walkin' After Midnight'' - in a sultry pop-blues growl. At one point, she strolls through the audience with an accordion, singing ''Under the Bridges of Paris.'' Oddly and interestingly, Ms. Legere and the band put Edith Piaf, Django Reinhardt, Bessie Smith, Patsy Cline and Marilyn Monroe on the same wavelength.  Daugherty and Field</p>
        <p>Good singing in a somewhat more conventional mode can be heard at Eighty Eight's tonight and tomorrow from Daugherty and Field and Mr. Harnar, two acts that should help disprove the conventional wisdom that the intimacy of cabaret makes it predominantly a woman's field.</p>
        <p>Bill Daugherty, a singer in his late 20's, and Robin Field, a songwriter, pianist and singer in his early 40's, enjoy one of those onstage chemistries that have the feel of a natural show-business compatibility. In ''Remember Radio?,'' one of their friskier numbers, the pair compress several decades of radio programs and personalities into an amusing montage of musical themes and sound effects. Their ''Salute to the Great Teams'' encompasses show business duos from Abbott and Costello to Burns and Allen to Mickey Mouse and Donald Duck. Balancing these nostalgic frolics are medleys that tie familiar songs - ''If I Love Again'' with ''If Love Were All, ''Mood Indigo'' with ''Rockin' Chair,'' ''Not a Day Goes By'' with ''Johanna'' - into lovely and intricate musical slipknots.</p>
        <p>''What's interesting about our partnership is that when we met two years ago, neither of us was looking for a partner,'' Mr. Field said last week. ''One night I heard Bill sing at the Five Oaks Restaurant in the Village and offered him a tape of my original songs. He called to say he would like to work on them, and I started out as his accompanist who would make a comment or two in the background. Bill is a musical sibyl with many different voices inside him. During the next year, we discovered that people became the most excited when we sang together. Professionally, we are pledged to each other in an unofficial noncontracted way.''</p>
        <p>The economics of cabaret are so precarious that rising young acts like Daugherty and Field have take on other work to make ends meet. Mr. Daugherty works in a record store, while Mr. Field does assorted musical chores from commercials to community theater. Mr. Harnar, who appears tomorrow at Eighty Eight's, used to work as the houseboy for the entertainer Phyllis McGuire (of the McGuire Sisters), and at the moment he supports himself as a singing waiter on the Upper West Side.  Jeff Harnar</p>
        <p>Mr. Harnar, who moved to New York in 1981 hoping for a career in Broadway musicals, developed an earlier version of his present cabaret act with Brian Lasser, the musical director for Karen Mason and one of the busiest and most creative arrangers on New York's cabaret circuit.</p>
        <p>''When I first approached Brian, he told me he didn't think cabaret worked for men, because audiences aren't ready to deal with male vulnerability,'' Mr. Harnar said. ''That brought us to the question of how far can you go and still be embraced by both men and women in an audience. The show we created was a 'Candide'-like journey that had a dark ending. This one retains some of the structure and material of the old one but is more upbeat. Instead of finding a subtext to the lyrics, I try to bring an optimistic feel to them.''</p>
        <p>The high points of Mr. Harnar's act include emotional renditions of ''Pick Yourself Up'' from the movie ''Swing Time,'' ''Yes,'' from the Kander and Ebb show ''70 Girls 70,'' and an original Lasser song, ''I'm a Little Guy.'' While communicating intense feeling, Mr. Harnar stops short of mawkishness.</p>
        <p>''There's no more fulfilling feeling than having shaped an evening that leaves people feeling moved and entertained,'' Mr. Harnar said. He could have been speaking for the hundreds of singers around the city who do cabaret with only distant expectations of stardom.  Fascinating Aida</p>
        <p>The three-woman song and comedy act Fascinating Aida epitomizes the lighter side of cabaret. In the show at the Ballroom, the trio, clad in sequined showgirl outfits, performs original lightly satirical songs. Most of them are written by the group's founder, Dillie Keane, and poke fun at everything from German lieder to Chekhov's ''Three Sisters.'' Their songs, patter and attitude belong to a tradition of nonsensical humor that includes Flanders and Swann, ''Beyond the Fringe'' and Monty Python.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keane, who formed the group in 1983 with two other women, one of whom, Nica Burns, is now the act's director, grew up in Ireland and studied music at the University of Dublin. She is now a regular musical contributor to the BBC Radio Four program ''Stop the Week.'' The two other performers, Adele Anderson and Denise Wharmby, come respectively from Birmingham, England, and Hobart, Australia. In the last five years, the act has attracted a growing cult following in both England and Australia. The lyrics of its cheery signature song, ''Sew on a Sequin,'' distill the mood of a show that brings to New York's cabaret world something the city has seen too little of in recent years, a whiff of sophisticated British nonsense:</p>
        <p>Sew on a sequin, when you've felt fate's piercing dart.</p>
        <p>If you're in the equinox of life, 'twill cheer your heart.</p>
        <p>Gather your organza, shimmer, shine, be gay.</p>
        <p>Don't give in to tears, just emulate the Milky Way.  In the Clubs This Weekend</p>
        <p>Here are the times and prices for the cabaret shows this weekend:  DAUGHERTY AND FIELD, Eighty Eight's, 228 West 10th Street (924-0088). Tonight at 8:30; cover, $10; two-drink minimum.  ANGELINA REAUX, New York Shakespeare Festival Public Theater, Susan Stein Shiva Theater, 425 Lafayette Street (598-7150). Tonight and tomorrow at 8 and Sunday at 7 P.M. Tickets, $25 today and tomorrow, $20 on Sunday.  FASCINATING AIDA, Ballroom, 253 West 28th Street (244-3005). Tonight and tomorrow at 9; cover, $15; two-drink minimum. Through Sept. 3.  JEFF HARNAR, Eighty Eight's, 228 West 10th Street (924-0088). Tomorrow, 8:30 P.M.; cover, $10; two-drink minimum. Through Sept. 24.  PHOEBE LEGERE AND THE HOT CLUB OF FRANCE, Michael's Pub, 211 East 55th Street (758-2272). Tonight and tomorrow, 9 and 11; cover, $15; two-drink minimum.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
