<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Biffle Finds Breakthrough at Darlington</title>
    <meta content="14nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/14/sports/14nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1761843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dodge Charger 500</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Viv</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biffle, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D6143EF937A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Biffle Finds Breakthrough at Darlington</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Biffle Finds Breakthrough at Darlington</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>DARLINGTON, S.C., May 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Greg Biffle wins Dodge Charger 500; photo (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Greg Biffle did not run out of gas or time or luck. For once, the engine did not blow, the crash did not come and Biffle was not left to wonder how a sure victory could become yet another sure sign that his charmed 2005 season was long past.</p>
        <p>In a confounding season of occasional dominance and occasional disaster, Biffle finally found his way back into victory lane Saturday night in the Dodge Charger 500 at Darlington Raceway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>DARLINGTON, S.C., May 13  Greg Biffle did not run out of gas or time or luck. For once, the engine did not blow, the crash did not come and Biffle was not left to wonder how a sure victory could become yet another sure sign that his charmed 2005 season was long past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Greg Biffle did not run out of gas or time or luck. For once, the engine did not blow, the crash did not come and Biffle was not left to wonder how a sure victory could become yet another sure sign that his charmed 2005 season was long past.</p>
        <p>In a confounding season of occasional dominance and occasional disaster, Biffle finally found his way back into victory lane Saturday night in the Dodge Charger 500 at Darlington Raceway.</p>
        <p>Biffle held off a late charge from Jeff Gordon for his first Nascar Nextel Cup victory of the season and his second in a row at Darlington.</p>
        <p>''We never give up,'' Biffle said as he emerged from his No. 16 Ford in victory lane.</p>
        <p>Biffle won this race a year ago for his third victory in his first 10 races. It was the start of a breakthrough year in which he won six races and finished second in the Chase for the Nextel Cup to Tony Stewart.</p>
        <p>Coming off that effort, Biffle entered this season as one of the contenders for the title. But he has endured a troubled season, and was 20th in the points standings entering Saturday's race. He also entered Saturday second to Stewart in the number of laps led in Cup races this year. And while Stewart had maintained a comfortable lead in the standings, Biffle had seen his hopes of making the 10-car Chase diminish through the first 10 races. Biffle has had engine problems, has run out of gas more than once and has crashed, all leading to a free fall out of serious contention for the Chase.</p>
        <p>But all of that began to turn around a week ago when Biffle finished fourth at Richmond. It was his first top-five performance of the season, and he celebrated as if he had won.</p>
        <p>The momentum carried to Darlington, where Biffle qualified ninth and quickly moved up in the field and into contention early Saturday night. He took over the lead from the pole sitter, Kasey Kahne, on Lap 36, maintaining that spot through the early portion of the race.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Matt Kenseth and Jimmie Johnson emerged as contenders, each leading for stretches. But in the final stages, Biffle gambled by going to pit road for fresh tires and fuel, hoping a caution flag would not come out. This time, his luck held. Biffle was back in the lead by the time the competition pitted and returned.</p>
        <p>Gordon raced past Kenseth and into position to make a run at Biffle in the closing laps. But with one lap to go, the lapped racecar of Ken Schrader appeared to block Gordon's path to the low side of the racetrack and a possible last-lap challenge.</p>
        <p>''It killed all of my momentum,'' Gordon said. ''I lost every chance that we had.''</p>
        <p>But it was a strong performance for a team that is still finding its way after struggling a year ago and finishing out of the Chase for the Nextel Cup.</p>
        <p>''It was a good run,'' Gordon said. ''I'm very happy to be up there battling for that win, obviously. It's been a little while since we've been able to do that.''</p>
        <p>He is not the only one saying that now. Two weeks ago, after a 38th-place finish at Talladega, Biffle was 23rd in points and 232 points behind the 10th and final place in the Chase standings.</p>
        <p>With the Richmond performance and Saturday's victory, Biffle has jumped to 14th place and is 106 points out of 10th place.</p>
        <p>He said he expected that momentum to continue as the series shifted to Lowe's Motor Speedway the next two weekends for the nonpoints all-star race May 20 and the Coca-Cola 600 on May 28.</p>
        <p>''It's unbelievable we're 14th in points,'' Biffle said. ''Good news for us and bad news for them. We feel like we tested extremely well at Charlotte and we feel like we're one of the better cars there.''</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Toyota has nabbed a high-profile driver for its start-up Nextel Cup program that begins competition in 2007. DALE JARRETT, 49, the 1999 Cup champion, will leave Robert Yates Racing after 12 years to join MICHAEL WALTRIP's new Toyota race team next season.</p>
        <p>Jarrett has won 32 Cup races, including three victories in the Daytona 500, and brings credibility and a built-in Southeast fan base to Toyota, a Japanese manufacturer.</p>
        <p>''When he first called me about the opportunity and the idea, I found it very intriguing,'' Jarrett said during a news conference before the race. ''They started showing me a lot of what was going on, what their plans were, how Toyota was going about this and opportunities that could be there for me not only in my last couple of years of driving the car, but beyond that. I saw this as a new challenge for myself.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
