<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thinking Triple Crown Before First Race Was Run</title>
    <meta content="14barbaro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/14/sports/othersports/14barbaro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1761827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jockeys, Drivers and Trainers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">matz, michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">brette, peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Matz, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EED7143EF937A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thinking Triple Crown Before First Race Was Run</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thinking Triple Crown Before First Race Was Run</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>ELKTON, Md., May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trainer Michael Matz and his assistant Peter Brette both believed after his first racetrack workout that Kentucky Derby winner Barbaro was superhorse who would sweep Triple Crown; undefeated colt will take second step in running of Preakness Stakes on May 20; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, after the big dark bay horse arrived at the European-styled training center here, the trainer Michael Matz and his assistant, Peter Brette, shared a transcendental thought about a colt by the ho-hum name of Barbaro. But they dared not say it aloud.</p>
        <p>Barbaro was a superhorse, Mr. Brette believed, after he first took him onto the racetrack for a morning workout. Barbaro could sweep the Triple Crown, Mr. Matz said he kept thinking. It was the beginning of what would become a most unorthodox plan to chase after one of sport's most elusive prizes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trainer of this year's Kentucky Derby winner hopes an unorthodox plan will lead to a Triple Crown sweep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, after the big dark bay horse arrived at the European-styled training center here, the trainer Michael Matz and his assistant, Peter Brette, shared a transcendental thought about a colt by the ho-hum name of Barbaro. But they dared not say it aloud.</p>
        <p>Barbaro was a superhorse, Mr. Brette believed, after he first took him onto the racetrack for a morning workout. Barbaro could sweep the Triple Crown, Mr. Matz said he kept thinking. It was the beginning of what would become a most unorthodox plan to chase after one of sport's most elusive prizes.</p>
        <p>''We were training for the Triple Crown,'' Mr. Matz said, daring to tempt racing's fates. ''It has been so long since anyone has won it, why not try something different?''</p>
        <p>In the Kentucky Derby on May 6, Barbaro validated Mr. Brette's opinion with a stunningly effortless victory. On May 20 in Baltimore, Mr. Matz says, his undefeated colt will take the second step toward fulfilling his prophesy by jetting away from the field in the 131st running of the Preakness Stakes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matz says he thinks he can succeed where six horses in the last nine years, from Silver Charm to Smarty Jones, failed after coming so close to horse racing immortality. He has thrown out a regimen that has been regarded by trainers as commandments etched in stone, opting instead for a new schedule, forged by his own personal setback and inspired by a brilliant colt.</p>
        <p>While most trainers organize training to maximize fitness and build race readiness, Mr. Matz has given Barbaro an unusual amount of rest between races in his budding career. Trainers usually prefer to have their horses experienced in having dirt kicked in their face, maneuvering through crowded fields and reacting to adversity before they run in the Triple Crown races, beyond being in shape.</p>
        <p>Barbaro, though, ran only five times before winning the Derby, and started his career only when Mr. Matz decided he was ready, in October, relatively late for a horse with Triple Crown ambitions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matz, 55, came upon his fresh-horse theory at the lowest point of what turned out to be an illustrious career in show jumping.</p>
        <p>In 1976, he was on the cusp of making the United States Olympic team and was forced to push his horse in the trials. Mr. Matz became an Olympian, but at the Montreal Games, he and his tired horse staggered through the competition, suffering 28 faults and knocking down 7 poles.</p>
        <p>''When I watched the replay, I felt agony,'' he said. ''No one, none of my teammates, wanted to get close to me. I decided then, I was never going to put a tired horse in a competition or race.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Matz says that a horse needs every advantage to win the Triple Crown, the most exacting and enduring challenge in the sport. It was back in 1978 that Affirmed became the last horse to sweep the Derby, the Preakness and the Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>In recent years, Mr. Matz has watched as six horses, weary from their Triple Crown campaigns, have fallen short.</p>
        <p>As a group, those six horses competed in an average of 8.5 races before the Derby, and an average of 3.8 of those races were as 3-year-olds, usually in the 12 weeks before the first Saturday in May. Bob Baffert trained three of those horses, and two -- Silver Charm and Real Quiet -- fell three-quarters of a length and a nose short from completing the sweep in the grueling mile-and-a-half Belmont Stakes. Eking out those last few gallops from a tired horse in the Triple Crown's third leg has vexed trainers in recent years.</p>
        <p>''It's a tricky balance to keep, and a lot of it depends on your horse and how he is progressing,'' said Mr. Baffert, who raced Silver Charm six times before the Derby and ran Real Quiet 12 times. ''You want him to be ready for anything in the Derby. I think most of us focus on winning the Derby.</p>
        <p>''Then you try to hold them together for the Preakness and Belmont. It looks like Michael had a horse that he could think Triple Crown with, and he believed enough in his colt's talent to try a different route.''</p>
        <p>Barbaro pulled into Churchill Downs having raced only once in the 13 weeks before the Derby. Between his starts, he was rested for five to eight weeks. His racing career looks odder still because his first three victories were on the grass -- not on dirt, the surface of the Triple Crown -- at distances of a mile, a mile and a sixteenth, and a mile and an eighth.</p>
        <p>Usually, Triple Crown hopefuls begin their careers on the dirt in races shorter than a mile involving one turn of the track before stretching to two-turn races in their third year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matz said he knew that Barbaro, as the son of Dynaformer -- an accomplished sire known for producing turf horses with stamina -- would relish those grass races. Actually, the trainer was listening to his horse.</p>
        <p>''We took our time with him because he needed to grow up mentally,'' Mr. Matz said. ''I would have run him on dirt, but the grass race at Delaware Park was the only one that came up that fit our schedule.''</p>
        <p>Following the trainer's regimen of allowing plenty of time to recover between races, Barbaro did not compete on the dirt until Feb. 4, in the Holy Bull Stakes at Gulfstream Park. When rain pelted South Florida and the racing surface became sloppy, Mr. Matz thought about pulling him from the race. But Mr. Brette, unworried about how Barbaro would handle a wet track, talked him out of it.</p>
        <p>''We had to try the dirt, as well as stay on schedule,'' Mr. Brette said.</p>
        <p>Barbaro was impressive winning the Holy Bull, but traditionalists were puzzled by Mr. Matz's decision to wait until the Florida Derby eight weeks later. By that time, Mr. Matz and Mr. Brette were well aware that they had a maturing colt with more gears than a bicycle in the Tour de France.</p>
        <p>To keep his horses happy, Mr. Matz has based his stable in Elkton, Md., at the Fair Hill Training Center, which is a sort of equine spa with Fifth Avenue amenities.</p>
        <p>He owns two spacious barns, has access to an adjacent veterinary clinic and pays maintenance fees ($5 a day for each of his 50 horses here) to the center.</p>
        <p>Its 350 acres are next to the 5,600-acre Fair Hill Preserve, once the fox-hunting estate of William du Pont Jr., and is veined by riding trails, dotted with pastures and home to a dirt, turf and more forgiving wood-chip training track. It is an oasis where horses can be treated as horses.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday morning, Barbaro grazed quietly after an effortless mile jog that once more had Mr. Brette feeling as if he had been atop a winged horse. ''If he is feeling this good four days after running a mile and a quarter, I can't imagine what he will be like in 10 days,'' he said, referring to the Preakness at Pimlico Race Course.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matz and Mr. Brette say they know they are tempting fate by talking of the Triple Crown when two legs remain.</p>
        <p>But they also have been unable to suppress thoughts of sweeping the series, then taking Barbaro to Europe in the fall to run on grass again, perhaps in the Prix de l'Arc de Triomphe, the most famous race in Europe.</p>
        <p>It is with this confidence that Matz has entered Barbaro to run against a compact field of perhaps six horses at Pimlico on May 20. When he gives Edgar Prado a leg up on Barbaro before the Preakness, Mr. Matz said he would offer him the same succinct instructions that he did at the Derby: ''Just ride him like he's the best horse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
