<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; Is It Fiction? Is It Nonfiction? And Why Doesn't Anyone Care?</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="624546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAKUTANI, MICHIKO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, EDWARD M (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANCHESTER, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGINNISS, JOE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEATH OF A PRESIDENT, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LAST BROTHER, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D8173CF934A15754C0A965958260" item-length="2132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; Is It Fiction? Is It Nonfiction? And Why Doesn't Anyone Care?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAKUTANI, MICHIKO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What's upsetting about "The Last Brother," by Joe McGinniss, isn't just that the author invented thoughts Senator Edward M. Kennedy might have had, or that in the opening section of the book Mr. McGinniss seems to have appropriated significant portions of his narrative from William Manchester's 1967 book, "The Death of a President." What's even more alarming is that "The Last Brother" represents the logical culmination of several disturbing trends in publishing, literary theory and American culture at large that have accelerated precipitately in recent years.</p>
        <p>The lines between fact and fiction have become so blurred nowadays that many readers are likely to shrug off Mr. McGinniss's startling acknowledgment that in creating his portrait of the Massachusetts Democrat, he has "written certain scenes and described certain events from what I have inferred to be his point of view," despite the fact that he did not even interview the Senator for the book. Indeed, we are daily assaulted by books, movies and television docudramas that hopscotch back and forth between the realms of history and fiction, reality and virtual reality, with impunity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What's upsetting about "The Last Brother," by Joe McGinniss, isn't just that the author invented thoughts Senator Edward M. Kennedy might have had, or that in the opening section of the book Mr. McGinniss seems to have appropriated significant portions of his narrative from William Manchester's 1967 book, "The Death of a President." What's even more alarming is that "The Last Brother" represents the logical culmination of several disturbing trends in publishing, literary theory and American culture at large that have accelerated precipitately in recent years.</p>
        <p>The lines between fact and fiction have become so blurred nowadays that many readers are likely to shrug off Mr. McGinniss's startling acknowledgment that in creating his portrait of the Massachusetts Democrat, he has "written certain scenes and described certain events from what I have inferred to be his point of view," despite the fact that he did not even interview the Senator for the book. Indeed, we are daily assaulted by books, movies and television docudramas that hopscotch back and forth between the realms of history and fiction, reality and virtual reality, with impunity.</p>
        <p>Tabloid programs routinely offer viewers re-enactments and dramatizations. NBC recently acknowledged that a newsmagazine program had rigged a crash demonstration. And Oliver Stone's 1991 film "J. F. K." suggested, without any documentation, that the assassination of President John F. Kennedy was a result of an enormous conspiracy involving the military-industrial complex, the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Central Intelligence Agency.</p>
        <p>The Kennedy family's travails have also provided fodder for several recent novels, including ones by Joyce Carol Oates, Dominick Dunne, D. M. Thomas and Michael Korda. In each, facts are of little interest to the authors; reality simply serves as a springboard for fantasy, speculation and improvisation.</p>
        <p>Certainly there is a long history of writers, from Shakespeare to Gore Vidal, reinventing historical figures.</p>
        <p>Tolstoy is reputed to have said that novelists should wait at least 50 years before fictionalizing a historical event. Today, that statute of limitations has shrunk to a couple of weeks or days: anyone channel-surfing in recent months could easily jump from news stories about David Koresh, Amy Fisher and the World Trade Center bombing to made-for-television movies about the same subjects. The old ad line "Is it live or is it Memorex?" becomes, "Is it Koresh or is it Tim Daly playing Koresh in 'Ambush in Waco'?"</p>
        <p>Another problem with such docudramas, and one of the pivotal problems with Mr. McGinniss's book, is that they do not even announce themselves as works of fiction, but instead masquerade as the truth. As the late Irving Howe once noted, such works "evade the responsibilities of both genres: the responsibility of fiction, to create an imaginary world with its own traits, and the responsibility of history, to be verifiable." At the same time, they unabashedly play both to people's hunger for information and relevance, and to their appetite for entertainment.</p>
        <p>The phenomenon has a brief history. Since Truman Capote published "In Cold Blood" in 1965, more and more journalists have been appropriating the techniques of fiction. But while writers like Capote, Tom Wolfe and, yes, Mr. Manchester in "The Death of a President" grounded their narratives in hours and hours of reporting, other writers have resorted to the sorts of imaginative leaps taken by Mr. McGinniss in "The Last Brother" (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25).</p>
        <p>In her 1977 "interpretive biography," "Closing Time: The True Story of the 'Goodbar' Murder," Lacey Fosburgh acknowledged that she had "created scenes or dialogue I think it reasonable and fair to assume could have taken place, perhaps even did."</p>
        <p>Similarly, Kate Millett, in her 1979 book "The Basement," a "nonfiction" account of the death by torture of a 16-year-old girl that took place in 1965, created lengthy feminist soliloquies and attributed them to her subject.</p>
        <p>In the first section of "The Last Brother," Mr. McGinniss employs a comparable technique, to "convey to a reader what it might have been like to be Teddy Kennedy," he says. The text is peppered with phrases like "it must have seemed to Teddy," "it must have occurred to him" and "it was entirely possible." Describing a walk that Mr. Kennedy took along the beach in Hyannisport with his sister Eunice, Mr. McGinniss writes: "Suppose -- not that there is any evidence he considered this -- he suddenly just veered left, away from his sister, and plunged, fully clothed, into the roiling, frigid waters of Nantucket Bay?"</p>
        <p>The rationale Mr. McGinniss offers for this sort of irresponsible speculation is that "the Kennedys are different from you and me," that he must employ unorthodox techniques to penetrate their "mythic persona."</p>
        <p>"Different subjects call for different techniques," he writes in an author's note. "I would contend that when an individual is as encrusted with fable and lore as is Teddy Kennedy (and his brothers), a writer must attempt an approach that transcends that of traditional journalism or even, perhaps, of conventional biography."</p>
        <p>The result of this approach, of course, isn't a skewering of the myth, but the perpetuation of another set of new fables. A Longer Peek Into the Private</p>
        <p>Although "The Last Brother" is extreme in its willingness to invent reality, the book is unfortunately symptomatic of a larger tendency in biography writing. In recent years, the craft of biography has grown increasingly prurient, as some biographers, like some of their colleagues in the news media, have chosen to put more and more emphasis on their subjects' private lives and peccadilloes.</p>
        <p>This phenomenon is not confined to Kitty Kelleyesque biographies of celebrities, but has begun to infect more mainstream books as well: Joan Peyser's recent study of George Gershwin ("The Memory of All That") devotes disproportionate space to rumors about the composer's private life; and Paul Johnson's study of intellectuals ("Intellectuals") dwells on the personal shortcomings of assorted thinkers -- Karl Marx's failure to bathe, for instance -- under the guise of analyzing their moral credentials.</p>
        <p>Joyce Carol Oates calls this new sort of book "pathography." "Its motifs are dysfunction and disaster, illnesses and pratfalls, failed marriages and failed careers, alcoholism and breakdowns and outrageous conduct," she writes in a review of David Roberts's biography of Jean Stafford. Interpretation Over Content</p>
        <p>Concurrent with this growing focus on the private has been a growing emphasis on the biographer's own role, as an interpreter of the subject's life. As the biographer Justin Kaplan has observed, "the 'how' became at least as important as the 'what' when biographers started thinking of themselves not as post-mortem amanuenses but as writers, even participants, agonistic heroes and joint tenants in ongoing posthumous lives."</p>
        <p>In "The Last Brother," Mr. Kennedy becomes little more than a canvas on which Mr. McGinniss can project his own hypotheses. "I never intended that it be viewed as a formal biography," the author explains, "and, as the reader will have observed, it has not been constructed in a way that would encourage such response. This is my view, and perhaps mine alone, of what life might have been like for Teddy -- especially during the 1960's, when he was forced to be not only man but myth as well."</p>
        <p>This demeaning of the subject of the biography (and the simultaneous elevation of the biographer's own role) is a phenomenon reflective of a society that prizes delivery over content, a society that relies upon spin doctors to "interpret" politicians' ideas.</p>
        <p>It is also a phenomenon that mirrors the current trendiness, in lit-crit circles, of deconstruction: a theory that emphasizes a critic's reading of a text, rather the text's actual content. Obsessed with the unreliability of language and the relativity of all interpretations, deconstructionists argue that all texts are indeterminate.</p>
        <p>As more radical deconstructionists see it, the very idea of the author is dead: for them, texts are the product not of an individual imagination, but of a collective culture and its language. As the scholar Alvin Kernan puts it in his book "The Death of Literature," this theory effectively "reduces the creative individual of romantic theory into little more than a factory worker assembling images, words, and ideas that are the common property of the culture and embedded in the language."</p>
        <p>Once this view of writing has been accepted, plagiarism becomes an outmoded concept, because, as the critic David Lehman has observed, the elimination of the author means that "the text enters the academic equivalent of the public domain."</p>
        <p>"Since it belongs not to the writer but to everyone," Mr. Lehman writes in his recent book "Signs of the Times," "the logic that labels plagiarism a vice is called into question."</p>
        <p>No doubt such highfalutin concepts were not on the mind of Mr. McGinniss when he sat down to write "The Last Brother." The current visibility of deconstruction in academic circles, however, reflects a more general intellectual climate; and Mr. McGinniss's heavy reliance on material in Mr. Manchester's earlier book -- and his publisher's willingness to release the volume in the face of a potential lawsuit from Mr. Manchester -- underscores shifting attitudes in our society toward originality and creativity.</p>
        <p>As the blurring of the lines between fact and fiction already indicates, the very concept of imaginative creation has come under assault, with writers trying to pass off thinly disguised retellings of actual events as real novels. Meanwhile, the meaning of writing itself has mutated, as the hiring of "ghosts" proliferates: few politicians these days write their own speeches, and even some columnists have come to rely heavily on assistants' research and jottings.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the precepts of post-modernism, involving the "quotation" of earlier works of art, have invaded the worlds of both high and popular culture, informing everything from movies like "Raiders of the Lost Ark" (which pays tribute to, even as it sends up, the old Saturday matinee serials) to novels like Kathy Acker's "Don Quixote" (which provides a feminist retelling of Cervantes's famous tale).</p>
        <p>Movie studios pay big money for the right to recycle books and plays, and they in turn sell their rights to television syndication. Even more frequently, no money changes hands at all; writers simply appropriate stories, ideas and motifs from their predecessors and call the result satire, homage, post-modern collage or, as the scholar Harold Bloom puts it, a Freudian "misreading" of their artistic precursors.</p>
        <p>D. M. Thomas used post-modernist arguments to defend his "inspirational use" of words belonging to a real-life survivor of Babi Yar in his novel "The White Hotel." And scholars have explained the heavy borrowing recently discovered in the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s speeches and papers in terms of the "oral tradition" of slavery, which regards language as communal property.</p>
        <p>As for "The Last Brother," Simon &amp; Schuster has defended Mr. McGinniss's use of material from Manchester's book, arguing that "restatement of fact already in the public domain is not plagiarism."</p>
        <p>In the opinion of Mr. Kernan, changing notions of originality, combined with new technological innovations, could very well obliterate traditional notions of copyright and plagiarism. In much the same way as the copying machine has altered the enforcement of copyright laws, he argues in "The Death of Literature," the growing use of computerized information banks will vaporize the conception of a book as an individual creation. The individual text, he says, will disappear "into the vast 'hypertext' of a database, the parts of which can be endlessly moved about and recombined in different configurations." The Implication: A Fading of Truth</p>
        <p>The two controversies surrounding "The Last Brother" -- the volume's apparent appropriation of material from Mr. Manchester's book, and its blurring of the lines between fact and fiction -- may seem like simple cases of laziness or opportunism or self-indulgence on the part of its author. But as a manifestation of broader developments in our culture, they have serious implications.</p>
        <p>The first, in assailing the concept of originality, threatens to alter radically the very definition of what it means to be a writer. The second, in erasing the boundary between fact and fantasy, suggests that there is no knowable reality, that it is futile to search for the truth, that verisimilitude is as good as the real thing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
