<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Onstage: Judge's Past, Politicians' Future</title>
    <meta content="24nago" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/24/weekinreview/24nago.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1689702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION: MANEUVERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, John G Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Connor, Sandra Day</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDE153FF937A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Onstage: Judge's Past, Politicians' Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Onstage: Judge's Past, Politicians' Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a decade, Washington has girded for a titanic battle to fill the next Supreme Court vacancy. But after President Bush nominated John G. Roberts last week to replace Sandra Day O'Connor on the court it looked like the spectacle might have to wait.</p>
        <p>That is not necessarily the case: For one thing, a small industry in Washington of advocacy groups have spent years preparing for Armageddon. They are not about to let the opportunity pass, for a variety of reasons, starting, of course, with their genuine concerns about the judiciary, but also because a good fight helps these groups raise money and guarantees their leaders a spot on the evening news. But more than that -- even if Judge Roberts ends up being a bit player in his own story, in no small part because his ideological background is making it hard for Democrats to build a case against him -- the confirmation process is shaping up as one of those unusually revealing moments in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Washington has girded for a titanic battle to fill the next Supreme Court vacancy. But it looks like the spectacle might have to wait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a decade, Washington has girded for a titanic battle to fill the next Supreme Court vacancy. But after President Bush nominated John G. Roberts last week to replace Sandra Day O'Connor on the court it looked like the spectacle might have to wait.</p>
        <p>That is not necessarily the case: For one thing, a small industry in Washington of advocacy groups have spent years preparing for Armageddon. They are not about to let the opportunity pass, for a variety of reasons, starting, of course, with their genuine concerns about the judiciary, but also because a good fight helps these groups raise money and guarantees their leaders a spot on the evening news. But more than that -- even if Judge Roberts ends up being a bit player in his own story, in no small part because his ideological background is making it hard for Democrats to build a case against him -- the confirmation process is shaping up as one of those unusually revealing moments in Washington.</p>
        <p>It has the potential to make and break new powers in the Senate, members of both parties said. It can test the political skills of the sizeable contingent of senators thinking about running for president in 2008, and pry open even slight differences within the parties over how to respond to these nominees. It also is giving Internet-based advocacy organizations that were not around last time, like MoveOn.org, an opportunity to show if they have as much sway with senators as some of these groups have claimed.</p>
        <p>''The opportunities in an off-election season for the public to be riveted on issues of real national importance are few and far between,'' said Edward P. Lazarus, a lawyer who has written about the court.</p>
        <p>The two most famous Supreme Court confirmation hearings of the past 25 years -- for Robert G. Bork and Clarence Thomas -- had lasting affects on the political system in Washington, the nation's view of the Senate and the reputation of some of its members, a lesson that has not been lost on this current Senate. Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts memorably defined Mr. Bork with scathing attacks, while Senator Arlen Specter's intense questioning of Mr. Bork so shook Mr. Specter's standing with conservatives that he pays a price for it to this day; it almost led to him losing his position as head of the Judiciary Committee.</p>
        <p>In the Senate, this first confirmation hearing in 11 years is bringing to the forefront a new generation of leaders, who are nudging aside familiar lions. Senator John Cornyn, the conservative Texas Republican the White House has tapped as its point man for the nomination battle (and who himself was mentioned as a possible O'Connor replacement) seems ready to supplant Orrin G. Hatch, the 70-year-old Utah Republican who was the conservative face of the nomination process in 1991. Senator Charles E. Schumer, a New York Democrat, appears to be crowding out Mr. Kennedy.</p>
        <p>''What happened to Kennedy?'' Bob Dole, the former Republican Senate majority leader, asked with a chuckle. ''I keep seeing Schumer. I'm going to tell Chuck something is wrong with my TV. I can't get anything on it but him.''</p>
        <p>In addition, a Supreme Court confirmation, low key or not, can spotlight the political dexterity and early strategic determinations of members of the Senate who are considering a run for the presidency.</p>
        <p>Democrats have a bit of a conundrum here, as they contemplate a scenario in which they approve Judge Roberts, only to have Justice Roberts hand down a decision noxious to Democratic primary voters, which they are forced to defend in the midst of a primary contest. ''When they think about Iowa 2008, that does create pressure on them to vote against him,'' said Steven Calabresi of Northwestern University Law School, a leading conservative scholar.</p>
        <p>The risk is that given what is now known about Judge Roberts -- or perhaps, what is not known -- Republicans may be able to portray Democrats as being obstructionist and out of the mainstream for opposing him. ''It is going to be tough,'' said David Axelrod, a Democratic consultant. ''You've got a very, very smart skilled lawyer in Roberts, and he's going to be very, very hard to pin down.''</p>
        <p>In this regard, no Democratic senator will be more closely watched than Hillary Rodham Clinton in a year when she has repeatedly defied the liberal orthodoxy of her party (and, some critics might argue, her own past). Some Democrats say they think she may be tempted to vote with the majority, assuming (and this is a big assumption) that she is assured that Judge Roberts would not vote to overturn Roe v. Wade.</p>
        <p>Another Democratic strategist suggested Mrs. Clinton might find herself on the opposite side of Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, who has been racing to the left since his loss in November, and has come as close to any Democrat to saying he would oppose Judge Roberts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry and Mrs. Clinton are not alone. A Democrat on the Judiciary Committee of particular interest is Senator Joseph I. Biden Jr. of Delaware, chairman during the hearings for Clarence Thomas, a notably garrulous senator who is considering a run for the White House.</p>
        <p>Things are not necessarily that much easier on the Republican side, where party members are for the most part looking at the same unrevealing record of Judge Roberts. With conservative leaders who have ties to the White House embracing him, there has been a race among some Republican senators to see who could emerge as his chief advocate in the Senate. John S. McCain of Arizona, who has suffered tense relations with conservatives, most recently for helping to orchestrate the deal designed to limit the use of filibusters against judicial nominations, could hardly have been quicker in rallying around Judge Roberts.</p>
        <p>But Republicans took note when Sam Brownback, the conservative Kansas senator and a long-shot presidential prospect himself, bolted from the conservative pack to tell The Kansas City Star that he had concerns about Judge Roberts's views on abortion. Mr. Brownback's words reflected what is in fact worry in some conservative quarters about exactly what Judge Roberts thinks about abortion.</p>
        <p>For Senator Bill Frist, the majority leader who is also likely to run for president, expectations appear to be working against him: No one will be surprised if Judge Roberts wins by a big margin, but if he doesn't, Mr. Frist will find himself dealing yet again this year with the perception that he has been unable to deliver the Senate for the president and conservatives in the party.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem for both parties is that the interests of their potential presidential candidates do not necessarily dovetail with peers who are not running for the White House. For example, some Democrats argue that the party should not waste scant resources on a losing fight, and instead should turn their attention to pressing the case against Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief adviser, who is under attack for his role in providing information that lead to the publication of the name of a covert C.I.A. agent.</p>
        <p>Other Democrats described this as a moment where the party could, win or lose, lay out strong differences with Republicans that would help set the stage for 2008.</p>
        <p>Democrats, lead by Senator Clinton and the party chairman, Howard Dean, have been trying to de-emphasize the party's identification with abortion among the general electorate. Once, or if, the questioning gets beyond Roe v. Wade, it will be noteworthy to see if Democrats press Judge Roberts on whether he would accept limitations on abortions that some Democrats find unacceptable, like restrictions on late-term abortions and requirements for parental notification.</p>
        <p>Still, no matter what headaches lay ahead for the Senate, Mr. Bush should consider himself lucky, at least for now. Richard Norton Smith, a presidential scholar at the Abraham Lincoln Presidential Museum in Springfield, Ill., recalled the bitterness Herbert Hoover felt when one of his Supreme Court nominees was defeated. A few weeks later, he was congratulated on the birth of a granddaughter.</p>
        <p>'It's a good thing she doesn't have to be confirmed by the Senate,'' he growled.</p>
        <p>THE NATION: MANEUVERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
