<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Find a Better Way to Choose Vice Presidents</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="447763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DA1230F937A15756C0A967958260" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Find a Better Way to Choose Vice Presidents</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your May 8 Op-Ed page reflected the continuing concern about the Dan Quayle situation in Leslie H. Gelb's column, "The Quayle Factor," and Kevin Phillips's article, "The Double-Bogey Man." Despite a discrepancy between the two regarding the polls on Mr. Quayle's acceptance as a potential President, both focused on his abilities and how, if at all, he would affect the 1992 election. To me, both articles missed the fundamental question -- that is, the method by which our Vice-Presidential candidates are selected in the first place.</p>
        <p>We live in a republic, a representative democracy in which holders of public office are somehow judged at the ballot box. This litmus test of a seeker of an office is required at every level, from the proverbial dog catcher up to the highest, that of our supreme commander, the President.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your May 8 Op-Ed page reflected the continuing concern about the Dan Quayle situation in Leslie H. Gelb's column, "The Quayle Factor," and Kevin Phillips's article, "The Double-Bogey Man." Despite a discrepancy between the two regarding the polls on Mr. Quayle's acceptance as a potential President, both focused on his abilities and how, if at all, he would affect the 1992 election. To me, both articles missed the fundamental question -- that is, the method by which our Vice-Presidential candidates are selected in the first place.</p>
        <p>We live in a republic, a representative democracy in which holders of public office are somehow judged at the ballot box. This litmus test of a seeker of an office is required at every level, from the proverbial dog catcher up to the highest, that of our supreme commander, the President.</p>
        <p>Once elected, the President is entrusted with the duty of selecting those whose positions are mandated by the United States Constitution -- the Supreme Court, the military leaders, the cabinet -- and by electing the President we have said, in effect, that we consider that individual capable of executing those and the thousands of other duties of President better than any other American.</p>
        <p>Except the selection of the Vice President.</p>
        <p>It is not a question of whether Mr. Quayle is suited to become President, but rather the way he has been placed in that position. It has been disturbing to me, as I am sure it has been to many Americans, that we have allowed the party candidate to point to someone in a crowd, as it were, and say to the world, "That's my man (or woman)." We have months, perhaps years, to scrutinize politicians who aspire to the Presidency in order to be sure of their beliefs and leanings, not to mention their moral behavior; but we more or less take on faith the choice of Vice-Presidential candidate, the motivation of which is usually more for regional or ideological balance than potential fitness for the job. The relatively short period between the convention and the election is hardly enough to uncover any more than the most egregious fault with the running mate, or, in the case of the 1988 election, permits a popular candidate to thumb his nose at voters.</p>
        <p>Harry Truman aside, our history of Vice Presidents who have succeeded to the office has been less than salutary. The tale that the selection process is designed so that the President must have a running mate who agrees with his philosophy was given the lie in 1960, when John Kennedy picked Lyndon Johnson, a powerful Senator and his political enemy, to run alongside him. Otherwise, the string of Coolidges, Agnews, Fords, Mondales and Ferraros who might have had a profound effect on American history is enough to send a shiver up our spines.</p>
        <p>I am not sure about a remedy for this glitch in our political system; the only solution that comes to mind would require all Presidential hopefuls to sign a pledge to run for Vice President if they finish second in the primary elections. While this method might expose us to a potential drag on the ticket, or worse, provide us with a Jesse (Helms or Jackson), it will remove some of the triviality connected with the process and give us someone who has at least earned a spot in the polling places. All we have now is veto power; if we feel strongly enough against the choice of a Presidential candidate's running mate, we can vote for the other guy. Not much of a choice. STANLEY KUSHNER North Haledon, N.J., May 10, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
