<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eating Well: The Debate Over Milk and an Artificial Hormone; More Milk, More Confusion: What Should the Label Say?</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DAIRY PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOVINE GROWTH HORMONE (BGH)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABELING AND LABELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONSANTO CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURROS, MARIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D81438F93BA25756C0A962958260" item-length="1452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eating Well: The Debate Over Milk and an Artificial Hormone; More Milk, More Confusion: What Should the Label Say?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURROS, MARIAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PUBLIC apprehension about milk from cows treated with the artificial bovine growth hormone is not going away, despite the efforts of the hormone's manufacturer to allay the fear.</p>
        <p>The conflict over the hormone, which the Federal Food and Drug Administration approved for use last November and which is meant to increase milk production, is reflected in torturous confusion over labeling of milk products.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PUBLIC apprehension about milk from cows treated with the artificial bovine growth hormone is not going away, despite the efforts of the hormone's manufacturer to allay the fear.</p>
        <p>The conflict over the hormone, which the Federal Food and Drug Administration approved for use last November and which is meant to increase milk production, is reflected in torturous confusion over labeling of milk products.</p>
        <p>Before it was approved for use, there had been warnings that using the drug -- known as recombinant bovine somatotropin (rbST) and recombinant bovine growth hormone (rbGH) -- would result in a drop in sales of milk products because of public concern about the hormone's safety.</p>
        <p>But there is no way to tell yet whether national sales have been affected. Lisa Watkins, a spokeswoman for the Monsanto Company of St. Louis, which is manufacturing the drug under the trade name of Posilac, said there was no change in milk sales in February, when the drug went on the market. But dozens of companies are advertising that their milk comes from cows that have not been injected with the hormone.</p>
        <p>Use of the drug, which is genetically engineered, was approved over the objections of those who believe it has not been sufficiently tested on humans.</p>
        <p>The critics include the General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of Congress, and scientists like Dr. Michael Hansen, a scientist at the Consumers Union, and Dr. Samuel Epstein, a professor of occupational and environmental medicine at the University of Illinois at Chicago. They also include public interest groups, like Mothers and Others for a Livable Planet, an environmental and consumer group; Women's Health Network, an organization devoted to women's health issues, and the Pure Food Campaign, a project of the Foundation on Economic Trends, a group headed by Jeremy Rifkin, a critic of biotechnology.</p>
        <p>In its decision to permit the use of the hormone, the F.D.A. acknowledged certain risks it described as "manageable." In the warning statement included with the drug, Monsanto says there are possible detrimental health effects on cows treated with the drug. They include reduced pregnancy rates and a greater risk of disorders involving reproductive and digestive organs. There is also an increased risk for mastitis, an inflammation of the udder.</p>
        <p>At the center of the confusion is a statement issued in the Federal Register by the F.D.A. on Feb. 10, about voluntary labeling of dairy products from cows treated with the hormone.</p>
        <p>Calling the suggested wording "interim guidance," meaning it has no force of law, the agency said that because all milk contains the natural hormone bST, it would be false and misleading to label any milk product as bST-free. But the term "rbST" could be used because rbST is the artificial hormone used in treated cows. Even labeling a milk product as rbST-free could be misleading, the agency said, because it implies that the "milk from untreated cows is safer or of higher quality than milk from treated cows."</p>
        <p>To avoid such an implication, the F.D.A. suggested that a statement be added to the label to put the claim in proper context: "No significant difference has been shown between milk derived from rbST-treated and non-rbST-treated cows."</p>
        <p>The agency has not recommended or required similar caveats for products whose labels say things like "no MSG," "no artificial color," "preservative free" or "organic."</p>
        <p>The agency's statement has caused confusion among those who have pledged not to use the hormone in their herds and would like to put some kind of statement on their products to that effect. It has also confused state authorities who are uncertain how to regulate the labeling.</p>
        <p>Monsanto has added to the confusion by warning companies through letters that labeling is false and misleading unless it complies with the F.D.A.'s suggested wording. Ms. Watkins said letters had been sent to at least six companies that have used advertisements, letters or labeling to indicate that their milk products contain no rbST. Monsanto neglected to mention that the F.D.A.'s statement on labeling does not have the force of law -- so that whether someone follows the suggested wording is of no consequence unless the statements are false and misleading.</p>
        <p>Many of the parties believe that if there are regulations governing labeling, they should be in the hands of the F.D.A., not states, individual producers or retail markets. And some believe that products containing the artificial hormone should be labeled. An F.D.A. official acknowledged that instead of clearing the air, the interim guidelines have muddied the waters, and the agency is trying to figure out what to do next. Dr. David A. Kessler, the Commissioner of the F.D.A., said that the agency wanted "to make it clear that voluntary labeling is permitted, and it would be best to put it in context."</p>
        <p>The F.D.A. has received thousands of comments about the labeling issue, but they have not been compiled yet.</p>
        <p>Even within individual state governments, there is disagreement about how to proceed. The Attorney General of New York, G. Oliver Koppell, advocates full disclosure because, he said, "I do not believe that a sufficient time period has elapsed to make conclusary statements that rbST is harmless." But Richard T. McGuire, the state's Commissioner of Agriculture and Markets, does not want products labeled because, he said, there is no difference between treated and untreated milk.</p>
        <p>Ms. Watkins said Monsanto believes that voluntary labeling is all right. In March, the company sent a letter to Dr. Kessler, asking him to "take immediate steps to stop this false and misleading food labeling and to inform the public and the marketplace that F.D.A. intends to enforce its interim guidance." The company enclosed examples of advertisements, food labels and promotions that they believe to be misleading.</p>
        <p>One example is a newspaper advertisement for the Elfco Food Co-op of East Lansing, Mich. "Concerned about the use of synthetic bovine growth hormone?" the advertisements asked. "Elfco offers milk, yogurt, cheeses and butter from farmers committed to dairy production without the use of rbGH."</p>
        <p>Elfco's statement did not include the suggested caveat.</p>
        <p>Monsanto has sued two companies that have made similar claims, saying they have made false and misleading statements.</p>
        <p>In addition, several trade associations -- the International Dairy Foods Association, the Grocery Manufacturers of America and the National Food Processors Association -- have sued the state of Vermont over a law that starting in June will require all products made from the milk of cows injected with the artificial hormone to say so on the label. The Nutrasweet Company, which is owned by Monsanto, is a member of the first two trade associations.</p>
        <p>"Everyone is terrified," said the owner of a wholesale dairy in the Northeast that was threatened with a lawsuit by Monsanto because of an advertisement the company had run in a newspaper. "It is quite ominous."</p>
        <p>The owner asked not to be identified because, he said, he did not want any more trouble with Monsanto.</p>
        <p>There are dozens of other companies that continue to label their products, including Farmland Dairies of Wallington, N.J. The company, which sells milk in the New York metropolitan area, has labeled its milk as follows: "Farmland Dairies Farmers have pledged in writing that they will not use rbST (recombinant bovine somatotropin) on their cows. When administered to dairy cows, rbST increases their milk production. Although the F.D.A. has approved the use of rbST and found no significant difference between milk derived from rbST-treated cows and those not treated, we want to know how you feel about this issue." The president of the company, Marc Goldman, said the company had received 800 letters and more than 1,000 telephone calls, all but two of which supported the decision not to use rbST.</p>
        <p>And earlier this month, Land O' Lakes, a huge dairy cooperative in Minnesota, began selling a Superior Brand milk that is free of the hormone, in addition to its regular line of milk, which contains it.</p>
        <p>Mothers and Others for a Livable Planet has compiled lists of other companies that are notifying customers about their artificial-hormone policy. The lists include supermarket chains and distributors that, according to Mothers and Others, have documents stating that they will carry some dairy products from cows that have not been treated with the synthetic bovine growth hormone. Products from brand-name companies on the list are all untreated. Regional lists are available from Mothers and Others for a Livable Planet, 40 West 20th Street, New York, 10011.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
