<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLOOD PRESSURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIET AND NUTRITION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL HEART, LUNG AND BLOOD INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood Pressure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood Pressure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4D81438F93BA25756C0A962958260" item-length="1264" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH good evidence that an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure, the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute has begun a major effort to prevent high blood pressure, rather than just detect and treat it. The effort, if successful, could result in Americans who are thinner, more active and less saturated with salt and alcohol, as well as being less susceptible to heart attacks, strokes, congestive heart failure, circulatory disorders and kidney disease.</p>
        <p>The problem is daunting. Thirty million to 50 million adults in the nation have high blood pressure, and each year another two million join their ranks. This makes high blood pressure, or hypertension, the most common risk factor for diseases of the heart, blood vessels and kidneys. Pressure Uncontrolled</p>
        <p>Because high blood pressure is so common, lacks warning signs and seems so innocuous for so many years, many people are far too casual about it. They typically fail on one or more of three counts: having their blood pressure checked regularly, adopting living habits that could lower it and, once hypertension is diagnosed, taking the medication that can control it. The result is tens of thousands of avoidable deaths and billions of dollars spent on medical care each year for preventable illnesses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH good evidence that an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure, the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute has begun a major effort to prevent high blood pressure, rather than just detect and treat it. The effort, if successful, could result in Americans who are thinner, more active and less saturated with salt and alcohol, as well as being less susceptible to heart attacks, strokes, congestive heart failure, circulatory disorders and kidney disease.</p>
        <p>The problem is daunting. Thirty million to 50 million adults in the nation have high blood pressure, and each year another two million join their ranks. This makes high blood pressure, or hypertension, the most common risk factor for diseases of the heart, blood vessels and kidneys. Pressure Uncontrolled</p>
        <p>Because high blood pressure is so common, lacks warning signs and seems so innocuous for so many years, many people are far too casual about it. They typically fail on one or more of three counts: having their blood pressure checked regularly, adopting living habits that could lower it and, once hypertension is diagnosed, taking the medication that can control it. The result is tens of thousands of avoidable deaths and billions of dollars spent on medical care each year for preventable illnesses.</p>
        <p>Even more lackadaisical are those whose blood pressure is on the high side of normal, just below the 140/90 reading that doctors have arbitrarily designated as the cutoff where "normal" ends and hypertension begins. Being high-normal is not a risk-free status. As blood pressure rises, so does the risk of developing any of its complications. People with high-normal pressure account for more than a third of preventable deaths related to blood pressure.</p>
        <p>When the millions of Americans with high-normal blood pressures are added to those with outright hypertension, the total comes to about three-fourths of Americans aged 35 and above with potentially life-threatening blood pressures.</p>
        <p>Doctors consider an optimal blood pressure to be below 120/80. The numbers refer to pressure measured in millimeters of mercury, with the higher number, or systolic pressure, representing blood pressure when the heart beats and the lower number, or diastolic pressure, representing blood pressure when the heart rests between beats. Both numbers are important; if either is elevated, health risks rise, and if both are elevated, they rise even more.</p>
        <p>Careful studies have proved that lowering blood pressure in people with hypertension is lifesaving. But according to the latest national health survey, in 1991 only 49 percent of those with hypertension were being treated with medications to lower blood pressure and only one in five of those under treatment had pressures below 140/90. Clearly, despite two decades of an intensive national effort to detect and treat people with hypertension, many continue to be at very high risk because of uncontrolled high blood pressure.</p>
        <p>Even when high blood pressure is reduced to the normal range, the risk of illness and premature death is higher than if the person never had hypertension. Prevention Is Best</p>
        <p>Hence the current campaign to prevent this scourge. To help it along, the national institute has established a toll-free information line, 800 575-WELL (575-9355), that describes strategies to achieve and maintain a normal blood pressure.</p>
        <p>That hypertension is preventable in the vast majority of people is obvious from one universal fact: only in industrialized countries does blood pressure rise with age. In less developed countries where few people are overweight, where the diet does not promote clogged arteries, where daily physical activity is routine, where heavily salted processed foods do not overload the body with sodium and where heavy drinking of alcoholic beverages is uncommon, blood pressure does not creep up and up as people get older, and hypertension is not a national epidemic.</p>
        <p>In a new report on primary prevention of hypertension prepared by 15 experts, the institute pointed out that even a small reduction in blood pressure in the population can save a significant number of lives. Lowering systolic blood pressure by a mere two millimeters of mercury can reduce deaths from stroke by 6 percent, heart disease by 4 percent and all causes by 3 percent. And as little as a one-to-three-millimeter drop in diastolic pressure can reduce the incidence of hypertension in the population by 20 to 50 percent, the report said.</p>
        <p>The experts listed these strategies as most likely to be effective:</p>
        <p>Watch your weight. An estimated 20 to 30 percent of hypertension is the direct result of excess body weight. Those who are overweight are two to six times as likely to develop hypertension as people of normal weight, and losing excess weight results in a commensurate drop in blood pressure.</p>
        <p>Consume less salt and other sources of sodium. Americans consume many times more sodium than the body needs and substantially more than their ancestors did. A 52-center study of 10,000 men and women in 32 countries showed that in those centers where body weight was low but sodium intake was high, hypertension was seven times more common than in centers where both body weight and sodium intake were low. Reducing sodium in the diet can lower blood pressure in people with normal blood pressure as well as in those with high blood pressure. This is particularly true for blacks and the elderly, who are more likely than others to develop hypertension. In addition to using less salt in cooking and at the table, check the labels of packaged foods for sodium content.</p>
        <p>Become physically active. Hypertension is less common among people who are physically active or physically fit, and such people are less likely to experience a rise in blood pressure with increasing age. Introducing regular physical activity to sedentary people results in an average drop in blood pressure of six to seven millimeters, even if no weight is lost. Daily activity is more effective than exercise done on a less frequent schedule, and exercise of low to moderate intensity is as effective as higher intensity activities.</p>
        <p>Drink less alcohol. Although consumption of one to two drinks a day is associated with a diminished risk of heart disease, a larger intake of alcohol raises the risk of various diseases, including hypertension. From 5 to 7 percent of hypertension cases can be attributed to excessive alcohol consumption. Cutting back to a maximum of two drinks a day can lower blood pressure independently of any weight loss.</p>
        <p>Consume more potassium. A low intake of potassium-rich foods has been suggested as one reason why American blacks are more likely than whites to develop hypertension, and consuming more potassium in foods and perhaps as a supplement may help prevent this disorder. Potassium-rich foods include bananas, oranges and cantaloupes. For More Information</p>
        <p>IN addition to calling a toll-free information line -- 800-575-WELL (575-9355) -- operated by the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, consumers can learn more about controlling high blood pressure from a 20-page brochure, "Empower Yourself: Control the Pressure . . . and Feel Good!" produced by the Coalition for Hypertension Education and Control. Designed to help those with high blood pressure obtain satisfactory treatment, the brochure includes a self-assessment test to help patients discuss with their physicians measures they might take to control their blood pressure. The brochure is available free to consumers who call 800-664-4447.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
