<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officials Apparently Lagged in Tracking Slain Truant Girl</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRIDGEPORT (CONN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEIN, ESTHER B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CORBETT, ERICA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D91438F93BA25756C0A962958260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officials Apparently Lagged in Tracking Slain Truant Girl</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ESTHER B. FEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEIN, ESTHER B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Connecticut officials apparently squandered several opportunities to track down a 10-year-old Bridgeport, Conn., girl who had not attended school since last September and whose slashed body was found Saturday night, discarded near the squalid house she shared with her mother, three younger siblings and her mother's boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Police detectives working on the case said they still had no reliable version of events or a suspect in the murder of the girl, Erica Corbett, whose troubled life and cruel death have brought criticism from local residents and officials charging that the child welfare system failed to look out for her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Connecticut officials apparently squandered several opportunities to track down a 10-year-old Bridgeport, Conn., girl who had not attended school since last September and whose slashed body was found Saturday night, discarded near the squalid house she shared with her mother, three younger siblings and her mother's boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Police detectives working on the case said they still had no reliable version of events or a suspect in the murder of the girl, Erica Corbett, whose troubled life and cruel death have brought criticism from local residents and officials charging that the child welfare system failed to look out for her.</p>
        <p>Still, neighbors of the girl, who now describe Erica's difficult life and accuse officials of letting her fall through the cracks, did not report that she or her siblings were being abused or neglected, a spokesman for the Department of Children and Families said.</p>
        <p>But officials of the department apparently did not follow up on reports by school officials that the girl -- who was registered at the Waltersville School but had not been to classes since September -- was spotted in the Bridgeport area. Seen in February</p>
        <p>Erica was seen one cold February day walking in the neighborhood near the Barnum School, which she had attended last year, by a nurse who recognized her from the school clinic, said Mildred Butter, a secretary who works at the school.</p>
        <p>She said she informed the Waltersville School, then spread the word to Barnum parents to be on the lookout for the girl and to report any sightings of her. In March, she said, a parent reported seeing Erica late one night with her 7-year-old brother, Eric, in Washington Park, a local hangout for drug dealers, prostitutes and gangs.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Butter said she called the Department of Children and Families and was told, without further explanation, that the child's case had been closed. When the parent who originally saw Erica spotted her again and followed her to 201 Arctic Street, Mrs. Butter said, she called the department again and pleaded with them to look into the case, saying the child had been truant since September, but she was again rebuffed.</p>
        <p>The principal at Waltersville School, Roberto Rodriguez, said he contacted the agency to pass on the address, but a spokesman for the agency said that Mr. Rodriguez did not follow up with a mandatory written report. "We are currently looking into what was reported and how it was reported," said David Dearborn, the department spokesman. "We don't have a referral on the books for this family for this year." Aide Looked for Her</p>
        <p>The Bridgeport schools superintendent, James Connelly, said that after Erica stopped attending school last September, a home-school coordinator went looking for her at two addresses, both of which turned out to be padlocked or abandoned.</p>
        <p>Truant officers following up on her case and that of her brother Eric, who had also dropped out of school, also failed to locate the children, Mr. Connelly said, and they concluded that the family had left town, "not an unreasonable assumption given the mobility of the homeless population."</p>
        <p>But state officials said yesterday that the girl's mother, Stacy Ann Corbett, was receiving public assistance checks at 203 Arctic Street, one door down from the spot where Erica's body was dumped and where her two brothers and sister -- ages 7, 4 and 18 months -- were found on Saturday night by the police, alone, hungry and dirty.</p>
        <p>State Senator Alvin Penn, a Bridgeport Democrat, said officials in the state welfare department told him that Ms. Corbett was currently receiving monthly payments of $884 and was listed as having five children. He said he had no explanation for where the fifth child might be. Several Speculations</p>
        <p>The police said yesterday that they were pursuing several accounts of Erica's murder, all still unconfirmed. Among them are reports that a man enticed her from the building with promises of toys; that the four children were left alone by their mother, then their mother's boyfriend; and that the child's body was left in the yard as a message of revenge to someone in the family.</p>
        <p>Mr. Connelly, the schools superintendent, said that there were "many more children" in the Bridgeport area who were truant from school and in potential danger, living as squatters in abandoned buildings either with or without parents, and that their numbers had grown over the last two or three years. He said he had no exact figures and would estimate only that they numbered "between two and 50."</p>
        <p>"I would hope to say that Erica and her brother were the only two kids like this in our schools, but they're not," he said.</p>
        <p>"What happened here is that the system didn't work. The system broke down. I don't know where the blame lies and even if we knew where she was, I'm not sure that means this crime would have been prevented."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
