<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Innovative Heart Device Is Still Short of Lucrative</title>
    <meta content="07place" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/07/business/07place.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1788115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Implants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Abiomed Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D61631F934A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Innovative Heart Device Is Still Short of Lucrative</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Innovative Heart Device Is Still Short of Lucrative</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barnaby J. Feder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE difference between a medical milestone for a company and a great achievement for its shareholders has been illustrated by the Food and Drug Administration's approval of the first implantable, self-sufficient artificial heart.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the F.D.A. cleared a small Massachusetts company, Abiomed, to sell its $250,000 device to as many as 4,000 severely ill patients a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The F.D.A. approved the first implantable, self-sufficient artificial heart but it is too large to fit into more than half of male patients and 80 percent of women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE difference between a medical milestone for a company and a great achievement for its shareholders has been illustrated by the Food and Drug Administration's approval of the first implantable, self-sufficient artificial heart.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the F.D.A. cleared a small Massachusetts company, Abiomed, to sell its $250,000 device to as many as 4,000 severely ill patients a year.</p>
        <p>The approval was the first time regulators had allowed anything more than experiments with mechanical replacement hearts for patients expected to leave the hospital.</p>
        <p>''It's a major advance in cardiovascular medicine,'' said Dr. Mark Anderson, chief of cardiac surgery at Robert Wood Johnson University Hospital in New Brunswick, N.J., one of a handful of hospitals where surgeons will be trained to implant the device, the AbioCor, before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>One might assume that it could also provide a financial breakthrough for a company that lost $6 million on sales of $13 million in its most recent quarter and has rarely reported a profit since going public in 1987.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street's enthusiasm -- the stock rose nearly 10 percent on Tuesday in the hour after the announcement -- quickly disappeared. The shares ended the day at $14.98, up just 1.8 percent, and gave up half that gain yesterday, closing at $14.84.</p>
        <p>The problem is that AbioCor is not so much a product as, at best, a steppingstone to the artificial heart that David M. Lederman, a former aerospace engineer, envisioned when he founded the company in 1981. His dream was to extend the lives of chronic heart failure patients condemned to die in American hospitals because they could not get a heart transplant. These days, there are about 50,000 such patients annually competing for slightly more than 2,000 human hearts.</p>
        <p>But the AbioCor is too large to fit into more than half of male patients and 80 percent of women. It also comes with a high risk of blood clots, and several patients in the trials died during the complex implantation surgery -- not an encouraging sign for a product that would need to be replaced at least every two years. None of the 14 patients receiving implants in a clinical trial from 2001 to 2004 survived as long as 18 months.</p>
        <p>While some insurers may pay for the device on a case-by-case basis, none are expected to routinely cover it in the foreseeable future. Not surprisingly, the F.D.A. and Wall Street analysts talk about the number of patients likely to get AbioCors in the next few years as being measured in only the tens -- not the thousands that the company is theoretically entitled to sell annually.</p>
        <p>Abiomed's artificial heart prospects might brighten considerably if it is successful in developing the AbioCor II, a device now being tested in animals. It is more than 30 percent smaller and intended to last as long as five years. If all goes well in the laboratories, AbioCor II may reach the market in 2008, finally giving investors a shot at a financial return on the more than $100 million the company has invested in the technology.</p>
        <p>Fortunately for shareholders of Abiomed, which is based in Danvers, Mass., its fate no longer rests primarily on achieving Mr. Lederman's ambitious dream. Throughout the long effort to develop the artificial heart, he kept the money-losing enterprise alive on research grants from the government and ancillary businesses, including one foray into dental products.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Abiomed sold a 14 percent stake to Genzyme for $15 million as part of a deal to work together on biotechnology-based cardiac surgery research. But the biggest daily breadwinners have been a $17,000 heart-assisting device and a $45,000 blood-pumping unit that hospitals hook up to patients to help weakened but relatively healthy hearts heal enough for the patients to go home.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lederman finally decided to step aside from day-to-day management in 2004, Michael R. Minogue, the executive he recruited from General Electric's medical equipment subsidiary, quickly came to the conclusion that saving natural hearts -- not replacing them when all else fails -- should be the company's main goal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Minogue shifted more of the company's investments to heart-assisting devices. And last year, he engineered the acquisition of Impella CardioSystems, a small German company that had developed a device to increase blood circulation through a catheter.</p>
        <p>''We are serving the one million patients with the potential to recover their own hearts,'' said Mr. Minogue, who added chairman to his titles of chief executive and president when Mr. Lederman retired shortly after the Impella deal. ''That's what cost-effective medicine is for.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Minogue's shift of the company's focus, many analysts had begun to treat the artificial heart as a virtual afterthought. In February, Alexander Arrow, who follows the company for Lazard Capital Markets, called it a ''wild card'' for bullish investors. Mr. Arrow raised his target price for the shares to $20 this week from $17, reasoning that AbioCor's approval raised the likelihood of long-term earnings from Abiomed's artificial heart technology, and thus the company's overall valuation, if not its near-term earnings prospects.</p>
        <p>Abiomed, which had been forecasting F.D.A. approval since the spring, has not changed its sales or earnings projections this week. Mr. Minogue said yesterday in a telephone interview that he would not make sales forecasts for AbioCor until the company had a track record to base them on, but he seemed unwilling to accept others' predictions that the sales would be minimal.</p>
        <p>''The F.D.A. said 25 to 50 a year, but we never said that,'' Mr. Minogue said.</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
