<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look Who's Stealing Nebuchadnezzar's Thunder</title>
    <meta content="02BABY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Babylon Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Babylon Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2D6173DF931A35755C0A961958260" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look Who's Stealing Nebuchadnezzar's Thunder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <dateline>BABYLON, Iraq</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across southern Iraq, but especially in the rubbled remains of this city with its magical name, some mud bricks unearthed from the distant past still carry the mark of Nebuchadnezzar, the fabled Babylonian king. It was Nebuchadnezzar who wrested the ancient capital back from the Assyrians, repelled Persian intruders and captured Jerusalem, establishing Babylon in the sixth century B.C. as the largest and most glorious city in the world.</p>
        <p>More than 2,500 years later, new bricks placed in Babylon's walls carry the same cuneiform script, but a very different inscription.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across southern Iraq, but especially in the rubbled remains of this city with its magical name, some mud bricks unearthed from the distant past still carry the mark of Nebuchadnezzar, the fabled Babylonian king. It was Nebuchadnezzar who wrested the ancient capital back from the Assyrians, repelled Persian intruders and captured Jerusalem, establishing Babylon in the sixth century B.C. as the largest and most glorious city in the world.</p>
        <p>More than 2,500 years later, new bricks placed in Babylon's walls carry the same cuneiform script, but a very different inscription.</p>
        <p>''In the era of President Saddam Hussein, the President of Iraq, God preserve him,'' the modern bricks read, ''who rebuilt Babylon, as protector of the great Iraq and the builder of civilization.''</p>
        <p>It is no coincidence, Iraqi officials say, that President Hussein has decided to embrace both Babylon and its most famous leader.</p>
        <p>''We would like to remind our people that this is not the first time we have faced a great challenge and overcome a great challenge,'' said Salah Mukhtar, editor of the Government newspaper Al Jumiriya.</p>
        <p>President Hussein has been the effective ruler of Iraq since 1968, but since he formally took up the reins of power in 1979, Iraq has experienced only three years unencumbered either by war or ostracism. From 1980 to 1988, its forces battled Iran in a conflict of attrition in which neither side truly gained, and since 1990 it has been isolated from most of the world as punishment for the invasion of Kuwait that ignited the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>But Iraqis remain fiercely proud both of that recent past -- Iraq defeated both Iran and the United States, many people here insist -- and of their distant history in this land once called Mesopotamia, the land between the Tigris and Euphrates Rivers that is remembered as the cradle of ancient civilization.</p>
        <p>There has been little opportunity for role models in intervening eras of Iraqi history -- troubled centuries in which Iraq was racked by Ottoman occupation, British colonialism and then fierce battles for power even after the monarchy was overthrown in 1958. And so it is in Babylon -- 60 miles south of Baghdad, and praised long ago by the Greek historian Herodotus as a city that ''surpasses in its splendor everything in the known world'' -- that the Government has found a favorite emblem.</p>
        <p>''The parallel is that Saddam Hussein is a national hero,'' Iraq's Information Minister, Hamid Yousif Hummadi, replied when asked what might link President Hussein and ancient leader whose formal title was King Nebuchadnezzar II. ''You may find this strange, because national heroes no longer exist in the minds of Western civilization. In the history of the United States, you have very few. You have Jefferson, Lincoln and, after that, you have only politicians who make promises they do not keep.''</p>
        <p>Every autumn in Babylon, in the replica of an ancient amphitheater, the Iraqi Government stages a festival, celebrating through poetry, dance and other pageantry the fact that ''from Nebuchadnezzar to Saddam Hussein Babylon invokes its glory on the path of jihad and glorious development,'' as last year's posters announced.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats say they do not know whether the President himself is a frequent visitor to a grand palace overlooking the ruins that was erected in white marble after the 1991 Persian Gulf war and dominates local landscape from a hilltop that road signs label Saddam Hill. The old, old Babylon whose most famous King was Hammurabi flourished in about 1800 B.C., but the era most celebrated in Iraq today is the city's more recent prime under Nebuchadnezzar, when it became a showcase of great walls, temples and the fabled Hanging Gardens, a wonder of the ancient world.</p>
        <p>Because much of Babylon was constructed from mud and wattle, and subjected to the spillage from the nearby rivers, few of its structures have survived the centuries. Of the murals and other treasures that remained, many were pried away by Western explorers at the beginning of this century and can be found now only in French and German museums.</p>
        <p>But in the grand renovation, which lasted from 1982 to 1988, Iraqi archeologists let neither destruction nor plundering stand in their way. Where only mounds of earth and scattered bricks remained, they built soaring walls and even a replica of the famous Ishtar Gate, its facade adorned with bulls and lions. Of Babylon's most fabled sites, what little has been reconstructed of the hanging gardens is mostly indiscernible, and the Tower of Babel, at the center of what was once a complex of temples, remains essentially a stump.</p>
        <p>Since the Persian Gulf war, even small archeological excavations have been ordered to a halt -- a consequence, officials at the site say, of the financial constraints imposed by the United Nations sanctions.</p>
        <p>A visitor who arrived at the site one recent weekday found no other tourists, although local authorities say two or three small busloads turn up on most days. On this day, at least, the museum and gift shop were closed, and no one seemed to know when they would reopen.</p>
        <p>No photographs showing the hilltop palace would be permitted, local officials cautioned from the outset. But a resident archeologist, Ismail Jassem Ali, was eager to point out other notable sites, crouching to point out the bricks inscribed by Nebuchadnezzar that lay at the base of the grand walls and reach high to point to those bearing the name of President Hussein, which lay like patchwork in the edifices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ali also called attention to an enormous sculptured lion, hewn from a block of basalt and perched atop the figure of recumbent human, whose left hand is clenched in the lion's mouth.</p>
        <p>''It is a symbol of the power and glory of Babylon,'' Mr. Ali declared.</p>
        <p>Babylon Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
