<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Santa Claus, a Comeback Year</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANTA CLAUS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Santa Claus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7D71E38F930A15751C1A962958260" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Santa Claus, a Comeback Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is more talked about than David Letterman or Newt Gingrich. He has enjoyed more comebacks than George Foreman or John Travolta. And though his origins date to the fourth century, he is as contemporary as "ER" or Green Day.</p>
        <p>This popular, powerful person is Santa Claus. And this holiday season, Santa Claus has assumed a far more visible role at the epicenter of the Christmas celebration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is more talked about than David Letterman or Newt Gingrich. He has enjoyed more comebacks than George Foreman or John Travolta. And though his origins date to the fourth century, he is as contemporary as "ER" or Green Day.</p>
        <p>This popular, powerful person is Santa Claus. And this holiday season, Santa Claus has assumed a far more visible role at the epicenter of the Christmas celebration.</p>
        <p>Skeptics who do not believe in Santa, or his resurgence, might consider the following list -- which, needless to say, has been checked twice:</p>
        <p>*One of the year's biggest box-office draws is "The Santa Clause" from Walt Disney Pictures, which in selling more than $107 million of tickets in only six weeks has bested a pregnant Arnold Schwarzenegger, a vampiric Tom Cruise and two generations of crews of the Starship Enterprise.</p>
        <p>*Hallmark Cards Inc., the country's largest purveyor of seasons' greetings, reports that sales of cards, gift wrap and ornaments bearing likenesses of Santa are particularly strong this year.</p>
        <p>*Advertisers are unleashing a phalanx of Santas upon consumers. The Coca-Cola Company has emblazoned jolly drawings of Santa Claus on soft-drink cans and bottles. In a new television commercial for Nabisco, two Santa Clauses in a department store discuss how to eat Oreo cookies. And a smiling Santa, naked but for his boots and hat, appears on a billboard for Maxfield, a Los Angeles clothing store.</p>
        <p>*Santa Claus was the subject this week of a new episode of "Biography," a series on the Arts &amp; Entertainment cable television network that usually profiles figures like Franklin D. Roosevelt and Clint Eastwood. The hourlong program traced the origins of Santa to St. Nicholas, a fourth-century bishop in what is now Turkey.</p>
        <p>*Santa Claus, like Diana, the Princess of Wales, and Oprah Winfrey, is a magazine cover star -- the subject for the first time of the cover article of the December issue of Better Homes and Gardens, America's fifth-largest magazine, with a circulation of more than 7.6 million.</p>
        <p>*One of only three known copies of the 1823 poem "A Visit from St. Nicholas" -- also known as " 'Twas the Night Before Christmas" -- that were handwritten and signed by the author, Clement Clarke Moore, was sold at auction at Christie's on Dec. 9 for $255,500. Pre-auction estimates of a price had ranged from $70,000 to $90,000.</p>
        <p>Why the lift in Santa's fortunes? The primary reason, some say, is a sense that society has begun to prize more highly many of the values that people believe are embodied by Santa Claus, from nostalgia to comfort to altruism.</p>
        <p>"The kind of consumer mood I'm seeing a lot is that we've lost our center, that our values are falling apart, that the media are filled with not only bad news, but shocking and appalling news," said Judith Langer, president of Langer Associates, a market research and trend consulting company in New York. "So maybe there's something very reassuring about this familiar figure, this generous figure."</p>
        <p>Jean LemMon, editor in chief of Better Homes and Gardens in Des Moines, said of Santa's prominence and predominance: "I think it's a connection we're all making."</p>
        <p>"When we live in a very fast-paced, high-tech world, there's a craving for nostalgia, for an emotional security blanket," she added. "Our responsibilities get heavier, yet still there is something of the child in all of us."</p>
        <p>The magazine's cover presents a beaming Santa Claus at the doorway of his home, a sack of toys at his feet and his reindeer at the ready. It was painted in 1963 by Haddon Sundblom, the artist whose depictions of Santa Claus as an active ambassador of good will, primarily through advertisements he created for Coca-Cola from 1931 to 1966, have significantly shaped Americans' images of Santa.</p>
        <p>For Christmas 1994, a grinning "Sundblom Santa" appears on packages of the company's flagship Coca-Cola Classic brand. And for the first time, Coca-Cola has licensed a Sundblom illustration to the Franklin Mint, which is selling a collector plate for $29.95.</p>
        <p>The Sundblom Santa is "a real, warm, giving person with human elements attached to him," said Phil Mooney, archivist for Coca-Cola in Atlanta, adding that the character was "a guy you can relate to, a guy you'd like to have at your home for the holidays; he'd grab a turkey leg and a Coke out of your refrigerator if you weren't careful."</p>
        <p>Those personality traits run like a thread throughout most of the current characterizations of Santa Claus.</p>
        <p>"Maybe people are reaching for something a little more . . . nice," said Bob Neuman, a senior vice president and group creative director at the FCB/Leber Katz Partners advertising agency in New York. He and his partner, Bob Phillips, produced the Oreo commercial for Nabisco.</p>
        <p>In the spot, one Santa, doffing his costume, confides to his colleague that "ever since I was a little kid, I'd eat the cream and leave the rest for Santa."</p>
        <p>The colleague, fully resplendent in Santa Claus garb, replies dryly: "I know. I missed the cream."</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuman said the commercial "reinforces the fantasy" of Santa Claus: "You don't want to believe, but you'd like to."</p>
        <p>That issue resonates particularly in "The Santa Clause," which stars the comedian Tim Allen as a divorced father who, under the title's stipulation, must assume Santa Claus's role and duties after inadvertently causing Santa's death.</p>
        <p>"This is clearly a fable for our times," said Steve Rudnick, who with his partner Leo Benvenuti wrote the film's screenplay. "It's all about belief."</p>
        <p>"It's a story of a father who can't connect with his son until he becomes Santa Claus," Mr. Rudnick added, "and finally becomes the father, and the person, he always knew he could be."</p>
        <p>"And it's not so much about Christmas and Santa," he continued, "as about kids losing their belief in magic too soon and too quickly. In our cynical times, we begin to lose that magic so early; it's nice to get it back."</p>
        <p>For all this conjecture about Santa's renewed role in Christmas, it could simply be a matter of size.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Langer of Langer Associates put it, "Maybe the baby boomers like to see someone a little plumper."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
