<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Displaying A Love For Paris</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUSSELL, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASON, RAYMOND</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DF1F38F930A15751C1A962958260" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Displaying A Love For Paris</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RUSSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RUSSELL, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is at the Marlborough Gallery a substantial exhibition of sculptures and reliefs, large and small, with associated drawings, by Raymond Mason, a British artist now 74 years old who has lived primarily in Paris since July 1946.</p>
        <p>Among "the foreigners in Paris," Mr. Mason is known for his wit, his wide and genuine reserves of knowledge and his readiness to speak his mind at all times and in all places. His love for Paris comes out in this show at all levels, from the studies of young people in the Latin Quarter to the polyester reliefs of Le Grand Louvre, and from the drawing of a single plane tree on the Boulevard St.-Michel to the steep-pitched views of the Rue Monsieur-le-Prince, with its unhurrying and villagey atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is at the Marlborough Gallery a substantial exhibition of sculptures and reliefs, large and small, with associated drawings, by Raymond Mason, a British artist now 74 years old who has lived primarily in Paris since July 1946.</p>
        <p>Among "the foreigners in Paris," Mr. Mason is known for his wit, his wide and genuine reserves of knowledge and his readiness to speak his mind at all times and in all places. His love for Paris comes out in this show at all levels, from the studies of young people in the Latin Quarter to the polyester reliefs of Le Grand Louvre, and from the drawing of a single plane tree on the Boulevard St.-Michel to the steep-pitched views of the Rue Monsieur-le-Prince, with its unhurrying and villagey atmosphere.</p>
        <p>When he feels like it, Mr. Mason has a gift for the portrayal of an understated happiness, whether in Paris or in the countryside near Menerbes, in Provence, where he spends the summer.</p>
        <p>But he is also a moralist who feels that there are cruelties and twists of fate that have their place in art. From that point of view, some of the show is distinctly unseasonable. The very large work called "A Tragedy in the North. Winter, Rain and Tears, 1977" is about as un-Christmassy as art can get.</p>
        <p>A little mining town in the desolate north of France is minutely reproduced, with the main gate of the mine, the penitential red-brick buildings, the tall blank fence and the greasy cobblestones. The townspeople wait for news in varying states of exhaustion and despair.</p>
        <p>Cheerful it is not, and cannot be. But with its deep perspective, its feeling for detail and its almost clinical insight into the choreographies of extreme distress, it is a remarkable achievement.</p>
        <p>And if it seems to hark back to the conditions of an earlier age, that does not mean that it is out of date. All over Central and Eastern Europe, not to mention the former Soviet Union, there are factories by the hundred in which disaster may strike at any time (and may not be reported).</p>
        <p>Among the other subjects treated in this show are the social history of Birmingham, England, where Mr. Mason was born, and the removal from Paris in 1969 of the great food markets that for generations had been in Les Halles to make way for an urban renewal project.</p>
        <p>Both are celebratory in tone. Mr. Mason sets before us an inventive and prosperous city in which there was plenty to be proud of. And when he tackles the enforced flight from Les Halles, he suggests that a whole world of plenty is on the move. It is only right that the big version of the Birmingham piece now has a place of honor in Birmingham itself, and that "Les Halles" is now in the great church of St.-Eustache in Paris.</p>
        <p>Along with the big sculptures are sketches and drawings that were prompted by just about everything, from the statues of Moliere and Boileau on the Louvre and the grape pickers in Provence to the look of London and Edinburgh and Stockholm.</p>
        <p>When invited to make decorations for the Georgetown Plaza in Washington, he researched the sojourn of George Washington and Pierre Charles L'Enfant in Suter's Tavern in Georgetown, when they were planning the future development of the city.</p>
        <p>And in his large-scale sculptures of crowds (one of which was for a time fitted neatly into the Tuileries Gardens in Paris), he did not just lump figures together. He gave thought to all the possible meanings of a crowd, from jubilation to violence. He has, after all, lived through the period in which Elias Canetti's "Crowds and Power" was one of the most influential books around.</p>
        <p>Despite recurrent attacks of ill health, Mr. Mason has always been a tremendous worker. Big sculptures about big subjects were always his meat. In Paris, he has enjoyed the friendship and the admiration of a gamut of French artists that included Balthus, Giacometti, Dubuffet and Henri Cartier-Bresson.</p>
        <p>It was with Balthus that he went to Switzerland to observe the centenary of Charlie Chaplin, and Mr. Cartier-Bresson's photograph of Mr. Mason drawing on a Parisian rooftop is a classic image of the artist at work.</p>
        <p>Some of his achievements passed almost unnoticed at the time and have since sunk from view. One of them (not in the show) is the scenery for Racine's "Phaedre," which he made in 1959 for Marie Bell, a great actress of the day.</p>
        <p>As is his custom, Raymond Mason gave his whole self to this redoubtable task, even though only two performances were scheduled. It is clear from black-and-white photographs taken at the time and reproduced in a weighty study of the artist's career by Michael Edwards (just out from Thames &amp; Hudson) that Mr. Mason worked at a high pitch of pity and terror to produce an erotic labyrinth of a kind that is latent in the text but not often seen in the theater.</p>
        <p>The multiplicity of his ambitions has not always served his reputation well. Puny and repetitive work is often preferred by critics, but Mr. Mason's is a big, generous nature. It is made clear in this show that when difficult things have to be said, he hunkers down and says them.</p>
        <p>The works of Raymond Mason remain at the Marlborough Gallery, 40 West 57th Street, Manhattan, through Jan. 7.  ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
