<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Perils Showing In Free Trade Accord</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CRISIS IN MEXICO: WASHINGTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4DA1E38F930A15751C1A962958260" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Perils Showing In Free Trade Accord</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ross Perot is not quite saying "I told you so," but he and other critics of the North American Free Trade Agreement are coming pretty close.</p>
        <p>To the discomfiture of the White House, which has counted the passage of the North American Free Trade Agreement as one of President Clinton's clearest triumphs, this week's financial turmoil in Mexico has revived the political perils involved in the agreement. And the peso's steep drop in currency markets, by making Mexico's exports to the United States much more competitive with American goods, can only make the President's job more difficult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ross Perot is not quite saying "I told you so," but he and other critics of the North American Free Trade Agreement are coming pretty close.</p>
        <p>To the discomfiture of the White House, which has counted the passage of the North American Free Trade Agreement as one of President Clinton's clearest triumphs, this week's financial turmoil in Mexico has revived the political perils involved in the agreement. And the peso's steep drop in currency markets, by making Mexico's exports to the United States much more competitive with American goods, can only make the President's job more difficult.</p>
        <p>If more goods from Mexico start pouring into United States markets, how will the White House persuade the public that free trade enriches the country and does not destroy jobs, particularly manufacturing jobs?</p>
        <p>Several Administration officials were quick to point out privately today that the peso's plunge might not have much effect on trade. Decisions to buy and sell goods across international boundaries are typically made many months in advance, and nobody knows how long the peso will stay at its current value, said the officials, who insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>Economists typically estimate that it takes at least six months for a shift in exchange rates to show up in trade patterns, and then the changes generally are slow to happen. Still, none of that prevented Mr. Perot from enjoying the moment.</p>
        <p>It is not clear who will benefit politically from the troubles in Mexico, other than Mr. Perot and perhaps any liberal Democratic challengers to Mr. Clinton's renomination for President. A broad coalition of moderate Democrats and Republicans were involved in the passage of the agreement and, earlier this month, a global free trade pact.</p>
        <p>During his campaign against the North American agreement last year, Mr. Perot had warned that the Mexican Government would devalue the peso by 25 to 30 percent in 1994 and unleash a flood of low-priced goods on the American market once trade barriers were removed.</p>
        <p>"I do not want to be vindicated, and I would like to be wrong," Mr. Perot said in a telephone interview today.</p>
        <p>While most professional economists may disagree with what Mr. Perot says, other critics of the agreement, like Ralph Nader, were quick to join him today in denouncing the Administration's decision to make available a $6 billion line of credit to Mexico. "Nafta was supposed to be about two-way trade, not U.S. taxpayer welfare to prop up the Mexican peso and the Mexican oligarchs," said Mr. Nader, the consumer activist and critic of free trade.</p>
        <p>The agreement took effect on Jan. 1 of this year, immediately eliminating three-fifths of the tariffs on trade among Canada, Mexico and the United States and gradually eliminating the rest over 15 years. The House and Senate approved it in November of last year after vigorous lobbying by the Clinton Administration.</p>
        <p>Administration officials refused to discuss the free trade pact publicly today, as part of a general reluctance to offend Mexico or frighten financial markets already agitated by the peso's 28.1 percent fall.</p>
        <p>Some Administration officials, though, pointed out today that by conventional economic theories, the total volume of trade matters much more than surpluses or deficits with one nation. Trade allows each country to specialize in producing whatever goods it can make most efficiently, while importing the rest. This specialization increases economic output around the globe.</p>
        <p>That argument may score with economists, but politically, trade balances between nations take on great importance, notably in the case of Japan.</p>
        <p>Through October, the United States surplus with Mexico rose to $1.71 billion from $1.32 billion in the first 10 months of last year, although in October the United States ran a rare deficit of $89 million. This, and the fact that relatively few jobs have been lost to low-wage Mexican competition, has helped the Administration to silence the critics from organized labor, environmental and consumer groups who fought the agreement last year.</p>
        <p>The main reasons cited for the Mexican action this week -- two political assassinations, a guerrilla insurgency in southern Mexico and a change of government -- are not what Mr. Perot specifically mentioned. But the effects could be the same: the shrinkage or elimination of the United States' trade surplus with Mexico, as the falling peso makes American goods more expensive in Mexico and Mexican goods cheaper here.</p>
        <p>At a hearing before a House panel on March 24, 1993, Mr. Perot warned that, "These guys are just playing poker with us, and they are going to have to devalue the peso."  CRISIS IN MEXICO: WASHINGTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
