<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. OFFICIALS SEIZE HUGE HEROIN CACHE</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="454539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEROIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MYANMAR</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">THAILAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LAOS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TREASTER, JOSEPH B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Laos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Laos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DD1F30F931A15755C0A967958260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. OFFICIALS SEIZE HUGE HEROIN CACHE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TREASTER, JOSEPH B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal agents in San Francisco yesterday announced the biggest seizure of heroin in United States history, raising more concerns that the drug is growing more and more popular.</p>
        <p>"There's been a tremendous amount of attention focused on cocaine," said Ralph B. Lochridge, a spokesman for the Federal Drug Enforcement Administration in Los Angeles. "But we have a serious heroin problem and it's growing."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal agents in San Francisco yesterday announced the biggest seizure of heroin in United States history, raising more concerns that the drug is growing more and more popular.</p>
        <p>"There's been a tremendous amount of attention focused on cocaine," said Ralph B. Lochridge, a spokesman for the Federal Drug Enforcement Administration in Los Angeles. "But we have a serious heroin problem and it's growing."</p>
        <p>United States Customs agents discovered the record shipment of heroin, nearly 1,080 pounds from Myanmar, Laos and Thailand, hidden in a cargo container among millions of clear plastic produce bags late last month. But they kept the discovery secret until yesterday when they arrested four people suspected of involvement in the smuggling.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press said authorities identified the defendants as Lu Chin Sheng; Jim Juichang Chen; his wife, Lucy Chen, and Kelly Paokui Chen, who is married to Jim Chen's brother. Mr. Sheng is from Bangkok, while the rest are Taiwanese who are resident aliens in the United States, said Bob Bender, the agent at the Drug Enforcement Administration's San Francisco office.  Twice Previous Record</p>
        <p>Heroin smuggling into the United States appeared to jump in 1988 when Federal agents seized 1,824 pounds, double the amount for the previous year, and it has continued at high levels, the authorities say. The previous record for a single shipment was 820 pounds found by agents in New York City in 1989 packed in rubber lawn mower wheels in dozens of boxes inside a cargo container.</p>
        <p>Federal agents and other drug experts said they regarded the seizure in San Francisco as an indication that a great volume of the drug is being shipped into the United States and said that intercepting one load was unlikely to have an appreciable effect on the nationwide supply of the drug.</p>
        <p>"For any shipment like this that you catch, you can assume that many more get through," said Mark A. R. Kleiman, a specialist on drug policy at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>Bumper crops of opium, the raw material of heroin, have been coming out of Asia and the drug is being sold on the street in this country in such potent blends that it can be snorted liked cocaine or smoked like crack, practices that have not been widespread since the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>Waiting for the Drugs</p>
        <p>Paul R. Andrews, the district director of Customs for San Francisco, said inspectors were waiting for the shipment of plastic bags when they were hoisted ashore from the holds of the cargo ship President Truman in the Port of Oakland on May 20. They had reviewed the manifest for the cargo, which had been loaded in Bangkok and shipped through Taiwan, and found "what we considered inconsistencies."</p>
        <p>A crew of Customs agents and National Guardsmen worked several hours unloading more than 1,300 boxes from the container. Most of the boxes contained two rolls of 1,000 or more plastic bags. But in one group of 59 boxes, lashed together on a wooden sled, the plastic bags had been replaced with heroin.  Followed to Warehouse</p>
        <p>Cakes of the narcotic, about six inches in diameter and looking somewhat like a small rounds of cheese, had been covered with a brown wax, then covered in silver wrapping paper decorated with colored balloons and the words: Happy Birthday. Finally, the parcels were swathed in masking tape and packed six to a box.</p>
        <p>The agents removed all but a few pounds of the drug and restored the shipment to look as if it had not been tampered with. When a broker trucked it to a warehouse in Hayward, east of San Francisco, the agents followed. They watched the warehouse, day and night, for the next month.</p>
        <p>Several times, men and women entered the warehouse. But the agents did not make a move, hoping that by waiting they would capture a greater number of smugglers. But on Thursday, as some of the suspected smugglers foraged through the cartons, the agents' hand was forced. "They discovered a hidden camera," said Rollin B. Klink, the special agent in charge of Customs in San Francisco. "They knew we were watching. So we went ahead and made the arrests."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
