<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jury Queries An Ex-Lawyer Of Lewinsky</title>
    <meta content="Y19STA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Paula Corbin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Francis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7D81F3DF93AA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jury Queries An Ex-Lawyer Of Lewinsky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal grand jury investigating relationship between Pres Clinton and Monica S Lewinsky hears tesitmony from lawyer Francis Carter, who helped prepare Lewinsky's statement in Paul Corbin Jones lawsuit (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal grand jury investigating the relationship between President Clinton and Monica S. Lewinsky today heard from the lawyer who had helped prepare her statement in the Paula Corbin Jones lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The testimony by the lawyer, Francis Carter, has been sought from the outset of the inquiry by independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr. Mr. Carter helped prepare an affidavit on Ms. Lewinsky's behalf in the lawsuit by Ms. Jones, in which Ms. Lewinsky denied under oath that she had had a sexual relationship with Mr. Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal grand jury investigating the relationship between President Clinton and Monica S. Lewinsky today heard from the lawyer who had helped prepare her statement in the Paula Corbin Jones lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The testimony by the lawyer, Francis Carter, has been sought from the outset of the inquiry by independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr. Mr. Carter helped prepare an affidavit on Ms. Lewinsky's behalf in the lawsuit by Ms. Jones, in which Ms. Lewinsky denied under oath that she had had a sexual relationship with Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky was referred to Mr. Carter by Vernon E. Jordan Jr., a close friend of the President. Mr. Jordan has said that he took Ms. Lewinsky to see Mr. Carter at about the time he was helping to arrange a job for her. At the time, she faced a subpoena in the sexual harassment lawsuit brought by Ms. Jones against Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>After a full day before the grand jury, Mr. Carter declined to answer reporters' questions. His lawyer, Charles Ogletree, said some questions had been posed about Mr. Carter's relationship with Mr. Jordan, but he declined to provide details other than to say Mr. Carter</p>
        <p>''testified completely, thoroughly and accurately.''</p>
        <p>But later today, in an interview with The Washington Post, Mr. Carter depicted himself as a lawyer who had been kept in the dark by his client, Ms. Lewinsky, about several important details. Ms. Lewinsky did not tell him that she had received gifts from President Clinton, or that Mr. Jordan was even then trying to help her find a job, The Post quoted Mr. Carter as saying.</p>
        <p>''I had no idea of any connection between Vernon and her and any job search,'' Mr. Carter recounted in The Post interview, published in Friday's editions. ''She never mentioned it, and neither did Vernon.''</p>
        <p>Had the subject of Mr. Jordan's job-hunting help come up, Mr. Carter said, ''I might have asked her why he was doing it.'' But he stressed that he still might not have thought anything was improper, because she also had ties to other prominent Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan has said he tried to assist Ms. Lewinsky at the request of President Clinton's personal secretary, Betty Currie. Mr. Starr is known to be investigating whether the job aid from Mr. Jordan was part of an illegal scheme to keep Ms. Lewinsky quiet about a possible affair with Mr. Clinton while the Jones lawsuit was still pending.</p>
        <p>A subpoena from Ms. Jones's legal team had demanded that Ms. Lewinsky turn over any gifts from the President (which reportedly included a brooch, a T-shirt and a copy of Walt Whitman's ''Leaves of Grass''), but Mr. Carter said Ms. Lewinsky never mentioned any gifts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter said Mr. Jordan, a powerful figure in Washington's political and social circles, never suggested how the case should be handled but simply ''took a piece of candy'' and left Mr. Carter and Ms. Lewinsky alone to get acquainted.</p>
        <p>Later, though, Mr. Jordan called him on several occasions to see how Ms. Lewinsky was doing.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Lewinsky had denied a sexual relationship with the President in the Jones affidavit, Ms. Lewinsky's second set of lawyers had proposed as part of secret immunity talks with prosecutors that she would be willing to testify that she did have sex with Mr. Clinton, lawyers involved in those talks said.</p>
        <p>But no evidence has surfaced to indicate that Mr. Carter did anything improper in helping Ms. Lewinsky prepare her original affidavit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter's appeared before the grand jury today after losing a court fight over whether his conversations with Ms. Lewinsky were protected by the lawyer-client privilege.</p>
        <p>Also today, Attorney General Janet Reno said she had not decided whether to open an inquiry about accusations in a new magazine, Brill's Content, that Mr. Starr made improper disclosures to reporters. Mr. Starr has denied those accusations. Ms. Reno said she had referred the matter to the Office of Professional Responsibility at the Justice Department to decide whether to pursue an inquiry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
