<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Passes Bill Requiring H.I.V. Tracking</title>
    <meta content="19LEGI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy, Right of</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4D71F3DF93AA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Passes Bill Requiring H.I.V. Tracking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Legislature, on final night of 1998 session, passes measure requiring that names of HIV-positive people be reported to state and mandating that govt health workers ask infected people to name their sexual partners so that they can be notified that they are at risk; aides to Gov Pataki says he intends to sign it; in addition to HIV tracking measure, both houses of Legislature pass two bills resulting from 11th-hour agreements with Pataki, one to create appeals process for people whose health insurance companies deny coverage for treatment, and another to expand health care for poor children (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the final night of the 1998 session, the State Legislature passed a measure requiring that the names of H.I.V.-positive people be reported to the state and mandating that government health workers ask infected people to name their sexual partners so they can be notified that they are at risk.</p>
        <p>The bill passed the Democrat-led Assembly 112 to 34, shortly before 2 this morning. The Republican-controlled Senate passed it Thursday night by a vote of 55 to 6. A large majority of Assembly members were known to favor the measure, which had been kept from a vote by the leadership in recent years. Aides to Gov. George E. Pataki, said he intends to sign it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the final night of the 1998 session, the State Legislature passed a measure requiring that the names of H.I.V.-positive people be reported to the state and mandating that government health workers ask infected people to name their sexual partners so they can be notified that they are at risk.</p>
        <p>The bill passed the Democrat-led Assembly 112 to 34, shortly before 2 this morning. The Republican-controlled Senate passed it Thursday night by a vote of 55 to 6. A large majority of Assembly members were known to favor the measure, which had been kept from a vote by the leadership in recent years. Aides to Gov. George E. Pataki, said he intends to sign it.</p>
        <p>In addition to the H.I.V. tracking measure, both houses of the legislature Thursday night passed two bills resulting from 11th hour agreements with the Governor, one to create an appeals process for people whose health insurance companies deny coverage for treatment, and another to expand health care for poor children.</p>
        <p>Thursday was the last scheduled day of the session but both houses are to return this morning to complete their business.</p>
        <p>As the Senate and Assembly met late into Thursday night to conclude what many legislators called a singularly unproductive year, leaders of the two houses and Governor Pataki failed to agree on a wide range of measures that appeared possible, even likely, as recently as a day or two ago: ending parole for violent felons, establishing charter schools, consolidating the state's multilayered court system, allowing dairy farmers to charge more for milk and permitting mutual insurance companies to sell billions of dollars' worth of stock.</p>
        <p>But it was a bitter internal fight over H.I.V. legislation among the Democrats who control the Assembly that occupied much of the last two days in that house, and provided the greatest drama on the final day.</p>
        <p>After years of resisting the concept, the Democrats who control the Assembly allowed their house to vote on the bill requiring reporting, by name, of people infected with the AIDS virus, to the State Health Department, which would keep a central registry of the names.</p>
        <p>Local health agencies would be required to interview all people reported as testing positive, ask them for the names of their sexual partners, and then warn those partners that they had been exposed to the virus. But the law would not penalize anyone who refused to divulge the names of their sexual partners.</p>
        <p>Twenty-eight other states, including New Jersey, already track H.I.V. cases by name, but many of those do not mandate the tracing of contacts. Passage of the measure in New York is significant because it has the nation's highest rate of reported AIDS cases.</p>
        <p>Public health officials have said that reporting by name and tracing contacts are needed to make sure that people are aware that they have been exposed to the virus, in part to reduce the risk of spreading the infection. Early detection of the virus is considered increasingly important since a new class of AIDS drugs called protease inhibitors has proven effective in treating the disease in many people.</p>
        <p>AIDS-treatment advocacy groups have fought the measure, contending that it would discourage people from being tested and seeking treatment. Some said patients could be effectively tracked without using their names, by assigning them identification codes. But supporters of the bill said such a system would be cumbersome and might hinder the ability to track the spread of the disease.</p>
        <p>It has long been clear that such a bill had enough votes to pass the Assembly -- nearly all the 53 Republicans and most of the 97 Democrats favor it -- but Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver kept it from coming to a vote for years.</p>
        <p>The bill's sponsor, Assemblywoman Nettie Mayersohn, a Queens Democrat, has been a loud and relentless advocate, spending years trying to embarrass Mr. Silver into allowing a vote. And many Assembly members have said the public pressure on them to act grew greatly with the news last fall that one man, Nushawn J. Williams, had infected more than a dozen women and girls in small towns in western New York.</p>
        <p>Thursday, Mr. Silver gave in to pressure from other Democrats. Many genuinely supported the measure, while others feared their failure to act on it would be used against them as a campaign issue by Republicans. Mr. Silver negotiated some minor changes with Ms. Mayersohn, then freed legislators to vote as they pleased. The bill squeaked through two committees, by votes of 11 to 10, before going to the floor.</p>
        <p>''This is a great moment for common sense,'' said Ms. Mayersohn. ''This is what we do with every other serious communicable disease, and what we should have done years ago with this one.''</p>
        <p>But Robert Jaffe, a lobbyist for Gay Men's Health Crisis, said, ''It really intrudes upon the relationship between the physician and the patient. The idea that H.I.V.-positive persons will disclose to government workers who they don't know and don't trust is a fantasy. From the beginning, we've been told this was being driven by the politics surrounding the Nushawn Williams case.''</p>
        <p>Despite the resolution of the AIDS issue, many legislators expressed disappointment about a session that seemed much more promising months ago. In April, many lawmakers were euphoric after the Legislature enacted the least-tardy state budget in five years. For the first time, the budget was hammered out in conference committees, with the involvement of many rank-and-file legislators, rather than in secret meetings among state leaders.</p>
        <p>But for those same lawmakers, the last seven weeks of the session -- and the final 48 hours in particular -- were a distinct letdown. Mr. Pataki, who is running for re-election, took much of the wind out of the Legislature's sails by vetoing $1.6 billion in spending it had approved, and the rest of the session sank into a morass of recriminations and election-year politicking.</p>
        <p>''Outside of getting a budget done in a timely way, there was virtually nothing accomplished here,'' said Assemblyman John J. Faso of Kinderhook, the Republican minority leader.</p>
        <p>One of the final deals made by lawmakers strikes at health insurers that deny people coverage for treatment, whose only option is to appeal the insurer. Instead, the agreement reached by Mr. Silver, Mr. Pataki and the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, would allow patients to appeal a denial of treatment -- including of experimental treatments -- to an independent arbiter chosen by the State Health Department. The bill passed Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The bill could neutralize what was shaping up to be an issue in the gubernatorial race. Lieut. Gov. Betsy McCaughey Ross, Mr. Pataki's former protegee who is now running against him as a Democrat, has made attacks on health maintenance organizations and calls for an outside appeals process a centerpiece of her campaign, and some of the other Democrats in the race have joined in.</p>
        <p>The Legislature also passed an expansion of the state's health care program for children of low-income families, which will be paid for by New York's share of a $24 billion Federal grant program established last year. About 420,000 children are eligible for the program, but fewer than half that number are enrolled.</p>
        <p>The state program, called Child Health Plus, makes health coverage  available at little or no cost. Income limits would be raised -- from $35,000 a year for a family of four, for example, to $40,000 -- expanding eligibility by about 35,000 children. It would also lower the fees charged to some families, and move some children in the program into Medicaid, the Federal health program, giving them a wider range of benefits.</p>
        <p>The most prominent proposal to fade away in the waning hours, and the one Mr. Pataki had pressed for most vigorously, would have ended parole boards' ability to release violent felons from prison early. Under the measure, felons would have been required to serve at least 85 percent of their sentences.</p>
        <p>As with many of the issues taken up this year, the Democratic Assembly leaders were reluctant to go along, but were aware that the Governor's position was popular, and that Democrats might pay a price at the polls for opposing it.</p>
        <p>In the second-to-last week of the session, Mr. Silver said he would accept the parole provision if it were linked to expanded education programs in prisons and to laws allowing some felons to be sentenced to drug treatment programs rather than prison. Mr. Pataki and Mr. Bruno rejected those conditions, and no compromise was reached.</p>
        <p>The Governor was the chief advocate for several other ideas that died in the last few days, like casino gambling and creating so-called charter schools, public schools with particular missions that operate largely independent of the usual bureaucracy. The Assembly Democrats and their allies, the teachers' unions, opposed the Governor's charter schools proposal, and while they insisted they were open to some other version, there was little evidence of a middle ground they would accept.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki also wanted to allow mutual insurance companies, which are technically owned by their policyholders, to sell stock to outsiders with limited compensation to policyholders.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
