<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China's Middle Class Savors Its New Wealth</title>
    <meta content="19BEIJ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumers and Consumption</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D81F3DF93AA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China's Middle Class Savors Its New Wealth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China's middle class is seen savoring its new wealth; like a phoenix rising from ashes of Communism, last few years have seen stunning growth of flourishing Chinese middle class; 10 years ago this group did not exist; today, its core of independent businessmen has been joined by growing number of private-sector lawyers, artists and employees of joint-venture companies; it is first defined by what its members have: cell phones, washing machines, computers and, increasingly, cars and homes; they go to Saturday night concerts and vacation abroad; but rapid accumulation of material things has left its psychological mark as well, infusing this group with a kind of independence and carefree optimism that has not existed in China for decades; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every Friday afternoon, dozens of late-model cars pull up to the iron gate of the three-year-old 21st-Century Experimental School, one of several new private schools here.</p>
        <p>In a city where sturdy black bicycles are still the favored mode of transportation and horse-drawn carts ply the streets, men in suits and women wearing expensive jewelry alight from Fords, Jeeps and BMW's, rushing excitedly into the building to pick up their children -- some as young as 5 -- who board at the school from Monday to Friday at a cost of $2,000 a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every Friday afternoon, dozens of late-model cars pull up to the iron gate of the three-year-old 21st-Century Experimental School, one of several new private schools here.</p>
        <p>In a city where sturdy black bicycles are still the favored mode of transportation and horse-drawn carts ply the streets, men in suits and women wearing expensive jewelry alight from Fords, Jeeps and BMW's, rushing excitedly into the building to pick up their children -- some as young as 5 -- who board at the school from Monday to Friday at a cost of $2,000 a year.</p>
        <p>It is a substantial sum in a country where the average annual wage is $1,000. And tuition does not include the $10,000 ''contribution'' that parents generally make when their children enroll. Still, parents fight to have their children here.</p>
        <p>''The tuition is high,'' said Du Juan, with bobbed hair, a cell phone, and a stylish jean vest, who owns an information consulting business. ''But it's worth it for my daughter's future. The teachers, the environment and the equipment are better here.''</p>
        <p>Like a phoenix rising from the ashes of Communism, the last few years have seen the stunning growth of a flourishing Chinese middle class. Ten years ago, this group did not even exist. Today its core of independent businessmen has been joined by a growing number of private-sector lawyers, artists and employees of joint-venture companies.</p>
        <p>It is first defined by what its members have: cell phones, washing machines, computers and, increasingly, cars and homes. On Saturday nights they go to concerts; in winter they vacation in Thailand. But the rapid accumulation of material things has left its psychological mark as well, infusing this group with a kind of independence and carefree optimism  that has not existed in China for decades.</p>
        <p>''For many people, the change in the last decade has really been tremendous -- so tremendous it's hard to measure,'' said Conghua Li, an analyst at Deloitte &amp; Touche Consulting Group in Toronto who was born in Beijing. ''Every time I go back I'm shocked and surprised, mostly in a good way.''</p>
        <p>There is no one statistic that defines this group, which broadly includes both company presidents (who seem to have it all) and young professionals who have just bought their first computer (and want it all, someday). They are people who work hard for what they achieve, for the most part without the family ties to the Communist Party leadership that have long defined China's most privileged class.</p>
        <p>The group portrait is best created like a pointillist painting from 1,000 small facts: Ten years ago, 95 percent of passengers on airline flights in China were foreigners; today, 95 percent are Chinese. Ten years ago, extremely few Chinese had stayed in five-star hotels; today about 10 percent of bookings are from Chinese travelers paying their own way. In 1990, there were no cellular phones in China. Now there are almost 17 million.</p>
        <p>The middle class is admired by college students who hope to join its ranks, and after years of ambivalence the Communist Party, since its congress last fall, has embraced it for its contributions to China's modernization. The Chinese Government has arranged for President Clinton to meet private businessmen during his state visit, which begins next week.</p>
        <p>''The social status of people like me has improved a lot in the last few years,'' said Fang Zeng, 33, a soft-spoken real estate developer. ''And that's a really big change.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Fang represented China at an international business conference and was tapped to be a delegate to his local Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference, an advisory body of distinguished non-Communist Party members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fang and his wife, who teaches at Beijing University, each own their own cars. For next year's vacation, they are deliberating between Europe and Australia. They have donated money to establish university scholarships and children's libraries in Beijing, among other causes. And, although they now live in a one-bedroom apartment provided by Beijing University, they are contemplating ownership once they have a child.</p>
        <p>''I could never have imagined I would be where I am today,'' said Mr. Fang. ''I have so many capabilities and choices.''</p>
        <p>Of course, his has been a complicated transformation, given the country's egalitarian tradition under Communism, because the wave of prosperity that has created a middle class has not carried all Chinese equally. For every 30-year-old entrepreneur who has moved up in social status, there are many more workers laid off from ailing state-owned factories who have fallen.</p>
        <p>The income gap between China's rich and poor is widening fast. In Beijing last year, the average annual salary for bosses of private companies was about $8,000 and for workers only $1,000, said Dai Jianzhong, a sociologist at the Beijing Academy of Social Sciences. The disparity between rich and poor is even greater in the countryside. While annual salaries for paralegal assistants at private law firms might be $2,000, assistant professors at the state universities make half that much.</p>
        <p>''In the last few years, there are a lot of people who have gotten rich very quickly,'' said Mr. Dai. ''But the tension between wealth and social inequality has not been addressed.''</p>
        <p>Some members of the new middle class say they feel the anger of those left behind.</p>
        <p>''Among writers there was a lot of discussion when I bought a car,'' said Zhang Kangkang, a novelist who says she cannot afford to leave her cramped one-bedroom apartment but used savings to buy a Japanese car in 1996 for $20,000. ''Many seemed to resent it. They said I was cutting myself off from the masses.''</p>
        <p>She said that when her husband, a college professor, took the $15,000, in cash, that she was paid for a screenplay to a local bank recently, the other customers cursed him.</p>
        <p>Although Chinese entrepreneurs began accumulating money in the late 1980's, it was not until the mid-90's that the accouterments of middle-class life -- cell phones, microwaves, a wide range of cars -- were readily available for purchase in China. Then the middle class really took off.</p>
        <p>''Last year was the year everyone in our compound bought cars,'' said Ms. Zhang, displaying the newly expanded parking lot.</p>
        <p>Some of the earliest entrants to the middle class, generally young high-tech entrepreneurs who quit state enterprises to start private companies nearly a decade ago, are now wealthy by any country's standards.</p>
        <p>Yan Junjie and Zhang Can were college sweethearts who began a computer company in 1990, when China was ''starting to transform from a planned to a market economy and was full of opportunity,'' Mr. Yan said.</p>
        <p>Their company, the Dyne Group, with revenues of $240 million last year, now sells computer systems and pharmaceuticals, and is branching out into furniture.</p>
        <p>''With the commercialization of housing this year, I think Chinese will be buying nicer furniture for their homes,'' Mr. Zhang explained, referring to the Government's plan to allow Chinese to purchase their Government-supplied apartments.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yan and Mr. Zhang live a life unthinkable a decade ago, with four cars (two Mercedes, one Lincoln, one Ford) and several homes: a villa in Beijing, a country house and a third in Fremont, Calif., where their company has its American office. Although Mr. Zhang would not disclose his own income, he said that many of his senior executives now own houses. The couple have been to Europe and Singapore, and only their busy work schedule keeps them from traveling more often.</p>
        <p>Like many newly rich Chinese, they seem vaguely uncomfortable when asked about wealth. Their favorite activity remains hiking in the mountains near Beijing. Following a common Chinese practice, their 9-year-old daughter lives with her grandmother in another part of Beijing, where she attends a public school.</p>
        <p>For most Chinese the move into the middle class is still a step-by-step process, with each choosing components of middle-class life he can afford.</p>
        <p>At 8 A.M. on a recent Saturday morning, a group of 20 friends and colleagues boarded a bus for a resort an hour outside the city, for a weekend of hiking, boating and karaoke. Young professionals in their 20's and 30's, they had each paid $50 to join this rite of the middle class.</p>
        <p>''My living standard has raised a lot,'' said Zhang Guoliang, 33, an affable lawyer with a video camera slung over his shoulder, who bought a Chinese-made Volkswagen last year. ''When I have the opportunity I will buy a villa in the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>Three rows behind him, Xu Guangli, an administrator at a joint-venture company, and Sun Huawei, an assistant to a trade arbitrator, both 24, discussed their weekend plans. They cannot afford to go abroad, they said, but try to take weekend trips each month, either on organized tours or by renting cars with friends.</p>
        <p>Fei Qinggang, the hand-shaking manager of Tai He Travel, said his small state-owned travel agency started offering weekend tours last June when it sensed a market demand, and in peak season now sends out up to 80 travelers a weekend.</p>
        <p>''The travel is quite striking,'' said Conghua Li. ''Ten years ago 'vacation' was not a concept in China. There was just no such thing.''</p>
        <p>But the change involves a shift in mind-set as well. ''There is now a significant middle-class market emerging,'' said Yukon Huang, head of the World Bank office in China. ''As in other countries, the middle class is more independent, more mobile'' and more active, he said, in public affairs.</p>
        <p>The parents at the 21st-Century Experimental School say they selected the school for its emphasis on creative thinking and independence -- not traditional Chinese values.</p>
        <p>''Public schools focus only on exams,'' said Zhang Jieting, 34, the businessman who founded the school. ''We focus on developing the child to meet the needs of the modern Chinese economy.''</p>
        <p>And middle-class Chinese bring with them the same sort of expansive optimism that characterized newly prosperous Americans after World War II.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zang, the real-estate entrepreneur, who is an avid reader, said that one of the biggest excitements for him is no longer having to check the price of books before buying them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Zhang, the writer, sounds like an excited teen-ager as she describes the sense of freedom that has come with her car: trips to galleries and to plays, carefree jaunts around a homeland that she had never explored before.</p>
        <p>''This is not just about money. It's about a better quality of life,'' she said. ''And it moves us toward greater spiritual and political freedom.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
