<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CABARET GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="19CABA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DC1E3DF93AA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="3469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CABARET GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER, in ''The Real Thing,'' Eighty-Eight's, 228 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 924-0088. Hefty and leonine, with a voice similar to Cher's, Ms. Dexter is a thoughtful interpreter who resists taking the easy path of overemoting as a pseudo-blues mama. In her new show, which focuses on songs about the unhappier aspects of love, Ms. Dexter plays the role of romantic sage, dishing out advice in clear, carefully rounded interpretations. Besides Cher, imagine a bluesier, gutsier Mama Cass singing a program ranging from standards like ''You've Changed'' to contemporary classics like ''I Can't Make You Love Me,'' identified with Bonnie Raitt. Tomorrow at 8:30 P.M. Cover: $15; two-drink minimum; no credit cards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER, in ''The Real Thing,'' Eighty-Eight's, 228 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 924-0088. Hefty and leonine, with a voice similar to Cher's, Ms. Dexter is a thoughtful interpreter who resists taking the easy path of overemoting as a pseudo-blues mama. In her new show, which focuses on songs about the unhappier aspects of love, Ms. Dexter plays the role of romantic sage, dishing out advice in clear, carefully rounded interpretations. Besides Cher, imagine a bluesier, gutsier Mama Cass singing a program ranging from standards like ''You've Changed'' to contemporary classics like ''I Can't Make You Love Me,'' identified with Bonnie Raitt. Tomorrow at 8:30 P.M. Cover: $15; two-drink minimum; no credit cards.</p>
        <p>''I LOVE NEW YORK,'' Rainbow and Stars, 30 Rockefeller Plaza, 65th floor, (212) 632-5000. The 18 songs included in this breezy four-person revue offer a gentrified tourist's-eye view of the city, jumping around in time from the era of Victor Herbert to that of Billy Joel. Each song is the musical equivalent of a snapshot taken during a mad dash around town. Stitching the songs together is an unseen voice, reading hyperbolic tour-guide blurbs about sites ranging from Coney Island (the cast takes a bumpy imaginary ride on a roller coaster) to the Empire State Building. The performers, who suggest a cross-section of white middle-class types, include Bryan Batt (campy and bustling), Lewis Cleale (thin-voiced and patrician) and Heather MacRae (cheery). Janet Metz, the only one to break through the surface of the material, makes ''Story of My Life,'' a song dropped from the musical ''Wonderful Town,'' something to remember. Through July 25. Tuesdays through Thursdays at 8:30 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays at 8:30 and 11 P.M. Cover charge: $40. Dinner is required for the early show.</p>
        <p>* SUSANNA McCORKLE, the Oak Room, Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, (212) 840-6800. The handsomely refurbished Oak Room at the Algonquin has reopened with a splendid new show by Ms. McCorkle celebrating both George Gershwin and Antonio Carlos Jobim, composers of different generations and nationalities who reached beyond the pop realm. Each composer is given a concise anecdotal history by Ms. McCorkle, whose sweet, smoky voice and insinuating delivery suggest Billie Holiday filtered through Julie London by way of Lee Wiley. She finds a common strain of erotic longing in both songwriters, eschewing high drama in favor of a dreamy contemplative approach. The high point is a languid ''I Loves You, Porgy'' that evokes a woman in sad hypnotic thrall to a dangerous but irresistible dream lover. Cabaret performing rarely gets this smart and sexy at the same time. Through July 4. Tuesdays and Wednesdays at 9 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays at 9 and 11 P.M. Cover: $40; $15 food or drink minimum.</p>
        <p>* JAMES NAUGHTON, Manhattan Theater Club, City Center, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. Who knew that James Naughton, the rugged Broadway presence in shows like ''City of Angels'' and ''Chicago,'' was also a crooner with a meltingly beautiful voice that suggests a cross between the young Bing Crosby and the 60's Joe Williams? Making his cabaret debut in Manhattan Theater Club's new performance series, Mr. Naughton performs everything from classic ballads like ''Star Dust'' and ''The Folks Who Live on the Hill,'' to Randy Newman dramatic monologues, to a 1962 novelty hit, ''I've Been Everywhere,'' by the country singer Hank Snow. An ultra-suave smoothie who maintains a safe emotional distance from his material, Mr. Naughton glides comfortably between genres, buoyed by an excellent pop-jazz quartet led by John Oddo. Through June 28. Tuesdays through Fridays at 7:30 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays at 3 and 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $35; $20 for students; $15 general admission 15 minutes before show time are subject to availability.</p>
        <p>STEVE ROSS, the Firebird Cafe, 363 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 586-0244. With his slicked-back hair, white dinner jacket and black tie, the singer and pianist Steve Ross fits to a T an earlier era's image of the perfect gentleman. Playing 1940's hotel-style piano and singing in a voice that suggests Fred Astaire filtered through Mabel Mercer, Mr. Ross conjures up an ambiance that could be 1939 or 1959 but is certainly not of the moment. His engaging new show, ''Hooray for Love,'' which culminates in a suite of Cole Porter gems, is a poised and sophisticated tour of a bygone show-business society ruled by the bons mots of Porter, Noel Coward and Lorenz Hart. It's a refreshing world to visit. Through July 4. Tuesdays through Thursdays at 9 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays at 9 and 11 P.M. Cover: $30; two-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>* ''SECRETS EVERY SMART TRAVELER SHOULD KNOW,'' Triad Theater, 158 West 72d Street, (212) 799-4599. Among the dozen songwriters who have contributed material to this witty early-60's-style revue spoofing the perils of travel, the show's musical director, Stan Freeman, and its bass player, Jay Leonhart, have provided several of the best bits. Mr. Freeman's ''Paradise Found'' extols the highly questionable pleasures of roughing it in Uzbekistan. Mr. Leonhart's ''Customs'' is the complaint of an explorer detained in customs with his menagerie of wildlife from all over the globe. The level of humor is not as scattershot as in most such shows. And its cast -- including John Sloman, Liz McConahay, Kathy Fitzgerald and James Darrah -- handles the material with tongue-in-cheek agility. Mondays, Wednesdays through Fridays at 8 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays at 3 and 7:30 P.M. Open-ended run. Tickets: $47.50; mezzanine, $42.50.</p>
        <p>* BOBBY SHORT, Cafe Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 570-7184. Last spring, the eternally ebullient Bobby Short took an eight-piece swing band into the Cafe Carlyle for the first time. And this season, his 31st at the club, they are back, and the chemistry between the singer-pianist and his band is clicking more harmoniously than ever. The unfussy, swinging arrangements featuring three brasses and three reeds bring out the exuberant belter in Mr. Short, who nightly turns the cafe into a euphoric private party in which he shouts out popular chestnuts with the enthusiasm of a roue who hasn't lost touch with the little boy inside. One of many high points is his revival of a 1936 Cole Porter nugget, ''Rap Tap on Wood,'' which wittily cautions against being carried away when the stock market is booming and life seems to overflow with milk and honey: times like the present. Through June 27. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8:45 and 10:45. Cover: $50; no minimum.</p>
        <p>* JULIE WILSON, Michael's Pub at Bill's Gay 90's, 57 East 54th Street, (212) 758-2272. Widely recognized as the queen of cabaret and the heir of Mabel Mercer in infusing everything she sings with a lifetime's accumulated wisdom and humor, Julie Wilson has settled in at the restaurant cabaret atop Bill's Gay 90's for what has turned out to be a semipermanent residence. Her new show, ''The Julie Wilson Song Book,'' is a far-reaching career survey that includes such signature songs as the Stephen Sondheim classics ''The Ladies Who Lunch'' (which nobody does with more ferocity) and ''I Never Do Anything Twice,'' as well as additions to her repertory that include ''The Lady Is a Tramp,'' ''Here's to Life'' and Fats Waller's ''Find Out What They Like and How They Like It.'' Tuesdays through Thursdays at 9:30 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays at 9 and 11 P.M. Cover: Tuesday through Thursday, $20; Friday and Saturday, $25; $15 food or drink minimum.</p>
        <p>BEMELMANS BAR, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. The singer Barbara Carroll. Through July 18. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9:45 P.M. to 12:45 A.M. Cover: $10.</p>
        <p>CAFE PIERRE, Fifth Avenue at 61st Street, (212) 940-8195. Kathleen Landis, a singer and pianist, performs ''Things Are Looking Up,'' songs celebrating the season and the Gershwin birthday centennial. She performs Tuesday through Saturday. Nancy Winston, a pianist and singer, performs on Sunday and Monday nights. No cover for either show; $12 minimum. Open-ended run. All performances at 8:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>DANNY'S SKYLIGHT ROOM, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. Singers. Tonight at 7, Carmen LaMar in ''The Kid in Me.'' Tomorrow at 7 P.M., John Rainbow and David Witherspoon; at 9:15 P.M., Traci O'Kelly. Sunday at 6:15 P.M., Jenny Lane performs in ''Singing and Dancing''; at 8:30 P.M., Kirsten Wendelborn. Cover: $6 to $15; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>DON'T TELL MAMA, 343 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 757-0788. Tonight: Jerry Laird, at 7; Denie Corbett, singer, with Vanessa Vickers and band, at 8; Stephen Browning, singer, at 9; Tommy Femia, Judy Garland impersonator, at 10. Tomorrow night: Swingirls, vocal group, at 6; Beverly Bonner and James R. Garrett, comedy, at 7; the Stand-Up Comedy Experience, at 8 and 10:15; Gina Augusta, singer, at 9. Sunday: John Patrick Schutz, singer, at 3 P.M; ''Who's Minding the Office?,'' singers, at 7 P.M.; ''Raven Snook,'' musical comedy with Fran Minarik, at 8 P.M. Covers: $8 to $20; two-drink minimum for all shows.</p>
        <p>THE DUPLEX, 61 Christopher Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-5438. Tonight: George Pellegrino, singer, at 8; ''Quirk,'' a play, at 10. Tomorrow night: Peter Cortesi, singer, at 6; Layla Ellison, singer, at 8; ''Backstage Bitches,'' a play, at 10. Sunday: Kim Austen, singer, at 4 P.M.; Richard Van Slyke, singer, at 7 P.M.; Paul Hallesy, singer, at 9 P.M. Cover: $8 to $15; two-drink minimum for all shows.</p>
        <p>SUPPER CLUB, 240 West 47th Street, (212) 921-1940. Fridays and Saturdays at 8 P.M., the Supper Club 17-Piece Big Band. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9:20 and 10:20, ''This Joint Is Jumpin','' 1940's-style cabaret, featuring Larry Marshall, with the Supper Club 17-Piece Big Band. Also tonight at 12:30 A.M., the Bellevue Cadillac. Tomorrow night at 12:30 A.M., the Flipped Fedoras and the Chrome Addicts. Music charge: $15 before 11 P.M.; $12 afterward.</p>
        <p>UPSTAIRS AT ROSE'S TURN, 55 Grove Street, West Village, (212) 366-5438. Tonight: ''Nervous Laughter,'' sketch comedy and improvisation, at 8; ''Crescendo Falls,'' a continuing soap opera, at 10. Tomorrow night: Rick Crom's ''Our Life and Times,'' musical revue, at 8; Keith Dougherty in ''Nana's Money Hole,'' comedy, at 10. Sunday: Rick Crom's ''Our Life and Times,'' at 6 P.M.; ''The Seth Rudetsky Show,'' variety, at 8 P.M. Cover: $5 to $15; two-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>YORK THEATER COMPANY, Lexington Avenue at 54th Street, (212) 935-5820. ''The Jell-O Is Always Red,'' a musical revue of the cabaret songs of Clark Gesner, with Mr. Gesner, Celia Gentry and Neal Young. Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2:30 and 8 P.M.; Thursdays and Fridays at 8 P.M.; Sundays at 2:30 and 7 P.M. Through June 28. Tickets: Wednesdays through Fridays and Sundays, $30; Fridays and Saturdays, $35.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
