<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall St. Firms Reward Chiefs For Strong '99</title>
    <meta content="Y12WALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1175793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neal, E Stanley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Komansky, David H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purcell, Philip J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mack, John J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D61E3EF931A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall St. Firms Reward Chiefs For Strong '99</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Top executives of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Co and Merrill Lynch received hefty compensations in 1999, which was most profitable year ever on Wall Street; Morgan Stanley paid top executives Philip J Purcell and John J Mack more than $26 million each in salary, bonus and stock options or 53 percent more than in 1998; Merrill Lynch almost tripled compensation of chairman and chief executive David H Komansky to $29.3 million; chief financial officer E Stanley O'Neal received $19.1 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Running an investment bank may not be the most lucrative job around anymore, but, judging by the compensation numbers from two of the biggest firms on Wall Street, the pay is still very good.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company, the biggest securities firm as measured by capital, paid its top two executives more than $26 million each in salary, bonus, stock and options last year, according to the firm's 1999 proxy statement. Those packages were 53 percent bigger than the amounts awarded in 1998 to the executives, Philip J. Purcell and John J. Mack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Running an investment bank may not be the most lucrative job around anymore, but, judging by the compensation numbers from two of the biggest firms on Wall Street, the pay is still very good.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company, the biggest securities firm as measured by capital, paid its top two executives more than $26 million each in salary, bonus, stock and options last year, according to the firm's 1999 proxy statement. Those packages were 53 percent bigger than the amounts awarded in 1998 to the executives, Philip J. Purcell and John J. Mack.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, which rebounded from a tumultuous year in 1998 but did not perform as well as Morgan Stanley, nearly tripled the compensation of its chairman and chief executive, David H. Komansky, to $29.3 million in 1999, according to Merrill's proxy statement. Mr. Komansky's package included a cash bonus of $8.2 million, stock worth $2.1 million, stock options worth $9.8 million and an insurance policy on his life worth $8.5 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Komansky's pay, certainly among the highest of any chief executive on Wall Street, came in a year in which the firm's No. 2 executive, Herbert M. Allison, was forced to resign and the firm changed its business model to accommodate low-commission stock trading over the Internet. Mr. Allison, who was president and chief operating officer, has not been replaced.</p>
        <p>The next best-paid senior executive at Merrill was E. Stanley O'Neal, the chief financial officer. He received $19.1 million, including options worth $11.5 million.</p>
        <p>''They're carting out compensation in 18-wheelers, but Wall Street is no longer the highest-paying industry of all like it used to be,'' said Graef Crystal, a compensation expert and shareholder rights advocate.</p>
        <p>The pay reports are the first from securities firms for 1999, which was the most profitable ever on Wall Street. They disclose the pay of top executives, but not necessarily the firms' best-paid employees. Often, top investment bankers and traders earn more than their bosses.</p>
        <p>The technology sector's heavy use of stock options to pay executives has made leaders of some relatively new companies in Silicon Valley much wealthier, at least on paper, than their counterparts on Wall Street. Even Mr. Purcell's pay, which Mr. Crystal had characterized as excessive in past years, seems more justifiable now, Mr. Crystal said.</p>
        <p>''The earnings per share are up sharply and the returns to shareholders are beautiful,'' Mr. Crystal said. ''He's done a very fine job.''</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley had a return of 32 percent on shareholders' equity last year, compared with 24 percent for Merrill.</p>
        <p>On top of his pay, Mr. Purcell gained $11.4 million last year from the exercise of stock options granted in previous years. Options give their holders the right, but not the obligation, to buy shares at preset prices. Mr. Purcell's exercises left him options worth about $102 million, according to the proxy.</p>
        <p>Besides the matching packages Morgan Stanley's board granted to top executives, Mr. Mack received options worth $2.2 million to replace shares he used to pay for the exercise of other options. Morgan Stanley calls such grants restoration options. Other companies call them reload options.</p>
        <p>Whatever they are called, Mr. Crystal rails against them. ''An option is supposed to die when it is either exercised or expires without being exercised,'' he said. ''With these, you can reload and reload and reload.''</p>
        <p>In 1998, Mr. Purcell's pay package was the same as Mr. Mack's, except for more than 600,000 restoration options Mr. Purcell received, which the firm valued at more than $14 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Purcell and Mr. Mack each received a salary of $775,000, a bonus of $12.1 million, stock worth $8.2 million and options worth $5.6 million.</p>
        <p>A third Morgan Stanley executive, Peter Karches, the president of its institutional securities group, took home more than $25 million last year. Mr. Karches, the president of the firm's institutional securities group, received a bonus of $11.8 million, stock worth $7.9 million and options worth $5.4 million.</p>
        <p>Two other Morgan Stanley executives, Vikram S. Pandit and Joseph R. Perella, received pay packages worth about $17.8 million. Mr. Pandit oversees the firm's stock underwriting, sales and trading operations; Mr. Perella is the head of the firm's investment banking division.</p>
        <p>At Merrill Lynch, three other executives received more than $14 million each last year. Thomas W. Davis, who oversees the institutional businesses, took home about $17.3 million, including $7.5 million in cash and stock, options worth $5.7 million and $3.9 million insurance policy.</p>
        <p>John L. Steffens, the longtime head of Merrill's brokerage network, and Jeffrey M. Peek, who has been trying to turn around Merrill's struggling mutual fund operation, each got about $7.5 million in cash and stock, options worth almost $5 million and an insurance policy worth about $2 million. Inside Merrill, Mr. Peek, Mr. Davis and Mr. O'Neal are considered leading contenders to succeed Mr. Allison as president later this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steffens gained more than $22 million last year from exercising 360,000 options, according to the proxy. Those moves left him with options worth about $63 million, the proxy shows. Mr. Komansky held options worth more than $110 million, it shows.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
