<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Listing Sought for Historic Corner of White Plains</title>
    <meta content="15WCZO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19961229T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="In the Region/Westchester" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="895631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region/Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Register of Historic Places</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Good Counsel Academy (White Plains, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EED6163EF936A25751C1A960958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Listing Sought for Historic Corner of White Plains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY McALEER VIZARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vizard, Mary Mcaleer</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nine school buildings and a chapel in White Plains, NY, all part of Good Counsel Academy, a Roman Catholic elementary and high school, are nominated for inclusion in National Register of Historic Places; photos; map (In the Region: Westchester ) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A CACHE of turn-of-the-century buildings, tucked away in a convent school off North Broadway, could become the largest historic site in this city, which is not known for its abundance of antique properties.</p>
        <p>Nine school buildings and a chapel, all part of the Good Counsel Academy, a Roman Catholic elementary and high school, have been nominated for inclusion in the National Register of Historic Places. The New York State Historic Preservation Review Board is now reviewing the nomination and is expected to recommend it for national designation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A CACHE of turn-of-the-century buildings, tucked away in a convent school off North Broadway, could become the largest historic site in this city, which is not known for its abundance of antique properties.</p>
        <p>Nine school buildings and a chapel, all part of the Good Counsel Academy, a Roman Catholic elementary and high school, have been nominated for inclusion in the National Register of Historic Places. The New York State Historic Preservation Review Board is now reviewing the nomination and is expected to recommend it for national designation.</p>
        <p>''If the board approves the nomination, it is forwarded to the National Register of Historic Places for Federal designation,'' said Ruth Pierpont, director of the Field Services Bureau at the state's Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Perservation. ''Applications don't get this far unless they already meet the national criteria.''</p>
        <p>The complex, which was built between 1890 and 1923, is among the very few historic sites left in the city, according to John Harrington, president of the Whtie Plains Historical Society. ''Urban renewal in the 1960's knocked almost everything down,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The city now has two buildings listed on the National Register -- the Jacob Purdy House, a former private residence built in the 1720's and now a museum, and the State Armory, built in 1909.</p>
        <p>''Since we have so few, we're really trying to hold onto what's left,'' Mr. Harrington said. ''The Good Counsel complex will be a great addition. It's wonderful that a whole complex of buildings has been preserved in this way. It will be the largest historic site in the city.''</p>
        <p>The school, on the west side of North Broadway between Crane and Lenox Avenues and adjacent to the Pace University campus, is in the oldest and most historically significant section of the city, according to Mr. Harrington ''Before the Revolutionary War, the village of White Plains was laid out along North Broadway,'' he explained. ''Where the school is used to be the village common.''</p>
        <p>The wide boulevard-like street is now lined with apartment buildings and commercial enterprises and its environs bear few traces of the neighborhood's early history. In fact, it is easy to miss the Good Counsel campus, since it is set back from the road and hidden behind leafy trees most of the year.</p>
        <p>The Sisters of the Divine Compassion, a religious order that owns and operates the school, began as missionaries working primarily with disadvantaged girls and young women in New York City in the late 19th century. Mother Mary Veronica, the order's founder, thought a change of scene to a more countrifed environment would be beneficial to her charges.</p>
        <p>In 1890, using her own money from a family inheritance, Mother Mary Veronica purchased a 15-acre estate on North Broadway from J. Tilford, of Park and Tilford, a well-known grocery retailer of the period.</p>
        <p>She quickly began the construction of a school complex. While most of its buildings have been altered somewhat over the years, they still maintain much of their historic integrity.</p>
        <p>As the school grew, so did its mission, which is now one of a general educational institution serving a more diversified population. ''The whole campus is a great example of the Romanesque and Mediterranean styles that used to be so prevalent in Westchester County,'' said John Bonafide, program analyst for the state's Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation.</p>
        <p>Trained in draftsmanship, Mother Mary Veronica is credited with the single-handed design of the campus's centerpiece, an 1897 stone chapel. The one-and-a-half-story structure, which seats 500, was modeled after the Church of St. Charles Borromeo, in Milan, Italy. It features dark oak exposed roof framing, an 1897 Odell tracker-action organ and original dark oak choir-loft furniture. Also noteworthy are the carved marble altar and stained-glass windows created by Handman Company, of Charing Cross, in London.</p>
        <p>The founder worked with architects, primarily Lawrence O'Connor, in the design of the rest of the school's buildings. ''She had a lot to say about every one of the buildings,'' said Sister Jane Keegan, director of grants research for the religious order, who is spearheading the preservation effort. ''Our founder was an amazing woman. She was very knowledgable and well-traveled, and found a way to use her talents to the upmost.'' Mother Mary Veronica started her life as Mary Caroline Dannat, an heir to a multimillion malt liquor business. She had endured a troubled marriage and raised two children before converting to Catholicism and founding the charitable religious order.</p>
        <p>''She's such an important 19th-century figure that we plan to research her life after completing the historic designation of the buildings,'' said Mr. Bonafide, of the state parks agency.</p>
        <p>In its heyday, the Good Counsel campus encompassed more than 30 acres. In 1975, it transferred ownership of 12 acres to Pace University, which now houses its law school in several of the convent buidings. None of the Pace properties, however, are included in the nomination for historic designation.</p>
        <p>OF the convent buildings nominated for designation to the National Register of Historic Places, a four-story, gable-roofed structure originally called the House of Nazareth was the first completed. Built in 1891, it now houses the Good Counsel High School. It still retains many of its original features, including paneled oak doors hung on ornate hinges, pine floors and pressed metal ceilings.</p>
        <p>The other buildings up for nomination include the original two-story Tilford mansion purchased by Mother Mary Veronica, built in 1856; a wood-frame cottage, circa 1901, and a century-old carriage house.</p>
        <p>One building on the campus is already listed on the National Register. Called Mapleton, built in 1857, it was once a private residence and now serves as the school's counseling center.</p>
        <p>Being listed on the National Register makes Mapleton eligible for government funding, explained Sister Jane Keegan. ''We have some grant proposals out there,'' she said. ''I heard they're sitting on Governor Pataki's desk. We're hopeful we'll get some money because the building really needs some work.''</p>
        <p>Even being nominated for historical designation opens the door to both public and private funding for the academy, Sister Jane Keegan explained. ''We got a grant from the New York State Landmark Commission, which is private, for some work we just completed on the chapel,'' she said. ''The money is only available to those buildings already on the National Register or in nomimation.''</p>
        <p>The work already completed on the chapel includes the installation of new lighting and replacement of the front steps, Sister Jane Keegan said. She added that there were now plans to restore the chapel's bell tower. ''We're hopeful that soon the church bells will be ringing again,'' she said. ''for the first time in decades.''</p>
        <p>In the Region/Westchester</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 29, 1996, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in some editions on Dec. 15 about Good Counsel Academy in White Plains misstated its location, and a map also misplaced it. The academy is on the east side of North Broadway, not the west, and it is south of Crane Avenue, not north.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 29, 1996, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in some editions on Dec. 15 about Good Counsel Academy in White Plains misstated its location, and a map also misplaced it. The academy is on the east side of North Broadway, not the west, and it is south of Crane Avenue, not north.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
