<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Long March</title>
    <meta content="625299SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="895407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kendrick, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinkead-Weekes, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, D H (1885-1930)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kendrick, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinkead-Weekes, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, D H (1885-1930)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">D H Lawrence: Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922 (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">D H Lawrence: Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922 (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFDA143CF936A25751C1A960958260" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Long March</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Kendrick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kendrick, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Kendrick reviews book D H Lawrence: Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922 by Mark Kinkead-Weekes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>D. H. LAWRENCE  Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922.  By Mark Kinkead-Weekes.  Illustrated. 943 pp. New York:  Cambridge University Press. $39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>D. H. LAWRENCE  Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922.  By Mark Kinkead-Weekes.  Illustrated. 943 pp. New York:  Cambridge University Press. $39.95.</p>
        <p>THE death of D. H. Lawrence at the early age of 44 was unfortunate for him, but readers of literary biography have reason to be grateful. If Lawrence had lived to Thomas Hardy's age (87), his ''Cambridge Biography'' would be twice as fat as it is, and it can already bring down most bookshelves.</p>
        <p>''The Cambridge Biography: D. H. Lawrence, 1885-1930'' made its debut in 1991 with John Worthen's volume ''The Early Years, 1885-1912,'' a relatively svelte 626 pages. The second, Mark Kinkead-Weekes's ''Triumph to Exile, 1912-1922,'' is the size of a cobblestone and weighs almost four pounds. It tracks Lawrence from May 3, 1912 (when he fled England for Germany with Frieda Weekley, nee von Richthofen), to Feb. 26, 1922 (when he and Frieda, long since married, sailed from Naples for Sri Lanka). This span of nine years, nine months and 23 days occupies Mr. Kinkead-Weekes for 718 large, closely printed pages, to which are added 225 of appendixes, notes and indexes. That's about a page for every three and a half days of Lawrence's life. The trend is ominous.</p>
        <p>In due course, we can expect the third, final volume, to be written by David Ellis, which will pursue its subject from Naples to the grave. That journey lasted only eight years and four days. But I tremble at the thought of the cinder block Mr. Ellis must even now be fashioning. Mr. Kinkead-Weekes excuses his own prolixity with the claim that ''the life of things tends to be found in detail, variation and change through time; though that story takes longer to tell.'' Mr. Ellis no doubt already believes this silliness; it's too late for him. But if other biographers follow, we're all in trouble.</p>
        <p>WE know, of course, that God is in the details. So, for that matter, is your cousin Fred. The biographer, it seems to me, ought not to aim at conveying a sense of ''the life of things''; poets and novelists do that pretty well (Lawrence among the best), and a stroll down the street is effective too. The biographer's art entails digesting sources, not just paraphrasing them, and constructing a portrait that, while obviously untrue to the ticktock of lived experience, nevertheless convinces the reader that the name on all those dust jackets also belonged to a creature of flesh and blood. The classic biographies -- James Boswell's of Samuel Johnson, Elizabeth Gaskell's of Charlotte Bronte, Lytton Strachey's of Queen Victoria -- do exactly that. ''Triumph to Exile'' does not; in fact, it refuses to try.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinkead-Weekes is no mere scribe of minutiae. He does inform us that in 1912, in Munich, Lawrence paid three shillings sixpence for ''a shapeless straw hat,'' and we learn that he was an ''excellent'' cook, handy with an omelet or ''an English Sunday roast,'' though we get no recipes. Mr. Kinkead-Weekes faithfully describes every hotel, pension and private house the Lawrences inhabited in their manic rambles across Europe, along with the rents they paid and the full history of every guest they received and every host who received them. He analyzes Lawrence's works, both great and small: ''Sons and Lovers,'' ''The Rainbow'' and ''Women in Love'' were completed during the period covered by ''Triumph to Exile,'' along with a steady stream of stories, poems and essays. Mr. Kinkead-Weekes accounts for them all, as well as for the crackpot theories, mostly centered on sex, that Lawrence was forever spinning out.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kinkead-Weekes is more than a chronicler; he's a theorist too. At the outset, he joins his co-biographers in announcing that they have chosen to divvy up their labors not for the reason that all human lives are short but as ''an explicit (even dramatic)'' gesture of solidarity with Lawrence in denouncing ''the old stable ego.'' ''Three Lawrences,'' they weirdly declare, ''will (we believe) answer all the more to ordinary experience of other people.'' Not content with this, Mr. Kinkead-Weekes slices his subject thinner, frequently asserting that ''it was a new Lawrence'' or ''a new Lawrence was indeed coming to be.'' I counted a good dozen ''new'' Lawrences during the long march of ''Triumph to Exile.'' If you believe Mr. Kinkead-Weekes's theories, it's a wonder Lawrence's friends recognized him when he showed up on their doorsteps. They did, however.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinkead-Weekes further fattens ''Triumph to Exile'' with many little notes, addressed apparently to himself, on what the biographer should and should not do. He must avoid playing Lawrence's ''creative imagination false by crude ideas about 'sources,' or simple extrapolations of literature to life.'' ''Again,'' Mr. Kinkead-Weekes mutters a few pages later, ''it seems impertinent to talk of 'sources' -- the only justification being to keep imagining Lawrence the writer, writing.'' He repeatedly reminds himself that writers spend ''most of their time writing,'' and that biographers ''often falsify the proportion of their lives.'' That's true, but perhaps he ought not to have seen it. It makes his whole enterprise fraudulent, or at best a fool's errand, the saddest of recognitions.</p>
        <p>Very late in ''Triumph to Exile,'' an elegiac note creeps in -- not for Lawrence, whose life ticks away toward its early end, but for Mr. Kinkead-Weekes, who goes on grappling with ''the question of biographic truth . . . always impossible, yet always to be sought for tirelessly.'' At that point, I lost my mild interest in what the Lawrences' tickets to Sri Lanka would cost (70 each, as it turns out) and began to ponder Mr. Kinkead-Weekes's tragic quest, which drove him without mercy yet compelled him always to acknowledge the futility of his labors. I picture him at his desk in Ramsgate, in the weak English sunlight, ruing the day he took early retirement from the University of Kent to write ''Triumph to Exile.'' I see him. . . . But what that story needs is a novelist, maybe even a D. H. Lawrence.</p>
        <p>Walter Kendrick is a professor of English at Fordham University and the author of ''The Secret Museum: Pornography in Modern Culture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Kendrick is a professor of English at Fordham University and the author of ''The Secret Museum: Pornography in Modern Culture.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
