<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="650781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D91031F93BA25752C1A965958260" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ACCORD ON HEALTH-INSURANCE BILL Three months after Gov. Cuomo vetoed a virtually identical bill, negotiators for the Legislature and the Governor said they had agreed on legislation that would require most health insurance policies to cover immunizations and preventive checkups for young people through age 19. A1. NEW YORK CITY  IN BLAST TRIAL, VISITS ARE RECALLED A former roommate of Mohammed A. Salameh, the lead defendant in the World Trade Center trial, said in court that two other men accused of helping to build and place a bomb in the complex visited Mr. Salameh in Jersey City just before the explosion. B3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ACCORD ON HEALTH-INSURANCE BILL Three months after Gov. Cuomo vetoed a virtually identical bill, negotiators for the Legislature and the Governor said they had agreed on legislation that would require most health insurance policies to cover immunizations and preventive checkups for young people through age 19. A1. NEW YORK CITY  IN BLAST TRIAL, VISITS ARE RECALLED A former roommate of Mohammed A. Salameh, the lead defendant in the World Trade Center trial, said in court that two other men accused of helping to build and place a bomb in the complex visited Mr. Salameh in Jersey City just before the explosion. B3.</p>
        <p>Two former Transit Authority workers have been awarded $6.3 million for injuries they said they received eight years ago as a result of exposure to toxic fumes from a solution they used to clean graffiti from subway cars. B3. NEW MULTICULTURAL CURRICULUM PLANNED Schools Chancellor Ramon C. Cortines said he has asked his staff and a special advisory board to devise a new curriculum that bolsters multicultural education. B3. Mayor Dinkins spoke at Yale about what he hoped his legacy would be. B4. A Queens Village deli owner was arrested on charges of trying to bribe detectives to overlook marijuana sales. B12. The number of runners who went to hospitals was more than the 45 transported by city ambulances. B12. REGION  THE ARTS AND FOOTBALL Poetry, the sound of trumpet riffs, artwork and short-story writing are not uncommon in the locker room of the football team at Eastside High School in Paterson, where four team members attend the Rosa Parks School of Fine and Performing Arts. B6. NO REWARDS IN TRADE-PACT DEALS So while the deals were being struck on sugar and orange juice and peanut butter to round up last-minute Democratic votes for the free trade pact, what did the New York metropolitan region get? Nothing. Most Democrats opposed the accord, and the two who supported it did not seek any special favors. A21. Impact of accord in region varies. A21. News organizations were denied the right to have representatives at a deposition given by Edward J. Rollins. B6. Vending machine operators in New Jersey are fighting town by town to keep cigarette machines legal. B6. Yale's mascot is retiring. B6. Sports betting in New Jersey was rejected. B7. A New Jersey limit on automatic dialing machines has been voided by a judge. B7. Thomas H. Jackson, provost of the University of Virginia, was named the next president of the University of Rochester. B8. Scientists say the bluefish population along the East Coast appears to have declined. B9. Chronicle B13</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
