<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slaying Suspect Dies in Shootout With Troopers</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="150553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KINDERHOOK (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERON, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LARSEN, MARK L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRIMMINS, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NAPANOCH (NY)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAUL, PATRICK D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF153BF931A35755C0A96E948260" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slaying Suspect Dies in Shootout With Troopers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES FERON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FERON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A man sought in the slaying of his former wife's lawyer was killed by state police officers yesterday in a pre-dawn shootout on a quiet upstate road, authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A man sought in the slaying of his former wife's lawyer was killed by state police officers yesterday in a pre-dawn shootout on a quiet upstate road, authorities said.</p>
        <p>A man sought in the slaying of his former wife's lawyer was killed by state police officers yesterday in a pre-dawn shootout on a quiet upstate road, authorities said.</p>
        <p>The dead man was identified as Mark L. Larsen, 43 years old, of Tillson, N.Y., a recluse who was wanted by the Columbia County Sheriff's Department for the killing last Thursday of John J. Crimmins, 40, a Chatham, N.Y., divorce lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crimmins, who represented Mr. Larsen's former wife, Marie, in a child-support dispute, was shot five times at close range and then stabbed after he walked out of his house to investigate a fire someone had started in his pickup truck. Suspect's Shack Searched</p>
        <p>According to the Columbia County District Attorney, Paul Czajka, investigators searching Mr. Larsen's home after the shooting found a piece of scrap paper with Mr. Crimmins's name on it. The suspect lived in a shack without electricity or running water on his family's farm in Rosendale, a town in Ulster County.</p>
        <p>Helicopters joined in the search for Mr. Larsen, who was described in a police bulletin as possibly armed with a shotgun, machete and an attack dog. He avoided detection until 4 A.M. today, when two state troopers stopped their patrol car to question a hitchhiker on Route 209 in Napanoch, near Ellenville.</p>
        <p>They did not know that the hitchhiker was Mr. Larsen, according to Sgt. Alfred N. Dorer of the state police in Middletown. ''He gave them a fictitious name and said his car had broken down and was in the parking lot of a supermarket nearby,'' the sergeant said.</p>
        <p>The officers drove off, found no car in the parking lot and returned to the hitchhiker.</p>
        <p>''As they started to get out, he began shooting,'' Sergeant Dorer said, and the troopers returned fire, killing Mr. Larsen. One Trooper Wounded</p>
        <p>One trooper, Patrick D. Paul, 24, was wounded in the left arm, left leg and chest, but he was protected from more serious injury by a bulletproof vest. He was reported in stable condition at the Albany Medical Center.</p>
        <p>The second trooper, Timothy J. Ruzzo, 29, was uninjured.</p>
        <p>Mr. Czajka, the District Attorney, said that the Larsens were divorced ''eight to 10 years ago'' but that ''within the last year there had been a legal action'' regarding the Larsen family farm in Rosendale.</p>
        <p>Mr. Czajka said that the investigation ''has not been closed with Larsen's death'' and that the police were continuing to look for his car, a red Volkswagen Rabbit. The gun that Mr. Larsen used in the exchange of fire with the troopers was not the one used in the Crimmins slaying, the prosecutor said.</p>
        <p>An investigator said Mr. Larsen and a red Volkswagen were seen the night before the Crimmins murder in the village of Kinderhook, where the lawyer lived, and, on the night of the murder, in Chatham, where Mr. Crimmins practiced law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larsen did not have a criminal record in New York State, Mr. Czajka said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
