<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Glittery Opening for New Bendel Store</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BENDEL, HENRI</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DULLEA, GEORGIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D91738F93BA15751C0A967958260" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Glittery Opening for New Bendel Store</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGIA DULLEA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DULLEA, GEORGIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON one floor of Henri Bendel's new store last night hung Isani's interpretations of the crisp "Jackie Kennedy" suits of the 1960's. On another floor, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis wore a beaded gold jacket over black chiffon as she shook hands on a receiving line.</p>
        <p>When someone asked what she thought of the revival, Mrs. Onassis smiled and said, "I think it's silly."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON one floor of Henri Bendel's new store last night hung Isani's interpretations of the crisp "Jackie Kennedy" suits of the 1960's. On another floor, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis wore a beaded gold jacket over black chiffon as she shook hands on a receiving line.</p>
        <p>When someone asked what she thought of the revival, Mrs. Onassis smiled and said, "I think it's silly."</p>
        <p>The occasion was somewhat more serious: the annual party of the Municipal Art Society, which likes to dine and dance in historic spaces saved from the wrecking ball.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, 300 landmark-minded guests in black tie showed up at Bendel's new home on Fifth Avenue, between 55th and 56th Street, to celebrate the marriage of "preservation and new construction," in the words of the project's chief architect, John Beyer of Beyer Blinder Belle.</p>
        <p>The women's specialty store, which opens on Saturday, preserves the facade of two landmark town houses: the former Rizzoli Building and the Coty Building. The center entrance opens onto a soaring atrium designed as a showcase for almost 300 panes of art glass designed by Rene Lalique and installed in Coty's perfumery in 1912.</p>
        <p>Balconies around the atrium allowed guests like Anne Bass, Paloma Picasso, Mario Buatta and Donna Karan to walk directly behind the glass with views onto Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>"These windows were covered by years of dirt and grime and nobody knew they were here," said the architecture critic Brendan Gill, who called the building "chic."</p>
        <p>Entering the store under the familiar chocolate-brown and white striped canopy, the guests found themselves in a Hollywood fantasy of shopping in Paris during the belle epoque.</p>
        <p>"It's slightly glorious, the way a store should look," Geoffrey Beene told a beaming Leslie H. Wexner, chairman of the Limited , which owns Bendel's.</p>
        <p>In one of the many Christian Lacroix touches, huge cabbage roses of satin covered a phantasmagoric Belter-style sofa and dangled from one chandelier. In the tableware department, a crystal chandelier dripped antique silver pitchers and creamers. On the wall of a tea shop, gilded cubes held fanciful teapots.</p>
        <p>"Look at all those teapots; they're divine," Brooke Astor said as the crowd sat down to a dinner of gravlax and veal, after which another 250 guests drifted in for dessert.</p>
        <p>Midway through dinner, Mr. Wexner took the microphone in front of the Lalique windows to say, to wild applause, that President Bush had just announced a cease-fire in the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>More applause greeted the Municipal Art Society's award of its president's medal to Justice William J. Brennan Jr., who did not attend the dinner. The Supreme Court justice, who retired last year after 34 years, wrote the 1978 decision upholding the landmark designation of Grand Central Terminal and landmark law in general.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the society's dinner, the fashion industry's cocktail party at the store on Tuesday night, whihc was attended by 1,500 people, was a mob scene. Polly Mellen of Vogue magazine darted up and down the stairs shouting, "Where are the shoes?" while Arnold Scaasi, Ivana Trump and Michael Kors were among those hugging the limestone railings.</p>
        <p>"Hopefully," Mr. Wexner said, glancing around the first floor with its Art Deco ambiance, "it doesn't feel commercial, it feels residential."</p>
        <p>That depends on where and when you live. For many women, the store's little niches and luxurious fitting rooms recalled a time when women had dressing tables and went to tea and gossiped, when women ate bonbons and read French yellow-back novels, when they shopped all day and had affairs.</p>
        <p>"Only now we have jobs," said the fashion designer Mary Ann Restivo. "This is a dream store."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
