<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fleeing Violence, Peruvians Fall Into Poverty</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LIMA (PERU)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHINING PATH (GUERRILLA ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Lima</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB143CF93BA15751C0A967958260" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fleeing Violence, Peruvians Fall Into Poverty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, Feb. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Santa Rosa communal kitchen in Monte Negro, a poor Lima neighborhood occupied by people who have fled violence in the Peruvian highlands, is a hub of activity every day. Some 30 women, dressed in traditional Peruvian colors and carrying their infants on their backs, feed themselves, their families and the community's orphans.</p>
        <p>The menu is limited: rice, a few carrots, peas, soy soup and bread.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Santa Rosa communal kitchen in Monte Negro, a poor Lima neighborhood occupied by people who have fled violence in the Peruvian highlands, is a hub of activity every day. Some 30 women, dressed in traditional Peruvian colors and carrying their infants on their backs, feed themselves, their families and the community's orphans.</p>
        <p>The menu is limited: rice, a few carrots, peas, soy soup and bread.</p>
        <p>To bring in a few more dollars, the women spend their afternoons sewing little tapestries depicting the life theyremember back in the highlands.</p>
        <p>Santa Rosa's kitchen is an example of how a small community of Andean people, called Quechuas, from Ayacucho Province pool what resources they have to cope with a new way of life.</p>
        <p>Beginning four years ago, the Quechuas started to leave their homes, escaping a conflict that is waged daily in the mountains between the military and the country's strongest guerrilla organization, the Sendero Luminoso, or Shining Path.</p>
        <p>"The army would come and you'd have to feed them; then the Sendero would come and you'd have to feed them," said a woman as she worked ona tapestry. "If one group knew you had fed the other, you'd get killed." Another woman said: "Finally, we couldn't even sleep in our homes. We had to go out to a river bank and hide at night."</p>
        <p>Accounts of indiscriminate killings by Shining Path guerrillas, trying to force people to join their ranks, and of unprovoked killings by the army, uncertain of its hidden enemy, are abundant. Of the 3,452 deaths from political violence in Peru last year, 20 percent were in Ayacucho.</p>
        <p>As a result of such conflict around Peru, people are seeking refuge in Lima. But in this city, buffeted by cholera, poverty and economic decline, theinflux has only increased the ranks of those living on the edge.</p>
        <p>Government officials say dozens of new shantytowns, or invasions as they are called, have sprung up in the last four years, built by people seeking relief from political violence in rural areas or simply hoping to find more opportunity in Lima. In an effort to cope with the soaring food prices, thousands of communal kitchens have been formed.</p>
        <p>While the first impression on entering Monte Negro is of dust and stones, the second is of fear. The women will not give their names and are visibly nervous when approached even by fellow Peruvians. And they will say very little about their past.</p>
        <p>That they fled violence is clear. What is less certain is whether they have escaped. Monte Negro and its neighboring shantytowns are considered a "red zone," where the Shining Path operates with near impunity.</p>
        <p>The presence of the group is visible throughout. Graffiti painted in bright red on the walls of buildings. call for the people to "fight and resist for the popular war" or proclaim "Long life to the people's war."</p>
        <p>A month ago, 20 women believed to be linked to the organization seized the local loudspeaker and urged the people to fight against repression.</p>
        <p>In quiet conversation, the women of Santa Rosa's kitchen, which is covered with bamboo and has a dirt floor, two crude gas stoves and three benches, betray a distinct anti-Shining Path sentiment. "We came here primarily for our children's sake," one said. "If you stay in Ayacucho, the Shining Path has so taken over the schools that you children get indoctrinated."</p>
        <p>But what is obvious after spending an afternoon here is that the Quechuas did not leave their fears behind.</p>
        <p>A man who entered the hut and greeted the women would identify himself only as a former official of the community. While echoing much of the sentiment already expressed, he stopped short of opening criticizing the Shining Path. He said the people in Santa Rosa came mainly because of brutality by the army or local militias armed by the Government to fight the guerrillas.</p>
        <p>"It's not really a war because in a war you would have two sides," he said. "It's really just the army coming looking for the Shining Path and then just killing people. No one really knows who the Shining Path is. You don't know their faces or their names."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
