<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Law, Catskill Casino Is Not Likely Anytime Soon</title>
    <meta content="18CASI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/18/nyregion/18CASI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1473345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mohawk Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Park Place Entertainment</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Catskill Development (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Park Place Entertainment Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Catskill Development</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D71431F93BA25750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Law, Catskill Casino Is Not Likely Anytime Soon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Despite Law, Catskills Casino Is a Dubious Bet Anytime Soon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newly disclosed audio tapes of secretly recorded conversation surface in suit between rival casino operators and Park Place Entertainment, world's largest gambling company; lawyers for Catskill Development say tapes support original claim that its rival Park Place Entertainment is trying to squeeze Mohawk tribe into deal for casino and out of agreement with Catskill; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a tale worthy of a novelist, fraught with intrigue, double-dealing, allegations of fraud, and, ultimately, enormous disappointment, all in search of what Indian tribes, casino operators and the administration of Gov. George E. Pataki regard as a potential gold mine: a casino in the Catskills, close by New York City.</p>
        <p>The idea of such a casino, where hundreds of thousands of customers would spend millions and make everybody else rich, has brought developers, gambling companies and tribes through the Catskills in recent years. Their efforts got a major boost 16 months ago when Governor Pataki and the Legislature authorized three tribal casinos in the Catskills, to generate revenues for a state that now faces a $12 billion budget gap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Indian tribes, casino operators and the administration of Gov. George E. Pataki regard a potential casino as a gold mine, but so far, no casino has opened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a tale worthy of a novelist, fraught with intrigue, double-dealing, allegations of fraud, and, ultimately, enormous disappointment, all in search of what Indian tribes, casino operators and the administration of Gov. George E. Pataki regard as a potential gold mine: a casino in the Catskills, close by New York City.</p>
        <p>The idea of such a casino, where hundreds of thousands of customers would spend millions and make everybody else rich, has brought developers, gambling companies and tribes through the Catskills in recent years. Their efforts got a major boost 16 months ago when Governor Pataki and the Legislature authorized three tribal casinos in the Catskills, to generate revenues for a state that now faces a $12 billion budget gap.</p>
        <p>But so far, no casino has opened in the once-thriving resort area of Sullivan County, whose hills are dotted with crumbling bungalow colonies and shuttered hotels.</p>
        <p>The reasons vary from anti-gambling opposition to intratribal disputes. But a big factor is squabbling among the rival partners for the Indian tribes, according to court papers and other documents.</p>
        <p>The tale is told in newly disclosed audio tapes of secretly recorded conversations that have surfaced in a lawsuit between rival casino operators and the largest gambling company in the world, Park Place Entertainment.</p>
        <p>In the case, Catskill Development, a small company that had concluded a partnership with the St. Regis Mohawk tribe to build a Catskill casino, accuses Park Place and its allies of using fraud, economic coercion and a $3 million loan to get the tribe to grant Park Place exclusive rights to build Mohawk casinos in New York State. The case, now nearly three years old, was dismissed in August, but Catskill Development's lawyers have appealed, and on Friday they filed a motion to reopen the case based on the newly disclosed audiotapes.</p>
        <p>What is not in dispute is that in April 2000, the tribe suddenly renounced its prior deal with Catskill Development for a casino in Monticello, in part, on promises that Park Place would rescue the Mohawks' ailing Akwesasne casino on the Canadian border and start building what Park Place said would be the largest casino resort in the world in the Catskills ''within four months.''</p>
        <p>What has been in dispute is why and how. Thomas P. Puccio, a lawyer for Catskill Development, said in a motion filed last Friday in United States District Court in Manhattan that the previously secret tape recordings buttress the claim of economic coercion. The tapes suggest that Park Place and a third company, the operator of the smaller casino, teamed up to squeeze the Mohawks to renounce their partnership with Catskill Development.</p>
        <p>On one audiotape the operator of the small casino, Ivan Kaufman, is heard telling Clive S. Cummis, now vice chairman of Park Place, that he is withholding paychecks at the casino to drive the Mohawks into the arms of Park Place. At the time, the Mohawk chiefs feared that the small casino would collapse.</p>
        <p>''The tapes graphically chronicle Park Place's use of severe economic pressure -- 'squeezing' the tribe by delaying its payroll at Akwesasne -- to force the Mohawks to drop Catskill and sign up with Park Place,'' Mr. Puccio said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Puccio's motion said that Park Place had failed to disclose the tapes during the proceedings. A lawyer for Catskill said Mr. Kaufman had also failed to give the tapes to Catskill in response to a subpoena in 2001.</p>
        <p>Walter Horn, who works with Mr. Kaufman, said that he did not know why Catskill did not get the tapes until recently. ''I assume Catskill, in their discovery, requested all these things from Park Place,'' Mr. Horn said. ''I don't know what happened.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cummis said the tapes violated laws related to interstate commerce, and then declined to comment, saying ''the matter is in litigation.'' He added that he had never had possession of the tapes. But Mr. Puccio's motion contained receipts showing that lawyers from Park Place received the tapes from Mr. Kaufman in 2001.</p>
        <p>The Mohawk chief, Paul Thompson, did not return phone calls requesting comment on the tapes.</p>
        <p>The Pataki administration had said that the state would reap hundreds of millions of dollars in revenue from three Indian casinos in the Catskills and three in northwestern New York. The state has borrowed about $300 million against future casino revenues. But only one casino has materialized, in Niagara Falls.</p>
        <p>The Catskill casinos were thought to have especially lucrative potential because Monticello is closer to New York City and millions of potential customers than the gambling halls in Atlantic City. Analysts estimated that a Catskill casino could generate revenues of $1 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Berman, a local businessman and a leader of Catskill Development, signed a deal in 1996 to build an Indian casino at the Monticello Raceway with the Mohawks, whose reservation straddles the Canadian border 350 miles to the north.</p>
        <p>Catskill hoped to give the Mohawks 30 acres of land at the Raceway and build a tribal casino there, under a newly enacted federal law. But in April 2000, the Mohawks dumped their partners and signed an unusual deal with Park Place.</p>
        <p>''I can't imagine that the tribe, or anybody who recognizes how long it takes to get land into trust for gaming, would want to undo four years of work,'' Rick Chiff, deputy chief of staff at the National Indian Gaming Commission, said at the time.</p>
        <p>At the time, gambling industry analysts and state officials speculated that the Mohawks had been misled by Park Place and its chairman, Arthur Goldberg, who they said was more interested in protecting the company's three casinos in Atlantic City. Mr. Goldberg had opposed gambling in New York, telling stockholders that a successful Catskill casino could reduce revenues in Atlantic City by as much as 20 percent.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Goldberg, who is now dead, and Mr. Cummis, the Park Place executive, vowed to build a $750 million casino at Kutsher's, near Monticello, and get federal approval ''within four months.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berman and Catskill Development sued Park Place. The lawsuit, which was dismissed in August, is on appeal. Catskill Development recently obtained the audiotapes from lawyers for the former operator of the Akwesasne casino, Mr. Kaufman, who has also sued Park Place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman's company managed the Akwesasne casino in a remote corner of New York since it opened in April 1999. But the casino was losing as much as $300,000 a month and had laid off hundreds of workers, many of them Mohawks.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Kaufman's lawsuit, Mr. Goldberg wanted to gain exclusive rights to gambling in the Catskills, not to rescue a failing upstate. Mr. Kaufman claims Mr. Goldberg reneged on a $30 million deal to buy his interest in the Akwesasne casino, and poisoned Mr. Kaufman's relationship with the Mohawks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman recorded telephone conversations with Mr. Cummis and Mr. Thompson, the Mohawk chief.</p>
        <p>But on Feb. 8, 2000, Mr. Thompson is heard on one of the recordings complaining to Mr. Kaufman that Park Place is being ''greedy,'' because it was saying it would only do a deal at Akwesasne if there were no other ''casinos in the Catskills'' than its own at Kutsher's. Mr. Goldberg ''wants it all,'' Mr. Thompson added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman confides that he may sue Park Place because of its failure to complete their agreed-upon deal at Akwesasne.</p>
        <p>But eight days later, a jubilant Mr. Cummis is telling Mr. Kaufman that the Mohawks have granted Park Place exclusivity. Mr. Kaufman confesses that he never thought that it would happen; Mr. Goldberg, he says, must be a ''genius.'' Mr. Kaufman reminds Mr. Cummis that he has helped Park Place and wants to consummate the deal at Akwesasne.</p>
        <p>''You got to remember the pressure on them with how we're squeezing them at Akwesasne is huge,'' Mr. Kaufman said. ''I have kind of delayed their payrolls and slowed it down so badly that, you know, they're looking at Arthur as a savior.''</p>
        <p>''Yep, they are,'' Mr. Cummis responded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horn denied that Mr. Kaufman was trying to coerce the tribe. ''He had no obligation to pay any of those monies,'' Mr. Horn said.</p>
        <p>The Mohawk chiefs were afraid that the collapse of the Akwesasne casino would undermine their tenuous hold on political power, according to Mohawk lawyers and several Mohawks who oppose the chiefs.</p>
        <p>On April 6, 2000, the Bureau of Indian affairs granted tentative approval for the Mohawk-Catskill Development casino, and Governor Pataki signaled he will endorse it.</p>
        <p>But ultimately, Mr. Goldberg and Mr. Cummis persuaded the Mohawks to abandon their original partners by promising, in Mr. Cummis's words, to build a casino at Kutsher's ''without any significant loss of time.'' The tribe, Mr. Cummis said, wanted ''us to pay them $3 million in cash'' to prop up the Akwesasne casino.</p>
        <p>The Akwesasne casino is still open, but the Kutsher's project is delayed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
