<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mad Emperor Meets His Match in a Rabbi With a Lifesaving Spell</title>
    <meta content="05BOOK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/05/books/05BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1405827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherwood, Frances</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Book of Splendor (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sherwood, Frances</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2DC1331F936A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mad Emperor Meets His Match in a Rabbi With a Lifesaving Spell</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Mad Emperor Meets His Match</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews book Book of Splendor by Frances Sherwood; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BOOK OF SPLENDOR  By Frances Sherwood  348 pages. Norton. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Stout, vain, self-willed and under a lowering psychotic melancholia, the Emperor Rudolph II dismisses his trusted manservant Vaclav from the imperial bedroom. He swaddles himself in cream silk and ermine, lifts a razor and inflicts a delicate cut on his wrist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Splendor" is based on history. But Frances Sherwood is the rare writer whose work goes far beyond what we think of as historical novels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BOOK OF SPLENDOR  By Frances Sherwood  348 pages. Norton. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Stout, vain, self-willed and under a lowering psychotic melancholia, the Emperor Rudolph II dismisses his trusted manservant Vaclav from the imperial bedroom. He swaddles himself in cream silk and ermine, lifts a razor and inflicts a delicate cut on his wrist.</p>
        <p>''Vaclav,'' he screams immediately. ''Do you not see, you knave, I am bleeding to death?'' Successively then, in the rhythm of the clockwork figures that circle atop one of Prague's Old Town towers, Rudolph's doctor, courtiers and guards troop in, followed by the clergy, heads of guilds, leading citizens and Maisel, the emperor's wealthy court Jew.</p>
        <p>Why the flirtatious dabble at suicide? It is an act of petulance. As one Prague resident remarks later: ''The emperor is so afraid of dying, he tried to get it over by killing himself.'' Capricious as a kitten, frightening as a panther, Rudolph instantly switches from petulance to autocratic mania.</p>
        <p>Two eminent English alchemists -- one, Queen Elizabeth's legendary John Dee -- will be sent for to prepare, on pain of death, an eternal-life elixir. As backup, Rudolph commands Prague's likewise legendary Rabbi Loew to devise, on pain of the destruction of the Jewish quarter and its inhabitants, an immortality spell.</p>
        <p>The clouds of imperial madness give way, for the tiniest of moments, to a patch of mad lucidity. How will he tell, the emperor wonders, whether the remedies have worked? ''How will I know that I will live forever? What if I live and then I die? What then?''</p>
        <p>''What then?'' would make a splendid title for Frances Sherwood's historical novel -- a confining category for such a freely expansive book -- set at the start of the 17th century. Her choice, though, ''The Book of Splendor,'' is not just a title but truth in labeling.</p>
        <p>How the author presents Rudolph, and what she does with him, is by turns a fiction, an essay and a Punch-and-Judy show about the comedy, the aberrance and the futility of power. About its humanity, too, in a way: the tyrant as infant. Conceive a Nativity scene with Herod burbling in the manger.</p>
        <p>If this were all, ''Splendor'' would be a chilly gem: a portrait of the rarefied atmosphere at power's heights (Hradcany Castle, in this case, set on a bluff above the town) and of the oxygen-starved delusions they breed. The author has surrounded her lethal imperial child, though, with a quirkily humane counterpoint.</p>
        <p>There is the astronomer Tycho Brahe -- the savant likewise as child, but an endearing one -- and Johannes Kepler, his disciple and mentor a posteriori. He instructs Brahe's theories, that is, by taking them further. There is Vaclav, who turns out to be something more and better than a servant, and Kirakos, the court doctor, who is also something more -- an Ottoman spy -- and then more and better than that. Ms. Sherwood's characters don't just possess qualities; they propagate them.</p>
        <p>The main counterpoint to the castle, though -- the heart and a dose of demonic cackle to ''Splendor's'' brain -- lies in the town below, specifically in the Judenstadt or ghetto. Here, in alternating and converging chapters, is the story of Rochel, the beautiful and restless bride of Zev the shoemaker. For a while we may wonder: another ''Fiddler on the Roof''? Forget it: heartwarming it may be but only to provide forging temperature for an armored spine and spark-spitting medulla.</p>
        <p>Rochel is an orphan; worse than that she is illegitimate and the product of rape; worse yet, the rapist was not a Jew but a Cossack. Only the prophetic love of Rabbi Loew and his wife, Perl, win her a grudging acceptance by the community and marriage to a fussy, loving, but, at that point, unloved older man. She is a free spirit confined. ''I have entered the forest of the dead,'' she exclaims when she sees Zev's dark dwelling, hung with tanned hides.</p>
        <p>But the ghetto is in danger, not just from the emperor's threat but also from whispers of pogrom from the town. So Rabbi Loew -- a real figure to whom a legend has attached -- goes down to the river bank and fashions a golem, traditionally meant to do household chores and defend the community.</p>
        <p>As prescribed, Yossel is a giant, though a gentle, loving one (until the end) and beautiful. He and Rochel exchange glances. ''A delicious tingle started at her heels, spread upward, and the tips of her fingers sizzled like a water bubble in a frying pan.'' Then come caresses, then much more. Ms. Sherwood writes with quiet but arousing eroticism; no small achievement for a coupling of maid and mud.</p>
        <p>Yossel's true strength is an innocent intelligence. Accompanying the rabbi, he stymies the emperor's pogrom threat by devising community life insurance. Each Jew, he tells Rudolph, will uniquely possess one secret word in the eternal-life spell that is being prepared for him.</p>
        <p>There is a violent and exuberant climax that enmeshes the castle with the ghetto. There are heroic deaths and a variety of ingeniously encouraging individual endings. The main ending is stunning: as Yossel tragically blossoms, we realize, Rudolph has been receding all the while into golemlike mud. Rochel grows old and wise. She writes books. Her face, by Ms. Sherwood's description, resembles her own jacket photograph. Why shouldn't an author have her personal golem, particularly when she uses it so well?</p>
        <p>As noted, ''Splendor'' is based on history. But Ms. Sherwood, author of ''Vindication,'' a treatment of the early English feminist Mary Wollstonecraft, is the rare writer whose work goes far beyond what we think of as historical novels.</p>
        <p>Instead of history's retrospective certainty -- this is how it was -- Ms. Sherwood projects her readers, as if by time machine, back into a place where everything is still to be discovered. We do not feel that her characters are keeping appointments. Rather than moving confidently backward out of the clarity of Now, we move uncertainly forward from a foggy Then. We are only truly in the past when we feel lost in it.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
