<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Work Force Adept at Recycling</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MENTAL RETARDATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSOLIDATED EDISON CO OF NY INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINGER, PENNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF1631F93BA35750C0A964958260" item-length="1191" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Work Force Adept at Recycling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SINGER, PENNY</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROSALEE ALLEN is 47 years old and for the first time she has a paying job. Marilyn Guzman, who is 28, is also working in her first real job. Both women are employed at Con Edison's Eastview operations center here, where they process rubber-coated cable wire for recycling. Their jobs were made possible by a training agreement between Con Edison and the Westchester Association for Retarded Citizens.</p>
        <p>"Recycling is a wonderful industry for our people because they are comfortable with the repetitive tasks that others find dull and boring," said Richard Swierat, executive director of the association, which trains people for the workplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROSALEE ALLEN is 47 years old and for the first time she has a paying job. Marilyn Guzman, who is 28, is also working in her first real job. Both women are employed at Con Edison's Eastview operations center here, where they process rubber-coated cable wire for recycling. Their jobs were made possible by a training agreement between Con Edison and the Westchester Association for Retarded Citizens.</p>
        <p>"Recycling is a wonderful industry for our people because they are comfortable with the repetitive tasks that others find dull and boring," said Richard Swierat, executive director of the association, which trains people for the workplace.</p>
        <p>Last April he presented the idea that people with disabilities could be trained to become valuable employees to George J. Delaney, vice president of Con Edison's Westchester division.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Delaney cut through red tape so quickly that in three months' time we had seven of our people in a vocational-training program, preparing scrap metal for recycling and refurbishing hardware for re-use at the Con Edison facility," Mr. Swierat said. The Benefits for Con Edison</p>
        <p>Mr. Delaney said that the program also makes "dollars and sense" for both organizations.</p>
        <p>"It's a good illustration of how private industry can effectively use people with disabilities in the work force," he said. "The principal value of our agreement with ARC is that it clearly shows that people with mental retardation and development disabilities can perform effectively.</p>
        <p>"But it's also a two-way street. With the hard work of the people from ARC, we are able to do a more complete job of recycling and re-using our materials than we were able to do before they came to us." From a Workshop to a Paying Job</p>
        <p>Three women and four men, 20 to 50 years old, from the association meet their job coach, Liery Wynn, at the association's workshop in Yonkers every morning at 9 o'clock to commute to their jobs at Con Edison.</p>
        <p>"The program is run out of our Yonkers workshop because we had people there who were ready to leave the sheltered workshop environment for outside jobs," said Mr. Swierat.</p>
        <p>The Westchester Association for Retarded Citizens is the largest private nonprofit agency serving the mentally retarded in the county. The vocational-training program is one of the specialized services it offers to give people who were previously thought to be unemployable an opportunity to find and keep real jobs.</p>
        <p>Before the workers could start their jobs at Con Edison, modifications to tools and work procedures had to be made for the safety of the trainees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Swierat praised the inventiveness of Con Ed employees. "Keeping safety first and foremost in mind," he said, "many of them worked on projects that ranged from redesigning tools, incorporating special safety features, to changing work procedures to make jobs easier for our people to handle." Shields Added to Tools</p>
        <p>John Anelli, the manager of distribution management at Eastview, said, "It is the finest program that I have ever been involved with at Con Edison." Working with the operating supervisor, Tom Evans, and other Con Edison employees, Mr. Anelli set up the work systems and procedures for the trainees.</p>
        <p>By adding shields and guards, for example, tools were revamped so that no cutting surfaces were exposed. A cement mixer was adapted to simplify the procedure for cleaning hardware for re-use. Other machines were redesigned with safety features, including the one workers use to cut wire cable into four-foot lengths. After the wire is cut, the workers bundle it so it can be melted down and re-used.</p>
        <p>"Just seeing what these people can accomplish once they've been trained is extremely gratifying," Mr. Anelli said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, the operating supervisor, said the human value of the program is its most important aspect. "Not only does it help the ARC people, but the Con Edison employees here at Eastview also feel good when they see that the ideas they have contributed to make the program work have been successful." Complex Work Being Done</p>
        <p>The newly trained group works under the supervision of Mr. Wynn, the jobs coach. He begins by evaluating the recycling jobs, breaking them into component parts, and then instructs the trainees on procedures and monitors their performance.</p>
        <p>"The work this group is doing is pretty complex," Mr. Wynn said. "They have to operate several different kinds of machines, but there haven't been any injuries. You know, Con Edison represents another world to them. They are so enthusiastic about what they are doing there that production has just about doubled."</p>
        <p>In addition to the 7 original workers, 25 to 30 more substitutes are being trained at the Con Ed site, Mr. Wynn said. "They fill in when one of the original seven are out, which isn't very often, but it's good to get as many of our people into the mainstream as possible."</p>
        <p>After 19 weeks of working on the recycling project five days a week, five hours a day -- the hours will be extended gradually -- the trainees have processed 100,000 pounds of copper, aluminum and tinned copper from scrap cable. They have cleaned, sanded and refurbished more than 9,000 pieces of overhead hardware, including insulators, metal couplings and gas pipes, and they have cleaned, scrubbed and painted more than 200 curb valve boxes -- the large metal boxes that connect residential gas pipelines to pipes in the street. Con Ed previously sold the boxes for scrap.</p>
        <p>The value of the work handled by the new workers not only covered the $5.25 hourly wage each trainee received but also enabled Con Edison to realize a saving of more than $35,000, Mr. Delaney said, adding that the company plans to bring reclamation materials from other parts of the Con Edison system in New York City to Westchester to be processed. 'She Hasn't Missed a Day'</p>
        <p>And the value of the program to Rosalee Allen and Marilyn Guzman?</p>
        <p>"More than anything, Rosalee looks forward to work," said Zoe Bonilla, Ms. Allen's sister. "She hasn't missed a day. Her self-esteem has risen, and she has become more independent. Our family has always been behind her, but the experience of getting into the mainstream has helped her gain more insight into herself."</p>
        <p>Gladys Guzman, Marilyn Guzman's mother, said: "It's the best thing that has happened to Marilyn. She enjoys her job so much; it has been a real learning experience for her. And she is so delighted to be earning a real salary. It has given her such confidence and a feeling of self-worth."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Guzman also praised the Association for Retarded Citizens for the work they do. "The people there, like Mr. Wynn, who Marilyn calls Big Daddy, are warm and caring and really dedicated to helping people like Marilyn lead productive lives."</p>
        <p>The ultimate goal for the association, Mr. Wynn said, is to prepare people to work on their own.</p>
        <p>"It's a big achievement, working without a job coach, getting to and from work alone," he said. "But some of our people have already taken that big step, and I feel that many of them in the Con Edison program will soon be ready. And I feel good about that."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
