<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/Fifth Avenue in the 50's; As Troubles Ebb, It's Becoming The Avenue Again</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="778763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FIFTH AVENUE (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DE1638F933A05754C0A963958260" item-length="1482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/Fifth Avenue in the 50's; As Troubles Ebb, It's Becoming The Avenue Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OUTSIDE of New York, few people realized there had been a change. Out there, a Fifth Avenue address still conjured up an image of an elegant street where an uninterrupted line of expensive stores like Tiffany blended with tourist-pleasers like St. Patrick's Cathedral.</p>
        <p>But recent reality has been far less pretty. Over the last decade even Fifth Avenue in the 50's, the avenue's "best" -- translation: priciest -- section, has been splotched by electronics and rug stores. High-fashion windows were eclipsed by seemingly permanent "going out of business" signs, and the ubiquitous street peddlers were turning the avenue into an obstacle course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OUTSIDE of New York, few people realized there had been a change. Out there, a Fifth Avenue address still conjured up an image of an elegant street where an uninterrupted line of expensive stores like Tiffany blended with tourist-pleasers like St. Patrick's Cathedral.</p>
        <p>But recent reality has been far less pretty. Over the last decade even Fifth Avenue in the 50's, the avenue's "best" -- translation: priciest -- section, has been splotched by electronics and rug stores. High-fashion windows were eclipsed by seemingly permanent "going out of business" signs, and the ubiquitous street peddlers were turning the avenue into an obstacle course.</p>
        <p>"It was like a flea market," said Tom Cusick, president of the Fifth Avenue Association. "Many good retailers took one look and said, 'I don't really want to be here.' "</p>
        <p>Now, Fifth Avenue is again living up to its posh reputation. The shoe store A. Testoni and St. John's Knits, both upscale retailers, have moved to Fifth Avenue and 53d Street, replacing electronics stores. Liz Claiborne is building a big store on the southwest corner of 52d Street, where persistently vacant space coexisted with an electronics store and a low-end men's clothing store. The Ferragamo family, which owns the building next door, has evicted an electronics store and a rug store, and is said to be negotiating with a high-fashion retailer.</p>
        <p>In other spaces, retail excitement is replacing respectable dullness. Banana Republic is at 53d Street, in Japan Airlines' former space. Gianni Versace is building a huge emporium, complete with roof garden, where Olympic Airlines once sat. And the Warner Brothers Studio Store is in a long-vacant bank branch at 57th Street.</p>
        <p>Some retailers are even choosing Fifth over Madison, reversing a flight of quality that reached a fever pitch when Barney's opened at 61st and Madison in 1993. One reason is the many tourists-cum-impulse-buyers that Fifth Avenue attracts.</p>
        <p>"On Madison people shop specific stores, but on Fifth they shop the street," said H. Gene Silverberg, chief executive of Bigsby &amp; Kruthers, which recently opened the Knot Shop, a tie store, across from St. Patrick's.</p>
        <p>"Tourists definitely go to Fifth Avenue; everything else is optional," agreed Efraim Grinberg, president of North American Watch, which opened a Movado store at 52d Street last year.</p>
        <p>That idea keeps getting converts. Faconnable, the men's clothing store, had always believed that their customer base was between 57th and 72d on Madison, said Alan Victor, an executive vice president of the Lansco brokerage who persuaded Faconnable to move to 54th and Fifth instead. Do they have regrets? "They're already talking about expanding," Mr. Victor said.</p>
        <p>Fifth Avenue landlords, of course, could not be more delighted. Sumitomo Realty, which owns 666 Fifth Avenue, at 53d Street, is looking to replace the B. Dalton bookstore, which wants to move, and to fill space once occupied by Pastrami &amp; Things.</p>
        <p>"We will certainly get more for the space than we would have gotten if the area hadn't redeveloped," said Arthur L. Bocchi, a Sumitomo vice president.</p>
        <p>Even landlords who say they were unaffected by the avenue's deterioration concede that new tenants have fewer qualms about moving in. "When you buy a house, you care about the neighborhood," said Kate D. Coburn, Rockefeller Center Management's vice president of retail leasing.</p>
        <p>Fifth Avenue's landlords are trying to make sure the neighborhood stays classy. According to Mr. Victor, Olympic Tower Associates has turned down several mass-market retailers for space it has available at 51st Street. "They want a tenant in keeping with H. Stern, Mark Cross and Versace, the others on that block," he said.</p>
        <p>The owners of the Crown Building at 57th have refused to renew the lease of a low-end jeweler, while the owners of the Scribner Building at 49th, where Brentano's is about to vacate 12,000 square feet, are taking their time negotiating deals.</p>
        <p>"We are marketing the Crown space to tenants who attract the same type of shopper as Tiffany or Bulgari nearby," said Kenneth M. Krasnow, an associate director at Cushman &amp; Wakefield who handles leasing at both buildings. "We'll go for a more popular-priced store at Scribner, but we still want a quality tenant."</p>
        <p>(Since the Brentano's interior is landmarked, Mr. Krasnow is marketing it primarily to European retailers, since they are more used to making their own retail images conform to unchangeable contours.)</p>
        <p>Such pickiness is terribly exciting to members of the Fifth Avenue Association, which has spent much of the last five years getting the avenue back in shape.</p>
        <p>"It's hard, walking down Fifth today, to relate to what was going on in 1990," Mr. Cusick recalled. "Liquidation signs were all over, and peddling was out of control."</p>
        <p>Moreover, many of the tackier stores had ironclad leases that economically pressed landlords felt forced to sign. "When the landlords were renting to the schlock stores, national chains weren't in the market," said Benjamin Fox, a partner at the New Spectrum store brokerage.</p>
        <p>Getting rid of it all was no easy task. Although Fifth Avenue zoning has strict signage rules, it took several lawsuits to get all the offensive signs taken down. And it took enforcement of penalties for consumer affairs violations to purge the street of "ripoff stores," as Mr. Cusick calls the stores that sold overpriced goods to tourists.</p>
        <p>PEDDLERS were even harder to oust. In 1990, a city court ruled that disabled veterans had a right to peddle anywhere in New York, and thousands of people applied for licenses. Many of them sold counterfeit versions of the goods being sold in the high-priced stores they parked in front of.</p>
        <p>They were followed by book and magazine vendors who, although rarely disabled veterans, remained relatively unhassled by the courts or the police. After all, nobody wanted to be accused of being harder on sellers of constitutionally protected speech than they were on sellers of T-shirts.</p>
        <p>The last group to arrive were the peddlers of watches and scarves. Most of them were unlicensed, and thus fair game for the law. But they usually displayed their wares in briefcases that could be shut in a second. Often they would pay lookouts to alert them if the police were anywhere near. By the time the officer arrived, the peddler was simply a person carrying a leather case.</p>
        <p>Most of the peddlers are gone now. A new state law requires veterans to abide by the same standards as other vendors, which means Fifth Avenue's zoning rules can again prohibit street sales. Other legal changes make it possible to use witness testimony to prosecute unlicensed vendors who have folded up their briefcases by the time a police officer arrives.</p>
        <p>"We had 1,818 encounters with vendors in the month of August 1993," Mr. Cusick said. "Eighteen months later we had one a day."</p>
        <p>But not all is roses on Fifth Avenue. When Warner Brothers moved to 57th Street, a great hue and cry arose from people who felt that mass-market entertainment had no place on New York's most elegant shopping street. Their cries accomplished little: Niketown, another entertainment emporium, is opening across the street, in the Trump Tower space vacated by Galeries Lafayette. And Goldfeil and Bally of Switzerland, sellers of, respectively, ultraexpensive jewelry and accessories, are giving way at 55th Street to The Disney Store, seller of, well, Mickey Mouse paraphernalia.</p>
        <p>Some brokers say such stores are better suited to Fifth Avenue's pedestrian mix. "Fifth Avenue gets the office workers and the Japanese tourists, but Madison has the wealthy East Side residents and European tourists that the quality retailers go after," said Richard Seligman, a senior managing director at Edward S. Gordon.</p>
        <p>Others say the mass merchandisers represent a net gain for an avenue that can now be all things to all shoppers. "Fifth Avenue has become an all-around consumer friendly place," said Rob Nager, director of retail leasing at Colliers ABR, who handles leasing at 650 Fifth Avenue, at 52d Street.</p>
        <p>The new populism has also helped revive Fifth Avenue south of Saks, where annual retail rents average $200 a square foot, compared with $400 north of 50th Street. And mass merchandisers, who normally rent huge spaces, do far better than that.</p>
        <p>"It's less expensive to rent below that imaginary border, yet that's where a lot of the big spaces are," said Mr. Krasnow, who believes that the quality retailing zone of Fifth Avenue now extends to 42d Street.</p>
        <p>Faith Consolo, managing director of the Garrick-Aug store brokerage, says that the lower stretch is particularly appealing to international retailers, because it offers the cachet of the Fifth Avenue address without the burden of the rents. "When they say 'Fifth Avenue,' no one asks '34th, 47th or whatever,' " Ms. Consolo said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
