<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Delegates Leaning to Right Of G.O.P. and the Nation</title>
    <meta content="29SEEL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/29/politics/campaign/29SEEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1607567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK 2004 -- NEW YORK: THE CONVENTIONEERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservatism (US Politics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times/cbs News Poll</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Connelly, Marjorie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Republican National Convention</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFDA1E3EF93AA1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Delegates Leaning to Right Of G.O.P. and the Nation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Delegates Leaning to Right of G.O.P. and the Nation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE and MARJORIE CONNELLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Connelly, Marjorie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican Party will show somewhat moderate face during convention, but delegates who gather in New York and are shaping party platform hold more conservative views than do most Republican voters or voters at large according to New York Times/CBS News Poll; variety of issues discussed; graph shows demographics of delegates and how they compare on issues (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Republican Party intends to show a somewhat moderate face to the nation during the convention this week in Madison Square Garden. But the delegates who will gather here and are shaping the party platform hold more conservative views than do most Republican voters, and substantially more conservative ones than those of voters at large, according to a New York Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>The delegates are nearly unanimous in their support for the war in Iraq. A full 96 percent said the United States did the right thing going into Iraq, compared with only 78 percent of all voters who call themselves Republicans and 46 percent of all voters. The figures on voters came from a separate, nationwide Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The delegates who shaping the party platform hold more conservative views than do most Republican voters, and substantially more conservative ones than those of voters at large.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Republican Party intends to show a somewhat moderate face to the nation during the convention this week in Madison Square Garden. But the delegates who will gather here and are shaping the party platform hold more conservative views than do most Republican voters, and substantially more conservative ones than those of voters at large, according to a New York Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>The delegates are nearly unanimous in their support for the war in Iraq. A full 96 percent said the United States did the right thing going into Iraq, compared with only 78 percent of all voters who call themselves Republicans and 46 percent of all voters. The figures on voters came from a separate, nationwide Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>And 86 percent of the delegates said the results so far in Iraq were worth the loss of American lives, compared with 70 percent of Republican voters and 36 percent of all voters.</p>
        <p>The poll of 1,200 of the 2,509 delegates was conducted from Aug. 3 to Aug. 23 by telephone, fax and e-mail. It has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus two percentage points. The nationwide poll of 823 voters was conducted by telephone from July 11 to July 15, and has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus three percentage points.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of the delegates described themselves as conservative, while one-third said they were moderate. Almost none of them perceive President Bush as a liberal, although 8 percent of Republican voters do.</p>
        <p>On social issues, the delegates tend to reflect their party. For example, 38 percent of both delegates and Republican voters say abortion should be outlawed altogether. Similarly, they reflect the party's division over embryonic stem cell research.</p>
        <p>But they are more conservative than the party as a whole when it comes to gay marriage. Just 3 percent of delegates say gay couples should be allowed to marry, while 11 percent of Republican voters would allow it. Almost half the delegates, about the same amount of Republican voters, said there should be no legal recognition of gay marriage, although 41 percent of delegates and 36 percent of all Republicans said gay couples should be allowed to form civil unions.</p>
        <p>Delegates generally take a more unilateral stance on foreign policy, believe in a more limited role for government and believe more in free trade than their fellow Republicans or voters at large. And they are happier with the current level of legal immigration than other Republicans.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of the delegates said the United States should be able to attack any country it thinks might attack the United States, while only half of Republican voters and a third of all voters agreed.</p>
        <p>And of the three groups, delegates have the least regard for the United Nations. Only 7 percent said it was extremely important for the United States to work through the United Nations to solve international problems, while a third of all Republicans and half of all voters agree.</p>
        <p>Just 3 percent of the delegates said that the United States should have stayed out of Iraq, while 19 percent of Republican voters and half of all voters agreed with that statement.</p>
        <p>The delegates are more in sync with their party on the question of whether the United States should try to change a dictatorship to a democracy where it can. About 40 percent of the delegates and Republican voters agree with that idea, while only 15 percent of Democratic voters do.</p>
        <p>The delegates named the economy as the most important issue in their states, but they also rated terrorism and defense as the next most important issues.</p>
        <p>In a follow-up interview, Norman Riffel, 65, a delegate from Springfield, Neb., who owns a moving and storage company, said: ''President Bush has to lay out a plan for addressing terrorism, creating more jobs and building stronger relationships with other nations. These are all high priorities.''</p>
        <p>In something of a rebuff to Republican officials who picked New York for the convention as an evocation of what they perceive as President Bush's finest hour, nearly one in five delegates said they should have picked someplace else.</p>
        <p>Thirty-one percent said they were somewhat or very worried about a terrorist attack in New York, slightly more than the 27 percent of Democratic delegates who were worried about an attack in Boston. But New Yorkers are even more concerned than the delegates, with 53 percent of them worried about a terrorist attack this week.</p>
        <p>While 94 percent of the Republican delegates said they had a good impression of New York, they expressed little interest in venturing out into the city. Asked if there was any particular place or thing that they wanted to be sure to see while here, the biggest percentage (29) said ''nothing.'' The next-highest percentage (21) named the Statue of Liberty, and the third-highest (16) said ground zero.</p>
        <p>They hold Rudolph W. Giuliani, who was mayor during the terrorist attacks, in high regard, even though he is more socially liberal than many of them. Ninety-one percent said they had a favorable view of Mr. Giuliani, which is nearly as many as the 94 percent with a favorable view of Vice President Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>They take a dimmer view of Senator John McCain, the maverick Arizona Republican, who was rated favorably by 62 percent (but who often tops other polls as one of the most popular politicians in America).</p>
        <p>In interviews, the delegates applauded President Bush, citing his character rather than specific policies. ''His conviction is his greatest strength,'' said Paul Willis, 50, a delegate from Pahrump, Nev., and a retired carpenter.</p>
        <p>But like others, Marti Halverson, a homemaker from Etna, Wyo., expressed concern that the president did not always put his best foot forward. ''His greatest weakness is inability to communicate,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She also said he had a job to do at the convention.</p>
        <p>''He has to convince the American public that in this case, in the case of Iraq, might is right,'' she said. ''Because so many good Republicans are doubting the plan.''</p>
        <p>People who become delegates to their party's conventions tend to be political activists, many of them driven into politics because of firm views on an issue or philosophy. Delegates to both the Republican and Democratic conventions in recent years have tended to be farther to the right or the left than voters in their own party and certainly farther from the center than the public at large.</p>
        <p>The Republican delegates are adamantly in favor of free trade, even at the cost of jobs at home, and strongly against regulation of business and the environment. This is substantially at odds with Republican voters as a whole.</p>
        <p>And more than their fellow Republicans, the delegates said they preferred cutting taxes to reducing the deficit, were less concerned that antiterrorism measures were restricting civil liberties, and believed that presidential candidates should discuss the role of religion in their private lives as part of their campaigns.</p>
        <p>The Republican delegates are less diverse by race, gender and income than the delegates at the Democratic convention were, but they are more diverse than the delegates at previous Republican conventions.</p>
        <p>For example, 85 percent of the delegates at this convention are white, compared with 89 percent in 2000 and 91 percent in 1996. Six percent are black, compared with 2 percent in 2000. (In Boston, 68 percent were white and 18 percent black.) Seven percent of Republican delegates are Hispanic, compared with 3 percent in 1996 (and 12 percent of Democratic delegates this year).</p>
        <p>Twenty-seven percent of the delegates said they were millionaires, compared with 14 percent of the delegates at the Democratic convention last month in Boston.</p>
        <p>A quarter of them are members of the National Rifle Association, while only 9 percent of the voters are, and 45 percent own a gun, while 30 percent of all voters do.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK 2004 -- NEW YORK: THE CONVENTIONEERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
