<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Xanadu Moves Ahead, but With Asterisks</title>
    <meta content="29NJXAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1607433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DEVELOPMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Meadowlands (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Meadowlands Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mills Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mack-Cali Realty Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kanam Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Meadowlands Xanadu</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DA103EF93AA1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Xanadu Moves Ahead, but With Asterisks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>Lyndhurst</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Meadowlands Commission, in 5 to 0 vote, paves way for Mills Corp, Mack-Cali Realty Corp and KanAm Group, under several caveats, to develop $1.3 billion Meadowlands Xanadu family entertainment and sports complex; approval includes 14 recommendations for changes and modifications; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE New Jersey Meadowlands Commission gave its blessing last week to the planned development of the $1.3 billion Meadowlands Xanadu family entertainment and sports complex. But it leavened that approval with more than a dozen recommendations for changes, including many that echoed the long-voiced criticisms of the plan's opponents.</p>
        <p>The 5-0 vote (with one abstention) paved the way for the scheduled groundbreaking ceremony on Sept. 29 for the 104-acre project that is to be built by a partnership of the Mills Corporation, a mall developer; Mack-Cali Realty Corporation; and the KanAm Group, a Munich investment group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE New Jersey Meadowlands Commission gave its blessing last week to the planned development of the $1.3 billion Meadowlands Xanadu family entertainment and sports complex. But it leavened that approval with more than a dozen recommendations for changes, including many that echoed the long-voiced criticisms of the plan's opponents.</p>
        <p>The 5-0 vote (with one abstention) paved the way for the scheduled groundbreaking ceremony on Sept. 29 for the 104-acre project that is to be built by a partnership of the Mills Corporation, a mall developer; Mack-Cali Realty Corporation; and the KanAm Group, a Munich investment group.</p>
        <p>From the start, the project -- five million square feet of activities and shopping that will include an indoor ski slope, a surfing pool and mini-Formula One racetrack -- has had the strong backing of the McGreevey administration.</p>
        <p>The governor at one time saw it as a gift to the long-neglected blue-collar communities in southern Bergen County, and as a way to make Democratic inroads in a once reliably Republican county.</p>
        <p>But perhaps most significant about the commission's vote was that it signaled the start of the tough effort to come in making final the details of the lease between the developers and the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority, which owns the land for the project. Permits to allow building must also come from the state's Department of Environmental Protection, Department of Transportation and the United States Army Corps of Engineers.</p>
        <p>It was to these more detailed discussions that the Meadowlands Commission directed its 14 recommendations for changes and modifications. They range from how to define the project's retail component and its actual impact on traffic, to the recommendation that developers be required to build costly air-monitoring stations on the site and a sewage-treatment plant and finance a shuttle-bus service that would serve the site until a proposed heavy-rail spur was built.</p>
        <p>Susan Bass Levin, chairman of the commission and commissioner of the state's Division of Community Affairs, conceded that the recommendations of the agency's hearing officers were full of misgivings and caveats.</p>
        <p>But she said that by approving the proposal with the recommendations, the commission was seizing the opportunity to set out what it expects from the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority, the D.E.P. and the D.O.T. in their ongoing dealings with the developers.</p>
        <p>In return, the commission was keeping alive a project that would bring jobs, economic development and tax revenue to the region. In addition it would allow the immediate payment of $160 million to the state by the developers who would also turn over to the commission some 587 acres of untouched wetlands they own adjacent to the site; that land would be held by a conservation trust.</p>
        <p>This is an essential element of the plan, Ms. Bass Levin said. She added that the commission was charged with making sure that the project complements the public's need for jobs, economic development and smart-growth policies that protect the environment.</p>
        <p>Despite the recommendations and caveats made by the commission, many critics of the development were unimpressed.</p>
        <p>Edward Lloyd, a lawyer who represents a number of environmental and mass transit advocate groups, said that enforceability of the recommendations was crucial. He accused the developers of creating the questions that were unanswered by ''stonewalling'' public agencies in the nearly two years since they were chosen to develop the tract. ''They should not be rewarded for their arrogance,'' he said, calling on the commission to delay acting on the project.</p>
        <p>Allen Magrini, a vice president and general counsel for Hartz Mountain Industries, one of the unsuccessful bidders to develop the site, said that all the unanswered questions about the project grew out of a process that was not as rigorous as it should have been. And the recommendations from the commission's hearing officers were ''too soft and unenforceable'' to affect the process.</p>
        <p>Jeff Tittel, director of the Sierra Club's New Jersey chapter, referring to the commission's meeting last Thursday, said: ''This is public relations and not public policy. We need to reopen the entire environment impact statement to get the answers we need on air quality and traffic and water. There are a lot of changes going on in New Jersey now, but gridlock is forever.''</p>
        <p>Bob Sommer, a spokesman for the developers, disputed any suggestion that the approval process was anything but open and thorough.</p>
        <p>DEVELOPMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
