<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rove Banks on Victory and Debunks Myths</title>
    <meta content="29ROVE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/29/politics/campaign/29rove.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1607644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN 2004: THE ADVISER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rove, Karl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rove, Karl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DC1F3EF93AA1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rove Banks on Victory and Debunks Myths</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rove Banks on a Victory and Debunks the Myths</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karl Rove denies myth that he is brains of Pres Bush administration; says he is credited with and blamed for all sorts of things he has nothing to do with; says he is confident of Bush victory in presidential election; contends that he has nothing to do with raising questions about Sen John Kerry's Vietnam medals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Karl Rove says that Washington is a city of myths -- and that the No.1 myth these days is Mr. Rove.</p>
        <p>No, Mr. Rove declared in an interview late on Friday, he is not the brains behind an intellectually challenged president, or the most powerful political consigliere the White House has seen in 50 years, or the shrewdly diabolical power behind the scenes engineering elections, destroying opponents and bringing new meaning to the term hardball politics. ''There needs to be a myth by which this town operates, and if you want to believe that, like, the president isn't that smart, you need to find an explanation, like I'm Bush's brain,'' said Mr. Rove, President Bush's chief political adviser. ''If you want to find an easy explanation for why a liberal senator from Georgia is defeated, you get to blame me. Everyone can blame me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Karl Rove declared in an interview that he is not the brains behind an intellectually challenged president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Karl Rove says that Washington is a city of myths -- and that the No.1 myth these days is Mr. Rove.</p>
        <p>No, Mr. Rove declared in an interview late on Friday, he is not the brains behind an intellectually challenged president, or the most powerful political consigliere the White House has seen in 50 years, or the shrewdly diabolical power behind the scenes engineering elections, destroying opponents and bringing new meaning to the term hardball politics. ''There needs to be a myth by which this town operates, and if you want to believe that, like, the president isn't that smart, you need to find an explanation, like I'm Bush's brain,'' said Mr. Rove, President Bush's chief political adviser. ''If you want to find an easy explanation for why a liberal senator from Georgia is defeated, you get to blame me. Everyone can blame me.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''It's just weird, the stuff I get credit for or blamed for that I just have nothing to do with. The things that people suggest I am saying or advocating, it's just absurd.'' Asked what he was referring to, Mr. Rove responded: ''I'm not going get into it. I read about myself in the newspaper and I say they must be talking about someone else.''</p>
        <p>''This town runs on myths, and that is one of the biggest myths it runs on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove spoke in a telephone interview before a Republican convention in which his friend of 30 years is to be nominated for a second term as president. In speaking of himself, Mr. Rove was somewhat reflective, and alternatively self-deprecatory and combative.</p>
        <p>But, not surprisingly, he was boosterish in talking about Mr. Bush, his hopes for the convention as well as of the state of the campaign against Mr. Kerry.</p>
        <p>''We have seen some steady movement since their convention,'' he said of the Democrats. ''We're going in slightly ahead. I'm confident that we are doing the right things to bring about victory.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove said that he had not decided whether he would remain in the White House if Mr. Bush won re-election. He said that he liked living in Washington, somewhat, but that he missed Texas.</p>
        <p>''The mind-set here is so much zero-sum,'' he said. ''Look, Texas politics is hardball. It's a blood sport. But at the end of the day, after everyone gets elected to office, they try to find a way to get the job done and work with comity with their colleagues.</p>
        <p>''Up here, the focus is much more short-term,'' Mr. Rove continued. ''It's, 'How can I get on the evening news?' The mind-set is toward saying things that are outlandish and will grab attention. And I recognize that people in both parties do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove brought up the subject of the unproven accusations about Mr. Kerry's war medals from a group of Vietnam veterans with ties to the Bush campaign. Democrats have described the attacks as an example of the kind of shadowy tactics that have been associated with Rove campaigns over the years. But Mr. Rove said he had nothing to do with them and he disputed the significance of his association with one of the group's main backers, Bob J. Perry.</p>
        <p>''A guy that I've known for 25 years. Look, when I moved to Texas, there were not a lot of Republican donors,'' Mr. Rove said. ''The fact that I was active in politics for 25 years, it would be shocking if I didn't know Bob Perry.''</p>
        <p>Asked what he thought of the advertisements, Mr. Rove responded, ''You're not going to get me commenting on those.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove did say that he thought Mr. Kerry had blown a chance at his convention and that Mr. Bush would not do the same. ''I think he missed an opportunity at his convention to inform people what his agenda is,'' he said. ''So far it's all, 'I'm not President Bush.'''</p>
        <p>Asked what he thought Mr. Kerry should do now, he said: ''I'm not going to serve as an unpaid adviser to the Kerry campaign. Each convention is an opportunity when there is a lot of attention paid to you, and the spotlight is on you. Their moment has now passed. Now it's going to be ours.''</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN 2004: THE ADVISER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
