<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Man's Struggle to Deal With the Challenge of Size, a Group Is His Shield</title>
    <meta content="24NEED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1072149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEEDIEST CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UJA-Federation of New York</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federation Employment and Guidance Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gershenson, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D8113CF937A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Man's Struggle to Deal With the Challenge of Size, a Group Is His Shield</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM GERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gershenson, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Man who has cerebral gigantism and is very large because of excess of growth hormone produced by his pituitary gland receives employment training, counseling and educational support at Federation Employment and Guidance Service, a beneficiary of UJA Federation of New York, one of charities supported by New York Times Neediest Cases Fund; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When his workday ends, Michael Gunther lets all of his co-workers leave the building first, before he takes another elevator, alone, down to the street.</p>
        <p>When he used to try to get in with them, he recalls, they often shouted: ''The elevator's too crowded! The elevator's too crowded!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When his workday ends, Michael Gunther lets all of his co-workers leave the building first, before he takes another elevator, alone, down to the street.</p>
        <p>When he used to try to get in with them, he recalls, they often shouted: ''The elevator's too crowded! The elevator's too crowded!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunther, 43, has cerebral gigantism, and the excess of growth hormone produced by his pituitary gland has made him extremely large. He says he wears size XXXXXXXL shirts, and his pants have a 66-inch waist. He is 6 feet 4 inches tall; he does not know for sure how much he weighs, because his scale does not measure past 300 pounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunther assembles hangers and stuffs coupons into shopping bags at a sheltered workshop run by  Federation Employment and Guidance Service, now known as FEGS. That group, which provides employment training, counseling and educational support services for those who have difficulty finding jobs, is a beneficiary of the UJA-Federation of New York, one of seven local charities supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Although his co-workers occasionally tease Mr. Gunther about his size, they are gentler than people outside the program. ''Besides, I have counselors and people here to take care of me, like a shield,'' Mr. Gunther said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunther, a native of Queens, has been at the workshop ever since he graduated from high school in 1976. He is paid at piecework rate and earns about $2,000 a year.</p>
        <p>His brother helps support him, and Mr. Gunther receives Social Security payments, but now he is in desperate need of money. The home in Queens Village where he lived with his mother, until she died in 1996, is now falling apart.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunther is gentle, but his impact is immense. The floorboards groan when he walks. His mattress is permanently dented on one side. The tiles on the bathroom floor have begun to chip and flake away.</p>
        <p>Not all of the problems around the house are due to Mr. Gunther's condition. His mother was sick for nearly 10 years before she died, and in those years she was unable to properly maintain their home.</p>
        <p>The paint has peeled from the front of the place and there are holes in the roof. ''When the deluge comes, I've got every pot in the place ready,'' Mr. Gunther said.</p>
        <p>Caseworkers at his workshop have tried for two years to find housing for Mr. Gunther, but it has been a frustrating search.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gunther said that as a result of a birth defect, he did not receive enough oxygen at birth, and he did not walk or talk until he was 5. Mr. Gunther suffers from generalized anxiety disorder, a condition that makes him nervous in new situations and often leaves him agitated.</p>
        <p>But, his case worker said, Mr. Gunther does not fit any of the standard categories used to assign housing for disabled people.</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, Mr. Gunther needs special accommodations because of his condition. He needs reinforced floors, widened doorways and a raised toilet. When he used the bathroom at one of the apartments he looked at, the toilet came off its moorings.</p>
        <p>While the search for a new home for Mr. Gunther continues, the workshop has provided a number of services to make his life more bearable. He receives counseling that has helped him accept his condition and deal with the teasing he gets.</p>
        <p>He used to holler at people who insulted him, but now he takes a deep breath and tries to go on with his work, he said. If he gets too upset, his counselors are there to calm him down. ''He is truly gentle, but he's loud, and he used to be on the verge of tears all the time,'' said Esty Frankel, Mr. Gunther's rehabilitation counselor.</p>
        <p>The workshop has also arranged for Mr. Gunther to join a support group in the hope of finding him friends, because he spends almost every weekend alone. He has gone with the group to see the tree at Rockefeller Center, and also recently went bowling. Although the alley could not find any 16W shoes to fit Mr. Gunther, he enjoyed himself and was proud of his efforts. ''Over 100,'' he said. ''That's not bad for a man of my size.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these  organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station, P.O. Box 4100, New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded $2,559,884.46  Recorded yesterday $97,900.82</p>
        <p>Total $2,657,785.28</p>
        <p>THE NEEDIEST CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
