<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smugglers' Helpers</title>
    <meta content="24THU33" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1072146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rjr Nabisco Inc</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D8113CF937A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smugglers' Helpers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial deplores connivance of an RJR Nabisco subsidiary at the smuggling of cigarettes into Canada (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How earnest and public-minded it sounded when tobacco company executives warned early this year that the attempt to jack up cigarette prices through the pending national tobacco bill would inevitably lead to smuggling and a black market. No less than Steven Goldstone, the chairman and chief executive of RJR Nabisco, warned that it was virtually impossible to stop a determined batch of smugglers, given that 14 million cigarettes can fit into a single truck. Mr. Goldstone called it ''irresponsible'' to ignore the smuggling that neighboring countries had experienced when they raised cigarette taxes.</p>
        <p>Well, now it turns out that Mr. Goldstone was assuredly right about the dangers of smuggling. The only problem was, he pointed his finger in the wrong direction. This week a marketing subsidiary of his own company pleaded guilty to criminal charges and paid $15 million for actions that enabled others to smuggle cigarettes into Canada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How earnest and public-minded it sounded when tobacco company executives warned early this year that the attempt to jack up cigarette prices through the pending national tobacco bill would inevitably lead to smuggling and a black market. No less than Steven Goldstone, the chairman and chief executive of RJR Nabisco, warned that it was virtually impossible to stop a determined batch of smugglers, given that 14 million cigarettes can fit into a single truck. Mr. Goldstone called it ''irresponsible'' to ignore the smuggling that neighboring countries had experienced when they raised cigarette taxes.</p>
        <p>Well, now it turns out that Mr. Goldstone was assuredly right about the dangers of smuggling. The only problem was, he pointed his finger in the wrong direction. This week a marketing subsidiary of his own company pleaded guilty to criminal charges and paid $15 million for actions that enabled others to smuggle cigarettes into Canada.</p>
        <p>The scheme was hatched after the Canadian Government raised tobacco taxes in an effort to cut smoking. Those taxes applied only to cigarettes sold in the Canadian market, not to exports. So cigarettes were shipped from a Reynolds plant in Canada to the United States, avoiding the Canadian levies. The guilty Reynolds subsidiary aided the filing of false statements by distributors that the cigarettes were to be shipped on to Russia and Estonia, a maneuver that exempted them from American taxes as well. In reality, the cigarettes were diverted into New York and ultimately back to Canada.</p>
        <p>The subsidiary has admitted only to customs violations, not smuggling. But in truth, says United States Attorney Thomas J. Maroney, the subsidiary knew that the cigarettes were destined to be smuggled back into Canada, in this case through an Indian reservation in upstate New York.</p>
        <p>RJR Nabisco says it ''very much regrets'' the episode and calls its subsidiary's actions ''inconsistent with the way Reynolds does business.'' It has closed the subsidiary and is taking steps to prevent a recurrence. But the apologies seem a bit late. The tobacco industry has long been accused of looking the other way when it comes to smuggling. Now we know it is even worse. The shame of this episode is that a subsidiary of America's second-largest tobacco company actually helped the criminals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
