<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canadian Family's Feud</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19941106T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="721752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCCAIN FOODS LTD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCAIN, HARRISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCAIN, WALLACE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DD103FF933A05753C1A962958260" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canadian Family's Feud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEIR public feud has been conducted with all the decorum of an adolescent food fight, but the scuffling siblings are a couple of sexagenarians who together founded one of Canada's most successful businesses.</p>
        <p>The brothers McCain -- Harrison, 66, and Wallace, 64 -- have quarreled for three years now over who will succeed them at the helm of McCain Foods Ltd., a $2.3 billion-a-year enterprise. Courts have tried to settle the dispute and failed. And their wrangling has occasionally disrupted the business, including embarrassing the big Canadian food processor in dealings with one of its biggest customers, McDonald's, the fast-food giant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEIR public feud has been conducted with all the decorum of an adolescent food fight, but the scuffling siblings are a couple of sexagenarians who together founded one of Canada's most successful businesses.</p>
        <p>The brothers McCain -- Harrison, 66, and Wallace, 64 -- have quarreled for three years now over who will succeed them at the helm of McCain Foods Ltd., a $2.3 billion-a-year enterprise. Courts have tried to settle the dispute and failed. And their wrangling has occasionally disrupted the business, including embarrassing the big Canadian food processor in dealings with one of its biggest customers, McDonald's, the fast-food giant.</p>
        <p>The McCain feud is Canada's answer to the recent dynastic spats in American business, like the fight within the Haft family, which owns Dart Drugs and Crown Books.</p>
        <p>Lately the Canadian corporate soap opera has been heating up. Earlier this month, Harrison McCain succeeded in getting Wallace pushed out of his post as co-chief executive -- a title and a joint command that the brothers had shared.</p>
        <p>Harrison was able to persuade a majority of the family shareholders to support the move against his younger brother. Harrison and Wallace each own one-third of the stock, and the families of two deceased brothers own the other third. Wallace was given a new position of vice chairman.</p>
        <p>WALLACE denounced his demotion as "vindictive," and he is proceeding with a court action that could lead to the family company being dismantled or sold. But a buyout of Wallace is also an option.</p>
        <p>His brother, Harrison, is now the sole chief executive. But he has agreed to step down once a successor is found.</p>
        <p>The brothers feuded over who within the family should become top dog. Wallace wanted his son Michael, 35, the head of McCain's operations in the United States. Harrison backed his nephew, Allison, 46, who heads the company's British business.</p>
        <p>Now it's likely to be neither. The board has a short-list of about six candidates, all outside professional managers. Harrison insists that the name of the successor will be announced "within weeks." But in a move sure to rile his brother, Harrison last week appointed his son Peter as the president of a new subsidiary, McCain Foods International Inc.</p>
        <p>The long-running sibling conflict has shaken McCain Foods, a food processor founded 40 years ago by Harrison and Wallace McCain in a former cow pasture in Florenceville, New Brunswick. Today, the company employs 12,500 workers on three continents to process foods like frozen french fries, pizzas and juices.</p>
        <p>Harrison McCain admitted last spring that the family feud may be "harming" the company "both with its customers and suppliers. The harm will become worse if nothing is done about the problem immediately."</p>
        <p>The incident involving McDonald's occurred two years ago. But it became public only this year, after the contents of a confidential report by a New Brunswick judge, Ronald Stevenson, who had tried unsuccessfully to mediate the dispute, were reported by The Financial Post.</p>
        <p>HARRISON McCAIN was not pleased with the performance of Michael McCain, Wallace's son, in the big United States market. In America, McCain Foods ranks fifth in highly competitive frozen potato market, and it is barely profitable.</p>
        <p>Lynal Root, senior vice president of purchasing of McDonald's International in Chicago, had drawn up a document discussing the fast-food chain's french-fry purchasing program and sent it off to Michael McCain, the head of American operations.</p>
        <p>But the Stevenson report shows that Harrison did an end-run around his nephew by drawing up a McCain's plan for supplying all McDonald's restaurants worldwide and dispatching it to Mr. Root.</p>
        <p>When he found out, Wallace furiously fired off a memo telling Harrison to keep his hands out of North American operations.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Root said the McCain family feud was "unfortunate." But, the McDonald's executive insisted, the family dispute "is not affecting us any place in the world."</p>
        <p>"I'm the one who started doing business with them many years ago," Mr. Root added. "They're our biggest supplier throughout the world, not in pounds, but in the number of countries they serve. They've done a whale of a job."</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 6, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about the feud between Harrison and Wallace McCain over the future management of McCain Foods Ltd., a large Canadian company they founded, referred incorrectly to some holdings of another family, the Hafts, who are involved in a similar dispute. The Hafts are not the outright owners of Dart Drugs and the Crown Books Corporation. Dart Drugs was sold to its employees in 1984. Crown Books is 51 percent owned by the Dart Group Corporation of Landover, Md., of which the Hafts are the major stockholders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 6, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article last Sunday about the feud between Harrison and Wallace McCain over the future management of McCain Foods Ltd., a large Canadian company they founded, referred incorrectly to some holdings of another family, the Hafts, who are involved in a similar dispute. The Hafts are not the outright owners of Dart Drugs and the Crown Books Corporation. Dart Drugs was sold to its employees in 1984. Crown Books is 51 percent owned by the Dart Group Corporation of Landover, Md., of which the Hafts are the major stockholders.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
