<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Profit For Chrysler In 4th Quarter</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNET, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DA1730F93AA25752C0A962958260" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Profit For Chrysler In 4th Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNET, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chrysler Corporation reported today that its earnings almost doubled to a record $777 million in the fourth quarter of 1993, beating even the rosiest predictions by Wall Street analysts.</p>
        <p>A recovering North American automobile market and Chrysler's revived line of cars and trucks contributed to a year of record earnings over all for the company, before taxes and charges for accounting changes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chrysler Corporation reported today that its earnings almost doubled to a record $777 million in the fourth quarter of 1993, beating even the rosiest predictions by Wall Street analysts.</p>
        <p>A recovering North American automobile market and Chrysler's revived line of cars and trucks contributed to a year of record earnings over all for the company, before taxes and charges for accounting changes.</p>
        <p>But in part because of a previously announced charge of $4.68 billion to account for the health care of its future retirees, Chrysler lost $2.55 billion, or $7.62 a share, for the year.  Total revenue for the year was $43.6 billion, compared with a record of $36.9 billion set in 1992. Previous Record in 1984</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended Dec. 31, earnings were $2.11 a share, compared with $1.12 a share, on net earnings of $356 million, in the fourth quarter of 1992. The most optimistic forecast, by Zacks Investment Research, had been $1.90 a share. Chrysler's previous record for a fourth quarter, in 1984, was $607 million.</p>
        <p>In heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange, Chrysler shares hit a record of $63.50 early in the day, before closing today at $62.50 a share, up 75 cents. It was the Big Board's second most actively traded issue. In a little more than a year, the stock has nearly doubled, reflecting the growing affirmation on Wall Street of the No. 3 auto maker's turnaround.</p>
        <p>"What this quarter says in no uncertain terms is that this is a superbly managed company," said Philip K. Fricke of Prudential Securities. "The company has been dead-on in product development." Further, he said, Chrysler's introductions of new vehicles, like the Neon subcompact, have occurred without the production glitches that restrained sales of new models in the past.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fricke added that at this point in a cyclical auto recovery heartening earnings surprises tend to be the norm. "Several positive forces start to come together at this point in auto cycles," he said. Increased sales volume spreads fixed costs more thinly, while buyers begin picking more expensive models and options, and, faced with robust demand, companies reduce rebates.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Chrysler reported that in the fourth quarter it further reduced rebates because of the popularity of vehicles like its mid-sized Dodge Intrepid sedan, Jeep Grand Cherokee sport utility wagon, and restyled Dodge Ram pickup. For the quarter, such incentives averaged $650 a vehicle, down 16 percent from $775 in the third quarter, and down 36 percent from $1,020 a year ago, said Gary C. Valade, Chrysler's executive vice president and chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>As a result, pretax profit per vehicle averaged $1,727 in the fourth quarter, and $1,335 for the year, far higher than that at the Ford Motor Company or the General Motors Corporation, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Along with growing profits and sales, Chrysler has gained market share. For the year, the company said it had picked up 1.4 percentage points to hold 14.8 percent of the North American car and truck market, its largest share since 1970, when it had 15.3 percent. G.M. controls about a third of the North American market, and Ford about a quarter.</p>
        <p>While Chrysler's overseas sales are growing -- the company reported today that they had jumped 45 percent for the year, to 105,849 vehicles -- it trails its domestic competitors in exploiting foreign markets. But with the Japanese and European markets slumping, Chrysler's insulation from those markets has proved a boon to the company's bottom line.</p>
        <p>The company reported today that it had further reduced its unfinanced pension liability -- essentially, the amount of money it had not set aside to cover the pensions of future retirees. That liability shrank to $2.2 billion at the end of last year, from $3.9 billion at the end of 1992, Mr. Valade said. The company put $3.5 billion into the fund during the year, but changes in the discount rate and new labor contracts that increased pensions ate up some of that, he said.  COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
