<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN HUNGARY, FLEXIBILITY AS DOCTRINE</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="149514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">HUNGARY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSZ, KAROLY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMM, HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Hungary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D6163BF93AA15756C0A96E948260" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN HUNGARY, FLEXIBILITY AS DOCTRINE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY KAMM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMM, HENRY</byline>
      <dateline>BUDAPEST</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Hungarians have often been quick to take advantage of changes blowing in from the East. They proved that again last weekend when a new generation of Hungarian Communist leaders succeeded in seizing power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Hungarians have often been quick to take advantage of changes blowing in from the East. They proved that again last weekend when a new generation of Hungarian Communist leaders succeeded in seizing power.</p>
        <p>The Hungarians have often been quick to take advantage of changes blowing in from the East. They proved that again last weekend when a new generation of Hungarian Communist leaders succeeded in seizing power.</p>
        <p>When the idea of changing the system was first allowed to be discussed in Eastern Europe in the 1960's, the talk was of replacing highly dogmatic Stalinist leaders with Communists who were ideologically sound but undogmatic - ready to experiment with their economies to increase production. A bit of borrowing of ideas from the West was tolerated.</p>
        <p>In those days, Janos Kadar, Hungary's leader since 1956, became the first of the nondogmatists, the deviser of ''goulash Communism,'' the party chief who allowed his economists some freedom to allow changes based on the capitalist notion that producers and consumers are better able than a central planning bureaucracy to stimulate an economy.</p>
        <p>Hungarian economic efforts had their ups and downs under Mr. Kadar, dictated not so much by Hungary's needs or Mr. Kadar's wishes as by the Soviet Union's increasing or decreasing fear of the political effects of movements for change in its dependencies in Eastern and Central Europe.</p>
        <p>Since Mikhail S. Gorbachev came to power in 1985, Communist leaders, seeking Soviet approval as the best way of rising to the top, have been inspired not only to be nondogmatic but even to let it be known that they are ''pragmatists.'' Last Sunday, the first of the new pragmatists reached the pinnacle. Prime Minister Karoly Grosz replaced Mr. Kadar as General Secretary of the Communist Party. Only 15 years old when Communism came to Hungary with the conquering Soviet Army, the new leader reached maturity with the first generation of Eastern Europeans for whom there has never been an alternative to Communism. Nothing about the 57-year-old Mr. Grosz (whose name is pronounced KA-roy Gross) shows his pragmatism more clearly than his newfound devotion to downgrading ideology.</p>
        <p>Until the ascendancy of Mr. Gorbachev in Moscow, Mr. Grosz had been counted as a leader in the orthodox wing of the party bureaucracy. He had overseen the ideological purity of the press and broadcasting and served as a tough party chief before becoming Prime Minister last June.</p>
        <p>For most Hungarians, the removal of Mr. Kadar, who retains a ceremonial role in the newly created position of party President, appears to be a psychological boost. They see it as the end of an era in which the boom of the 1970's soured in this decade to stagnation, inflation of about 20 percent a year, the painful introduction of capitalist-style income- and value-added taxes, falling real wages and the threat of unemployment. Hungarians have been pained in recent years to see the shrinkage in the purchasing power of their wages and extra earnings in their second and third jobs, as well as in the tolerated but marginal private sector. From proudly calling their country ''the best barracks in the socialist camp,'' they have taken to comparing their economic standard to that of the deprived Poles. The truth, economists here say, lies somewhere in between.  Toughness and Ambition</p>
        <p>The vast majority of Hungarians, who have never been persuaded that Communism is the road to well-being, believed that Mr. Kadar's nondogmatic ideology was not the worst, but not good enough. They would like to believe that the new official talk about pragmatic approaches and the emphasis on decentralization and market mechanisms is sincere.</p>
        <p>They hope that Mr. Grosz, whom they associate more with toughness and ambition than with liberal changes, will continue to see advantage in his new orientation. In this hope, they find encouragement in the arrival of two new Politburo members who are regarded as earnest advocates of change, Rezso Nyers and Imre Pozsgay.</p>
        <p>Since he became Prime Minister, Mr. Grosz has made himself a spokesman for the market system and relations with the West. He has paid official visits to West Germany, where he obtained a one-billion-mark (about $590 million) line of credit, and to Britain, where he won the pragmatic approval of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher. He has received the public assurance that President Reagan is looking forward to his visit to Washington, tentatively set for July. A supporter of Mr. Grosz has called his efforts ''realpolitik.'' Mr. Grosz has invited American businessmen such as Edgar M. Bronfman, Ronald S. Lauder and George Soros to visit Budapest. A belief that good relations with Jewish businessmen are a key to success in the capitalist world did not vanish in Hungary with the victory of Communism over traditional nationalism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadar did not meet the customary East European fate of either holding power until death or being overthrown by a Politburo coup and disappearing into oblivion. His election to a ceremonial post and the public handshake - no matter how sincere - between the new and old leaders, are seen as accomplishments of the era of Gorbachev and pragmatism.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
