<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Rules Report on Police In Chicago Should Be Released</title>
    <meta content="20chicago" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/20/us/20chicago.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1762931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davey, Monica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruethling, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biebel, Paul P Jr (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DC133EF933A15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Rules Report on Police In Chicago Should Be Released</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Rules Report on Police in Chicago Should Be Released</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONICA DAVEY; Gretchen Ruethling contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ruethling, Gretchen; Davey, Monica</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Paul P Biebel Jr rules that special prosecutor's report on accusations of torture by Chicago police officers over two decades should be made public; report is result of investigation spanning four years and costing more than $5 million; inquiry stems from accusations by 192 people that police officers at two city stations tortured them; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A judge here ruled on Friday that a special prosecutor's report on accusations of torture by Chicago police officers over two decades should be made public, as a United Nations panel in Geneva urged American authorities to investigate the claims further.</p>
        <p>The result of an investigation that has taken four years and cost Cook County more than $5 million, the report is likely to be released in several weeks, prosecutors said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHICAGO, May 19  A judge here ruled on Friday that a special prosecutor's report on accusations of torture by Chicago police officers over two decades should be made public, as a United Nations panel in Geneva urged American authorities to investigate the claims further.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A judge here ruled on Friday that a special prosecutor's report on accusations of torture by Chicago police officers over two decades should be made public, as a United Nations panel in Geneva urged American authorities to investigate the claims further.</p>
        <p>The result of an investigation that has taken four years and cost Cook County more than $5 million, the report is likely to be released in several weeks, prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>The investigation stems from accusations by 192 people that police officers at two city stations tortured them -- beating them, shocking them with electric devices and trying to suffocate them -- from the 1970's to the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>''After the third torture session, I understood that these guys weren't going to let me out of there alive if I didn't say what they wanted,'' said David Bates, who was among the people whose cases were investigated by the special prosecutor. Mr. Bates said police beat him and covered his head with a typewriter cover in 1983 until he confessed to a crime he says he did not commit.</p>
        <p>About two dozen people marched outside of the criminal courthouse on Friday morning, calling on Circuit Judge Paul P. Biebel Jr. to make the report public, though lawyers for some of the officers have argued it should be kept from public view.</p>
        <p>Judge Biebel, responding to inquiries from prosecutors as to whether they could make the report public, said the public's right to learn details of the investigation outweighed the privacy rights of individual officers.</p>
        <p>''The release of the report will address the issues which have led to rumor and speculation which have spread unimpeded over the fabric of the Cook County criminal justice system for more than 30 years,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Spokeswomen for the city of Chicago's law department and for the police department said those entities supported release of the report.</p>
        <p>Many of the accusers have pointed to officers who were overseen by Commander Jon Burge, who was fired from the Chicago Police Department in 1993. Richard Sikes, a lawyer who represents Mr. Burge in three lawsuits against him, said he has seen no signs of torture in the cases he has handled.</p>
        <p>He suggested that Mr. Burge may have become a magnet for people in Chicago who want to claim they were wrongfully convicted, saying, ''I think there's a lot of bandwagon here, in my view.''</p>
        <p>In Geneva, the United Nations Committee against Torture released its own report, which, along with calling on the United States to close the detention center at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, and criticizing interrogation techniques, took note of the ''limited investigation and lack of prosecution'' in connection to the accusations of torture in Chicago.</p>
        <p>It called on American authorities to ''promptly, thoroughly and impartially'' investigate the accusations, and provide the committee with more information.</p>
        <p>It was uncertain whether the special prosecutor's report in Chicago could lead to indictments.</p>
        <p>Robert D. Boyle, who was appointed as assistant special state's attorney in the case beside Edward J. Egan, the special prosecutor, said the report had to be ''fine-tuned'' and was not yet ready for release. In addition, a small part of it, including identifying information about a former assistant state's attorney, will not be made public for at least two weeks, a second judge ruled on Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
