<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buffett Buys Company Crippled by Asbestos Suits</title>
    <meta content="Y21BUFF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/21/business/21BUFF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johns Manville Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Berkshire Hathaway Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buffett, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D91E39F932A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buffett Buys Company Crippled by Asbestos Suits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Warren E Buffett's Berkshire Hathaway Inc acquires Johns Manville, maker of building materials, for $1.9 billion in cash; seller is Manville Personal Injury Settlement Trust (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a value investor, Warren E. Buffett likes to buy things on the cheap. Yesterday, he found a bargain that could have been marked, ''For Sale: $1 Billion Off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett's holding company, Berkshire Hathaway Inc., bought Johns Manville, the maker of building materials, for $1.9 billion in cash. Last week, a deal collapsed in which Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst and Bear Stearns offered to acquire the company for $2.9 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a value investor, Warren E. Buffett likes to buy things on the cheap. Yesterday, he found a bargain that could have been marked, ''For Sale: $1 Billion Off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett's holding company, Berkshire Hathaway Inc., bought Johns Manville, the maker of building materials, for $1.9 billion in cash. Last week, a deal collapsed in which Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst and Bear Stearns offered to acquire the company for $2.9 billion.</p>
        <p>Manville filed for bankruptcy in 1982 to protect itself from creditors and thousands of asbestos-related lawsuits. The seller yesterday was the Manville Personal Injury Settlement Trust, an independent trust set up to pay asbestos victims that itself became the majority owner of the company when Manville reorganized in 1988. Under the terms of the deal, Berkshire is protected from any liabilities arising from Manville's old asbestos business. Those remain with the trust.</p>
        <p>The deal was Mr. Buffett's fifth acquisition this year and followed his disclosure last month that Berkshire had purchased a 15 percent stake in the USG Corporation, the nation's largest wall board manufacturer. Like Manville, USG was plagued by asbestos health claims.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Berkshire paid $3.6 billion to buy other companies in construction-related businesses, including Benjamin Moore &amp; Company, a paint maker; Shaw Industries, a carpet manufacturer, and Justin Industries, a brick maker that also sells Tony Lama boots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett's latest move comes as the stock market continues to fall amid worries about the economy's health. Though the construction industry rises and falls with the broader economy, analysts praised the deal yesterday, pointing to Mr. Buffett's penchant for buying companies when they have fallen out of favor.</p>
        <p>''Warren always says you should buy snow shovels in July, not in January,'' said Alice Schroeder, an analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''And that's what he's doing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Buffett was able to acquire Manville ''for a song,'' said Robert R. Marshall, an analyst at First Union Securities Inc., because Berkshire has a stash of money to draw on. That puts the company in a better position than many leveraged buyout firms, which rely on an increasingly tight loan market to make deals.</p>
        <p>''It pays to have cash in a market like this,'' Mr. Marshall said.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was the inability to arrange enough financing that sank the richer Hicks, Muse-Bear Stearns deal for Manville. Hicks, Muse, a leveraged buyout firm, and Bear Stearns, an investment bank, planned to finance the transaction through $2.35 billion in senior loans and high-yield debt -- too tall an order, it turned out, in a credit-squeezed market. It did not help that Manville's third-quarter results fell below expectations as the construction sector waned.</p>
        <p>Hicks, Muse and Bear, Stearns ended up dropping their acquisition plans after the firms made a revised -- and lower -- bid for the company that was rejected by Manville's board. Mr. Buffett approached Manville about a week ago, executives  close to the deal said, offering $13 a share, a premium of about 20 percent over Manville's stock price on Tuesday. Manville stock rose $2.13 yesterday, to close at $12.88; Berkshire shares fell $1,400, to close at $66,500.</p>
        <p>''It looks like a very attractive price,'' Ms. Schroeder said of Mr. Buffett's offer for Manville. ''He can get them at a bargain when everyone else is getting out of the cyclicals.'' Manville had traded at a significant discount to most stocks, selling for only seven times its estimated earnings. The average company in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index trades at 25 times earnings.</p>
        <p>Manville will become a wholly owned unit of Berkshire and remain based in Denver. Current executives will continue to manage the company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
