<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jordan Frees Man Convicted Of Killing Wife</title>
    <meta content="21RELE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/21/nyregion/21RELE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jordan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abequa, Mohammad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abequa, Nihal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDE1F39F932A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jordan Frees Man Convicted Of Killing Wife</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mohammad Abequa, who murdered his wife in New Jersey in 1994 and fled to Jordan with their two young children, has been pardoned by Jordanian court after serving five years of 15 year sentence; reaction of family of slain Nihal Abequa express outrage; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was troubling enough to the victim's family that Mohammad Abequa, who murdered his wife in New Jersey in 1994 and fled to Jordan with their two young children, was sentenced to only 15 years by a Jordanian court.</p>
        <p>But then yesterday came the news that the confessed killer had been pardoned for his crime after serving five years in prison, and had been set free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was troubling enough to the victim's family that Mohammad Abequa, who murdered his wife in New Jersey in 1994 and fled to Jordan with their two young children, was sentenced to only 15 years by a Jordanian court.</p>
        <p>But then yesterday came the news that the confessed killer had been pardoned for his crime after serving five years in prison, and had been set free.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abequa had been imprisoned for the murder after the victim's family and high-ranking American officials, including President Clinton, had used every available diplomatic channel to persuade Jordan to extradite him to the United States to face charges or, failing that, to prosecute him in Jordan. Prosecutors in New Jersey informed the victim's relatives yesterday that Mr. Abequa had been freed.</p>
        <p>Nesime Dokur, the elder sister of the victim, Nihal Abequa, said the telephone call telling her of the killer's release thrust her back into the pain of the days after her sister's body was found under her bed, her head in a plastic bag.</p>
        <p>Then she had to break the news to her sister's children, Lisa, 12, and Sami, 9, who now live with her in New Jersey. ''They comforted me, because I was choking and crying,'' she said. She said the children knew she had been to their mother's grave on Dec. 1, the day she would have turned 47.</p>
        <p>Though the case took on aspects of international diplomacy, at its heart was the plight of a woman who had feared death at the hands of her husband and was ultimately proved correct.</p>
        <p>The Abequas married in 1986. She was a longtime United States citizen born in Turkey, he a recent immigrant from Jordan who planned to return to his homeland and wanted to raise his children there. In April 1994, she filed for divorce, accusing her husband, now 53, of child abuse and extreme acts of cruelty, and adding that he even stole money from his children's piggy banks.</p>
        <p>The couple separated, but on a weekend visit to their Parsippany-Troy Hills apartment in July, Mr. Abequa strangled his wife, saying later that she was too westernized and that she had shown him a tattoo inscribed on her leg by a new boyfriend.</p>
        <p>By the time the police found her body, Mr. Abequa had fled to Jordan, where he told his mother that he had brought the children to see his native land. But Jordanian authorities were notified of the killing, and Mr. Abequa was captured in late July.</p>
        <p>At the time, Jordan and the United States had no extradition treaty, and despite personal pleas to King Hussein from President Clinton, Attorney General Janet Reno and New Jersey's United States representatives and senators, he was not returned to the United States for a trial.</p>
        <p>Instead, he was tried in Jordan, with the help of New Jersey detectives and prosecutors. He faced a possible sentence of death by hanging but, after testifying that the murder was not premeditated, was sentenced to 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>''We had to use all the influence of our government to get him tried and sentenced,'' Senator Frank R. Lautenberg of New Jersey told The Associated Press. ''This is a very sad moment.''</p>
        <p>Diplomatic pressure had also been applied to bring the two children, who were being cared for by Mr. Abequa's family, back to the United States, where a judge had granted custody to Ms. Dokur and her elderly mother. The children were American citizens and did not speak Arabic.</p>
        <p>Officials said yesterday that they did not know why, or even exactly when, the pardon had taken place. John B. Dangler, the Morris County prosecutor, said he had been told that it was a ''palace pardon,'' granted by the king, and that Mr. Abequa was one of a group of prisoners that had been released.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Abequa was released sometime in November, the American Embassy in Amman learned of the pardon only in recent days, after Mr. Abequa went to the embassy to visit an official who had been to see him in jail, Mr. Dangler said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dangler said that Mr. Abequa's brother was a general in the Jordanian army, but that it was not clear whether family connections influenced the pardon.</p>
        <p>After the Abequa case, Jordan and the United States signed an extradition treaty. Calling the pardon ''an affront to justice,'' Mr. Dangler said he would explore whether steps could be taken to return Mr. Abequa to New Jersey, where an indictment for murder and two counts of kidnapping still stands against him.</p>
        <p>But, he said, he does not expect help from Jordanian authorities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
