<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off Floor, Onto Wall With Shelving</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED71E31F935A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off Floor, Onto Wall With Shelving</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE spring housecleaning, organizing a garage as fall and winter approach can be an annual ritual. Taking as many items as possible off the floor is a key to "making space." One way is to buy metal or heavy-duty plastic utility shelves that stand on the floor.</p>
        <p>Although relatively expensive -- sufficient shelving for an average garage can cost hundreds of dollars -- purchased shelves can be assembled fairly quickly and look nice. Some styles can be arranged to provide work surfaces and storage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE spring housecleaning, organizing a garage as fall and winter approach can be an annual ritual. Taking as many items as possible off the floor is a key to "making space." One way is to buy metal or heavy-duty plastic utility shelves that stand on the floor.</p>
        <p>Although relatively expensive -- sufficient shelving for an average garage can cost hundreds of dollars -- purchased shelves can be assembled fairly quickly and look nice. Some styles can be arranged to provide work surfaces and storage.</p>
        <p>Shelves whose components slide together and fasten without nuts and bolts are the easiest to assemble and are generally sturdier than their counterparts, chiefly because there are no fasteners to loosen. Plastic shelving has the advantage of resisting rust, but it may not be strong enough to support heavy loads like paint cans or serve as a workbench.</p>
        <p>Compare shelving specifications before buying. If the main difference between inexpensive and expensive shelving is the shelf material, not the legs or braces, you may save money and create strong shelving by buying the inexpensive variety and replacing weak shelf material, usually thin hardboard, with plywood or solid lumber.</p>
        <p>If you have a power saw consider making your own shelving. Use 1 x 3-inch lumber for the brackets. For each you will need one piece for a horizontal shelf support and another for a brace attached at an angle beneath it. Saw the pieces to the same length -- the recommended maximum is 20 inches -- and miter the ends of the brace at 45-degree angles, so that they slope toward each other.  Attach the pieces to the garage wall before fastening them together. If the wall studs are exposed, place the pieces against the side of a stud and fasten each with a single 7-penny nail, 2 1/4 inches long, or a 10-gauge two-inch-long screw.</p>
        <p>In that position the bottom edge of the horizontal piece should rest on a mitered end of the brace. Place a level on the horizontal piece and shift the brace, if necessary, to center the bubble.</p>
        <p>After marking where the brace and horizontal piece meet, remove the level and drill a vertical pilot hole upward through the brace and into the support. Fasten the pieces together with a three-inch screw. Add a nail or screw to each piece where it rests against the stud.</p>
        <p>Horizontal spacing between braces cannot exceed three feet, or the shelves will sag. Vertical spacing should allow for large items.  Measure heights carefully when installing brackets to assure that shelves will be level.</p>
        <p>If the wall studs are not exposed find them by determining their locations from visible fasteners or using an electronic stud finder. Studs are usually at 16- or 24-inch intervals.</p>
        <p>Attach 2 x 4's vertically to studs spaced the desired distance apart placing their wider surfaces against the wall and installing into the studs 16-penny, 3 1/2-inch, nails or three-inch-long screws through both the surfaces and the wallboard.</p>
        <p>Fasten brackets to the edges of the 2 x 4's.  On masonry walls fasten 2 x 4's with masonry nails, anchor bolts or gunpowder-driven fasteners.</p>
        <p>Shelves can be wide boards or plywood. Fasten them to the tops of the brackets with screws. Besides shelves, you can also make racks for garden tools and other equipment.</p>
        <p>A rack can consist of a single board fastened across several studs. To install two or more racks so that one is above the other on a wall attach the uppermost rack as high as you can reach.</p>
        <p>After mounting the rack, attach brackets for holding tools. Hang tools from the brackets. Attach the lower rack and position brackets so that its items will fit between those from the above.</p>
        <p>Exposed ceiling joists accessible from a stepladder are an often overlooked storage area in many garages. Lay a sheet of plywood at least a half-inch thick across them as a platform for storing seldom-used or seasonal items.</p>
        <p>You can suspend a second platform beneath the joists. Build U-shaped wood slings, each consisting of 1 x 3's fastened to form three sides of a square or rectangle. Attach the slings' uprights to the sides of the joists so that the slings are aligned and hang at identical heights. Lay a piece of plywood between the uprights as a platform.</p>
        <p>Cleaning and applying sealer to concrete garage floors improves appearance and helps prevent cracking. Moisture entering pores in the concrete causes cracking by repeatedly freezing and thawing. The culprits are usually snow and ice melting off parked vehicles.</p>
        <p>Remove thick oil and dirt by scraping with a putty knife. After scrubbing stains with a driveway cleaner or other detergent, wash the entire floor with similar detergent applied with a long-handled brush or pressure washer. Rinse the floor with plain water and let it dry.</p>
        <p>Concrete sealer, which comes in cans and bottles, should be applied by spraying, spreading or pouring. Apply two coats if the floor has never been sealed or one if sealer has been previously applied. Renew the sealer when water no longer forms beads on the surface.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
