<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Chooses White House Adviser as Budget Director</title>
    <meta content="Y23APP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/23/politics/23APPO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1491160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Office of Management and Budget</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolten, Josh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Office of Management and Budget</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bolten, Josh</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5D71631F930A15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Chooses White House Adviser as Budget Director</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Chooses White House Adviser as Budget Director</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>President Bush names Joshua Bolten, little-known but highly influential White House adviser, as OMB director, succeeding Mitchell E Daniels Jr; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush chose a little-known but highly influential White House adviser, Joshua Bolten, today as the director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>The appointment comes at a time of record federal deficits, the most expensive military buildup in a generation and coming election-year fights with Congress over taxes and spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush chose a little-known but highly influential White House adviser, Joshua Bolten, as the director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush chose a little-known but highly influential White House adviser, Joshua Bolten, today as the director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>The appointment comes at a time of record federal deficits, the most expensive military buildup in a generation and coming election-year fights with Congress over taxes and spending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolten, 48, is to replace Mitchell E. Daniels Jr. as overseer of the nation's $2.23 trillion federal budget, one of the most powerful and difficult jobs in the capital. In a brief, rare public appearance with Mr. Bush this morning, he promised to be a ''tight-fisted custodian of the people's money,'' and then noted that budget director ''is not the easiest job in government.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Republicans close to the White House said that the genial Mr. Bolten was not as likely to antagonize Capitol Hill as Mr. Daniels, who once told reporters that the motto of Congress was ''don't just stand there, spend something.'' With the smooth Mr. Bolten, one senior administration official said, ''you won't feel the knife going in.''</p>
        <p>Republicans said today that Mr. Bolten, a single-digit millionaire from his days at the Goldman Sachs investment banking firm, would probably bring even more power to the budget director's job. As deputy chief of staff to Mr. Bush, Mr. Bolten has been in charge of all domestic policy at the White House and was critical to the formulation of the administration's two rounds of tax cuts and the creation of the Department of Homeland Security. He is a central player on the White House economic team, with his former Goldman Sachs colleague, Stephen J. Friedman, and has frequently closed legislative deals for Mr. Bush on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolten almost never speaks to reporters, a valuable attribute in a White House that prizes secrecy.</p>
        <p>''Josh Bolten is brilliant, he is tireless, he remains calm in any storm,'' Mr. Bush said in announcing the appointment. ''He is a man of complete integrity. No member of my staff has served with greater skill or earned greater respect amongst his colleagues than Josh Bolten. I'm honored that he's agreed to join my cabinet.''</p>
        <p>Republicans said Mr. Bolten's appointment probably meant that domestic policy would be largely driven out of the budget director's office, particularly the administration's plans to overhaul Medicare, provide prescription drug coverage and push for a new round of tax cuts this fall. Mr. Bolten, they said, could emerge as an unusually strong budget director because of his previous White House experience and close ties to the president.</p>
        <p>''Josh Bolten took over the White House domestic policy show and the economic policy show,'' said Lawrence Kudlow, an associate budget director in the Reagan administration who is the host of a CNBC-TV talk show and is close to Vice President Dick Cheney. ''Now he's going to have the number-crunching influence of the agency. If you sit in the Roosevelt Room where these decisions are hashed out, the people with the numbers have tremendous advantage. They can price out in great detail any new program thought that comes out of the West Wing.''</p>
        <p>But Karl C. Rove, the president's powerful political adviser, said in a telephone interview today that Mr. Bolten ''won't be doing two jobs'' -- that of budget director and chief White House domestic policy adviser. Mr. Rove also said Mr. Bolten was ''one of the most personally popular and widely respected members of the West Wing staff.''</p>
        <p>''I cannot say enough good things about the guy,'' Mr. Rove said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear if Mr. Bolten would emerge from his West Wing office, where he displays a series of photographs of Mr. Bush's hands, to speak to the press. Today an aide said Mr. Bolten would not comment until his nomination was confirmed by the Senate, where Mr. Bush's choice for deputy budget director, Clay Johnson, has been held up for months by Senator Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia. Mr. Byrd, the senior Democrat on the Appropriations Committee, is protesting an administration jobs policy, but his office had no comment today on whether the senator would also block Mr. Bolten.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolten's appointment was welcomed with reservations by Senator Jon Corzine, Democrat of New Jersey, a former co-chairman of Goldman Sachs. For a short time in the 1990's, Mr. Bolten worked as Mr. Corzine's chief of staff at Goldman Sachs. Mr. Corzine said he remembered him as a pragmatist who liked tax cuts, but not a supply-side true believer like many of the economists who have influenced Mr. Bush's tax-cutting plans.</p>
        <p>''He is conservative,'' Mr. Corzine said, ''but I don't think he's ideological on much of anything.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he said, ''he will be in a position of defending policies that I think are on the wrong side of the tracks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolten grew up in Washington, the son of a Central Intelligence Agency officer who worked in the agency's covert espionage arm. In keeping with the policy of the agency, he was instructed to tell his friends that his father worked at the Pentagon, not the C.I.A. He went on to graduate from St. Albans, the exclusive private boys' school in Washington, then Princeton University and Stanford Law School.</p>
        <p>In the first Bush administration, Mr. Bolten was the general counsel to the office of the United States trade representative and then worked for Goldman Sachs in London. In 2000, he was the policy director of Mr. Bush's presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>A recent financial disclosure form of Mr. Bolten lists assets of as much as $4 million, including a house in Key West, Fla. He owns two motorcycles, a Harley Davidson and a Victory. In a White House of early risers, staff members say he makes it to the 7:30 a.m. senior staff meeting with only a few minutes to spare.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
