<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Action Plan For a Reluctant Greenspan</title>
    <meta content="26VIEW$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shiller, Robert J (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Irrational Exuberance (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DC123DF935A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Action Plan For a Reluctant Greenspan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic View column on Irrational Exuberance, book by Yale University economist Robert J Shiller, which warns of economic perils posed by overvalued stock prices and discusses possible remedies for problem, besides imposition of higher interest rates; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR all those who doubt that a speculative bubble hangs dangerously over the economy -- and the doubters number in the tens of millions -- Robert J. Shiller's new book is sobering. He describes a market so out of control that the run-up in the Roaring 20's looks like a molehill, compared with the Mount Everest of the 90's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shiller, a Yale University economist, called his book ''Irrational Exuberance,'' borrowing the phrase coined by Alan Greenspan in December 1996. The Federal Reserve chairman has tried ever since to soften stock prices, but investors -- that is, nearly half the population -- have laughed in his face. The Fed notches up interest rates and stocks rise anyway, as if they were an addiction like cigarettes or liquor, just as much in need of a warning label.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR all those who doubt that a speculative bubble hangs dangerously over the economy -- and the doubters number in the tens of millions -- Robert J. Shiller's new book is sobering. He describes a market so out of control that the run-up in the Roaring 20's looks like a molehill, compared with the Mount Everest of the 90's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shiller, a Yale University economist, called his book ''Irrational Exuberance,'' borrowing the phrase coined by Alan Greenspan in December 1996. The Federal Reserve chairman has tried ever since to soften stock prices, but investors -- that is, nearly half the population -- have laughed in his face. The Fed notches up interest rates and stocks rise anyway, as if they were an addiction like cigarettes or liquor, just as much in need of a warning label.</p>
        <p>Posting such a label -- in this case, coming right out and saying that we are in a stock market bubble -- would be the sort of government intervention that Mr. Greenspan resists. But stocks today are greatly overvalued -- perhaps by more than $7 trillion, Mr. Shiller says -- and even free-market economists wonder about the efficacy of the Fed's interest rate strategy.</p>
        <p>''Some of us believe that the speculation has gone so far that there is no easy or painless way out,'' said one such economist on Wall Street, Albert Wojnilower. ''The question is whether to acknowledge this and open the floor to other solutions. That is what Greenspan would be doing if he declared that speculation is driving up stock prices.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan said in 1996 -- and he continues to say today -- that irrational exuberance might be driving up stock prices. But he has never stepped over the line and bluntly stated that it is. Instead, he has kept one foot firmly planted in the camp of those who regard the market's performance as rational. Rising productivity and the prospect of rising corporate profits, he says, bring investors tumbling sensibly into stocks in anticipation of future gains.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan has acquired enormous prestige for his astute nurturing of the economy in recent years. But he is in danger of dissipating that prestige by insisting on rational monetary policy -- the notching up of interest rates -- to discipline an irrational situation. Why should investors be deterred from borrowing money at 6 or even 10 percent, Mr. Wojnilower asks, when they believe that stocks bought with the borrowed money will go up 20 percent by year-end? Getting interest rates high enough to stop that fervor would bust the economy.</p>
        <p>What would happen if Mr. Greenspan declared bluntly that irrational exuberance controls the market and is running roughshod over all the sensible reasons for owning stocks? For one thing, such frankness would encounter resistance. The Clinton administration, in an election year, prefers to view the market as reflecting corporate America's strength and profitability. And most Wall Street traders like Mr. Greenspan's current ambivalence.</p>
        <p>But public recognition of the bubble might finally propel America into vigorous debate about ways to control the market fever.</p>
        <p>THERE are a half-dozen remedies besides higher rates. On everyone's list is tightening margin requirements. Investors could be required to put up 60 or 70 percent of the purchase price of a stock, instead of the present 50 percent. Mr. Greenspan objects that small investors, the biggest users of margin debt, would be forced more than big investors to pull back. But they would also be saved from painful losses in a market sell-off.</p>
        <p>Bank regulators could put up another obstacle to the purchase of securities on credit. They could require banks to increase the capital that backs such loans, which by one measure rose to $23.4 billion in February from $18.1 billion just last November. The government, in effect, would be allocating credit, a role shunned in Washington today.</p>
        <p>A transaction tax on all stock trades, of the sort once proposed by James Tobin, the Nobel laureate in economics, would slow trading. So would an old Warren Buffett idea: a 100 percent capital gains tax on stocks held for too short a term, say less than a year. That would encourage people to invest for the long term, more cautiously.</p>
        <p>The so-called suitability rules could also be extended. These require brokers to check that a customer's investment goals are in line with his income, net worth and the like. A broker is bound by the rules to discourage a grandmother from sinking all her savings into a profitless Internet company. Suitability rules do not now cover day traders and online investors, though formal proposals already exist to extend them.</p>
        <p>Remedies like these might sap the speculation without bringing down the economy. But even proponents worry that it is already too late to prevent a damaging market crash or a painful sell-off -- the denouement in the past of speculative bubbles that have gone unrecognized for so long.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
