<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/Brooklyn Heights and Cobble Hill; National Chains Vie for Piece of the Local Retail Pie</title>
    <meta content="26COMM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Heights (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cobble Hill (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cvs Drug Stores</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barnes &amp; Noble</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cohen's Fashion Optical</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holusha, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DC143DF935A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/Brooklyn Heights and Cobble Hill; National Chains Vie for Piece of the Local Retail Pie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holusha, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn Heights and neighboring Cobble Hill, long home to locally owned businesses, are attracting national retailers such as CVS, Barnes &amp; Noble and Cohen's Fashion Optical; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BROOKLYN HEIGHTS and neighboring Cobble Hill have long been the home to locally owned businesses catering to the residents of the largely low-rise neighborhoods and the nearby court system. But now the area is beginning to attract national retailers, at the same time as some local businesses are expanding.</p>
        <p>CVS Pharmacy has leased 12,000 square feet of space on the first floor and basement of the building at 150 Court Street, and Cohen's Fashion Optical opened last week in 2,000 square feet at 189 Montague Street, a few blocks away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BROOKLYN HEIGHTS and neighboring Cobble Hill have long been the home to locally owned businesses catering to the residents of the largely low-rise neighborhoods and the nearby court system. But now the area is beginning to attract national retailers, at the same time as some local businesses are expanding.</p>
        <p>CVS Pharmacy has leased 12,000 square feet of space on the first floor and basement of the building at 150 Court Street, and Cohen's Fashion Optical opened last week in 2,000 square feet at 189 Montague Street, a few blocks away.</p>
        <p>Work is proceeding on a building at 100 Court Street, between Schermerhorn and State Streets, that will house a 2,300-seat, 12-screen Regal Cinema and a 12,000-square-foot, two-level Barnes &amp; Noble bookstore.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Steven Hoose is adding 4,000 square feet, doubling the size of Perelandra, the health foods store that he and his wife, Madi, operate at 175 Remsen Street.</p>
        <p>According to a report by Ingram &amp; Hebron Realty, 22 new restaurants and retail stores have opened in the area in the last two years, including Sprint and Nine West, attracted by the affluence of the residents and lower costs compared with Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I like the neighborhood,'' said Oleg Volovichenko, one of the managers of Cohen's Fashion Optical, as he arranged eyeglasses of different styles in glass cases in preparation for the store's opening. He noted that a new apartment building being completed almost directly across Montague Street from his store would have asking rents of $1,900 to $6,800 a month when leasing begins in April.</p>
        <p>He said he expected that families who could afford those rents would have enough income for other consumer goods, including eyeglasses. This is the first retail venture for Mr. Volovichenko, who said he also operated a wholesale optical business.</p>
        <p>Cohen's signed a 10-year lease for the space on the first floor of a nine-story office building. The initial rent is $65 a square foot a year, well below the hundreds of dollars a square foot commanded in prime retail locations in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The CVS Pharmacy lease -- in a building that once housed the administrative offices of the Brooklyn Hebrew Orphan Asylum, according to a newly uncovered sign on the building -- is for the first floor and the basement. The retailer plans to use both levels as sales space, rather than use the basement strictly for storage.</p>
        <p>The lease, also for 10 years, has an initial rental rate of $40 a square foot, reflecting both that the store is several blocks from where Cohen's is in the heart of the Brooklyn Heights and that larger retail spaces -- CVS is roughly six times the size of Cohen's -- usually rent for less per square foot than smaller ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoose of Perelandra -- the name comes from the title of a book by C.S. Lewis -- has been selling health food to Heights residents since 1976. He said he started on Montague Street, expanding three times there before moving to Remsen Street.</p>
        <p>The growth of the business reflects changes in society and people's attitudes toward food, Mr. Hoose said, as well as the development of a wider variety of products.</p>
        <p>''In 1976, this was a fringe business,'' he said. ''Not many people were interested in the products and the variety was not wide enough for people to do all their shopping in a health-foods store''</p>
        <p>Now, he said, a full line of products is available, including soups that are freshly cooked daily. He said the store sold to the ''incredibly diverse'' residents of the neighborhood and to workers in the nearby courts and office buildings of downtown Brooklyn. ''The business has changed dramatically,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Frances Schor, president of the Treeline Management Company, which owns and manages several buildings in Brooklyn Heights, said the demographics of the area were attractive to retailers. She said the new apartment building on Montague Street, which will have 32 stories, demonstrated the point.</p>
        <p>W HEN people can afford to pay several thousand dollars a month in rent, they are going to demand other services and that will draw retail,'' she said. ''These people are spenders and they are going to want to eat out at restaurants, go to movies and shop in stores they are accustomed to, like the Gap and Limited.'' She said that while the Heights  was formerly perceived as more intellectual than consumerist, people moving in recently had been largely highly paid professionals with a free attitude toward spending.</p>
        <p>Treeline manages the building at 175 Remsen Street. Ms. Schor said that when  Mr. Hoose wanted to expand into adjacent space in the building formerly occupied by a bookstore and an airline ticket office, a gourmet food operator bid against him to try to get into the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>One of the issues roiling the real estate scene on Brooklyn Heights is the apparent intention of the city to sell three buildings currently used by the Board of Education, at 110 and 131 Livingston Street and at 65 Court Street. ''The city has sent us information on selling the Board of Education buildings and we think they are serious,'' said Robert Hebron, a partner in Ingram &amp; Hebron.</p>
        <p>The main Board of Education building at 110 Livingston Street contains 361,000 square feet of space, while No. 131 has 64,000 square feet. The one at 65 Court has 286,000 square feet, which would be a lot of inventory hitting the market all at once if the city proceeds rapidly.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hebron said there was talk of converting 110 Livingston Street to residential use, which would help retailers in the area by increasing the population.</p>
        <p>Other developments in adjacent areas will affect the real estate market in the Heights and the amount of pedestrian traffic passing by the stores.</p>
        <p>Forest City Ratner Companies, the developer of the million-square-foot Metrotech Center several blocks to the east of the Heights, is expected to proceed this year with a building at 330 Jay Street, which is also known as 12 Metrotech Center. The building is expected to be ready for occupancy by the winter of 2002.</p>
        <p>The $350 million, 950,000-square-foot building will house the Kings Country Family Court, New York State Supreme Court and related city and country agencies. These agencies will lease 780,000 square feet  of space from the Ratner companies, leaving 170,000 square feet on the top floors for commercial tenants.</p>
        <p>The Ratner companies are also attempting to pre-lease space in 9 Metrotech Center, a new million-square-foot building that it said would be ready for occupancy in the spring of 2001.</p>
        <p>To the north of Brooklyn Heights is an area called Dumbo that is marketed, in part, as a location for the high technology, Internet-related companies referred to as dot-coms. The acronym stands for Down Under the Manhattan Bridge Overpass.</p>
        <p>James Whelan, the director of the recently formed Downtown Brooklyn Council, an advocacy group for the area, said 100,000 square feet of space in the Dumbo area had already been leased by dot-com companies and that 250,000 more square feet was being prepared by Two Trees Management, the dominant developer in the area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whelan said one of the new tenants was Bliss, a cosmetics distributor that operated its e-business from the location. Another newcomer, he said, is Anatomical Travelogue, a medical imaging company.</p>
        <p>He said the area is not trying to compete with Lower Manhattan, although the Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce and others are seeking to have the area included in an expansion of the Plug'n'Go program that helped the downtown area attract technology companies.</p>
        <p>''We're competing with west Chelsea,'' he said. ''We're cheaper and have better transportation links.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
