<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fertilize, but Feed Those Plants With Care</title>
    <meta content="WCGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fertilizer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faust, Joan Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFD7153DF935A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fertilize, but Feed Those Plants With Care</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Faust, Joan Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Lee Faust offers guidelines for using plant fertilizer; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that spring is here, things will start moving along rapidly. It may be time to explain the intricacies of plant fertilizer.</p>
        <p>The novice gardener may be overwhelmed by the vast assortment of fertilizers that fill the garden suppliers' shelves. The products are in bags, boxes and bottles. Many of them are labeled for particular plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that spring is here, things will start moving along rapidly. It may be time to explain the intricacies of plant fertilizer.</p>
        <p>The novice gardener may be overwhelmed by the vast assortment of fertilizers that fill the garden suppliers' shelves. The products are in bags, boxes and bottles. Many of them are labeled for particular plants.</p>
        <p>All plants in the garden will benefit from a spring feed. The question usually is, which sort of feed?</p>
        <p>To get plants off to a good start, plan to have an ample supply of bagged dry fertilizer such as 5-10-5. This is a basic all-around fertilizer that can be used for most garden plants.</p>
        <p>The numbers on the bags need not be confusing. They refer to the percentages of the three main ingredients in a fertilizer: Nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P) and potassium (K). The numbers merely reflect the percentages of these three basic ingredients.</p>
        <p>If the number is high, particularly the first number, it means that a generous amount of nitrogen is in the fertilizer. Something like 20-6-4 may be noted on a fertilizer particularly packaged for use on lawns.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen is the most easily leached of any of the nutrients. A high nitrogen formula is often applied to lawns in spring for that initial green-up boost. (Many gardeners are finding, however, if they followed the current recommendations to feed their lawn around Thanksgiving time, this added nitrogen boost is not necessary.)</p>
        <p>Another kind of fertilizer that is fast catching on is the slow-release fertilizer. This fertilizer is usually boxed and contains tiny pellets of plant food.</p>
        <p>The tiny beads are coated with a water-soluble resin that dissolves slowly when the resin becomes moistened. The release is controlled so that the pellets can provide nutrients to a plant for several months. Commercial greenhouse growers have found these types of fertilizer a tremendous help knowing they can be applied to pots of plants and know that the plant will have good nutrition after they are sold.</p>
        <p>These controlled-release fertilizers are also helpful for perennial plantings. A good handful of this type of fertilizer should supply a normal-sized perennial for three to maybe four months. Rose bushes could do with a good handful, too. Big feeder plants such as peonies might do with two handfuls. If during the summer the perennial shows signs of hunger it can be feed lightly again.</p>
        <p>The trick is to be careful so as not to burn the plants. These potent slow-release fertilizers always have clear application directions on the boxes and they should be followed carefully.</p>
        <p>One of the trickiest sorts of fertilizers to use are the animal manures.  They should always be allowed to weather for a few months before they are applied. Otherwise the animal manures can burn plants if used fresh due to the high urine-salt content.</p>
        <p>A quick fix for needy plants are the water-soluble fertilizers. The nutrients in these formulas are immediately available to the plants as soon as they filter down to the root systems. But since these fertilizers are quite expensive, their use should be limited. The water-solubles are especially effective for window boxes and patio tubs where the compact network of roots often needs a nutrient boost.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, when it is difficult to feed individual plants, many gardeners have found it just as easy to broadcast plant fertilizer over a wide area, such as a large flower border. The best time to do this is before a rain storm for the particles of fertilizer are quickly washed down into the soil and off the emerging shoots.</p>
        <p>When plants have been in the ground for a lengthy period, they usually have very deep and convoluted roots systems. Sometimes professional feeding is needed for large shrubs and trees where the commercial power augers can be used to go down deep into the soil and place the nutrients where they are most needed.</p>
        <p>Organic fertilizers such as cottonseed meal, dried blood, bone meal and the like are derived from organisms and may not have as high nutrient ratios as the other formulated fertilizers. Also, it is important to check the label of the particular organic fertilizer to be sure that the plant receives the proper nutrients it needs. Usually the organic source provides only one, maybe two nutrients and it is important that proper supplemental sources are added.</p>
        <p>The gardening season will proceed now at a good pace. So it is essential that the plants are provided all the help that can be given.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
