<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hillary Clinton Escaped Collapse in the Markets That Cost Many Fortunes</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMODITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REFCO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONE, ROBERT L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TROELSTRUP, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAIR, JAMES B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DD103FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hillary Clinton Escaped Collapse in the Markets That Cost Many Fortunes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGDALE, Ark., April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fifteen years after brokers and customers at the Refco brokerage office here plucked money from the commodities markets and then watched their portfolios collapse, the office is attracting renewed attention for the role it played in earning nearly $100,000 for Bill and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's, the office was a "money machine for everyone" one client recalled this week, and a clutch of lawyers, farmers and bankers in this prosperous corner of Arkansas watched spellbound as the whirling electronic ticker kept score of their winnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fifteen years after brokers and customers at the Refco brokerage office here plucked money from the commodities markets and then watched their portfolios collapse, the office is attracting renewed attention for the role it played in earning nearly $100,000 for Bill and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's, the office was a "money machine for everyone" one client recalled this week, and a clutch of lawyers, farmers and bankers in this prosperous corner of Arkansas watched spellbound as the whirling electronic ticker kept score of their winnings.</p>
        <p>But more than a half-dozen former brokers and customers interviewed this week said that when the cattle futures market took a sharp, abrupt dive in October 1979, they and about 100 other investors crashed. Many lost their homes, depleted their bank accounts and frantically sold their high-priced toys. Mrs. Clinton, however, had stopped trading shortly before the crash.</p>
        <p>It is not known how many customers in the office fared as well as Mrs. Clinton, who avoided the collapse and turned a $1,000 stake into a $99,537 profit. Explaining Success</p>
        <p>The White House has said Mrs. Clinton traded on her own, relying on an astute reading of The Wall Street Journal and guidance from James B. Blair, a friend who was the top lawyer for Tyson Foods Inc., the state's largest employer.</p>
        <p>But the former brokers and clients said it was also possible that Mrs. Clinton had benefited from favorable treatment from her broker, Robert L. (Red) Bone, who ran the Refco office in Springdale. Mr. Bone, a commodities dealer, was disciplined by regulators both before and after the records show that he handled trades for Mrs. Clinton. The discipline was not related to Mrs. Clinton's account.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Mercantile exchange fined both Mr. Bone and Refco for record-keeping failures in this period, an inquiry that a former senior regulator said stemmed from concerns about possible mishandling of bulk orders and the allocation of winning and losing trades to various customers. Officials at the White House say that Mrs. Clinton had not known of Mr. Bone's regulatory problems at the time she was trading.</p>
        <p>Such allocations of bulk orders was a significant problem at brokerage firms across the country in the late 1970's. But the advent of computerized record-keeping in the 1980's helped to curb the practice. Lack of Records</p>
        <p>Because of the lack of records at Refco, investigators pushed hard for the cooperation of the office's brokers who might have known how the trades were allocated.</p>
        <p>The regulator, John Troelstrup, then vice president of the exchange's Law and Compliance Division, said: "We had to find someone to tell us about it. Did we try? Yes. Did we succeed? No."</p>
        <p>Mr. Troelstrup, now in private practice, acknowledged that the placing of block trades, which was legal at the time, would have "facilitated" the shift of winning investments to Mrs. Clinton's account. But he said his own review of the First Lady's records suggested she was an instinctively gifted trader, "akin to a racing driver with an instinctive feel for maneuvering in heavy traffic."</p>
        <p>In lawsuits tried in the 1980's, at least one Springdale broker admitted that he had allocated winning trades from bulk orders of commodities to favored clients, according to a former Refco client involved in the litigation. The brokerage was sued by scores of customers, including some brokers who had personal accounts. The company prevailed in most of the suits.</p>
        <p>A second former Springdale broker who spoke on the condition of anonymity said in a recent interview that the office did in some instances allocate trades to client accounts after it was clear which trades were winners and which were losers. In one instance, this former broker said, a customer in the Springdale office opened an account in his girlfriend's name, placed the trades without her knowledge and then presented her with a six-figure check at a raucous birthday party. No Recall About Clintons</p>
        <p>Mr. Bone, who insisted in interviews last month that he did not recall ever trading for the Clintons, could not be reached for further comment today.</p>
        <p>Brokers and customers in Springdale agree that the central figures in the office were Mr. Bone, a former employee of Tyson Foods, and Mr. Blair, who was in the late 1970's serving as an outside counsel to Tyson.</p>
        <p>The two men could hardly have been more different. Mr. Blair was editor in chief of the Arkansas Law Review while a student at the University of Arkansas School of Law. He rose to prominence in the state, and then in national Democratic Party, and has long been a confidant of the Clintons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bone, who has achieved considerable success as a professional poker player in Las Vegas, Nev., has told associates that he spent some of his childhood in an orphanage. In an interview last month, Mr. Bone said he worked at Tyson Foods from 1960 to 1973, rising to become the personal bodyguard of Donald J. Tyson, chairman of the company. He said he and Mr. Tyson were roommates when the chicken executive was "between wives." Regulatory Problems</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Bone traded egg futures for the company, participating with other Tyson executives in what regulators later said was an attempt to corner the market in 1970. It earned him his first regulatory reproof: a one-year suspension from trading.</p>
        <p>By the late 1970's, Mr. Bone was running Refco's Springdale office, and Mr. Blair, a partner in a respected local firm, quickly became one of his biggest clients.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Bone, Mr. Blair represented him in his first and second divorces. "We've always talked and understood each other," Mr. Bone said. "He's as common as an old shoe."</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair caught the commodities fever. An associate said he had installed an electronic ticker in his office to keep minute-by-minute track of the exchanges' movements. And with good reason. A former broker, Bill R. McCurdy, recalls that Mr. Blair kept a copy of a $1 million Refco check on his wall, the profits from an opportune investment. Big Commissions</p>
        <p>The brokers were doing well. Mr. McCurdy said he was earning $10,000 monthly in commissions, and others said they earned as much as $100,000. One young broker, a former hamburger cook just a few years out of high school, amassed a collection of more than a dozen Corvettes, a former client said.</p>
        <p>This was the milieu in which Mr. Blair, a good friend of the Clintons' encouraged Mrs. Clinton to begin commodities trading in Springdale. The White House says she opened the account in October 1978, just a few weeks before Mr. Clinton's landslide victory in his first gubernatorial race. Records say her first trades netted a 530 percent profit.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton had few assets. Under the rules followed by Refco, that meant that Mr. Bone was personally liable if she ran up losses and was unable to pay.</p>
        <p>It is not clear exactly how the orders were placed. Mrs. Clinton's account was one of the few in the office that was nondiscretionary, meaning that either she or someone with her power of attorney had to personally phone in orders to her broker.</p>
        <p>In 1979, shortly after Mrs. Clinton had stopped trading, the bottom fell out. Brokers and customers in Springdale accused the chairman of Refco, Thomas Dittmer, of urging them to buy cattle, even as he was selling it. While some juries ruled against Refco, there is no record that any of the suits ultimately prevailed; Mr. McCurdy, the former broker, said he did win a $100,000 out-of-court settlement from Refco.</p>
        <p>In July 1979, Mrs. Clinton withdrew $60,000, most of what was left in her Refco account. She never placed another trade with the brokerage, and stayed on the sidelines for the October debacle, when Mr. Blair and nearly all the other brokers and customers stayed in the market and bet wrongly that cattle prices would rise.  White House officials said that Mrs. Clinton, who was pregnant that fall with her daughter, Chelsea, simply "lost her nerve" for commodities speculation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
