<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Just Say 'Ouch'; It Pains a Nation of Stoics to Say 'No' to Pain</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMUNE SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAIN-RELIEVING DRUGS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2DF103FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="1110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Just Say 'Ouch'; It Pains a Nation of Stoics to Say 'No' to Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN in the final stages of the cancer that killed him, 59-year-old James Nickolaus refused to take medication to ease his pain. "He didn't want to die an addict," said his daughter, Janet, a psychiatric nurse in Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>A majority of Americans are similarly stoic, according to recent studies, believing that only moral weaklings use narcotics. Contrary to the popular notion that Americans are pill poppers, seeking relief at the first twinge of discomfort or depression, research strongly suggests that they are actually under-medicated for severe pain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN in the final stages of the cancer that killed him, 59-year-old James Nickolaus refused to take medication to ease his pain. "He didn't want to die an addict," said his daughter, Janet, a psychiatric nurse in Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>A majority of Americans are similarly stoic, according to recent studies, believing that only moral weaklings use narcotics. Contrary to the popular notion that Americans are pill poppers, seeking relief at the first twinge of discomfort or depression, research strongly suggests that they are actually under-medicated for severe pain.</p>
        <p>Recently released Federal guidelines on relieving cancer pain said patients often suffer needlessly. And statistics of the National Institute for Mental Health show that only 2.5 million of the 12.5 million Americans suffering from clinical depression in any given year receive any type of medical treatment.</p>
        <p>"We have this moralistic impulse," said Dr. Herbert D. Kleber, the medical director of the Center on Addiction and Substance Abuse in New York City. "We place a certain value on the stiff upper lip," Dr. Kleber said, "and look with disdain on people weak enough to need medication."</p>
        <p>So while drug abuse remains a major problem in this country, many people who freely stock their cabinets with an array of over-the-counter bromides still refuse medicine when they need it the most.</p>
        <p>William F. May, a professor of ethics at Southern Methodist University, said that these paradoxical impulses are born of the same compulsion to control oneself and one's emotions.</p>
        <p>The tendency to "gut it out" rather than "give in" to medication is deeply, if not uniquely, American, Mr. May said, because this country was carved out of the wilderness in a harsh Northeastern climate where survival depended on hard work and endurance.  "If the Puritans had landed in San Diego, maybe we would have had Jonathan Edwards in a hot tub," he said. "But instead our view is that we should conquer nature and conquer the body."</p>
        <p>Some doctors say that the stiff-upper-lip syndrome claims the lives of patients who are, if anything, addicted to stoicism.</p>
        <p>"Depression is not only a very painful condition; it's lethal," said Dr. Paul H. Wender, a professor of psychiatry at the University of Utah School of Medicine. "Ten to 15 percent will kill themselves."</p>
        <p>There is still debate among doctors about how to balance the benefits of pain relief with unwanted risks, though there is no question of offering pain relief without treating the underlying cause, be it a sprained ankle or a psychological trauma.</p>
        <p>But the push for increased acceptance of pain relief gained momentum from new evidence that pain suppresses the immune system has gained acceptance, with doctors citing their own experience that physical and emotional strain inhibits healing. New studies by researchers at the University of California in Los Angeles suggest that painkillers may help retard the growth of tumors -- at least in laboratory animals.</p>
        <p>"What this shows is that pain can kill," said Dr. John Liebeskind, professor of psychology at U.C.L.A. Fears of Addiction</p>
        <p>Yet some Americans would apparently rather die than take drugs to relieve pain. "Most people are terrified of the pain, which is driving the assisted suicide movement, but they fear drugs even more," said June Dahl, a professor of pharmacology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison Medical School.</p>
        <p>Most often, patients shun strong medicine because they fear addiction, although studies have concluded that very few of them -- less than 1 percent in hospital settings -- become psychologically addicted to pain medication. At the National Institute on Drug Abuse, Dr. Alan I. Trachtenberg said the prevalence of untreated pain had been seriously under-estimated and abuse of prescription drugs had been over-estimated.</p>
        <p>Outdated medical dogma also causes many people to refuse painkillers. Medical treatment was traditionally thought to be useless unless it hurt; in 1849, the vice president of the American Medical Association announced that "pain is curative."</p>
        <p>On that point, religion and science seemed at one time in perfect accord.</p>
        <p>"In the mainline religious traditions you won't find any support for the view that suffering or pain is intrinsically valuable," said Laurence J. O'Connell, president of the Park Ridge Center for the Study of Health, Faith and Ethics in Chicago. "But that doesn't mean that people in the past have not preached that suffering is good, and a lot of our culture flows out of 17th- and 18th-century Christianity."</p>
        <p>Today, patients take about half their prescribed pain medication, according to a study by researchers at the City of Hope National Medical Center in Duarte, Calif. Their research also suggests that family members often withhold painkillers and doctors are sometimes apprehensive about prescribing them. A California researcher recalled interviewing the mother of a 7-year-old child in Philadelphia who cried for his medicine while dying of cancer. But she refused him, fearing he would become addicted.</p>
        <p>Michael Sullivan, a 53-year-old Los Angeles salesman who was cured of lymphoma last year after a bone-marrow transplant, had an extremely hard time convincing his oncologist to prescribe the painkillers he needed for chest and bone pain just so he could stay on the job and retain his insurance, said his wife, Lynne Rivera. And when the doctor finally did, she said, a pharmacist at first refused to fill the prescription.</p>
        <p>Several doctors said they do under-medicate for pain, but they blamed state regulators. In New York -- one of 10 states where prescriptions for controlled substances are closely monitored -- physicians said they fear being investigated if they prescribe too many narcotics.</p>
        <p>The Mayday Fund, a New York City foundation, was founded in 1992 to educate the public by encouraging patients to demand pain relief from their doctors. "We thought if we told people, 'You don't have to suffer,' they'd be interested," said Fenella Rouse, its executive director. "But they weren't."</p>
        <p>In a national public opinion poll sponsored by Mayday, 92 percent of 1,000 Americans polled at random said they felt pain is an inevitable part of life. Fully two-thirds said the last time they felt serious pain they endured it. Professionals and city-dwellers, while still overwhelmingly resistant to medication, were somewhat less stoic than blue-collar workers and residents of small towns or rural areas.</p>
        <p>"Most people thought more should be done to relieve pain," Ms. Rouse said. "But they didn't want to take drugs. And they thought everybody else was taking too much medicine."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
