<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Questions, Questions, Questions Only the Season Will Answer</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D9103FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Questions, Questions, Questions Only the Season Will Answer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, DAVE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Cardinals go against the Reds in Cincinnati tonight, it will be the first Sunday night opener in major league history, the start of the National League's 125th season.</p>
        <p>But with three divisional champions and a wild card in both the American and National League playoffs, for the first time there also will be no pure pennant races as you've known them. Baseball also has no commissioner. And if the Players Association and the owners keep snarling at each other, there may be no season after the All-Star break, or after Labor Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Cardinals go against the Reds in Cincinnati tonight, it will be the first Sunday night opener in major league history, the start of the National League's 125th season.</p>
        <p>But with three divisional champions and a wild card in both the American and National League playoffs, for the first time there also will be no pure pennant races as you've known them. Baseball also has no commissioner. And if the Players Association and the owners keep snarling at each other, there may be no season after the All-Star break, or after Labor Day.</p>
        <p>But other questions surround whatever may develop:</p>
        <p>Now that the Mets' general manager, Joe McIlvaine, has supplied Dallas Green with first baseman David Segui and shortstop Jose Vizcaino in two quick deals, how many good young players will he eventually get in a trade for Bret Saberhagen?</p>
        <p>Don't you get the feeling that George Steinbrenner will erupt into making louder noises around the Yankees than he did last year?</p>
        <p>How soon will Michael Jordan wake up one morning in Birmingham or Chattanooga or Huntsville and ask himself, "What am I doing here?"</p>
        <p>On the ascent of Juan Gonzalez of the Rangers and Ken Griffey Jr. of the Mariners to the slugger's mountaintop of 500 homers, who will be the first to hit 50 in a season? Maybe this season?</p>
        <p>In their second season, can the Rockies possibly attract more customers than last year's major league record of 4,483,350?</p>
        <p>Won't closer Duane Ward's sore arm create more problems for the Blue Jays' chances of an American League East and World Series three-peat than slugger Joe Carter's broken thumb?</p>
        <p>At age 46, will Charlie Hough's 25th major league season be the last for the oldest Marlin in the ocean?</p>
        <p>If the Orioles don't win after having invested $42.85 million in free agents Rafael Palmeiro, Chris Sabo, Sid Fernandez and Lee Smith, will their new owner, Peter Angelos, wish he were a crabcake?</p>
        <p>Why did the Astros trade for Mitch (Wild Thing) Williams if Xavier Hernandez is the closer the Yankees hope he is?</p>
        <p>How many years will it be before somebody, anybody, matches what Mark Whiten, the Cardinals' right fielder, did last season: 4 homers and 12 r.b.i. in one game?</p>
        <p>Has anybody noticed that Bo Jackson hit five homers for the Angels this spring? But how often will he whiff?</p>
        <p>Without Will Clark batting third on a Giants team all but conceded the National League West title, will his absence affect not only Matt Williams but also Barry Bonds's bid for an unprecedented fourth m.v.p. award?</p>
        <p>Will the Brewers ever be quite the same now that Robin Yount has retired following Paul Molitor's defection to the Blue Jays?</p>
        <p>Will realignment help Davey Johnson, the Reds' manager, surface in the post-season playoffs from the National League Central?</p>
        <p>Who, if anybody, will succeed Nolan Ryan and George Brett on their pedestals as future first-ballot Hall of Famers?</p>
        <p>By trading Rickey Henderson to the Blue Jays last season for rookie right-hander Steve Karsay and then signing baseball's career stolen base leader and career lead-off-the-game home run hitter as a free agent, didn't the Athletics show how it's possible to have your cake and eat it, too?</p>
        <p>No matter how good rookie left fielder Tony Tarasco is, won't the Braves miss the 36 homers and 117 runs batted in supplied by Ron Gant last season?</p>
        <p>At age 42, Dave Winfield has more than 3,000 hits, but will the Twins' designated hitter last long enough to hit 47 more homers for a career total of 500?</p>
        <p>If 20-year-old Korean right-hander Chan Ho Park is the National League Rookie of the Year, he would be the seventh Dodger so honored during Tommy Lasorda's reign as Dodger manager; the others were Rick Sutcliffe in 1979, Steve Howe in 1980, Fernando Valenzuela in 1981, Steve Sax in 1982, Eric Karros in 1992 and Mike Piazza last season. Has any major league manager had more?</p>
        <p>When Jacobs Field opens Monday in Cleveland, will it finally open a new era for the Indians, who haven't finished in first place since 1954?</p>
        <p>After hitting 34 homers and driving in 100 runs last season, Phil Plantier is the best young slugger nobody knows, but if he has another big year, will the Padres trade him (as they have so many others) rather than pay him what he deserves?</p>
        <p>Will John Olerud of the Blue Jays hit .400 for as long as he did last season?</p>
        <p>Did you know that right-hander Anthony Young, who was on an 0-27 streak before being credited with a Mets victory in relief last July 28, needs a 30-0 record for the Cubs this season to lift his career record to .500?</p>
        <p>With every quote, isn't Sparky Anderson, the Tigers manager, more and more the reincarnation of Casey Stengel?</p>
        <p>Everybody in Montreal is wondering how much the Expos will miss second baseman Delino DeShields, traded to the Dodgers for right-hander Pedro Martinez, but won't the Expos miss Dan Duquette, now the Red Sox general manager, much more?</p>
        <p>And perhaps baseball's most embarrassing question this year: What if a wild-card team wins the World Series? Even more embarrassing, what if two wild-card teams meet in the World Series?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
