<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back to Basics In the West Village</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREENWICH VILLAGE (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDF133FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back to Basics In the West Village</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDALOUSIA ++ (212) 929-3693; 28 Cornelia Street, near West Fourth; $; Mastercard</p>
        <p>A charming Moroccan restaurant filled with ceramic curios and adorned with colorful tapestries, Andalousia specializes in aromatic North African dishes and serves some of the best couscous in town. Breewats -- small flaky pastries stuffed with fillings like sweet chicken stewed with dried lemons, a pea-and-carrot mixture or minced lamb -- are fine openers. There are also clean and fragrant salads, like hummus, grated carrots with raisins in a sweet orange marinade, and mashed eggplant with parsley, cumin and minced olives. The couscous is delicious, served with a variety of toppings, including steamed carrots, peas, zucchini and squash, spicy merguez, shredded chicken and tender chunks of stewed lamb. Excellent tagines -- Moroccan stews -- are served in traditional brown earthenware crocks; and B'stilla resembles a sweet chicken pot pie that is encased in phyllo with almonds and topped with a flaky crust seasoned with sugar and cinnamon. ($25 and Under: 2/18/94)  FLORENT</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDALOUSIA ++ (212) 929-3693; 28 Cornelia Street, near West Fourth; $; Mastercard</p>
        <p>A charming Moroccan restaurant filled with ceramic curios and adorned with colorful tapestries, Andalousia specializes in aromatic North African dishes and serves some of the best couscous in town. Breewats -- small flaky pastries stuffed with fillings like sweet chicken stewed with dried lemons, a pea-and-carrot mixture or minced lamb -- are fine openers. There are also clean and fragrant salads, like hummus, grated carrots with raisins in a sweet orange marinade, and mashed eggplant with parsley, cumin and minced olives. The couscous is delicious, served with a variety of toppings, including steamed carrots, peas, zucchini and squash, spicy merguez, shredded chicken and tender chunks of stewed lamb. Excellent tagines -- Moroccan stews -- are served in traditional brown earthenware crocks; and B'stilla resembles a sweet chicken pot pie that is encased in phyllo with almonds and topped with a flaky crust seasoned with sugar and cinnamon. ($25 and Under: 2/18/94)  FLORENT</p>
        <p>MARNIE'S NOODLE SHOP ++ (212) 741-3214; 466 Hudson Street, at Barrow Street; $; no credit cards</p>
        <p>Marnie Henricksson, a self-trained cook with a love for Asian food, turns out beautiful platters of cold Asian-style noodles and steaming bowls of soup at this unassuming spot. Ms. Henricksson may not offer truly Asian fare, but her fresh and flavorful dishes are definite crowd pleasers. Current appetizers include fish cake salad; Thai lemon grass soup with shrimp and cilantro; and spicy chicken wings. The cold noodle dishes are among the best on the menu: Chinese sesame noodles lightly coated in oil and topped with tahini, cucumber and lemony poached chicken breast. The same noodles also come with a rich Indonesian peanut sauce or an Asian pesto made with cilantro, mint, basil and ground peanuts. Among the hot noodles, the Southeast Asian saute are fat white wheat noodles in a coconut milk and ginger sauce with sprightly chunks of chicken breast. Korean beef noodles are served in a bowl with slices of stir-fried flank steak, shiitake mushrooms and carrots. ($25 and Under: 10/2/92)  MI COCINA ** (212) 627-8273; 57 Jane Street, near Hudson; $$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>The dusty-rose-tinted dining room has floor-to-ceiling windows on one end, a small colorful kitchen on the other, and a zinc-topped bar from which splendid margaritas flow, creating an atmosphere that helps make Mi Cocina one of the most genuine and welcoming Mexican restaurants in town. Engaging starters include empanadas de hongos filled with shiitake and cheese in a roasted tomato sauce; steamed tamal de acelgas filled with spicy pork and Swiss chard; and sopitos con queso de cabra, cornmeal crusts topped with goat cheese, salsa, onions and cilantro. A thick, dark and complex mole poblano -- the sauce that energizes so many good Mexican dishes -- is delightfully evident in the chicken enchiladas, seasoned with onions and sesame seeds. Other good entrees are the fajitas made with tender charred skirt steak, onions, guacamole and tomato; grilled strip steak with roasted garlic, grilled scallions and black beans; and pechuga con rajas a la crema, a grilled chicken breast preparation served in a light cream sauce with roasted poblano strips and onions. (Review: 11/1/91; revisited: 3/ 28/94)  9 JONES STREET ++ (212) 989-1220; 9 Jones Street, near Bleecker; $$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>This warm, comfortable 55-seat restaurant has soft beige walls, brick-red Tuscan floor tiles and well-spaced tables. Appetizers include a lusty braised beef and barley soup; grilled quail served with a little apple and goat cheese tart; a green salad of arugula, watercress and chickory tossed in spicy miso dressing, and hickory-smoked salmon with portobello mushrooms and polenta. Main courses are pan-seared tuna steak with lentil sauce and red pepper chutney; roasted salmon with fava beans and roasted tomatoes; grilled aged sirloin steak, and sauteed calf's liver with barolo wine sauce and gnocchi. ($25 and Under: 12/10/93)  PARIS COMMUNE ++ (212) 929-0509; 411 Bleecker Street; $; Diner's Club, Mastercard, Visa</p>
        <p>Candlelight, brick walls with dusty portraits, and an old wood floor contribute to a casual charm. Pleasing French bistro fare includes delicate steamed mussels in white wine and garlic, warm goat cheese salad, and hearty country terrine of pork and veal, served with grainy mustard, small salty olives and sharp cornichons. Simple dishes are the best of the main courses. Among them are grilled loin of pork served with a chunky fruit compote; steak with a peppercorn sauce; grilled salmon; sauteed calf's liver with a shallot sauce; and a nicoise salad made with either grilled tuna or chicken. ($25 and Under: 10/16/92)  TRATTORIA PESCE PASTA ++  (212) 645-2993; 262 Bleecker Street; $; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>A friendly little restaurant festooned with old-fashioned Italian trappings, Trattoria Pesce Pasta features a small roster of familiar dishes that are usually prepared with gusto. The pasta e fagioli, a smoky broth with beans and vegetables and full of macaroni, is restorative, and the minestrone is rich with fresh vegetables. Entrees include linguine with white clam sauce; penne tossed with broccoli, zucchini and garlic; grilled salmon with a light mustard sauce; grilled tuna steak with a garlic-rosemary and olive oil sauce, potatoes and escarole; gnocchi with pesto or marinara sauce; and a mixed grilled seafood plate that might combine shrimp, calamari, sea scallops, monkfish, tilefish, shark and salmon. ($25 and Under: 9/24/93) Comfort Food</p>
        <p>ANGLERS &amp; WRITERS + (212) 675-0810; 420 Hudson Street, near Morton Street; $; no credit cards</p>
        <p>This enchanting, family-run American restaurant has all the warmth and charm of a house in the country. The fare is nostalgic and copious, and service could not be more accommodating. Try a humble chicken and vegetable soup or whitefish chowder, then on to the family-style dinner, with rib-sticking, heart-warming staples like lamb stew, chicken pot pie and Bourbon-glazed country ham with candied fruits. Other friendly options are roasted chicken with spinach, salad nicoise with yellowfin tuna, and gnocchi in a Bolognese sauce. (Article: 5/21/93)</p>
        <p>Summaries of reviews use the star system; others are culled from articles (indicated by +), the $25 and Under column (++) and Diner's Journal (  GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
