<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gerald Williams 'Takes It Easy,' Seriously</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE AGENTS (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDA103FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gerald Williams 'Takes It Easy,' Seriously</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES,</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman standing among dozens of clamoring fans threw two Yankee hats toward Gerald Williams from the overhang to the locker room here today. The outfielder and his longtime pal, Juan Watkins, immediately feigned a departure. The woman yelled in protest.</p>
        <p>"I thought you were giving us one apiece," Williams said, his serious look fading into a smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A woman standing among dozens of clamoring fans threw two Yankee hats toward Gerald Williams from the overhang to the locker room here today. The outfielder and his longtime pal, Juan Watkins, immediately feigned a departure. The woman yelled in protest.</p>
        <p>"I thought you were giving us one apiece," Williams said, his serious look fading into a smile.</p>
        <p>The normally low-key Williams is feeling a little more frisky than usual these days. For one thing, the 27-year-old has made the club's major league roster.</p>
        <p>For another, he is among friends. He grew up in nearby LaPlace, La., and guesses that "between 60 and 70" pals have come to see him play against the Boston Red Sox in the Superdome. A Frightening Reminder</p>
        <p>Friday night, they saw him get a single and be hit by a pitch on his right (throwing) hand in three at-bats. The hit-by-pitch represented a major scare to a guy who has finally found a home in New York after yo-yoing between the majors and minors the last two seasons.</p>
        <p>"I thought of '87, when I shattered the bone in that hand," he said. "But it's fine."</p>
        <p>Because Williams cannot be sent to the minors a third time without the Yankees losing him to free agency, this is a critical season for their relationship. Yet Williams seems to be taking the situation with almost a shrug.</p>
        <p>There's a reason for that. The ninth of 13 children raised by Dorothy Williams, he said his mother taught him some solid basics.</p>
        <p>"I don't dwell on the negative," he said. "And I take everything easy, good or bad. It helps to understand your job in being able to handle all situations. For instance: I'm having a good spring, but there are only 25 positions. Suppose 28 guys have good springs, then three people have to go. That's reality." Depth and Speed</p>
        <p>Manager Buck Showalter figures the 6-foot-2-inch, 190-pound Williams gives his club more quality depth. "He runs well and he gives us some options off the bench," the manager said.</p>
        <p>Williams, who is hitting .341 this spring with two home runs, has played in 57 games with the Yankees over the last two seasons. Asked the highlight of that experience, he said, "Just being able to compete."</p>
        <p>Then he added, rather uncharacteristically: "Well, a lot of guys have trouble getting their first hit. Mine came on the first swing, first pitch."</p>
        <p>Bragging clearly comes painfully for him. "Things change minute to minute," he said, before his major league status became official. "What's that old phrase, 'In a New York minute?' That's how quick something can happen around here.</p>
        <p>"The encouraging thing is they've told me I've had a good spring. I've done most of the things they've asked of me. Mr. Steinbrenner has told me he likes the way I go hard." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees now expect BERNIE WILLIAMS, who overcame a sore throwing shoulder, to be their starting center fielder on opening day. Manager BUCK SHOWALTER said that Williams, who had a triple and stolen base in an extended spring training game in Tampa on Saturday, would work out with the team in New York on Sunday "and if everything goes well, he will start Monday. All indications are that he is ready to go."</p>
        <p>The Yankees announced five roster moves to get down to the 25-player limit, putting pitcher PAUL GIBSON on the 15-day disabled list retroactive to March 31, and optioning infielders DAVE SILVESTRI and SAM HORN and pitchers ROYAL CLAYTON and MARK HUTTON to Class AAA Columbus.</p>
        <p>Left-hander JIM ABBOTT gave up seven hits and two runs over five and one-third innings in New York's 3-3 tie in 10 innings on Saturday with the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>Horn hit a 430-foot home run, and the Yankees, who ended the spring with a 12-15-1 record, scored the tying run in the ninth as GERALD WILLIAMS, who had reached base on an error, beat a two-out force play throw to second base.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
