<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In 'C'mon And Hear,' Songs By Berlin</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCCARTER THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, ALVIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">C'MON &amp; HEAR: IRVING BERLIN'S AMERICA (REVUE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDB153FF930A35757C0A962958260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In 'C'mon And Hear,' Songs By Berlin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIN, ALVIN</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"MY ambition is to reach the heart of the average American," Irving Berlin said. "Not the highbrow nor the lowbrow, but that vast intermediate crew which is the real soul of the country. My public is the real people."</p>
        <p>So here is an evening of Irving Berlin songs, among the most accessible on America's all-time hit parade, that leaves one utterly baffled. Go figure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"MY ambition is to reach the heart of the average American," Irving Berlin said. "Not the highbrow nor the lowbrow, but that vast intermediate crew which is the real soul of the country. My public is the real people."</p>
        <p>So here is an evening of Irving Berlin songs, among the most accessible on America's all-time hit parade, that leaves one utterly baffled. Go figure.</p>
        <p>Not that the concept -- the word seldom seemed more ominous -- of "C'mon and Hear: Irving Berlin's America" isn't handily explained in the program of the McCarter Theater, where the show is having its world premiere. A decade-by-decade affair, it starts with the immigrant dream (1900) and ends with the Depression nightmare (1935).</p>
        <p>Right away, the subtitle is misleading. Berlin, who was called "the great American minstrel," wrote songs for another three decades -- right through the Eisenhower years (remember "They Like Ike"?) and beyond the Kennedy era. Thus, a subtitle adjustment (Irving Berlin's America by half) would serve the cause of correctness, if not catchiness.</p>
        <p>But wait. The confusion is just beginning. Don't presume that the songs representing the century's first 35 years were written during that time. Unaccountably, midway in Act I -- say, 1910 -- "You're Just in Love" from "Call Me Madam" (the show with the "Ike" campaign song) pops up. "You Keep Coming Back Like a Song," which begins the first act, comes from the 1940's; "God Bless America," which ends it, brings us into 1919 but was written about 20 years later.</p>
        <p>Both are sung by Carol Woods, who mysteriously ascends in an attic full of clutter and memories when the curtain goes up. By the end of Act II, when Ms. Woods sings "Supper Time," it's clear that she has been playing the maid. (Where's the concept that avoids stereotypical casting? It wasn't Irving Berlin who wrote that "everybody ought to have a maid.")</p>
        <p>A glance at the program reveals that the maid's name is Rose Santos. Indeed, each of the 10 cast members is assigned a character, which means that between Ms. Woods's first and last numbers, a story is meant to unfold through songs, movement and scenic evocations of a ship's mast, the Lower East Side, a sweatshop, the trenches of war, a Park Avenue penthouse and a Wall Street skyscraper.  No sooner does Ms. Woods remove the sheets from a piano, a trunk and some chairs than the rest of the cast stumbles in, singing about freedom.</p>
        <p>It seems that Molly McGuire (Laurie Beechman) is in love with Nathan Singer (James Hindman) but somehow winds up marrying Eric Carlson (John Hickok). Which is not to ignore Sophie Stendhal (Mary Testa), who marries Nathan, and Anna Schiller (Karyn Quackenbush), who had been paired with Eric.</p>
        <p>Then there's Ida Mae Lewis (Stephanie Pope), who is being wooed by Gino da Vinci (Ted L. Levy), Percy Ishmael (Alton Fitzgerald White) and Bruno Marcus (Rodney Scott Hudson). And that ought to add up to 10, counting Rose. All this futile plot finagling spanning 35 years, and that includes a suicide, interferes with the songs instead of drawing inspiration from them.</p>
        <p>It is pointless to sum up or sort out a jumble that, at best, offers a tenuous clue as to why one song or another is being sung. Berlin's simple melodies can barely sift through a contextual strain and bogus reference points. The result has all the disadvantages of a so-called concept show, misconceived by George Faison and David Bishop, with none of the advantages of a staged concert.</p>
        <p>The songs, more than 50 out of a possible 1,000 or so, are stretched and squeezed into unaccommodating contexts or altered in tempo and style. Notable alterations include "Blue Skies" as a soaring immigrant anthem; a slow-starting "Alexander's Ragtime Band," Berlin's first hit -- it has the lyric that gives the show its title -- and a slow-burning "Puttin' On the Ritz."</p>
        <p>Mr. White, who can sustain a note as if breathing were an optional activity, does a stomping, insistent "This Is the Army, Mr. Jones." And Mr. Levy taps a cappella, fabulously.</p>
        <p>For one miscalculation, note the torchy rendition by Ms. Beechman and Ms. Testa of "You Can Have Him" (from "Miss Liberty," circa 1949), a paean to women as doormats.</p>
        <p>Ms. Woods and Ms. Beechman, both known for their capacity to tear up a theater with a blast of sound, are as adept at summoning enormous reserves of restraint and subtlety. Ms. Woods's gospel-tinged "God Bless America" has a comforting grace; it's her honky-tonk "I Left My Door Open and My Daddy Walked Out" that raises the rafters.</p>
        <p>In duet with the impressive Mr. Hindman, Ms. Beechman affectingly sings "Be Careful, It's My Heart" and "Always" and pours feeling into a limpidly phrased "What'll I Do?" Replicating a Judy Garland image on a stool is needless.</p>
        <p>Ms. Pope delivers a velvety "Shaking the Blues Away," and Ms. Testa, decked out in red, white and blue, gamely enlists the audience in a sing-along with "For Your Country and My Country." All through, one hears singing, but there's no show there.</p>
        <p>"C'mon and Hear: Irving Berlin's America," produced by the McCarter Theater Center for the Performing Arts, 91 University Place in Princeton. Remaining performances are today at 2 P.M., Wednesday through Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 and 7:30 P.M. Box office: (609) 683-8000.  THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
