<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Movies</title>
    <meta content="1023critic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/23/arts/television/23tv-movies.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1711973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S CHOICE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DE103FF930A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Movies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Movies on TV</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIRTH (2004)  Saturday at 9 p.m. and Saturday/Early Sunday at 4 a.m. on Starz.  Anna (Nicole Kidman, right) is understandably upset when a 10-year-old boy shows up at her elegant Manhattan apartment building to announce that he is the reincarnation of her dead husband. Of course she doesn't believe the child (the surrealistically mature Cameron Bright), at first. But eventually she is convinced, and this plays havoc with her life, which includes a forthcoming glamorous wedding on the beach. If David Lynch had directed this disturbing film, it might have had sex scenes. As it is, directed by Jonathan Glazer, the bathtub encounters are creepy enough. The stirring score is by the French composer Alexandre Desplat.</p>
        <p>SABOTEUR (1942)  Saturday at 10:30 p.m. on TCM.  Alfred Hitchcock was in fine form in this wartime (and therefore intensely patriotic) black-and-white thriller. It begins with a fatal incident involving a fire extinguisher at an aircraft factory, and Barry Kane (Robert Cummings), a young employee, is wrongly accused. With ''Fugitive''-like purpose, Barry goes on a cross-country search for the man who really did it, teams up with a famous model (Priscilla Lane, left, with Cummings) and finds a nest of very un-American upper-crust spies. Hitchcock serves up several scenes that could have been the big finale: a life-threatening announcement at a black-tie party in a New York mansion, a shootout at a movie theater and a dizzying chase that ends (''The sleeve! The sleeve!'') atop the Statue of Liberty, on the little balcony surrounding the torch.</p>
        <p>TRAVELLER (1997)  Saturday at 11:35 p.m. on Channel 7.  Bokky (Bill Paxton, right) and his new apprentice (Mark Wahlberg) are part of a group of happy-go-lucky down-home grifters, the guys who come to your door offering to repave your driveway or paint your house for half the going price. Then, just after they've driven away with your cash, you learn that they did a deliberately lousy job. Bokky's mistake is falling in love with a pretty bartender (a forceful Julianna Margulies) who says she needs $30,000 or so for a loved one's surgery. He runs into a little trouble when he decides to play with the big kids for the biggest score of his life. Jack N. Green directed.</p>
        <p>BEFORE NIGHT FALLS (2000)  Sunday at 10 p.m. and Monday at 6 a.m. on IFC.  Whether he is in pre-Castro Cuba or 1980's New York, the poet and novelist Reinaldo Arenas (Javier Bardem, far left, with Johnny Depp as a well-dressed friend) had a ferocious passion for life -- and for sex. Julian Schnabel directed this haunting film, based on Arenas's memoir about his life as an artist and as a gay man. In his first American film, Mr. Bardem gives an unforgettable performance, which ends with his character's 1990 suicide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BIRTH (2004)  Saturday at 9 p.m. and Saturday/Early Sunday at 4 a.m. on Starz.  Anna (Nicole Kidman, right) is understandably upset when a 10-year-old boy shows up at her elegant Manhattan apartment building to announce that he is the reincarnation of her dead husband. Of course she doesn't believe the child (the surrealistically mature Cameron Bright), at first. But eventually she is convinced, and this plays havoc with her life, which includes a forthcoming glamorous wedding on the beach. If David Lynch had directed this disturbing film, it might have had sex scenes. As it is, directed by Jonathan Glazer, the bathtub encounters are creepy enough. The stirring score is by the French composer Alexandre Desplat.</p>
        <p>SABOTEUR (1942)  Saturday at 10:30 p.m. on TCM.  Alfred Hitchcock was in fine form in this wartime (and therefore intensely patriotic) black-and-white thriller. It begins with a fatal incident involving a fire extinguisher at an aircraft factory, and Barry Kane (Robert Cummings), a young employee, is wrongly accused. With ''Fugitive''-like purpose, Barry goes on a cross-country search for the man who really did it, teams up with a famous model (Priscilla Lane, left, with Cummings) and finds a nest of very un-American upper-crust spies. Hitchcock serves up several scenes that could have been the big finale: a life-threatening announcement at a black-tie party in a New York mansion, a shootout at a movie theater and a dizzying chase that ends (''The sleeve! The sleeve!'') atop the Statue of Liberty, on the little balcony surrounding the torch.</p>
        <p>TRAVELLER (1997)  Saturday at 11:35 p.m. on Channel 7.  Bokky (Bill Paxton, right) and his new apprentice (Mark Wahlberg) are part of a group of happy-go-lucky down-home grifters, the guys who come to your door offering to repave your driveway or paint your house for half the going price. Then, just after they've driven away with your cash, you learn that they did a deliberately lousy job. Bokky's mistake is falling in love with a pretty bartender (a forceful Julianna Margulies) who says she needs $30,000 or so for a loved one's surgery. He runs into a little trouble when he decides to play with the big kids for the biggest score of his life. Jack N. Green directed.</p>
        <p>BEFORE NIGHT FALLS (2000)  Sunday at 10 p.m. and Monday at 6 a.m. on IFC.  Whether he is in pre-Castro Cuba or 1980's New York, the poet and novelist Reinaldo Arenas (Javier Bardem, far left, with Johnny Depp as a well-dressed friend) had a ferocious passion for life -- and for sex. Julian Schnabel directed this haunting film, based on Arenas's memoir about his life as an artist and as a gay man. In his first American film, Mr. Bardem gives an unforgettable performance, which ends with his character's 1990 suicide.  CRITIC'S CHOICE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
