<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ISRAEL BROADENING SEARCHES OF ARABS</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARABS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARTRAND, SABRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arabs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D81E3EF936A35751C1A966958260" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ISRAEL BROADENING SEARCHES OF ARABS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRA CHARTRAND, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARTRAND, SABRA</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Dec. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to growing fear over a rash of Palestinian knife attacks on Jews, the police broadened surveillance of Arab workers in Israel today with spot checks, searches and a new network of roadblocks along the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Israeli news organizations said that officials of the Defense and Justice ministries were also considering simplifying the procedures for deporting Palestinians who are believed to have incited violence against Israelis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to growing fear over a rash of Palestinian knife attacks on Jews, the police broadened surveillance of Arab workers in Israel today with spot checks, searches and a new network of roadblocks along the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Israeli news organizations said that officials of the Defense and Justice ministries were also considering simplifying the procedures for deporting Palestinians who are believed to have incited violence against Israelis.</p>
        <p>Some rightist politicians and security officials argue that the procedures, which allow Arabs facing deportation to appeal to the Supreme Court, are too long and cumbersome.  61 Deported in 3 Years</p>
        <p>A Defense Ministry spokesman declined to confirm that such a proposal was being considered, but said that Defense Minister Moshe Arens supported the use of deportations. Israel has deported 61 Palestinians since the Palestinian uprising began nearly three years ago. The last five expulsions were carried out in August 1989.</p>
        <p>Justice Minister Dan Meridor said tonight, "Not only is there nothing to prevent deportations, but when there is no alternative, we will use expulsions as a means against inciters."</p>
        <p>The United States and the United Nations have condemned the expulsions as a violation of the Fourth Geneva Convention. Israel has signed the Convention, but argues that the treaty refers to mass deportations rather than expulsions of individuals.</p>
        <p>On Monday night, Mr. Arens said he had not ruled out the possibility of blocking travel from the West Bank and Gaza Strip if Palestinian violence in Israel continued. The territories were shut off by the army for several days after the killing on Oct. 8 of at least 17 Palestinians at Al Aksa Mosque by the Israeli authorities.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Arens said Israeli officials knew most Palestinians in the territories "do not participate in violence at all, and we have to think about their ability to earn a living."  Anxiety in the Heartland</p>
        <p>More than 20 Israelis have been stabbed over the last two months. Five of the victims died of their wounds and seven Arab attackers were killed.</p>
        <p>Until this fall, anxiety about knife attacks had been limited largely to Jews in the occupied territories and along the boundaries between Arab and Jewish sections of Jerusalem. But recent stabbings have also frightened Israelis in the heart of the country, in Tel Aviv, the Galilee and the southern coast. Requests for gun permits have soared, and thousands of Jews have begun carrying pistols, knives and mace.</p>
        <p>The police and some of the Arabs captured after the stabbings said the attacks were meant to avenge the killings of the Arabs at Al Aksa Mosque. But the police said the attacks were also incited by two Muslim fundamentalist groups active in the occupied territories -- Hamas, the Arabic acronym for the Islamic Resistance Movement, and the Islamic Holy War.</p>
        <p>As the Arab uprising in the territories approaches the end of its third year, Palestinians are increasingly frustrated by its failure to produce concrete achievements. About 762 Palestinians have been killed by Israeli soldiers since the uprising began on Dec. 9, 1987, but there has been no movement towards a political solution to the Palestinian problem.  Call for Lethal Weapons</p>
        <p>Representatives of the two Muslim fundamentalist groups have expressed anger that stone-throwing and mass demonstrations have brought them few tangible gains. Both of the groups recently urged supporters to turn to more lethal weapons.</p>
        <p>In a leaflet issued in its name on Nov. 2, Islamic Holy War said it was urging "an escalation of stabbings, and calls on all its operatives to train for stabbing operations, to continue our revolution and terrify the enemy."</p>
        <p>The stabbings have led the police to impose tight restrictions on about 110,000 West Bank and Gaza Arabs who work in Israel.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the police, Ruth Shlesinger, said a new network of mobile roadblocks had been set up along Israel's 1967 border with the West Bank. Under new orders, there will be at least one officer at each roadblock. Metal detectors will be used to hunt for knives, she said, and Palestinians can be bodily searched along with their cars and posessions.</p>
        <p>The police are also stepping up spot checks of Palestinans. In Petach Tikva, four West Bank Arabs were arrested when three knives were found in the trunk of their car. The police did not say whether they had proof that the knives were to be used as weapons.</p>
        <p>The Police Ministry announced that beginning today, every policeman will be required to carry a pistol or Uzi submachine gun at all times. The ministry is also considering equipping public bus drivers with guns.</p>
        <p>Public fear seemed to culminate on Sunday, when three Arabs riding a el Aviv bus stabbed four Israeli passengers. One of the victims, a yeshiva student, died of his wounds.</p>
        <p>The police said that more Israelis might have been stabbed if the driver and a passing policeman had not been armed.</p>
        <p>Israelis are alarmed by the outbreak of attacks in places like Tel Aviv. In an Israel television report on Monday night, a bus driver, Salman Bassu, displayed the progression in the weapons he has carried in 17 years of work.</p>
        <p>"I always traveled with brass knuckles," he said, pulling one weapon after another out of a case. "After that I went on to a switchblade, and now I have a gun in my bag 24 hours a day."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
