<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Underground Down Under</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAVES AND CAVERNS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW SOUTH WALES (AUSTRALIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JENOLAN CAVES (AUSTRALIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Wales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DE133DF93AA25750C0A963958260" item-length="1736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Underground Down Under</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I FIRST visited Jenolan Caves, 113 miles west of Sydney, five years ago, after an advertisement I saw at my Sydney hotel announced a day tour by bus that combined them with the Blue Mountains. What I did not realize was that there were nine caves open to the public at Jenolan, and on a day trip from Sydney it is possible to visit only one. On that visit I chose Lucas Cave from the options offered on the tour, and marveled at its vast chambers adorned with stalactites and stalagmites. But curiosity about the caves I didn't see made me want to return; I finally managed to do so last August. As a cave lover who has roamed through caverns in the United States, France and Italy, I was delighted by what I found.</p>
        <p>About 300 caves are estimated to exist in the Jenolan region, all thought to be part of a vast interconnected system. Although Jenolan derives from an aboriginal word meaning "high mountain," the aborigines are not known to have explored the underground labyrinths. Each of the caves that tourists see has its own name, and the entrances to most are inside an enormous natural bridge called the Grand Arch. Others are approached through a special manmade entrance near the ticket office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I FIRST visited Jenolan Caves, 113 miles west of Sydney, five years ago, after an advertisement I saw at my Sydney hotel announced a day tour by bus that combined them with the Blue Mountains. What I did not realize was that there were nine caves open to the public at Jenolan, and on a day trip from Sydney it is possible to visit only one. On that visit I chose Lucas Cave from the options offered on the tour, and marveled at its vast chambers adorned with stalactites and stalagmites. But curiosity about the caves I didn't see made me want to return; I finally managed to do so last August. As a cave lover who has roamed through caverns in the United States, France and Italy, I was delighted by what I found.</p>
        <p>About 300 caves are estimated to exist in the Jenolan region, all thought to be part of a vast interconnected system. Although Jenolan derives from an aboriginal word meaning "high mountain," the aborigines are not known to have explored the underground labyrinths. Each of the caves that tourists see has its own name, and the entrances to most are inside an enormous natural bridge called the Grand Arch. Others are approached through a special manmade entrance near the ticket office.</p>
        <p>Caves at Jenolan first attracted attention in 1838, when an escaped convict was tracked to a hideout in one of them. Guided tours were organized shortly afterward. The most spectacular caverns -- the ones currently on view -- were discovered between 1860 and 1904. In 1866, in what now seems a far-seeing move, the New South Wales Government made the caves and the mountainous area above them a nature reserve, which today is administered by the conservation-minded Jenolan Caves Reserve Trust. The trust also oversees two other cave systems in the same region: Wombeyan Caves, south of Jenolan, and Abercrombie Caves, to the west of Jenolan. There are five show caves open at Wombeyan and three at Abercrombie.</p>
        <p>The Jenolan Caves were formed millions of years ago by an underground river that kept hollowing out passages in the region's limestone; when the water reached certain weaknesses in the stone, it sank through them to create still lower passageways. Because there are so many levels at Jenolan, each tour requires climbing steps. The journey through River Cave, which is considered especially strenuous, involves 1,298 steps. Fortunately, they are not all in one place. And though I am middle-aged and not especially athletic, I emerged from River Cave without panting.</p>
        <p>In caving parlance, the caves open to the general public are known as "show caves," because they are electrically lighted and can be visited without undue discomfort. Each tour lasts between 90 minutes and two hours. Occasionally, special Extended or Grand Tours are offered that combine parts of several caves on one visit. A schedule listing the times of the tours available each day is posted beside the ticket office. In addition, six other caverns can be explored by special arrangement as "adventure" or "wild" caves. Groups view them by means of battery lights and are required to wear coveralls and helmets. Several of these caves are muddy and involve crawling and slithering. Whether one prefers show caves or wild ones depends, in part, upon whether one considers caving an esthetic or an athletic experience. I stuck to the show caves and was richly rewarded.</p>
        <p>My overnight visit to Jenolan this summer began with a tour of Imperial Cave, so named because it was proclaimed the "grandest of the lot" at its discovery in 1879. Imperial is especially suitable for the infirm because its paths have the least number of stairs. Narrow passageways give way to high arched chambers adorned with cascades of stone formations. There are many shawls, fluted columns and statue-like stalagmites, most of them milky-white. At one point, small stalagmites stretch away beneath a ledge like the walls and towers of a city seen from a distance. The cave also abounds with helictites, odd, delicate and intricately twisted formations that variously recall seaweed, strings, loops and elaborate but indecipherable calligraphic doodlings. Near the end of the 90-minute tour, steps lead to an underground stream. And a few stalactites dangle over the water like the boughs of a weeping willow tree.</p>
        <p>The stately Imperial Cave is very different from the caves I saw on a guided Grand Tour, which in slightly more than two hours combined Orient Cave with parts of River Cave and Lucas Cave. Although whiteness dominates the Imperial, Orient Cave glows with a multitude of oranges, browns and pinks, hues caused by the presence of iron in the formations. It is easy to understand why turn-of-the-century explorers, awed by its splendor, gave sections of the cave such exotic names as Persian Chamber and Egyptian Chamber.</p>
        <p>Orient Cave has wall niches resembling coffers of gems. But what make it extraordinary are its large domed rooms crowded with mountainous stalagmites, chandeliers of stalactites and jumbles of helictites as tangled as birds' nests. There are also stone spires, shawls, banners, canopies and a shining snowlike deposit of dogtooth spar crystals. The sheer array of formations may remind American caving enthusiasts of Virginia's comparably adorned Luray Caverns.</p>
        <p>Guides at Orient and other Jenolan caves occasionally point out shapes in the stone that they think resemble everything from emus and kangaroos to eyeglasses and a map of Australia. Some scientific purists disdain such fantasizing, and in several American and French caves I have felt that the guides were insufferably whimsical, but the right dose of poetic imagery given by the Jenolan guides can help focus dazzled eyes on the profusion of details.</p>
        <p>A long flight of stairs descends precipitously from Orient into River Cave. Among that cave's attractions are a whole room of stone shawls and a pure-white stalagmite that has been appropriately named the Minaret. At the cave's lowest level, a lagoon of deep blue water reflects the rocky ceiling like an eternally unclouded mirror. The Grand Tour ended after passing through some of the stalactite-decorated rooms of Lucas Cave, named after John Lucas, an early Australian political leader who championed conservation. They were as impressive as I had found them on my first visit five years before.</p>
        <p>I did this Grand Tour the morning after I arrived at Jenolan, having stayed overnight at Caves House, a rambling inn only a few minutes' walk from the Grand Arch. The previous afternoon, after checking in, I visited Imperial Cave. To my surprise, when I re-entered Caves House late in the afternoon after my tour, I found myself in the midst of Christmas. Because Dec. 25 in the antipodes comes during the hot summer, some Australians long for a traditional winter holiday. Many inns, hotels, restaurants and resorts try to satisfy this yearning with Christmas-like celebrations in July or August.</p>
        <p>Since the temperature outdoors was in the high 50's (the caves themselves are only a few degrees cooler), no New Yorker could think the place wintry. Nevertheless, at the inn, built in 1889 in a mock-Tudor style, fireplaces roared, a Christmas tree dominated the parlor and I feasted on roast turkey in the high-celinged dining room. At 5 P.M. guests were welcomed at a party featuring cheese and mulled wine, and Santa Claus made an entrance, tossing candy to children.</p>
        <p>Next, as part of the holiday treats, came a special evening tour of sections of Imperial, River and Lucas Caves, during which the commentary focused specifically upon the ways in which water had shaped the caverns. I had seen some of these cave rooms that afternoon and would see others the next morning. Yet what made this particular tour unusual was the way in which the guide offered detailed, yet never formidably erudite, commentaries on the ways in which water affects cave geology. Even during festivities, the emphasis at Jenolan is always on caves.</p>
        <p>The men and women who serve as guides are genial as well as informative. Let staff members realize how much you love -- really love -- caves, and you may find yourself involved in ardent conversations with like-minded aficionados. John Callaghan, a deputy interpretation manager, described a vacation in America that began with what he termed "the usual visit to Disneyland," and then went on to Carlsbad Caverns in New Mexico, Mammoth Cave and other Kentucky caverns and some of the caves of Virginia. A few guides at Jenolan have had formal academic training in geology. But most, I learned, are there because they were bowled over by the beauty of the place. An underground guide  Getting There</p>
        <p>Several Sydney sightseeing bus companies, including Australian Pacific Tours, A.A.T. Kings and Great Sights South Pacific, offer daily tours with basically identical schedules and rates to the Blue Mountains and Jenolan Caves. In addition to going on day trips from Sydney, which leave at 8:45 A.M. and return in the early evening, reaching the caves at lunchtime, visitors also have the option, at a higher price, of staying overnight at Caves House and taking another bus back to town the next day. The sightseeing companies that schedule trips to Jenolan have offices conveniently located next to one another on Circular Quay.</p>
        <p>Typical rates are those of Australian Pacific Tours, telephone (61 2) 252-2988, fax (61 2) 247-2052. A day round trip (cave admission included) is $52.85, calculated at 1.34 Australian dollars to the United States dollar. Overnight stays, per person, are $153 with private bath, $131 with shared bath.</p>
        <p>The caves, of course, can also be reached by motorists in their own cars. A word of caution, though: anyone made queasy by heights or unused to driving on the left-hand side of the road may find the journey on the narrow mountainside road to and from Jenolan a hair-raising as well as a breathtaking experience. Accommodations</p>
        <p>Caves House offers the independent traveler various types of accommodation. With its rooms filled with comfortable old-fashioned-looking furniture, it reminded me of a New England country inn. Rates are by the room, ranging from $56.50 nightly with shared bath to $92 with private bath.</p>
        <p>A guest house near the main inn building offers rooms with bath at $71 nightly and, with shared bath, at $28 a night. Reservations: (61 63) 59-3304, fax (61 63) 59-3227.  JACK ANDERSON is a dance critic for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JACK ANDERSON is a dance critic for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
