<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT, US WORRY?</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TEXAS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARDS, ANN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEICKER, LOWELL P JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDUM, TODD S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D91339F93AA25750C0A963958260" item-length="5504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT, US WORRY?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDUM, TODD S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their names -- Cuomo, Richards and Weicker -- were among the best-known in government. Now they're private citizens again. On a recent Saturday morning, they arrived at The New York Times without their customary entourages. Weicker came with his wife, Richards with an aide and Cuomo alone. They remain closely informed and fiercely opinionated.</p>
        <p>In a two-hour conversation, Democrats Mario M. Cuomo and Ann W. Richards and Republican-turned-Independent Lowell P. Weicker Jr. looked back at the November election and looked forward to what the results are likely to mean for the country. They offered some guesses about the 1996 election; they appraised the obligations of ex-officeholders; and most of all, they talked about the angry middle class.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their names -- Cuomo, Richards and Weicker -- were among the best-known in government. Now they're private citizens again. On a recent Saturday morning, they arrived at The New York Times without their customary entourages. Weicker came with his wife, Richards with an aide and Cuomo alone. They remain closely informed and fiercely opinionated.</p>
        <p>In a two-hour conversation, Democrats Mario M. Cuomo and Ann W. Richards and Republican-turned-Independent Lowell P. Weicker Jr. looked back at the November election and looked forward to what the results are likely to mean for the country. They offered some guesses about the 1996 election; they appraised the obligations of ex-officeholders; and most of all, they talked about the angry middle class.</p>
        <p>After 12 years as Governor of New York, Mario Cuomo has become a partner in the Manhattan law firm Willkie Farr &amp; Gallagher and is writing a book of his political observations to be published by Simon &amp; Schuster in October. Ann Richards, who spent four years as Governor and eight years as Treasurer of Texas, is now a senior adviser in the Austin office of the Washington-based law firm of Verner, Liipfert, Bernhard, McPherson &amp; Hand. Lowell Weicker, a three-term Senator from Connecticut and then independent Governor, is chairman of Dresing-Lierman-Weicker, a health care company in Bethesda, Md.</p>
        <p>The following are edited excerpts of the discussion. It was moderated by Todd S. Purdum, a White House correspondent for The New York Times who covered the Cuomo campaign last fall. THE ELECTION, RECONSIDERED Todd Purdum: Was it a good thing the Republicans won? Ann Richards: I think so.  Purdum: Why?</p>
        <p>Richards: I think that any system, whether it is a social system, a government system, sociological, economic system that stays entrenched has a tendency to be defensive about itself. Government itself must change to be able to deal with the changing problems. I feel very strongly that change is good because it stirs up the system. Mario Cuomo: I think it's very good. The people who won in 1994 now have to come forward with purported solutions. I've always believed that on the economy -- the first of the two problems which are the economy and cultural corrosion -- you have to do a lot more with infrastructure, a lot more with high tech, a lot more investing. We couldn't convince people to do that.</p>
        <p>The Republicans now have a different proposal: "We'll give you a gains tax cut, a middle-class tax cut that will take care of the economy." I think that's a lot of baloney and that will very, very quickly become clear. So they have their shot. They give you a middle-class tax cut. They run into trouble with the deficit. It does nothing to improve your economy substantially and people come to understand that the Democrats were right. Clinton was right. You have to invest.</p>
        <p>On cultural corrosion, I have said and a lot of other people have said, "Well, you can't just punish the kid for having a baby." Even if she doesn't have the second baby, you haven't solved the problem. They need other avenues to dignity. You need more than punishment. Of course they must develop a sense of responsibility, but you also have to give them a chance to have a job, the chance to get educated, the chance to fulfill themselves. That means you have to do a lot of positive things.</p>
        <p>So far the Contract With America is purely negative. Let's forget that it's punitive. To the extent that it insists on responsibility, I'd agree with it, but then it stops there. It doesn't create any opportunity. I think that will become clear, too. They don't go far enough.</p>
        <p>So I think the change is good, because in the end I think it vindicates what a lot of us have been saying. Look, you should be tougher, you should make stricter rules. We're trying to do that in our state, but that is not enough.</p>
        <p>In the end to get rid of the violence, there is no point in sending people away to jail for longer terms. I built more prison cells than any governor in history; all the governors together didn't build as many as I did. Of course, you have to do that. It's true. . . .  Richards: I built more than you did.</p>
        <p>Cuomo:  [ Grinning ]  You didn't need them; you kept killing them. No, in my state, I built more than all the governors before me, but that's not enough. Being tough is not enough to stop crime. You have to do something about the drug problem and being tough is not going to stop the drug problem. This has been our thesis; we haven't been able to prove it.</p>
        <p>Now you give them their day. They give you money for more prisons. They do their thing, which falls short of what you said was needed and it will become apparent that they will not solve the problem, not by multiplying the death penalty, not by increasing the number of jail cells. So giving them their day allows you to make your case by their failure. Lowell Weicker: I'm glad  [ the Republicans won ]  because to my way of thinking this plays out the great free-lunch theory that was started by Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Now talk about change. When I was a young man, joining the Republican Party, Democrats were spendthrifts, horrible as to how they viewed the government, the spending of monies. If anybody made the Democrats look like minor leaguers when it came to fiscal responsibility it was Ronald Reagan. The free lunch theory of government was put into action by President Reagan, continued by President Bush, but the reason why nobody had to pay a price was moderate Republicans, when the Republicans had a majority in the Senate -- and I was a part of that group -- managed to forestall the worst effects of the Reagan economics program. And the governors of the states stepped into the breach to again forestall the worst of the consequences.</p>
        <p>Now the public having been given a small taste of the free lunch, from two Republican executives, all of a sudden felt, let's have more of this, not knowing that this time there was no political safety net to forestall the consequences of the free lunch. No moderates control the Republican Party within the United States Senate. And the governors themselves are under enormous pressure to accede.</p>
        <p>The fact is that we're not doing very well because the Federal Government doesn't have any money. It's out of money. Therefore, it can't choose the most sensible options toward the resolution of any problem. And how is that going to get improved by what is being presented in terms of free-lunch economics? Now, not only will there be the thrill of the free lunch, but there will be the disappointment of what happens when you've eaten this free lunch and you have nothing to show for it.</p>
        <p>The American people have never been made to suffer the consequences of Reagan economics, of Bush economics. So now it's going to happen.  Cuomo: Lowell made a very, very good point that you have to stay with. When Reagan did this, the people didn't notice, why? Because the states raised their real property taxes, if they had them; they raised their sales taxes. While he was cutting the income tax, the progressive tax, in Washington, all the states, most of them, were raising their local taxes to pick up the tab.</p>
        <p>Now you can't do it anymore at the local level, because the pressure has mounted against you. They won't do it; they want to cut their taxes. You can't raise yours. There is going to be the inevitable lack of services, lack of roads and bridges work, lack of criminal-justice services and lack in social services. And that will manifest itself.  Richards: I do not wish ill will to the Republicans at the expense of hard times for the American public. I think it's a hard price to pay, but the truth is that the chickens are coming home to roost. And those chickens roosting are going to be felt in a lot of ways across this society, not just by the poor but by all of us. WHAT THE VOTE MEANT Purdum: By one analysis, the cumulative aggregate margin of victory that changed the control of Congress was about 18,000 votes. If you take the 14 closest races in which Republicans won, I am told that the total would add up to roughly a few thousand votes. So if you look at it that way, what was the election about?  Richards: I think that the election itself was only the tip of what is a much larger sociological and economic change. I think this election was a manifestation of the serious anxiety in the population. Mario and I have talked about this before, but I think if the Republicans had been in power, you would have seen a similar occurrence, which was that the mood was get rid of what you've got and get something else just in case it might make me, the voter, feel better.</p>
        <p>And the fact that the Democrats were in power, that they had control of Congress for a long time, that they had the Speaker, the President, many of the governors. That it was a real expression on their part of a desire for change.</p>
        <p>I think that the social programs of this country got set 60 years ago in the 1930's. My criticism of the Democrats is that we have tinkered and shaved and moved things around to the margins of the basic programs that were established a very long time ago. We've not seen any really dramatic alteration of those programs.</p>
        <p>And so what's happening in the United States is that no one is addressing the fact that you can no longer maintain a middle-class existence by simply being willing to work hard. The old truisms that were established -- that all of us accepted, Number 1, if you're willing to work, there will be a job for you, is no longer true. And Number 2, that a public school education is sufficient to maintain a middle-class existence.</p>
        <p>Now that neither of those is true, it's causing enormous unease among people. They see massive layoffs in a readjusting society. Even the people equipped to work within the com puter society are all afraid that their skills are going to be insufficient.</p>
        <p>So what happens to the Americans out there who are told that they must provide for their family? They look around them and there is no security. There's no security. I think that's what you saw evidenced in a big way in the last election. Weicker: First of all, to me the election was a continuation of an unwillingness of the American people to run their government.</p>
        <p>Now the essence of our whole system is that the people are the engine. They've given up that power and they've done it increasingly election after election after election. I think we all recognize whether -- it wouldn't make a difference whether it was Republicans or Democrats, you've got government by minority right now in this nation, overwhelmingly, at not only the Federal level but state and local, even more so.  Purdum: You mean by that the loudest, angriest, whiniest part? Weicker: I'm saying to you, when 38 percent of the people vote, put at its broadest terms, I suspect that means that probably 20 percent is the majority and that sure is not a majority when compared to the entire voting universe out there. Everybody loves to blame the Republicans and the Democrats, Washington, the capital of Texas, Albany, Hartford, whatever. Everybody likes to point the finger as if the business of government had nothing to do with them. And that in itself is an attitude that ought to be kicked in the butt.</p>
        <p>The reason why we have what we have, good and bad, is because the American people make things happen or they don't happen. We have moved from a politics of accountability to a politics of re-electibility.  So that is all encompassing as to how the candidates and officials present themselves.</p>
        <p>Both parties, and the candidates of both parties on any difficult issue try to achieve the softest possible landing. And the harshness of reality doesn't permit you a soft landing on any of these tough issues. So deficits do not get resolved. Cities don't get resolved. Racial isolation doesn't get resolved. These are tough issues. You can't soft land them, but everybody knows that if you try to take a hard position on it, you don't get elected. That's everything. Unfortunately for the greatness of the United States, we're going to come to the realization it isn't everything. Cuomo: You asked what happened in the election. Nobody knows. And what difference does it make? Is it an instruction to the American people, this tiny difference of 6 percent in a total vote of 38 percent? Is it an instruction to the politicians?</p>
        <p>The Republicans try to make you believe that they voted for the Contract With America. Nobody knew what the Contract With America was, until a couple of weeks before when they started describing it.</p>
        <p>If you asked anybody on Election Day in New York State, "Where's Cuomo on the Contract With America?"  [ they'd have said ]  "Mario's a good guy; he doesn't make contracts. Whatever you said about Cuomo, he's honest. He never made a real contract. No, not that kind of contract, a Gingrich. Who's Gingrich? What's Gingrich? Is that a thing or is it a person?"</p>
        <p>So this notion that the people went to the polls in Texas and in New York and in other places and said here's how we feel on the economy -- it wasn't like that, I don't believe, and I don't think it makes any difference.</p>
        <p>I showed my mother Fortune magazine once. She saw Lee Iacocca's face on the cover and she asked me, in Italian, who he was and I said who he was. She said, "Ah, Italiano" and I said, "Yes, he is." And I said, "He's complaining because he makes $16 million, and he thinks he should make 25." She said, "What does he do?" I said, "He makes cars." She said in Italian, "What's the matter, you can't make a car?"</p>
        <p>The notion that you can get rich and powerful -- that's why they came here. Now that group is growing. The group on the bottom is also growing, unfortunately. And they've dropped out. They're not even voting against anybody. They've given up on it. They've created their own culture in a lot of places.</p>
        <p>It's that group in the middle that shifts and you shift just a small percentage of them -- 7 points is a landslide -- right, the country goes right. And we all react to it as though everybody did it.</p>
        <p>I think the important thing is, what is it -- quite apart from the vote -- that is creating this heavy sense of negativism, disconcertment, if you will, anger, willingness to scapegoat? Anybody who goes to people's houses and talks in living rooms and listens at the dining room table, knows that there's a lot of anger, a lot of confusion and therefore people want change, something better.</p>
        <p>WHY AMERICA IS SO ANGRY Cuomo: What is the basic mood? Here's what I believe it is. The biggest event in my lifetime was the Second World War and we have never been able to recreate it. Some people say thank God, but there's something we lose by not recreating what happened in the Second World War.</p>
        <p>The Second World War was the last time that this country believed in anything profoundly, any great single cause. What was it? They were evil; we were good. That was Tojo, that was that S.O.B. Hitler, that was Mussolini, that bum. They struck at us in the middle of the night, those sneaks. We are good, they are bad. Let's all get together, we said, and we creamed them. We started from way behind. We found strength in this common commitment, this commonality, community, family, the idea of coming together was best served in my lifetime in the Second World War.</p>
        <p>You never had a war quite like it. In the beginning of Iraq, you thought you did and a lot of people got excited. Hot dog, we've got another Hitler -- Saddam Hussein. But then after a while, everybody got confused. Was it the oil? What the hell am I fighting for the Emir for? Who is the Emir? What is an Emir? What's Kuwait? What did they do for me? Why is my son going? So that lost its luster as a cause. We haven't had another great cause.</p>
        <p>We've not had a great hero or heroine since Martin Luther King, Jr. and John Kennedy. And they were taken down by fate. "Where have you gone, Joe DiMaggio?" It was perfect -- Paul Simon from Queens summed it all up. Where are our heroes, great causes? No cause. No hero. No heroine. Nothing big to believe in. Nothing to wrap your arms around.</p>
        <p>Now, specifically two other things happened. Your economy after the Second World War was incredible to the economists, because they predicted depressions, no markets, nine million coming out of the service. How are you going to put them to work? Japan, Europe down. Whom are you going to sell to? They figured out the G.I. Bill of Rights. Eisenhower started building roads. He started manufacturing, the growth of technology that you got from the war. You brought Japan to life. You brought Europe back to life. They started buying from you. You became the maker, the seller, the broker, the creditor. You ran the joint until the 70's.</p>
        <p>In the 70's something changed very dramatically. When I was growing up, when you said "Made in Japan," it meant you drop it on the floor it breaks. In the 1970's when you said, "Made in Japan," it meant when you close the car door, it sounded like a bank vault door. Japan was back, making things better than you were. They started taking your markets away.</p>
        <p>You used to be a creditor; now you're a debtor. Five and half trillion bucks Federal debt. You used to snap your fingers and say interest rates. Now they tell you to go to hell. You've lost your dominance as some of us were trying to say in 1984. We've got debt mounting. We're falling behind. It's going to catch us.</p>
        <p>It did finally in '88, '89. People out of work now, they're beginning to understand. That factory worker said, "Jesus, I thought I could work for the rest of my life." I married Matilda while I was in school in the 50's. My father thought I was crazy. I said: "Pa, don't worry about it. If I get out of school, I'll be able to work three jobs." And I did. There was all the work in the world. That was the 50's. You knew that if you kept your health and you wanted to work and you worked like hell, you could outwork the other guy and do very well.</p>
        <p>That's all changed. We finally understand that our futures are uncertain in this global economy and people are nervous about it and they don't see you doing anything about it. The guys at the top don't care because the investors are doing very well. The guys at the bottom have given up. They're on drugs. They're in trouble. But the guy and the gal in the middle -- the $30,000-a-year factory worker -- are very nervous.</p>
        <p>That's what this is all about: "If I can make a living, I don't give a damn about your social problems. I'll move away from them. I'll move into a house; I'll build a big wall. I'll have security guards, my own swimming pool. The heck with all the trouble. My kids are safe. I'll send them to a very special school. I'll insulate them from all the pain." And you can do it.</p>
        <p>But the economy is weak and so people don't have that option and now they confront all the following which happened when I was Governor: crack, AIDS, homelessness, babies making babies, the manifest instability of families, children killing children with semiautomatic weapons. That affected everybody. You can't move away from that. You see it every night. It gets to your son. He can be a drug addict. You put this all altogether and the people are confused, angry.</p>
        <p>Of course they tear down whatever power is in place. If it were Republicans, Ann's right, they would have knocked off the Republicans. This is Clinton, this is Mitchell, this is Foley. We don't know if they did it or didn't do it. "All we know is you're in charge. Hey, Mario, you've been there 12 years. Don't give us your long answers. You can talk about anything, but we don't hear it. We like you; we think you're honest and all that, but please go get yourself a job, will you, because maybe we need somebody who will chop off their heads."  THE STATE OF THE MIDDLE CLASS Weicker: Dear friends, I've got news for you. The middle class has done very well in this country, extraordinarily well, and this Balkanization of us as a people into whatever our economics are or race or opportunities or our problems, I think very ill-suits the vision that is the United States of America. Why, for example when we refer to poor people in this country do we say "welfare"?</p>
        <p>How about all the welfare, if you want to call it that -- I don't chose to call it that, I prefer assistance -- to all Americans? What about everything that the middle class gets? What was the biggest part of our budget in the state of Connecticut? It was Medicaid driven by nursing homes for middle-income Connecticut, putting mom and dad at the poverty level just to get them in a nursing home -- 10 percent of the budget in the state of Connecticut. You call that welfare? I think so. I had no problems with it, but I think if we all look at what assistance we've received from our Government, whether it's me and the G.I. Bill or whether it's nursing homes or whether it's Head Start.</p>
        <p>I think the sooner we understand that whatever our opportunity or our problem, we have all been there at one time or another asking for assistance and the more we feel that somebody's entitled to something special or that the only way you're going to get that is to walk over the back of the other individual, the more we debase America. I'm sorry but I think that the America we know is gone. The fact is that for all the criticisms of public education and welfare and all the rest of these programs, we're still the best in the world.</p>
        <p>What we're doing now is dismantling the essence of our greatness whether it's education or the creating of economic opportunity or the fact that we have compassion for segments of the society that no other nation of the world has ever had.</p>
        <p>Why the hell are we tearing ourselves apart? That's different from saying we can't do better. We can, but right now the American people, as I've said before, just better understand that the problem doesn't reside with a few politicians. It resides with them -- the fact that they've got to go ahead and participate. They've got to demand accountability, which could very well be a painful process. And they're going to have to put money up front in order to make sure that the problems don't compound downstream. Cuomo: When Lowell starts talking about what we've done with the middle class, I get a stomachache, because I tried a couple of times going to Long Island, saying what you're talking about, the middle class. You guys have one of the best university systems in the world. It doesn't cost you diddly -- no tuition increase for my first seven years. You have one of the best highway systems in the world. Who uses it? You have the largest park system in the whole world, right here in New York State. That's all middle class. Who the hell do you think goes there? Not the black guys from my old neighborhood.</p>
        <p>We have created a middle-class paradise and you're beating up on the poor people, because they're taking food off your table.</p>
        <p>I got killed; Dave Garth had a heart attack. "Our chances are slim enough," he said.  [ laughter ]</p>
        <p>You've got to focus again on what it is that the current policies are going to do and what they're not going to do and what the result of that is going to be. This approach to me really says this: "Look, we're not really going to try to solve the problems of the poor people. They're not us. They don't vote for us. We win without them. As a matter of fact we win by running against them." Reagan holds up the jobs and says if they wanted to work, they could. He says, the homeless, if they wanted shelter, they could have it. A baby having babies. It's only because nobody ever told her how to do the right thing. And they're pretending that the problem will solve itself.</p>
        <p>So you have an attitude really that says, and Reagan did it, look, I can pile up the debt, I can con you with my smile. He made the denial of compassion respectable. That was his greatest thing. He was so genial, so non-threatening, so popular, and so lovable that he made America forget that you have an obligation, Number 1, in compassion, and also in common sense. Because unless you solve those problems, they'll come back to haunt you. That's what's going to happen.  THE ESSENCE OF LEADERSHIP Purdum: What should people be willing to give up? Can you persuade them? Is there a way to persuade them?  Weicker: My problem with the two parties, my own, having belonged to it for 30 years, the Democrats also, is that leaders aren't being produced. I suspect that both of these individuals  [ indicating Richards and Cuomo ]  will remain powerful forces within the Democratic Party because I think we are going to come back to the issue of leadership.</p>
        <p>The answer now is that the American public doesn't want leadership. It doesn't want to make sacrifices, but like we always do, Americans have an uncanny knack of all of a sudden coming around to what needs doing and they'll do it. Richards: Mario said a little bit ago that he had not seen anything that equaled, nor have I, the commitment of the nation that we felt in World War II. There was a brief moment when we decided that we were going to put a man on the moon; that we were going to commit ourselves to something that was larger than this nation with the space program.</p>
        <p>If the atmosphere that exists today existed then, we would never have gone into space. You wouldn't see the satellite system that exists, the modern communication ever having taken place. You would not have seen the enormous technological advances that have taken place as the consequence of the space program. And that was not our intention. Our intention was to put a man in space. The consequences of that were that we became technologically in the forefront of the world at having done enormously important scientific things.</p>
        <p>So you say, what should Clinton do? What should some other leader do? Call us to a larger national purpose. What that is, well, if I'd known that, I would still be in office. Cuomo: I think that's sad. I think Ann has put her finger on it: what is the national purpose? I've tried once describing the character of the American people. And I came up with four marks of the American character. One was what are we as Americans. Well, we came here for opportunity; that's a big one, everybody, papa, mama, the immigrants. Liberty, absolutely, well, there's never been a freer place that stayed well ordered as wonderfully well as we have, except for the Civil War. Responsibility, yeah, opportunity, liberty, but responsibility. You have to work here, if you break the law, you go to jail. It's the fourth one, after opportunity, liberty, responsibility that is the tricky one. Is it individuality or is it family? Is it community or is it individuality? Do you really believe in the notion of community? As Jeremiah shows, you will find your own welfare in the welfare of the whole community. Do you really believe there is a connection between you and the kid in the ghetto, even if you moved out, even if she's black, even if she's not yours?</p>
        <p>I say in the end our national purpose must be to think as a family. There are two political motivations. One is compassion; doesn't work. The other is self interest; does work. When self-interest and compassion come together in the same objective, then you have a perfect political position.  ON ISOLATION IN OFFICE Purdum: Is this mood of antipolitics a real thing? Does it have any roots?  [ to Richards ]  In 8 years as Treasurer and 4 years as Governor did you get too isolated from people? Too much time in the helicopter, too little time in the neighborhoods? Is that a bum rap? Richards: I spent more time on the road probably than any governor in the history of the state. It wasn't just a matter of speaking to Rotary clubs and Chambers of Commerce either. It was a matter of holding town forums to be able to bring people in to talk about problems. We did a series of summits for young people because it seems to me that when you talk about juvenile crime, you need to talk to juveniles to find out really what's going on in their lives.</p>
        <p>And I had one young man say: "Governor, you're talking about what we can do in the schools. Don't you understand it really doesn't make any difference what you do in the school, as long as I go home? Once I leave school and hit the war zone" -- which is what he called his neighborhood -- "what you do in school all day doesn't make any difference." That kid very clearly saw that school was a component part of his life, but unless we made some difference in the circumstances under which he and his family lived we couldn't correct in school what was taking place in a larger world. So the relevance that this young man saw to what government action did to actually make anything better in his life simply did not exist and he ain't going to vote. Cuomo: I didn't lose touch with the people of my state. It's just that I couldn't give the people what I knew they wanted all the time. I couldn't see my way to giving them the tax cut over the last four years, because I didn't think it was the right judgment. Of course they wanted the tax cut. Of course they want the death penalty. Now maybe I'm wrong, but I just couldn't see it that way. So my problem politically was not being out of touch with them; it was not being able to give them what they asked for in enough of the cases to win popularity and as things got worse in their perception, they were less and less willing to forgive me the differences.  THE ROLE OF A FORMER GOVERNOR Purdum: So what's the job of a lapsed politician in all this?  Richards: What responsibility do I feel as a citizen of this country now that I am no longer an elected official? I feel the same responsibility that I felt before I was in office and that is that I must do my part as best I see to help make my state and my country better. And I'll continue to do that in whatever way the opportunity offers itself.</p>
        <p>But I've got probably a different point of view and different feelings about it. Mario's going to do one thing. Lowell, I guess is going to do another and I'm probably going to do another because we are going to act now as individual citizens, but I don't feel that I have some soapbox attached to my belt to drag around from one place to the other. I don't feel that it's up to us somehow to carry some banner into the fray. Mario and I talked about this when we did our Dorito commercial  [ for the Super Bowl ] . People call in. . . . Cuomo: I was hoping you would get through this without mentioning. . . .  [ Laughter ] . Richards: You get a jillion telephone calls from people who love you and people who might have some other interest in you to save the world with television talk shows and radio talk shows. I just don't see myself in that role and not to be snide or mean. I mean this honestly. I don't have time to talk to anyone who has time to call a radio program.  Weicker: I'd better respond to this. Peter Brown, who writes for Scripps- Howard, read that I was going to do a radio talk show, so he called me and said, "Lowell, why are you doing this?" And I said, "Well, Peter, to respond to all the unanswered bull that's out there." Richards: Well, that's the best answer I've heard yet. Cuomo: You have three ex-governors here. You accumulate their lifetimes of experience in politics and living, it's about 100 years. It would be kind of foolish to throw it away. And what we're saying is, look, we learned an awful lot. Let's see if we can't share some of it. We made a lot of mistakes, maybe you can avoid some of them. THE OUTLOOK IN 1996 Purdum: What do you make of the political woods for '96? Who's the Republican ticket going to be?  Richards: Phil Gramm.  Purdum: Really? And for Vice President? Richards: Oh, I have no idea. Whoever he likes and whoever will buy it.  Cuomo: President Clinton will be the Democratic nominee. I don't know who will be on the Republican side. The one thing that I'm surest of between now and '96 is that three things will happen that nobody figured on and they could change everything. So my guess is that Bill Clinton is the Democratic candidate.  Purdum: Are you saying three events that can't be predicted now? Cuomo: Three events. There are always at least three. Weicker: Clinton for the Democrats, Dole for the Republicans and a major third-party, centrist candidate. And it won't be Ross Perot.  Purdum: It won't be Colin Powell, either? Weicker: I'm not saying that. I'm just saying to you I think there will be a major third-party candidate, a centrist, who will have great appeal and that it will be a very tight three-way race. Richards: In that scenario, if Lowell is right, it will be a tight three-way and I think ultimately Clinton will win it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
