<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Answer Time for In-and-Out Syracuse</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NCAA BASKETBALL TOURNAMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DD1F30F93AA25750C0A963958260" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Answer Time for In-and-Out Syracuse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., March 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We are about to find out about Syracuse.</p>
        <p>We know the start. A season-opening loss to George Washington and then 14 consecutive victories. And then losses in seven of its last 10 games. So very hot and then so very cold. How good is this bunch?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We are about to find out about Syracuse.</p>
        <p>We know the start. A season-opening loss to George Washington and then 14 consecutive victories. And then losses in seven of its last 10 games. So very hot and then so very cold. How good is this bunch?</p>
        <p>We are about to find out.</p>
        <p>They tackle the defending national champions, the Arkansas Razorbacks, in Midwest Regional tournament second-round play here on Sunday afternoon at the Erwin Center. And the Orangemen appear as eager to answer the question as those who are asking.</p>
        <p>"We've handled pressure defense well at times and sometimes not too well," said Syracuse Coach Jim Boeheim. "We don't have as much depth as they have but in this tournament you must have eight guys that can play and we have eight guys that can play. This is a great challenge. Can we handle it? That is what this game is all about."</p>
        <p>When asked about the special flavor of meeting Arkansas, the stellar Syracuse guard Lawrence Moten said: "Oh man! We couldn't ask for a better game or a better team to play against. They have a strong array of defenses and pressure. They will be at their best and we hope that brings the best out in us. This will be a game to see."</p>
        <p>Forward Lucious Jackson added: "We'd like to think the pressure is on them. If we lose, we go home. If they lose, they lose their national title and go home."</p>
        <p>Syracuse (20-9) beat Southern Illinois by 96-92 here on Friday afternoon to advance; Arkansas (28-6) edged Texas Southern, 79-78.</p>
        <p>Syracuse matched and then surpassed the Southern Illinois offensive show with one of its own in producing what Boeheim described as his team's best offensive performance of the season. He said the Arkansas game could be another one in the 90's or, maybe, the scoring will be much lower. "It is really hard to tell until you get out there," he said, "because the flow of the game and what you do to take this away and what they do in response and then vice versa. You never know, but I expect it to be uptempo."</p>
        <p>And that could be good for Syracuse. It is 5-0 in games in which it scored 90 or more points and 12-1 in games in which it scored 80 or more. Here is what it doesn't want to do: trail at halftime or lose in shooting percentage to Arkansas. Syracuse is 0-5 when trailing at the half and 0-6 when it gets outshot.</p>
        <p>Among its victories during the 14-game victory streak were triumphs over Princeton (67-65), Arizona (94-84) and Villanova (61-60). During its skein to end the season, it lost to Kentucky (77-71), to Connecticut (77-70) and in the Big East tournament to Providence (71-69).</p>
        <p>"We were up 10 points on Connecticut and led Kentucky by 15," Jackson said. "Nobody just went out and beat us up and made us look real bad. We lost those games because we made mistakes at the end. We didn't take care of the ball and we didn't play the full 40 minutes. I think our seniors made the difference and pulled us out of that funk and got us ready for the tournament. We made a promise to ourselves not to go out with a fizzle but with a bang, to do something to keep the Syracuse basketball tradition going and to make ourselves proud."</p>
        <p>That is important to all of the Orangemen. After probation and all the playoff disappointments, Syracuse wants to recapture not only the glow of its early-season run but also the glow of its past. To solidify its place as a prominent figure on the national stage.</p>
        <p>You do that against champions. You do that against Arkansas.</p>
        <p>Syracuse says that this game should be a lot like playing against Georgetown or Connecticut from a defensive standpoint. Both teams, like Arkansas, employ multiple defenses and various full- and half-court traps. Boeheim, however, reminds everyone that his team, too, is not the easiest to adjust to. His team mixes and matches and switches on both sides of the court, too.</p>
        <p>"When we had that losing spell, I just tried to remind everyone that life goes on and so does basketball and that there was still a lot of basketball to be played," Moten said. "That streak is behind us. We're working on something here. And right now, we're 1-0."  N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
