<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marbury Leads Lincoln To P.S.A.L. Championship</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC SCHOOLS ATHLETIC LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEMASIO, NUNYO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DA1E31F93AA25750C0A963958260" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marbury Leads Lincoln To P.S.A.L. Championship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NUNYO DEMASIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEMASIO, NUNYO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephon Marbury was mobbed by his teammates yesterday after Lincoln's stirring 61-56 victory over Robeson at Madison Square Garden in the Public Schools Athletic League A championship game between the Brooklyn schools.</p>
        <p>"I've got everything now," screamed Marbury, who won his first title. "I've got everything now."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stephon Marbury was mobbed by his teammates yesterday after Lincoln's stirring 61-56 victory over Robeson at Madison Square Garden in the Public Schools Athletic League A championship game between the Brooklyn schools.</p>
        <p>"I've got everything now," screamed Marbury, who won his first title. "I've got everything now."</p>
        <p>The scene was starkly different from last year, when Marbury was sprawled on the court and crying after shooting 5 of 24 in losing to Martin Luther King in the final.</p>
        <p>Marbury scored a game-high 26 points to lead the Railsplitters (24-3), who had lost in the final the last two years, before a crowd of 8,842, including Georgia Tech Coach Bobby Cremins. Marbury will attend Georgia Tech next season.</p>
        <p>Marbury hit two free throws to give top-seeded Lincoln a 59-56 lead with 11 seconds remaining. Todd Myles, who helped Robeson win last year's B championship at the buzzer, missed a 3-pointer with 5 seconds left.</p>
        <p>"It took three years," said Marbury, who hit 10 of 13 free throws yesterday. "We always came up short. This year we came up big."</p>
        <p>Lincoln faced an imposing frontcourt with an average height of 6 feet 8 inches, while the Railsplitters' tallest player was 6-6 Jamel Thomas.</p>
        <p>Gerald Hawkins (21 points) took advantage of dismal shooting (36 percent) by third-seeded Robeson (20-7, 12-1). Many of his points were on the fast break off long outlets from Thomas, who grabbed a game-high 17 rebounds.</p>
        <p>"Jamel has played like this throughout the playoffs," said Lincoln Coach Bobby Hartstein, whose teams have been to the final 7 of the last 10 years, winning in 1986 and 1991.</p>
        <p>With 7:15 left in the game, Marbury made a 3-pointer to tie the score at 40-40. Then Hawkins made a free throw after being fouled on a fast-break layup to give Lincoln a 41-40 lead it never relinquished.</p>
        <p>Shamel Jones had a team-high 17 points and 4 blocks and Jameel Watkins had 12 rebounds and 4 blocks for Robeson.</p>
        <p>In the P.S.A.L. B championship, Francis Lewis of Queens defeated Theodore Roosevelt of the Bronx, 63-58.</p>
        <p>Hannibal Bates of Francis Lewis sat by himself in a corner of the locker room, clutching his trophy as tears streamed down his face.</p>
        <p>"For 17 years, all I thought about was getting on a team and going to the Garden," said the 5-11 junior guard, his voice barely audible. "We wanted to represent our school and our borough. We had to come through." Bates came through, scoring a game-high 22 points.</p>
        <p>Despite having no player over 6-3, the Rough Riders (21-3, 15-2) used their quickness to move to within 57-55 with about a minute left. But they missed 3 of 6 free throws in the last 43 seconds, while Bates made 3 of 4 free throws to clinch the game for Lewis (23-3, 15-0).</p>
        <p>In the P.S.A.L. girls championship, Manhattan Center put a halt to A. Philip Randolph's Cinderella-like run through the playoffs with a 34-27 victory. "I knew they would come as tough as they did," said Manhattan Center Coach Varleton McDonald, referring to Randolph's players. "We're used to scoring 60 and 70 points a game."</p>
        <p>The sixth-seeded Cougars (20-6, 10-5) -- who have no seniors -- earned their first final appearance ever by stunning second-seeded King, 40-39, last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Jaywana Bradley of Manhattan Center (27-3, 13-3) scored a game-high 15 points.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
