<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Task Force for Recouping Stolen Property</title>
    <meta content="BURGLE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="959229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weizel, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6D81338F932A1575AC0A961958260" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Task Force for Recouping Stolen Property</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD WEIZEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weizel, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of Bridgeport (Conn) Regional Burglary Squad, task force which has recovered more than $150,000 worth of stolen power tools since its inception in January; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN burglars broke into his garage and storage shed earlier this year and made off with thousands of dollars' worth of rare specialty tools, 79-year-old Louis Ashen of Fairfield figured the items were gone forever.</p>
        <p>Since only about half of residential burglaries are even reported to police, only 10 percent of those are ever solved and even then the stolen items are recovered in only a fraction of the cases, Mr. Ashen was not being unduly pessimistic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN burglars broke into his garage and storage shed earlier this year and made off with thousands of dollars' worth of rare specialty tools, 79-year-old Louis Ashen of Fairfield figured the items were gone forever.</p>
        <p>Since only about half of residential burglaries are even reported to police, only 10 percent of those are ever solved and even then the stolen items are recovered in only a fraction of the cases, Mr. Ashen was not being unduly pessimistic.</p>
        <p>Enter the Bridgeport Regional Burglary Squad, a task force that includes 13 detectives from 10 Fairfield and New Haven County towns and cities. The Bridgeport-based unit busted a major burglary ring operating out of the Hollow section of the city and recovered more than $150,000 in power tools. Mr. Ashen will get back some of his property.</p>
        <p>Since its inception in January, the unit says, it has recovered nearly $300,000 worth of stolen property and has made several dozen arrests.</p>
        <p>''I never thought in a million years they would find my tools, it's kind of like a miracle,'' said Mr. Ashen, whose home was also burglarized 10 years ago. ''I'm obviously very thankful this task force has been formed.''</p>
        <p>Police chiefs in the region agree, pointing to a recently released Department of Public Safety report that showed  that while there was a statewide 5.2 percent decrease in reported burglaries in 1996, burglaries were on the rise in Bridgeport, Milford, Norwalk and Shelton (4 of the 10 towns in the regional anti-burglary task force).</p>
        <p>Easton Police Chief Jack Solomon, who worked on several regional task forces during more than 30 years with the State Police, is credited with coming up with the idea for the new burglary unit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomon said that when he became chief in Easton two years ago it was obvious to him that burglary had gotten less attention in the Bridgeport and New Haven areas in recent years, taking a back seat to reducing gang-related and other crimes of violence. ''All the towns around here were getting clobbered with burglaries and I thought that by sharing intelligence and manpower, we could greatly cut into the way burglars do business,'' said Mr. Solomon.</p>
        <p>The way many burglars do business is through a network that begins with selling stolen goods to fencing operations, including pawnshops. In Bridgeport alone there are more than 20 pawnshops, so Mayor Joseph P. Ganim has announced that the  city will stop renewing pawnshop licenses.</p>
        <p>''This whole area was being deluged with burglaries and we had to do something collective to combat the problem because these fencing operations, many that run out of pawnshops, were running rampant,'' said the Shelton Police Chief, Robert E. White, who supports the task force.</p>
        <p>While the anti-burglary squad was established as a pilot program in January -- patterned after the Bridgeport regional auto-theft task force that has cut car thefts by 60 percent since 1991 -- official announcement of the burglary unit was held off until late May.</p>
        <p>The Bridgeport Police Chief, Thomas Sweeney, said that the unit's operations would be evaluated shortly, and draw additional participants.  Towns and cities now involved are Bridgeport, Fairfield, Stratford, Milford, Westport, Trumbull, Norwalk, Easton, Monroe and Shelton.</p>
        <p>''People often think only about violent crime,'' Mr. Sweeney said, ''but being burglarized is frightening and can cause a great deal of trauma. And that's not to mention the loss of valuable property and items of tremendous sentimental value.''</p>
        <p>Chief Sweeney said that four Bridgeport detectives have been assigned to the task force, including the squad commander, Sgt. Paul Wargo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wargo said that the regional approach works because the departments can pool information as well as experienced personnel.</p>
        <p>''I feel like we have an all-star team of detectives who have come together to try and cut into an area of crime that many people take for granted,'' said Mr. Wargo. ''Anytime you can pool your resources and target a specific area of crime, you can develop an even greater expertise in that area and become more effective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wargo said that the unit has been conducting at least one search and seizure operation every week. Recently, the task force made an excursion to New Haven to check a  pawnshop where the owner was suspected of obtaining newly stolen goods. Detectives, who said they had received a tip, obtained a search and seizure warrant and raided the shop.  The owner, they said, sat stunned when they burst in and began gathering suspected stolen goods, including a computer screen and several vacuum cleaners that still had price tags.</p>
        <p>''I have nothing to say, but I can't believe that in America the police could just burst in here like this,'' said the shop's owner, a 72-year-old man who denied knowledge that any of the thousands of items in the shop had been stolen.</p>
        <p>One of the detectives, Pete Zaksiwicz of Shelton, said ''The problem is it's difficult to prove because it's tough to trace a lot of the items in here to actual stores or homes.'' He added that the New Haven police would further investigate to determine whether there was enough evidence to revoke the shop owner's license.</p>
        <p>Another detective, Peter Ellsworth of Milford, said that the reason most stolen property can never be returned is because most stores don't keep adequate inventory records, and most people fail to engrave identification on valuables.</p>
        <p>But, the police said, not everyone could be as lucky as 27-year-old Joseph Genovese of Wallingford, who  got back his 1990 Eastern Connecticut State University College World Series Championship ring after the burglary squad recovered it during a raid on a Bridgeport pawnshop.</p>
        <p>''In a case like that we can trace it through his name, initials or even through the school,'' said Mr. Zaksiwicz. ''But most people,'' he said, ''need to be thinking about engraving some form of identification into their valuables . . . so that if we do recover the items we can get it back to them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
