<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Overtime, Fetisov Remedies Devils' Problems</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA FLYERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DB1239F93AA25751C0A964958260" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Overtime, Fetisov Remedies Devils' Problems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Feb. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With one blistering shot from the top of the left circle in overtime, Slava Fetisov made the Devils forget their troubles tonight and provided the heralded Russian defenseman with an unforgettable moment.</p>
        <p>Wiped out by the Fetisov goal at 1 minute 42 seconds into the extra period was a sluggish start by the Devils, their prolonged lack of high intensity, their continued ineptness on the power play and especially their lapse that allowed the Philadelphia Flyers to tie the game with 5 seconds left in regulation time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With one blistering shot from the top of the left circle in overtime, Slava Fetisov made the Devils forget their troubles tonight and provided the heralded Russian defenseman with an unforgettable moment.</p>
        <p>Wiped out by the Fetisov goal at 1 minute 42 seconds into the extra period was a sluggish start by the Devils, their prolonged lack of high intensity, their continued ineptness on the power play and especially their lapse that allowed the Philadelphia Flyers to tie the game with 5 seconds left in regulation time.</p>
        <p>Fetisov's first winning goal in his three seasons in New Jersey gave the Devils a 4-3 victory at the Byrne Meadowlands Arena, as well as a franchise record of six consecutive victories and triumphs in 15 in the last 20 (15-4-1) games. The goal was set up with a perfectly timed pass from the right side by one of his Russian compatriots, Valery Zelepukin. A Longtime Goal</p>
        <p>"I'll have this goal on my mind for a long time," Fetisov said of his shot that beat Ron Hextall and ended Philadelphia's unbeaten streak at six games (4-1-1). "I saw Hextall move toward me and my feeling was to shoot it low."</p>
        <p>Kevin Todd, Dave Barr and Eric Weinrich scored the goals in regulation for the Devils, who took 28 shots at Hextall.</p>
        <p>Rod Brind'Amour had the first two goals for Philadelphia before Kevin Dineen got the tying one against Chris Terreri, who had another inspiring performance in goal for the Devils.</p>
        <p>The biggest blemish of the night for the Devils (32-18-7) was their power play. They came up empty in five chances, which means they now have one goal in their last 26 manpower advantages.</p>
        <p>The Flyers came into the game ranked 20th among the league's 22 teams on the power play, but they capitalized the first time they had the advantage.</p>
        <p>With Fetisov in the penalty box, Brind'Amour got his first of the night from close range on the right side, jumping on a rebound of Dineen's shot, 4:50 into the game.</p>
        <p>Todd's 16th of the season tied it for the Devils with 3:02 left before the first intermission by beating Hextall over the stick from low in the slot after a pass by Stephane Richer.</p>
        <p>Terreri's most spectacular save in the first 40 minutes came in the waning moments of the first period when he sprawled to his right to deny Mark Pederson while the Devils were a man short.</p>
        <p>Terreri's second most spectacular save also came against Pederson by sprawling to his right, this time during a 2-on-1 break for the Flyers at 3:15 seconds into the third.</p>
        <p>Barr started and finished the play that resulted into the Devils' second goal, 5:20 into the middle period with a pass to Bruce Driver, the captain of the Devils.</p>
        <p>Driver returned the favor and Barr relayed the puck to Tom Chorske on the left neat Philadelphia's blue line before taking off for the net. Chorske feathered a perfect pass to Barr, who redirected it through Hextall's legs for his sixth of the season.</p>
        <p>Brind'Amour's second of the night and 21st of the season that tied it for the Flyers came after a nice move on Terreri from right to left, 7:03 into the second.</p>
        <p>After Weinrich regained the lead for the Devils with his third of the season with 7:15 left, Dineen shocked the Devils with his 22d to force the overtime. SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>CLAUDE LEMIEUX , the leading goal- scorer for the Devils with 34, bruised his left ankle early in the second period and missed the balance of the game. His absence forced Coach TOM McVIE to shuffle his lines and double-shift some players. Penguins 7, Maple Leafs 1</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH (AP) -- Joe Mullen scored three goals in the first period and Ron Francis scored twice as Pittsburgh ended a season-worst six-game streak without a victory. Nordiques 4, North Stars 0</p>
        <p>QUEBEC (AP) -- Owen Nolan scored his 30th goal and added two assists as Quebec, behind John Tanner's first league shutout, snapped a 10-game string without a victory.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
