<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SoHo's Mr. Clean; A One-Man Anti-Grime Unit</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STREETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAFFITI</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOHO AREA (SOUTH HOUSTON INDUSTRIAL DISTRICT) (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">IANNACONE, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEINFIELD, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DC1F3DF93AA25751C0A964958260" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SoHo's Mr. Clean; A One-Man Anti-Grime Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEINFIELD, N R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He keeps the garbage barrels and the brooms in the basement. Stacked in a faded cupboard at the end of his hallway are his acetone and his Vandal Mark Remover for blotting out graffiti, as well as his spectrum of paints (black, red, white, brown). He has a snow shovel, a spade for adding dirt around the trees, a wad of work gloves.</p>
        <p>Every day, Anthony Iannacone gathers his utensils and scrambles out to the street, his feet making scrabbly sounds as he tramps down the stairs. This is Sullivan Street, between Broome and Spring, in SoHo. Rolling one of his big barrels on wheels, working a whisk broom and a dust pan on a stick with practiced authority, he picks up every crumpled candy wrapper, every squashed-out cigarette butt, every pile of dog excrement, until the street is clean. Perfectly clean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He keeps the garbage barrels and the brooms in the basement. Stacked in a faded cupboard at the end of his hallway are his acetone and his Vandal Mark Remover for blotting out graffiti, as well as his spectrum of paints (black, red, white, brown). He has a snow shovel, a spade for adding dirt around the trees, a wad of work gloves.</p>
        <p>Every day, Anthony Iannacone gathers his utensils and scrambles out to the street, his feet making scrabbly sounds as he tramps down the stairs. This is Sullivan Street, between Broome and Spring, in SoHo. Rolling one of his big barrels on wheels, working a whisk broom and a dust pan on a stick with practiced authority, he picks up every crumpled candy wrapper, every squashed-out cigarette butt, every pile of dog excrement, until the street is clean. Perfectly clean.</p>
        <p>He is thorough. If there is fresh graffiti, he attacks it with his solvents and paints. If any outdoor lightbulbs on the buildings have burned out, he replaces them. Then, and only then, is he content.</p>
        <p>"Everything has to be perfect," he explained. "I leave when all the litter is gone and everything's just right. Listen, I take pride in where I live."</p>
        <p>Say all you want about how New Yorkers don't care. Say all you want about how they'll let their buildings molder, how they'll live with any amount of grime and detritus. Go on and on about how they'll close their eyes to the patches of graffiti and shrug their shoulders at indolent dog owners who refuse to curb their pets. Go ahead and chafe about how they won't lift their pinky to help one another.  Cleaning Now and Forever</p>
        <p>Not Anthony Iannacone. He is just another resident of the block, with a job as a part-time cashier at Off-Track Betting. But he is someone, his neighbors agree, just a little below the angels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iannacone's passion has made Sullivan Street between Broome and Spring among the cleanest in New York. No litter survives more than a few hours. There is no graffiti. There are trees in every spot but one -- he is working on getting it replaced. There are five curb-your-dog signs. He got them put up. There's a no-littering sign. Mr. Iannacone had that put there. When street lamps burn out, he calls to get fresh ones. He painted all the street-lamp bases. Inside the lobbies of the buildings, he posted signs: "No More Menus Please." In the warm weather, he adds dirt around the trees and sprinkles a layer of decorative white pebbles. He can barely wait until spring, when he plans to plant flowers around the trees.</p>
        <p>It was not always so. Mr. Iannacone knows. He has lived in the same fifth-floor walkup at 67 Sullivan Street all of his 28 years. Since he was a child, he has had a thing about messes, his mother confirms, but he left the outdoors to others. It was three years ago that the filthy conditions roused him into battle.</p>
        <p>He tells it best: "A lot of people were walking their dogs and leaving the dog droppings on the sidewalk. There's a school around the corner, and the kids would come over and throw bottles and hamburger wrappers. Some of the trees were missing and the weeds were up to your waist. One day, I just said, 'Look, I'm tired of living this way.' I went out and bought supplies and started cleaning. And I haven't stopped. People are always asking me why do I do it. I tell them because I like to live nice."</p>
        <p>It happens that the block is thick with Iannacone relatives. Anthony Iannacone, a dark-haired man with a sparse mustache and a 10,000-watt smile, shares an apartment with his parents -- his father retired from delivering mail and his mother retired from raising five children.</p>
        <p>In the adjacent apartment resides one of Anthony Iannacone's sisters and her daughter's family. Three uncles and four aunts live on the block. One uncle, Andrew Paciaffi, likes to shadow Mr. Iannacone on his rounds and badger him for forgetting to wear his gloves. "You don't know what you're picking up," he rebukes him. "Where are your gloves?"</p>
        <p>The block is a sprawl of boxy brick buildings, with the side bordered by the back of a Mobil gas station, a car wash and a mini-mart. Last summer, Mr. Iannacone gave the walls of the gas station a new coat of paint.</p>
        <p>It was late on a Saturday afternoon, the sky shrouded with storm clouds, and the street buzzed with purpose. Bundled up in knockabout clothes, his forehead puckered, Mr. Iannacone got out his barrel and grabbed hold of his broom and dustpan.</p>
        <p>He started at the Broome Street corner and worked his way to Spring, moving slowly, missing nothing. He began with a balled-up party invitation, a Chiclets package, four butts, three leaves and a pizza menu.</p>
        <p>He glared at a pile of dog feces. "When will they learn," he sighed meditatively, and scooped it up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iannacone knows everyone on the block, all 75-odd families and their pets. He greets them by name.</p>
        <p>"Hi, Doris,"</p>
        <p>"Hey, what d'ya say, Anthony."</p>
        <p>"Hi, Joan."</p>
        <p>"How's it look, Anthony?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Iannacone got a Chinese menu (Hunan style), more cigarette butts, a wrapping from the four-roll size of Charmin toilet tissue.</p>
        <p>Breathing quick, shallow little breaths, he moved to the other side of the street and started all over again.</p>
        <p>Diana Yardley Davis, another neighbor, shambled past. "This man is wonderful," she said. "He makes my morning. He makes my evening. And he's not even my husband."</p>
        <p>In the beginning, Mr. Iannacone paid for his supplies out of his own limited funds. Then one of his aunts began soliciting donations from other residents around Christmas. The first year drew $250, then $450 and finally $900 this December.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iannacone swept up a Butterfingers wrapper and a pass to a sex club. Then he saw something on the sidewalk and his face showed alarm. Graffiti. In luminous yellow was inscribed: "Don't Give Up. REVS."</p>
        <p>"That really aggravates me," he said in a querulous voice.</p>
        <p>The wind came slicing through and sent part of a newspaper skidding under a car. Mr. Iannacone snatched it up as quickly as a magician.</p>
        <p>"Hey, Anthony, look over here," one of the neighbors called out. "There's the former mayor."</p>
        <p>His face softened with curiosity. Sure enough, Edward I. Koch was bending into a car. "Say hi to Anthony," the neighbor said.</p>
        <p>"Hi, Anthony," Mr. Koch boomed.</p>
        <p>"I know Ed likes to see the streets clean," Mr. Iannacone said.</p>
        <p>The sun was fading and chilliness spread over Mr. Iannacone's skin, but he was almost done. With his wrench, he opened up a fire hydrant and flooded the street for a few minutes. Then he fetched his acetone and a rumpled underwear top.</p>
        <p>Returning to the graffiti, he knelt down on his hands and knees and, his face tensed, he soaked the underwear with acetone and scrubbed furiously. "I don't know why they do this," he said. "I think it's because they want to see me work."</p>
        <p>The paint began to yield. Once the scribbling was faint, he said, "Okay, I'll let the rain finish the rest."</p>
        <p>Darkness arrived and the street was quiet. And clean. Absolutely clean. Mr. Iannacone said that his work was done for now. He thought he would go up and relax for a bit. He knew it was Saturday night, the mad hours, always hard on the street.</p>
        <p>"I'll probably come down a little later and check out how the street's holding up," he said. "The cleaning supplies might have to come out again tonight. We'll just have to see."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
