<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hard Times in the Schools -- A Special Report; In Classrooms, the Economy Is Teaching a Harsh Lesson</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT HEALTHY (OHIO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MONTEBELLO (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHIRA, SUSAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB163AF93AA25751C0A964958260" item-length="2789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hard Times in the Schools -- A Special Report; In Classrooms, the Economy Is Teaching a Harsh Lesson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN CHIRA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHIRA, SUSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hard times are reaching into the American classroom.</p>
        <p>Just when politicians are calling for a revival in American education, the recession is leaving principals and teachers across the country with less money for more students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hard times are reaching into the American classroom.</p>
        <p>Just when politicians are calling for a revival in American education, the recession is leaving principals and teachers across the country with less money for more students.</p>
        <p>The toll is uneven, and not all the cuts are dire. But reports are somber across the economic spectrum. Schools in the hardest-hit areas have no art, no music, no librarians and no counselors. Teachers comb rummage sales and attics for supplies. School districts stop running buses and hold Bingo nights to pay for sports programs.</p>
        <p>"A year ago we received the nation's education goals and I was told to post them on my wall," said Jane Gaskell, principal of Pembroke Hill Elementary School in Pembroke, N.H., referring to the six ambitious education goals President Bush has said he wants achieved by the year 2000. "We're not even getting close. I read my education journals and hear about these innovative programs and I laugh and say, 'The band's playing on.' "</p>
        <p>There are no up-to-date national figures on public school spending cuts, but interviews with experts on school finance, national education groups and principals of 27 schools in 13 states suggest that this year is bad and that next year will be worse.</p>
        <p>The latest estimates available for spending on elementary and secondary education from the National Center on Education Statistics project a 5.8 percent increase by Federal, state and local governments for the school year that began this fall.</p>
        <p>But the notion of an increase may be misleading because these estimates were made as the recession was just unfolding. In many cases, rising school enrollments, local reluctance to raise taxes and state fiscal problems have meant that schools actually have less money than before.</p>
        <p>So far this year, 30 states have reported budget deficits or revenue shortfalls, according to Anthony Hutchison, a fiscal analyst for the National Conference of State Legislatures. States and towns pay 94 percent of all education costs. Although surveys show that most state legislatures had planned to increase spending on education this school year, Mr. Hutchison said he expected that the recession would pare those increases or force actual cuts in many cases before the end of this year. Rising school enrollments have meant that a small increase can actually be a cut. Even more than states, cities and towns appear to be cutting education spending as voters worried about the economy reject tax increases.</p>
        <p>The worst-off schools are in the Northeast and California, according to Steven D. Gold, director of the Center for the Study of the States at the Rockefeller Institute of Government in Albany. In a survey conducted this December by the National Association of Elementary School Principals, 74 percent of the 650 principals who responded reported budget cuts. Forty percent of the principals said teachers had been let go. Nearly half the principals cut back music, art, and programs for gifted children; 80 percent have eliminated field trips.</p>
        <p>Critics have long contended that money's role in education is overrated. It is clear that some school bureaucracies absorb too much money before it reaches the classroom; the National Center for Education Statistics has found that nearly 40 percent of money for education does not go directly to the classroom but is spent on administration, guidance counselors, transportation and other services.</p>
        <p>But it is equally clear that in many places schools are hobbled. In rural Hancock County in eastern Tennessee, schools depend on fund raisers to buy all school supplies. In Belington, W.Va., teachers run booths at the local fair to raise money so that they can attend workshops. In Los Angeles, the Aragon Avenue School had to cut playground hours in a neighborhood where children have nowhere else to play.</p>
        <p>Young as they are, children in these schools notice. "I think we're cheated out of a lot of things," said Cathleen Miles, a fourth-grader who is organizing a bake sale to raise money for Public School 243 in Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn, one of New York City's poorest neighborhoods. "We used to go to science class and learn about animals. We haven't got to a computer class yet this year, or a music class."</p>
        <p>Here are three case studies of what budget cuts have meant to individual schools. Mount Healthy, Ohio A Leaking Roof And No Scissors</p>
        <p>When money got so tight that the kindergarten teacher had to scour garage sales for Lego sets and the nurse was cut back to once a week, the teachers at Rex Ralph Elementary School put the ad in The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>"Invest in America's Future," the headline read, inviting benefactors to adopt the school in Mount Healthy, a middle-income suburb of Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>No one did.</p>
        <p>So the eight leaks in the roof keep dripping, the copier and computer stay broken, the missing "F" volume in the school's only set of encyclopedias goes unreplaced, and teachers continue without a pay raise for a third year.</p>
        <p>Times are bad in Mount Healthy, and over the last year and a half voters have rejected four requests for local tax increases to pay for education. The district now spends $4,376 per student, below the national average of $5,240.</p>
        <p>State cuts are looming on top of local ones. The district's treasurer, Rebecca Brooks, said the state, which supplies much of Mount Healthy's education budget, held education aid below the inflation rate last year and will cut aid next year.  'The Worst I've Ever Seen'</p>
        <p>That means more trouble ahead for Rex Ralph Elementary, where the principal is already making do with one-quarter the money for supplies he had two and a half years ago. "This is my 24th year in education, and this is the worst I've ever seen it," said the principal, Clifford A. Strefelt, a tall, hearty man whose voice these days sounds permanently mournful.</p>
        <p>The librarian is gone, and a school aide darts between the computer room and the library. The music teacher now spends half her day at the high school, so instead of music every day, the children have 35 minutes twice a week. Class sizes have risen from 23 a few years ago to nearly 30 now. Wanda Tucker, the school secretary, bought her own thermometer and bandages for the four days a week she doubles as school nurse.</p>
        <p>In a country pledged to be the best in math and science by the year 2000, the students at Rex Ralph Elementary use patched-up science textbooks dating from 1981, have no beakers or hot plates for science experiments and saw their computer time cut in half, from four hours a week to two.</p>
        <p>"They have nothing special -- no field trips, no paper, no equipment," said Karen Schneider, who praises the school but is nonetheless considering switching her two children to parochial schools. "Our athletic department is raising money through Bingo."</p>
        <p>Many parents have rallied behind the school. But the campaign for local tax increases has divided the community, parents say, pitting neighbors who send their children to parochial school against those who chose public schools. "For what people spend on cable TV, we could finance the levy," said Gerry Gutfreund, a children's book writer whose daughter is in first grade at Rex Ralph Elementary.</p>
        <p>The local Parent-Teacher Association has tried to fill the biggest gaps, buying a copying machine (now broken) and donating money for library books. But as much as the obvious cuts, teachers mourn the extra touches that they believe make the difference between excelling and just getting by.</p>
        <p>Jan Brown has no scissors for her first graders. Catherine Thomas, a fourth-grade teacher, cannot afford the extra paper it takes for the packages of puzzles and games she used to create to help children learn math.</p>
        <p>And Beverly Chrisanthus has had to abandon her cherished second-grade play because there is not enough paint, paper or staples for scenery or enough rehearsal time now that the school has to close one evening a week to trim heating and electricity bills.</p>
        <p>"I'm drained some days," Mrs. Chrisanthus said. "I wish someone could come in and see how my day starts, with tears, lost money, 'Mom's mad at me' -- then we're supposed to sit down and train these little minds to be the best at math in the world."</p>
        <p>Sitting in the library, a group of sixth graders reeled off a list of problems: Old books, big classes, outdated maps, no field trips, no student council.</p>
        <p>"Money's more important than us," said Sadie Gaston. "We're left out," said Michael Hill. Brooklyn A Proud Tradition Lost to Cutbacks</p>
        <p>Once, Joyce Washington saw her school as a testament to the promise of urban education. Now it speaks more eloquently of loss.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Washington is principal of the Weeksville School in the heart of Bedford-Stuyvesant, one of New York City's poorest and most crime-ravaged neighborhoods, which nonetheless boasts a proud history as a free black community and a stop on the Underground Railroad for escaping slaves.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn school built much of its curriculum on that history and created a small museum filled with mementos from Weeksville's past. With the help of the Bank Street College of Education, the school retrained teachers, published student writing, and adopted the Follow Through program, designed to insure that the gains of the Head Start preschool program did not fade once children entered elementary school. The Weeksville School, also known as P.S. 243, was chosen as a national model, and helped develop similar programs at 100 other schools.</p>
        <p>But after 23 years, the programs are gone.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Washington's school has a high percentage of foster children, scarred by abusive or drug-using parents and then bounced from one foster placement to another. The students are familiar with violence. One parent, Marcella Mobley, tells of hitting the ground the other day across the street from the school, unable to reach her son as shots rang out.</p>
        <p>A previous cut eliminated the social worker who used to help children, families and teachers cope with these horrors. And with the end of the Follow Through program this fall, the Weeksville School lost a teacher trainer, a neighborhood worker who got parents involved, extra money for books and field trips, and a rich collaboration with Bank Street that sought to recreate a public school along the lines of the institution's nationally renowned private one.</p>
        <p>On top of those cuts came others forced by the recession's blows to New York's economy. New York City spends $5,915 on each elementary school child, above the national average, and $16,746 for children in need of special education. The city had to trim school budgets by less than 1 percent this fall, but much deeper cuts are expected next year.</p>
        <p>Now a nurse gets to the Weeksville School just once a month. There is no longer a special science teacher to set up a room that children vividly recall as full of animals and science projects. With three school aides gone, it is hard to control children in the lunchroom. Class sizes range between 30 and 35 because the school lost three teachers.</p>
        <p>Children are not being taught in closets here. Plants still line many classrooms, and on bright days the sun streams through, creating an aura of cheer. But the contrast between what was and what is rankles parents, teachers and students. For a school with high ambitions, making do is not good enough.</p>
        <p>"We'd like to have extra math and science labs, and we do not have access to things like that," said Elmen Meggs, whose grandchildren attend the school and who used to work with the Follow Through program as a parent coordinator. "We know that science and math are important for our children." Difficult Choices</p>
        <p>Maurice Rosenthal used to spend three periods a day with gifted math students. But in one example of the difficult choices posed by cuts, he is now assigned full time to the slowest math students. By giving up his own preparation periods, he manages to see the gifted students twice a week.</p>
        <p>"They could use much more than that," he said. "People don't see the beauty of a child who says, 'I really solved this problem."'</p>
        <p>The school's students are acutely aware of what they are missing. Their conversation is peppered with lists of what they had last year: a full-time science teacher, a creative writing teacher, a school store, smaller classes, clean bathrooms.</p>
        <p>"We're just overwhelmed," said Martha Smith, whose class of 32 sixth graders cannot take science books home at night because there are not enough to go around. "We don't have the supplies we need. We do a lot of group activities in class, and it's hard to keep it under control. When everyone is here, we don't have enough seats." So far this year, Ms. Smith has already spent $400 of her own money to buy supplies such as paper or chalk.</p>
        <p>Her class has been thinking about why so much has changed. "Maybe they think we're not worth it," said Bryant Adderley. Montebello, Calif. Used to Plenty, Shocked by Cuts</p>
        <p>When Vivian Hoorn walked into her classroom this fall, she could not believe what she saw: 45 children staring back at her.</p>
        <p>"I thought, 'Surely they will take half these children away,' " she said.</p>
        <p>But the children were not going anywhere. Budget cuts have pushed class sizes near 40 at Montebello Intermediate School, a school for fifth to eighth graders just east of Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hoorn's class shrank to 38 after several children moved out of the district. She and other teachers are trying to continue the creative teaching methods that have won their school praise in the past. But teachers and students say there is a price.</p>
        <p>"You're too stuffed in," said Danny Nunez, as he sat in his sixth-grade class of 42 students. "You can't get as much attention as you did last year," said Julie Franco. "There are so many kids the teacher has to give to," said Jeannette Sanchez.</p>
        <p>The Montebello school district, struggling with state budget cuts and its own fiscal problems, had to slash spending by 20 percent this fall and may need to cut an additional 10 percent next year. California, especially hard-hit by this recession, has cut education spending by 12 percent after inflation in the past three years, according to Roger Rasmussen, director of the independent analysis unit of the Los Angeles Unified School District.</p>
        <p>Like many other school districts in a state that experienced explosive growth in the 1980's, Montebello drew up its budgets and negotiated multi-year raises with teachers expecting that the good times would roll on. When the recession struck, the district was not prepared for the decline in state aid and is now cutting deeply, according to Montebello's acting superintendent, Darline Robles.</p>
        <p>The district now spends about $4,000 per student, below the national average. Montebello's overwhelmingly Hispanic students come from six towns that range from very poor to affluent.</p>
        <p>The cuts have jolted Montebello Intermediate, which belonged to a district once known for lavishing moeny on its schools. Class sizes soared because the school lost 12 of 58 teachers, including several bilingual teachers whom the principal, Judith L. Petersen, ranked among her best. Clerical and custodial help was cut. A special art program that took children to local museums had to go.</p>
        <p>To Ms. Petersen, who was a student at Montebello in the prosperous 1950's, the cuts are particularly frustrating because she believes that schools now must aim higher than in the past, when many teachers assumed less talented children would drop out.</p>
        <p>"We're keeping kids in schools that when I went to school we didn't manage to keep," she said. "It really breaks my heart to lose our funding when I honestly believe we are so close to making it happen."</p>
        <p>These days at Montebello, truancy is up because the lone remaining attendance officer, Virginia Garcia, is so overrun keeping track of 1,700 students, and the students are betting their parents will not find out they have played hooky.</p>
        <p>Art Revueltas, an assistant principal, dumped an envelope on his desk, and out spilled a gun, several bullets, and a pile of switchblades. So far this year, he has seen three students who told him they had tried to kill themselves, and held up their scarred wrists to prove it.</p>
        <p>"These things still go on, and we have fewer people to deal with them," he said. "We have said we can handle all this if you just give us more money. The public is saying that we still want you to do that, but we are going to give you less. Maybe the social contract we've been living under has been cancelled."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>In New York, a week off for students is a headache for parents. Page B1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
