<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Executive Named to Head Apollo Theater</title>
    <meta content="30APOL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/30/nyregion/30APOL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apollo Theater (Harlem)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aol Time Warner</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Derek Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Harlem</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">englewood</location>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Attorney General</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Harms Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DE153FF933A05750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Executive Named to Head Apollo Theater</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Derek Q Johnson, a top executive of AOL Time Warner, is named president of Apollo Theater, solidifying entertainment conglomerate's control of troubled Harlem landmark (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Q. Johnson, a top executive of AOL Time Warner, was named president of the Apollo Theater yesterday, solidifying the entertainment conglomerate's control of the troubled Harlem landmark.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, 40, said yesterday that he would step down as an AOL Time Warner senior vice president to assume his new post.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Q. Johnson, a top executive of AOL Time Warner, was named president of the Apollo Theater yesterday, solidifying the entertainment conglomerate's control of the troubled Harlem landmark.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, 40, said yesterday that he would step down as an AOL Time Warner senior vice president to assume his new post.</p>
        <p>A former deputy Manhattan borough president, Mr. Johnson is a close associate of Richard D. Parsons, a co-chief operating officer of AOL Time Warner. Mr. Parsons recently became chairman of the nonprofit Apollo Theater Foundation, which runs the state-owned theater.</p>
        <p>Outlining his new role, Mr. Johnson said he would focus on fund-raising and on plans, which are yet to be formulated, to make the 1,500-seat theater part of a major cultural center on 125th Street. The immediate priority, Mr. Johnson said, will be restoring the theater's facade, rehabilitating an adjacent storefront that will house a gift shop, and replacing the marquee.</p>
        <p>The management changes, which were first reported yesterday by The Daily News, represent the final chapter in a long-running legal battle. In 1998, Attorney General Dennis C. Vacco sued the theater and six members of the foundation's board, including Representative Charles B. Rangel, the powerful Harlem congressman who was then the board's chairman, and accused them of mismanaging the Apollo's finances. Mr. Rangel denied wrongdoing, but as part of a settlement with Mr. Vacco's successor, Eliot L. Spitzer, he resigned as chairman and agreed to leave the board at a later date.</p>
        <p>The departure of Mr. Rangel, who was replaced on the board by his wife, Alma, is expected to ease the way for the AOL Time Warner executives to proceed with plans to restore the storied theater and ultimately expand it.</p>
        <p>One longtime board member, Lloyd Williams, the president of the Greater Harlem Chamber of Commerce, praised Mr. Johnson but said some local residents were concerned about an AOL Time Warner ''takeover.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams said Mr. Parsons would have to address the perception among some that his company has too much power over the theater.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parsons, however, said he was well aware of the community's concerns. ''This is hardly a takeover,'' he said. ''Our commitment is to work with the board to revive a community resource.''</p>
        <p>Renovations planned for the theater require approval from the city Landmarks Preservation Commission, which will review the Apollo's proposals on Tuesday. The theater has $5 million available for renovations, but the money must also cover a new sound system and new seats and carpeting, Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>The daily operations of the theater will be left to a new executive director, David D. Rodriguez, the former executive director of the John Harms Center in Englewood, N.J.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
