<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And When He Was Bad, He Certainly Was Busy</title>
    <meta content="30SMIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/30/arts/30SMIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jenney, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Zurich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Zurich</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Soviet Union</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Cornell University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Zucker, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Close, Chuck</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bartlett, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wegman, William</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tucker, Marcia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Joan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D8163FF933A05750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And When He Was Bad, He Certainly Was Busy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews exhibition of Neil Jenney paintings at Gagosian Gallery uptown; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Neil Jenney: The Bad Years, 1969-70,'' at the Gagosian Gallery uptown, is an outstanding exhibition whose title invites a snappy retort: Both of them? Still, in those two years Mr. Jenney helped put representational painting on a new course and established precedents for the art of the 1970's, 80's and 90's in ways that have yet to be fully recognized.</p>
        <p>This show may change that. It brings together more of his ''bad'' paintings than ever before, including several that have never been exhibited. It is his first New York gallery show in a dozen years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Neil Jenney: The Bad Years, 1969-70,'' at the Gagosian Gallery uptown, is an outstanding exhibition whose title invites a snappy retort: Both of them? Still, in those two years Mr. Jenney helped put representational painting on a new course and established precedents for the art of the 1970's, 80's and 90's in ways that have yet to be fully recognized.</p>
        <p>This show may change that. It brings together more of his ''bad'' paintings than ever before, including several that have never been exhibited. It is his first New York gallery show in a dozen years.</p>
        <p>Its title almost reads as a deflationary dig at art-show pretension, a joke made on purpose. After all, the paintings are jokes that work really well, which means that they have their own kind of depth.</p>
        <p>Who is or was Neil Jenney? A precocious, largely self-taught abstract painter, he arrived in New York from Boston in December 1966 and rapidly developed into one of the art world's most independent and reclusive stars, known for playing hardball during his off hours (in a city league) and for refusing gallery representation.</p>
        <p>In the late 1960's and 70's Mr. Jenney became a kind of artistic pace car, a little ahead of the pack but also outside the action in a lane of his own. By 1967, when he was just 22, he was making soft Process Art sculptures and appearing in some of the first exhibitions of the related tendencies -- Process, Conceptual and Body Art -- that came to be called Post-Minimalism. These included ''Earth Art'' at Cornell University, ''When Attitude Becomes Form'' at the Kunsthaus in Zurich and ''Anti-Illusion: Procedures/Materials'' at the Whitney Museum of American Art, all in 1969.</p>
        <p>Yet by then Mr. Jenney had moved on, and he revealed where in his first appearance in a Whitney Biennial, also in 1969: to vaguely representational paintings notable for their haphazard execution and deadpan plays on words and images. Buster Keaton could not have been more droll.</p>
        <p>''Fish and Pole,'' Mr. Jenney's contribution to the 1969 Whitney Biennial, is the first painting at Gagosian, followed by no fewer than 20 like-minded works. The canvas shows a large sketchily painted fish and a broken fishing rod lying in a field of slurred green brush strokes that read as grass. Its title is painted like a punch line in plain white letters across the bottom of its plain black frame. Its buzzy closed circuit of language and image, object and painting can still make you laugh, and then think twice.</p>
        <p>The painting's title pulls apart a familiar phrase: not fishing pole but fish and pole. The resulting two objects evoke an age-old conflict between man and nature in which neither completely wins. We glimpse this inner tension and then glide back to the once-over-lightly surface where paint, image, frame and concept all have an equal weight, one that is light and built for speed.</p>
        <p>In the subsequent paintings the light and speed become a bit monotonous, a well-executed schtick. But the best works bounce the viewer back and forth between surface and depth. The subdivided clichés of their titles frame the seemingly banal images with hints of dark thoughts and irreconcilable differences: conflicts between world powers, men and women, art and society, humans and nature.</p>
        <p>''Them and Us'' shows two jets, one with the insignia of the United States, the other with that of the Soviet Union, flying side by side on a surface of drippy blue. ''Brushed and Broomed'' compares the results of a freshly wielded paintbrush and broom: contrasting a pile of dust with some red brush strokes on the wall, not intended to overjoy whoever is cleaning up. ''Here and There,'' a  widely reproduced work, is nothing but a crisp white fence, a worldly descendant of the Minimalist grid, dividing the greensward in half. ''Trees and Lumber'' shows several rows of a pine forest; the trees on the left are standing, and those on the right are identical to them except that they have been cut down.</p>
        <p>Made at a time when most young artists were avoiding either representation or painting, Mr. Jenney embraced both and put them together in a new way. It was immediately identifiable as post-Pop; today it also looks Post-Conceptual, and ahead of its time. In the thick of the Conceptualist moment, he pronounced painting not only viable but also capable of absorbing all the non- or anti-painting strategies around it.</p>
        <p>He wasn't alone. Joe Zucker, Chuck Close and Jennifer Bartlett had a similar process-oriented approach, which broke down painted images into their component parts and procedures. Some of Ree Morton's work had a similar objectness. And William Wegman was combining words and image with flat-footed American humor.</p>
        <p>But in doing all these things at once, Mr. Jenney may have been unmatched. In 1978 Marcia Tucker, who had organized the Whitney's ''Anti-Illusion'' exhibition, built a show called '' 'Bad' Painting'' around his 1969-70 paintings, along with the work of Joan Brown, William N. Copley and Mr. Wegman, at the fledgling New Museum of Contemporary Art. The same year Richard Marshall included them in ''New Image Painting,'' a largely forgotten trendlet that preceded American Neo-Expressionism.</p>
        <p>By then Mr. Jenney was otherwise engaged. In 1971 he began developing a painstaking hyperrealism that both built on and contradicted his ''bad'' paintings. The Gagosian show finishes with three of these works as well as some fairly lame canvases silk-screened with aphorisms, which are best taken as oblique artist's statements. ''Style Is Technique Plus Symbolism,'' begins the most pertinent.</p>
        <p>The paintings' titled black frames, now thickened and elaborately customized to the point of seeming bunkerlike, persist. Not surprisingly, nature is a dominant theme. ''Atmosphere'' (1984-92) and ''Morning'' (1996) are gorgeous skylike monochromes, modernist additions to Hudson River School painting.</p>
        <p>The most interesting work, and a new one, is ''North America Divided'' (1992-99), which shows the sheared surface of a large tree stump seen through the top of a rickety split-rail gate and a bit of corroded electric fence. In it Mr. Jenney seems to retrieve some of his ''bad'' painting's surface weirdness and inner tensions. The realism is almost northern European in its perfection, but the forms are all carefully textured, minutely sculptural, oddly American.</p>
        <p>In front of this dour yet exquisite painting, the Civil War, manifest destiny and the cost of human progress flicker across the brain. So does the question of how long it will be before Mr. Jenney shows new work again.</p>
        <p>''Neil Jenney: The 'Bad' Years, 1969-70'' is at the Gagosian Gallery, 980 Madison Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 744-2313, through April 13.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
