<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Around the World in 71 Days or Less</title>
    <meta content="03BOAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/03/sports/othersports/03BOAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1364787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trophee Jules Verne</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Around-the-World Trips</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brest (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Kersauson, Olivier</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Peyron, Bruno</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DA123DF930A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Around the World in 71 Days or Less</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Around the World, Hoping for 71 Days or Less</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former French radio personality Olivier de Kersauson will sail 110-foot trimaran in race for fastest nonstop voyage around world, competing for Trophee Jules Verne; race begins and ends at French port of Brest; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aboard a 110-foot trimaran named after an American Indian, Geronimo, 11 French sailors are preparing for one wild ride. Fittingly, Geronimo's captain -- the five-time circumnavigator and the former French radio personality Olivier de Kersauson -- has a bit of cowboy in him.</p>
        <p>''I like Geronimo; he would never accept surrender,'' said de Kersauson from Paris in a telephone interview last week. ''I think this value is a good one for me. I like people who don't surrender.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aboard a 110-foot trimaran named after an American Indian, Geronimo, 11 French sailors are preparing for one wild ride.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aboard a 110-foot trimaran named after an American Indian, Geronimo, 11 French sailors are preparing for one wild ride. Fittingly, Geronimo's captain -- the five-time circumnavigator and the former French radio personality Olivier de Kersauson -- has a bit of cowboy in him.</p>
        <p>''I like Geronimo; he would never accept surrender,'' said de Kersauson from Paris in a telephone interview last week. ''I think this value is a good one for me. I like people who don't surrender.''</p>
        <p>Later this month, de Kersauson and his crew will set out from France to compete again for the Trophée Jules Verne, an award emblematic of the fastest nonstop voyage around the world beginning and ending at the French port of Brest.</p>
        <p>De Kersauson, the current record holder for the passage, in 1997 circled the globe in 71 days 14 hours aboard a trimaran. His plan is not only to better that mark, but also to obliterate it. ''Maybe we can make something around 60 days,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Jules Verne concept was the brainchild of another French multihull star, Bruno Peyron. When Peyron made his first attempt in 1993 with the American sailor Cam Lewis among his crew, he hoped to complete the trip in fewer than 80 days. He did so with 16 hours to spare.</p>
        <p>A year later, the New Zealand sailor Peter Blake took five more days off the record, lowering it to 74 days and change.</p>
        <p>Blake and Peyron both employed big catamarans for their offshore exploits. Peyron went on to become the founder of The Race, last year's round-the-world marathon that was won by yet another cat, Club Med. In fact, the entire fleet was made up of giant catamarans.</p>
        <p>And Peyron has taken one of those catamarans, renamed it Orange after a French telephone concern, and will also begin another Jules Verne attempt this month.</p>
        <p>In this world of rugged offshore sailing, it seems only de Kersauson believes three hulls are better than two. It is not a point he presses too hard, however.</p>
        <p>''On a trimaran you have all the compression working on the main, central hull, while on a cat you have the compression of the rigging and the sails working on the crossbeam that is attaching the hulls together, and that's important,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''But I don't think one boat is better than the other,'' he added. ''In some conditions it'd be better to be in a cat, in some it would be better in a tri.''</p>
        <p>At 57, de Kersauson is the elder statesman of the French offshore sailing scene. His career began in the mid-1960's when he signed on as first mate to the legendary Frenchman Eric Tabarly, who was fresh off his historic victory in the 1964 singlehanded transatlantic race.</p>
        <p>It turned out to be an invaluable eight-year apprenticeship.</p>
        <p>''I was very happy and very proud to be sailing with him,'' de Kersauson said. ''We were discovering the world, he was always pushing hard and wanting to race. It was a great chance to be sailing such a lot of different boats with such a captain.''</p>
        <p>De Kersauson credits Tabarly with opening the doors for himself and many other young French sailors. ''He was a hero,'' he said. ''He was as well known as Bridget Bardot. After Tabarly, there was a lot of interesting sailing in France and it was easy for a boat bum like me to find sponsors for a racing boat.''</p>
        <p>Between races, de Kersauson enjoyed a long if slightly sporadic career as host of a radio show that covered many topics, though none too seriously. ''Sometimes it was very funny, sometimes less,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It paid very well and I did it for years,'' said de Kersauson, who retired three years ago. ''It let me have a life of adventure without being born with silver in my mouth.''</p>
        <p>While de Kersauson has many years, if not decades, over many of his younger crewmen, he does not see his age as a disadvantage. ''I am intellectually very fit,'' he said, laughing. ''Of course I am not as strong physically as I was when I was 35, but I'm still stronger than a lot of men that age.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, de Kersauson enjoys what he is doing more than ever. After the Jules Verne attempt, he has laid out an ambitious three-year plan that will take him and Geronimo on races and record attempts all over the world.</p>
        <p>''As long as I have my teeth I have to eat,'' he said. It was a mixed metaphor of sorts, but the point was clear. He is, therefore he sails.</p>
        <p>''If everything works out I will be at sea nine months a year which is perfect for me,'' he said. ''I am happy when I'm sailing. I like to read the sea, to try and understand my meteorological future. I think driving a boat is something that's beautiful and perfect. I love it.''</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
