<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Louisiana Opening Offers Chance to Recast a Shaky Relationship With Washington</title>
    <meta content="22louisiana" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/22/us/22louisiana.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Breaux, John B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blanco, Kathleen Babineaux (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nossiter, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blanco, Kathleen Babineaux</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DA1430F931A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Louisiana Opening Offers Chance to Recast a Shaky Relationship With Washington</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Louisiana Opening Offers Chance to Recast a Shaky Relationship With Washington</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NOSSITER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nossiter, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, March 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis says with Louisiana Gov Kathleen Babineaux Blanco decision not to run for re-election reflects her standing shredded by post-Hurricane Katrina failures; she is highest profile victim to date of storm's political fallout; many Democrats suggest former senator John B Breaux could be her possible successor; Breaux is Congressional veteran who has dual identity as creature both of Washington and Louisiana, offering possible transformation in poor way skeptical Congress and federal bureaucracy view state (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since Hurricane Katrina, Louisiana has been a needy ward of Washington, though rarely a cooperative or cheerful one.</p>
        <p>With Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco's political exit this week, the dysfunctional relationship, so vital to the battered state but so marginal to the capital, could shift sharply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco’s political exit this week, the dysfunctional relationship between Louisiana and Washington, could shift sharply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since Hurricane Katrina, Louisiana has been a needy ward of Washington, though rarely a cooperative or cheerful one.</p>
        <p>With Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco's political exit this week, the dysfunctional relationship, so vital to the battered state but so marginal to the capital, could shift sharply.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blanco, her standing shredded by post-Katrina failures, announced Tuesday that she would not run for re-election, becoming the highest-profile victim to date of the storm's political fallout. Enter -- possibly -- John B. Breaux, the former senator whom many Democrats all over the state are suggesting as the governor's possible successor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breaux has been coy about his intentions in this fall's race. It is clear, though, that his main asset in a possible race would be a background precisely the opposite of the incumbent's: a lifetime of experience in the ways of Washington, as well as a hand permanently extended across the party aisle.</p>
        <p>His dual identity as a creature both of Washington and of the Louisiana swamps could appeal to voters weary of the state's wars with Washington, offering a possible transformation in the way a hitherto skeptical Congress and federal bureaucracy have viewed this stepchild state.</p>
        <p>Louisiana, the balky aid recipient, is like some far-flung subtropical possession the government cannot quite ignore. It is still hugely dependent on Washington for housing reconstruction money, infrastructure replacement and protection from storms and criminals. Rancor and partisan speech-making, as practiced by Ms. Blanco, Mayor C. Ray Nagin of New Orleans and other officials, have so far not served it especially well.</p>
        <p>Few doubt that Mr. Breaux, a Cajun deal maker of legendary smoothness, would bring an entirely different approach. Republicans have begun attacking him even before any announcement of his candidacy, demonstrating its potential potency.</p>
        <p>''What Breaux brings is 'cred,' '' said the veteran Louisiana pollster and political consultant Elliott Stonecipher. Mr. Breaux ''brings, from the outside view, all the things Louisiana doesn't have,'' he added.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mr. Breaux, now a lobbyist with the top Washington firm Patton Boggs, released a statement saying merely that he was ''seriously evaluating what is best for Louisiana, and determining whether I can be helpful for the state as a candidate for governor.'' He added that he would make a decision ''in the near future.''</p>
        <p>The leading Republican, Representative Bobby Jindal, is also well placed in Washington, having worked as an assistant secretary in the Department of Health and Human Services under President Bush and led a bipartisan commission seeking changes for Medicare.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Breaux has been in Washington since before Mr. Jindal was born, starting in 1968 as an aide to the man he later replaced in the House, the future governor (and later convicted felon) Edwin W. Edwards, a fellow native of the Cajun region of Louisiana.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breaux served 14 years in the House and then 18 in the Senate, along the way earning a reputation as the Democrat perhaps most willing to compromise with Republicans on taxes, social spending, health care and other contentious issues, to the sometimes ill-suppressed irritation of fellow party members. Mr. Breaux always said he was more interested in passing legislation than in scoring political points.</p>
        <p>He played tennis with the previous President Bush, was courted as a potential energy secretary by the current president, and once joked, after a trade-off with the administration early in the Reagan era, that though his vote was not for sale ''it is available for rent.''</p>
        <p>It is unlikely that, were Mr. Breaux stuck in the sort of permanent negotiations with Washington that is now the lot of Louisiana officials, he would resort to the blustering warfare that Ms. Blanco has sometimes practiced.</p>
        <p>Just last month, the governor blasted Washington Republicans as having ''discriminated'' against ''our people.'' The remarks drew a quick, sharp retort from Mr. Bush's emissary to the region, Donald E. Powell, said to have been deeply angered.</p>
        <p>In the past week, federal officials threw Ms. Blanco's entourage into a panic when they said Louisiana was breaking rules by doling out housing aid money for the Road Home program in small allotments instead of giving homeowners the option of getting lump sums.</p>
        <p>The program has been widely criticized as being too slow in making grants to desperate homeowners. After hurried negotiations in Washington, state officials agreed this week to change the rules, allowing homeowners without mortgages to get lump-sum payments of up to $150,000. The state's lack of savvy in dealing with Washington was pointed up again.</p>
        <p>Yet the Washington savvy with which Mr. Breaux is widely credited carries its own pitfalls here, too, in a peculiar election year in which beleaguered local voters are more fed up, and more ready for change, than perhaps at any time since the desperate Huey Long years of the Great Depression. Mr. Breaux represents skill, but he also symbolizes the political establishment.</p>
        <p>''In a year of reform, John Breaux is a clear personification of Louisiana's history, not its future,'' said Mr. Stonecipher, the consultant.</p>
        <p>And in a year when voters here may be looking for something ''radical,'' said another veteran Louisiana political consultant, Raymond D. Strother, ''I don't know that the relationship with Washington is as important as offering hope.''</p>
        <p>While saying that Mr. Breaux is a ''loved and popular figure in Louisiana,'' Mr. Strother added that he ''will represent the status quo unless he can find a way to become an agent of change.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
