<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Head to Head Over the Prosecutors</title>
    <meta content="l22prosecutors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1834719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDC1430F931A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Head to Head Over the Prosecutors</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush in Conflict With Lawmakers on Prosecutors'' (front page, March 21):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush in Conflict With Lawmakers on Prosecutors'' (front page, March 21):</p>
        <p>When the commission investigating the 9/11 attacks compromised with the White House and allowed the president and the vice president to be interviewed together, off the record and not under oath, the country lost an opportunity to learn the truth about the machinations of the government before the attacks.</p>
        <p>In a similar way, President Bush is now seeking a similar compromise to hide information from the Congress about the role the White House played in the untimely firings of the eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>This is not the time for another compromise with the president. If the executive branch of the government defies any subpoenas issued by Senate Judiciary Committee calling for testimony of employees of the White House, under oath with transcripts, and the committee persists in demanding the testimony, the president said he was willing to go to court over the matter.</p>
        <p>Only the Supreme Court can decide whether the president can meet the demands of the Congress on his own terms and with a limited selection of documents, or whether the legislative branch of government can uncover the truth about such matters as the White House involvement in the firings of the attorneys.</p>
        <p>Burton Kreindel  Newton, Mass., March 21, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The president's reaction to a formal Congressional inquiry into the matter of the fired United States attorneys is puzzling. He objects to ''a partisan fishing expedition aimed at honorable public servants.'' But isn't that what led to the firings in the first place?</p>
        <p>Gerard Farrell  Summit, N.J., March 21, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''What People Really Need'' (editorial, March 21):</p>
        <p>The truth is so obvious that if the Bush administration weren't so oblivious, it would be embarrassed by its blatant indication of intent to lie.</p>
        <p>Anyone who is afraid to testify under oath or to have records of his testimony available is shouting from the rafters that truth will not be forthcoming.</p>
        <p>Let us hope that in this instance spin will not replace reality and that we will be able to force out the truth by legitimate Congressional functioning.</p>
        <p>Ruth Karter  Coconut Creek, Fla., March 21, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Why I Was Fired'' (Op-Ed, March 21) :</p>
        <p>David C. Iglesias, the United States attorney for the District of New Mexico from October 2001 through last month, writes, ''Only a written retraction by the Justice Department setting the record straight regarding my performance would settle the issue for me.''</p>
        <p>As an American citizen, I believe that nothing short of a full, open investigation with all players in this debacle testifying under oath would set the record straight for me.</p>
        <p>Chris Fives  Basking Ridge, N.J., March 21, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
