<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Retailers Go to Self-Service, New Products Raise Questions</title>
    <meta content="18FLAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/18/business/18FLAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1512998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">High-Definition Television (Hdtv)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Panasonic Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television Sets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sharp Electronics</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sharp Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Panasonic Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DC1330F93BA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Retailers Go to Self-Service, New Products Raise Questions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Retailers Go to Self-Service, New Products Raise Questions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Television makers are unhappy with shift in electronics retailing away from commissioned sales clerks to hourly workers, who they do now think have know-how to sell their high-priced but technologically complex sets, such as those for high-definition television and or with flat-panel displays; Panasonic is putting more product information on its Web site and even in its cartons as result; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has the television sales clerk been eliminated at just the wrong time?</p>
        <p>Nearly all of the major electronics dealers have moved to a self-service format with hourly workers. The reasoning is that commissioned sales clerks, who could make as much as $100,000 a year, are overkill if they are selling $50 DVD players or $250 digital cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has the television sales clerk been eliminated at just the wrong time?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Has the television sales clerk been eliminated at just the wrong time?</p>
        <p>Nearly all of the major electronics dealers have moved to a self-service format with hourly workers. The reasoning is that commissioned sales clerks, who could make as much as $100,000 a year, are overkill if they are selling $50 DVD players or $250 digital cameras.</p>
        <p>But the next hot consumer electronics product is digital television. There is a growing demand because of the advent of high-definition broadcasts and sleek new flat-panel display formats. With prices from $500 to $10,000 and technology that is still confusing, digital TV's might well be tailor-made for a traditional sales floor with personal service.</p>
        <p>''As the top players become more similar, here is a great opportunity for people like us with a trained sales force,'' said Kenneth R. Weller, chief executive of Good Guys, a West Coast electronics chain. The chain can doubly benefit, he said, because people who buy big televisions can be talked into buying new surround-sound systems and other services.</p>
        <p>TV makers are mourning the move to self-service, even as they ship more and more products to the mass retailers.</p>
        <p>''I went to Circuit City because I was waited on'' before it changed its sales strategy, said Rick Calacci, senior vice president of Sharp Electronics, a unit of the Sharp Corporation. Sharp Electronics is the leading maker of LCD, a type of flat-screen television. It now gives its latest models first to dealers with ''assisted sales floors'' that know how to talk customers up to more expensive products, he said.</p>
        <p>To cope with fewer commissioned sales clerks, Panasonic, a unit of the Matsushita Electric Industrial Company, has put more product information on its Web site and even in its cartons. ''We want to make our television box so attractive and appealing, with all the features easy to comprehend, that you can make a decision even if it is piled on a shelf in a Wal-Mart or Costco,'' said Merwan Mereby, Panasonic's director for sales planning.</p>
        <p>Best Buy and Circuit City respond that their hourly employees are still trained in product details and that customers prefer a lower-pressure environment. Both are rearranging their sales floors to make space for flat-screen televisions so customers can see and decide what they want for themselves.</p>
        <p>''We are going to have such a large assortment of televisions that people will say, 'I can't shop for a television unless I come here,' '' W. Alan McCollough, the chief executive of Circuit City, said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
