<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blacks and Jews Join Hands for a Brighter Future</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="577317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACIAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HASIDISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HARLEM (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CROWN HEIGHTS (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LUBAVITCH MOVEMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, ARI L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, JESSE L (REV)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service"></object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LIBERATORS: FIGHTING ON TWO FRONTS IN WORLD WAR II (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hasidism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA1F3AF93BA25751C1A964958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blacks and Jews Join Hands for a Brighter Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARI L. GOLDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDMAN, ARI L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than 18 months of racial and ethnic unrest, Jews and blacks joined hands last night in an emotional session at Harlem's historic Apollo Theater to recall their past alliances and pray for future healing.</p>
        <p>The reason for the gathering was the showing of a documentary on the black soldiers who liberated Jews from Nazi concentration camps at the end of World War II. But the real drama occurred on the great stage of the Apollo after the house lights came up and Jews and blacks hugged, wept, held hands and vowed to put their differences behind them. Jackson and Dinkins Speak</p>
        <p>It was an emotional catharsis that included the singing of "We Shall Overcome," personal reminiscences from the Rev. Jesse Jackson and Mayor David N. Dinkins's quoting the great Talmudic sage Hillel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than 18 months of racial and ethnic unrest, Jews and blacks joined hands last night in an emotional session at Harlem's historic Apollo Theater to recall their past alliances and pray for future healing.</p>
        <p>The reason for the gathering was the showing of a documentary on the black soldiers who liberated Jews from Nazi concentration camps at the end of World War II. But the real drama occurred on the great stage of the Apollo after the house lights came up and Jews and blacks hugged, wept, held hands and vowed to put their differences behind them. Jackson and Dinkins Speak</p>
        <p>It was an emotional catharsis that included the singing of "We Shall Overcome," personal reminiscences from the Rev. Jesse Jackson and Mayor David N. Dinkins's quoting the great Talmudic sage Hillel.</p>
        <p>Those at the Apollo last night seemed weary of the fighting and eager to come together, nodding and applauding as the Mayor quoted the first-century Jewish scholar by asking, "If not now, when?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson, who first suggested that the film, "Liberators: Fighting on Two Fronts in World War II," be used as a vehicle for reconcilliation , said, "The walls that came down in Dachau and Buchenwald must not be resurrected in Crown Heights or any place."</p>
        <p>As he spoke, he reached out for the hands with those around him. At one point he held tight to Rabbi Leib Glanz, an official of the Satmar Hasidic group, which is based in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. At another he clasped the hand of Abe Chapnick, a concentration camp survivor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson, who angered Jews in 1984 when he called New York City "Hymietown," spoke softly and haltingly as he implored the group to remember it was bound by historic links. His appearance was one of several recently in which he has reached out to the Jewish community.</p>
        <p>As the film was shown at the Apollo last night before an invited audience of 1,200, it was also viewed by gatherings of blacks and Jews at more than 100 other locations around the city, including synagogues, churches and private living rooms.</p>
        <p>At the Apollo, the audience members included the Rev. Al Sharpton; Betty Shabazz, the widow of Malcolm X; Felix Rohatyn, the financier; Peggy Tishman of the Jewish Community Relations Council, Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem and Robert M. Morgenthau, the Manhattan District Attorney.</p>
        <p>"We intend to go on the moral offensive," Mr. Jackson told the crowd, "and take this message to the nation. We will defeat hatred and fear and violence."</p>
        <p>"The pain and violence surrounding Crown Heights is a challenge to come together, not to fall apart."</p>
        <p>After Mr. Jackson spoke, Rabbi Glanz prayed for healing, saying, "Let us have peace and show the world that we all have backgrounds where we suffered. Let us say to suffering, enough is enough."</p>
        <p>Rabbi Glanz's Satmar group was among those who met with Mayor Dinkins at a tense private meeting in Crown Heights on Wednesday. The primary group in Brooklyn neighborhood, the Lubavitch, had no major officials at the Apollo, although several Lubavitch followers attended.</p>
        <p>A Jewish communal official who spoke on the condition of anonymity said that tickets had been set aside for Lubavitch officials but that they declined to attend, saying that they did not feel that enough progress had been made at the Wednesday meeting to warrant their attendance.</p>
        <p>Several of the speakers at the Apollo last night recalled the great alliance between blacks and Jews. Symbols of that alliance, they said, included the tragic -- like the murder of three civil rights workers, two Jews and one black, in Philadelphia, Miss., in 1964 -- and the triumphant, the march through Selma, Ala., in which the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. was joined by a host of rabbis.</p>
        <p>The focus of the evening was the encounter between two black Army units, the 761st Tank Batallion and the 183d Combat Engineers, and the emaciated, hollow-eyed survivors of Buchenwald. As one survivor, Rabbi Yisrael M. Lau, now the chief rabbi of Tel Aviv, said in the film, "To us, they looked like angels."</p>
        <p>Ms. Tishman called on the audience to "symbolically re-enact that moment of reconciliation and brotherhood."</p>
        <p>"Not simply to rekindle, but to refuel the lamp of brotherhood in this city," she said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins received a standing ovation when he took the podium to introduce the movie. He said that "images and words have been used to great harm" in the city, and that "it is our task to use them to heal."</p>
        <p>The work of reconciliaton, he said, "will take more than one film and one evening." And he called the night at the Apollo "the first volley in a long campaign."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
