<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Olympian Adds Harrowing Tale to Repertory</title>
    <meta content="27gardner" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/27/sports/othersports/27gardner.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WRESTLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Utah</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gardner, Rulon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D81E3EF934A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Olympian Adds Harrowing Tale to Repertory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Olympian Adds a Harrowing Tale to List</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the small plane he was flying in hit the water in a remote part of Lake Powell in southern Utah on Saturday, Rulon Gardner said, his first thought was that it was a dream.</p>
        <p>Gardner, who won a gold medal in Greco-Roman wrestling at the 2000 Olympics with a stunning victory over the three-time Olympic champion Aleksandr Karelin of Russia, had already survived two accidents. In 2002, he was stranded in the wilderness overnight while snowmobiling in Wyoming; two years later, he was hit by a car while riding a motorcycle in Colorado Springs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Survival in extreme circumstances has become a habit for Rulon Gardner, who won a stunning victory in wrestling at the 2000 Olympics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the small plane he was flying in hit the water in a remote part of Lake Powell in southern Utah on Saturday, Rulon Gardner said, his first thought was that it was a dream.</p>
        <p>Gardner, who won a gold medal in Greco-Roman wrestling at the 2000 Olympics with a stunning victory over the three-time Olympic champion Aleksandr Karelin of Russia, had already survived two accidents. In 2002, he was stranded in the wilderness overnight while snowmobiling in Wyoming; two years later, he was hit by a car while riding a motorcycle in Colorado Springs.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, he was in a single-engine plane with two pilots, Randy and Leslie Brooks, brothers from American Fork, Utah, who were taking him to look at a houseboat.</p>
        <p>They were flying low over the lake when the plane suddenly dived and hit the water.</p>
        <p>''I thought, This is not possible,'' Gardner said in a telephone interview yesterday from his home in Utah. ''This kind of thing doesn't happen twice.''</p>
        <p>The plane crashed Saturday afternoon and Gardner, 35, and the pilots plunged into 44-degree water, according to the authorities in Garfield County, Utah. They evacuated the plane before it sank, and Gardner said they swam for more than an hour to shore. They huddled overnight on a beach in Good Hope Bay before being rescued by a bass fisherman Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>Leslie Brooks was admitted to a local hospital and treated for frostbite to his feet. The other two had no injuries.</p>
        <p>''I'm actually doing very, very well,'' said Gardner, who had to have a toe amputated because of frostbite after the 2002 incident. ''My arms are a little sore.''</p>
        <p>Lake Powell, a reservoir, is 186 miles long and has nearly 2,000 miles of shoreline, including many remote canyons. According to Kevin Schneider, a spokesman for the Glen Canyon National Recreation Area, the plane is believed to have crashed about 30 miles by boat from the nearest hint of civilization, the Bullfrog Marina. That is where the fisherman took the three after they were found.</p>
        <p>At this time of year, boat traffic on the lake is very light, he said, making it more unlikely that they would be found quickly.</p>
        <p>''They are very fortunate to be alive,'' Schneider said. ''They had three things that could have killed them. No. 1, a plane crash. Second, swimming more than an hour to shore, and No. 3, spending a night wet and cold in basically freezing temperatures. They were 3 for 3.''</p>
        <p>Survival skills have become a habit for Gardner, who gathered rocks on the beach to give them some protection from the wind, then told the Brookses they should all huddle together to conserve body heat through the night.</p>
        <p>Gardner said that during the swim to shore, he needed constant encouragement from the Brookses. Gardner, at 6 feet 2 inches and nearly 300 pounds, said he was not a strong swimmer.</p>
        <p>''They were the reason I lived through the swimming, because I thought, I'm done,'' he said. ''I would not be here if it weren't for them encouraging me.''</p>
        <p>Gardner is used to being the inspirational one. His victory at the Sydney Games was one of the greatest upsets in Olympic history. He handed Karelin the only defeat of his 13-year international career, winning by 1-0 in the gold medal match of the Greco-Roman superheavyweight division.</p>
        <p>With that, Gardner, the youngest of nine children who grew up on a farm in Afton, Wyo., became an instant folk hero. The fame did not change him much; his matter-of-fact personality simply made him all the more appealing as a sports star.</p>
        <p>His story took on an even more improbable dimension after he survived being stranded in the wilderness in 2002, when he became separated from friends during a snowmobiling outing.</p>
        <p>He continued his wrestling career despite having had his toe amputated. At the 2004 Olympics, he won a bronze medal and left his shoes on the mat in a tearful scene that announced his retirement.</p>
        <p>Since then, Gardner has made a career of motivational speaking and coaching at wrestling clinics.</p>
        <p>In the past year, Gardner has also been studying to be a pilot. He said that he was one test from earning his license as a private pilot and that his ordeal over the weekend had not deterred him from wanting to fly.</p>
        <p>''You just try to make the best decisions you can,'' Gardner said. ''You just take life as it comes to you and do your best.''</p>
        <p>WRESTLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
