<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lost Amid Change? Take a Number</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="785368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBER, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED61538F93BA1575BC0A963958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lost Amid Change? Take a Number</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEBER, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's usually the business people who get upset when a longstanding area code is suddenly changed: all the stationery and business cards that need to be reprinted, all the computerized phone equipment that needs adjustment. It costs money.</p>
        <p>For an ordinary person with a phone, the irritation is subtler but more unsettling. It's like an eviction from one's psychic address, no small disruption in a world that seems ever more bent on isolating its inhabitants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's usually the business people who get upset when a longstanding area code is suddenly changed: all the stationery and business cards that need to be reprinted, all the computerized phone equipment that needs adjustment. It costs money.</p>
        <p>For an ordinary person with a phone, the irritation is subtler but more unsettling. It's like an eviction from one's psychic address, no small disruption in a world that seems ever more bent on isolating its inhabitants.</p>
        <p>To many people, modern life seems fundamentally rootless; all our institutions -- the family, the school, the church -- appear to have crumbling foundations. The two-party system of government is in flux. Corporations are in a perennially diversifying, fragmenting mode. The networks aren't the networks any more; they aren't even what they were a month ago. Baseball players move indiscriminately from one team to another; our loyalties, as Jerry Seinfeld has pointed out, are no longer to teams but to uniforms.</p>
        <p>Of course, this is dehumanizing. People need things to count on, to believe in, to go home to, figuratively speaking. Untethered, they freak, gain weight, join cults. This is where the concept of psychic address becomes crucial; that is, your area code, your ZIP code, your bank code, your computer entry code, your Social Security number and half a dozen other cryptographic series that you know by heart and use every day now serve as the currency of identity. In the ever-advancing technological era, these are numbers that distinguish you in the world, that locate you on civilization's grid as someone who lives somewhere, works somewhere, has money somewhere, is a citizen somewhere, maybe even owns a few things.</p>
        <p>Call me (212), or 10012 or 676988321.</p>
        <p>Nice to meet you.</p>
        <p>Unlike most numbers, however, the area code is fundamentally friendly. Three digits nestled inside their parentheses, they make their owner a part of a community. They connect people, gather them in a collective embrace. In the modern world, the area code is as defining as a tribe; we are the "203" people, Connecticut residents have always been able to say.</p>
        <p>No more. That is why sympathy for those people of Hartford, among the 48 percent of Connecticut's populace that is losing the area code that has been its since 1947, and for like sufferers of recent years in places like Vancouver, Wash.; Tucson, Ariz., and even London, is not misplaced. And that explains the move by the municipal government in Schaumburg, Ill., to sue Ameritech, the local phone service supplier, over a plan that would give Schaumburg two area codes. (Though, truth be told, litigiousness is no solution for the alienated.)</p>
        <p>A brand new area code defines a new region, makes you suddenly an immigrant in the place in which you have lived for years. It can be divisive. When 212 became 718 in Brooklyn, Queens, and, more recently, the Bronx, outrage reigned, as though the phone company had dissociated those boroughs from New York City, defining them as provincial Manhattanites had been doing disdainfully for years: the outer boroughs.</p>
        <p>Generations ago, there were operators: "Eula Mae, get me Floyd down at the filling station." Then there were exchanges that meant something, threw a spotlight on a neighborhood: BUtterfield 8, MUrray Hill 7, SUsquehanna 9. Gone. Area codes, of course, never meant anything. And it is perhaps a poignant sign of the times that now when random digits disappear from people's lives they are mourned. You can hear it in people's voices when they answer the phone, less these days with eagerness and anticipation and warmth than plaintiveness and uncertainty: "Hello?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
