<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. TRADE DEFICIT SOARS TO RECORD</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="750554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALANCE OF PAYMENTS AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANGER, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DE1F3EF930A15750C0A963958260" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. TRADE DEFICIT SOARS TO RECORD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANGER, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an ominous sign for the economy and the Clinton Administration, the nation's trade deficit soared by two-thirds in January to a record $12.23 billion.</p>
        <p>There was strong evidence that the United States' usual imbalance, caused largely by Asian nations that export far more to this country than they buy in return, was being worsened as Mexico, recently a major importer of American goods, plunged deeper into economic crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an ominous sign for the economy and the Clinton Administration, the nation's trade deficit soared by two-thirds in January to a record $12.23 billion.</p>
        <p>There was strong evidence that the United States' usual imbalance, caused largely by Asian nations that export far more to this country than they buy in return, was being worsened as Mexico, recently a major importer of American goods, plunged deeper into economic crisis.</p>
        <p>The severity of the trade gap reported today by the Commerce Department took the Clinton Administration by surprise. Although the dollar fell to a record low of 89 Japanese yen in New York trading, the decline was relatively modest, given the big jump in the deficit.</p>
        <p>Still, the White House is particularly concerned, several Administration officials acknowledged, because a further deterioration in trade could keep the dollar weak. And if the economy slows as expected later this year, it could open the door to Republicans to attack what has been the Administration's stronghold: a healthy economy.</p>
        <p>The exceptionally big trade deficit in January was the largest number ever reported, but it is hard to be absolutely sure that it exceeded all previous months because the Commerce Department recently changed its method of calculation.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the big jump in the trade deficit can also be seen as a measure of the economy's continued strength. Imports continued to climb, reflecting strong consumer demand. But exports declined even faster.</p>
        <p>What's worse is that the latest figures make clear that predictions about the fallout from the collapse of the Mexican peso are already coming to pass. Mexico, which has helped compensate for a chronic trade deficit with Asia, is now beginning to help widen the gap. Today's numbers are expected to be the first in a long series of Mexican trade surpluses with the United States as the steep devaluation of the peso hurts America's third-largest export market.</p>
        <p>The trade gap with Mexico was $863 million in January after a $19 million surplus in December. Such figures seem certain to worsen: Some economists are expecting a deficit with Mexico of $15 billion or more this year as a recession caused by Mexico's economic austerity plan begins to bite into that country's imports. But the White House can hardly complain about the Mexican austerity plan, because its Treasury Department wrote much of it.</p>
        <p>"Mexico has to run a big trade surplus with us if this plan has a chance of working," a senior Administration official said recently. "But it is not going to be easy to explain that to workers in Texas or California."</p>
        <p>Until recently, the Administration was boasting that 700,000 new jobs had been created in the last year because of increased trade with Mexico. Now, no one in the Administration wants to speculate, at least publicly, about what could happen to many of those jobs in the next year.</p>
        <p>"We're seeing a lot of bad things happen simultaneously," said Lawrence Chimerine, the chief economist of the Economic Strategy Institute, a Washington research organization that advocates a more aggressive trade stance. "In a few months this is going to be a political issue again, and an issue of economic growth."</p>
        <p>Yet trade has hardly been mentioned in the months since the Republicans took control of both houses of Congress. That is little surprise at a time of continued economic expansion and low unemployment. But it usually flares up as a political issue as soon as there is any evidence of economic slowdown in which critics can argue that imports are costing American jobs.</p>
        <p>The quandary for the Clinton Administration is that the classic economic solution for a big trade gap -- a weaker dollar that makes American exports less expensive abroad and imports more expensive -- could not only prove to be a political liability but is also unlikely to provide any relief this time around.</p>
        <p>Already, the dollar's low levels against the German mark and the yen are hurting American prestige. So the Administration is hardly in a position to push the dollar lower. And even if it wanted to, the weak dollar is unlikely to help American exporters in the markets that count the most: Japan, Mexico, Canada and China.</p>
        <p>For reasons that are as complex and confused as the trading relationship between Tokyo and Washington, the deficit with Japan has been virtually immune to currency shifts. The two countries have been trying for a decade to narrow the trade gap, only to find the effort frustrated by Japanese trade barriers, an inability by Detroit to overcome Japan's advantage in the automobile industry that accounts for much of the gap, and a low American savings rate, which requires constant injections of capital from abroad to finance both private investment and Government borrowing.</p>
        <p>In fact, Japan was one of the few bright spots in today's trade report, with the deficit in the trade in goods -- a figure that excludes increasingly important American services like insurance and telecommunications -- declining to $4.86 billion, from $5.55 billion in December. But that decline was almost certainly a temporary result of the Kobe earthquake, which paralyzed one of Japan's busiest ports. Most Japanese companies have since worked out alternative routes for their exports.</p>
        <p>Nor is the growing deficit with China, which jumped by a third in January to $2.72 billion, likely to be affected by the weakness of the dollar. China's currency loosely follows the dollar, as do the currencies of many of the Southeast Asian nations that also run large trade surpluses with the United States. And while the dollar is weak in comparison with the yen and the mark, it has strengthened by 50 percent in comparison with the peso, and is also stronger compared with the Canadian dollar.</p>
        <p>The figures announced today indicated that exports in January totaled $60.70 billion in goods and services, while imports were $72.93 billion. The $12.23 billion deficit was $5 billion more than the December figure, and $4.8 billion more than the figure in January 1994.</p>
        <p>The gap widened with most of American trade partners, with the deficit with Western Europe growing to $1.3 billion from $200 million and Asian nations contributing to about 80 percent of the total gap. The surplus with South and Central America fell sharply. But the deficit narrowed slightly with Canada.</p>
        <p>Today's figures came out days before President Clinton is scheduled to begin a series of regional economic conferences around the country to listen to workers and business executives, and presumably to laud his Administration's economic successes.</p>
        <p>In the past, he has always listed the nation's export boom as one of his proudest accomplishments, arguing that it creates jobs that are higher-paying than average. The statistics support his case. In political terms, however, the growing trade deficit may undercut his arguments that free trade is an undiluted advantage for American workers and companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
