<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wayne Newton's Libel Award Against NBC Is Overturned</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ORGANIZED CRIME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIBEL AND SLANDER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO (NBC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALADDIN HOTEL (LAS VEGAS, NEV)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEWTON, WAYNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BISHOP, KATHERINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1531F932A0575BC0A966958260" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wayne Newton's Libel Award Against NBC Is Overturned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE BISHOP, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BISHOP, KATHERINE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal appeals court today overturned a $5.2 million libel award to the singer Wayne Newton against the National Broadcasting Company, ruling that the network's news reports suggesting links between Mr. Newton and organized crime had not been shown to be deliberately or recklessly false.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal appeals court today overturned a $5.2 million libel award to the singer Wayne Newton against the National Broadcasting Company, ruling that the network's news reports suggesting links between Mr. Newton and organized crime had not been shown to be deliberately or recklessly false.</p>
        <p>A Federal appeals court today overturned a $5.2 million libel award to the singer Wayne Newton against the National Broadcasting Company, ruling that the network's news reports suggesting links between Mr. Newton and organized crime had not been shown to be deliberately or recklessly false.</p>
        <p>In a unanimous decision, a three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit found that there was insufficient evidence to show that NBC News reporters had either deliberately lied or recklessly disregarded the truth, the legal standard that applies when libel suits are brought by public figures.</p>
        <p>Morton Galane, the Las Vegas lawyer representing Mr. Newton, said he had not received a copy of the ruling and could not comment. He said he had been unable to talk to Mr. Newton, who is in Los Angeles making a movie.</p>
        <p>'A Major Victory'</p>
        <p>Floyd Abrams, the New York lawyer representing NBC, called the ruling ''a major victory, not only for NBC, but for the ability of all Americans to receive news.'' He added, ''The case never should have been commenced and was totally without merit.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newton filed suit against NBC after the network broadcast a report in October 1980 entitled ''Wayne Newton and the Law,'' about Mr. Newton's purchase of the Aladdin Hotel and Casino in Las Vegas. Two more reports were broadcast in November 1980 and June 1981.</p>
        <p>After an eight-week trial in 1986, a Federal jury in Las Vegas found that the reports had created a false impression that organized crime figures had assisted the singer in the purchase in exchange for a hidden share in the casino and that Mr. Newton had failed to disclose to Nevada gaming officials his association with two men linked to organized crime, Guido Penosi and Frank Piccolo.</p>
        <p>The jury awarded $19.3 million, including $5 million in punitive damages, to Mr. Newton. The award for punitive damages was the largest against a news organization in a libel trial.</p>
        <p>Overall Award Was Reduced</p>
        <p>The jury's total award was later reduced, to $5.2 million, by Federal District Judge Myron Crocker.</p>
        <p>In the appeals court ruling today, written by Judge William A. Norris, the court held that almost all the facts reported by NBC were beyond dispute, including the reports that Mr. Newton had financial problems at the time he sought to purchase the casino and that he testified falsely before the gaming board.</p>
        <p>The court also found that Judge Crocker had erred in ruling that Mr. Newton had grounds for a lawsuit because the journalists should have foreseen how the reports would be interpreted. The proper standard in the case is whether the reporters realized that statements were false or entertained serious doubt as to the truth of their statements, the appeals court ruling said.</p>
        <p>The appeals court's review of the case showed ''almost no evidence of actual malice, much less clear and convincing proof,'' the ruling said.</p>
        <p>Michael G. Gartner, the president of NBC News, said the decision ''represents a sound victory for investigative journalism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
