<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the stump, in the rights arena, echoes of a religious thinker's vision live on.</title>
    <meta content="07BELI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/07/national/07beliefs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1602213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Beliefs"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinfels, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rauschenbusch, Walter (1861-1918)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Christopher H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Kingdom Is Always But Coming, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDF103CF934A3575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the stump, in the rights arena, echoes of a religious thinker's vision live on.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The DNA of Social Gospel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Steinfels</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinfels, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Steinfels column on 'social Christianity' preached by Walter Rauschenbusch a century ago and continuing echoes of it in America today; notes Christopher H Evans's new biography, The Kingdom Is Always But Coming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A century ago, Walter Rauschenbusch was the leading thinker of what was first known as ''social Christianity'' and then simply as the social gospel. The textbooks say that by 1918, the social gospel, like Rauschenbusch himself, was on its deathbed; but in fact its genes lived on in religious responses to the Depression and helped shape the civil rights movement of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Indeed, traces of social gospel DNA can be found almost anywhere that religion mixes with American politics--in President Bush's religion-based initiative and his talk of ''compassionate conservatism,'' for instance, as well as in Senator John Kerry's effort to close the ''God gap'' between more religious and less religious voters by preaching how values must be manifest in actions and not just slogans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the stump, in the rights arena, echoes of a religious thinker's vision live on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A century ago, Walter Rauschenbusch was the leading thinker of what was first known as ''social Christianity'' and then simply as the social gospel. The textbooks say that by 1918, the social gospel, like Rauschenbusch himself, was on its deathbed; but in fact its genes lived on in religious responses to the Depression and helped shape the civil rights movement of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Indeed, traces of social gospel DNA can be found almost anywhere that religion mixes with American politics--in President Bush's religion-based initiative and his talk of ''compassionate conservatism,'' for instance, as well as in Senator John Kerry's effort to close the ''God gap'' between more religious and less religious voters by preaching how values must be manifest in actions and not just slogans.</p>
        <p>For Rauschenbusch, the central theological idea of the social gospel was the kingdom of God. Standing in a line of Jewish prophets, Jesus had proclaimed, in the words of the Lord's Prayer, ''thy kingdom come, thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.'' Christianity had lost the centrality of this call to regenerate society in accord with God's will, Rauschenbusch argued, as the church came to focus on otherworldliness, on the salvation of individual souls, and on its own power.</p>
        <p>The high point of Rauschenbusch's influence stretched from 1907, when he published ''Christianity and the Social Crisis,'' still a classic religious text, to 1914, when the outbreak of World War I cast a shadow on his idealism.</p>
        <p>But the roots of his theology went back to the decade, from 1886 to 1897, that he spent as a young pastor of the Second German Baptist Church in the notorious Hell's Kitchen neighborhood of New York. The poverty, disease and desperation he encountered among tenement-bound laborers and immigrants convinced him, as it had a growing number of religious leaders, that Christianity had to address the stark social divisions and economic dislocations then racking American cities.</p>
        <p>''The Kingdom Is Always But Coming'' (Eerdmans), a new biography of Rauschenbusch by Christopher H. Evans, relates how the young pastor ''felt an agony over the number of funerals he had to conduct, especially for children who died as a result of poverty-induced disease.''</p>
        <p>'''Oh, the children's funerals! They gripped my heart -- that was one of the things I went away thinking about -- why did the children have to die?''' it quotes Rauschenbusch as saying.</p>
        <p>The biography points up the many seemingly contradictory elements in Rauschenbusch's outlook. He was justifiably seen as a religious radical, and yet he remained in many respects a conventional white male Victorian-era middle-class Protestant, a kind of revolutionary on behalf of conservative values. Not only were strong families the basis of a good society in his view, but women at home as wives and mothers were the basis of strong families.</p>
        <p>Like many other social gospelers, he gave little attention to racism, which he considered a problem of the American South. He viewed the new waves of Roman Catholic immigrants with apprehension, and anti-Catholicism runs like a dark thread through his theological thought. Taking for granted the cultural primacy of Protestantism, he could couch his calls for fundamental social reform in terms of ''Christianizing America'' without any self-consciousness.</p>
        <p>Some of these juxtapositions can be jarring, but others remind us of a time when later ideological and religious categories were still in flux. Protestantism was moving in two directions at once. Nascent premillennial fundamentalism emphasized biblical inerrancy and the approaching end times. Burgeoning postmillennial Protestant liberalism welcomed academic biblical criticism and adapting doctrine to modern conditions. But these two forces had not yet split Protestantism into two warring camps.</p>
        <p>From his German Lutheran pietist and Baptist background, Rauschenbusch inherited an evangelical emphasis on personal conversion and religious experience, and he could combine that emphasis with a theology based on recent biblical scholarship and the liberal emphasis on Jesus' earthly ministry rather than atonement by death on the cross. Socialism, like Protestantism, in those decades before Lenin and Bolshevik totalitarianism, was in flux. Rauschenbusch could call himself a socialist, although he never denigrated the market. He advocated standard Progressive-era reforms and, while deploring gross inequalities of wealth, remained friends with John D. Rockefeller.</p>
        <p>The social gospel has not fared well at the hands of historians and theologians. In the first volume of his three-volume history, ''Modern American Religion,'' Martin E. Marty describes most social gospel exponents as ''vague on program, weak on detail, generally out of touch with laborers, inept at politics''--only to add quickly that they ''were still prophets of a new order.''</p>
        <p>Theologically, the social gospel has never quite escaped Reinhold Niebuhr's critique of liberal Protestant reform efforts as naïvely optimistic and sentimental about the force of love, unwilling to acknowledge the realities of self-interest, conflict, sin and tragedy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans's biography confirms some of these criticisms, but it refutes others, at least in the case of Rauschenbusch, who never rejected individual conversion and salvation for social transformation but melded them together, who did not believe in inevitable progress, who rejected utopianism, acknowledged social conflict, had a real sense of the tragic and emphasized the place of the cross and suffering in his theology.</p>
        <p>It is a melancholy story that Mr. Evans tells, nonetheless. By the age of 30, Rauschenbusch had become almost totally deaf, which contributed, despite a marvelous marriage, to a lifelong loneliness and a sense of failure at being unable to pass on his religious faith to his children. But it was World War I, when as a German-American he found his pleas for peace and neutrality suspect, that especially darkened his final years.</p>
        <p>Yet his message stayed bright. Four decades later, the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. wrote, ''It has been my conviction ever since reading Rauschenbusch that any religion which professes to be concerned about the souls of men and is not concerned about the social and economic conditions that scar the soul, is a spiritually moribund religion only waiting for the day to be buried.''</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
