<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Torre Believes Umpires Are After Irabu</title>
    <meta content="28YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irabu, Hideki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3DB1531F93BA1575BC0A961958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Torre Believes Umpires Are After Irabu</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Aug. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problems besetting New York Yankees pitcher Hideki Irabu discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With some exasperation and disenchantment in his voice, Joe Torre expressed concern tonight that Hideki Irabu has become a marked man among American League umpires. While the Yankee manager claimed that he was hesitant to even discuss the delicate topic, he initiated the notion after questions about Irabu were broached before the Japanese pitcher took the mound tonight against the Oakland Athletics.</p>
        <p>Torre said he believed that Irabu's pitching delivery and the fact that he was called for seven balks during his minor league apprenticeship had put him under an even bigger microscope. Toss in Irabu's histrionics on the mound, which have bothered umpires, and Torre feels the Japanese pitcher is in a perilous position before he throws his first pitch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With some exasperation and disenchantment in his voice, Joe Torre expressed concern tonight that Hideki Irabu has become a marked man among American League umpires. While the Yankee manager claimed that he was hesitant to even discuss the delicate topic, he initiated the notion after questions about Irabu were broached before the Japanese pitcher took the mound tonight against the Oakland Athletics.</p>
        <p>Torre said he believed that Irabu's pitching delivery and the fact that he was called for seven balks during his minor league apprenticeship had put him under an even bigger microscope. Toss in Irabu's histrionics on the mound, which have bothered umpires, and Torre feels the Japanese pitcher is in a perilous position before he throws his first pitch.</p>
        <p>''He has to be careful,'' Torre said. ''Evidently, he has a 'Wanted' sign hanging from somewhere. People are out for him. Once you do the behavioral stuff, we have to bend over backwards to make sure balks don't happen.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have advised Irabu about controlling his behavior, but he had a reputation for having emotion  in Japan and he has exhibited flashes of it during his first six starts in the major leagues. Irabu kicked angrily at the dirt on the mound after he was called for his second balk in an 8-5 victory over the Angels in Anaheim last Wednesday night, causing the second-base umpire, John Hirschbeck, to admonish him. A month earlier, he kicked the resin bag, almost slammed his glove on the grass and appeared to spit toward the fans in a 6-2 loss to the Brewers in Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>''With all the advance publicity, I'm sure they're keeping closer watch on him than other guys,'' Torre said. ''They could say, 'Let's look out for this guy.' ''</p>
        <p>Hirschbeck has made comments that would indicate that Torre's suspicions are unfounded. He said that he was unaware the Yankees had counseled Irabu about bridling his emotions.</p>
        <p>''Oh, is that true?'' Hirschbeck said last week. But Hirschbeck became aware of it quickly and said: ''You can't do that stuff out there. This is the big leagues.''</p>
        <p>As the discussion about Irabu's treatment continued tonight, Torre appeared to sense that it was a mistake to ever bring it up, that if the umpires had not been targeting Irabu before, they might now.</p>
        <p>''You hate to cry about it,'' Torre said. ''There are times when umpires don't want to call things all the time. They'll tell a guy to be careful on this or careful on that.''</p>
        <p>Torre paused and said, ''I probably shouldn't even have said what I just said.''</p>
        <p>Irabu's apparent problem is that he sometimes takes the signs from the catcher without placing his foot on the pitching rubber. Torre speculated that the right-hander's extra movement after receiving the sign was something the umpires are not used to and that could be at the root of his problems. In six starts, Irabu already leads the Yankees with 3 of their 10 balks.</p>
        <p>Still, balks notwithstanding, the 28-year old right-hander had his finest start the last time out when he whiffed eight, walked one and permitted two earned runs in six and two-third innings against the Angels. Going into tonight's start, he was 4-2 with a 6.40 earned run average after winning his last two starts. ''He needs to continue to show consistency and carry it all through a game,'' said Billy Connors, the Yankee pitching coordinator. ''He doesn't have to be perfect. He just has to keep us in the game.''</p>
        <p>Connors later added, ''I still think, with the stuff he has, he's going to be one of the best pitchers in the league.''</p>
        <p>For now, Irabu is trying to be a pitcher who stays in the rotation. The Yankees demoted him to Class AAA Columbus for two starts to see if he could rectify his problems and somehow help them during the pennant race. ''If I see what I saw the last time, I'll be very pleased,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>How important has REY SANCHEZ been? When a reporter asked General Manager BOB WATSON on Wednesday about the Yankee infielder, who not only has batted .472 since being acquired from the Cubs nine games ago, but has also been adroit defensively, Watson said: ''What's wrong? Is there something wrong?'' Told it was simply a request to discuss how adeptly Sanchez has performed, a relieved Watson said, ''You scared me for a second.'' Despite Sanchez's terrific play, Watson could be eyeing an elite second baseman for 1998. ''There may be teams who can't keep their second baseman because of salaries,'' Watson said. ''We could get a front-line second baseman in the off season.'' . . . DAVID CONE tossed about 30 pitches at Yankee Stadium on Wednesday as he continued to test the tendinitis in his right shoulder. He will throw off a mound on Friday and can be activated next Tuesday. But JOE TORRE guessed that Cone would probably return against the Orioles in a four-game series that begins next Thursday. ''We'll save him for the Baltimore series,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
