<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="596248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSECTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITRONELLA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D8103BF935A25750C0A965958260" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. CLAIBORNE RAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Significant Dots</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>What are the three dots I see on the heads of many insects?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Significant Dots</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>What are the three dots I see on the heads of many insects?</p>
        <p>A. "Chances are, they are the simple eyes, or ocelli," said Dr. Betty Faber, an entomologist and staff scientist at the Liberty Science Center in Jersey City, N.J.</p>
        <p>Many insects have both compound and simple eyes, she said. A compound eye is the familiar faceted bulge on the fly, for example, but a simple eye is "just one little hexagonal surface," she said.</p>
        <p>"They are not believed to generate an image, though we do not really know what an insect sees," Dr. Faber said. "They are believed to be receptors sensitive to light and dark."  Citronella</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Does citronella, the insect repellent, come from citrus fruit?</p>
        <p>A. The oil is present in small amounts in orange peel, but the main source is citronella grass, the common name for Cymbopogon nardus. It is a tall, fragrant, cultivated Asiatic grass that is closely related to other fragrant grasses, like lemon grass (Cymbopogon citratus), the herb used for flavoring Thai foods and the source of lemon oil. They both belong to the huge Graminiae family of sturdy, woody grasses; bamboos and sugar cane are more distantly related members of the same family.</p>
        <p>Citronella grass grows only in the tropics and subtropics, and in the colder regions of its range it grows only in summer.</p>
        <p>Scientists say the smell of citronella oil irritates mosquitoes so they interrupt their feeding. Citronella grass also produces citral, another mosquito-repellent oil.</p>
        <p>Another plant, called citrosa, or Pelargonium citrosum Van Leenii, is a new genetically engineered cultivated variety with a powerful perfume that growers say offends insects, at least until the smell disperses, but scientists are skeptical about its performance. Citrosa contains chromosomes of both citronella grass and an African geranium with fleshy leaves that release the fragrance easily.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions about science to Questions, Science Times, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions of general interest will be answered in this column, but requests for medical advice cannot be honored and unpublished letters cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
