<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Big Spender in Albany: It's Blue Cross, the Lobbyist</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="596358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EMPIRE BLUE CROSS AND BLUE SHIELD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D61031F935A25750C0A965958260" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Big Spender in Albany: It's Blue Cross, the Lobbyist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, March 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield, facing major legislative battles amid a fiscal crisis that led it to warn it would shut down, spent more than all but one other organization last year to lobby lawmakers in the State Capitol.</p>
        <p>The company, New York State's largest insurer, spent $511,576 on lobbying as the State Legislature enacted major changes in the way health insurance rates are set in New York and approved a plan to infuse the company with $100 million to reduce the severest impacts of a rate increase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield, facing major legislative battles amid a fiscal crisis that led it to warn it would shut down, spent more than all but one other organization last year to lobby lawmakers in the State Capitol.</p>
        <p>The company, New York State's largest insurer, spent $511,576 on lobbying as the State Legislature enacted major changes in the way health insurance rates are set in New York and approved a plan to infuse the company with $100 million to reduce the severest impacts of a rate increase.</p>
        <p>Empire's lobbying expenses were disclosed today in the annual report by the Temporary State Commission on Lobbying, which showed that the amount of money spent by unions, trade groups and municipalities on wooing legislators in Albany reached a record of $34.8 million in 1992, a 13.7 percent increase over 1991.</p>
        <p>Only the statewide teachers union, New York State United Teachers, spent more on lobbying -- $514,444 -- than Empire, a nonprofit company that receives tax breaks and other advantages from the state.</p>
        <p>Nothing prohibits an organization or private company, even those that receive benefits, from lobbying lawmakers in the Capitol.</p>
        <p>An Empire spokesman, John F. Kelly, defended the company's extensive lobbying efforts, saying the expense ultimately benefited its customers by assuring wider access to health insurance and cheaper premiums. 'A Legitimate Question'</p>
        <p>But others, including public advocacy groups, questioned the propriety of spending money to lobby while the company was raising rates and receiving the infusion of funds from the state.</p>
        <p>"Should a company getting money from the government use that money to try to get more money from the government?" said Julian Palmer, the executive director of New York State Common Cause. "That's a legitimate question."</p>
        <p>It is impossible to gauge precisely what benefits, if any, Empire gained through its lobbying expenses, but the company's emergence in the top ranks of lobbyists came as sweeping changes in the state's insurance laws prompted one of the most intense debates of last year's legislative session, as well as one of the most intense lobbying campaigns by organizations on both sides.</p>
        <p>The measure, adopted by the Legislature last July, bars private insurance companies from discriminating against the elderly or the ailing in setting rates, forcing them to accept all applicants, regardless of their medical condition, and to set rates without regard to age, sex or risk of illness, as Empire had done for years. The measure takes effect on April 1.</p>
        <p>Officials at Empire had long argued that the company suffered a competitive disadvantage because private companies wooed away their younger, healthier customers, who normally have lower medical costs. 'Reams and Reams'</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said Empire spent about $325,000 of the $511,576 total to print and mail more than 500,000 postcards to its customers, who then sent many of those cards to their legislators in Albany. They also bombarded the lawmakers themselves with their arguments.</p>
        <p>"Many organizations were out there opposing this," Mr. Kelly said. "We had to inundate legislators and their staffs with reams and reams of papers explaining our position."</p>
        <p>The fight also prompted the Health Insurance Association of America, a trade group in Washington, to join the top ranks of lobbying clients in the state for the first time. The association, which opposed the law because it restricts private insurance companies, spent $283,394, according to the commission.</p>
        <p>In addition to the money it spent on the insurance laws, Empire spent $183,241 to hire Hinman, Straub, Pigors &amp; Manning, one of the largest and most influential lobbying firms in Albany, to help sway lawmakers during the long, politically charged debate over rate increases.</p>
        <p>In the first week of January, after months of tense negotiations and dire warnings by Empire that it would collapse, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the Legislature agreed to provide the company with the infusion of cash to settle a lawsuit filed against the state by the company and to avert rate increases as high as 60 percent for its 1.4 million customers.</p>
        <p>"There's a public good that came out of this," Mr. Kelly said of Empire's lobbying expenses.</p>
        <p>The commission on lobbying was formed in 1978 to try to bring public scrutiny to lobbyists and their clients. Since it began issuing its annual reports, the amount of money spent on lobbying -- in fees and expense reimbursments -- has risen more than 500 percent, to this year's high of $34.8 million.</p>
        <p>"This is the tab for getting the message across to decision makers," the commission's chairman, Bartley F. Livolsi, said today.</p>
        <p>In 1992, he said, the largest share came from business and industry interests, followed by health-care and insurance interests. The largest individual clients included the City of New York, which spent $456,302; the Hospital Association of New York State, which spent $405,833, and the Civil Service Employees Association Inc. and Political Action Fund, which spent $368,960.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
