<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexicans Hopeful as They Await Bush Today</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="404251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">UHLIG, MARK A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALINAS DE GORTARI, CARLOS (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED81E3EF935A15752C1A966958260" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexicans Hopeful as They Await Bush Today</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK A. UHLIG, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UHLIG, MARK A</byline>
      <dateline>MONTERREY, Mexico, Nov. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to capitalize on the warmest official American-Mexican relations in recent memory, Mexican authorities prepared for the arrival of President Bush here on Monday for a two-day state visit that is expected to focus largely on trade issues.</p>
        <p>The visit, which will be the sixth meeting between President Bush and President Carlos Salinas de Gortari, is seen here as a confirmation of the good personal ties between the two leaders, who held their first talks even before Mr. Bush was sworn in as President.That theme has dominated descriptions of the meeting by aides to Mr. Salinas, who has staked much of his personal and political success on his ability to work as an equal with Mr. Bush in improving relations between the two countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to capitalize on the warmest official American-Mexican relations in recent memory, Mexican authorities prepared for the arrival of President Bush here on Monday for a two-day state visit that is expected to focus largely on trade issues.</p>
        <p>The visit, which will be the sixth meeting between President Bush and President Carlos Salinas de Gortari, is seen here as a confirmation of the good personal ties between the two leaders, who held their first talks even before Mr. Bush was sworn in as President.That theme has dominated descriptions of the meeting by aides to Mr. Salinas, who has staked much of his personal and political success on his ability to work as an equal with Mr. Bush in improving relations between the two countries.</p>
        <p>But officials familiar with the agenda said that the meeting would also include substantive talks, dominated by efforts to eliminate potential obstacles to a free-trade agreement that would link North American economies in a giant new trading partnership.</p>
        <p>They said the two leaders would also confront a variety of more divisiveissues, ranging from drug enforcement efforts to violence against illegal Mexican immigrants entering the United States near San Diego, where ethnic tensions have flared in recent months. Preventing Problems</p>
        <p>"This is not so much a meeting to solve problems as to prevent them," said a Mexican official involved in preparations for the visit. "We believe we have better relations with this Administration than with any other in years, and we don't want to lose the chance to keep things going forward."</p>
        <p>Preliminary discussions toward a Mexican-American free-trade agreement have been under way since the two Governments formally accepted the idea during a visit by Mr. Salinas to Washington in June.</p>
        <p>Since then, however, the environment for direct negotiations has been sharply affected by a series of international developments, ranging from the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait to the stalemate of the Uruguay Round of international trade talks in Geneva.</p>
        <p>Among the major outstanding issues in the talks is the degree to which any free-trade agreement would cover Mexico's large oil sector, which Mr. Salinas has repeatedly said must be excluded from negotiation. American interest in that issue has grown with the potential for conflict in the Persian Gulf, but senior aides to Mr. Salinas asserted again last week that he would not accept oil as part of the trade package.</p>
        <p>Other concerns, officials said, include efforts in both countries to allay domestic opposition to the pact, which must overcome sharp differences in everything from wages to environmental restrictions. Diplomats and officials on both sides have also expressed worry over the potential political fallout from continued charges of fraud against Mr. Salinas's governing party, most recently during local elections Nov. 11 in the state of Mexico, just outside the capital. Canada's Role Is Issue</p>
        <p>The format of the trade negotiations themselves has also been thrown into question by the proposed participation of Canada, whose inclusion in any formal agreement would create a trading zone some 25 percent larger than theEuropean Community.</p>
        <p>A free-trade pact between the United States and Canada went into effect last year. But the announcement of negotiations toward a similar agreement between the United States and Mexico prompted immediate Canadian demands for some sort of participation or representation in the new talks.</p>
        <p>The idea of permitting a new participant at the negotiating table has been opposed by many proponents of the agreement, who have argued that it would slow the progress of the talks, which both sides hope to complete before the end of Mr. Bush's term in 1992.</p>
        <p>But senior Mexican officials now say that some degree of Canadian participation appears inevitable, if only in the form of an invited observer or other special status.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
