<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Linebackers Scarce At Giants' Practice</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D91439F93BA25751C1A965958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Linebackers Scarce At Giants' Practice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Dec. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants' defense was missing two of its valuable parts at practice today. One was Lawrence Taylor, who was excused for what team officials called personal reasons. The other was outside linebacker Corey Miller, who was hospitalized with flu-like symptoms.</p>
        <p>Taylor, within earshot of reporters, loudly told one team official that he was "going to court." No other details were available. Taylor was not available for comment, and the team had no official comment. The linebacker was expected to be available for Monday night's game in New Orleans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants' defense was missing two of its valuable parts at practice today. One was Lawrence Taylor, who was excused for what team officials called personal reasons. The other was outside linebacker Corey Miller, who was hospitalized with flu-like symptoms.</p>
        <p>Taylor, within earshot of reporters, loudly told one team official that he was "going to court." No other details were available. Taylor was not available for comment, and the team had no official comment. The linebacker was expected to be available for Monday night's game in New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Miller's absence could potentially turn out to be more serious. Although he looked fine on Thursday, he apparently became very sick late last night and early this morning. Chances are he will play on Monday night but more than likely will not be 100 percent healthy. He is expected to practice on Saturday.</p>
        <p>The absence of Taylor and Miller left just one veteran available to practice at the linebacker spot, and that was Carlton Bailey. The other starting veteran inside linebacker is Michael Brooks and he's out with a foot injury.</p>
        <p>If for whatever reason Miller can't go, the Giants might go with Marcus Buckley. Kanavis McGhee, who plays both on the defensive line and at outside linebacker, is also available. Headed for Hawaii</p>
        <p>This season the Giants have a number of Pro Bowl candidates, unlike last year, when many wanted just to forget the season. Good records mean good publicity, and since the Giants are 10-3 and being mentioned as a potential Super Bowl team, their chances of sending players to Hawaii increase. Here are some of them:</p>
        <p>*A lock. Cornerback Mark Collins may have the best chance of any Giant. His usual competitors are Washington's Darrell Green and Philadelphia's Eric Allen, but both players, especially Green, are having down seasons. Collins's numbers are outstanding. He leads the team with three interceptions, one returned for a touchdown. He's fourth on the team in tackles with 57, has one quarterback sack and has knocked down 14 passes. Consider that in 1989 he earned All-National Football Conference honors with 81 tackles and 2 interceptions. He already has more interceptions than that and has a chance at getting more tackles.</p>
        <p>*A near lock. When Carlton Bailey joined the Giants, some of the veterans wouldn't even talk to him. Many were loyal to the former Giant Pepper Johnson and when Johnson was cut, some players blamed Bailey for it. Funny how things change. He leads the team with 113 tackles. Now, everyone stops by his locker to say hello.</p>
        <p>*Was a lock. Michael Brooks, who has already been to one Pro Bowl, was on his way to another. He is one of the most dominating players in the game today. But he sprained ligaments in his foot on Dec. 5, has missed the last two games and will probably miss Monday night's game and next week's game against Phoenix. For Brooks, it's just a question of how much the fans, players and coaches remember about how dominating he was before the injury.</p>
        <p>*Outside shot. Running back Rodney Hampton's chances were also hurt by injury when he missed three games because of arthroscopic knee surgery. That makes it all the more amazing that he has rushed for 860 yards, 173 last week against Indianapolis. The problem for Hampton is there are too many other backs in the league with better numbers, like Emmitt Smith from Dallas.</p>
        <p>*Nostalgia pick. Phil Simms doesn't have the numbers of, say, Troy Aikman. Simms has 13 touchdowns and 9 interceptions, and rarely will he pass more than 40 times in a game (he doesn't need to with Hampton in the game). But no quarterback has been more steady or a better leader. Elliott Hopes to Return</p>
        <p>Offensive lineman Jumbo Elliott was walking around the locker room today, his back wrapped in a bandage. Elliott, who has disk problems and spurs in his lower back, still holds out hope he can return this season.</p>
        <p>He wasn't very talkative today, saying only that he felt a lot better than he did before a steroid injection this week eased the pain. Elliott won't play against the Saints, but when asked if he would play against Phoenix he said, "I hope so." Simms' Last Shot?</p>
        <p>Although he doesn't like to talk about it publicly, this is certainly one of the last chances Phil Simms will have at another Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>"I don't think of it quite in those sad terms," he said. "You don't get too many opportunities in this league. It is hard, no matter how good your team is, to get to 10-3 and have the best record in football with a chance to get home-field advantage. Honestly, it probably could be my last chance. The good thing is we will take advantage of the situation."  PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
