<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About/Translation Services; The Growing Gelt in Others' Words</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="481595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Translation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA123BF933A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About/Translation Services; The Growing Gelt in Others' Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH America's export engine revving up, the nation's translation services are reaping the benefits. To make money abroad, more and more companies are tailoring their products to local markets. That means having legal contracts, technical information, instruction manuals and other materials translated into and out of dozens of foreign languages.</p>
        <p>The largest translation companies say demand has grown rapidly in recent years, changing what was once a cottage industry of dozens of tiny firms into a full-fledged business with a myriad of small- and medium-sized competitors fighting for market share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH America's export engine revving up, the nation's translation services are reaping the benefits. To make money abroad, more and more companies are tailoring their products to local markets. That means having legal contracts, technical information, instruction manuals and other materials translated into and out of dozens of foreign languages.</p>
        <p>The largest translation companies say demand has grown rapidly in recent years, changing what was once a cottage industry of dozens of tiny firms into a full-fledged business with a myriad of small- and medium-sized competitors fighting for market share.</p>
        <p>Companies like All-Language Services in New York, which was founded in 1946 with five translators, have been flourishing. All-Language, which is privately held, now has 90 translators working in 59 languages. Its revenues -- it does not disclose dollar figures -- have tripled since 1980, according to Lorraine Kennedy, executive vice president. The company's growth has been spurred on by a fourfold increase in the volume of Japanese translated since 1986.</p>
        <p>"There has always been a good deal of sophistication about language in the Fortune 500 companies," said Victor J. Hertz, president of Corporate Language Services, a privately held company in New York with affiliates in Europe. "What you're witnessing now is a burgeoning of interest from middle-level and small businesses."</p>
        <p>The maturing of the translation business has also been reflected in a spate of recent consolidations. Since the mid-1980's, the translation division of Berlitz International, the subsidiary of Macmillan Inc., best known for its language schools, has bought six translation companies in the United States and Europe. Berlitz now has about $30 million in revenues from translations.</p>
        <p>Another industry leader, Alpnet Inc., based in Salt Late City, is publicly traded. Alpnet, which had $22.5 million in 1990 revenues, has also grown through acquisitions overseas.</p>
        <p>Despite its growth, the translation business is highly competitive and very fragmented. Experts say that the industry is so diffuse -- from tiny outlets to major companies -- that there are few reliable estimates of its size. If corporate and government translation divisions are included, "the total industry could be as high as $10 billion," said Michael J. Mulligan, a vice president of the translation division of Berlitz.  U.S. Firms Abroad  The Advantage Of Native Ability</p>
        <p>Even for companies that have all their operations in the United States, professional translation is very much an international business, employing for the most part people translating into their native language. Industry officials say that only by maintaining such a standard can they insure that a translation is competent.</p>
        <p>Translation companies like Berlitz, with offices around the world, take this requirement a step further by insisting that most translations be done by native speakers in the country where the item is to be read. For example, a service might fax or send electronically to its Paris office a document that needs to translated into French.</p>
        <p>"If you're not in country, then you don't speak the same language that they're speaking in that country," said Mr. Mulligan. Berlitz has 250 translators working in 19 offices in 13 countries.</p>
        <p>The move over the last few years to sending work to other countries has been helped by fax machines, modems and computers. Businesses can now take their work formatted on a desktop publishing program to a translation service that sends it electronically to an office in another country. The translators then return the work ready for printing. Rates in the industry vary widely, depending on how complicated the document is, the language it is to be translated into and what other services, like editing or desktop publishing, are required.</p>
        <p>The largest translation companies usually charge 10 cents to 50 cents per word, though rates may be higher for the most difficult work and for technical and legal documents.</p>
        <p>Some languages also cost more to translate than others. Asian and Scandinavian languages are often more expensive: the Asian ones because they are complicated and the Scandinavian ones because of high labor costs in those countries. The Speed Premium  Building Business On Flexibility</p>
        <p>Industry leaders say much of their growth has been sparked by the increasing sophistication of American companies, particularly the smaller ones, as they explore the export market. While large companies can set up their own translation departments, smaller ones do not have the resources for such an undertaking and must seek help elsewhere.</p>
        <p>"Translation is no longer an afterthought," said Thomas F. Seal, the president of Alpnet, which has 22 offices in nine countries. "When companies are designing products upfront, they are realizing the need to do translation. We've seen a large increase in contacts from the development phase."</p>
        <p>One such company is Maynard Electronics of Lake Mary, Fla., which makes computer software and hardware for backing up data. Maynard, which had revenues of about $100 million last year, recently began aggressively pushing into the European market.</p>
        <p>The company found that its distributors in Europe were not translating its manuals adequately or fast enough, so it hired Alpnet to create German, French, Dutch, Spanish and Italian versions of the documents.</p>
        <p>"The key was that we needed to get translations out sooner so we could get a good edge on the market," said Dawn Woods, a translation specialist at Maynard. Surviving Change  Bring the U.S. Up to Speed</p>
        <p>While pleased with growth in recent years, industry leaders complain about the haphazard nature of the translation market. Demand for a language may rise or fall because of political or economic changes in a country. For example, the integration of Europe into a single market has led to an increased demand for German, French and Spanish translations.</p>
        <p>The business is also oriented toward projects -- with clients providing work in fits and starts -- so it is often difficult to plan.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, many translation services have specialized, employing people who concentrate on translating legal work or technical and scientific documents into a specific language.</p>
        <p>"If somebody needs a love letter translated, they can go to a next-door neighbor," said Ms. Kennedy, of All-Language Services. "But 99 percent of the stuff we do is very specialized. You can't rely on dictionaries for this stuff."</p>
        <p>And the industry remains extremely competitive. Large outfits with hundreds of full-time translators and offices around the world might vie for the same contracts as small services that keep costs low by employing a freelance staff.</p>
        <p>"The fact that the industry is fundamentally fragmented means that there is always somebody with relatively low overhead willing to do a project for relatively low costs," said Mr. Mulligan of Berlitz.</p>
        <p>Moreover, even though American companies are using translation services more, many remain less familiar with the importance of language in exporting than their rivals in Europe and Asia.</p>
        <p>"The main message now is that in Europe and Asia, you are dealing with people who are very language savvy," said Richard Huarte, the executive director of operations in the United States for Inlingua, a Swiss company with 250 offices in 22 countries, including 24 in the United States.</p>
        <p>"The United States is really in its infancy in this area," he said. "We've come a long way, but we're still quite behind." A GLUT OF GOVERNMENT WORK</p>
        <p>To communicate with new immigrants who continue to move to the United States, Federal, state and local governments must translate documents into dozens of languages. This business has been an area of rapid growth.</p>
        <p>"Our translation business from government agencies has at least doubled in size in the last six years," said Edward Nef, the director of the Washington office of Inlingua, the American subsidiary of the big Swiss translation service. Inlingua has bid on contracts for the United States Customs Service and the Social Security Administration.</p>
        <p>Some agencies, like the Immigration and Naturalization Service, have their own translators. But in an age of immigration, even those offices cannot keep up with the number of languages spoken in the United States. For example, last year, the Office of Special Counsel for Immigration-Related Unfair Employment Practices, a division of the Justice Department, had to translate documents into Arabic, French, Spanish, Korean, Japanese and Chinese. Some of these documents are used by workers to file legal complaints against their employers.</p>
        <p>Government agencies also use translation services because they are quicker than waiting for the government to do the work itself, said Tyrone Harrison, an administrative assistant at the Office of Special Counsel in New York. "Translation services have made things easier because once the documents are written in English, we can go ahead and proceed with a case more rapidly," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
