<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/October 13-18</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="481579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DF173BF933A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/October 13-18</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joel Kurtzman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ECONOMY For Better or Worse, Citicorp's Star Is Hitched to the Economy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ECONOMY For Better or Worse, Citicorp's Star Is Hitched to the Economy</p>
        <p>Citicorp is the national economy in microcosm. Badly hurt by the recession, especially in real estate, the nation's largest banking company reported a loss last week of $885 million in the third quarter. Its chairman, John S. Reed, said he expected losses on business and commercial real estate loans to rise for a few more quarters as a consequence of the slumping economy. In the first three quarters of the year, Citicorp charged off as a loss $3.97 billion of loans. Its holdings of badly delinquent loans is now $9.64 billion. Much of that comes from its aggressive push into consumer and mortgage lending, especially in the West where the recession lingers. All this makes some analysts question whether the worst really is behind the nation's biggest bank. "We clearly have picked up more, or at least our fair share, of problems," Mr. Reed said. Vigorous growth in the economy would do wonders. America in the Jalopy Age  Showroom traffic is way up as Detroit dazzles consumers with loads of new models. But too few browsers are becoming buyers. Sales for early October, when the new-model year began, were down 10.1 percent compared with a year earlier, in the early days of the recession. Analysts attribute sales resistance even among the most car-conscious consumers to nervousness about the economy. The result is that America's fleet of cars is more ancient than ever -- a rust-eaten 7.6 years, according to Charles Brady, an analyst at Mabon Securities Corporation in New York. When, the auto makers wonder, will all those jalopies ever be replaced? Getting Stubborn on Prices  With the economy growing at barely single-digit rates, prices should be tumbling. How else could shopkeepers move those goods? But prices are not. Last week, the Commerce Department reported, the Consumer Price Index jumped 0.4 percent in September after increasing 0.2 percent in August. If you exclude volatile food and energy prices from the index, "you get an annualized inflation rate of 4.6 percent, which appears high," said Samuel D. Kahan, chief economist at Fuji Securities in Chicago. That makes some wonder if the Federal Reserve will ease interest rates or simply stand pat. "Right now the Fed wants the economy to expand," said Mr. Kahan. That Curious Warehouse Watch  Number-crunching economists often pose questions to themselves, such as: "At today's sales rates, how long will it take to clear the economy of all its inventoried goods?" The answer to that, they reason, indicates when factory orders will pick up as the nation's stores restock. Right now, according to the Commerce Department, it would take 1.49 months to clean the nation's warehouses of their goods. That is the lowest rate in a year and suggests the economy is picking up. "The recovery is likely to witness stable growth rather than a double-dip," said Jerry Jasinowski, of the National Association of Manufacturers. But at the rate at which those inventories are being cleared, stable growth will also be slow growth.  A Widening Trade Gap  Americans sure love their imported goods. The nation's trade deficit with the rest of the world surged by 13.6 percent during August to $6.76 billion, according to the Commerce Department. That happens, the theory says, when the economy is poised for recovery. Not this time. The deficit grew in August because exports slipped 3 percent to $34.16 billion as growth abroad stalled. Before the figures were released, the consensus among economists was that August's deficit would narrow to $5.35 billion. They were off by $1.41 billion.  What Are the Factories Up To?  The nation's economic puzzle is composed of pieces not necessarily taken from the same box. Consider factory orders and capacity utilization. According to the Federal Reserve, factory orders were up 0.1 percent in September as inventories were slowly being used up. That was expected. But factory capacity utilization actually dropped in September to 79.7 percent from 79.8 percent in August and 80 percent in July. Factories working less were producing more?  Bad News in Housing  Since March, housing starts have been picking up. But according to the Commerce Department, they dropped 2.2 percent in September. On its own, that is bad enough. But housing starts are also an indicator of the economy's future course. Buy a house and pretty soon you must fill it. Then you must make the payments. The payments part is what people are worrying about. No Boost for the Jobless  President Bush may style himself the kinder, gentler President, but he wields his veto power with alacrity. Since he has been in office, he has killed 23 bills. Congress attempted to overturn 12 and failed each time. Last week, the survivor was Mr. Bush's veto of a bill extending unemployment benefits for people who have already exhausted their coverage. Extending benefits to the estimated 3.4 million unemployed whose benefits have lapsed "would significantly increase the Federal deficit," Mr. Bush said. Maybe so. But those words sounded far from gentle. COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Milken's Plea for Lenience  Last week, Arthur Liman, the principal defense attorney for Michael Milken, the jailed junk-bond financier, asked the court to reduce Mr. Milken's 10-year sentence. In a 31-page memorandum to the court, Mr. Liman cited Mr. Milken's 29 meetings with the government and hundreds of hours of debriefings, as evidence of his client's desire to cooperate. Mr. Liman also drew the court's attention to Ivan F. Boesky, the convicted swindler. Mr. Milken's crimes were not as bad as Mr. Boesky's, according to Mr. Liman, yet Mr. Milken's sentence was harsher. Since the court has heard all this before, sympathy is not expected. The Good and the Bad at Big Blue  While the International Business Machines Corporation has been developing its strategy for the future through linkages with dozens of other smaller computer makers, its day-to-day business has been suffering. Last week, Big Blue reported its earnings fell 84.5 percent in the third quarter to $173 million. Its revenue also fell, to $14.43 billion from $15.28 billion. Investors moaned, analysts saw glimmers of hope. Big Blue also said it had trimmed sales, administrative and research expenses. And last week it announced it was selling its $400 million stake in the MCI Communications Corporation. Ultimately, Wall Street could not make up its mind about I.B.M. The stock fell $2.125 then rose $3 to $104.25 and finished the week at $100.25. USAir Losses Ease a Bit  USAir, one of the nation's ailing carriers, reported a loss last week of $81.4 million for the third quarter. That was good news. Analysts had expected worse. USAir lost $120.3 million the quarter before. The airline also said it was planning to trim expenses by $400 million. Chasing That Cellular Profit  So far, no cellular telephone company has figured out a way to make money. But they are good at dreaming big. Last week, McCaw Cellular Communications Inc. unveiled its visions of the future. It said it had developed hardware and software to link its cellular systems around the country into a seamless web of talk. The network will be called Cellular One. Sixty million potential subscribers live in the area it covers. But to make it truly national, McCaw will try to convince other companies to join its network. "What follows next is persuading partners, not acquiring them.It's politics, not finance," said Craig McCaw, the company's chairman. It had better be. McCaw still has $5 billion in debt from previous acquisitions.  TRW Allows a Free Peek  TRW Inc. mostly makes satellites and car parts. But it also has a division that produces credit reports -- and makes enemies, among state attorneys general, in Congress and at consumer groups. So, TRW said it would make its reports available without charge to the people in its files. CBS Misses the Ballpark  Pity poor CBS. It bought the rights to air major league baseball to add a little punch to its ratings. But CBS lost out to the Senate confirmation hearings of Judge Clarence Thomas. Last Sunday, according to David Poltrack, senior vice president for research at CBS, 27 million homes tuned into the Judge Thomas saga, compared with just 9.2 million homes at the ballgame. The ratings show that a program that is part politics, part National Enquirer, may have a future on TV. INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Unify? Count the Ukraine Out  Immediately after the Soviet republics declared their independence from Moscow's central control, Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev proposed a new treaty to create a new union. Russia's President, Boris N. Yelt sin and most of the other leaders of the republics were enthusiastic. But last week the Ukraine had a change of heart. It refused to sign the treaty. The new economic union was too encumbering, its Parliament said, especially the proposal to set up a single central bank and currency. What worries the Ukraine most is the idea of falling under the sway of neighboring Russia once again. "The republics agreed to the treaty thinking they could get raw materials from Russia on better conditions than they now do," said Vladimir Kvint, a lecturer at Babson College in Boston. "But Russia wants to impose political conditions on them now. That makes the whole treaty a question mark."  Ford Faces Facts at Jaguar  The Ford Motor Company bought Britain's Jaguar in 1986 for $2.7 billion. It might be sorry it did. The luxury automaker is in a slump. Sales have fallen from 45,000 cars last year to well below 30,000 this year. Jaguar has even had to scrap some new models and stop development on others. Last week, union representatives were summoned by Ford to talk about layoffs. Rumors are that 1,400 workers will have to go. So far this year 2,500 Jaguar workers have been dismissed.  Honda Latest Concept  Most concept cars never get built. They are sketches in metal and plastic to sharpen designers' skills and drum up excitement for the brand. Last week, Honda unveiled a prototype two-seater dubbed the EP-X (efficient, personal, experimental). The car seats the passenger behind the driver -- talk about stiff necks. But it does have an advantage: an estimated 100 miles a gallon. In the tradition, chances are slim the EP-X will ever be built.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
