<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Eastern European Rock Survive Freedom?</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="481725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="POP VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CZECHOSLOVAKIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PULNOC (BAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAVEL, VACLAV</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOLLAG, BURTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D8163CF933A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Eastern European Rock Survive Freedom?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jon Pareles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"A time of madness, a time of mirrors/ A time of desperation, a time of amazement." With those words from the title song of its first major-label album, "City of Hysteria," the Czechoslovak band Pulnoc might be summing up the persecution and revolution that its members lived through.</p>
        <p>For a band just making its worldwide debut, Pulnoc (pronounced PULL-notes) carries a long history. Its prior incarnation, the Plastic People of the Universe, was the catalyst to the overthrow of Communism in Czechoslovakia. Pulnoc may be the only rock band ever to have liner notes by its nation's president. And, like Czechoslovakia, Pulnoc ("midnight" in Czech) has emerged from a dark period, when its role was clear, to an uncertain future of competing in an international free market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"A time of madness, a time of mirrors/ A time of desperation, a time of amazement." With those words from the title song of its first major-label album, "City of Hysteria," the Czechoslovak band Pulnoc might be summing up the persecution and revolution that its members lived through.</p>
        <p>For a band just making its worldwide debut, Pulnoc (pronounced PULL-notes) carries a long history. Its prior incarnation, the Plastic People of the Universe, was the catalyst to the overthrow of Communism in Czechoslovakia. Pulnoc may be the only rock band ever to have liner notes by its nation's president. And, like Czechoslovakia, Pulnoc ("midnight" in Czech) has emerged from a dark period, when its role was clear, to an uncertain future of competing in an international free market.</p>
        <p>Music that meant resistance to an official culture, and was thus defined in part by its enemies, inevitably changes both form and meaning when those enemies are gone. At home, Western companies whose albums used to be smuggled and bootlegged behind the Iron Curtain are rushing to capture new markets. (Time Warner subsidized a free concert in Moscow by AC/DC, Metallica and other bands on Sept. 28, doubtless impressing Time Warner stockholders at a meeting three days earlier.) Out in the world market, musicians might well be tempted to copy winning foreign formulas, as does Russia's unctuous band Avtograf, and others will choose to work with foreign professionals (witness Russia's once-dissident rocker turned David Bowie imitator, Boris Grebenshchikov, who made an album produced by David Stewart of the Eurythmics).</p>
        <p>Pulnoc, whose members used to perform through amplifiers made from gutted transistor radios, has gleefully embraced modern electronics. But the album's first words, as translated, are "What once was has not departed/ It still remains with me/ And bears evil witness."</p>
        <p>Before, when the Plastic People sang about funerals or delirium, they were considered seditious for suggesting alternatives to the optimistic party line. Now, when Pulnoc sings about poison mushrooms or a nightmare in which terror "plants a black flower by my side," the malaise seems to be a matter of temperament and gothic literary tastes. Like a former state industry that has become privatized, Pulnoc, a reluctant, contrary state symbol, now stands for no more than its own artistic goals.</p>
        <p>Pulnoc is a special case among Eastern-bloc rockers, because the Plastic People were obsessively persecuted. But along with other cultural exports from the former Soviet empire, it may find that capitalism is nearly as tricky as communism, if not as openly brutal. Instead of repression, Pulnoc may have to contend with indifference.</p>
        <p>"City of Hysteria," which was recorded this year in New York City, is not just a collection of hard-won and cranky songs, but an artifact of the cold-war thaw. The album is an idiosyncratic combination of 1990's synthesizers and guitar sounds with a late-1960's rhythmic sense.</p>
        <p>An album of bleak, minor-key songs, most of them sung in Czech, isn't a typical top-10 contender. Yet the riffs are pithy and memorable, the beat lands squarely between the Velvet Underground and slow hip-hop, and the layers of cello, viola, keyboards and, especially, wayward guitar create an eerie atmosphere, as if a spotlight were suddenly flashed on a medieval alley, sending rats skittering for cover.</p>
        <p>The copy used as liner notes on "City of Hysteria" was written in 1984 by Vaclav Havel, now President of Czechoslovakia, when he was a dissident playwright and the members of Pulnoc were still leading the Plastic People of the Universe. The band got started in 1968, in the fall after Soviet tanks crushed the liberalization movement known as Prague Spring. "We never wanted to overthrow the regime. We just wanted to make rock-and-roll," Milan Hlavsa, the bassist and composer for both the Plastic People and Pulnoc, has said. But the band's surreal lyrics (written by band members and Czechoslovak poets) and wild performances disturbed an increasingly censorious bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>In 1973, the Government decreed that the Plastic People's music would have a "negative social effect" on young people. Repression turned the band into heroic dissidents. Members of the Plastic People and other underground rock groups were arrested for "organized disturbance of the peace" in 1976.</p>
        <p>The trial of the band members and their manager brought together artists and intellectuals, who coalesced as the human-rights movement Charter 77, the center of the growing Czechoslovak opposition. Mr. Havel, one of the movement's leaders, allowed the Plastic People to perform and record at his country house. The band made three albums, released by Czechoslovak expatriates, in 1978, 1979 and 1981 -- albums on which a solemn drumbeat carries bleak, dissonant songs, as close to 20th-century chamber music as to contemporary rock. "Midnight Mouse," released in 1987, offered more straightforward rock.</p>
        <p>But after 20 years together the band dissolved. In 1988 Mr. Hlavsa started Pulnoc, with two other ex-Plastic People and four younger musicians. The band immediately won professional status and even permission to tour the United States.</p>
        <p>So why aren't Pulnoc's songs more cheerful? My guess is that memory, culture and sheer stubbornness have a lot to do with it. Pulnoc's cultural heritage includes not just Lou Reed, Frank Zappa and the Fugs but Franz Kafka and the religious reformer and heretic Jan Hus; its musical roots extend to Czechoslovak folk songs and classical music, both filled with dissonance and melancholy. Other Eastern-bloc bands may rush to crank out love songs and English-language anthems, but they're likely to find that the world market is already saturated with similar products; in the long run, Pulnoc's stubbornness is probably a better strategy.</p>
        <p>Pulnoc knows exactly what it's up against. On "City of Hysteria," the band plays a borrowed song that is both obvious and inspired: the Velvet Underground's "All Tomorrow's Parties," sung in the sober alto of Michaela Nemcova. "What costume shall the poor girl wear/ To all tomorrow's parties?" the song asks -- exactly the question now being pondered in places where Communism used to decree all the answers. BETWEEN ROCK AND A REVOLUTION</p>
        <p>PRAGUE</p>
        <p>The musical tastes of President Vaclav Havel of Czechoslovakia (in photograph) appear to have been influenced by two factors: the classical tradition of Central Europe and the political liberalization of the Prague Spring in 1968.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because the latter occurred during Mr. Havel's own lifetime, rock-and-roll seems to have left the stronger mark.</p>
        <p>Mr. Havel has a long history with the rock group Pulnoc's predecessor, Plastic People of the Universe, a leading Czecho slovak rock band that was anathema to the former Communist Government. Michael Zantovsky, Mr. Havel's press spokesman and confidant, says, "Havel's involvement with the Plastic People had a lot to do with his being where he is today."</p>
        <p>Mr. Havel has an extensive record collection, about half of it classical and the other half rock-and-roll and jazz. (He often listens to CD's in his official car.) According to Mr. Zantovsky, Havel's pop favorites include Bruce Springsteen's "Born in the U.S.A.," which he once played to a visiting group of American Congressmen; Paul Simon's "Rhythm of the Saints"; a recent memorial album for Andy Warhol by Lou Reed and John Cale entitled "Songs for Drella," and albums by the Rolling Stones.</p>
        <p>Among his collection of dogeared albums from the 60's are those by the Velvet Underground, the Doors and the Mothers of Invention. "I feel he's quite conservative in his musical tastes," says Mr. Zantovsky.</p>
        <p>Favorite classical composers include Mozart and the Czechs Janacek and Dvorak. Among contemporaries, Mr. Havel also likes the hard-rocker Michael Kocab, a former member of Parliament, and, of course, Pulnoc. --</p>
        <p>Burton Bollag</p>
        <p>POP VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
