<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman, 37, Is Charged With Killing Her Husband</title>
    <meta content="12elephant" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC163EF931A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman, 37, Is Charged With Killing Her Husband</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA BUCKLEY and REBECCA CATHCART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cathcart, Rebecca; Buckley, Cara</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Hamilton Heights woman was arrested and charged yesterday with murder after a fight with her husband at their home, the police said.</p>
        <p>Donna Cobbs, 37, had repeatedly hit her husband, Kevin Cobbs, 38, in the chest with a ceramic elephant, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Hamilton Heights woman was arrested and charged yesterday with murder after a fight with her husband at their home, the police said.</p>
        <p>Donna Cobbs, 37, had repeatedly hit her husband, Kevin Cobbs, 38, in the chest with a ceramic elephant, the police said.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the fight at 6 a.m., Mr. Cobbs tried to leave the apartment, on St. Nicholas Place near West 153rd Street, and collapsed. Ms. Cobbs tried to revive him with CPR, and then called 911, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cobbs, who the police said had been stabbed once in the torso, was pronounced dead one hour later at Harlem Hospital Center, where his wife worked as a nurse.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they found a small knife in the apartment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cobbs told the police that Mr. Cobbs had been choking her. She told investigators that she had clubbed Mr. Cobbs with the elephant, but denied that she had stabbed him, the police said. There were no reports of domestic disputes at the home, the police said, adding that the victim may have been intoxicated.</p>
        <p>The couple have six children, neighbors said, including 7-year-old twin girls. The police said the children were not at home yesterday morning.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said the couple seemed to get along, and were friendly, although they kept to themselves.</p>
        <p>''They seemed very warm,'' said Sondra Narvaez, 33, who lives in the apartment below the family's unit. ''She was very nice. She always tried to speak Spanish with me.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Narvaez said she saw Mr. Cobbs returning home Friday night about 11 p.m., but that nothing seemed unusual. The family had lived there at least 11 years, she said.</p>
        <p>Detectives combed the home yesterday, and they took the intact tan ceramic elephant, which is less than one foot tall.</p>
        <p>The six-story building where the family lives in is dingy and filthy, with rotting chicken bones, garbage and feces strewn along the stairs and stairwells. But Ms. Narvaez, who sometimes sold Avon products to Ms. Cobbs, said she often noticed how immaculate the family's narrow, three-bedroom apartment was, even though eight people lived there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
