<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former KLA Manager To Return as President</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="479881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KLA INSTRUMENTS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHROEDER, KENNETH L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DA173EF931A25753C1A967958260" item-length="337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former KLA Manager To Return as President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence M. Fisher</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The KLA Instruments Corporation said yesterday that Kenneth L. Schroeder, who was on the company's management team from 1979 to 1987, would return as president and chief operating officer, effective Nov. 4. KLA, based in San Jose, Calif., produces image automation systems used in manufacturing semiconductors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schroeder, who is 47, resigned effective Oct. 18 from Genus Inc. of Mountain View, Calif., a maker of semiconductor manufacturing equipment, where he was president and chief operating officer. Genus said that his position would not be filled immediately, but that his responsibilities would be assumed by William W. R. Elder, the chairman and chief executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The KLA Instruments Corporation said yesterday that Kenneth L. Schroeder, who was on the company's management team from 1979 to 1987, would return as president and chief operating officer, effective Nov. 4. KLA, based in San Jose, Calif., produces image automation systems used in manufacturing semiconductors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schroeder, who is 47, resigned effective Oct. 18 from Genus Inc. of Mountain View, Calif., a maker of semiconductor manufacturing equipment, where he was president and chief operating officer. Genus said that his position would not be filled immediately, but that his responsibilities would be assumed by William W. R. Elder, the chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>At KLA, Mr. Schroeder succeeds Robert R. Anderson, a co-founder, who has been named vice chairman. Kenneth Levy, also a co-founder, becomes chairman and continues as chief executive.</p>
        <p>"Bob has wanted to curtail his direct involvement with the company for some time to pursue other financial interests, but it has taken time to find the right combination of skills in a C.O.O. that would allow that to happen," Mr. Levy said in a statement. Mr. Anderson will continue to advise the company's senior management team but will reduce his activities at the company to approximately two days a week, Mr. Levy said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schroeder, who will also be named to KLA's board, joined the company as vice president of manufacturing and then became, successively, vice president and general manager of the reticle and photomask inspection division, and of the wafer inspection division. In 1985, he became senior vice president of the company.</p>
        <p>In 1987, Mr. Schroeder left KLA to become president and chief executive of Photon Dynamics, a San Jose start-up company, where he remained until joining Genus last year.</p>
        <p>"He has the right combination of proven operational skills, knowledge of the semiconductor business, and first-hand experience with our particular segment of the industry to optimize KLA's business performance," Mr. Levy said.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS PEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
