<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pagliarulo Hits It a Ton As Twins Win It in 10</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="479778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TORONTO BLUE JAYS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MINNESOTA TWINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D81738F931A25753C1A967958260" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pagliarulo Hits It a Ton As Twins Win It in 10</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Oct. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American League Championship Series was billed as a battle of the bullpens. Even though Minnesota Manager Tom Kelly was immensely proud of his relief corps, anchored by stopper Rick Aguilera, he conceded that Toronto's group was deeper.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the battle of the bullpens raged into extra innings in Game 3 at the Skydome. This time, the Blue Jays' relievers failed. Right-handed rookie Mike Timlin gave up a one-out, pinch-hit home run to Mike Pagliarulo in the 10th inning that allowed the Twins to sneak away with a 3-2 victory and a 2-1 lead in the series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American League Championship Series was billed as a battle of the bullpens. Even though Minnesota Manager Tom Kelly was immensely proud of his relief corps, anchored by stopper Rick Aguilera, he conceded that Toronto's group was deeper.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the battle of the bullpens raged into extra innings in Game 3 at the Skydome. This time, the Blue Jays' relievers failed. Right-handed rookie Mike Timlin gave up a one-out, pinch-hit home run to Mike Pagliarulo in the 10th inning that allowed the Twins to sneak away with a 3-2 victory and a 2-1 lead in the series.</p>
        <p>The Twins will try for a second straight victory Saturday night when they send Jack Morris -- an 18-game winner during the regular season and the victor in Game 1 in Minnesota on Tuesday -- to the mound. He will face right-hander Todd Stottlemyre (15-8).</p>
        <p>"Our bullpen did great, even though we did walk some people," Kelly said. "The bottom line is we got it done. Fortunately, Pagliarulo bombed one. I think that surprised everyone in the stadium."</p>
        <p>No one was more excited than Paglia rulo, a platoon third baseman.</p>
        <p>"It might have been the shortest game of my life, but the sweetest game of my life," Pagliarulo said. "I was real excited. I almost missed first base."</p>
        <p>Pagliarulo, who hit 32 homers with the Yankees in 1987 but only six for the Twins this season, batted for Scott Leius, the starting third baseman.</p>
        <p>He connected off Timlin with a bases-empty drive over the right-field wall that was the Twins' first homer in the playoffs. It capped a satisfying comeback for the Twins, who fell behind by 2-0 in the first but chipped away to even matters after six.</p>
        <p>Until Pagliarulo's home run, Toronto relievers David Wells and Tom Henke had limited the Twins to one hit in three and one-third innings. Praise From Puckett</p>
        <p>"To come in here to win in the top of the 10th in their park says a lot about us," said Kirby Puckett. "Emotionally, we're all drained. We won't be in the driver's seat until we win it all. We still have to come back tomorrow.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people thought Pags was washed up, but we knew he wasn't. He's a hard worker. He swings about a thousand swings every game, so if it could happen for anybody I'm glad it happened for him."</p>
        <p>Erickson, like teammate Kevin Tapani in Game 2, started off shakily. Tapani allowed the Blue Jays a 3-0 lead after three innings and the Twins never recovered in a 5-2 loss. Tonight, Erickson faltered in the first, but the Twins recovered.</p>
        <p>"When we got behind 2-zip, I'm worried about my kid," Kelly said of Erickson. "He threw 30-some pitches the first inning. When you're on a three-man rotation, it's not the best way to go about it. He was nervous, obviously nervous. He's 23 years old. I think pitching in the playoffs might have worn him out a little bit."</p>
        <p>The first Toronto run came by way of a familiar vehicle, a laser-shot of a home run to dead center by Joe Carter, who collected 23 of his team-high 33 home runs and notched 64 of his team-high 108 runs batted in at the Skydome.</p>
        <p>The home run was the first by either team in the series (not to mention the first in an American League playoff game in 51 innings, the longest homerless streak in the history of post-season play). A second run crossed shortly thereafter when Candy Maldonado followed a two-out walk issued by Erickson to John Olerud and an infield single by Kelly Gruber with a double to the base of the left-field wall.</p>
        <p>The hit, the first of the series by Maldonado, also produced the first run batted in for Toronto by someone other than their 3-4-5 hitters: Carter, Olerud and Gruber.</p>
        <p>Erickson settled down after that and worked his way nicely out of a two-on, no-out jam in the fourth. His determination proved important because the Twins, still in close proximity, started chipping away at Jimmy Key in the fifth. Carter Is Injured</p>
        <p>The left-hander had allowed only one hit and one base-runner in the first four innings. But in the fifth, Shane Mack drove a ball to deep right, putting a triple on the board and a scare of the worst sort into the Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>The scare was supplied by Carter, who tried a leaping catch by planting his left foot halfway up the pliable outfield wall. When he landed, he appeared to do so awkwardly. He then limped after the ball, relayed it, and went down in a heap.</p>
        <p>Though Carter writhed in pain for a while, he was able to resume play. But he came out for a pinch-runner in the seventh inning after being intentionally walked. He was later described to be suffering from a slightly sprained right ankle.</p>
        <p>"I think Joe played two innings on guts," said Cito Gaston, the Toronto manager. "He was hurting the whole time. The last time he hit, he finally admitted he couldn't run. I don't know what's going to happen tomorrow. Hopefully we can D.H. him."</p>
        <p>Key was not able to maintain his shutout. The next batter after Mack tripled was the struggling Kent Hrbek, who was 1 for 8 while batting cleanup against right-handed starters in the first two games of the series.</p>
        <p>Batting sixth in tonight's lineup, he had grounded out in his first time at bat against Key. This time, Hrbek hit a grounder again, but it was good for a run as Mack scored just ahead of second baseman Roberto Alomar's throw to the plate. Exit Erickson</p>
        <p>That made it 2-1, Toronto. But Erickson didn't stick around to see the Twins tie it. The right-hander opened the Jays' fifth by issuing his fifth walk of the game. He had a 1-2 count against the next hitter, Carter, when Kelly went to the mound and hooked him in favor of David West. The former Met made it interesting by striking out the side, but not before issuing a second walk in the inning and throwing a wild pitch.</p>
        <p>One inning later, Key lost the lead. And again, he was hurt by the extra-base hit. First, Chuck Knoblauch doubled with one out for his fifth hit in three games. Then Puckett, emerging from what had been a 1-for-7 slump, picked up his second straight hit, a run-scoring single. INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>With four managerial firings and two hirings this playoff week, baseball appears to have forsaken its rule barring clubs from announcing personnel moves during postseason play. It's no mistake. The decision to waive the rule was made by Commissioner FAY VINCENT.</p>
        <p>"I became persuaded that there were so many managers not knowing what their futures were that it had gotten to the point that it was unfair to the various individuals," the commissioner explained before Game 3 of the American League  Championship Series.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
