<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teach Your Children Well</title>
    <meta content="Shulevitz.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Education; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/27/books/review/Shulevitz.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1785476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Luker, Kristin</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">When Sex Goes to School (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DA143EF934A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teach Your Children Well</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Teach Your Children Well</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Judith Shulevitz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shulevitz, Judith</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN SEX GOES TO SCHOOL</p>
        <p>Warring Views on Sex --</p>
        <p>and Sex Education -- Since the Sixties.</p>
        <p>By Kristin Luker.</p>
        <p>368 pp. W.W. Norton &amp; Company. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does sex education make a difference in young people’s behavior? Not much, Kristin Luker writes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN SEX GOES TO SCHOOL</p>
        <p>Warring Views on Sex --</p>
        <p>and Sex Education -- Since the Sixties.</p>
        <p>By Kristin Luker.</p>
        <p>368 pp. W.W. Norton &amp; Company. $25.95.</p>
        <p>Only toward the end of a 300-odd page book about sex education in America does Kristin Luker permit herself a bottom line: it doesn't matter what teachers say because it won't change what students do. Only that's not how she puts it. Luker, a sociologist, avoids bold assertion. She prefers to excavate her points with a fine brush. Does sex ed lead teenagers to have more sex or have it sooner, as critics insist? There's no evidence that it does. Does sex ed increase contraceptive use, as defenders reply? Also hard to prove. American teenage girls start having sex later than they did 10 years ago and favor birth control more and get pregnant less than they did 20 years ago, but if sex education can claim credit for their caution, it can't claim much. AIDS and virginity pledges are equally proximate causes.</p>
        <p>So why do school boards panic when forced to vote on human sexuality curriculums? Why has the Republican Party deemed support for abstinence education worthy of inclusion on its national platform? Luker, a professor at the University of California, Berkeley, and author of the landmark book ''Abortion and the Politics of Motherhood'' (1984), has been talking to activists for and against sex education for a somewhat astounding 20 years, and at this point probably knows what they're thinking better than they do. In ''When Sex Goes to School'' (a cheesy title, but never mind), she argues that the fight over sex education is no mere bread-and-circuses distraction from the so-called real issues. Nor are our differences of opinion minor fractures in the social body. We can't agree about sex education because we can't agree about sex, and the way in which we disagree about sex has everything to do with how we're breaking apart as a nation.</p>
        <p>Luker identifies Americans' competing visions of sexuality as ''liberal'' and ''conservative,'' but even she acknowledges that those terms are too flabby to nail down our real differences. More muscular terms, it seems to me, would be ''naturalist'' and ''sacralist.'' Naturalists, whom Luker calls sexual liberals, hold that sex is natural and unmysterious, a healthy, pleasurable, quasi-recreational activity. Sacralists, whom Luker calls sexual conservatives, consider sex sacred but dangerous, transformative when contained by marriage but destructive outside it. Sex education, to the naturalist, involves nothing more than helping young people manage the risks of having sex by giving them the facts. It's information, not values. To the sacralist, conventional sex education is chock-full of values, but all the wrong ones. It's an indoctrination in secularism, teaching kids to be irresponsible and draining sex of its mystery and power. ''Sexuality isn't peanuts and popcorn, although there are those who made it be that,'' says one minister Luker talked to. ''Thinking of sex that way, it's such a diminution of what is actual and real.''</p>
        <p>Luker traces the debate about sex education back to its invention by the ''social hygienists'' of the Progressive era, but she locates the source of present-day hostilities in the sexual revolution of the 1960's, which she calls as ''disorienting and historically important'' as the French, American and Russian Revolutions. ''Like them,'' she writes, ''it will continue to reshape human life in profound ways for many, many years to come.'' She illustrates her thesis with stories from four small towns across America where sex-ed disputes became bitter enough to attract media attention. (Luker picked her locales with the help of a clipping service, which may explain her book's biggest handicap. She interviewed mainly active members of the Protestant religious right and their opponents -- most of them parents -- who showed up en masse at school board hearings. It would have been nice to hear from observant Jews, Muslims and Catholics, and also from teenagers, even if they don't testify before school boards in newsworthy numbers.)</p>
        <p>Many of Luker's most telling stories come from what you might call the sexual neoconservatives, liberals who were mugged, to borrow a phrase, by some painful encounter with extramarital sexuality. Sandy Ames, for example, started out as a supporter of the National Organization for Women: ''I was moving up, I was in middle management, and I had my own company car. All that kind of stuff, at 25. Married and got pregnant and he left me, and it just kind of opened my eyes.'' That's when she moved back in with her parents, had her daughter, started going to church and wound up opposing sex education. Then there's Mrs. Boland, as Luker calls her, who probably started out as a conservative but became a radical when her husband raped their daughter. It's not, she told Luker, that her husband had ever taken a sex-ed class; it's that the ''morally neutral, 'values-clarification''' approach had frayed the social restraints that she feels ought to have kept men like her husband in line. ''The way sex is taught nowadays,'' said Mrs. Boland, in Luker's paraphrase, ''takes the 'thou shalt nots' out of it and validates personal preference over right and wrong.''</p>
        <p>Luker, however, makes it hard to accept generalizations about the way sex is taught nowadays. The battle lines are clear. There's ''comprehensive'' sex education, so called because it's meant to start early and keep going through 12th grade, and also because it teaches safe sex along with biology. And there's abstinence education, in which teachers tell students not to have sex till marriage. ''Comprehensive'' sex ed describes; abstinence education proscribes. But such distinctions tend to blur in the classroom. Opponents of sex education are forced to tailor their message to the Internet generation by presenting self-restraint not as a moral necessity but as a choice, as well as a form of birth control -- the safest form -- and from that, any smart student could deduce that sex involves making choices and that contraception is good. Meanwhile, ''comprehensive'' sex educators have stopped sneering at abstinence, if they ever actually did. A surprisingly large number of teachers in ''comprehensive'' programs (few of which are particularly comprehensive) told researchers in one study that the message they want their students to take home is not to have sex.</p>
        <p>If the two sides are moving closer together and sex education doesn't work anyway, what exactly are we fighting about? The drama of this book comes from watching the exceptionally thoughtful Luker try to figure that out. ''The sexual conservatives and sexual liberals I interviewed live in the same towns, practice the same professions, have similar educational and social backgrounds ... and often belong to the same church,'' she writes. And yet, she concludes, ''the two sides have very little in common.'' They disagree on ''basic questions about human nature,'' and therefore on the kind of society they want to live in. Conservatives are ''modern-day Calvinists'' who believe ''humans are fundamentally capable of the worst'' and that society must protect itself through hierarchies, boundaries and unquestionable moral codes. Liberals worry about society encroaching on the individual, and have doubts about all of the above.</p>
        <p>One way to get these conflicting worldviews out in the open is to fight about marriage, which Luker thinks is the true subject of the sex-ed wars. Irene Thomas married at 28 and wouldn't want her daughter getting married much earlier than that, because the girl needs time to establish a career and also because Irene considers early marriage -- ''usually done on a hormonal basis'' -- a mistake. Judy Samson, happy to have married at 30, wouldn't want her daughter to have to wait till then to make love: She would ''feel a sense of loss if my daughter had no sexuality until she was 29 or 30.'' These women consider marriage one choice among others -- the right one, probably, but only when people are ready -- and want their children to be acquainted with their other options in the meantime. But to Jenny Letterman, marriage is the only option, and she doesn't want her son encountering mixed messages that might lead him astray, so that he comes to marriage as '''damaged goods,' hardened and jaded and closed off from the miracle of true emotional and physical intimacy that a happy marriage can bring,'' Luker writes. She ''can't just live and let live because marriage, one of the most cherished institutions in her life, is being devalued in the classroom.''</p>
        <p>In a nice twist ending, Luker, who starts out a textbook liberal, comes to see what Jenny means. The advent of contraception and abortion may have allowed some women to pursue their dreams, but ''by loosening men's ties to marriage and family'' it made those more interested in marriage than careers more likely to wind up as poor, single mothers. Luker also thinks that marriage is under stress, although, being a sociologist, she ascribes that stress to socioeconomic forces -- the impoverishment of the working class, which makes the poor less able to afford marriage; the rise of a wealthy elite free not to worry about the vicissitudes of single parenthood -- rather than to declining American morals. Luker even sees merit in abstinence education. While researching her book, she was stunned to learn how much pressure teenagers now put on one another to have sex. By making it a virtue to refrain, she says, ''abstinence programs may in fact provide valuable social support for the idea that young people (young women in particular) don't have to be sexually active if they don't want to be.'' They could create a ''zone of sexual autonomy.''</p>
        <p>But if the notoriously inconclusive data on sex education show anything, it's that teaching abstinence makes it more likely that young people will have unsafe sex once they start having it. So what to do? Unsatisfyingly but perhaps unsurprisingly, Luker gives two answers, one typically liberal, the other somewhat more conservative. The liberal answer: more choices and more information. Teach both the naturalist and sacralist perspectives as part of an important lesson in civic life, which is that fellow citizens may legitimately disagree about how sexuality contributes to ''social and personal flourishing.'' Her conservative answer: take the long view. ''If what is at stake is both a real and metaphorical attempt to manage one of the largest and most pervasive cultural, social, political and economic shifts of our times within the intimate realm of the family,'' she writes, ''you can imagine that it might be difficult to get opposing sides to sit down and come up with a working plan.'' It might indeed.</p>
        <p>Judith Shulevitz is a critic and essayist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Judith Shulevitz is a critic and essayist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
