<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regional Outlook</title>
    <meta content="27local" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1785900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2D8103EF934A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regional Outlook</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Litsky</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frank Litsky of The New York Times looks at the top teams in the East in Division I-AA, Division II and Division III.</p>
        <p>The college football powerhouses this fall seem sure to include Notre Dame, Texas, Southern California, Ohio State, Florida and New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frank Litsky of The New York Times looks at the top teams in the East in Division I-AA, Division II and Division III.</p>
        <p>The college football powerhouses this fall seem sure to include Notre Dame, Texas, Southern California, Ohio State, Florida and New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire?</p>
        <p>Absolutely. While those other traditional powers are among the 119 teams in the N.C.A.A.'s Division I-A, where stadium crowds can exceed 100,000 and football budgets run into many millions of dollars, New Hampshire is among the 118 teams in Division I-AA, where crowds are smaller, athletic scholarships are fewer or nonexistent and the football atmosphere is less frenetic.</p>
        <p>The strongest I-AA conference in the East is the Atlantic 10, and the strongest of its 12 teams is New Hampshire. In major preseason rankings, New Hampshire was chosen as the best I-AA team in the nation by two polls and second best by a third.</p>
        <p>The I-AA national championship is decided by a 16-team postseason tournament, not through polls or statistical doodling or a handful of bowl games, as is done in Division I-A. New Hampshire is a solid I-AA candidate for the national title, along with Appalachian State, Montana, Southern Illinois and others.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire, like many other I-AA programs, likes to play a road game every year against a I-A team. The publicity, especially if the I-AA team wins, is good, and the financial guarantee helps support the entire athletic program.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 9, the Wildcats of New Hampshire will open their season against the Wildcats of I-A Northwestern. Northwestern plays in the powerful Big Ten, but it is recovering from a season in which it finished last in Division I-A in total defense, allowing 480 yards a game.</p>
        <p>New Hampshire lives on its offense, especially its passing, although there may be an expanded running game this year. The defense has lost seven starters, and Coach Sean McDonnell said, ''Concerns on the defensive side are many.'' But the team scored 41.7 points a game as the Wildcats went 11-2 last season, and the offense returns two dynamic starters.</p>
        <p>One is the junior quarterback Ricky Santos, a close runner-up last year in voting for the Walter Payton Trophy, the I-AA equivalent of the Heisman. The other is the senior wide receiver David Ball, who needs only six touchdown catches to break Jerry Rice's I-AA career record of 50.</p>
        <p>Despite big games by both players, New Hampshire was upset by Northern Iowa, 17-14, in the I-AA quarterfinals last December. The sting remains.</p>
        <p>''I'd say the Northern Iowa game, more than the polls, is the No. 1 reason we go out and work hard,'' Ball said. ''It's great and it's an honor to be ranked No. 1, but it's more about what happens on the Saturday when you should be playing and you're not because you got beat. That's what pushes us.''</p>
        <p>A look at prospects in the East in Division I-AA, Division II and Division III:</p>
        <p>Atlantic 10 (I-AA)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- A poll of coaches and members of the news media ranked New Hampshire, Hofstra and Massachusetts as the top teams in the conference's North Division and James Madison, Richmond, Delaware and William and Mary atop the South. James Madison was 7-4 last season but lost those four games by a total of 16 points. Its high-scoring offense augments a defense that allowed only 15.3 points a game last year, fifth best in I-AA. This is the last year for football in the Atlantic 10, with all conference teams moving to the Colonial Athletic Association next year for football only.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- QB Ricky Santos and WR David Ball, New Hampshire; DB Tony LeZotte and DE Kevin Winston, James Madison; LB Gian Villante, Hofstra; RB Steve Baylark, Massachusetts; RB Omar Cuff, Delaware.</p>
        <p>Patriot League (I-AA)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Colgate, Lafayette and Lehigh are the best in this league, which offers no football scholarships. Colgate's Jordan Scott rushed for 1,364 yards last year as a freshman, but the defensive line is new. Lafayette plays six road games, and Lehigh must adjust to a new head coach, Andy Coen.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- RB Jordan Scott and S Geoff Bean, Colgate; QB Brad Maurer and DE Marvin Snipes, Lafayette; QB Sedale Threatt, Lehigh.</p>
        <p>MAAC (I-AA)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Duquesne has won the past seven conference titles. Its 37-game conference winning streak is the best in the nation and the Dukes are dominant again. Marist may be the only challenger.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- RB Jeremy McCullough and CB Kyle Postell, Duquesne; RB Obozua Ehikioya, Marist; LB Andrew Lipski, Iona.</p>
        <p>Northeast (I-AA)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Albany, which last year was last in the conference in scoring (17.1 points a game) and first in scoring defense (17.6), has a solid defense again. Central Connecticut and Stony Brook, both with new head coaches, should contend in this strong league.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- LB Colin Disch and DL Michael Dungey, Albany; RB Jo Jo Freeman, Central Connecticut; QB Anthony Doria, St. Francis (Pa.).</p>
        <p>Northeast 10 (II)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- C. W. Post, which won two games in last season's N.C.A.A. tournament, has the edge. In a league in which each program is limited to 36 football scholarships, Southern Connecticut (good passing and an active secondary) and Bentley are the next best teams.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- CB Woody Aime and WR Jo-el Kimaiyo, C. W. Post; QB Steven Armstrong, Southern Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Empire 8 (III)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Ithaca has won every title in the conference's four-year history and is a clear favorite again. Other contenders are St. John Fisher and Alfred.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- C Justin Brunell and K Brett Kitenplon, Ithaca; LB Gene Lang, St. John Fisher; RB Elmer Newsome, Alfred.</p>
        <p>Liberty League (III)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Union, 11-1 last year, should be the best again despite a new offensive line. Hobart is also nationally ranked and could match last season's 9-2 record.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- RB Tom Arcidiacono, WR Steve Angiletta and QB Anthony Marotti, Union; RB Doug Blakowski, Hobart; TE Jon Branche, Rensselaer.</p>
        <p>New England</p>
        <p>Small College (III)</p>
        <p>TEAM TO WATCH -- In a conference in which teams play no outsiders, Trinity has won 30 straight games and 4 straight conference titles. Its defense should carry it through again.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- LB Christian Allen and RB Gennaro Leo, Trinity; C Chris Kenney, Williams; DB Mike Bracco, Colby.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Athletic (III)</p>
        <p>TEAMS TO WATCH -- Rowan was a national contender last year despite playing the last half of the season without its best quarterback, Mike Orihel. He returns this year from a hand injury. Cortland State and Montclair State are also contenders.</p>
        <p>PLAYERS TO WATCH -- QB Mike Orihel, DE Randy Tosh and DE Keith Heimerl, Rowan; DB Aharon Kiett, Kean.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
