<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="27ctlistingsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1785672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DA133EF934A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="2384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Brookfield Afternoons at the Arbor: ''Dixieland Jazz Party,'' Randy Sandke, John Alfred and others. Aug. 27 at 4 p.m. Free. Brookfield Library, 182 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-6241.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Bill Kirchen, roots. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $32. Fairfield Theater Company, 70 Sanford Street. (203) 259-1036.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Summer Sings: Choral concert, presented by the Fairfield County Chorale and the Trinity Chorale. Monday at 8 p.m. $5. Trinity Episcopal Church in Southport, 61 Unquowa Road. (203) 254-1333.</p>
        <p>Kent Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons'' and Astor Piazzola's ''Four Seasons of Buenos Aires.'' Sept. 2 at 8 p.m. St. Andrew's Church, 1 North Main Street. (860) 355-5930.</p>
        <p>New London Labor Day Concert presented by the United States Coast Guard Band. Sept. 3 at 2 p.m. Free. Leamy Hall Auditorium, Mohegan Avenue. (860) 701-6826.</p>
        <p>Sherman Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons'' and Astor Piazzola's ''Four Seasons of Buenos Aires.'' Friday at 8 p.m. $10 to $20. Lake Mauweehoo Clubhouse, Route 37 South and Leach Hollow Road. (860) 355-5930.</p>
        <p>Stamford The Harmonica Guys. Sept. 2 at 2 p.m. Free. Sterling Glen of Stamford, 77 Third Street. (203) 327-4551.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Chester ''The 60's Project'' by Janet Brenner and Ken Levine, directed by Richard Maltby Jr. Through Sept. 3. $50. Norma Terris Theater, 33 North Main Street. (860) 873-8668.</p>
        <p>Hartford Tennessee Williams's ''Summer and Smoke,'' directed by Michael Wilson. Thursday through Oct. 1. $22 to $57. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>Ivoryton Neil Simon's ''The Sunshine Boys.'' Through Sept. 3. Ivoryton Playhouse, 103 Main Street. (860) 767-7318.</p>
        <p>New Haven Shakespeare's ''Much Ado About Nothing'' and ''Robin Hood,'' adapted by Alfred Noyes, in alternating performances, presented by the Elm Shakespeare Company. Through Sept. 3. Free; donations accepted. Edgerton Park, 75 Cliff Street. (203) 393-1436.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Late Night Catechism,'' one-nun show by Vicki Quade and Maripat Donovan. Through Aug. 27. $20 and $25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New London Shakespeare in the Arboretum: Euripides' ''Iphegenia at Aulis,'' directed by Derron Wood. Through Sept. 3. $15; seniors and students, $12; children under 12, $10. Flock Theater, 10 Prospect Street. (860) 443-3119.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Make Me a Song,'' written and directed by Rob Ruggiero. Through Sept. 24. $35 to $45. TheaterWorks, 5 Brookside Avenue. (860) 350-6863.</p>
        <p>Sharon ''Divas Do the 60's,'' popular songs from the 1960's. Aug. 27 at 5 p.m. $25 to $35. TriArts' Sharon Playhouse, 49 Amenia Road. (860) 364-7469.</p>
        <p>Westport Arthur Miller's ''The Archbishop's Ceiling,'' directed by Gregory Mosher. Through Sept. 10. $35 to $55. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-5137, Extension 197.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Chester ''Mixed Media Landscape Paintings by Marlene Lenker.'' Through Oct. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Beth Shalom Rodfe Zedek Synagogue, 55 East Kings Highway. (860) 437-8664.</p>
        <p>Essex New works by Christopher Zhang. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brick Gallery Essex, 10 Main Street. (860) 767-2545.</p>
        <p>Essex ''Cut,'' multimedia works by Michael Souter. Through Sept. 4. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Garvin Gallery, 8 Novelty Lane. (860) 767-9481.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Paintings by the Sea,'' new works by Karl Soderlund. Through Sept. 4. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Karl Soderlund Gallery and Studio, 1657 Post Road. (203) 319-1929.</p>
        <p>Farmington ''Greetings From Unionville,'' postcard exhibition. Through Oct. 31. Hours: Wednesdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. Unionville Museum, 15 School Street. (860) 673-2231.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Best in Show: Dogs in Art From the Renaissance to the Present.'' Through Aug. 27. ''The Nature of Dogs.'' Through Nov. 26. ''Jazz Photographs From the Bruce Museum Collection.'' Through Oct. 22. ''Bruce Museum Collection Highlights.'' Saturday through Oct. 29. $6 and $7; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Guilford 59th Annual Juried Exhibition, works by various artists. Thursday through Sept. 22. Reception: Thursday, 6 to 8 p.m. $5 and $7; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Thursdays and Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 7 p.m. Guilford Art Center, Route 77. (208) 318-0411.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum Collection.'' Through Dec. 31. ''Shifting Terrain,'' contemporary landscape photography by Andy Goldsworthy, Sally Mann and others. Through Nov. 5. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Kent ''President's Art Show and Sale,'' juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through Sept. 3. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Kent Art Association, Route 7. (860) 927-3989.</p>
        <p>Kent Etchings by Robert Andrew Parker, bronze sculpture by Peter Woytuk and oil paintings by Yuri Vaschenko. Through Aug. 27. Oil paintings by Dennis Hartley. Sept. 2 through Oct. 6. Reception: Sept. 2, 2 to 5 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morrison Gallery, 5 Maple Street. (860) 927-4501.</p>
        <p>Lakeville Paintings by Emilie Clark, Franklin Evans and Katia Santibanez. Through Sept. 10. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morgan Lehman Gallery, 24 Sharon Road, Route 41. (860) 435-0898.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Paintings by Joan Jardine and Roxann Poppe Leibenhaut. Through Wednesday. Hours: Mondays, noon to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>Madison ''The Putney Painters,'' works by contemporary artists from Putney, Vt. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 6 p.m. Susan Powell Fine Art, 679 Boston Post Road. (203) 318-0616.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Tusks! Ice Age Mammoths and Mastodons,'' fossil specimens, replicas and artifacts from the ice age. Through Oct. 1. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Mystic ''Bring On da Juice,'' works by Diana McCue, Chelle Lu Messina and Margaret Tyler. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Emporium Gallery, 15 Water Street. (860) 536-3891.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Texture,'' juried exhibition of works by 22 national and international artists. Through Sept. 17. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Breaking the Binding: Printing and the Third Dimension,'' three-dimensional books. Through Sept. 7. Free. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 8:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays, 8:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 121 Wall Street. (203) 432-8131.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Golden Years,'' installation by John Fleming. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Serene Scenes of Summer,'' works by area artists. Through Friday. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Elm City Artists Gallery, 87 Audubon Street. (203) 444-3100.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Kehler Liddell,'' works by Jessica Cuni Applebee, Dean Fisher, Edith Borax Morrison and others. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Haskins Laboratories Gallery, 300 George Street, 9th Floor. (203) 772-2788.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''White Heat II,'' works by Clint Deckert, John Schieffer and others. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. White Space Gallery, 1020 Chapel Street. (203) 495-1200.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Britannia and Muscovy: English Silver at the Court of the Tsars.'' Through Sept. 10. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New London ''An Undulating Presence,'' installation by Susan Benarcik. Through Sept. 3. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''The Beauty of the Ordinary,'' works by Lawrence Gunerman and Marilyn Gunerman. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich ''Through the Eyes of Children: The Rwanda Project,'' photographs by young survivors of the Rwandan genocide. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays, 6:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Fridays, 6:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 7 a.m. to 5 p.m. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Velimir Chlebnikov,'' featuring paintings by Anselm Kiefer. Through Oct. 1. ''Land Mine,'' works by Laleh Khorramian, Wangechi Mutu and Michael Zansky. Through Oct. 1. ''Mary Temple: Extended Afternoon.'' Through Thursday. ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Build to Scale: Auto, Plane and Boat Model Masterpieces.'' Through Oct. 29. $4 to $8; members and children 3 and under, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Stamford Museum and Nature Center, 39 Scofieldtown Road. (203) 322-1646.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''The 41st Annual Art Department Faculty Exhibition.'' Tuesday through Oct. 15. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Stratford Exhibition of the R-4 Helicopter's Arctic and Antarctic exploits. Through Sept. 30. Free. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. National Helicopter Museum, 2480 Main Street. (203) 375-8857.</p>
        <p>Wallingford Sculptures by Marc Mellon and Babette Bloch. Through Nov. 18. Paul Mellon Arts Center, Christian Street. (203) 697-2261.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''From the Farm to the Front: Our Towns and the Revolutionary War,'' historical objects from the Waterbury region. Through Sept. 3. $4; children under 16, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mattatuck Museum Arts and History Center, 144 West Main Street. (303) 753-0381.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Summer Light,'' works by Ira Barkoff, Robert Dente, Anne Hebebrand and others. Through Sept. 9. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport ''The Cafe, the Beach, the Bedroom,'' paintings by Robert Baxter. Through Oct. 2. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockwell Art Gallery, 15 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 227-1800.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Women of Westport: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Westport Young Woman's League.'' Through Sept. 3. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Annual Summer Art Exhibition,'' works by more than 50 local Wilton artists. Through Wednesday. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Piercing the Veil,'' oil paintings by Tina Sotis and alabaster sculpture by Louise Porter-Hahn. Through Sept. 17. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Paris,'' works by Robert Crawford. Through Sept. 14. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. P. H. Miller Studio and Gallery, 495 Main Street. (203) 263-3939.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Changing Times,'' directed by André Téchiné; in French with English subtitles. Sunday through Tuesday. $8; seniors and students, $7. Cinestudio, 300 Summit Street. (860) 297-2463.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Fahrenheit 451,'' directed by François Truffaut. Wednesday at 6:30 p.m.. Free. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Bloomfield Jill Knight Weinberger, author of ''Vienna Voices.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Prosser Public Library, 1 Tunxis Avenue. (860) 243-9721.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Kevin Phillips, author of ''American Theocracy.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Ansonia Butterfly and dragonfly nature program; nets provided for up-close inspection. Aug. 27 at 3 p.m. Free; reservations required. Ansonia Nature Center, Deerfield Road. (203) 736-1053.</p>
        <p>Guilford Bird-watching walk led by Sunrise Birding. Thursday at 6 p.m. $5. Chaffinch Island Park, Chaffinch Island Road. (203) 453-6724.</p>
        <p>Pomfret Center ''Nighthawk Watch,'' nature program led by Andy Rzeznikiewicz. Aug. 27 at 6 p.m. $9; members, $4. Connecticut Audubon Society at Pomfret, 189 Pomfret Street. (860) 928-4948.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Ecology Sail'' on the SoundWaters schooner. Aug. 27 at 2 p.m. ''Sunset Sail'' on the SoundWaters schooner. Aug. 27 at 6 p.m. $30; children, $20. Brewer Yacht Haven Marina, Bateman Way. (203) 406-3319.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bristol Touch-a-Truck Festival, explore trucks including a fire truck, ambulance, tractor and snowplow. Friday, 5 to 8 p.m. $4. Imagine Nation Museum, 1 Pleasant Street. (860) 314-1400.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Carnival of the Animals Dance Workshop,'' led by teachers and students from the Ballet School of Stamford. Ages 5 to 10. Tuesday at 2 p.m. Free; reservations required. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Robert the Guitar Guy,'' children's musician. Tuesday at 11 a.m. Free. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Brookfield Afternoons at the Arbor: ''Dixieland Jazz Party,'' Randy Sandke, John Alfred and others. Aug. 27 at 4 p.m. Free. Brookfield Library, 182 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-6241.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Bill Kirchen, roots. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $32. Fairfield Theater Company, 70 Sanford Street. (203) 259-1036.</p>
        <p>Fairfield Summer Sings: Choral concert, presented by the Fairfield County Chorale and the Trinity Chorale. Monday at 8 p.m. $5. Trinity Episcopal Church in Southport, 61 Unquowa Road. (203) 254-1333.</p>
        <p>Kent Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons'' and Astor Piazzola's ''Four Seasons of Buenos Aires.'' Sept. 2 at 8 p.m. St. Andrew's Church, 1 North Main Street. (860) 355-5930.</p>
        <p>New London Labor Day Concert presented by the United States Coast Guard Band. Sept. 3 at 2 p.m. Free. Leamy Hall Auditorium, Mohegan Avenue. (860) 701-6826.</p>
        <p>Sherman Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons'' and Astor Piazzola's ''Four Seasons of Buenos Aires.'' Friday at 8 p.m. $10 to $20. Lake Mauweehoo Clubhouse, Route 37 South and Leach Hollow Road. (860) 355-5930.</p>
        <p>Stamford The Harmonica Guys. Sept. 2 at 2 p.m. Free. Sterling Glen of Stamford, 77 Third Street. (203) 327-4551.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Chester ''The 60's Project'' by Janet Brenner and Ken Levine, directed by Richard Maltby Jr. Through Sept. 3. $50. Norma Terris Theater, 33 North Main Street. (860) 873-8668.</p>
        <p>Hartford Tennessee Williams's ''Summer and Smoke,'' directed by Michael Wilson. Thursday through Oct. 1. $22 to $57. Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street. (860) 527-5151.</p>
        <p>Ivoryton Neil Simon's ''The Sunshine Boys.'' Through Sept. 3. Ivoryton Playhouse, 103 Main Street. (860) 767-7318.</p>
        <p>New Haven Shakespeare's ''Much Ado About Nothing'' and ''Robin Hood,'' adapted by Alfred Noyes, in alternating performances, presented by the Elm Shakespeare Company. Through Sept. 3. Free; donations accepted. Edgerton Park, 75 Cliff Street. (203) 393-1436.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Late Night Catechism,'' one-nun show by Vicki Quade and Maripat Donovan. Through Aug. 27. $20 and $25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New London Shakespeare in the Arboretum: Euripides' ''Iphegenia at Aulis,'' directed by Derron Wood. Through Sept. 3. $15; seniors and students, $12; children under 12, $10. Flock Theater, 10 Prospect Street. (860) 443-3119.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Make Me a Song,'' written and directed by Rob Ruggiero. Through Sept. 24. $35 to $45. TheaterWorks, 5 Brookside Avenue. (860) 350-6863.</p>
        <p>Sharon ''Divas Do the 60's,'' popular songs from the 1960's. Aug. 27 at 5 p.m. $25 to $35. TriArts' Sharon Playhouse, 49 Amenia Road. (860) 364-7469.</p>
        <p>Westport Arthur Miller's ''The Archbishop's Ceiling,'' directed by Gregory Mosher. Through Sept. 10. $35 to $55. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-5137, Extension 197.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Chester ''Mixed Media Landscape Paintings by Marlene Lenker.'' Through Oct. 31. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Beth Shalom Rodfe Zedek Synagogue, 55 East Kings Highway. (860) 437-8664.</p>
        <p>Essex New works by Christopher Zhang. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brick Gallery Essex, 10 Main Street. (860) 767-2545.</p>
        <p>Essex ''Cut,'' multimedia works by Michael Souter. Through Sept. 4. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Garvin Gallery, 8 Novelty Lane. (860) 767-9481.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Paintings by the Sea,'' new works by Karl Soderlund. Through Sept. 4. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Karl Soderlund Gallery and Studio, 1657 Post Road. (203) 319-1929.</p>
        <p>Farmington ''Greetings From Unionville,'' postcard exhibition. Through Oct. 31. Hours: Wednesdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. Unionville Museum, 15 School Street. (860) 673-2231.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Best in Show: Dogs in Art From the Renaissance to the Present.'' Through Aug. 27. ''The Nature of Dogs.'' Through Nov. 26. ''Jazz Photographs From the Bruce Museum Collection.'' Through Oct. 22. ''Bruce Museum Collection Highlights.'' Saturday through Oct. 29. $6 and $7; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Guilford 59th Annual Juried Exhibition, works by various artists. Thursday through Sept. 22. Reception: Thursday, 6 to 8 p.m. $5 and $7; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Thursdays and Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 7 p.m. Guilford Art Center, Route 77. (208) 318-0411.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum Collection.'' Through Dec. 31. ''Shifting Terrain,'' contemporary landscape photography by Andy Goldsworthy, Sally Mann and others. Through Nov. 5. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Kent ''President's Art Show and Sale,'' juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through Sept. 3. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Kent Art Association, Route 7. (860) 927-3989.</p>
        <p>Kent Etchings by Robert Andrew Parker, bronze sculpture by Peter Woytuk and oil paintings by Yuri Vaschenko. Through Aug. 27. Oil paintings by Dennis Hartley. Sept. 2 through Oct. 6. Reception: Sept. 2, 2 to 5 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morrison Gallery, 5 Maple Street. (860) 927-4501.</p>
        <p>Lakeville Paintings by Emilie Clark, Franklin Evans and Katia Santibanez. Through Sept. 10. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Morgan Lehman Gallery, 24 Sharon Road, Route 41. (860) 435-0898.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Paintings by Joan Jardine and Roxann Poppe Leibenhaut. Through Wednesday. Hours: Mondays, noon to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>Madison ''The Putney Painters,'' works by contemporary artists from Putney, Vt. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 6 p.m. Susan Powell Fine Art, 679 Boston Post Road. (203) 318-0616.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Tusks! Ice Age Mammoths and Mastodons,'' fossil specimens, replicas and artifacts from the ice age. Through Oct. 1. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Mystic ''Bring On da Juice,'' works by Diana McCue, Chelle Lu Messina and Margaret Tyler. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Emporium Gallery, 15 Water Street. (860) 536-3891.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Texture,'' juried exhibition of works by 22 national and international artists. Through Sept. 17. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Breaking the Binding: Printing and the Third Dimension,'' three-dimensional books. Through Sept. 7. Free. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 8:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays, 8:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 121 Wall Street. (203) 432-8131.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Golden Years,'' installation by John Fleming. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Serene Scenes of Summer,'' works by area artists. Through Friday. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Elm City Artists Gallery, 87 Audubon Street. (203) 444-3100.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Kehler Liddell,'' works by Jessica Cuni Applebee, Dean Fisher, Edith Borax Morrison and others. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Haskins Laboratories Gallery, 300 George Street, 9th Floor. (203) 772-2788.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''White Heat II,'' works by Clint Deckert, John Schieffer and others. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. White Space Gallery, 1020 Chapel Street. (203) 495-1200.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Britannia and Muscovy: English Silver at the Court of the Tsars.'' Through Sept. 10. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Yale Center for British Art, 1080 Chapel Street. (203) 432-2800.</p>
        <p>New London ''An Undulating Presence,'' installation by Susan Benarcik. Through Sept. 3. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''The Beauty of the Ordinary,'' works by Lawrence Gunerman and Marilyn Gunerman. Through Sept. 30. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich ''Through the Eyes of Children: The Rwanda Project,'' photographs by young survivors of the Rwandan genocide. Through Thursday. Hours: Mondays, 6:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Fridays, 6:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 7 a.m. to 5 p.m. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Velimir Chlebnikov,'' featuring paintings by Anselm Kiefer. Through Oct. 1. ''Land Mine,'' works by Laleh Khorramian, Wangechi Mutu and Michael Zansky. Through Oct. 1. ''Mary Temple: Extended Afternoon.'' Through Thursday. ''Bitter Fruit,'' photographs by Paul Fusco. Through Feb. 25. ''No Reservations: Native American History and Culture in Contemporary Art.'' Through Feb. 25. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Build to Scale: Auto, Plane and Boat Model Masterpieces.'' Through Oct. 29. $4 to $8; members and children 3 and under, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Stamford Museum and Nature Center, 39 Scofieldtown Road. (203) 322-1646.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''The 41st Annual Art Department Faculty Exhibition.'' Tuesday through Oct. 15. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>Stratford Exhibition of the R-4 Helicopter's Arctic and Antarctic exploits. Through Sept. 30. Free. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. National Helicopter Museum, 2480 Main Street. (203) 375-8857.</p>
        <p>Wallingford Sculptures by Marc Mellon and Babette Bloch. Through Nov. 18. Paul Mellon Arts Center, Christian Street. (203) 697-2261.</p>
        <p>Waterbury ''From the Farm to the Front: Our Towns and the Revolutionary War,'' historical objects from the Waterbury region. Through Sept. 3. $4; children under 16, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mattatuck Museum Arts and History Center, 144 West Main Street. (303) 753-0381.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Summer Light,'' works by Ira Barkoff, Robert Dente, Anne Hebebrand and others. Through Sept. 9. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport ''The Cafe, the Beach, the Bedroom,'' paintings by Robert Baxter. Through Oct. 2. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockwell Art Gallery, 15 Myrtle Avenue. (203) 227-1800.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Women of Westport: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Westport Young Woman's League.'' Through Sept. 3. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Annual Summer Art Exhibition,'' works by more than 50 local Wilton artists. Through Wednesday. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Piercing the Veil,'' oil paintings by Tina Sotis and alabaster sculpture by Louise Porter-Hahn. Through Sept. 17. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Paris,'' works by Robert Crawford. Through Sept. 14. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. P. H. Miller Studio and Gallery, 495 Main Street. (203) 263-3939.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Changing Times,'' directed by André Téchiné; in French with English subtitles. Sunday through Tuesday. $8; seniors and students, $7. Cinestudio, 300 Summit Street. (860) 297-2463.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Fahrenheit 451,'' directed by François Truffaut. Wednesday at 6:30 p.m.. Free. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Bloomfield Jill Knight Weinberger, author of ''Vienna Voices.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Prosser Public Library, 1 Tunxis Avenue. (860) 243-9721.</p>
        <p>Litchfield Kevin Phillips, author of ''American Theocracy.'' Thursday at 7 p.m. Free. Oliver Wolcott Library, 160 South Street. (860) 567-8030.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Ansonia Butterfly and dragonfly nature program; nets provided for up-close inspection. Aug. 27 at 3 p.m. Free; reservations required. Ansonia Nature Center, Deerfield Road. (203) 736-1053.</p>
        <p>Guilford Bird-watching walk led by Sunrise Birding. Thursday at 6 p.m. $5. Chaffinch Island Park, Chaffinch Island Road. (203) 453-6724.</p>
        <p>Pomfret Center ''Nighthawk Watch,'' nature program led by Andy Rzeznikiewicz. Aug. 27 at 6 p.m. $9; members, $4. Connecticut Audubon Society at Pomfret, 189 Pomfret Street. (860) 928-4948.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Ecology Sail'' on the SoundWaters schooner. Aug. 27 at 2 p.m. ''Sunset Sail'' on the SoundWaters schooner. Aug. 27 at 6 p.m. $30; children, $20. Brewer Yacht Haven Marina, Bateman Way. (203) 406-3319.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bristol Touch-a-Truck Festival, explore trucks including a fire truck, ambulance, tractor and snowplow. Friday, 5 to 8 p.m. $4. Imagine Nation Museum, 1 Pleasant Street. (860) 314-1400.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Carnival of the Animals Dance Workshop,'' led by teachers and students from the Ballet School of Stamford. Ages 5 to 10. Tuesday at 2 p.m. Free; reservations required. Ferguson Library Main Branch, 1 Public Library Plaza. (203) 964-1000.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Robert the Guitar Guy,'' children's musician. Tuesday at 11 a.m. Free. Wilton Library, 137 Old Ridgefield Road. (203) 762-3950.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
