<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Resume Their Hit Parade and Rescue Pérez</title>
    <meta content="27mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/27/sports/baseball/27mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1785954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D7103EF934A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Resume Their Hit Parade and Rescue Pérez</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Resume Their Hit Parade and Rescue Pérez</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez made his Mets debut last night, pitching for the first time in the majors in more than two months. He had the type of performance that makes a manager's hair fall out, looking brilliant one minute and hopelessly lost the next.</p>
        <p>But these are the Mets, and relief never seems to be more than a seven-run inning away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez looking brilliant at times and hopelessly lost at others in his Mets debut, but the Mets’ offense bailed him out with a seven-run seventh inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oliver Pérez made his Mets debut last night, pitching for the first time in the majors in more than two months. He had the type of performance that makes a manager's hair fall out, looking brilliant one minute and hopelessly lost the next.</p>
        <p>But these are the Mets, and relief never seems to be more than a seven-run inning away.</p>
        <p>The Mets' offense had the type of night that makes the ink run out of a scorekeeper's pen. Pérez left the game with the Mets trailing the Philadelphia Phillies, but they erupted later in the game for an 11-5 victory at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>''We're never going to quit; that's the same as we've been playing since the season started,'' Carlos Beltrán said. ''It doesn't matter how far behind we are in the game, we're going to try and get back.''</p>
        <p>Shawn Green had the winning hit, a two-run double in a seven-run seventh inning. Beltrán and Carlos Delgado each had two-run homers, setting a single-season franchise record by homering in the same game for the 10th time. And the littlest Met, Endy Chávez, made a big contribution with 4 of the Mets' 15 hits.</p>
        <p>The Mets (79-49) are back to their winning ways after losing for the first time in eight games in the series opener Friday. And the Phillies (65-64), who have pestered the Mets this season, cooled off after winning six of their previous seven games.</p>
        <p>The Mets took a 2-0 lead on Beltrán's homer to right field off Phillies starter Jon Lieber in the first inning. The 47,019 fans responded with a chant that is becoming familiar in these parts: ''M-V-P! M-V-P!''</p>
        <p>A bundle of significance was packed into the home run. Not only was it the 200th of Beltrán's career, but it was also his 38th of the season, tying the career high he set in 2004 while with the Kansas City Royals and the Houston Astros. The two runs batted in gave Beltrán 108 for the season, also tying his career high, established with the Royals in 1999.</p>
        <p>Pérez, who battled the butterflies at the start of the game, said the early lead calmed him.</p>
        <p>''I was feeling a little nervous because it was a new team,'' said Pérez, a left-hander who was called up from Class AAA Norfolk to fill in for Tom Glavine, who is coping with a circulatory condition.</p>
        <p>Pérez flirted with disaster early on, walking two consecutive batters after getting the game's first out. After pitching out of the jam, he was nearly flawless over the next three innings, striking out five batters.</p>
        <p>Pérez did not allow a hit until Shane Victorino's run-scoring single in the fifth inning cut the Mets' lead to 2-1. He then walked Chase Utley to load the bases for Ryan Howard. Pérez was one strike away from ending the inning when he left a slider high and over the plate. Howard crushed it over the right-field wall for a grand slam, his first of the season. It was also his National League-leading 46th home run.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, the Phillies led, 5-2, though Pérez had allowed only two hits.</p>
        <p>''He was just lights out,'' Manager Willie Randolph said of Pérez. ''He just got out of his rhythm. The same pitches he was making earlier in the game, he just had a tough time in the inning making them. He had the 0-2 pitch and you can't hang a slider to the big boy.''</p>
        <p>Pérez, whom the Mets acquired along with reliever Roberto Hernández from the Pittsburgh Pirates for outfielder Xavier Nady at the trading deadline on July 31, was the 13th pitcher to start for the Mets this season. He was 2-10 for Pittsburgh earlier this season, but Randolph said Pérez would probably get another start at some point.</p>
        <p>Pérez left after five innings with a dizzying pitching line of five earned runs, seven strikeouts and five walks. Pedro Feliciano, who pitched the seventh, earned the victory.</p>
        <p>The Phillies' lead began to crack in the sixth inning. After Beltrán walked, Delgado fought back from an 0-2 count, fouling off three pitches from Lieber before hitting a two-run homer to left-center field, cutting the Phillies' lead to 5-4.</p>
        <p>Delgado's sacrifice fly off the reliever Aaron Fultz with no outs and the bases loaded in the seventh inning tied the score.</p>
        <p>Then the onslaught began in earnest. After David Wright was intentionally walked to load the bases again, Green smacked an opposite-field, two-run double that proved to be the difference.</p>
        <p>''Just trying to drive somewhere, and it worked out,'' said Green, who was traded to the Mets from the Arizona Diamondbacks on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>José Valentín was then walked intentionally to load the bases once more, and Chávez followed with a two-run double of his own, giving the Mets a 9-5 lead.</p>
        <p>''Four hits, tying my career high in one game, is nice,'' said Chávez, who also had three singles.</p>
        <p>Then, with runners at second and third, the Phillies decided not to intentionally walk the next batter to load the bases. That may have been a mistake because Chris Woodward smacked a pinch-hit single to score Valentín and Chávez and give the Mets a cushy six-run lead.</p>
        <p>''It is contagious,'' Beltrán said of the Mets' seventh inning. ''When you find a way to get on base and the guys get on base, you just lift the team.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
