<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This AIDS Ban Invites Ridicule</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL RESTRICTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA1639F93AA25755C0A967958260" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This AIDS Ban Invites Ridicule</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American policy to block visits or permanent immigration by foreigners infected with the AIDS virus came under justifiable criticism at the international AIDS conference in Italy this week. The policy has very little public health value. Its chief effect is to make the United States a laughingstock in world medical circles. The policy should be abandoned, quickly.  The U.S. currently bans entry to foreigners infected with several diseases, including syphilis, gonorrhea, leprosy, tuberculosis -- and the virus that causes AIDS. But the Department of Health and Human Services has proposed to eliminate all but infectious tuberculosis from the list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American policy to block visits or permanent immigration by foreigners infected with the AIDS virus came under justifiable criticism at the international AIDS conference in Italy this week. The policy has very little public health value. Its chief effect is to make the United States a laughingstock in world medical circles. The policy should be abandoned, quickly.  The U.S. currently bans entry to foreigners infected with several diseases, including syphilis, gonorrhea, leprosy, tuberculosis -- and the virus that causes AIDS. But the Department of Health and Human Services has proposed to eliminate all but infectious tuberculosis from the list.</p>
        <p>The wisdom behind that proposal seems plain. Neither AIDS nor any of the other diseases to be struck is spread through air, food or water to casual bystanders. Virtually the only way for an adult to get AIDS in this country is through unprotected sexual intercourse with an infected person or by sharing contaminated drug needles.</p>
        <p>But the Justice Department, responding to an avalanche of complaints, blocked the new H.H.S. policy, leaving the old rules in place pending further debate. The two chief arguments for the ban are superficially plausible. One is that some of the infected foreigners will surely spread the virus to Americans. The other is that infected immigrants will eventually require costly care.</p>
        <p>But the danger is slight. And if cost is the issue, then the U.S. would ban all foreigners with kidney disease, cancer or other costly ailments. It enforces no such mean-spirited policy in those cases, nor should it for AIDS.</p>
        <p>The ban is particularly silly for short-term visitors. Trying even to identify such individuals brings widespread condemnation. The World Health Organization and European health ministers plan to boycott the international AIDS conference in Boston next year unless the U.S. changes its policy.</p>
        <p>How to handle foreigners seeking permanent residency is a tougher issue because the longer they stay the greater the chance some might spread the virus or require care. But by one government estimate, only about 600 AIDS-infected individuals would be admitted as permanent residents each year -- compared with a million Americans already infected. And finding them among the 600,000 admitted each year would require costly testing. If the goal is to fight AIDS, this is not where to spend the money. The rate of infection is far less among the foreigners than among Americans.</p>
        <p>What a travesty that the United States, with one of the largest AIDS-infected populations in the world, has taken a stance that implies the danger comes from abroad. The Bush Administration should reverse this ban, whose chief effect is to give the U.S. an international black eye.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
