<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Language; Through a Cocktail Glass, Darkly</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIQUOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIMES, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE173BF936A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Language; Through a Cocktail Glass, Darkly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRIMES, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF YOU THINK IT'S tough to get a decent dry martini, try tracking down the origin of the word. Or for that matter, getting the real story behind any cocktail -- not only long-forgotten rip-snorters like the fog-cutter, the snap-neck and the leg tangle but also bona fide classics.</p>
        <p>At every turn, the student of bacchanology faces the bewildering blend of misinformation, lore and legend that constitutes barroom etymology -- a pseudoscience bearing the same relation to real etymology that barroom philosophy bears to the thought of Hegel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF YOU THINK IT'S tough to get a decent dry martini, try tracking down the origin of the word. Or for that matter, getting the real story behind any cocktail -- not only long-forgotten rip-snorters like the fog-cutter, the snap-neck and the leg tangle but also bona fide classics.</p>
        <p>At every turn, the student of bacchanology faces the bewildering blend of misinformation, lore and legend that constitutes barroom etymology -- a pseudoscience bearing the same relation to real etymology that barroom philosophy bears to the thought of Hegel.</p>
        <p>Take the</p>
        <p>sidecar,</p>
        <p>a fine old drink of brandy, Cointreau and lemon juice. According to David A. Embury, author of the invaluable "Fine Art of Mixing Drinks" (1948), it was invented "by a friend of mine at a bar in Paris during World War I and was named after the motorcycle sidecar in which the good captain customarily was driven to and from the little bistro where the drink was born and christened."</p>
        <p>Note the distinguishing barroom-etymology features. The inventor of the drink, of course, is a good friend. The time and place are supplied, but hazily. Embury specifies his good friend's rank but fails to give his name. And then there's the wild leap that somehow gets a motorcycle sidecar into a cocktail glass. Why not the Three Wheeler or the Bald Front Tire?</p>
        <p>The spurious-origin story has walked hand in hand with the cocktail for nearly two centuries. The word</p>
        <p>cocktail</p>
        <p>has inspired perhaps the most notorious fraud of all -- the Flanagan Fallacy. Virtually every account of the cocktail's origins drags in Betsy Flanagan, an innkeeper during the Revolutionary War who stirred a drink with a rooster tail and dubbed it a</p>
        <p>cocktail.</p>
        <p>Some versions place the inn at Four Corners, in Westchester County, N.Y.; others locate the sacred ground a few miles away in Elmsford. For the real location, turn to Chapter 16 of James Fenimore Cooper's "Spy," published in 1821 but set in the 1780's. There, Flanagan and feather first appear, as real as fiction.</p>
        <p>Even eyewitness testimony tends to arrive through the distorting lens of a shot glass. The</p>
        <p>Bronx cocktail,</p>
        <p>rather quaint today but once a major player in saloons across the country, would appear to be well documented. "Johnny Solon is the inventor of the original Bronx cocktail!," wrote Albert Stevens Crockett in his history of the old Waldorf-Astoria's bar. And how did Crockett know? He talked to Solon himself, the Waldorf's bartender, who recalled the day early in the century when he mixed up a variation on the</p>
        <p>duplex</p>
        <p>(equal parts French and Italian vermouth, with a twist of orange peel). Solon decided to add gin and orange juice. And the name? "I had been at the Bronx Zoo a day or two before," Crockett quotes Solon as saying, "and I saw, of course, a lot of beasts I had never known. Customers used to tell me of the strange animals they saw after a lot of mixed drinks." And so the Bronx -- not the borough but the home of pink elephants. The story is about as convincing as a heffalump.</p>
        <p>The most elusive, legend-encrusted cocktail of them all is, of course, the mighty</p>
        <p>martini</p>
        <p>, that beguiling blend of gin and vermouth.  The Oxford English Dictionary gives the earliest use of the word as 1894, citing an advertisement for Heublein's Club Cocktails -- a line of premixed bottled drinks. But the drink is older than that. William F. Mulhall, bartender at the swank Hoffmann House hotel in New York, recalled mixing martinis back in the 1880's. And in his splendid treatise on the subject, "The Silver Bullet," Lowell Edmunds, chairman of the classics department at Rutgers University, turned up a martini recipe in the 1888 edition of Harry Johnson's "Bartender's Manual."</p>
        <p>The O.E.D. also asserts that</p>
        <p>martini</p>
        <p>comes from Martini &amp; Rossi vermouth -- even though the Italian vermouth was not exported to the United States at the time. (John Simpson, co-editor of the O.E.D., concedes that the etymology may be more complicated than previously thought and that the next edition of the dictionary will acknowledge the fact.)</p>
        <p>There are other claimants to the martini title. One is the Martini-Henry rifle, used by the British army between 1871 and 1891. No shred of evidence has ever been offered linking the drink and the gun, other than the fact that both have a strong kick. Slightly more tantalizing is the shadowy figure of Martini di Arma di Taggia, bartender at the Knickerbocker Hotel in New York early in the century. In his "World of Drinks and Drinking," the British writer John Doxat claimed to possess the tape-recorded testimony of an Italian bartender who recalled arriving at the Knickerbocker in 1912 and encountering a new cocktail of dry gin, dry vermouth and orange bitters invented by Martini. The late date torpedoes that theory.</p>
        <p>A third candidate is something called the Martinez cocktail. Perhaps named after the Northern California town of the same name, it pops up in the 1887 edition of Jerry Thomas's "Bon Vivant's Companion," the most famous of the early American books on drinks. The only problem is the recipe: one dash bitters, two dashes maraschino, one ounce Old Tom (i.e., sweet) gin, one wine-glass sweet vermouth, with optional dashes of sugar syrup. This is no martini; it's a molten gumdrop.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the drink has set off a ferocious dispute between the cities of Martinez and San Francisco. In the San Francisco version of the martini's invention, a thirsty traveler on his way to Martinez stopped at the El Dorado saloon, where Jerry Thomas tended bar, and asked for "something new." Presto! The Martinez. In the Martinez version of the story, a prospector returning from the gold fields stopped in a Martinez saloon and, after asking for two bottles of whisky, threw down a nugget on the bar. Instead of change, he got a new drink.</p>
        <p>The bogus origin story continues to haunt the troubled discipline that H. L. Mencken once called "alcoholology." In the early 1970's, the makers of Galliano liqueur decided to promote their product by suggesting it be mixed with vodka and orange juice to make a new drink: the</p>
        <p>Harvey Wallbanger.</p>
        <p>As part of its advertising campaign, the company created a fictional surfer by the same name. Inevitably, the cartoon character has taken on a life of his own. Today, reputable cocktail books duly note that the drink was named after a Californian named Harvey who tended to bang into walls after having had a few too many.  Now that I think about it, I seem to remember the guy. That's right -- he was a good friend of mine.</p>
        <p>William Grimes is an editor of this magazine. His history of the American cocktail is to be published next spring. William Safire is on vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Grimes is an editor of this magazine. His history of the American cocktail is to be published next spring. William Safire is on vacation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
