<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Democrat Who Still Awaits A Final Word on a Victory</title>
    <meta content="07BISH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/07/nyregion/metrocampaigns/07BISH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1438576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2002 ELECTIONS: LONG ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Absentee Voting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bishop, Timothy H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grucci, Felix J Jr (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED71E3EF934A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Democrat Who Still Awaits A Final Word on a Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Democrat Who Still Awaits a Final Word on a Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa</byline>
      <dateline>WESTHAMPTON BEACH, N.Y., Nov. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Democrat Timothy Bishop holds 2,421-vote lead over Rep Felix J Grucci Jr in New York's First District, although he stops short of claiming victory because some 6,000 absentee ballots have yet to be counted; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a bleak election for the nation's Democrats, one ray of hope was the Congressional campaign of Timothy H. Bishop, a political neophyte from Southampton who was holding a 2,421-vote lead today over Representative Felix J. Grucci Jr. in unofficial returns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop stopped short of proclaiming victory, since about 6,000 absentee ballots remained uncounted in New York's First District and Suffolk County Board of Elections officials were preparing to recanvass the votes, a standard procedure. Preliminary returns indicated, though, that he had squeaked past Mr. Grucci by 50 percent to 49 percent, so Mr. Bishop was confident enough to spend the morning thanking voters at the Ronkonkoma station of the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Timothy H. Bishop, a political neophyte from Southampton, N.Y., held a 2,421-vote lead on Wednesday over Representative Felix J. Grucci Jr. in unofficial returns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a bleak election for the nation's Democrats, one ray of hope was the Congressional campaign of Timothy H. Bishop, a political neophyte from Southampton who was holding a 2,421-vote lead today over Representative Felix J. Grucci Jr. in unofficial returns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop stopped short of proclaiming victory, since about 6,000 absentee ballots remained uncounted in New York's First District and Suffolk County Board of Elections officials were preparing to recanvass the votes, a standard procedure. Preliminary returns indicated, though, that he had squeaked past Mr. Grucci by 50 percent to 49 percent, so Mr. Bishop was confident enough to spend the morning thanking voters at the Ronkonkoma station of the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
        <p>''I would like it if it were a done deal,'' Mr. Bishop said in an interview today at his campaign office here in a small strip mall. ''I'm sure when the absentee ballots are counted, we're going to have at least the same margin of victory we have now.'' Official election returns are expected to be announced next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grucci, 50, is a Republican incumbent in a nation with a popular Republican president, in a state where the Republican governor won re-election comfortably, and in a district where Republicans have a nearly 3-to-2 enrollment edge over Democrats. He is the former supervisor of Brookhaven Town, where about two-thirds of the district's voters live. His family's company, Fireworks by Grucci, is a Long Island institution.</p>
        <p>Given the abundance of factors in Mr. Grucci's favor, Mr. Bishop's ability to outpoll his opponent, even in preliminary returns, could be considered a feat.</p>
        <p>Asked what Mr. Bishop did right, Democrats simply suggested that his political stances were attractive to voters in the district, which includes most of eastern Long Island. Members of both parties also pointed to the missteps of his opponent.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to extract what it was that Bishop did that was positive because the negativity that Grucci created overwhelmed everything,'' said Stanley B. Klein, a political science professor at the C. W. Post Campus of Long Island University and a Republican committeeman from Suffolk County. ''The incumbent is not beaten by the challenger -- the incumbent shoots himself in the foot,'' Dr. Klein said.</p>
        <p>In particular, critics of the Grucci effort have cited a television and radio advertisement in which his campaign suggested that as provost of Southampton College, Mr. Bishop had ignored or covered up rapes on campus. The ad, based on a discredited article in a student newspaper, turned against Mr. Grucci, increased the name recognition of his opponent and raised questions about Mr. Grucci's judgment, the critics said.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Bishop also pointed to his emphasis on environmental conservation and the need for a generous prescription drug plan for the elderly, a big population on the East End of the Island.</p>
        <p>Of his strong showing at the polls, he said: ''I think it says that the issues that are dear to Democrats are the issues that are important to the people of Long Island. We're talking about helping the middle class, we're talking about jobs, we're talking about fiscal responsibility, we're talking about lending a helping hand to seniors where right now that doesn't exist. That's Long Island.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grucci has not conceded defeat. ''We have no regrets in this campaign,'' said his campaign director, Kevin B. Molloy. He blamed Mr. Bishop for the campaign mudslinging. (Bishop commercials cited a report indicating that Fireworks by Grucci had contaminated local drinking-water wells.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Molloy also pointed to the influx of money from the national Democratic Party. Both races received national attention and money, and spending on each side exceeded $2 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop is a 12th-generation resident of Southampton. He graduated from College of the Holy Cross, in Worcester, Mass., in 1972, and has spent his entire professional career at Southampton College, as an admissions officer, financial aid director and, most recently, as provost.</p>
        <p>THE 2002 ELECTIONS: LONG ISLAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
