<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Passes Bill on Steps Advised by Sept. 11 Panel</title>
    <meta content="14homeland" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/14/washington/14homeland.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luo, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Homeland Security Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6D81131F937A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Passes Bill on Steps Advised by Sept. 11 Panel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Passes Bill on Steps Advised by Sept. 11 Panel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LUO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Luo, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate passes legislation that would enact more recommendations made by Sept 11 commission, but bill faces threat of White House veto because it offers expanded union rights to airport screeners; bill authorizes $3.1 billion in domestic security grants to states over next three years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate passed legislation on Tuesday that would enact more recommendations made by the Sept. 11 commission, but the bill faces the threat of a White House veto because it offers expanded union rights to airport screeners.</p>
        <p>Passage of the bill, more than two years after the bipartisan commission issued its findings, came on a vote of 60 to 38, with a smattering of Republicans joining with Democrats to approve it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bill faces the threat of a White House veto because it offers expanded union rights to airport screeners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate passed legislation on Tuesday that would enact more recommendations made by the Sept. 11 commission, but the bill faces the threat of a White House veto because it offers expanded union rights to airport screeners.</p>
        <p>Passage of the bill, more than two years after the bipartisan commission issued its findings, came on a vote of 60 to 38, with a smattering of Republicans joining with Democrats to approve it.</p>
        <p>The legislation authorizes $3.1 billion in domestic security grants to states over the next three years, tightens security provisions affecting travelers entering the country and establishes requirements to improve the sharing of information between the Department of Homeland Security and state and local governments.</p>
        <p>''When this bill becomes law, we will have taken a critical step toward building a safer and more secure America for the generations to come,'' Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, an independent from Connecticut who is chairman of the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has made clear it will reject counterterrorism legislation that includes language pushed by Senate Democrats, granting collective bargaining rights to employees of the Transportation Security Administration. Administration officials said the labor requirements would hamper the department's flexibility in responding to terrorist threats.</p>
        <p>Bolstering the veto threat, Senator Jim DeMint, Republican of South Carolina, sent a letter to the White House last month signed by 35 other Republican senators who said they were prepared to sustain a presidential veto.</p>
        <p>''If you follow this through, it just doesn't make sense,'' Mr. DeMint said Tuesday in an interview, explaining that he believed that the union provisions would actually endanger Americans by leaving the Department of Homeland Security less nimble. ''It's about security. The bill is about security. It's not about government workers. It's not about unions. It's just about how do we keep this country more secure.''</p>
        <p>Collective bargaining rights are also in a House bill approved in January as one of Democrats' priorities in their first 100 hours of work as the new majority.</p>
        <p>Representative Bennie Thompson, Democrat of Mississippi and chairman of the House Committee on Homeland Security, said it was important for airport screeners to have the right to file grievances through a union.</p>
        <p>''I think given the morale of many D.H.S. employees is as low as it can go,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''People don't feel like they're appreciated. People don't feel like they can go to their supervisor and let them know where vulnerabilities exist without fear of some kind of job action against them.''</p>
        <p>Both bills include new requirements that all cargo on passenger planes be inspected in the same manner as checked baggage. The House bill's language, however, is stricter.</p>
        <p>Officials of the transportation security agency have said the requirement would be cumbersome and prohibitively expensive, estimating its cost at $600 million a year. They say that the existing system in which about 30 percent of air cargo is inspected is adequate.</p>
        <p>But Carie Lemack, president of Families of Sept. 11 who lost her mother in the terrorist attacks, said the measure was essential.</p>
        <p>''The fact that we make passengers go through security -- we screen their checked baggage and yet there's a whole cargo area of the plane that is not screened,'' she said. ''It's a large loophole that terrorists can penetrate.''</p>
        <p>An important difference between the bills that will have to be worked out in a conference committee involves how domestic security grants are allocated. The Senate bill would distribute the money more evenly among the states, with each receiving a guaranteed minimum. The House bill offers a smaller minimum and would direct more money to more populous states, on the theory that they face a bigger threat, a position supported by big-city mayors and other officials from the larger states.</p>
        <p>Another major difference in the House bill is it has language that requires all shipping containers heading for the United States be screened for hazardous materials at the port of origin, a provision that the Bush administration opposes.</p>
        <p>Timothy Roemer, a member of the Sept. 11 commission who was a former Democratic congressman from Indiana, said he had been exasperated by how long it has taken for the recommendations to wend their way through the legislative process.</p>
        <p>''These recommendations are now two years old, and there are new threats coming at us, new transnational threats coming at us and new Al Qaeda threats coming every day,'' Mr. Roemer said. ''All these are compelling and immediate needs to plug holes in our national security.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
