<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Offering No Apologies, Cranston Faces Judges</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE COMMITTEE ON ETHICS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LINCOLN SAVINGS &amp; LOAN ASSN (IRVINE, CALIF)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRANSTON, ALAN (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEATING, CHARLES H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D81031F934A25752C1A966958260" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Offering No Apologies, Cranston Faces Judges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frail and drawn, Senator Alan Cranston entered the majestic Senate hearing room this afternoon, made his way to the desk reserved for him, sat down and faced six fellow Senators who will be both his judge and jury.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Chairman, the Bible states in Ecclesiastes that there is 'a time to be silent and a time to speak,' " he said. "This is my time to speak."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frail and drawn, Senator Alan Cranston entered the majestic Senate hearing room this afternoon, made his way to the desk reserved for him, sat down and faced six fellow Senators who will be both his judge and jury.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Chairman, the Bible states in Ecclesiastes that there is 'a time to be silent and a time to speak,' " he said. "This is my time to speak."</p>
        <p>After declining to appear on Thursday for the opening of the Senate Ethics Committee's extraordinary hearings on the links between five Senators and the owner of a failed savings and loan association, Mr. Cranston had come to give his side of the story. The California Democrat has emerged as the Senator most intimately linked to Charles H. Keating Jr., the owner of the savings institution. Of the five, Mr. Cranston is perhaps the most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>For 30 minutes, as his sister, Eleanor Cameron, his son, Kim, and his daughter-in-law, Colette, looked on, Mr. Cranston gave perhaps the most emotional political speech of his career. He has already announced that he will not run for a fifth term in 1992 because of prostate cancer, and he gave up the chance to seek re-election to his Senate post as majority whip. Of 'Unwritten Rules'</p>
        <p>Today, in a firm voice, he accused the committee's special counsel, Robert S. Bennett, of holding him to "unwritten rules defining unethical behavior never adopted" by the Senate. For any senator to charge him with such violations, he said, is "sheer hypocrisy."</p>
        <p>He challenged the competence of regulators who monitored Mr. Keating's Lincoln Savings and Loan Association and he accused his judges of using the same fund-raising tactics for which he has been criticized.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Bennett," he said, "you don't write the rules. I don't write the rules. This committee doesn't write the rules. The Senate writes the rules. The fact is that the Senate does not have any rules like those Mr. Bennett seems to want."</p>
        <p>There were no apologies and no contrition -- just a persistent undercurrent of indignation, especially when he discussed allegations that Kim Cranston, who ran several voter registration organizations that received $850,000 in Keating contributions, had misused the money.</p>
        <p>Calling his son "the most ethical person I've ever known," he said, "I am incensed by the false accusations that he financially benefited from any of the nonpartisan voter registration programs."  An Aggressive Stance</p>
        <p>Of the five Senators whose political lives are on the line over their involvement with Mr. Keating, the 76-year-old Democrat has adopted perhaps the most aggressive and combative stand.</p>
        <p>He said in his presentation that he was absent from the panel's opening session on Thursday because of a need to assemble his personal affairs before he begins radiation treatments for his cancer on Monday, but the message was unmistakable. Lawyers for some of the other Senators said privately that Mr. Cranston was, in effect, snubbing the panel, almost challenging its authority.</p>
        <p>This was evident as his lawyer, William W. Taylor 3d, challenged one of the most senior members of the Senate, Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina. Mr. Taylor asked that Mr. Helms be removed from the case, citing campaign statements by Mr. Helms last month referring to Mr. Cranston as "the leading water carrier in Congress for that S.&amp; L. kingpin Charles Keating." A Troubling Accusation</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said the statement showed that Mr. Helms was not impartial, and the accusation seemed to both trouble and embarrass the committee members.</p>
        <p>The North Carolina Senator argued that his statement was justified because Mr. Cranston had contributed to the campaign of Mr. Helms's opponent through a political action committee to which Mr. Keating had contributed "a huge sum of money."</p>
        <p>Rising to challenge Mr. Helms, Mr. Taylor noted the amount of the contribution was $10,000 by Mr. Keating. But Mr. Helms insisted that he would stay on the panel. And after a brief adjournment, the panel said it would support Mr. Helms's decision to remain on the panel.</p>
        <p>In a presentation lasting all morning, Mr. Bennett outlined four instances in which he said Mr. Cranston had solicited Mr. Keating for large contributions, while at the same time discussing with the savings executive how he could intervene with regulators on Mr. Keating's behalf.</p>
        <p>In one instance, Mr. Cranston's chief fund-raiser, Joy Jacobson, arranged a meeting between Mr. Keating and the Senator in September 1987 in which the savings executive wanted to see if Mr. Cranston could arrange a meeting for him with the new chairman of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board, M. Danny Wall.</p>
        <p>In a memorandum to the Senator, Ms. Jacobson said, "You should ask Keating for $250,000."</p>
        <p>The meeting took place on Sept. 24. Mr. Keating's chief counsel, James Grogan, delivered checks totaling $250,000 to Mr. Cranston on Nov. 6. Six days later, Mr. Cranston called Mr. Wall and told the regulator, "He shouldn't let personality factors cause difficulties for our constituents."</p>
        <p>Another occasion was on Jan. 8, 1988, when Mr. Cranston and his son dined with Mr. Keating, who "went into a tirade about the regulators," Mr. Bennett said. Mr. Keating asked the Senator to call Mr. Wall again and arrange a meeting between the two men. Such a meeting was set up after a call by Mr. Cranston, and on Feb. 10, 12 days after the meeting between Mr. Keating and Mr. Wall, the Senator and his son flew to Mr. Keating's corporate headquarters in Phoenix and received donation checks of $500,000.</p>
        <p>By day's end, Mr. Cranston seemed relieved but tired.  As he left the hearing room, he had a parting shot for Mr. Helms. Asked if he was disappointed that Mr. Helms remained as one of the six panel members, he said yes.</p>
        <p>Does that mean he will not get a fair hearing?</p>
        <p>"I think five members will be fair," he said. "I hope Senator Helms would be fair."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
