<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Consider Their Ways and be Wise</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOVEJOY, THOMAS E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLDOBLER, BERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, EDWARD O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ANTS, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED8173FF93AA15754C0A966958260" item-length="1615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Consider Their Ways and be Wise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS E. LOVEJOY; Thomas E. Lovejoy, a biologist who is the assistant secretary for external affairs of the Smithsonian Institution, has written and edited several books on animal biology.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOVEJOY, THOMAS E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ANTS</p>
        <p>By Bert Holldobler and Edward O. Wilson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 732 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>The Belknap Press/Harvard University Press. $65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ANTS</p>
        <p>By Bert Holldobler and Edward O. Wilson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 732 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>The Belknap Press/Harvard University Press. $65.</p>
        <p>THE ANTS</p>
        <p>By Bert Holldobler and Edward O. Wilson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 732 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>The Belknap Press/Harvard University Press. $65.</p>
        <p>Ants are practically everywhere. Only Antarctica, Iceland, Greenland and the part of Polynesia lying east of Tonga lack native ants, but even beyond the kingdom of the ants there are tramp species that have hitchhiked there on human activities. And now comes a book that, while it is intended to be an authoritative account of the study of ants (myrmecology), also makes the intricacies and fascinations of all 8,804 species of the single family (Formicidae) accessible to the average reader. Written in clear, expository English, ''The Ants'' is adorned with excellent illustrations in which the diminutive looms large. The chapter sections taken together could provide a story line in themselves: for example, ''Ant Gardens.'' ''Plants Feed Ants: Food Bodies.'' ''Plants Feed Ants: Extrafloral Nectaries.'' ''Ants Feed Plants: Myrmecotrophy.''</p>
        <p>The authors - Bert Holldobler, the Alexander Agassiz Professor of Zoology at Harvard University and a professor of behavioral physiology at the University of Wurzburg in Germany, and Edward O. Wilson, who is the Frank B. Baird Jr. Professor of Science at Harvard and the author of such books as ''On Human Nature'' and ''Sociobiology'' - are world leaders in ant research. Yet they have managed, largely, to avoid a pedantic and suffocating style. While it is impossible to write a definitive tome and make it 100 percent transparent to the nonscientist, this volume achieves the utmost clarity; jargon is kept to a judicious minimum. Its size, weight and price may discourage many people, but I consider it a tremendous bargain.</p>
        <p>I once had the privilege of following one of the authors, Mr. Wilson, through a day in a tropical forest. I had thought I knew it well. But our trek was a six-legged revelation: everywhere Mr. Wilson looked he found ants and termites in multitude, as if he had the myrmecological equivalent of the Midas touch. That night we were treated to a spectacle of tiny regiments bearing myriad green banners as a colony of leaf cutter ants engaged in defoliation to provide mulch for a subterranean fungus farm.</p>
        <p>Ants indeed remind us of the importance of little things, and of how plants and invertebrates really run our world. They make up in number what they lack in size: one hectare (just under 2.5 acres) of Ivory Coast savannah in Africa holds 7,000 colonies and 20 million individuals. In a high-ground tropical forest ants compose one-third of all the biomass (animal weight). Because harvesting ants cannot carry home with them all the seeds they gather, in New York State ants are estimated to disperse one-third of herbaceous plant species. In tropical forest soils less than one-tenth of one percent of nutrients go below five centimeters, less than two inches. Yet huge leaf cutter ant nests (one nest had 1,000 entrances and 1,027 chambers and produced 38,481 males and 5,339 queens in its third year) are carved to a depth of six meters, almost 20 feet, providing soils near nests an energy and nutrient flow 10 times greater than normal. In New England forests the activity of ants in soil turnover is equal to that of earthworms, and in tropical forests it is even greater.</p>
        <p>Ants provide a Lilliputian echo of the diversity of living patterns so generally characteristic of life on earth. Predators, pastoralists and agriculturalists are to be found among the 11 subfamilies. There are ants that harvest wild seed so effectively they compete with rodents. The weaver ants team up in a formicid version of roof raising: ants by the dozen pull the edges of two leaves together until larvae spin silk to sew them together. The Chinese have used weaver ant nests, translocating them to citrus groves, as an effective form of pest control for 1,700 years.</p>
        <p>The military style is adopted by driver ants (Africa) and army ants (New World tropics). It is awesome indeed when half a million army ants are swarming in an Amazon forest. The pioneering English ecologist Charles Elton called an army ant swarm the most macabre ecological event he ever witnessed. But ''The Ants'' is a book that goes far beyond sound bites. We learn not only of birds that make their living following army ants to pirate their prey, or the moths that follow to feed on the droppings of the birds. We also learn of the internal physiological and reproductive rhythms that drive the cyclic swarming behavior of ants. We discover as well ants that hunt in columns, and we find out how new colonies are formed.</p>
        <p>One of the most interesting aspects of ant biology is the ants' relationship to plant species, which dates back at least to the time of the dinosaurs. Some acacias grow hollow thorns to provide accommodation for ants; other plants provide food as well. The quid pro quo in these cases is largely defense. The ants attack would-be grazers of their plant hosts, or vines and other plants that might otherwise overgrow them. The treatment of ant-plants in ''The Ants,'' as with other topics, is exhaustive but not exhausting. One table lists six pages of ant-plant relationships involving domatia (ant dormitories), but a reader can skim or even skip it and still be able to follow the narrative of the text. The book is replete with tidbits that fascinate by themselves: someone has actually proven with isotopes and examination of plant cell structure that some plants benefit from the nutrients provided by ant garbage dumps in special sections of domatia.</p>
        <p>It doesn't stop there. Ants not only disperse plants, they also weed around some host plants. The authors even go into what ants don't do. Why is ant pollination so rare? The likely answer is that the antibacterial secretions ants use to combat bacterial and fungal growth in nests seems to interfere with pollen germination.</p>
        <p>It is of course the elaborate social systems of ants that fascinate most people, including the authors. The small scale of ants adds to the possibilities, for one can manipulate colonies (for instance, by removing a whole caste temporarily from one and then restoring it) to try to fathom the true meaning of the social structure. The leaf-cutting ants present an extreme: hunter-gathering ants collect the leaf fragments and turn them over to the agriculturalist castes; six different sizes and types of ants process the vegetation in assembly-line fashion. We learn that behavioral variety outstrips morphology: there are seven castes but 22 social functions.</p>
        <p>In honey pot ants one caste serves a food storage function for the entire colony, their huge distended abdomens holding a sort of honey. Many ants have soldier castes, generally of larger size, some with huge swollen heads that can block nest entrances. The illustrations in this book complement the text nicely. The figure of the minor worker of the Asian marauder ant makes the point of caste variation dramatically: the minor sits atop the head of a member of the major caste that is 500 times its weight.</p>
        <p>The temptation has always been great to draw parallels between ant and human behaviors (''Go to the ant, thou sluggard, consider her ways and be wise'' - Proverbs 6:6-8), but the authors are careful not to exceed the bounds of careful comparison. For example, we learn that ants do not play.</p>
        <p>It is hard to believe that anyone has not sprawled out on the ground as a child, enrapt in observation of these tiny insects. Clearly we are fortunate that Mr. Holldobler and Mr. Wilson never were able to tear themselves away. Science is rarely good literature. ''The Ants'' is an exalting exception. The authors approach the lyrical as they pursue their ''personal muse'': ''To an exquisite degree ants are creatures of the ground.'' The reader who vaults over what is often perceived as a scientific wall and enters the kingdom of the ant in this book will discover that the enraptured child was indeed gazing at wonders.</p>
        <p>WHEN ANTS MAKE A BEELINE</p>
        <p>A great deal of the flexibility observed in the behavior of individual ants can be attributed to learning. . . . It is true that some complicated responses, such as self-grooming and regurgitation, appear to be wholly programmed. . . . Other responses are altered according to experience. . . . The simplest form of learning in ants, like that in other animals, is habituation. . . . When an ant colony is disturbed by the intrusion of a glass rod into the nest, the workers launch an attack. If the disturbance is repeated at close intervals . . . the ants grow steadily less responsive. In this fashion ant workers can be ''tamed.'' . . . Even large, venomous species can be picked up, allowed to walk over the hand, and fed (carefully!) with sugar water. . . . Ants are capable of feats of learning considerably more sophisticated than simple association when finding their way through the environment. . . . An outward-bound worker winds and loops in tortuous searching patterns until she encounters food. But then she takes a direct route, the ''beeline,'' in her return trip to the nest. This feat is made possible by sun-compass orientation, that is, using the sun as a reference point for guided movement. . . .</p>
        <p>A closer examination of the actual behavior of ants reveals some peculiar shortcomings. . . . They cannot duplicate the mammalian feat of reorganizing their memories to construct a new response in the face of a novel problem. A dog can . . . work purposefully around a transparent barrier instead of trying to push its way through. . . . No behavior approaching this level of sophistication has been observed in ants.</p>
        <p>From ''The Ants.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
