<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Secretly Linked to the Same Woman</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DORFMAN, ARIEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANTUNES, ANTONIO LOBO</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FADO ALEXANDRINO (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDF143FF93AA15754C0A966958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Secretly Linked to the Same Woman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARIEL DORFMAN; Ariel Dorfman's most recent book is a collection of stories, ''My House Is on Fire.'' He teaches literature at Duke University.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DORFMAN, ARIEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>FADO ALEXANDRINO</p>
        <p>By Antonio Lobo Antunes.</p>
        <p>Translated by Gregory Rabassa.</p>
        <p>497 pp. New York: Grove Weidenfeld. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>FADO ALEXANDRINO</p>
        <p>By Antonio Lobo Antunes.</p>
        <p>Translated by Gregory Rabassa.</p>
        <p>497 pp. New York: Grove Weidenfeld. $24.95.</p>
        <p>FADO ALEXANDRINO</p>
        <p>By Antonio Lobo Antunes.</p>
        <p>Translated by Gregory Rabassa.</p>
        <p>497 pp. New York: Grove Weidenfeld. $24.95.</p>
        <p>In the late 1960's, Antonio Lobo Antunes was sent to Angola to serve as a medic in the fruitless war that Portugal was fighting to retain its African colonies. Out of that experience came in 1979 an extraordinary fictionalized memoir that was translated into English in 1983 as ''South of Nowhere.'' Through a hallucinatory monologue set in a Lisbon bar, its protagonist managed not only to explore the degrading consequences of that specific war but to recall the bitter homecoming of so many soldiers of other countries and other times as they mourned their own lost innocence.</p>
        <p>The same obsessive scrutiny of the nightmare world of the colonial war veteran, the same brutally lyrical language, the same maelstrom of erotic violence and guilt can be found in Mr. Lobo Antunes's second novel to be published in English. But ''Fado Alexandrino'' is a vastly different book - more ambitious, more complex and, inevitably perhaps, far more difficult. The one lonely narrator of ''South of Nowhere'' has been fractured here into four failed combatants who, as they expose their own crisscrossed lives during one tumultuous night, also recount the sprawling epic of their country in the 10 years after its troops came home from Africa.</p>
        <p>Although of different rank and social class, all four men share a common destiny of frustration that seems emblematic of their nation's history. Somewhat in the same way that, even after they have crumbled, the country's 400-year-old empire and the almost 40-year dictatorship of Gen. Antonio de Oliveira Salazar continue to influence the present, so too do the past mistakes of these men continue to haunt them, contaminating not only their efforts to alter their society but also their compulsive attempts to find comfort in sex, and maybe even in love. Not surprisingly, the bedchambers of Portugal end up being as much a battle zone as the jungles of Mozambique.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lobo Antunes has chosen to transmit his characters' stories through a dense web of confessions laid before a silent and enigmatic figure they call the Captain - an army investigator? a psychoanalyst? the author himself? - who accompanies them on a long orgiastic night out on the town with five prostitutes. Though this technique - which juxtaposes Africa and Portugal, a rape and a funeral, yesterday and today and anticipations of a possible tomorrow - can be confusing and even tiresome at times, it is crucial to the author's intention of revealing the hidden, mingled layers of his nation's subconscious, of charting how far it has traveled from the experiences of the now-legendary Vasco da Gama, who set sail many centuries ago to claim the world for Portugal and inspired the great poet Luis de Camoes's 1572 epic, ''The Lusiads.'' Now all that is left of that archetypal unity are the splintered masks and voices of the ruined Portuguese male, and the only exploratory journey a descent into a shattered series of private hells.</p>
        <p>Before the night is over, Mr. Lobo Antunes's characters will have revealed that they are secretly linked to the same women, that they have been making love to one another's wives and mistresses and fiancees. And, because of this connection, one of them will be murdered, ''lying face down on the sidewalk . . . amid the indifference or the fright or the hunger of the birds.''</p>
        <p>Will the dead man be the lieutenant colonel who has spent his years in the army serving whatever faction happens to be in power, drifting from bed to bed in an attempt to exorcise memories of his dead wife? Or will it be the second lieutenant who, divorced by his high-society lesbian wife, returns to his country from Brazil to marry a deformed and jealous dwarf? Or will it be the noncom who was tortured and imprisoned for belonging to a Maoist sect, but has since lost all belief in the revolution? Or another soldier, who sold his body to strangers in order to have enough money to impress the young woman he loved - who dumped him anyway, almost as soon as they married? Ultimately, it does not really matter; the turmoil of their society will, like the primeval sex they fear so much, end up swallowing them all, their existence nothing more than a ''beach full of detritus and seagulls and the slimy mouths of sewer pipes.''</p>
        <p>What is miraculous in ''Fado Alexandrino,'' which often reads like a mad amalgam of Dos Passos and Celine, is that its readers are not themselves devoured by this chaos. For the author, with the very energy and vision that he denies to his blindly cynical characters, narrates this account of their lives with a remarkable, savage swirl of imagery that controls and sustains the wanderings of their jumbled fates, allowing us to look deep into the predatory origins of their incessant violence - a revelation made possible in English by Gregory Rabassa's splendid translation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lobo Antunes's earlier book, ''South of Nowhere,'' was a masterpiece that, unfortunately, did not catch on in America. The more arduous and disturbing ''Fado Alexandrino'' gives readers in the United States a second chance to plunge into the strange and yet oddly familiar war-weary world created by one of Portugal's pre-eminent writers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
