<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Perfection, He's Toast of the Town</title>
    <meta content="19WELL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wells, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Letterman, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Late Show With David Letterman (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D91739F93AA25756C0A96E958260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Perfection, He's Toast of the Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher David Wells plays in celebrity golf tournament in Connecticut and appears on David Letterman's television show day after pitching perfect game against Minnesota Twins; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Wells wonders how long his revel can last. It is not a probing self-analysis; he's too free spirited for that. But on the day after pitching a perfect game -- a day when he was the talk of Howard Stern's radio show and a guest on David Letterman's television show -- the Yankee left-hander sat at a table in a black leisure suit after his Letterman gig and twirled an empty bottle of water.</p>
        <p>''There'll be a day when I get my butt kicked,'' Wells said yesterday to a group of reporters, ''and people will say, 'That guy pitched a perfect game?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Wells wonders how long his revel can last. It is not a probing self-analysis; he's too free spirited for that. But on the day after pitching a perfect game -- a day when he was the talk of Howard Stern's radio show and a guest on David Letterman's television show -- the Yankee left-hander sat at a table in a black leisure suit after his Letterman gig and twirled an empty bottle of water.</p>
        <p>''There'll be a day when I get my butt kicked,'' Wells said yesterday to a group of reporters, ''and people will say, 'That guy pitched a perfect game?' ''</p>
        <p>Wells can frolic at least until his next start, on Saturday in Boston. His gambols began Sunday night, after he had retired 27 straight Minnesota Twins at Yankee Stadium to record the 15th perfect game in major league history. Wells ate pizza and drank Champagne at Dorrian's Red Hand Restaurant on Manhattan's Upper East Side with his teammates David Cone and Graeme Lloyd. ''The pizza was great,'' he said, sounding like an aficionado.</p>
        <p>Other patrons, among them Mets catcher Todd Pratt, stood to applaud the entrance of the beefy, balding Wells. Then it was off to Chinatown, for more partying with Cone and Dale Sveum, another teammate.</p>
        <p>Reporters tailed New York's newest action hero throughout the evening, which displeased him. ''Why don't you tell me where I was last night?'' he asked yesterday.</p>
        <p>Wells said he slept well Sunday night and did not dream about the game. ''I didn't dream,'' he said. ''I'm still in awe.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning he arrived an hour late for the Carol Rosen Celebrity Golf Classic in Wilton, Conn., a tournament whose host was the Yankees' pitching coach, Mel Stottlemyre; the event benefits the Leukemia Society of America.</p>
        <p>''I almost didn't leave,'' Wells said. ''Played 10 holes.'' Who were the other members of his fivesome? ''I forget their names. But they were awesome,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Wells arrived with Lloyd at the Rolling Hills Country Club in Wells's black BMW, wearing a black cap with a No Fear logo and dark sunglasses. On the ninth hole, his Sunday luck held. A 45-foot wedge shot rolled in for an eagle. ''Pick it up,'' he told a partner who was lining up a 15-foot putt. ''We're done here.''</p>
        <p>After a shower, a change into his leisure suit and a limousine ride to the Ed Sullivan Theater in Manhattan, Wells decamped with his girlfriend, Nina Fisher; a Yankee publicist, Jason Zillo, and a friend to the green room of ''Late Show With David Letterman.'' Forty minutes into the show -- after Matthew Perry of ''Friends,'' after Matthew Broderick, the star of ''Godzilla,'' and after Letterman said, ''He celebrated by retiring 27 Heinekens in a row'' -- Wells ambled out for about five minutes of chat.</p>
        <p>''Take me through the last out,'' Letterman said.</p>
        <p>''You'll get me all nervous again,'' Wells said.</p>
        <p>''Which Twin was it?'' Letterman asked, mocking the Minnesotans as if they were Lilliputians.</p>
        <p>''Pat Meares,'' Wells answered.</p>
        <p>What did George Steinbrenner, the Yankees' principal owner, have to say after the performance?</p>
        <p>''Good job, Dave,'' Wells responded in a deep voice.</p>
        <p>Did he get any bonuses for pitching the perfect game?</p>
        <p>Yes, said Wells, a call came from Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who will present him with the key to the city today at noon on the steps of City Hall. ''I told him it wasn't a good idea,'' Wells said. ''I might use it to open too many of the wrong doors.''</p>
        <p>Wells's romps are not finished. Gregg Clifton, his Boston-based agent, is fielding offers for endorsements and speaking engagements. (Wells will talk to Stern, and Regis and Kathie Lee, this morning.) Yankee beat reporters and the team's office have been swamped with ''Where's David Wells?'' inquiries. Wells and Clifton will meet Friday in Boston to make decisions.</p>
        <p>Wells is also tending to some family business. At the Ed Sullivan Theater last night, he said that he still had not spoken about the perfect game with his father, David Dritt, or his 6-year-old son, Brandon.</p>
        <p>Wells said the two left the Yankee clubhouse at 2:30 on Sunday afternoon, an hour into the perfect game, so that Dritt could take Brandon home to Wells's former wife in Florida, to comply with their divorce agreement.</p>
        <p>Oddly, Wells had been scheduled to be on last night's Letterman show well before perfection was thrust upon him. He was supposed to be 1 of 10 Yankees brought onstage to recite Letterman's nightly top 10 list. Nine other Yankees could not be roped in for the assignment, so the entire appearance had been canceled.</p>
        <p>''If I was Dave I wouldn't go to a Yankee game because of that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
