<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Far, Britain Grants Asylum to Few on Hijacked Afghan Jet</title>
    <meta content="Y02BRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1180663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Straw, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DC1139F931A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Far, Britain Grants Asylum to Few on Hijacked Afghan Jet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, March 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British government says only four of dozens of passengers who applied for political asylum after their plane was hijacked from Afghanistan last month will definitely be allowed to remain in Britain; says 27 have been ordered to leave country, while status of remaining passengers has yet to be decided; Jack Straw, home secretary, faces virulent anti-immigrant sentiment from political opposition (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only four of the dozens of passengers who applied for political asylum after their plane was hijacked from Afghanistan last month will definitely be allowed to remain in Britain, the government said tonight. Twenty-seven others have been ordered to leave the country with their families, while the status of the remaining passengers has yet to be decided.</p>
        <p>What to do about the Afghans has been a political headache for the government since they arrived in Britain on Feb. 6 and spent four days aboard an Ariana Airlines Boeing 727 at Stansted Airport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only four of the dozens of passengers who applied for political asylum after their plane was hijacked from Afghanistan last month will definitely be allowed to remain in Britain, the government said tonight. Twenty-seven others have been ordered to leave the country with their families, while the status of the remaining passengers has yet to be decided.</p>
        <p>What to do about the Afghans has been a political headache for the government since they arrived in Britain on Feb. 6 and spent four days aboard an Ariana Airlines Boeing 727 at Stansted Airport.</p>
        <p>In the face of virulent anti-immigrant sentiment from the political opposition and from a number of newspapers, the home secretary, Jack Straw, vowed last month to rule on the asylum requests personally. He would, he told Parliament, seek to ensure that the Afghans left Britain ''as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>But in a written statement to Parliament today, Mr. Straw made it clear that it had not been a case of simply ejecting unwanted people from the country. He had been obligated to consider factors like the troubled domestic situation in Afghanistan, he said, as well as the individual circumstances of each asylum applicant.</p>
        <p>Having done that, Mr. Straw said, he had decided to grant political asylum to two men ''because I am satisfied that their applications disclose a well-founded fear of persecution'' as set out by the 1951 United Nations convention on refugees. The wife of one of the men is to be given what is called exceptional leave to remain, which means that her case will be reconsidered in four years, and the couple's child will be allowed to stay.</p>
        <p>As for the 27 people he is ordering to leave the country, along with five dependents, Mr. Straw said, ''I am not satisfied that they have a well-founded fear of persecution by reason of their race, religion, nationality or membership of a particular social group or political opinion.''</p>
        <p>Significantly, however, Mr. Straw is not forcing the 32 to return to Afghanistan, where many have said they fear reprisals by the repressive Taliban military government. Instead, he is trying to find a third country that will accept them.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the last year for which figures are available, 1,600 Afghans sought asylum in Britain, a home office spokesman said. Of those, 35 were granted asylum, 1,500 were granted exceptional leave to remain, and 65 were told to leave the country.</p>
        <p>Asked why those now being ejected were not given exceptional leave to remain, the spokesman said,  ''They're not being rewarded for being on that plane.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Straw said as much in his statement. ''In these cases,'' he said, referring to the people he had decided to eject from the country, ''I have decided that the public interest in deterring future hijacks for the purposes of claiming asylum is a very strong one and, therefore, I have decided that they should not be given permission to stay in this country.'' The ejected Afghans will have the right to appeal.</p>
        <p>When the jet landed in Britain after being hijacked on a domestic flight from Kabul, the Afghan capital, it had about 170 people aboard. Seventy-three returned to Afghanistan on Feb. 14, and two more have asked to return home. Fourteen people have been charged with hijacking the plane, and six others and their dependents, who are seeking asylum and are related to the 14, have had their decisions postponed until criminal trials are held. In eight additional cases, Mr. Straw said, he needs more information before he can reach a decision.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
