<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters;   A Commissioner For Consumers Has High Hopes</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSUMER AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREEN, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D8113BF93AA25751C0A966958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters;   A Commissioner For Consumers Has High Hopes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBERTS, SAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years ago this month, New York City imposed its paradigmatic consumer protection law. Bess Myerson was consumer affairs commissioner then, followed briefly by Betty Furness. Those were the golden days of the consumer movement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years ago this month, New York City imposed its paradigmatic consumer protection law. Bess Myerson was consumer affairs commissioner then, followed briefly by Betty Furness. Those were the golden days of the consumer movement.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago this month, New York City imposed its paradigmatic consumer protection law. Bess Myerson was consumer affairs commissioner then, followed briefly by Betty Furness. Those were the golden days of the consumer movement.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow, though, may herald the resurgence of an agency with the rare ability to collect more money than it spends while also enhancing the reputations of its commissioner and the mayor. Mayor David N. Dinkins is to swear in Mark Green as the city's Consumer Affairs Commissioner.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Dinkins, the appointment of Mr. Green represents an opportunity to convey the image of an administration vigorously protecting the salaries of the middle class and the dwindling resources of even more vulnerable New Yorkers - the young, the elderly, the poor and the disabled - when budget constraints are forcing the Mayor to curtail city services.</p>
        <p>For the glib but cerebral Mr. Green, who sometimes speaks in slogans, the position offers public exposure and an opportunity, after 20 years as an independent consumer advocate, to put the city's money and legal might where his mouth is.</p>
        <p>''While the department has been a competent licenser, it has been a relatively quiet advocate,'' Mr. Green said. ''There's a lot of room to raise the agency's voice and revenue.''</p>
        <p>The job marks a major adjustment for the 44-year-old Mr. Green, an energetic Ralph Nader protege who has spent the last decade - with a detour in 1986 to run unsuccessfully against Alfonse M. D'Amato, the Republican United States Senator - lobbying for a liberal agenda through his nonprofit Democracy Project.</p>
        <p>''This is the first job in which I haven't had to help raise money for my own salary,'' Mr. Green said of the $97,000-a-year commissionership.</p>
        <p>''In fact, I may be the only commissioner whose salary went up when he joined city government. My sacrifice is not financial, but mobility.''</p>
        <p>In 1979, Mr. Green rejected the job of consumer adviser to President Jimmy Carter -largely, he said, because of philosophical disagreements about energy deregulation and other issues.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Dinkins was elected last November, Mr. Green stepped aside as co-chairman of a panel searching for a consumer affairs commissioner once he was persuaded that he need only look in a mirror to find the perfect candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green hopes to transform the Consumer Affairs Department from a monitor of weights and measures and collector of license fees and fines (it took in $11.9 million last year and spent $10.4 million) into a more vocal advocate and law-enforcement office. The fact that his most recent predecessors (identify one if you can) are not household names is a reflection of their styles, if not their records.</p>
        <p>''Let's ask why Bess Myerson succeeded 20 years ago,'' Mr. Green said. ''Because Bess exploited a prior prominence, hired a great staff and had a supportive mayor. I'm no Miss America, but several of those elements exist for my tenure, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Green seeks to elevates concerns of consumers, and, therefore, their champion, to a higher plane than ''housewife issues.''</p>
        <p>''Tell it to a family of four earning $20,000 that is overpaying $1,000 for an old refrigerator sold as new,'' he said, cautioning that cumulative abuses erode not only the economic health of families on the margin but also their faith in government.</p>
        <p>Might not aggressive consumer advocacy sometimes clash with Mayor Dinkins's eagerness to cast his administration as receptive to business?</p>
        <p>''I will be resolutely anti-business-abuse, which is pro-business,'' Mr. Green declared. ''The scale of consumer justice is tilted against consumers - business has the resources, lawyers, contacts. My assignment and history are to lend my weight and voice to the consumer side of the scale so there will be a better balance.''</p>
        <p>Will public office still his partisan voice? Mr. Green said he is satisfied for now that he has persuaded the Senate to investigate conflict-of-interest allegations against Mr. D'Amato. ''My private opinion of Al D'Amato has not altered, but I won't spend time prosecuting the case,'' Mr. Green said.  Will he run again for the Senate in 1992? Less likely now than before his appointment, Mr. Green said. The only Sherman-like statement he would issue is a pledge to enforce the antitrust law of the same name.</p>
        <p>''It is wrong to precondition appointive office on not seeking elective office,'' Mr. Green said, slyly recalling the appointed City Clerk who ran three times for Manhattan Borough President, David Dinkins.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
