<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>India Grounds Airbus Planes After Crash</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRBUS A320 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INDIAN AIRLINES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAZARIKA, SANJOY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD173AF93AA25751C0A966958260" item-length="315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>India Grounds Airbus Planes After Crash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANJOY HAZARIKA, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAZARIKA, SANJOY</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Feb. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Indian Government grounded all 14 Airbus A320 aircraft flown by its domestic carrier today after the crash of an Airbus plane last week that killed 97.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Indian Government grounded all 14 Airbus A320 aircraft flown by its domestic carrier today after the crash of an Airbus plane last week that killed 97.</p>
        <p>The Indian Government grounded all 14 Airbus A320 aircraft flown by its domestic carrier today after the crash of an Airbus plane last week that killed 97.</p>
        <p>The decision was made after a meeting of top officials of Indian Airlines, the Government-run carrier, and the Civil Aviation Ministry, who appointed a committee to investigate the airline's ability to operate the sophisticated aircraft.</p>
        <p>Indian Airlines' chairman, R. Prasad, resigned last week, accepting ''moral responsibility'' for the crash.</p>
        <p>The grounding of the aircraft is expected to disrupt the schedule of Indian Airlines, which carries about 11,000 passengers a day with a fleet that also includes Boeing 737's. The airline has been criticized frequently for delays and inefficient service.</p>
        <p>Breathing Difficulties</p>
        <p>In another incident involving one of the airline's A320's, a flight from the southern city of Madras on Saturday returned only 20 minutes after takeoff when passengers complained of breathing difficulties.</p>
        <p>The crash occurred on Wednesday as the plane, with 146 on board, came down short of the runway at the airport of the southern city of Bangalore.</p>
        <p>The Press Trust of India reported that the Government had set up a court of inquiry led by a high court judge to investigate the crash.</p>
        <p>The decision to buy 31 of the wide-bodied aircraft for about $1.2 billion - the rest of the planes have not been delivered - was made under the administration of former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi, who was voted out of office last year.</p>
        <p>There has been widespread criticism of the deal, much of it focusing on the apparent unpreparedness of the airline and ground installations in maintaining the aircraft.</p>
        <p>In November, airline maintenance engineers organized a protest seeking more training in Toulouse, France, at the headquarters of Airbus Industrie, the European consortium that manufactures the plane.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
