<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>67 British Barristers, Dressed for Success</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="LAW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL PROFESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEAD, DEBORAH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EDER, BERNARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">THE LAW PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D71530F934A15757C0A966958260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>67 British Barristers, Dressed for Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH STEAD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEAD, DEBORAH</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On Tuesday morning, 67 British barristers put on wigs, gowns, waistcoats, lace cuffs, britches and silver-buckled shoes and went to the House of Lords.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On Tuesday morning, 67 British barristers put on wigs, gowns, waistcoats, lace cuffs, britches and silver-buckled shoes and went to the House of Lords.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday morning, 67 British barristers put on wigs, gowns, waistcoats, lace cuffs, britches and silver-buckled shoes and went to the House of Lords.</p>
        <p>There, and later at the law courts on the Strand, they were sworn in as members of an elite group among the 8,000 barristers who practice in England and Wales. They were awarded the title of Queen's Counsel, or named a ''silk,'' by the Lord Chancellor who heads the judiciary.</p>
        <p>''Taking silk'' is an old tradition here; it reaches back to the 17th century, which explains the Jacobean attire. But it is by no means merely ceremonial. In addition to the symbolic privileges - the right to wear a silk gown, for example, and to sit in the front row of the courts they argue in - the 10 percent of barristers who attain the rank of Queen's Counsel can often multiply their incomes by the prestige of the positions and get in line for judicial appointments.</p>
        <p>''It's a great spur to work, and it's public recognition of one's integrity in court,'' said Bernard Eder, at 37 years old one of the youngest silks appointed this year from 384 applicants.</p>
        <p>'Like Traveling First Class'</p>
        <p>The author John Mortimer, who created the books about the fictional barrister ''Rumpole of the Bailey,'' said taking silk ''is like traveling first class instead of tourist.''</p>
        <p>But Rumpole, readers will recall, has a low opinion of the tradition. And increasingly, so do others within and outside Britain's legal profession, including solicitors, the lawyers who draft court pleadings but are not allowed to argue them in the higher courts.</p>
        <p>A brochure on fees recently published by one group of barristers who share office space here lists daily fees of up to $1,650 for a Queen's Counsel barrister with 16 years' experience, as against a $1,200 maximum for a junior barrister with 28 years' experience. This is the name given to those, no matter their age, who have not made Queen's Counsel.</p>
        <p>Other critics cite the selection process, which is a result of private consultations between the Lord Chancellor's office and leading members of the judiciary and the bar. ''It's a flagrant abuse of patronage,'' said Anne Grosskurt, a spokeswoman for the Legal Action Group, a nonprofit organization working for improved legal services. ''It's an old-boy system.''</p>
        <p>Few Women and Blacks</p>
        <p>This year, only one woman made the list, and altogether there are just 37 women and five blacks among the approximately 1,125 practicing silks.</p>
        <p>The Bar Council would also like to see the system changed a bit. ''In my view, the decision should primarily rest with the judges,'' said Roger Henderson, chairman of the Bar Council's public affairs committee.</p>
        <p>The Lord Chancellor's office publishes no formal criteria for attaining silk. The Lord Chancellor does offer failed applicants the chance to find out why they did not make the grade, and barristers may apply as often as they like for the titles, which are awarded annually.</p>
        <p>Those who have made Queen's Counsel point out that risks go along with the privileges. Mr. Eder put it this way: ''When you're a senior junior, you can be the cat's whiskers. Then you become a young silk and you're fighting again.''</p>
        <p>He paused, relishing the thought. ''I like fighting,'' he said. ''I love a good day's cross-examination.''  LAW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
